<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000973">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Elliot Richardson </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR ELLIOT RICHARDSON</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Alan James</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 30, 1996</p>
                <p>Copyright 2001 ADST</p>
                <p>[Note: This interview, edited by Ambassador Richardson, is incomplete due to the
                    death of Ambassador Richardson]</p>
                <p>Q: Today is May 30, 1996, and this is an interview with Elliot Richardson. My
                    name is Alan James. The focus of the interview will be your experiences in the
                    field of foreign policy as Under Secretary of State, Ambassador to the United
                    Kingdom, and Special Representative of the President to the Third United Nations
                    Conference on the Law of the Sea. By way of introduction, would you say a little
                    bit about your background to set the scene for our interview. Talk about your
                    family, education, and that sort of thing. We ask you to do this because these
                    interviews are supposed to be read years from now by people who really need some
                    orientation as to the people who are giving the interviews.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I understand the need for that! Indeed, I have become increasingly
                    conscious of the futility of efforts to stave off oblivion. So let me begin by
                    saying that I was born in Boston in 1920, grew up there, and went to school at
                    independent schools in greater Boston. Then I went to Harvard College at a time
                    when it was very easy to get in. I had one year of law school before Pearl
                    Harbor or rather in the year of Pearl Harbor. I came back to law school after
                    three years in the army. Having decided, even in College, that I wanted to go
                    into politics, I started early on at the local level in Brookline,
                    Massachusetts. Then I worked for the Republican State Committee in 1952, which
                    was the year in which Eisenhower was a candidate. Following that I spent two
                    years as the legislative assistant to Massachusetts senior Senator Leverett
                    Saltonstall. After some time, I became an associate in a Boston law firm, came
                    back into the government as Assistant Secretary of Health, Education and Welfare
                    in the Eisenhower Administration, then U.S. Attorney in Massachusetts. I ran and
                    lost the Republican nomination for Attorney General of Massachusetts in 1962. I
                    was serving in the second year of my four-year term as Attorney General when I
                    got a call from John Mitchell in December of 1968 asking if I might be
                    interested in the number two job at the State Department. I had previously
                    turned down the number two job at the Department of HEW thinking that that would
                    be more of what I had done before and because I was then heavily immersed in
                    what I thought was an important effort to develop a more coherent approach to
                    the problems of the criminal justice system in Massachusetts. At any rate, I
                    agreed to come to Washington to meet with the Secretary of State-designate,
                    William P. Rogers in his office at the State Department. At the outset of that
                    meeting I tried to persuade him that he really ought to seek someone with a
                    broader and deeper background in foreign policy than I had. I pointed out to
                    him, I hope politely, that I had really no more background in foreign policy
                    than he did and that he might want to be able, therefore, to call upon the
                    experience and knowledge of someone who had been engaged in it for much of his
                    career. But I didn't dissuade him, and to me the job had always seemed like a
                    wonderfully challenging and attractive one. I remembered William Bedell Smith
                    and, I can't remember his name, but he owned the house which is now the Cosmos
                    Club.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sumner Wells.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. And another Under Secretary was my father's college classmate,
                    Joseph C. Grew. I always thought that was a great job. So when Rogers seemed
                    absolutely serious about the invitation for me to come, I agreed that I would do
                    so.</p>
                <p>The first work I did actually began before the change of Administration. I was
                    asked to work with Henry Kissinger at the Hotel Pierre in New York on the
                    charter governing the role of the National Security Council. After a couple of
                    meetings with Kissinger the remaining contacts I had were with General Andy
                    Goodpaster. The upshot of that was a document that in important ways spelled out
                    the roles of the Security Council and the Department of State.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>Q: Back to the NSC in a moment, but might we begin by your stating what your
                    brief was as Mr. Rogers' Deputy. Were you his alter ego, or did you have special
                    areas you were going to concentrate on while he tended to others?</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I think the phrase alter-ego was used, but whether it was used
                    directly in conversation with Will Rogers, I am not sure. My general
                    understanding was that I would take on anything specific that he wanted me to
                    do. I thought of myself as an executive officer in the military. But I also had
                    some functions that arose out of my role as the Chairman of the Under
                    Secretary's Committee of the NSC which included the number two people in
                    Defense, Treasury, Justice, Commerce, Labor, and I am not sure who else. I
                    somehow, probably because of the earlier contact at the Pierre and my role in
                    the Under Secretary's Committee, became almost from the outset the principal
                    point of contact between the Department and the NSC process in general and Henry
                    Kissinger in particular. We had lunch once a week and met regularly in other
                    connections. It was understood from the beginning that although not an ex
                    official member of the NSC, I would attend all NSC meetings whether or not the
                    Secretary was also there. That developed a connection that proved to be
                    extremely important during the term in which I served for State. But knowing
                    that I was deficient in substantive background, I began from day one to try to
                    make up for that. I was living at the Cosmos Club, and my wife and children
                    stayed back in Boston until the end of the school year. I read cables and other
                    material, night after night, in the library of the Cosmos Club, and I gradually
                    accumulated considerable information. In the same period, I got a lot out of the
                    substantive meetings held with the relevant Assistant Secretaries and their
                    Deputies who were literally all Foreign Service officers. I also served as the
                    Chairman of the Committee on Presidential Appointments, that is appointments to
                    the positions of assistant secretaries, agency heads, and ambassadors. So there
                    wasn't much that I didn't have some contact with.</p>
                <p>Q: How did you organize your own office? Was it in any particular effective way?
                    Was it organized for you? How did you work with the staff secretary at SS?</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I didn't try to do any reorganizing of the office of the Under
                    Secretary. There were three key career people in the office when I arrived. One
                    was Arthur Hartman who was in effect the Executive Secretary, I am not sure what
                    the title was, of the Under Secretaries Committee. He had working with him, I
                    think he must have been a civil servant and not a Foreign Service officer but I
                    am not sure of that, named Claus Ruser. My staff assistant was Mort Abramowitz.
                    I brought with me two people, one of whom was Jonathan Moore, who had served
                    with Bill Bundy when he was Assistant Secretary of Defense for ISA and had been
                    in the USIA in Africa and had also been on the foreign policy staff of Governor
                    Romney. I also brought with me Wilmot Hastings, a lawyer who had been my first
                    assistant when I was Attorney General of Massachusetts. I also brought with me
                    my secretary, Cetta Leonardi, who had been with me in my Massachusetts jobs and
                    stayed with me for quite a long time after that. It was a great office.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>As to the executive Secretariat, there wasn't a lot of occasion to work directly
                    with the people in that office except during the time of some emergency, but I
                    looked at a lot of the material that came through them and I admired very much
                    the efficiency of the process whereby information was funneled in from all over
                    the world and passed on and distilled, or left in the same form, to people who
                    could use it or needed it. As I indicated, a lot of my education in those months
                    came from reading a very large portion of that material.</p>
                <p>Q: You mentioned that you got to know the Assistant Secretaries quite well and
                    their Deputies. Is this a good organization of the Department? Is it a good way
                    for the Department to be organized? Did the Assistant Secretary system function
                    satisfactorily as you look back on it?</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I thought it did in general. I thought the people who had those jobs
                    were highly capable. It's significant, by the way, that Richard Nixon, had, by
                    the time he took office as President, visited something like 64 countries around
                    the world. In those countries he had been briefed by, and in some cases,
                    traveled with Foreign Service officers. He knew a great many of them, and he had
                    a great respect for many of them. He had, before I came on board, already chosen
                    the Assistant Secretaries for some of the Bureaus including Marty Hillenbrand
                    for Europe, Joe Sisco for NEA, and Marshall Green. Actually, Marshall Green did
                    not come on right away; he kept Bill Bundy in EA.</p>
                <p>At any rate, within the areas subject to the jurisdiction of the geographical
                    bureaus, the quality of the analysis and recommendation was of very high order.
                    I came to believe, in due course, that the problem with the conduct of foreign
                    policy was and remained, always I was close to it, one of excessive absorption
                    in short-term operations at the expense of longer-term strategic planning and in
                    the coordination of the planning process, as between geographic bureaus. I used
                    to make a speech over and over again in those days to the effect that you guys
                    have to understand that this is the first time in the history of the United
                    States when we have had to have a foreign policy. Before World War I, we were
                    only beginning to see ourselves as a player on the world scene. Between World
                    War I and World War II we opted out, and for quite a long time after World War
                    II, really until now, we have had such a surplus of military and economic
                    muscle, we could flounder our way out of almost any trouble we got into. I would
                    add, “You ought to have on your desk a little sign like the IMB sign, the one
                    which says 'Think.' Your sign should say 'Scheme'.”</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>Let me back up. The established process largely consisted of the observations and
                    insights of hugely capable and well-trained people in the field who recorded the
                    significant political-economic developments in their country and region. These
                    reports would come back to the Department, then be distributed by the Executive
                    Secretariat. The reports would elicit instructions which would go back to the
                    field. The instructions would be carried out and the results would be reported
                    back. The high-prestige functions of the Foreign Service officer or the diplomat
                    were centered on the day by day, week by week, year by year execution of this
                    process. It did not allow for stepping back and looking at U.S. interests and
                    global developments from the point of view of how the United States should most
                    effectively deploy limited resources and influence on behalf of the things that
                    seemed most important. That led me to recommend to the Secretary, who acted on
                    the recommendation, changing the name of the Policy Planning Staff to Planning
                    and Coordination Staff. I thought it ought to be an instrument of the Secretary
                    that would perform for him a role similar to that performed by the National
                    Security Council for the President. I also believed that each of the geographic
                    bureau heads should also have a similar capability attached to them, and that
                    each of these should be linked to each other via the Planning and Coordination
                    Staff. This would, I hoped, enable them to have direct input into the NSC
                    process. I became convinced that we should try to strengthen the strategic
                    planning capabilities of our overseas missions, and this led to the selection of
                    Graham, then DCM in Tokyo, to head a project with this aim. This was the kind of
                    thing that primarily interested me, and I would have liked to have stayed with
                    longer.</p>
                <p>Q: I recall that the Secretary appointed you Chairman of the Committee on
                    Presidential Appointments fairly early on, and you promised that you would have
                    a major and comprehensive review of foreign policy mechanisms and try to make
                    better use of what you called unique human resources. Did the Board make
                    progress as far as you could see?</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I thought of the unique human resources as many times made the point
                    that I learned early on when I was in a meeting with a lot of Foreign Service
                    officers sitting around the table, to watch their expression and their small
                    reactions. I found that if I saw somebody raise an eyebrow or suppress a smile
                    and catch the eye of a career colleague, that was my cue to ask a question. I
                    found that I would invariably get a straight, informed, intelligent answer. Why
                    was it that these answers were seldom volunteered? I had to conclude that it was
                    because many career people had had difficult encounters with political
                    appointees who, suspecting that the professionals were pursuing an agenda of
                    their own, failed to take adequate advantage of the latter's experience and
                    advice. But I developed early on and have a great deal of respect for the
                    Foreign Service.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>I might add parenthetically, because I think it is important, a footnote to
                    history. I have heard so often that I would like to believe there must be
                    something in it that I was regarded by the Foreign Service as an effective and
                    articulate champion of its professional role and capability. It was also obvious
                    that I was the Department's most continuous and closest collaborator with Henry
                    Kissinger. How was it possible for me to be both? Surprisingly, that question
                    has never been asked by anyone to my face. If anyone did ask me, I would tell
                    them that the answer is very simple. The State Department chaired all the
                    Inter-Departmental Groups of the NSC. I was the Chairman of the Under
                    Secretaries Committee. Most papers, the National Security Studies Memoranda, for
                    example, that went into the NSC process came out of these groups. Most of the
                    work was done by State Department people. I would therefore say to my State
                    Department colleagues, “Look, our influence depends on the quality of these
                    papers. You should think of them as being like a well designed, hydro-dynamic,
                    projectile fired into a viscous fluid. The better designed it is, the more
                    deeply it will penetrate.” Then I had another less pleasant image. I would say,
                    “Surely, you must have been to the dentist and had him run that little pick
                    around your teeth. You know that everything is fine as long as the point of the
                    pick moves smoothly. But if it catches, he'll dig away at that little spot, and
                    maybe make a mark on the chart of your teeth, and that's a cavity that will have
                    to be dealt with at another appointment. You come back for the next appointment,
                    and the drill is going zzz...zzz...zzz and then suddenly goes chunk into a
                    hollowed-out place where the tooth is rotted away. You should think of Henry
                    Kissinger's mind as being that pick going over the paper: you don't want it to
                    catch, and of course you don't want any rotten places.” The better the paper is,
                    the more influence we have. So I never allowed to appear that there was any
                    possible conflict of interest, rivalry, or competition between the NSC process
                    and the Department. The only issues were issues on the merits.</p>
                <p>I served on the so-called Verification Panel which developed the SALT I
                    negotiating strategy. I had a lot more to do with the Middle East than Kissinger
                    did until May or at least the Spring of 1970. I met regularly with Yitzhak
                    Rabin, then the ambassador of Israel, and Abdul Hamid Sharaf, the ambassador of
                    Jordan, who was spokesman for the front-line Arab states. I tried to pursue some
                    sort of dialogue directed toward the realities of the Arab/Israeli situation. I
                    had a lot to do with the development of an approach toward a more realistic
                    relationship with China. In fact, Win Brown and Mort Abramowitz brought to me in
                    March, I believe, of 1969 the suggestion that if the United States wished to
                    show a serious interest in moving toward a more realistic relationship with
                    China, there were steps we could take to communicate that signal. Those were the
                    days in which Walter Stoessel was in Warsaw conducting a large and unprofitable
                    dialogue with the Chinese. So Win and Mort drafted for me a memorandum from me
                    to the President listing five or six things that could be done if we wished to
                    communicate this message. I got the memorandum back from Nixon a few days later
                    with his own hand-writing on it telling us to go ahead on I think three of these
                    initiatives, to modify one, and drop one. It had his initials on the bottom. I
                    gave a speech at the War College in September of 1969 arguing for a triangular
                    relationship in which, having moved toward a closer relationship with China,
                    there would have been created a equilateral triangle in the East with the Soviet
                    Union on one side, China one side, and the U.S. and Japan on the third side.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>All of that kind of thing, including the NSSM we did on what should be the U.S.
                    reaction toward Soviet aggression toward China, was done in a climate in which
                    cooperation between the Department and the White House was a given. Rogers was
                    not actively involved in that process because he really did not want to be.</p>
                <p>Q: ...which led to the perception on the part of the press that he was being
                    by-passed or overshadowed by Kissinger. This is what I recall, vaguely, from the
                    time.</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Of course, he was overshadowed by Kissinger. I have kidded Kissinger
                    about this. I've told him he's gotten far too much credit for his Machiavellian
                    skills when, in fact, in that situation all he had to do was fill a vacuum.</p>
                <p>We all have the defects of our qualities, and Rogers' principal defect grew out
                    of his qualities as a lawyer. Lawyers who have had a lot of exposure to
                    litigation come to think in terms of cases. Cases involve critical outbreaks of
                    some form of conflict between two or more sides. Rogers told me that he thought
                    speculation about the dynamics of interacting geostrategic forces and the
                    balance of power and so on was a waste of time. He really made no effort to get
                    into those issues. Nixon, conversely, had developed enormous interest in them,
                    going back to the early days of the outbreak of the Cold War, when he had taken
                    his first trip to Europe in connection with the development and implementation
                    of Secretary Marshall's proposal for an American initiative to rebuild Europe.
                    He went with Christian Herter, among others, and came back with a much larger
                    perspective on the U.S. role.</p>
                <p>One of the things that, despite the trauma of my resignation back in 1973, I have
                    never failed to underscore, whenever the question arose, is the proposition that
                    the architect of the Nixon foreign policy was Nixon. He came into office with a
                    highly developed strategic sense. One example that seemed to me at the time to
                    be particularly striking was his decision to go to Bucharest on his first trip
                    abroad as the President of the United States. There in President Ceausescu he
                    found an individual who was slavishly conformist to Soviet domestic policies in
                    the conduct of domestic policies in Romania. But Ceausescu took advantage of his
                    conformity on that side in order to be highly independent with respect both to
                    the convening of the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe as a means
                    of undermining the Brezhnev doctrine while at the same time being the only
                    Eastern bloc leader who maintained diplomatic relations with China. Thus Nixon,
                    in one stop, simultaneously conveyed the interest of the U.S. in normalizing
                    relations both within the Eastern bloc and with China as long term objectives. I
                    got my cue from that right away. Without even being asked I got my staff to
                    compile for me an inventory of all the problems we had with each of the
                    countries in Eastern Europe from the Hungarian crown jewels and the Mindszenty
                    detention to the Romanian gold.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>Nixon's Guam Doctrine was a product of the same strategic perspective. He was
                    looking toward the question of how the U.S. could sustain the Western free-world
                    position against Soviet pressure at lower cost, over the long haul. The way to
                    do that was to eliminate the prospect of clashes or friction peripheral to the
                    central contest. What he was trying to do seemed clear to me, and I thought it
                    made a lot of sense. I began on my own to explore the potential of a two-China
                    policy, for example. But Rogers just wasn't interested in that kind of thinking.
                    When, on the other hand, an American plane was shot down off of North Korea, he
                    sprang into action and handled the situation extremely well.</p>
                <p>I take it that this is a record that will not be published at antime?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It will not be published. It is supposed to be
                        unclassified, buit is not available to the general public.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: One of the ironies of the situation I concluded, was that Rogers
                    somewhat looked down on Nixon. I think he found it very difficult to be his
                    subordinate. I think his connection with Nixon went back to the time when Rogers
                    had a leading role in shaping the strategy with which Nixon dealt with the slush
                    fund situation in the 1952 campaign and that gave rise to the Checker's speech.
                    I couldn't help feeling that he didn't engage with Nixon much because he was
                    uncomfortable somehow in doing so. The result was that he left a door open, and
                    all Kissinger had to do was walk through it.</p>
                <p>Q: That puts it really well. I gather from what you have been saying is that you
                    think the state of coordination among the agencies on foreign policy matters was
                    pretty good.</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: It was pretty good. I do not think there was a lack of coordination.
                    When you asked me this earlier, I went into a longish explanation of why I
                    thought the process needed a longer-range, more comprehensive and integrated
                    strategic orientation or approach. But that would have been in addition to, and
                    not a substitute for, what was already being done. By the way, this is not
                    entirely a digression. It bears on what I said earlier about Nixon's travels and
                    his role in the appointment of career people. Another FSO, by the way, who
                    belongs on that list is U. Alexis Johnson, whom he brought back from Japan as
                    the Under Secretary for Political Affairs.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>This is a story that has to be written. I still think there are a lot of things
                    that ought to be said about Nixon that only compound one's awareness of what a
                    paradoxical and even contradictory character he was. But he not only made the
                    kind of appointments that I just spoke of, but with respect to political
                    appointees, from the time I came in, I never saw a new name beyond the 18
                    individuals whom he had decided at the outset he wanted to give ambassadorial
                    appointments. I got in the discussion with Tom Flanagan who was on his White
                    House staff on where these people would go. The White House never told me where
                    they should go. They never put on any pressure. I would meet with them and we
                    would discuss it. I remember one nice man with whom I discussed several
                    intermediate level posts for which he might be qualified. He said he didn't feel
                    up to those, adding, “I have served on some of these promotion boards that they
                    have for Foreign Service officers, and I know what those guys can do. I don't
                    feel that those posts are appropriate for someone like me.” I said, “Well, what
                    about Iceland?” He said, “That would be dandy! I think I would be good in
                    Iceland.”</p>
                <p>There was one man, on the other hand, who wanted Paris, and when that went to
                    somebody else, he wasn't named for any other appointment. Parenthetically, we
                    did not push anybody out until we had a replacement. We left the Shrivers in
                    Paris until September. We left Sol Linowitz in the Organization for American
                    States. We left Schaetzel in Brussels, and so on around the world. I mentioned
                    Bundy already. There was no movement in the White House to get him out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...well that was very long-sighted...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: The upshot of that was that by the end of Nixon's first year in
                    office, the portion of Foreign Service officers who held ambassadorial
                    appointments was higher than when he came in. I would bet you that that has not
                    happened with any other president.</p>
                <p>Q: I imagine not. I don't want to impose any more on your time. What I wanted to
                    do was to ask you to elaborate on the development of LOS policy during your time
                    as Under Secretary because I think you had a significant role in that, and maybe
                    we can pick that up at the next time.</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: It isn't a long story, but I think it is relevant.</p>
                <p>Q: I think it's relevant particularly given your later appointment as Special
                    Representative of the President. But after we do that I would like to spend some
                    time on your ambassadorship in the UK and then a little more time on LOS. So I
                    will work this out with Marguerite when this will be convenient for you.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: You can see it is tempting to unload a lot of things that I have
                    never had the occasion to put on paper elsewhere. I did put that bit about
                    Kissinger and Rogers in my new book. I am not sure that Rogers is going to like
                    it very much, but then I think that maybe Kissinger won't either.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Q: This is a continuation of an oral history interview with the Honorable Elliot
                    L. Richardson in the offices of Millbank, Tweed, Hadley, and McCloy. Today is
                    November 7, 1996. In the last interview, we talked about your tenure as deputy
                    to Secretary of State William P. Rogers from 1969 to 1970. Today I'd like to
                    pick up where we left off by asking you to talk about the Nixon administration's
                    Law of the Sea policy. I might just note that my research has reminded me that
                    in February 1970, President Nixon in an address to Congress called for an
                    international agreement on the width of the territorial sea. A few months later,
                    his administration endorsed the concept that the resources of the deep sea bed
                    is the common heritage of mankind. What was the impetus for President Nixon's
                    initiatives? Having talked about that, I'd like to know what your own role was.
                    As I recall, you were pretty central to the development of policy on the Law of
                    the Sea.</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: That is true. The impetus for President Nixon's initiative was the
                    phenomenon, called “creeping jurisdiction.” In response partly to President
                    Truman's assertion of U.S. control of the minerals in the continental shelf out
                    to the 400 meter isobath, the West Coast Latin American countries, which had
                    steeply shelving coastlines descending to depths greater than 400 meters, very
                    close to shore, had asserted territorial sea claims out to 200 miles from shore.
                    That had created a lot of problems with the access of American tuna boats to
                    those waters. Coincidentally, I had been the principal staffer on Capitol Hill
                    in 1954 who handled on the Senate side the adoption of the Fisherman's
                    Protective Act of 1954, which undertook to bail out American tuna boats, pay the
                    fines, and procure the release of the fishermen seized by those countries. The
                    theory was that if the U.S. wished to maintain its position that these were high
                    seas areas and American boats acting on that premise got seized, then the U.S.
                    government should stand in back of its position.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>When I came to State in 1969, I found that the problem of tuna boat seizures had
                    recently become very acute. Various sanctions were under consideration,
                    including the dispatch of destroyers to the area. Consideration was being given
                    to involving the so-called “Hickenlooper Amendment.” I became involved very
                    early on with that problem. The question now of passage through straits (at that
                    time, the concept of “transit passage” had not yet originated) became important
                    because we and many other countries were contemplating an extension of the
                    territorial sea to 12 miles. That would have eliminated any high-seas corridor
                    through all of the world's most important straits since all of them are less
                    than 24 miles wide. In the meantime, the archipelagic countries like Indonesia
                    were agitating the issue of converting archipelagic waters into the equivalent
                    of internal waters, which would have impeded the transit of our ships and
                    submarines through the Indonesian archipelago as well as any other
                    archipelago.</p>
                <p>For all of these reasons, my counterpart at Defense, David Packard, and I got
                    together early on in the Nixon administration to discuss what initiatives might
                    be taken. Our thrust was primarily toward the convening of a conference dealing
                    with maritime issues. It's a very long story, but the upshot of that in due
                    course was the realization that if the maritime countries alone convened a
                    conference, it would be like holding a party to which nobody else came. The
                    resulting agreement would be of no value against the coastal states asserting
                    broader jurisdiction. It was that which led to the conclusion that there would
                    have to be a conference that addressed coastal-state and landlocked-state
                    interests, as well as maritime-state interests. Hence, the so-called “package
                    deal” that was understood from the outset would be the objective of the Third
                    United Nations Conference on the Law of the Sea. But Packard and I agreed that
                    we should stimulate some sort of initiative to contact the Soviet Union with the
                    idea that each of us had a national interest in maintaining maximum freedom of
                    maneuver for our own naval forces against the other's. I can't now recall
                    exactly how that was followed up.</p>
                <p>In 1970 the Under Secretaries Committee of the NSC, which I chaired, developed a
                    proposal to extend coastal-state jurisdiction over mineral resources in the
                    continental margin, but provided that some fraction of the proceeds like 2.5% of
                    gross sales would be shared among developing countries. This proposal was put
                    forward by our then Legal Adviser, Jack Stevenson, at a conference in Geneva, I
                    believe, in the summer of 1970. Ironically, it was shot down by the developing
                    countries themselves. Francis X. Njenga of Kenya was the mastermind of that
                    oddly self-destructive move. I can't resist adding parenthetically that when I
                    came on board in 1977, as head of the Law of the Sea delegation, the then Under
                    Secretary of State for Economic Affairs, Dick Cooper, and the Assistant
                    Secretary of the Treasury for International Affairs, Fred Bergsten, both urged
                    me to see if we could revive this proposal because it could generate very
                    substantial economic assistance to developing countries. I was obliged to tell
                    them that, as a result of U.S. support in the meantime for the 200-mile
                    Exclusive Economic Zone and of our own proposal for coastal-state jurisdiction
                    over the continental shelf, that it was too late to go back to that
                    proposal.</p>
                <p>This was roughly all that I had to do with the Law of the Sea in thaperiod.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>Q: I find it interesting that the Nixon administration, a Republican
                    administration, endorsed Pardo's concept that the minerals of the deep sea bed
                    are the common heritage of mankind. Was this looked on as necessary in order to
                    advance our strategic and other interests in the Law of the Sea?</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I think it was not so much that as that it was a common sense
                    proposition. If you were not prepared to carve up the deep seabed the way Africa
                    was carved up in the 19th century, it followed that it was a global commons and
                    had to be so administered. There is no workable way around that proposition. It
                    had already been affirmed by LBJ before we took office.</p>
                <p>Q: That's the interesting thing about Law of the Sea. I was talking in another
                    interview about how historically, it has been a bipartisan effort. Both parties
                    are looking on it as something very much in the interests of the United States.
                    It's kind of ironic that 12 years later, another Republican administration in
                    effect turned its back on the idea of the common heritage of mankind for a
                    number of reasons.</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Not quite. Let me go back for one moment first. The proposal that we
                    put forward in Geneva on the distribution of proceeds from exploitation of the
                    continental shelf was by far more significant in terms of actual potential
                    benefit to developing countries than anything that could ever have been
                    generated by the deep seabed. It was a tragedy, in a way a tragic-comedy, that
                    the exploitation of the nickel, copper, cobalt, and manganese continued in
                    manganese nodules was ever viewed as potentially yielding a “bonanza,” which, as
                    you remember, they were widely advertised as potentially doing. But the truth,
                    as I soon learned, was that the maximum worldwide annual sales of nickel came to
                    only $2 billion a year. Even if all nickel production had been from the seabed,
                    the fraction of the profits that would have gone to developing countries and so
                    on wouldn't have amounted to more than $50 or $100 million a year. And, of
                    course, the seabed market share would in fact never have been more than a
                    fraction of the total market. Adding royalties from the sale of the other seabed
                    minerals would still have been far short of a “bonanza.” When you consider that
                    the Continental Shelf Convention only went out to 400 meters, and that our 1970
                    proposal called for dividing the proceeds of oil and gas production from depths
                    greater than 400 meters, it's apparent that we were talking really big money. It
                    was ironical as hell that Njenga and the developing countries shot it down—one
                    of the most shortsighted things they ever did. The proposal was not
                    inconsistent, on the other hand, with the Nixon administration's basic approach.
                    It was distinctly to the left of the Clinton administration in many things. The
                    Reagan administration in its turn didn't so much repudiate the concept of the
                    common heritage as choke on various provisions whereby access to it would be
                    subject to restrictions on free-market principles, including a condition on the
                    transfer of technology and a production ceiling of some sort designed to protect
                    the producers of the same minerals from land-based sources, and a few other
                    things like that, which they enumerated and which, as you know, have since been
                    addressed by amendments to the charter.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Q: One other question. I infer from your remarks that the development of policy
                    went along really fairly smoothly. It's always important for some people who
                    would think it was a good idea and push it to work pretty hard at it. But you
                    didn't run into serious resistance within the administration?</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No. I didn't run into any serious resistance within the
                    administration on any significant issue involving State Department interests and
                    policy. I remarked earlier on the answer to a question which nobody in the press
                    ever asked, of how it happened that Richardson was in constant contact with and
                    working cooperatively with Henry Kissinger, while also being viewed by his
                    colleagues in the State Department, including most especially the career
                    services, as the State Department's champion in the foreign policy development
                    process? The answer, I believe, says quite a lot about what I think was the
                    rationality of Nixon's strategic direction of foreign policy, the clarity of his
                    objectives, and the potential therefore of supplying input.</p>
                <p>By the way, if you would like to do an interesting piece of research, I have a
                    suggestion for you. One of Henry Kissinger's books, I'm not sure which,
                    identifies a statement I made about the Soviet Union and China as reflecting the
                    most important foreign policy initiative taken by the Nixon administration. Bill
                    Bundy, who has been working for 10 years or so on a book about the Nixon foreign
                    policy, has independently arrived at the same conclusion. The statement was to
                    the effect that the United States would take very seriously (the words are very
                    important, but I don't remember them precisely, and regard as a significant
                    threat to U.S. national security interests any aggressive action taken by the
                    Soviet Union against China. Bill Bundy asked me what I could remember about how
                    that statement got made and why, of all people in the administration from the
                    President through the Secretary of State and on down, I got to be the person who
                    made it publicly. I had no memory of it. I talked to my then chief assistant,
                    Jonathan Moore, Art Hartman, who was the chief staff person for the Under
                    Secretaries Committee, and Morton Abramowitz, who was my staff assistant. None
                    of them had any recollection of it. I know that there was an interdepartmental
                    group on U.S.-Chinese security related issues, including the question of how the
                    U.S. would react to Soviet aggression. I remember that Miriam Camps, then
                    director of Policy Planning, took a leading, if not the leading, role in the
                    development of that so-called NSSM, and this might have led to the statement in
                    question. If it was that important, it's worth checking out. As to whether it
                    was that important, I don't have an independent view at this moment. But I would
                    sure like to know. One person that might have some recollection of it is, I
                    think, Bob Barnett. There are two Barnett brothers, right?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Doak Barnett and someone.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I think it was Bob. There must be something in threcord on that.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's worth checking into.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>Q: I just have one other question to ask you about your time as Under Secretary
                    of State. You must have met a number of interesting and important people in your
                    travels during that time. Are there any that struck you as worth commenting
                    about? Perhaps your relationships with some of them were useful and significant
                    when you were Special Representative to the President to the Law of the Sea
                    Conference.</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: That is an interesting question. I'd have to reflect on the latter
                    part of it. One of the most understandably interesting contacts was that with
                    Jean Sainteny. Jean Sainteny had been the last French governor of Indochina.
                    Something about the manner in which the turnover of power had been handled had
                    created great trust and regard for him on the part of the government of North
                    Vietnam. As I think I probably mentioned before, it had been understood that as
                    Under Secretary of State I would sit in on all NSC meetings. One of my details
                    became the development of the political proposals that were to be presented to
                    North Vietnam as integral to the proposed peace settlement. My staff and I
                    developed a plan under which, to put it simply, there would be elections at the
                    local level, the provincial level, and nationally within the whole of South
                    Vietnam. The distribution of power at each level would be allocated in
                    proportion to the number of votes received by the South Vietnamese pro-U.S.
                    candidates and pro-North Vietnam, the Viet Cong candidates. Kissinger thought
                    that there was some question as to whether or not the generosity and fairness of
                    this proposal had been adequately communicated to the top levels of the North
                    Vietnamese government. De Sainteny's wife was a very bright and attractive woman
                    who had been a student of Henry's at Harvard. She was the author, among other
                    things, of a well-known book called “Love in the Western World,” which traced
                    the literary and artistic conventions from the classic through the medieval and
                    romantic periods, and so on. I never read the book, but it was along those
                    lines. Anyway, it was through her that Henry came to know her husband, Jean de
                    Sainteny. It was his thought that I should brief de Sainteny and ask him to make
                    sure that a clear understanding of this proposal got directly to the top levels
                    of the Viet Cong and the North Vietnamese government.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>I want to add a piece which I don't remember talking about but which was one of
                    the most important of my initiatives in that period. I stopped in Paris to see
                    de Sainteny on the way to Brussels in December, 1969. My purpose in going to
                    Brussels was to sell our NATO allies on a mutual and balanced force reductions
                    initiative. In those days, there was pressure within the United States
                    particularly, but also in other Western countries for cutting the level of U.S.
                    forces committed to Europe. The biggest threat came from the so-called
                    “Mansfield Amendment” that would have forced a reduction of 50,000 U.S. troops
                    in Europe. It occurred to me that the most effective counter to the Mansfield
                    Amendment would be agreement among the NATO allies and proposal for mutual and
                    balanced force reductions, thus making inexpedient a unilateral reduction. So, I
                    went to Brussels in December to sell that idea, did sell it, and NATO did
                    propose it early in 1970. I forget when. The irony of it was, the Soviets
                    delayed and delayed in their response to it. This is another interesting subject
                    to research. I was no longer in the State Department when, in May of 1973, I
                    think, the Mansfield Resolution was finally brought up and was being debated on
                    the floor of the U.S. Senate. While the debate was still underway the Soviet
                    Union suddenly announced its acceptance of negotiations on mutual and balanced
                    force reductions. This announcement knocked the Mansfield Resolution on the head
                    then and there. It worked like a charm. Stan Resorl was named to represent the
                    U.S., and these negotiations went on for years in Vienna.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, I do remember.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, naturally enough, the question arose, was the Soviet timing
                    inadvertent or advertent? For several years after that whenever I ran into a
                    highly placed Soviet foreign policy type, I would ask him, “Did you do this
                    deliberately because you did not want to see the destabilization consequent upon
                    a U.S. reduction, which might force an increase in German forces to offset ours,
                    and thus be considerably quite disturbing from your point of view, or was it
                    just by chance?” I got both answers. The guy (I can't now remember his name) who
                    seemed to be closest to the decision was a senior staffer for the Soviets,
                    equivalent of the National Security Council, said it was deliberate, but others
                    told me it wasn't. Now, that would be an interesting question to check out.
                    That's why I was going to Europe. I suppose that, speaking of contacts in NATO,
                    Tetsinyani, who was then Under Secretary of NATO for something like Political
                    Affairs and later became ambassador to the U.S. One of the most interesting
                    characters I met in those days was Joseph Luns, who has succeeded Brolio as
                    Secretary General of NATO. He was one of the most entertaining characters I ever
                    met, a nonstop raconteur. One of the most amusing experiences I ever had was on
                    a flight from Washington to Norfolk to celebrate the 20th anniversary of NATO. I
                    sat on the plane across from Dennis Heale and Luns. They vied with each other
                    the whole way down on swapping funny anecdotes. I wish I'd had a tape
                    recorder.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you see the transcript, of course, you can add to it.
                        Wencourage you to do so.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I'm throwing in some things here that may not be in your script. They
                    are among the most interesting. By the way, I am being interviewed this
                    afternoon, coincidentally, on another initiative that I think was of significant
                    long-term importance. I remember discovering with shock and surprise that the
                    U.S. had badly neglected its mandate over the Strategic Trust Territory of the
                    Western Pacific, which was being administered by the Department of the Interior.
                    The economic conditions in the territory were miserable. We were not doing much
                    of anything for its people. We were going to have to give up Cameroon Bay. We
                    might also lose our bases in the Philippines. The least we ought to do is be
                    sure of access to bases in the Trust Territory. It was inevitable that we were
                    eventually going to have to yield the mandate that entrusted the United States
                    with this territory under the Trusteeship Council of the UN. There would be a
                    referendum offering various choices. In the meantime, therefore, we'd better get
                    on the stick and improve our relations with these people. So I promptly got in
                    touch with the Department of the Interior. Fortunately, they had a very good guy
                    in charge of this kind of thing. He was Edgar Kaiser, Jr., Assistant Secretary
                    of the Interior. What we did then must all be in the records: what step-ups then
                    began on education support, agricultural assistance, and other things. But I
                    consider that one of my more important initiatives.</p>
                <p>I haven't told you about Israel and the Arabs—I should. That was probably the
                    most important thing I was involved with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Please do. I think that...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: When I came in, Joe Sisco was Assistant Secretary for the Middle
                    East. Henry Kissinger until the very end of my tour stayed away from the Middle
                    East. I think he was insecure about his German-Jewish background and, of course,
                    whether he would be viewed as detached enough to address it. In any case, he
                    didn't. The upshot was that I became the point of contact for Yitzhak Rabin,
                    then ambassador to the U.S., and the representative of the front-line Arab
                    states. Ambassador Sharaf of Jordan. He was a Harvard College graduate, a very
                    intelligent, thoughtful, decent, and fair-minded man. I met alternately with
                    Rabin and Sharaf almost from the beginning of my period at State then. The
                    paramount objective of our discussions was promoting direct face-to-face
                    negotiations between the Arabs and the Israelis. Rabin believed that if the
                    Arabs could be committed to respect the right of Israel to exist, its
                    territorial integrity, and so on in exchange for peace in accordance with the
                    Security Council Resolution 345, that this would not only be in the interest of
                    Israel but also that Arab honor would undergird their support for the promises
                    they had made once they had sat down face-to-face and reached an agreement. But
                    the problem was bringing that about. I suggested to Rabin one day that Israel
                    ought to hire the Hall of Mirrors at Versailles so that each side could sit at
                    the table back to back but look at the other side in the mirror in front of
                    them. The upshot of all that was a very important memorandum that I left behind
                    when I left State in May. I had an assistant then named Rein, whom I later
                    convinced Phil Trezise, Assistant Secretary for Economic Affairs, to take on as
                    his Deputy for aviation negotiations. A very bright young guy, Burt Rein was one
                    of the very few people at that point ever to graduate from the Harvard Law
                    School with a summa degree. He worked with me at the end on a memorandum which
                    said, in effect, that there would never be a peace settlement on the
                    Arab-Israeli front until and unless the grievances of the people aggrieved were
                    squarely addressed. The people aggrieved were clearly the Palestinians. For 20
                    years the Palestinians had been brushed aside as “the refugee problem” because
                    they were stateless. They had no UN representation, no ambassadors. My recent
                    book discusses this as an example I won't now explain of what I call the “Mount
                    Washington Fallacy.”</p>
                <p>I made some efforts to find responsible people among the Palestinian community on
                    the West Bank who might become its representatives in such a discussion. I don't
                    remember how I found him, but I located one highly regarded old man who had (not
                    that old, perhaps, from my present perspective) who had recently retired as a
                    secondary school principal. He broke down and wept in my office because, he
                    said, “for 20 years I have been trying to get somebody to focus on the fact that
                    we are the people whose territory was occupied. We represent a very large
                    fraction of the populations of Jordan, Syria, and Iraq. As long as we feel that
                    we have a just claim that is not being redressed, there will be no real peace.”
                    I think that memorandum was among the most important things I had to do with,
                    next perhaps to the memorandum I sent to the President about China. I must have
                    told you about that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think we did talk about that last time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: You asked me about personalities. I'd have to stop and think about
                    that. If I get any good thoughts on it, I could fill them in later.</p>
                <p>Q: That would be fine. There is plenty of opportunity to do that. We've been at
                    this for 45 minutes. I don't want to impose on your time. You've got other
                    things on your mind.</p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I have five more minutes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's just jump in a little bit to your tour as ambassador
                        to thCourt of St. James's.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: You probably know more about that than I do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, but people want to hear what you have to say and not
                        what want to say. I've said it once in an interview I did.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I might as well level with you and anybody who later realizes this.
                    The job you had, the job the DCM had, the jobs the economic counselor and the
                    information officer had in London were all important jobs. The job the
                    ambassador had was not. I think there are two reasons for that. One is that
                    Presidents and Secretaries of State like dealing directly with their British
                    counterparts. The other reason, at least in that period, was that there were few
                    large issues that needed to be taken up by the American ambassador with the
                    British foreign secretary, Chancellor of the Exchequer or, indeed, the Prime
                    Minister. On the economic front, in almost all the difficult issues, the party
                    seeking some action or some benefit was on the British side—landing rights for
                    the Concorde or Pilkington Plate Glass, for instance. There were a lot of things
                    that properly fell within the role of the DCM, a highly capable guy. All the
                    Embassy's junior people were highly capable and experienced. But the things they
                    dealt with were not appropriately things that I was called upon to deal
                    with.</p>
                <p>The result was, therefore, that my role and my wife's was largely one of trying
                    to maintain and sustain cordial relations with a variety of people. We
                    deliberately sought to broaden the range of people who were invited to Winfield
                    House. I was perhaps the only ambassador who ever met with the Executive
                    Committee of the Trade Union Congress, whom I invited for dinner one evening at
                    the chancery. We had people from a variety of other roles and backgrounds. I
                    found it very valuable that having been both a politician and a bureaucrat, I
                    could empathize with and imagine what was going on politically, where Callahan
                    and Heale and Jenkins were involved, and also...I can't come up with the
                    name.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Harold Wilson?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Not Wilson. I didn't see him a lot. That reminds me, though, of a
                    conversational gambit I sometimes employed when I found myself sitting next to a
                    corporate CEO or a prominent leader. I would lean over to him and say, “You
                    know, it's so interesting to have the opportunity to meet someone like yourself.
                    I can't resist asking a question that has long fascinated me.” I used this on
                    Wilson at a luncheon he gave for me at Number 10 Downing Street. I said, “Has
                    intrigue ever played a significant part in your career?” He had a row of pipes
                    in front of him, including a colored pipe that had been given to him by Gerry
                    Ford.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Nelson Rockefeller, too. I remember, we went to call
                        on hiand Rockefeller pulled out three colored pipes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, he did? Puffing on one of his pipes, Wilson said, “Well, in my
                    career, I can't say that I've ever practiced intrigue on my own account, but I
                    have been called upon from time to time to deal in the requirements of
                    counter-intrigue.” Well, damned if sometime later I heard Wilson give the
                    principal speech at the annual dinner at the British Academy. He spent a lot of
                    time building on the uniqueness of his own prime ministerial career and then
                    turned to some of the insights derived from that experience. “In the course of
                    my career,” he said, “I have never found it necessary to engage in intrigue.
                    There have been times, however, when I have been obliged to practice
                    counter-intrigue.”</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
