<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001428">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Louise Ostermeier and Henrietta Curry</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2007</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>LILLIAN ELEANOR OSTERMEIER AND HARRIET CURRY</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: February 21, 2002</p>
                <p>Copyright 2006 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Eleanor, would you tell me when and where you were born ad
                        something about your family please.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I was born in Illinois on a farm in 1913. So, you see, I'm not very
                    young. My parents lived on the farm for their entire married life. I came and
                    went from there all my life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's talk a little bit about your family. Your
                        family must have been of German extraction.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Yes. German.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where in Illinois was this farm?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: We were about 25 miles from Springfield, right in the center of
                    Illinois.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What type of crops were they raising there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Corn and soybean.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you speak German at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: No. I didn't speak German. My father didn't speak German either. His
                    parents came over from Germany, so I know something about the family.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did the family come from?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: From Hanover. They came over. My great-grandfather came with is seven
                    children, one of whom was my grandfather. They came into New York Harbor, and
                    went up the Hudson River, and crossed to Ohio. They lived in Ohio until one by
                    one, they started coming to Illinois, and eventually all the family came to
                    Illinois.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did the family first leave Hanover and come to the
                        United States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I've got it written down someplace, but it's in the 1840s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: 1840. On your mother's side, what was her background?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I guess my mother was mostly English, but they used to say she was
                    Scottish. It was a mixture. She was really basically Scotch, I think. Of course,
                    many Scotts traveled and went to Ireland first, and then came to the United
                    States. Her parents came to upper New York State and settle there. Eventually,
                    for one reason or another, one member of the family went out to Illinois, and
                    she went out to Illinois, and another member came out afterwards. They always
                    kept in touch with the New York relatives. Half of them were in one place, and
                    half in the other place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your mother's maiden name?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Montgomery.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Montgomery. How much education did your parents have,
                        would you say?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: They had whatever grade school education people had in those days. My
                    mother went to business college. My father also went to a business college for
                    accounting, and so forth, for management, but very briefly. They lived within
                    two miles of each other in this little community. They met and married, and
                    moved four or five miles away. My father built a house, and they lived in it the
                    entire time they were alive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you grow up as a farm girl?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Definitely, and during the depression.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: So, all my education was business education. We couldn't afford
                    college.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have brothers or sisters?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I have one brother who stayed on the farm his whole life, and a
                    sister, who eventually married somebody in the military. They moved around her
                    whole married life. She is now deceased, but her daughter lives here in Virginia
                    suburbs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As far as school, you went to a small school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I went to a rural school for eight years. My first education was in a
                    one-room country school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was going to say, one room? How does that work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: It was very interesting. As I look back, it was quite a small school,
                    but I used to listen to all the other classes. I was the youngest one in school,
                    to begin with. I listened to everybody reciting their lessons. I got a broader
                    education than I might have otherwise. Eventually, I went to the community high
                    school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The community high school was in which city or town?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: It was in a little town called Edinburg, Illinois. It was about five
                    miles from the farm.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In high school, what sort of subjects appealed to
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I took what was offered, which was the absolute minimum. I liked to
                    travel, from the very beginning, when I started to work. I used to take trips,
                    when I could afford to feed myself. I think that helped direct me to the Foreign
                    Service, but that was a long time afterwards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the farm, what sort of chores were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I didn't do much myself. My mother had chickens, and that sort of
                    thing, and I helped with that, but I didn't ever do the real farm work. My
                    brother was there, and he was the one to do that. Just to finish this off; our
                    farm had been in the family. My grandfather owned the land, and eventually my
                    father bought it from him. Now, my brother farms the land. They just recently
                    got a plaque that says, “Centennial Farm,” because the same farm has been in the
                    same family for 100 years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, Harriet, we will move to you then. When and where
                        were you born?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I was born I Annapolis, Maryland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Annapolis, Maryland, not very far away. My father was a Marine officer. My
                    mother was the daughter of the Minister at St. Anne's Church in Annapolis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes. This is on Church Circle.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: An Episcopalian church.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: That's right, that's where mother met my father, two children came.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When were you born?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: 1925, 77 years ago, almost.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your father's background?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: He was from a rather poor family. I heard recently that his father had
                    committed suicide. I knew he had died when my father was very young. He had a
                    sister, in Germantown, Pennsylvania. There were of German and Irish background.
                    He was going to a trade school during World War II. He was going to be a dairy
                    farmer, but ran away from school to join the Marine Corps.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're talking about World War I.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: No, well yes, during World War I. While he was in the marine corps, an
                    officer persuaded him to go to Annapolis, to get some training. He hadn't gone
                    to college.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, he went to the Naval Academy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember what class he was in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Yes, 1923.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you sort of live the life of a Navy junior, going from
                        base to base?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: It wasn't very typical. We lived at Quantico several times and at Port au
                    Prince when my father was stationed with the Marines in Haiti, a number of times
                    in California when my father was stationed on a ship nearby or at sea.</p>
                <p>My father went to law school through the Navy at George Washington University in
                    Washington, DC.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go to school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Woodrow Wilson High School in Washington, DC.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, where did you go before?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I went to a number of schools in different cities, but largely in
                    Washington. I first started school in s small town outside Los Angeles, called
                    Point Fermin. My father was aboard a ship. That was for a year or tow. We came
                    to Washington for a couple of year; went to Quantico where I went to school for
                    a year, out to California again, and back to Washington. So I went to a lot of
                    Washington schools. I went to E.V. Brown, now the Chevy Chase recreational
                    center (but I can still sing “the Brownies go marching along,” that is, if I
                    could sing.) I went to a junior high school outside of Philadelphia where my
                    father was at the Philadelphia Navy Yard, and then we came back to Washington
                    where I went to Woodrow Wilson High School.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I school, were there any subjects that particularly
                        interested you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: No. Most of them I didn't mind, but one I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which one?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Math.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Welcome to the club.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: My father said he took geometry four times at Wilson because he had four
                    children who all had it at Wilson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Eleanor, we'll move back to you. In high school, were
                        there any particular subjects that interested you? You said there wasn't
                        much offered. How about reading? Anything in particular?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I suppose I read quite a lot in my early days. The subjects studies
                    in high school were science, algebra. It was just the classic small high school
                    studies. I don't' think I was particularly good at that. I always made good
                    grades, and I didn't have to work very hard. I used to kind of coast along, and
                    daydream, and suddenly realize I hadn't prepared my lesson, and I would prepare
                    about 10 minutes before class.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were in high school, the depression was well
                        under way. How did the depression hit your family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Well, it hit the farm families pretty hard. But, in some ways, farm
                    families were better off than everybody else, because they could eat. It used to
                    be kind of a joke that prices were so bad, and nobody had any money, that high
                    school kids had more money than their parents, because they just happened to
                    have it in their pockets. We just didn't have any money. For that reason, I did
                    not go to college. It was all my parents could do to pay the tuition for the
                    commercial school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you say commercial school, this is an institution
                        that doesn't quite exist today. What was the commercial school?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: It was called business college, in those days. They offered subjects
                    that one would take, and one would need. Being business, they offered various
                    degrees of accounting, which I did not take. I took shorthand and typing. I was
                    very good in both, and got out rather quickly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were somewhat isolated being on a farm. Did you have
                        any goal in mind? You said you liked to travel, but did it translate itself
                        into anything?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: My main goal was to get through school, and to get a job, because we
                    needed the money so much. My first job was $10.00 a week, and then I worked for
                    $15.00 a week. I worked for law offices.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You worked in a law office. What were you doing in the law
                        office?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I was the secretary. I was the only secretary in the law office for
                    three lawyers, because they couldn't really afford to hire anybody. It was a bad
                    time for them. I made an impression on my bosses. They would ask me to do this,
                    and do that. My shorthand was so good, they used to get me short-time jobs as a
                    court reporter, because everybody was being foreclosed in those days. There were
                    so many court cases, they needed a court reporter. I used to make a little money
                    on the side being a court reporter, which was a pretty fast coin. There was also
                    something in those days called The Homeowners Loan Corporation. I don't' know if
                    you have ever heard of them or not. Everybody was losing their property, and
                    their mortgages were being called. People would get loans through the
                    government. It was a corporation called the Homeowners Loan Corporation. One of
                    my bosses had gotten the contract to the closing cases. He was always so busy.
                    He was impressed with me, and almost turned the whole thing over to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I want to take it up to the time when you moved to the
                        government.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: My employers were embarrassed because they couldn't pay me more
                    money, and they thought I should be doing something. They encouraged me to take
                    the civil service for the state. I took the test, and went to work for the State
                    of Illinois, in the Department of Public Instruction. I work there for several
                    years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were you, Springfield?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Springfield, Illinois. Of course, then the war came along. I don't
                    remember exactly how I was persuaded, but I decided to take the federal civil
                    service. I was assigned to a government office called the War Department. In
                    those days, it was the local office in Springfield. That is how I got into the
                    government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, well Harriet, let's move to you. While you were in
                        high school, were you involved in any clubs or dramatics, or Glee Club, or
                        anything like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I was involved in what they called The Hi Writers Club. I did think that
                    once I was going to write. I'm trying to think what else I was involved in, but
                    I don't remember. I wasn't a typical student, as my sister was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You would have graduated from high school when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: 1943.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: 1943, so the war was on. Where were you at that time? Here
                        in Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I was in Washington. My father was stationed in the Navy Department. Of
                    course, I can remember where I was when Pearl Harbor happened. I didn't know
                    what I was going to do. I graduated from high school and went to George
                    Washington University for two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you taking there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Everything. It was introduction to this, and introduction to that, and
                    introduction to Zoology which I hated (cutting up an earthworm was o fun). It
                    was a junior college course. Then, I got bored, and I stopped. I worked at
                    various jobs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So then what happened? Did you end up in the
                        government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Well, I didn't want to work for the government. My brother-in-law, later
                    on, in the 1940s, used to tease me about being “a government girl” when I wasn't
                    in the government. I didn't like the stigma that I thought was attached to the
                    government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that time, of course, particularly during the war,
                        Washington was just loaded with young women.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>CURRY: Ten women to every man, I think, something like that. But, I worked for a
                    daily lobby and The Evening Star, which no longer exists, Brookings Institution.
                    Some of these were summer jobs, in between college semesters, and in high
                    school. I started out as a mimeograph clerk for the American red Cross, for $100
                    a month.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We might say for the record, a mimeograph clerk was
                        equivalent to running a Xerox machine.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: It was worse than that. My mother made me an apron, because of the filthy
                    ink that would get on my clothes. It was really worse than that, and worse than
                    that purple stuff on the telegrams that we used to have to handle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I used to have to do some of that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I'm sure you did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, how did you end up working for the State
                        Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I went on a trip to Europe by myself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would have been when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: In 1952 or 1953. Yes, I was working for the World Bank, for five
                    years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing for the World Bank?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I was first a secretary and then a voucher examiner. I went to Europe for
                    six or seven weeks, and I liked the taste of independence. I decided I would
                    like to live all over, not out of a suitcase. I had a friend whose husband
                    worked in the State Department, as a Foreign Service office. I went to apply at
                    the State Department. I was 30 then, and the lady who was the personnel manager
                    didn't think I was the type, apparently. She said, “You know, you can't come
                    home for Christmas?” So, after a day later, I went to what was then the AID
                    program. I think it was ICA at that time; International Cooperation
                    Administration. I was afraid they were going to hire me before I got out the
                    door. But, I went to Tel Aviv with them for two years, and then transferred to
                    the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, we will come back to that. Eleanor, how did you end
                        up in the Washington area, in the State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Well, I was working in Springfield, as I said, for the War
                    Department, in an office that was there. I had taken a federal civil service
                    secretarial job exam. Then, the job I was working in was slowly being abolished
                    at the end of the war. The Veterans Administration was going to open up
                    everywhere. There was a report that there was to be an office in Springfield.
                    So, another girl and I went to Chicago to apply, to work for the Veterans
                    Administration. My intention was to return to Springfield. I had an interview
                    with a man who was going to be the director of the whole Midwest area of the
                    Veterans Rehabilitation Section. He said, “I'll tell you, if you will work for
                    me for six weeks, here in Chicago, I will promise to send you to Springfield
                    when we open the office.” That was the last I ever thought about Springfield,
                    because I was promoted, and I decided I would stay in Chicago. I worked in
                    Chicago during the big days of the Veterans Administration. Then, the
                    Administration more or less accomplished its purpose, and started reducing
                    staff. I saw people all around me just desperate, because they were losing their
                    jobs. I thought that this was not for me. I went down to an employment agency,
                    and applied for a job as a secretary. The person who interviewed me said, “I
                    would like to send you out to Kemper Insurance to interview with Mr. Kemper.” I
                    said, “I don't want to work in insurance.” She said, “Well, this is for the
                    chairman of the company, and I think you might be interested.” So, she sent me
                    out to be interviewed by James Kemper, who had founded Lumberman's Mutual and
                    all the other Kemper companies. He offered me a job, and I stayed to work for
                    him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What type of person was Mr. Kemper? How did he
                        operate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: He was an interesting person. He had come up from almost nothing.
                    They used to say he would sell the policies during the day time, and wrote them
                    at night. He really founded several big insurance companies, in the course of
                    time. He was just work, work, work. He had some human frailties. He drank too
                    much, for one thing. You have probably heard that. But, I worked for him. He had
                    two or three secretaries, but I was his principal dictation secretary. I went
                    with him when he would travel sometimes, and take notes, and stuff like that. He
                    was a big Republican, and Eisenhower appointed him ambassador to Brazil. So, I
                    came to Brazil with him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, let's talk a bit a bout Brazil. You went to Brazil
                        when, and how long were you there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Well, I was trying to think. It was 1954, I guess. Kemper did not
                    stay very long at all. He was not diplomatically inclined, and was anxious to
                    get back to his company. So, he stayed a little over a year. In the meantime, I
                    decided I was going to stay in the Foreign Service. The man who replaced him was
                    going to come for a short term, because he was due to retire. That was James
                    Clements Dunn. So, I was just perfect. He had had the same secretary for years,
                    but she decided not to come with him, because she wasn't going for a one year
                    appointment, she was going to retire, or do something too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He had been ambassador to Italy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Yes, a long time in Italy. He had also been ambassador in France.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, he was a major figure in the Foreign Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Yes he was. He was very distinguished. He was one of the few career
                    ambassadors when they first appointed career ambassadors. So, there I was when
                    he came. It was something made to order almost, our relationship. He thought I
                    was great and I thought he was great. He made some good recommendations. He was
                    afraid I wasn't going to stay in the Foreign Service. He recommended that they
                    give me whatever post I had asked for, whatever was on my wish list. He thought
                    I should stay in the Foreign Service, and he was about to leave. London was the
                    place I first put on my list. One day he received a letter saying, “We have
                    decided to send your secretary to London.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll pick that up when we come back. But, what was
                        Ambassador Dunn's method of operation? The short time you were there, how
                        did you see him operating there in Brazil?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: It's hard to recall now. My experience was so limited in those days.
                    I didn't know the difference between one or the other. But, my relationship with
                    Mr. Kemper was largely related to the previous experience. He brought his
                    business with him. People would come and go that I knew. I was a personal
                    secretary, but not really what you would call a Foreign Service secretary, in
                    the real sense. I thought Mr. Dunn was really terrific from the day I laid eyes
                    on him. He was very quiet and reserved, but definitely business. He got along
                    very well in Brazil.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well. Harriet, we've got you into Washington. You
                        mentioned you were being interviewed for AID, or ICA at that time. Did that
                        appeal to you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I enjoyed the post, and it was one way to get overseas, which is what I
                    wanted. My first post was Tel Aviv.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Tel Aviv, at a very interesting time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Tel Aviv from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: 1956 to 1958. I was wrong about the dates that I got started looking for a
                    job in the Foreign Service. I said 1952, but from 1951 to 1956, I worked for the
                    World Bank. I worked for the World Bank for five years. I enjoyed Tel Aviv
                    except during the fall, when the Israelis went into Egypt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the Suez crisis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: The first one, yes. The first time the Israelis went into Egypt. When I
                    later visited friends in Cairo, they referred to is at the “Israeli incursion”.
                    The Israelis were talking about it as the “Israeli campaign”. During that time,
                    for about seven months, everybody in the AID program except a few officers and
                    me were evacuated. I thought of transferring directly from there, in Tel Aviv,
                    to the embassy, to see if I could work for the Sate Department, but it wasn't
                    possible. But, it put the bug in my ear. After I left, after two years in Tel
                    Aviv, again I saw that same personnel officer. A transfer was arranged,
                    eventually, after nine months in Washington, in the Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's talk a little about Tel Aviv. While you were
                        there, you must have gotten involved, through acquaintances and all, in the
                        state, with the Israelis essentially under siege, and all that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Yes. It was a very interesting place to be. I had some Israeli friends,
                    but mostly embassy friends, particularly during the seven months, when the AID
                    operation was suspended. I went to fascinating places, historically, such as
                    Nazareth. We couldn't get to Jerusalem often, but you could go there, with
                    permission. I picked up old coins that were on the beach surface. I learned a
                    little bit more about the Bible being real.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you left Tel Aviv, you moved out of ICA. Where did
                        you go? I mean, you came back for nine months in Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>CURRY: I was in the Department of State. The arrangements were made for me to
                    transfer to the Department of State, from ICA. I had a job in the Department for
                    nine people, but I was sort of the low girl. I was the lowest of three girls in
                    one office. That wasn't much fun, because even my boss thought I was smarter
                    than that. But, it was the way things had to be worked out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then, what happened? You came into the Foreign Service,
                        and wither?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Then, I went to Paris. I loved that. I hadn't thought I wanted to go to
                    Paris. I didn't go to Paris on my trip to Europe. I was afraid of the French,
                    for some reason!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, we'll come back to Paris. We'll move to London.
                        Eleanor, you were in London for sometime, weren't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Yes, 13 years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thirteen; years, by God.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I said I was assigned to London, but I didn't mention the particular
                    job. I was definitely assigned to be secretary to the minister, who was Walworth
                    Barbour. I was there for five years while he was there. He was made ambassador
                    to Israel. I fully expected to be moved, because that was as long as anybody was
                    allowed to stay at post. Of course, I was unhappy to move, but I didn't have
                    anything to say about it. A couple people in the embassy and the departing
                    ambassador, Ambassador John Hay Whitney, recommended that if Bruce wasn't
                    bringing a secretary, there was one built-in in London. He wasn't bringing a
                    secretary, and he chose to keep me there, which was a wonderful stroke of luck
                    for me. He stayed for eight years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you were in London from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: 1956 to 1969. I was assigned then to the embassy in Ottawa, to be the
                    ambassador's secretary there. I was there for a year. Ambassador Bruce was named
                    to the Paris peace talks. I wrote to congratulate him. He wrote back and said,
                    “Would you come to Paris?” So I went to Paris.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's go back to, Walworth “Wally” Barbour. He became
                        quite a fixture in Tel Aviv. He was a very well known ambassador there, but
                        he was the Deputy Chief of Mission in London?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Yes, DCM in London.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was he like to work for?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: We had a good friendly, personal relationship, but I thought he was
                    reserved. He was very smart, intelligent. People consulted him about so many
                    things. He was a real Foreign Service officer. He gave me lots of
                    responsibility. He hadn't been happy with the previous secretary. It just grew
                    into a very good minister-secretary relationship. I don't know what I was going
                    to say about that, but he was great to work for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that time, how would you describe the type of work you
                        were doing? What were some of the issues, elements, you were dealing
                        with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Well, when I first got to London, Harriet, you were talking about the
                    Suez Canal problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This caused quite a rift between the United States and
                        Great Britain.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Yes it did. I lived near the embassy. I guess because I was also
                    secretary to the minister, I got called in two or three times in the middle of
                    the night to assist in conferences. They were having conferences. It was very
                    much the subject of the day, in those days. While Barbour was a real Foreign
                    Service officer, he more or less ran the embassy. Both ambassadors were; well
                    Whitney was, until Bruce came. Bruce didn't come until after Barbour left. He
                    more or less ran the embassy. But, they had a very close working relationship.
                    He was highly regarded by everybody.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the other secretaries' backgrounds?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Well, most of them, the junior secretaries, so to speak, were in the
                    Foreign Service. I made lots of friends. But, I was unique in my experience. I
                    was older than most of them. As I say, Whitney was there as ambassador. He and
                    Mr. Barbour worked very closely together. Barbour was a professional and Whitney
                    was a politically appointed ambassador. I became a close friend of Whitney's
                    secretary, but the other secretaries were just Foreign Service secretaries. I
                    keep in touch with a couple of them to this day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, when Bruce came, was there a change in how the
                        embassy worked, that you saw, or how he used you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I suppose so. He was an old London hand, you see. He had been in
                    London at various times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During the war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: That's right. He had a great affiliation and feeling about London as
                    a place to be. He was very glad to be back. He was really a professional in many
                    ways. It used to be kind of a joke that Bruce would dictate a telegram, which a
                    junior officer would normally dictate, but of course he was closely connected
                    with the higher ranking British officers. They used to say the Foreign Service
                    officers all over the country would bid to get a chance to read Bruce's
                    telegrams. He was a great person to work for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the British you dealt with, outside the
                        embassy, or with the staff, within the embassy? What was your impression of
                        them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Well, I always had very good relationships with them. I knew people.
                    There was an organization called Embassy Secretaries in London. We had a little
                    club; secretary to the German ambassador, the secretary to the French
                    ambassador, and also some secretaries in the foreign office. We would have
                    little social gatherings. I knew quite a few of those people very well. As far
                    as the embassy people were concerned; I met Harriet at the embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It must have been handy, and getting to know, in social
                        terms, the other secretaries to the other ambassadors.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Yes, it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You can sort of call, and smooth things over.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Well, we did a certain amount of that, but usually it was a young
                    officer who did that sort of thing. But, it was a personal relationship. It was
                    interesting to see how different countries, the secretaries' duties were
                    different than mine might have been. This was actually started before Whitney
                    left. His secretary was also in this group. I was included, probably, because I
                    was the minister's secretary, but it then extended after I became the
                    ambassador's secretary. I kept in touch with some of those ladies for years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you think of any examples that struck you as being
                        somewhat different? How some of them were being used?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Well, it's hard to remember now, but they definitely did have
                    different duties. Some of them were very much involved, almost like a junior
                    Foreign Service officer would be, and some of them were involved more on a
                    social level, like a social secretary might be. It's hard to make a
                    comparison.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Obviously, Bruce and his wife had a very active social
                        life, as part of his duties. Did you get involved in this much?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Very little, because there was a social secretary to Mrs. Bruce at
                    the embassy. I still keep in tough with her after many, many years. She stayed
                    on and worked for Walter Annenberg. We had a good personal relationship,
                    although our duties didn't cross very much. We had a very good personal
                    relationship, and Harriet knew her, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Harriet, you were in Paris from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: From 1959 to 1961. 1959 was vintage year. It really was. I went in March
                    and the chestnuts were in blossom. Then I worked with AID/ICA people. Again, it
                    wasn't the embassy, but it was a State Department job. I'm trying to think what
                    they called it.</p>
                <p>I was stationed in an office in the Hotel Talleyrand. There were four male
                    officers and one lady economic officer. The men all smoked cigars in the office
                    which was a big room with partitions. The three secretaries complained about
                    their cigars, but it didn't help. They seemed to think we were being
                    unreasonable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of work were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Nothing very interesting, but I loved being in Paris. I enjoyed it very
                    much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember any of the officers, and who they
                        were?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: George B. Gardner was the head of this office. The others were Ed
                    Hermberg, Robert Brungart, Abraham Katz and I am afraid I forgot the lady's
                    name. All were under John Tuthill.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tuthill was later ambassador to Brazil. Did you get any
                        feel there for our relations with the French?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>CURRY: No, I was too dumb. The only thing I knew was I liked being there, and I
                    liked them. My family and friends couldn't understand why I liked the French,
                    but I had some very nice acquaintances. I had a good landlady, which was unheard
                    of, and a good concierge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From Paris, where did you go, in 1961?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Then, they opened up posts in Africa. They were eager to fill them, and I
                    went to Dakar. That is when I worked for the number two man, the ECM, who was
                    Ross McClelland. The ambassador's secretary was leaving about a year later. At
                    the same time, I was asking for a third year. I was asked if I would work for
                    the ambassador, who was a political appointee, by Kennedy, Philip M. Kaiser.
                    When Kennedy died, Johnson reappointed him. After he was there for three years,
                    he went to London, to work as the number two person for Ambassador Bruce. That
                    is where I met Eleanor, because he took me with him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find Phil Kaiser?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Oh, he was a character, but we got along fine. I knew how to operate with
                    him, and his wife. I liked them both, and we became quite good friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Senegal like in those days?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: It was a former French colony, s they had some good restaurants there. It
                    was not very exciting. If I was disappointed at all, it was a bit boring to me,
                    but lovely beaches, that we used to go to, very nearby. It was a nice, calm,
                    lazy life. Phil Kaiser was involved when the Cuban crisis came up. He was
                    involved in trying to persuade President Kennedy not to let the planes land at
                    Senegal's base.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned that Phil Kaiser was quite a character. In
                        what way was he a character?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: He was pretty sure of himself, and also, I thought, slightly defensive, in
                    being a political appointee, but I was told he had worked for the government,
                    which he had. He had worked for the Department of Labor. A little bit of
                    personal work for him, I didn't mind, it wasn't the kind of thing you don't see
                    secretaries doing often but it was some personal work. He had a little bit of an
                    ego, maybe not a little.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know he falls to one side. He has written a number of
                        books. He was interviewed by our program. He was a Rhodes Scholar, which he
                        would never let you forget.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: That's right. He didn't let you forget. He knew England before he was
                    assigned to the Embassy. He has three interesting sons. Of course Robert was
                    always with the Washington Post. David, the middle son, is a professor at the
                    Naval War College in Newport, Rhode Island, and the youngest, Charles is trying
                    to make a living writing. All four Kaisers have published books.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about Mrs. Kaiser?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: She was a very kind-hearted person. I always liked her. She didn't have a
                    mean bone in her body, but she was misunderstood by a lot of people, because she
                    did like to help people. I put “help” in quotes, because she felt she was
                    helping them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get a feel for dealing with the Senegalese, at
                        all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Not at all. They seemed to be nice people. They didn't bother us. I didn't
                    feel threatened by them or anything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about Senghor? How was he viewed? What were people
                        saying about him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I thought he was highly respected, and an intellectual poet. He had a
                    white French wife. I don't know whether people resented it or not. I rather
                    doubt they did, because there were mixed marriages. I don't really know what the
                    Senegalese thought. I think there were a number of attempted coups, at one time
                    or another, while we were there, which didn't amount to anything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, when you asked to extend, this was somewhat
                        unusual?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Yes, and I should explain, probably, because I came from a very busy,
                    hectic office in Paris, and an easier, nice life. I wouldn't call it lazy. I had
                    enough work to do, but I didn't feel Dakar was pressure. I didn't want to go
                    home after two years, on home leave, and then go back. I just wanted to stay
                    there an extra year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did your family think about this, way over
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>CURRY: As far as I know, they weren't concerned about it. My family let me do
                    what I wanted to do. I think they thought I had a level head.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, Eleanor, in the first place, when you took off on
                        this Foreign Service career, what did your family think about this? Did they
                        have much feel for what you were doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Well, I think they were a little shocked beyond words. I had been
                    living in Chicago, and they were living downstate. So, we had kind of been
                    apart, but it was a great occasion when I took a train to Washington. My young
                    nephews and niece all went out to the train with me, as if I were going off for
                    the rest of my life. There were tears. I think I mentioned earlier that I had
                    worked for the state in the Illinois Department of Public Construction. I had
                    become friendly with some of the people there. Their comment was that I was the
                    last person in the world they would eve expect to go off in the Foreign Service.
                    I t was not in my character. I think that was the general feeling. We were in a
                    small town, and didn't have a lot of international experience, or education. We
                    hardly knew what an ambassador did or was. They were all just a little
                    surprised. It was a little joke in my family that I came home at some point, and
                    my parents were going off on what they called a “Prairie Farmer tour”. That was
                    a big thing for farm families to do. They had these quite expensive and very
                    nice tours. That was for three or four weeks. They were escorted in.</p>
                <p>I was home, and I went down to the railroad station to see my parents off. It was
                    kind of a joke afterwards that my father just lived to tell people that his
                    daughter worked for the American ambassador in London. I think, by that time, he
                    had become very proud of me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went to Paris in 1971 or 1972?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: 1971, 1972. I left London in 1969, and went to Ottawa, from 1969 to
                    1971.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, let's talk a little about Ottawa. What were you doing
                        in Ottawa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I was secretary to the Ambassador with Adolph Schmidt who was a
                    political appointee. It was a very nice post, but quite a contrast.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel that it was kind of “small town” stuff.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I suppose I did in a way. I just adapted to the occasion. Are you
                    familiar with the city of Ottawa?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: In those days, the Ottawa government was on a hill. The American
                    embassy was across the street. They used to refer to their departments as the
                    block, the south block, the east block, the west block, the north block. They
                    jokingly referred to the American embassy as the south block. We had a very
                    close relationship with the Canadians. But, now they have built a new embassy in
                    Ottawa. I haven't seen it, but I understand it is quite nice.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The government turned over the old embassy to the prime
                        minister, something like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Oh, did they? I don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did Adolph Schmidt work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: He had been a friend of Ambassador Bruce. He was quite impressed to
                    get Ambassador Bruce's secretary. He was extremely nice to me. He treated me
                    like an officer. I sat in on meetings. I had a wonderful relationship with him.
                    Of course, I only stayed a year. This lisle seal is my parting gift from
                    him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh. Well, you went with Ambassador Bruce to the peace
                        talks. What were the peace talks?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: They were going to try to settle the war in Vietnam. I think we had
                    one previouwhatever his title was. It was quite an international announcement
                    when Bruce was going to go to the peace talks. I didn't participate. I didn't
                    really know what was gong on. He would go. He was more or less a figurehead,
                    because the embassy had its speakers, the representatives. Because of his
                    prestige, he was a very important person.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were things going to his office that you were dealing
                        with, concerning this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Very little, very little. He spent a lot of time on some personal
                    things. These were personal diaries he brought up to date, and what have you.
                    But, he would go to the meetings. What was his name? The Foreign Service office,
                    who is now dead, was the principal representative. They would go together. But
                    Bruce was really the name. I'll think of the man's name.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel that Bruce was feeling a little left out, or
                        beginning to get bored with the whole diplomatic business, or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I don't know. He did something for UNESCO. What does UNESCO stand
                    for?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Social organization; United Nations Social and Economic
                        Organization, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: He had some dealings with that in Washington. Then, he had a great
                    tragedy in is life. His daughter was killed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, terrible.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: I think he was probably glad to get back into a more active life, but
                    he only stayed a year. He knew he was only going to be there a year when he took
                    the job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After a year there, what did you do then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Well, I was nearing, what was then, the retirement age of the Foreign
                    Service; which used to be 60. During the days I was working for Ambassador
                    Bruce, I had been offered a job at Dumbarton Oaks as secretary to William R.
                    Tyler, who was going to take the job there as director. In the meantime, then,
                    of course, lots of things changed. He did go there as director. By the time I
                    was free to take the job, he had another Foreign Service secretary. He asked me
                    if I would take the job. I worked for the Foreign Service Grievance Board for
                    quite a few months. That was my final assignment before I took a month, before
                    my retirement date came up. William R. Tyler was on the Foreign Service
                    Grievance Board. We had talked about, when I eventually retired, that I would
                    have this job. So, he approached me one day and said he didn't want to offer me
                    the secretary's job, he wanted to offer me another job, which was the
                    administrative officer, which was completely beyond my experience. It would be
                    directly under him, so I went to work at Dumbarton Oaks as the administrative
                    officer for a couple years. Bill Tyler retired and I didn't want to stay on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any connection with Ambassador Merrell?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Yes, as I told you, when I first went to London, it was the old
                    embassy. Were you ever at the old embassy in London?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A long time ago.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Well, it was Number One Grosvenor Square. It was a completely
                    different lay out. Across the hall from the minister's office was an office
                    which was some of the protocol of the embassy. Ruth Merrell was the protocol
                    occupant of that job. She didn't do a lot of protocol work, because that was a
                    job that really wasn't in the budget. She did a lot of other jobs too. Because
                    she was directly across the hall from me. Of course, her previous life was both
                    junior ambassadors and all, she was very much a part of the ambassador's suite.
                    We became very good friends. I met her brother, George, who of course was a
                    retired ambassador. He came to visit Ruth. As a matter of fact, he died in
                    London. I was in his presence quite a number of times. He had a stroke and his
                    communication was not good. Because I had been associated with him so much, I
                    was able to talk with him more than lots of people. He would start to say
                    something, and he couldn't think of it, so I would say, “Oh, you mean...” So, we
                    got along very well. The day he died, he had a Chinese servant, Tow, who had
                    worked for him when he was ambassador in Ethiopia. Tow was with him on the
                    street in London and he collapsed, and had a stroke and actually died. Tow piled
                    him into a taxi and came to the embassy to get Ruth, but he was dead. (Tow was
                    pronounced “Doe”.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Harriet, where did we leave you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Senegal. In Senegal I did work for William L. Eagleton, who was the charg�
                    d'affaires, in Nouakchott, Mauritania, where Ambassador Kaiser was also
                    accredited, when he came to Dakar to report to Ambassador Kaiser. When
                    Ambassador Kaiser and I went to London after Dakar, Bill Eagleton also went
                    there as a political officer for two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the London connection where you and Eleanor met.
                        You came with Phil Kaiser. He was deputy chief minister there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in London from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: From 1964 to 1969. Eleanor and I left at about the same time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did Phil Kaiser work in the embassy? I would have
                        thought there would have been a problem with a possible leak because he had
                        so many connections, particularly as a Rhodes Scholar. This can make for a
                        difficult relationship with ambassadors.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>CURRY: I think because the relationship with the ambassador was a good
                    relationship. I'm going to tell you something that always amazed me. They had
                    offices connected by a bathroom used by both Ambassador Bruce and Ambassador
                    Kaiser. It was always a polite thing. They knocked on the door, but Ambassador
                    Annenberg had that door locked so he alone used it. I thought this was an
                    example of how things might have changed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of things were you doing for Phil Kaiser?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: He did reporting of meetings. It was interesting work, the dictation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find life for yourself in London?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I loved it, I really did. I thought it was fine. I had Ruth Merrell who
                    was sharing an office with me for a couple of years, and Eleanor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was her title?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: She was a protocol adviser, sort of, how to seat people and all that. Not
                    just that, but sending out invitations. I had horrible handwriting. She took
                    over writing invitations. Ruth and Eleanor were very good to me as far as things
                    to do, and fun to have. I had a life of my own, but I also had a good time with
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Phil Kaiser get around much in England?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I think he did, but not as much as I did, possible. He was invited out for
                    weekends, and I know he went to Ireland. He had friends there. I would go off on
                    my own quite often.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of things occupied you when you had some free
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I would go to the theater as much as I could. I took in a lot of theater.
                    For example, I would drive to Stratford and see three plays in a weekend, an
                    evening performance, and the next day a matinee and another evening performance.
                    I would go alone or with Eleanor and, or other friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, in 1969, when you left there, wither?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>CURRY: Where did I go? I went back to Washington. It's silly, I can't remember. I
                    wonder if it was Jamaica. Yes, it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Jamaica for how long?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: About three years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was that, because usually you have a political
                        ambassador, and often they are quite controversial? Who was your
                        ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Vincent de Roulet, appointed by President Nixon. He had come from
                    California but lived in New York when he was appointed. His wife was the niece
                    of Jock Whitney (small world). Both of them treated me very well, but he was
                    controversial.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is he the one who arrived on the yacht?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: He sent it there. I don't know why people resented that. If you have a
                    yacht, why not use it. He also had race horses.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why not, right. But, I've heard other things about his
                        relations with the rest of the embassy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Several things were written about him that were not very nice. He was a
                    little bit defensive. His way of protecting himself, would be arrogant. People
                    didn't like that, of course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find yourself acting as sort of the mollifier
                        between...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: No, I couldn't mollify people, if they didn't like him. I got along with
                    him, but I also got along with Phil Kaiser. They were somewhat alike though
                    neither would understand that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then, you went off to Ireland?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>CURRY: No. Then I went to USUN, the U.S. Mission to the United Nations, in 1973
                    and worked for Ambassador W. Tapley Bennett, the number two man. While I was
                    there, his ambassadors, known as the U.S. Permanent Representatives to the U.N.,
                    were John Scali, Pat Moynihan and Bill Scranton, successively. New York City was
                    great although the job was difficult in that the secretaries would often have to
                    wait a long time while their bosses were “across the street” at meetings at the
                    U.N. and the secretaries wouldn't be put to work until the men came back to
                    dictate the meetings. One time, late in the evening, Ambassador Bennett had gone
                    home, forgetting that I was waiting to be dictated to. But there was more
                    theater and I think I got itchy feet because I left ether after three years and
                    went to Dublin in 1976. Shall I go on?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, why not.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: From that, working for a Republican appointee, Walter Joseph Patrick
                    Curley, Jr. Then, Jimmy Carter came in and Ambassador Kaiser got back in. He
                    went to Hungary, Budapest. I went with him there. Then, another year, it was
                    Vienna. After that year in Vienna, I went back to Washington, and worked for
                    Joan Clark as the director general's secretary, which was not very good. There
                    was very little to do. I was unhappy finding a civil service person doing all
                    the work I had been doing for ambassadors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But, you kept working for Kaiser, is that right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I worked for him for eight years; in Senegal, for three years, and London
                    for five years. Then, after eight more years, when he was nor working in the
                    Foreign Service, he came back in, and then I worked for him for another four
                    years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You can work for a man who is difficult for other people
                        to work for, is that it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I don't know how difficult he was for other people. Ambassador Kaiser was
                    probably difficult to work for, and other people thought that. I think probably
                    the last four years were a mistake, in a way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is this in Hungary?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: Yes, and after that the year in Vienna.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Vienna, this idle European experience, how did you find
                        that, as compared to other places?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>CURRY: I liked it. I liked the Hungarians. It wasn't as sophisticated as London,
                    of course, Nothing really was. But, it was interesting tome. I was glad I went
                    to Budapest and then Vienna, rather than the more sophisticated country
                    last.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you retire after Vienna?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, you came back to work for Joan Clark. How did you find
                        Joan Clark?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I admired her very much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She was the Director General to the Foreign Service, at
                        this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: After that, Ambassador Clark became Assistant Secretary of Consular
                    Affairs. She frankly told me she wasn't asking me to continue working for her
                    because I wasn't a self-starter, in that when there was nothing to do, I read
                    the newspapers. I resented the fact that a civil servant did all the things I
                    was used to doing for the ambassadors I had worked for, such as sorting and
                    reading telegrams. I did work for her successor as Director General, Roy
                    Atherton, until Bill Eagleton was assigned as Ambassador to Syria and I went
                    there as his secretary. This was from 1985 until 1988, and my next-to-last post.
                    It was fascinating visiting the country with the Eagletons.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find Syria? Syria is a difficult place, isn't
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: The government was difficult. I didn't have to deal with the government,
                    but as a country, it was fascinating. Ambassador Eagleton and his family took me
                    on many trips they went on. I couldn't have done them by myself, because I
                    didn't know any Arabic. We went to Turkey, and traveled around, looking at
                    ruins. It was during the hostage problems. The Syrians, at that time, were not
                    going to upset us. Well, they did upset us by not helping set the hostages free.
                    But, we did have some very exciting times when the hostages did come out.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>I gather that Syria is not as easy a place to live in as when I was there. It
                    could be difficult. One of them smashed the front window of my car, because I
                    had not understood I was gong the wrong way on a one-way street, because there
                    was no sign. The police asked me what I was doing. I thought he was motioning me
                    forward, to hurry up and get out of there, but he wasn't, he was telling me to
                    go back. So, he took his hand and broke my windshield. The feeling there was
                    that it was too bad, but I was going down a one-way street the wrong way. But,
                    there was no way for me to know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you retire after Syria?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: No, I had one last year. I went to Islamabad and worked for Robert Oakley.
                    That wasn't pleasant at all. I had a few trips that were fascinating, but I
                    didn't like the work, and I didn't care for some of the people. Then, I retired
                    because of age.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just to finish up, and Eleanor we'll come back to you,
                        what have you done since you retired?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CURRY: I've done some volunteer work. I do go the bookstore at the State
                    Department. Do you know the bookstore? Then, I do some church work and also work
                    for the Washington Cathedral. Right now, I'm trying to get my income tax return
                    done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Eleanor, you retired from the Foreign Service
                        when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: After I left the Grievance Board, I came to work at Dumbarton
                    Oaks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did you work for Dumbarton Oaks.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Two years. This was while Tyler was director. This was the ob that
                    had been promised to him all his life by Mrs. Bliss. She always wanted him to be
                    director of that, and so he took the job, but he was waiting for real
                    retirement. But, he had offered me the job, and I went to work for him at
                    Dumbarton Oaks. I was an administrative officer, which was very interesting,
                    because I didn't have the background, but I certainly got along very well with
                    him. I was appointed by Harvard University; so I retired too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What have you done since you left?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>OSTERMEIER: Well, I've done a certain amount of volunteer work, but not as much
                    as Harriet. I was a volunteer at the Cathedral for maybe ten years. What else
                    have I done? I worked for Meals on Wheels for a few years. I worked at my
                    family's genealogy, so I've been gong down to the archives, puttering around,
                    getting all this background information, which has occupied my time. I traveled
                    back and forth to Europe four or five times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, boy. Well, I think we can stop at this point. It's
                        been fun.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
