<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001378">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Jacob J. Kaplan</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2007</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Foreign Assistance Series</p>
                <p>JACOB J. KAPLAN</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: W. Haven North</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: March 22, 1999</p>
                <p>Copyright 1999 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: March 22, 1999 the interview is with Jacob J. Kaplan.
                        Let's start off with a brief summary of your association with Foreign
                        Assistance and AID.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>An overview of a career with foreign assistance</p>
                <p>KAPLAN: My association with foreign assistance goes back to my arrival in
                    Washington in 1943. I was assigned to OSS and put to work evaluating European
                    food supplies. That soon led to moving to London to participate in a Combined
                    Working Party on European Food Supplies, preparing estimates of food the Army
                    would have to bring along to Europe to feed the people. Subsequently, I joined
                    the State Department at the end of the war and quickly became involved in the
                    preparations of the Marshall Plan. I left once the Marshall Plan had been
                    submitted to Congress to take up a position at Yale. I decided after a couple of
                    years that I really wanted to get back into public service. I joined ECA and
                    worked in ECA in Washington and Paris. Then I came back to the State Department,
                    which had taken over the function I was performing in Paris. I was Assistant
                    Coordinator for Program under Douglas Dillon and then George Ball. Then I was a
                    member of the group that put AID together, the President's Foreign Aid Task
                    Force. I then became head of IDOS, a unit in AID. I resigned from the government
                    soon after President Johnson took office. Thereafter, I established a small
                    consulting business, International Finance and Economics. It did not do
                    contracting with AID since and I did not think it was appropriate. I did other
                    kinds of consulting work. Some brought me back into contact with either the
                    World Bank or the UN Development Fund, as well as helping multinational firms
                    and other U.S. government agencies.</p>
                <p>Early years and education</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. Let's go back to where you were born, where you grew
                        up, where you went to school?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: I was born in Somerville, Massachusetts in 1920. My family moved to
                    Cambridge a year later. I grew up in Cambridge, went to the Cambridge High and
                    Latin School and to Harvard, took degrees there in Economics and then before the
                    war, took a position at Iowa State College.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These degrees were through the Doctorate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: I was then an ABD, what is now known as “All but dissertation.” The Ph.D.
                    came later. A few months after I came to Iowa, Pearl Harbor was bombed. I
                    returned to Massachusetts, went into the Army, served in OSS in Washington,
                    London, Italy, and Austria. I returned to the U.S. at the very end of 1945, and
                    joined the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your OSS experience must have given you some firsthand
                        exposure to international affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: My graduate work was focused on food and agriculture which I thought was
                    going to be my field.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why food and agriculture?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: I was a city boy, New England, but as an undergraduate I was steered into
                    a course that Ken Galbraith was giving on Agricultural Economics by people who
                    said he was a very stimulating person. Indeed he was a very charismatic teacher.
                    He got me interested in food and agriculture problems. I wrote a senior honors
                    thesis on the Food Stamp Plan, which I think was then a year or two old.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was domestic food and agriculture?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Yes, entirely, domestic. I went on to do graduate work and decided I had
                    better go see some real farming and get my feet in real dirt. I went out to
                    Iowa, which then had a wonderful department headed by Ted Schultz, later
                    chairman of the Economics Department in Chicago. He was another charismatic
                    teacher. That is how I came to be recruited by OSS to work on food and
                    agriculture. There Bill Malenbaum and I developed the concept of food balance
                    sheets, which I think FAO still uses. We developed it. Shortly after I joined
                    the State Department, the head of FAO asked us to help get it introduced into
                    their work and we did.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>In Europe, I started out working on food and agriculture but then was sent to
                    Austria at the very end of the war to head the OSS economic reporting section. I
                    went into Vienna with General Clark's mission that was trying to negotiate with
                    the Russians about the terms of occupation zones in Austria. I was brought along
                    to take a look at the food situation in Vienna. It was disastrous. The Russians
                    had lived off the countryside and seized every bit of food in the city,
                    including everything in the stores as well as the warehouses. The population was
                    literally starving. My responsibilities broadened to include doing economic
                    studies about other parts of the Austrian economy. Thereafter, my interest
                    centered entirely on international economics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So then from OSS work, you went on to what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Joined the State Department as head of the economic section on Southern Europeand
                    contributed to the beginnings of the Marshall Plan - 1946</p>
                <p>KAPLAN: From OSS work I joined the State Department, as head of the economic
                    research section on Southern Europe, an area defined to include Italy as well as
                    the Balkans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What year was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: 1946. By 1947 the European economic crisis was becoming dire. Van
                    Cleveland, then in charge of Europe in the Department's economic area, asked me
                    to help put together an interim aid program for Italy. I did that , then worked
                    on the Italian...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was before the Marshall Plan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN:This was just before the Marshall Plan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We were starting an aid program before?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN:People forget that we spent about fifteen billion dollars on foreign aid
                    before the Marshall Plan, various kinds, in various parts of the world. Most of
                    it was for relief and rehabilitation. The European economy was nevertheless in
                    pretty sad shape. By 1947, people in the State Department were concerned about
                    what could be done to rebuild the European economy. Secretary Marshall came back
                    from a very unhappy meeting with Stalin where he became convinced that Stalin
                    had absolutely no interest in helping restore economic health in Western Europe.
                    He felt that we needed to do something. That led to Marshall's speech and to the
                    European Recovery Program.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your role?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: I was a major contributor to the Italian studies and to the preparation
                    of the “Brown Books,” which were Charles Kindleberger's responsibility. They
                    provided hundreds of pages of statistics on European production, balance of
                    payments, imports, exports, commodities, needs by country, by sector, and so
                    forth. I sometimes joke that the volumes Kindleberger turned out were so
                    overwhelming that Congress passed the bill a few weeks afterwards, but that is
                    what happened.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the main issue that you were addressing in
                        Italy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: We were concerned about high unemployment, extreme poverty, and how to
                    restart an economy that had been shattered by 20 odd years of fascism as well as
                    the war. There had been practically no private investment in Italy during those
                    20 years; it was almost all government financed. Some of us were very concerned
                    that initiative in the private sector had thus been deadened. While at Yale, I
                    wrote a pamphlet about the Italian recovery program, explaining this, but I was
                    wrong. The entrepreneurial spirit picked up in Italy very, very fast. In fact,
                    the economy started to boom a couple of years after Marshall Plan help began to
                    arrive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the help that we were providing them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: The help we were providing first emphasized food, energy, and raw
                    materials. The first two years of the Marshall Plan were entirely focused on
                    filling the pipeline of goods. After the war ended, the Europeans had at first
                    imported things they needed from the U.S. and the rest of the world, partly
                    using aid money, earlier aid money, and partly drawing down the foreign exchange
                    reserves that many of them had accumulated during the war. That foreign exchange
                    was pretty well exhausted by the end of 1947 and the pipeline was getting very
                    empty. So our first efforts were directed toward providing food, raw materials,
                    coal, oil, and other commodities that were needed to enable European factories
                    and agriculture, to restart and expand production.</p>
                <p>Of course in Italy, to come back to your earlier question, a major concern was
                    the strength of the communist party, financed from Moscow and making a very
                    strong and effective appeal. The working class in Italy was impoverished and
                    struggling. It was attracted by Marxist visions of a new society that would be
                    bountiful and fair to everybody.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Soviets weren't providing any economic resources at
                        the time or were they?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: No, they were only providing money to finance the communist party.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any conditions associated with this aid at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: No. The only firm condition was the one in Marshall's speech. That is,
                    the Europeans had to get together, decide among themselves what each could do,
                    and then agree on what their needs were. If they could do that, we would try to
                    help. We did. We were, of course, pushing our views about economic policies. The
                    ECA had missions in every one of the countries, headed by a political figure of
                    a stature that made it possible to discuss policies with governments at the
                    highest levels. However, we never threatened to cut off aid if they didn't do as
                    we urged. There was a lack of arrogance, I believe, in our behavior. People talk
                    about the American hegemony at that time. That is valid in the sense that we
                    were the dominant economic power. But we didn't behave like the classic hegemon.
                    We were interested in creating stable societies in western Europe, not in
                    selling an ideology. While we wanted them to free up their economies, to
                    reestablish free markets, to remove many controls, every country was allowed to
                    do so at its own pace. In fact, of course, they wanted the same thing as we did,
                    but they wanted to do it in ways that were both politically acceptable and
                    consistent with their judgment about economic possibility, as they did. But the
                    lifting of controls, the freeing up of markets was a long process, 15 20 years.
                    Privatization came very much later, almost a 1990s phenomenon in Western
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said this was a process, a mutual review, how did that
                        work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: After Marshall's speech, the British and French Foreign Ministers, Ernest
                    Bevin and George Bidault, called a conference of thEuropean countries to figure
                    out how to respond. First they encountered a flap with the Russians, who wanted
                    each country simply to tell the U.S. what it needed, package those needs, and
                    ship the package over and let the U.S. do what it pleased. Bidault and Bevin
                    were persuaded that that wasn't what was asked for, nor would it work. The
                    Russian Foreign Minister, Molotov, just walked out of the conference. Eric Roll,
                    an important British official, was with Bevin when he came back from the meeting
                    and said, “Get Prime Minister Atlee on the phone.” Roll got Atlee on the phone
                    and Bevin said to him, “He walked out, he walked out muttering threats.” That
                    was the end of that. Thereafter, the Western Europeans went to work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was our one condition I guess? Wasn't it, that they
                        get together?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: That they get together, review each other's programs, reach an agreement
                    on what each could do and put together a package of what they jointly thought
                    their minimum essential needs were.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that work as a process?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: It worked very well. Understandably, the first collection of needs they
                    put together was bigger than we thought we could manage. Negotiations went back
                    and forth, but finally the U.S. administration put together a package that could
                    be presented to Congress. It was based on what Europe finally submitted but with
                    some further pruning of their figures.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of criteria were they using to judge each
                        other's proposals?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: They were judging what was available, where they could increase their own
                    production if they had certain materials available. They were also taking a look
                    at their balance of payments. Basically, the Marshall Plan sought to fill the
                    dollar gap in each country's balance of payments. We were all using balance of
                    payments projections realizing that they can always be questioned and argued
                    about. The Europeans did argue among themselves. Obviously each country wanted
                    to get as much aid as possible. When they were faced with the need to cut back
                    the total, they had to agree about the cuts that would be made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were decisions that the Europeans had to make
                        themselves?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: They had to make themselves and submit the results to us. As the Marshall
                    Plan operated we, in fact, made decisions about who would get how much but based
                    on what the Europeans had submitted. For the first two years, we insisted that
                    the Europeans divide up the aid, after which we modified their division
                    somewhat. In the second year the division process became very acrimonious among
                    the Europeans. They decided that they really couldn't do that any more. They set
                    up a committee consisting of Robert Marjolin, the unsung genius of the Marshall
                    Plan in Europe as Secretary General of the OEEC, and Baron Snoy of Belgium, a
                    very wise and understanding man. They worked out percentages for each country.
                    Thereafter, any recommendations about the division of aid were based on this
                    Snoy-Marjolin formula.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which was a percentage for each country?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Right, that was the way it worked for the succeeding two years of the
                    Marshall Plan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any idea how those percentages were
                        derived?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: Yes. They were based on a critical analysis of each country's estimates.
                    A particularly bitter argument had taken place between the British and the
                    Belgians. However, a compromise was suggested and accepted, which was the way
                    the OEEC and European reconstruction worked. People compromised after arguing,
                    sometimes quite vigorously. Compromise was essential since the OEEC operated by
                    the rule of unanimity. Each decision had to be agreed to by every member.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That didn't paralyze the process?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: In the 15 years that the OEEC existed, I don't believe that a single veto
                    was ever exercised. De Gaulle walked out on a British proposal for a European
                    industrial free trade area. He interpreted it, probably quite correctly, as an
                    attempt to subvert the Common Market and made it plain that the French would
                    have nothing to do with it. The negotiations just broke off, but there was never
                    a veto. Understanding the need for compromise was accepted by a generation of
                    very great European statesmen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what was your role in this process?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Served as secretary to a study group on long term U. S. Foreign Assistance policy
                    - 1949</p>
                <p>KAPLAN: I left the State Department after the Marshall Plan was submitted to
                    Congress in order to accept an appointment at Yale in the Institute of
                    International Studies. In my second year, 1949, the Council on Foreign Relations
                    organized a study group about post Marshall Plan foreign economic policy. They
                    assembled a very talented and experienced group of people, including Galbraith,
                    Harlan Cleveland, then a senior official in ECA, Tom Finletter, former head of
                    the U.S. ECA mission to Britain, George Ball, later Under Secretary of State,
                    Jacob Viner, the dean of the international economics profession, Gardner
                    Patterson, then an economics professor at Princeton, later the Deputy Director
                    of the ITO, Issador Lubin, former Commissioner of Labor Statistics, Paul Nitze,
                    long time senior figure in the State and Defense Departments. I was asked to
                    serve as secretary of the group and prepare discussion papers. There was never
                    much agreement. Everybody had ideas, discussed them respectfully, but never
                    reached specific consensus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you trying to come up with?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: I later published my own conclusions in an article in World Politics. I
                    thought we needed a continuing foreign aid program. I felt the U.S. had
                    interests in the world and our economic predominance required accepting
                    responsibility. I hoped there would be an end to the need for aid in four years,
                    but doubted that there would be. The President ought to have a foreign aid
                    agency that had both funding and flexibility in the use of those funds. We were
                    going to have to be responsive to the needs of the Third World. Resentment in
                    the Third World was widespread about the Marshall Plan. U.S. officials tried to
                    explain that European recovery would probably do them more economic good than
                    any direct aid. While I think that was true, poorer countries were nonetheless
                    resentful. Basically, that was the tenor of my article.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were viewing the globalizing of the foreign
                        assistance program from the Marshall Plan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Yes. The chairman of the study group began with his proposal for an
                    International Investment Authority. The group was receptive but its discussion
                    of specifics ran far afield and consensus could not be reached.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They thought with the Marshall Plan, it was over and
                        out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Some didn't think the American Congress would support continued aid. Some
                    felt that the Third World was going to have to deal with its own problems, that
                    it could not absorb much capital soon. Some thought unilateral U.S. tariff
                    reduction was more important. Some emphasized the problem of U.S. agricultural
                    price supports. It was a very varied group. They were very bright, wise and
                    perceptive about all the problems of making U.S. policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what caused you to think that there should be an
                        extension of the program, what was in the world that was influencing you
                        that said yes we need to extend this into other parts of the world?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: I felt as the dominant economic power in the world, with far more
                    resources than anybody else, that we were going to have to assume
                    responsibilities that others had been assuming in the prewar period. I was
                    conscious of the Communist problem and of the appeal that Marxism had to the
                    poor and impoverished and to the appeal of anti imperialism in the Third World.
                    That made it very difficult for the French and the British, to assume the role
                    that they had played in the past, even if they had the economic capacity to do
                    so. I felt we had to be a player in the world, and we couldn't be a player
                    unless we were prepared to be generous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you couldn't get a consensus from your Group on
                        this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: No. The original idea was that the group would publish it's report in
                    Foreign Affairs, the council's journal. The chairman resisted my conclusions, so
                    I published my views in World Politics. Much of that paper reflected views and
                    ideas I had derived from one or another member of the study group, though I
                    could not claim that it was a consensus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well we want to make a reference to that so people can
                        look it up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: World Politics, October 1950. Actually it contains a philosophy and
                    attitude towards foreign aid that, in very broad terms, has continued throughout
                    the rest of my writings and career in foreign aid. Basically, I felt that we had
                    interests and power and we could not protect those interests without being
                    willing to use our economic power.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's probably still the case in a way , but we'll
                        come to that later. After your work with Yale and the committee what was
                        next?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Returned to ECA to work on European regional issues and then to Paristo serve on
                    the Board of the European Payments Union - 1950</p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Well, after two years at Yale I decided that I really did not want to
                    remain an academic. I had grown up thinking I wanted to be an academic but as a
                    result of my war time and post war experiences, I began to realize that my real
                    interests were in the application of economic analysis to real world policy
                    problems. Hence, I went back to ECA in 1950. I soon found myself a member of a
                    new staff that had been established to deal with European regional problems.
                    Primarily, the staff served to backstop the OEEC. It also dealt with NATO, which
                    had by then come into existence, and which became very important once the Korean
                    war broke out in June 1950. Also, we provided some backstopping and support for
                    the European coal and steel community which had just come into existence. It was
                    a group of people, all of whom believed in the importance of European economic
                    integration. We wanted to promote it and Dick Bissell, the ECA Deputy
                    Administrator, set the staff up for exactly that purpose.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which was in the State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Within the ECA, a European regional staff. Its first head was John
                    Hulley, who had been a major contributor to the European Payments Union concept.
                    He shortly resigned and I succeeded him as chief of that Division.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you trying to bring about?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: We were trying to promote economic integration through specific moves.
                    That had actually begun with the European Payments Union Agreement. The OEEC was
                    a forum that conducted discussions and meetings on all sorts of issues, but its
                    major decision making role had been in the division of aid. By 1950 that was no
                    longer practicable. The real problem was that although European production was
                    well above prewar levels, trade within Europe was still 15% below and European
                    dollar balance of payments was still in serious deficits. Neither the Europeans
                    nor we in ECA had any great confidence that the need for aid was going to end by
                    1952. It was important for the Europeans to get rid of their bilateral trade
                    agreements, to learn to be competitive with each other. Maybe that would
                    increase productivity sufficiently to give them enough confidence to free their
                    restrictions on trade with the dollar area. That was the purpose of the EPU to
                    which we were giving strong support. ECA had provided the capital to get it
                    started. In 1954, I went to Paris as the U.S. Representative to the Managing
                    Board and stayed there for five years. It was probably the best work experience
                    of my life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was mainly putting together the Payment Union?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Well, the Payments Union was together by then; it had functioned for
                    several years, quite effectively. At the time, there were two issues. First, how
                    was Europe going to get ready for convertibility and second, when were they
                    going to reach the point when they could make their currencies convertible. The
                    British were pushing for an early move to a very limited kind of convertibility.
                    They wanted to reestablish the London financial and gold markets, which had been
                    dormant because of trade and payments restrictions and because the British
                    balance of payments itself was so weak. They had some hope they could
                    reestablish those markets if the EPU were abolished. Most of their permanent
                    officials had opposed its formation in the first place. Hugh Gaitskell, their
                    Minister of State for Economic Affairs and later the Chancellor, overruled them.
                    He was an economist by training and was persuaded by our very able staff in
                    Paris that the Union would indeed be in Britain's interest, and so it turned out
                    to be. The Bank of England and the Treasury civil servants were very unhappy
                    about the whole affair and did not cooperate terribly well.</p>
                <p>The Germans were also restless, particularly Mr. Erhard, the Economics Minister,
                    who preached convertibility at any audience who would listen, though he had not
                    succeeded in persuading his own government that Germany should move to
                    convertibility before the rest of Europe was ready to move. The OEEC convened a
                    Ministerial Conference on Convertibility. Harold Stassen, by then the head of
                    the foreign aid agency, MSA, brought me along as his principal advisor. We were
                    trying to figure out a way to hold Europe together, hold European integration
                    together, and to promote European integration at least until such point as they
                    really were able to become convertible together successfully. The Conference was
                    able to agree that the EPLI should be changed to provide more flexibility.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>When I came to Paris, the first issue was negotiating changes in the EPU
                    Agreement to establish the conditions under which a move to convertibility could
                    be made. The British were given a veto power, the power to move when they were
                    ready. By late 1954, their situation had deteriorated to a point that they put
                    off any such move to convertibility. Then the EPU went on.</p>
                <p>The Managing Board was the place where the most intensive economic policy
                    coordination took place that had ever occurred up to that time. Country's
                    situations were reviewed regularly. Every member of the Union had accepted an
                    implicit commitment to keep its payments with the rest of the members in balance
                    over time and the Board supervised that commitment. It reviewed a country's
                    position when it was getting out of balance. It made recommendations, both to
                    the surplus countries and the deficit countries and they were accepted and
                    proved successful. It had become a very prestigious and influential body because
                    it had dealt with several crises in its early days very effectively. It had thus
                    acquired a great deal of clout. In 1957, the Board was finally able to get the
                    French government to accept conditions that required economic policy changes in
                    return for a special credit. The EPU incidently did impose conditions on its
                    credits. It invented the idea of conditionality, which the IMF later took
                    over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were conditions associated with...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: They were fiscal and monetary conditions designed to help countries get
                    their payments back into balance. In some cases, recommendations were made to
                    surplus countries. They didn't get credits, but they had to give credit. They
                    would get recommendations to remove trade restrictions that affected countries
                    in difficulties.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there other issues you addressed in that role?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: The Board had two major crises. One was with France, which had fallen out
                    of step with EPU Agreement. The Agreement not only involved keeping one's
                    payments in balance but also reducing quantitative restrictions on trade with
                    each other. A companion European Code of Trade Liberalization required countries
                    to free at least 75 percent of their trade in each of three major categories.
                    The French had done so, fell back, later conformed and then fell back again.
                    They were in economic and financial difficulties all through the '50s. The U.S.
                    had provided them with a lot of aid and urged that they bring their economy into
                    better balance. However, the governments changed every few months and none of
                    them was willing to do anything unpopular. So the problems just rolled on. They
                    got involved in fighting in Vietnam and later pulled out. We paid most of their
                    bills, including retroactive payments for bills for their Vietnam expenditures
                    before they moved out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather we were supporting...?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: They were in trouble and we were still generous. But by 1957, the U.S.
                    government had had it. The French had run through the very large reserves
                    accumulated from our earlier aid and they were desperate for further help. We
                    told them to go to the other Europeans, who were in a position to help. The
                    other Europeans were willing but they insisted that there be conditions. Finally
                    in the fall of '57 a new French government put together a program that seemed to
                    be acceptable. The EPU was willing to provide them with some credit, and the IMF
                    offered a little more credit. The Germans offered a substantial credit and the
                    French sent a mission to Washington to seek some more aid from the U.S. The
                    German Chairman of the Board pleaded with me to persuade Washington to provide
                    something. It would be politically embarrassing if Germany were the only
                    bilateral contributor. It would be embarrassing for the French as well as for
                    the Germans. I did go to Washington and passed this message along. The U.S. did
                    make a modest contribution to the package and the program worked fabulously
                    well. De Gaulle took over shortly thereafter. After a lot of debate he decided
                    to honor the EPU's conditions and the French economy and balance of payments
                    thrived thereafter. All of this is told in a book about the EPU that I co
                    authored with Gunther Schleiminger. It appeared in 1989.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was called the European Payments Union: Financial
                        Diplomacy in the 1950s by Jacob J. Kaplan and Gunther Schleiminger,
                        Clarendon Press, Oxford, 1989. Were there other issues?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Then we had Turkey. Turkey had been a member of the Union from the very
                    beginning, but it never removed quantitative restrictions on its imports. It
                    kept asking for credit all the time, and none of the Board's members was
                    responsive. Finally, in 1958, things had really gotten desperate. The U.S. had
                    been providing substantial aid to Turkey for years and we were certainly not
                    interested in increasing it. Turkey was then in real trouble and had huge debts.
                    The Europeans had been letting them buy goods with export credit guarantees and
                    the debts were enormous. An IMF staff member, a former Czech national named
                    Ernest Sturc, had developed a relationship with the senior people in the Turkish
                    bureaucracy. He went to Ankara and persuaded them to introduce a decent
                    stabilization program. Mangoldt, the German chairman of the EPU Board, also went
                    there. Thereafter, I got a telephone call from Washington saying that the
                    stabilization program looked very good but that Turkey would need a financial
                    package of X amount. The U.S. and the IMF can provide some, but how about the
                    Europeans? Can you get them to fill the gap? Knowing the European attitude
                    toward the Turks and their behavior up to that point I was very skeptical but
                    said I'd try. I invited Mangoldt to lunch at one of his favorite restaurants in
                    Paris and fearfully explained the need to finalize the operation quickly. To my
                    surprise, he thought the stabilization program could succeed. This was a chance
                    to bring Turkey back into being a full scale member of the OEEC and thus to fill
                    out the last gap in the European Community. So we wrote some numbers down, put
                    together a package, and agreed to recommend all its components to our
                    governments.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>I guess there is no point in my now not telling tales out of the school. In Paris
                    at that point a Treasury representative held the rank of Minister in the U.S.
                    delegation, of which I was a member. He was a retired banker who had little to
                    do except exchange gossip and views with anybody who would talk to him. A friend
                    of the Ambassador, he saw my reporting cables. I had reported my conversation
                    with Mangoldt in an “eyes only” telegram. My Treasury colleague promptly drove
                    to Frankfurt and related its contents to Emminger, then the key international
                    person in the German Central Bank. Emminger had been angling for Mangoldt's job
                    for sometime and he proceeded to put the kibosh on the proposal before Mangoldt
                    had a chance to approach Bonn. And so we had to recover, as we did. The Germans
                    contributed a little less than we had suggested, and the other Europeans more.
                    It was amazing that small countries like Belgium and even the French offered
                    money. France had just been given a package itself. It offered a small sum if
                    the others would agree. We thus were able to put together a package that was
                    approved at an OEEC Ministerial Meeting and it all worked. We also set up a
                    group to deal with Turkey's debts. The European debts were almost all government
                    guaranteed, while our debts were all private, some substantial, some very small.
                    I remember 10 dollars owed to a bookseller in Philadelphia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Put together a rescheduling of the debts?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: We put together a rescheduling of the debts. The Europeans wanted them
                    repaid as soon as possible. We were providing aid and didn't want our aid money
                    to be used to pay off European government debts. I was a thorn in the Europeans'
                    side, but after awhile we reached an agreement and it was successful. In fact,
                    the debts were cleared off on schedule.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there economic policy conditions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Very tight conditions that the Turks adhered to for awhile. They got into
                    trouble again later on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there other issues?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: The other issue was the timing of convertibility. The British senior
                    civil servants and the Bank of England had been recommending such a move for a
                    long time. Finally, they had a new Chancellor of the Exchequer, previously the
                    Minister of Agriculture, and persuaded him on the idea of moving fast. At the
                    same time, the U.S. had just appointed a new Secretary of the Treasury, a former
                    Secretary of the Navy, whose understanding of these matters was not yet very
                    profound. The Governor of the Bank came to Washington, met with the Secretary,
                    and told him what Britain proposed to do. Convertibility sounded wonderful to
                    the Secretary. The Governor asked him not to tell anybody or it would all fall
                    apart. The Secretary asked if he could tell the President. The reply was yes,
                    but nobody else. None of the U.S. officials who had been involved in
                    convertibility discussions for years knew about the move until the British told
                    their European colleagues that they would act in a few weeks. It was all agreed.
                    Despite the fact that they acted prematurely, it worked. However, the British
                    ran into serious balance of payments trouble and had to be rescued by the IMF a
                    couple years later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were in a very pivotal role in that location,
                        weren't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: It was a great role working with a great Board. Almost all of my
                    colleagues except Mangoldt held key positions in their governments. They came to
                    Paris for meetings once a month or more, if necessary, but otherwise had full
                    time jobs in key international financial policy roles in their governments. They
                    were a sophisticated group, very committed to European integration and to making
                    the Payments Union work. It was a great job, the most educational work
                    experience of my life. I learned much more there than I did in graduate school.
                    I also established valuable friendships.</p>
                <p>Q: I'm sure you were learning in a very practical way.</p>
                <p>KAPLAN: In a very practical way from wise men, with very good judgement and real
                    commitment to getting constructive things done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, from that you moved to what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Returned to Washington as Assistant Coordinator for Program in State - 1959</p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Once the EPU was liquidated, I felt it was time to come home. I had small
                    children and wanted to get home. By that point, Douglas Dillon, former
                    Ambassador to France, had been appointed Under Secretary of State for Economic
                    Affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which was what year now?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: 1959. A very able man, he turned his position into a much more important
                    job than it had been. He acquired the title of Coordinator for Mutual Security.
                    That conferred authority over ICA, the economic aid agency that was essentially
                    engaged in technical assistance projects in the Third World. He also chaired the
                    Board of the Development Loan Fund which had money to lend for projects. In
                    addition, there were all the other aid-giving parts of the U.S. government: the
                    Export/Import Bank, the Department of Agriculture, and contributions to the U.N.
                    Development Program to the World Bank and a new Inter-American Bank.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there defense or economic support funding at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: There was defense support to a few, countries administered by ICA. ICA
                    had two funding categories, defense support and supporting assistance. The
                    defense support worked for countries that had military programs, the supporting
                    assistance for countries where we had other special security interests including
                    military bases. It was all scattered and diverse. ICA had lost much of its
                    skilled personnel as it lost responsibilities. Dillon centralized broad policy
                    control over U.S. foreign assistance, something that had not existed since
                    Stassen was pushed out of the foreign aid agency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the Mutual Security Agency?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Stassen headed the Mutual Security Agency with strong support from
                    President Eisenhower. He had cabinet rank. However, he became a tragic figure
                    after announcing on the steps of the White House that he intended to campaign
                    against Nixon for the Vice Presidency. That was the end of his political career
                    and he was moved out of the foreign aid agency. Robert Taft's law partner became
                    head of the Mutual Security Agency and proceeded to cut the aid budget year
                    after year. That continued until Dillon took over. Dillon created a small staff,
                    a coordinating staff under Jack Bell, one of the best Foreign Service officers I
                    ever encountered. Bell had been chief of the ICA mission to Pakistan. He was
                    appointed to be Dillon's Deputy Coordinator. I was the Assistant Coordinator for
                    Program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had a mini agency but you still had all these...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: We had an agency of probably 20 25 people but we had broad policy control
                    over U.S. foreign aid. After Secretary Dulles passed on, Dillon also became the
                    Under Secretary of State, the key person on foreign affairs. He understood aid
                    as a very important instrument of foreign policy. My job was deciding how much
                    money we were going to ask of the Budget Bureau for each country and category of
                    foreign aid. Mr. Stans, the head of the Budget Bureau, thought it was all a
                    waste of money. With the President's support, Dillon was able to go forward with
                    his request to Congress. One or another committee of the Congress would cut.
                    Each time, we had to redo the budget and determine who was going to get how
                    much. Dillon also had control over military assistance. The Defense Department
                    ran the military assistance program, but State, in the person of the Coordinator
                    for Mutual Security, had to approve how much money could be spent for each
                    country.</p>
                <p>Q: So he had Military assistance then he had the Development Loan Fund, and the
                    ICA and...?</p>
                <p>KAPLAN: As Under Secretary, he could deal with Agriculture and also with the
                    Export Import Bank. Thus, he could put country packages together by centralizing
                    control over all U.S. funds in dealing with foreign governments. It worked very
                    well. Then came the election in 1960.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before you get to that, was there any dominant objective
                        or interest in this group that was guiding how you allocated resources?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: We thought the major lesson for foreign aid to be derived from the
                    successful Marshall Plan was the importance of country programs. We thought we
                    should use our resources in a concentrated way to help with countries that were
                    trying to expand their economies responsibly and that were willing to recognize
                    and be responsive to U.S. interests. We tried to put as much as possible into
                    those countries that were, in those days the term “friendly” was used. We were
                    then dealing with a world where a non-aligned group of countries tried to
                    position themselves between the Soviets and the U.S. and play one off against
                    the other. Nehru, Sukarno, and Nasser were the most prominent. We felt we didn't
                    want to get into that game. We preferred to concentrate our resources on the
                    countries that were aligned with us and supportive. Money was concentrated on
                    about 15 20 countries. In the last budget we put together (1960), I tossed in a
                    contingency fund for Africa and Latin America that caused some consternation
                    among those U.S. officials who preferred to limit aid to those continents to
                    technical assistance. There was not a separate African Bureau in the State
                    Department in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did you make it a contingent? Contingent on what?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: Well, we could use it for whatever constructive purpose that might arise,
                    such as regional integration. All the Latin American experts opposed sending any
                    money to Latin America, arguing that it would just go down the drain. We should
                    only give them technical assistance. If they would introduce appropriate
                    conditions for private investors, they would then have plenty of money for
                    constructive purposes. As for the people who dealt with Africa, well,
                    practically nobody was much concerned about aid except through the colonial
                    powers. African countries were just becoming independent in 1960.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What motivated you to put them in the picture?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Well, I felt that as the dominant economic power, we had interests
                    everywhere and we needed to have some facility to promote those interests.
                    Dillon went along and the contingency funds request stayed in. Then there was a
                    change of administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any particular development strategy or
                        philosophy dictating the use of the funds?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: The development strategy was to negotiate with recipient countries about
                    their economic programs, including their economic policies and their investment
                    priorities. We should reach agreement about what they needed and about what they
                    were prepared to do to help themselves.</p>
                <p>With the change in administration, Mr. Dillon became Secretary of Treasury and
                    George Ball took his job in the State Department. Ball, a member of the 1949
                    Council on Foreign Relations study group, wasn't much interested in foreign aid.
                    His interest was in trade policy. He really wanted to get out from under foreign
                    aid responsibilities. The new President Kennedy was very interested in foreign
                    aid and wanted a better program. Many ideas floated around at that point about
                    how to improve foreign aid. Walt Rostow's Stages of Growth had appeared and he
                    was on the White House staff. By that point, the foreign aid program had been
                    reviewed and re authorized with changes year after year. People spoke about
                    pulling the plant out of the ground to see how it was growing.</p>
                <p>The new President set up a task force to recommend a new foreign aid program.
                    Despite the pleadings of some of us, who understood the importance of the
                    coordinator role, Ball didn't want to have anything to do with it. He had Harry
                    Labouisse appointed to head the task force. Frank Coffin, who had just been
                    appointed head of the Development Loan Fund, was another member, Ted Tannenwald,
                    served as the lawyer, Jack Bell was added and George Gant served as the
                    organization and administrative expert. Frank Coffin was put in charge of
                    developing a program. Tannenwald was involved in preparing and presenting
                    legislation to Congress. Labouisse was a dedicated man, but not very forceful.
                    As the most experienced foreign aid official, Bell became the most forceful
                    personality on the task force.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bell was in OMB at this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: No, this was John O. Bell, Jack Bell. It's easy to confuse the Bells.
                    Coffin was put in charge of developing a new program. A sub group under his
                    chairmanship was appointed, consisting of myself, Jim Grant from ICA, Lester
                    Gordon from the Development Loan Fund and Isaiah Frank from the State
                    Department's Economics Bureau. We met interminably, long days with lunches
                    brought in. Many controversial issues arose. Perhaps the principal controversy
                    was between Jim Grant and myself. Jim was really sold on the Stages of Growth
                    with economic developmenas the dominant purpose of our aid programs. He would
                    have divorced aid from foreign policy. I felt that our national interests should
                    be the focus, as the only kind of program that would get the domestic support
                    that it needed. We had long arguments about terminating aid to some of the
                    defense support countries, or greatly restricting it, putting more money into
                    India and other countries that had multi-year development plans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Five year plans were important in those days?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Absolutely. They were a major element in the stages of growth concept.
                    After AID was enacted, Rostow pushed for making multi year commitments to four
                    or five countries that had good plans. My friend Bill Malenbaum, by that point a
                    professor teaching development at the University of Pennsylvania, commented that
                    the Stages of Growth book was a marvelous theory but had little to do with
                    reality in the less developed world. I think he turned out to be correct. India
                    had great plans, but they were all paper documents. No mechanisms existed to
                    implement them, so that economic results over those four or five years bore
                    little relationship to the plans. Someone once said that plans are no better
                    than the mechanism for implementing and revising them. I regard that as a wise
                    observation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the practical difference between you and Jim
                        Grant in terms of what your perspective was, in terms of how it actually
                        might be applied?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: Our assignment was to put together a program to present to Congress with
                    illustrative amounts for each recipient. We were in complete agreement about
                    most of the proposed program. There was no disagreement about the importance of
                    country programs. There was no disagreement about the importance of central
                    control over all U.S. foreign aid, though that never got through Congress. I'm
                    not even sure the Administration finally sought it from Congress. There was no
                    disagreement about the basic administrative structure. We were in agreement that
                    ICA and the Development Loan Fund should be folded together. We were also in
                    agreement that there should be a grant program as well as a loan program, and
                    that the loans should be on very easy repayment terms, virtually grants. But we
                    were in disagreement about how the money should be allocated to different
                    countries.</p>
                <p>We are talking about my 40 year old memory, I should warn you, I could be
                    misrepresenting it. An AID publication went out to all its employees. When AID
                    was 20 or 25 years old, it distributed a special anniversary issue. Coffin wrote
                    a long, very honest account of the functioning of that program task force.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you characterize that difference? You said national
                        interest and development but how did that differ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: The difference was whether to put money into countries that were trying
                    to thwart our foreign policy and may have been less serious about development.
                    Much lip service was paid to development, but if you looked at their policies,
                    their priority was to build steel mills, to finance an airline, to finance
                    automobile production. When they eventually got money, they built the highest
                    cost airline, the highest cost steel mills, and the highest cost automobiles in
                    the world. I didn't see much point in putting much money into that sort of
                    activity. They claimed to have a well-conceived development plan that would soon
                    raise them into self sustaining growth. Remember self sustaining growth in
                    Rostow's book? He had them all flying off to such a level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who resolved this, or did it ever get resolved?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Oh, it got resolved, as usual in some sort of a compromise. India and
                    Pakistan did get money. As best I can remember, Grant wanted to cut off Taiwan
                    and Iran and to slash Korea and Turkey. He later became the mission director in
                    Turkey and did in fact bring the economic aid program to an end there, at least
                    for awhile.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You referred to some structural changes that you brought
                        about, like merging the Development Loan Fund and ICA. Were there other
                        structural changes that you had in mind? You talked about country programs
                        and a regional focus why was that; ICA was very functionally oriented why
                        the switch?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: The switch was related to the idea of trying to strengthen the economies
                    and societies of the recipient country, which meant focusing substantial
                    resources there. A substantial part of the resources we had available were
                    intended for countries that were prepared to adopt sensible policies and
                    reasonable programs, that could command political support in the U.S., and thus
                    continued funding. Once you went to the functional programs you were dependent
                    on special interests in the U.S. to provide support for appropriations. That had
                    very little to do with national interests, with national security or foreign
                    policy interests.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The communist threat ,was that a dominant consideration in
                        the allocations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: No, the communist threat was always in people's minds, but in all my
                    experience in the aid field, including the Marshall Plan, I don't remember it
                    having much impact on policy decisions. It played a big role in dealing with
                    Congress, in seeking public support and in Congressional testimony. Basically,
                    we did not wan to give money to countries that weren't going to use it very
                    well. That would not do much good, even in terms of maintaining support of their
                    populations for democratic processes. I remember there was some urgency to the
                    Italian interim aid program in 1947 because of a Communist threat in their
                    upcoming elections, but Italy really needed food, quite apart from whether there
                    were elections or not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it was more public rhetoric rather than a fundamental
                        consideration; your impression?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: That was always my feeling. To the extent that the program built strength
                    in the noncommunist world, it served U.S. interests.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anymore on the task force?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Headed up the International Development Organization Staff (IDOS) in AI- 1961</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: There was one more idea, whose implementation I more or less inherited.
                    Europe had now recovered to a point where it should be accepting some of the
                    responsibilities for foreign aid. Accordingly, we should be trying to get them
                    to pick up more of those responsibilities. At that time, the British were being
                    helpful to some of their colonies and former colonies, the French to their
                    colonies, and that was about it. I have noted the German contribution to France
                    and Turkey. For the rest, the Europeans were engaged primarily in export credit
                    guarantees. We needed to get them involved partly because they were capable,
                    partly because it was hard to persuade Congress to vote funds when the others
                    would not. In fact, much of our money was indirectly helping to finance the
                    exports of many of these other developed countries. That was another constituent
                    part of the new program. It led to creating a separate staff in the new AID
                    called IDOS, the International Development Organizations Staff, an obscurantist
                    title that some management expert invented. I was reluctantly persuaded to head
                    that staff for awhile.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What year was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: 1961.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The beginning of AID?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: As soon as AID came into being.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you supposed to be doing in that job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: We were supposed to be doing two things: (1) coordinate our programs with
                    all other donors and (2) persuade them to increase their contributions. I had
                    two deputies, one in charge of relations with the big potential donors, the
                    Europeans, Japan, and the World Bank. The other handled relations with the UN
                    program, the Colombo Plan, other international groups, and organizations that
                    were providing aid. We stationed a senior ICA officer, Herman Kleine, in New
                    York and had supporting staff in Washington. We were exchanging information with
                    the UN about their program and our related ones. They would send proposals for
                    new projects to Washington. We would get the appropriate U.S. officers to
                    comment, attempt to avoid duplication, try to see if we could not get
                    reinforcing activities. We had also stationed an officer in Paris and in London.
                    We were trying to build relations with other donors and coordinate our programs
                    with theirs.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>Most of my personal effort was trying to persuade governments to increase their
                    aid programs. By that point, I was well acquainted with European officialdom, I
                    knew how the governments worked, where the power was, and who made decisions. I
                    also knew many of their senior officials and had pretty good personal relations
                    with them. I put much effort into Germany as the country that could then afford
                    a major aid effort. I made a number of trips. The Germans had created a new
                    cabinet job for foreign aid, under a very ambitious man, who later became
                    president of Germany. Unfortunately, he was not terribly interested in
                    increasing foreign aid, in fighting for a bigger foreign aid budget. Such aid as
                    Germany provided was administered by their Economics Ministry, with the support
                    of the foreign office.</p>
                <p>The British had programs mostly for their existing and former colonies, but were
                    making loans on commercial terms, though we were making loans on very soft
                    terms. I laid the groundwork for traveling with Fowler Hamilton, the first AID
                    Administrator, to London. Despite resistance by the Bank of England and his
                    civil servants, the Chancellor of the Exchequer was persuaded that it was in
                    British interests to meet us part way in softening their loan terms.</p>
                <p>I made one visit to Japan, where the foreign office was interested in increasing
                    aid. Their Finance Ministry told me that they preferred to put all their aid
                    money into the World Bank. When i asked why, the response was that Japan got two
                    dollars worth of business for every dollar put in the World Bank. That was as
                    far as I got there.</p>
                <p>At that time, I felt that the couple years I spent in IDOS were not terribly
                    fruitful. As time went on, I realized that we had been over achievers. Not too
                    many more years later, most of these developed countries were providing much
                    more foreign aid than we were. Our programs were decreasing while theirs were
                    growing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did the DAC fit into this picture at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: IDOS was also back stopping the DAC.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now did they create it when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: The DAG had been created the previous year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: That was the predecessor in the OEEC.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Development Assistance Group?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Development Assistance Group. When the OEEC was transformed into the
                    OECD, the DAG became the DAC.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was the prime mover for bringing DAC into
                        being?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: That came from the State Department. The IDOS group took over the
                    Economic Development division from the State Department. Ball arranged it,
                    thinking that the State Department should leave the development business to AID.
                    He also wanted to see more integration of personnel. IDOS had Foreign Service
                    officers as well as former ICA personnel. I had a very good staff. They worked
                    hard and I think we did lay the groundwork.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you relate to the DAC a lot?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of issues were you trying to get them to
                        address, mainly the levels of aid?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Well, that was not easy to do. We put much effort into the DAC,
                    recruiting Willard Thorp, Assistant Secretary of State under President Truman,
                    to be the Chairman of the DAC. I persuaded Seymour Rubin, the General Counsel of
                    ICA, to become the U.S. Representative to the DAC. He used the DAC to explain
                    how our programs worked, what we did. Managing foreign aid programs was new to
                    most of the others, and our explanations helped overcome reluctance to move
                    forward. We also tried to get the DAC involved in more direct coordination,
                    organizing and sharing responsibility for country programs. That did not work
                    very well, though we did set up a coordinating group on Turkey and Greece under
                    the OECD/DAC. The World Bank set up consortia on India, Pakistan, and a few
                    others.</p>
                <p>Q: What do you mean by a country program?</p>
                <p>KAPLAN: What was the country going to do with its resources, how much aid did it
                    want, what was it going to do with the aid, what policies was it going to adopt.
                    Really very much like the Marshall Plan. You put the whole package together of
                    policies, domestic production, trade and aid to see whether all these parts fit
                    together into a consistent package.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And this was supposed to be done under the DAC?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: Well, we tried, and the World Bank tried to do it under their Consortia
                    and Consultative Groups. The DAC tried it with Turkey and Greece and it worked
                    for awhile. We recruited Mangoldt, the former Chairman of the EPU Board, to head
                    the Turkish aid group.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But that was under the DAC?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: It was under the DAC, yes. It was hard to get the DAC to become a
                    decision making body, to become operational as well as exchanging information. I
                    would have liked to have seen it become much more operational. There is a limit
                    to which exchange of views is useful. The DAC became a forum where views were
                    exchanged and the chairman wrote a very good annual report with much useful
                    information.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your understanding; why was there a reluctance to
                        make it operational?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Everybody wanted to do their own thing, including the U.S. The AID
                    regional directors were no more interested in coordinating aid operations than
                    the Europeans were. To some extent, AID regions had too much money in those
                    years. They were having trouble obligating all their funds and didn't want other
                    countries picking off their good projects. I had at one point suggested to some
                    of them, a way to get the others to do more was to present them with a project
                    that might interest them and their companies. We could suggest that they finance
                    it if they were interested.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Too competitive?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Well, the AID regions had money and not enough projects. They were not
                    going to turn over good projects that were ready to be financed to somebody
                    else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any substantive issues that the DAC was trying
                        to get agreement on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: We tried to get a resolution about loan maturities and interest rates and
                    succeeded. Again, it was not as good as we wanted but an improvement in what
                    existed. We tried to get a little more control over the export credit business.
                    We also talked about some countries taking the lead in one or two less developed
                    countries, taking the lead responsibility rather than spreading aid everywhere.
                    Furthermore, we talked about regional groupings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any development philosophy emerging at that
                        time; any emphasis on how to promote involvement?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: I don't think so. The Europeans were very export promotion minded. We
                    were not. There was a tendency to prefer discrete projects rather than country
                    programs. Somebody said the aid business was bogged down in “projectitis.”
                    Governments wanted to finance a project that might have an export component, and
                    that they could identify as theirs. Countries with smaller programs felt there
                    was not much point in talking about country programs. That is why we tried to
                    suggest they take responsibility for one country or two and concentrate their
                    resources there. That did not fit with export promotion. After all, foreign aid
                    was still a learning experience in the early 1960s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the fact that you had started this interest in
                        Latin America and Africa; was that something you were working on then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: The Alliance for Progress came along. My very limited role is an
                    interesting story. The first meeting to organize the Alliance occurred in the
                    summer of 1961, not too long after the Bay of Pigs. The idea was generated in
                    the White House, by the White House staff. A conference was organized in Punta
                    del Este, Uruguay, at a time when the task force was functioning. ICA was very
                    weak on the Latin American side. Labouisse and Bell thought the task force ought
                    to have a representative on the delegation, and they asked me to be their
                    representative. I did not pretend to be a Latin American expert and asked myself
                    what might I contribute to the delegation. The Coordinator's office had a very
                    good Latin American desk officer, a Foreign Service officer named Herbert
                    Higgins. We talked about it. Realizing that the plan for the Alliance involved
                    all kinds of policy changes in Latin America, we concluded that the Latins were
                    likely to ask how much foreign money would be available to support the program.
                    I asked Higgins to research how much money had gone into Latin America during
                    the preceding year or two, whether from ICA, the Department of Agriculture, the
                    Export-Import Bank, the IMF, the Inter-American Bank, Europe, private capital,
                    and so forth. He dug up numbers totaling just under $2 billion per year. Since
                    the Alliance for Progress was proposed as a 10 year program, that led to the
                    conclusion that at least $20 billion dollars should be available. When we put it
                    all together, it did not even require an increase in AID appropriations, in what
                    we had already put into the AID budget. It would not require any further
                    Congressional action. I put this account in a memo. Bell sent it up to Secretary
                    of State Dean Rusk. As usual, the State Department Secretariat distributed it
                    for comments. They were all very negative. Every comment thought that it was a
                    very bad idea to promise the Latins any money. I saw the comments, but that was
                    the last I heard of it.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>I went off with the delegation. It stopped in Brasilia. As head of the
                    delegation, Secretary of the Treasury Dillon visited the Brazilian president,
                    regarded as a rather shaky character in his relations with the U.S. Most of the
                    large delegation stayed outside the room. Dillon went in with John Leddy, his
                    Assistant Secretary, and a few others. When Leddy exited the meeting, he came
                    over to me with a smile on his face. He said that I had just saved the
                    conference. The Brazilian president wanted to know how much and was told 20
                    billion dollars.” Apparently, Rusk had sent my memo, possibly including the
                    comments, to Dillon and Leddy and they used the data to respond to the
                    Brazilian, who was pleasantly surprised and agreed to support the U.S.
                    proposal.</p>
                <p>Q: Were there any conditions associated with the $20 billion?</p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Indeed there were. The Alliance for Progress proposal that had been
                    developed in the White House was nothing but conditions. It was a program to
                    increase living standards and social welfare. I have forgotten the details, but
                    it would provide some education to every child over some age, full primary
                    education to a large percentage of those children, better housing and clean
                    water. There were all kinds of sectoral goals that the Latins would commit to
                    achieve.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about conditions, about performance on their economic
                        policies? Things like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: That too, but I don't remember much of the details. Again, we are talking
                    about forty year memories. Some details are very vivid and some are not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the Africa side? Was there anything you were
                        associated with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: No. I was not. They were just emerging as independent countries. Two
                    things I do remember. One had to do with the push to make multi year commitments
                    in support of development plans, including one in Nigeria. Nigeria had not yet
                    developed its oil and we only had a technical assistance program in Nigeria. The
                    mission director wanted to use it all the aid for technical assistance. I really
                    don't remember any more.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But what was the concept behind that? Was it some sort of
                        a long range assistance strategy or something like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Well, they had a four year plan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Out of the concept that you and Grant and others had
                        discussed way back?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: Something like that. The other thing I remember was the Congo situation.
                    Around 1961 or 1962, the Belgians departed hastily and pulled all their people
                    out. The Congo, if I remember correctly, had only five citizens with a college
                    education. They had nobody even to operate the telephone switchboards in
                    Kinshasa or Leopoldville, as it was then called. Argumentative telegrams
                    abounded between our ambassador to the Congo and our ambassador to Belgium. I
                    have forgotten the name of the ambassador to the Congo, but the ambassador to
                    Belgium was Douglas MacArthur, not the General, but his nephew, a Foreign
                    Service officer. They had a cable war that rivalled anything going on in the
                    Congo.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember the issue?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Our man in the Congo wanted to keep the Belgians out of the place, not
                    let these imperialists back. He wanted the United States to provide aid and
                    rebuild the economy. MacArthur, with considerable justification, asked how many
                    technicians do we have that speak French? They would have to learn the language,
                    as well as the country and its people. The Belgians know the country and are
                    capable of helping it. We may exercise some restraint on what they do and
                    participate and play a role without taking responsibility for a very difficult
                    problem. Again, I don't remember the details. I remember the controversy. I
                    visited Belgium on one of my trips to encourage more aid and talked to many
                    Belgian officials whom I knew and visited MacArthur to report what I had
                    learned. We talked about the Congo, but I don't remember how all of that finally
                    worked out. I can hardly forget the controversy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right, well it was very controversial at that time. Were
                        there any other dimensions of this work in IDOS at this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: No. At that point, I had had 20 wonderful years of government service. I
                    had participated in a variety of interesting and constructive endeavors. I
                    thought it was time to decide whether I was going to be a civil servant for the
                    rest of my life or try to do something else. I had reached an age where I had to
                    make that decision. Moreover, at that time, I was not too happy with what was
                    happening in AID.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: The new President did not seem to be much interested in foreign economic
                    aid. I'm referring to Lyndon Johnson. I was in AID throughout the Kennedy
                    administration. Kennedy was very supportive of everything AID was doing. I did
                    not think Johnson was. Economic aid totals declined over the balance of the
                    1960s while prices rose. Aid money was being diverted to Vietnam and its
                    neighbors. I obviously had different ideas about what the U.S. should be doing
                    about foreign assistance. I was not about to urge friends in Europe to put money
                    into Vietnam. It would not have been fruitful anyway. And so I left and wrote a
                    book about foreign aid.</p>
                <p>Left AID and wrote a book and articles on foreign aid - 1965</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What year was this you left?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: This was 1965. I wrote a book that included what I had learned and also
                    what I thought ought to be done differently.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Challenge of Foreign Aid: Policy, Problems, and
                        Possibilities, by Jacob J. Kaplan, published by Prager, in 1967. Is there
                        any way of summing up the main point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Well, that would be hard. The basic thrust is a challenge to what I
                    called the “economic development syndrome.” The notion that the overriding
                    function of foreign aid was to maximize GNP everywhere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were challenging that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: I was indeed. I challenged it on a variety of grounds. First, I did not
                    think that was the overriding interest of the United States. Secondly, I did not
                    think that was the overriding interests of governments in developing countries.
                    Their overriding interests in almost all cases was to stay in power. They had
                    all kinds of specific interests in addition to increasing the GNP. I thought we
                    ought to be allocating money to countries on the basis of country programs and
                    to countries that were cooperative. Once we had decided on how much money to
                    make available to a country, then we should try to get that money used to
                    promote development, but a broader concept of development than merely raising
                    GNP. It ought to include social and political development as well as...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Political development, what do you mean by that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: Democracy, elections, human rights, governments that are responsive to
                    their people, and responsible. I also urged again the consolidation of all U.S.
                    foreign aid in a single independent agency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You wrote about aid coordination too? I raise that because
                        of a whole new interest in coordination.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Yes. Sy Rubin, who had been our minister to the DAC and was then
                    Executive Director of the American Society of International Law, organized a
                    project and I produced a pamphlet in 1978. It reviewed all the possible ways of
                    coordinating and stressed the importance of getting more and better
                    coordination. One of the weird stories in the pamphlet concerns Kenya, where
                    there were 356 projects and 34 different donors. A government that was
                    struggling to function effectively needed time to deal with all these well
                    motivated people. Coordination was minimal. Everybody did their own thing. Nor
                    was it clear that all the projects added up to very much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your basic solution to that kind of a
                        problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: We suggested two approaches. First, a coordinating group in every
                    country, I don't know if by that point I had given up on the UN. Earlier, and in
                    my book. I had proposed making the UN Development Fund, then headed by Paul
                    Hoffman, the coordinator of all UN aid expenditures. Every UN specialized agency
                    had its own aid program, some funded by the UN Development Fund, some of it not.
                    The UN Development Fund was primarily dividing up its money among the
                    specialized agencies, with each one doing its own thing, keeping its own people
                    employed. Paul wanted to play a coordinating role, with the UNDP special
                    representative in each country having authority over what the specialized UN
                    agencies were doing. Thus, they would coordinate. We tried to support him, but
                    it just didn't work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When was this you were pushing this idea?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: 1962 63.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When it was first formed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: It didn't work very well. I had at that point suggested that if it did
                    work, I would have liked to see all of technical assistance gradually moved
                    under the coordinating authority of the UNDP special representative.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To the UN?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: To the UNDP. I still think that there is a tremendous waste of money and
                    very meager results from technical assistance programs. They seem to do some
                    good for awhile in some small area. The notion of replication was current, but
                    it has never worked well. Demonstration does not work. You really have to have
                    country programming.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's your basic theme.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: That is my basic theme. Technical assistance should be related to the
                    rest of the country program. Some of it is obviously related. The World Bank
                    relates it to its projects, with a technical assistance component in almost all
                    its projects, as it should have. Some of its technical assistance relates to a
                    need to improve education and the skills of the population.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The country program should be a very comprehensive
                        program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Should be a very comprehensive program. I prefer the term growth, rather
                    than development. What we want is to see stable, growing, and democratic
                    societies in the Third World. That is what we should be supporting. We should
                    seek growth in every dimension, every sector, politically and socially, as well
                    as economically. An awful lot of these ideas have come in later. People have
                    begun to consider the division of income in these countries. That is a
                    relatively recent idea. But it should have been thought of a long time ago.
                    Excessive concentration of income in these countries is why so many are
                    unstable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So your country program includes the political, the
                        governments...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Yes, indeed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did the country program come from?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Where does it come from?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How does it get formulated? A lot of agencies have their
                        own country programs but yours is...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: Well, you need a coordinating mechanism. If one agency has a country
                    program, that doesn't cover very much. The World Bank has a country program, but
                    it may provide only five or 10 percent of all assistance to the country. What is
                    wanted is some central country program, worked out with the country. Much
                    technical assistance and loan project concepts come from the donor, not from the
                    country. I don't think that works very well. I did some work with the World Bank
                    at one point and asked how many of their projects were conceived and initiated
                    by the countries asking for financing. I was told maybe 10 percent. All the rest
                    were generated at IBRD headquarters. That may be all right. I don't know. If
                    countries don't feel that the project is their idea and their priority, it isn't
                    going to be very effective.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's been a theme of yours throughout your
                        comments.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: I make that observation all the time. I think you have got to give
                    countries a certain amount of flexibility in deciding what is important, even if
                    it is different than what you think is important. They may even be right. I
                    remember being told that McNamara never wanted to finance telephone projects,
                    air transport, or tourism for whatever reason. He probably had his reasons but
                    some countries felt that improving their telephone service was basic and that
                    has later become widely recognized. Tourism is, after all, a great development
                    project. I think if he had been responsive to what countries regard as their
                    priorities, some of the Bank's efforts might have been more beneficial.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are there other aspects that you want to comment on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: The UN matter that I referred to. Sometime in the 1970s there was a
                    disastrous drought in the Sahel. The UN was seized with helping. Brad Morse,
                    then the head of the UN Development Fund, called and asked if I would help. I
                    was then running a consulting business and agreed. When I turned up in New York,
                    staff skepticism was very evident. I employed some expertise and tried to put
                    together a sensible approach to the situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of approach did you have in mind do you
                        remember?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: My memory is a little dull but I think what we were talking about is
                    developing existing human capacities, their skills with animals, trying to
                    settle people in the valleys were there was a reasonable amount of water and
                    fertile land, where the cattle population could be expanded. I became quickly
                    discouraged as I realized that Morse really could not control the specialized
                    agencies. Each wanted to do their health program, their agriculture program,
                    their labor program and what not. It was an occasion for me to revisit an old
                    idea. The coordination of technical assistance should be done at the country
                    level. Possibly if the DAC were engaged in country programming, it could do
                    some, too.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>Concluding observations</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's go back to some general questions. Looking
                        back over your association with foreign assistance, do you think it was
                        effective, did it have an impact, did it make a difference in the world over
                        the last 40 years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: The programs in the early years certainly worked. There were many success
                    stories in the Third World. For example, Greece and Korea, which were both
                    widely called basket cases in Washington. Thailand, Taiwan, and Israel are
                    others.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was it that seemed to produce those successes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: U.S. country programs in almost every one of those cases.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were comprehensive programs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: I sometimes kidded my World Bank friends that none of these countries got
                    very much money from the World Bank, that the few countries that received large
                    sums from the World Bank didn't do very well for a long time. India, for
                    example. I have gathered that India picked up its socks in the 1980s, and their
                    economy began to improve. What I have been reading recently suggests that it is
                    going downhill again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think , apart from country programs, was there any
                        particular development area that foreign assistance has made a difference
                        in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: You mean developing sectors?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: I really don't have a basis for judgement. I know there has been an
                    enormous improvement in education. I know there has been an enormous improvement
                    in health statistics. I know there's been a great improvement in water supplies.
                    There has been a considerable improvement in agriculture here or there. I am
                    really not in a position to judge whether that is a result of country efforts or
                    of foreign assistance. I remember there was a lot of improvement in the water
                    supply in Latin America, probably as a result of Alliance for Progress work. I
                    am sure there are other examples of that sort, but I'm really not in a position
                    to judge the sector work.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would you size up your experience in Foreign
                        Assistance?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: I thought it was very productive for most of the 20 years I was involved.
                    The experience in Europe was fantastic. The results were there and it also led
                    to a lot of...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You feel that the success in Europe was...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Was due to country programs and the integration of the European economy,
                    as well as the dedication of the Europeans. In the Third World, some of the
                    countries that I have mentioned as success stories were countries in which we
                    concentrated our aid in the 1950s and 1960s. Subsequently, the amount of aid has
                    dropped and private investment has become the dominant source of capital. There
                    has been substantial economic growth. There is certainly much more democracy in
                    Latin America, much less dictatorship than there was 30 years ago. Africa is
                    still very distressing, although there are some shining spots. Ghana apparently
                    is doing very well. My wife was a member of the first Peace Corps group in
                    Sierra Leone. Things went beautifully there until the 1990s. The current
                    situation is very distressing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any general thoughts you would like to
                        add?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Yes, I have some general thoughts. I think the United States needs a
                    foreign aid program; it needs a much more focused foreign aid program than it
                    has. It needs to deal with the real problems. It is making a terrible mistake
                    hiding behind international agencies, asking them to do it and providing support
                    from behind. That would have been a disaster if we had tried it in Europe. The
                    only way to be effective is to assume responsibility. To be sure, you are likely
                    to be criticized. But if we don't assume responsibility, we cannot expect to get
                    good results. Or we will get bad results.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And we're still the dominant economic power.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: We're still the dominant economic power and we still can afford a larger
                    foreign aid program. It ought to be a results oriented foreign aid program. It
                    should focus on longer term results. People sometimes have said that some
                    foreign aid is something a new ambassador can carry along with him, hand over to
                    the government and thus get into the government's good graces. That is not what
                    foreign aid should be used for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say it should be more focused, what do you mean by
                        focused?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: Focused on results. Focus on the needs, on what the country is prepared
                    to do for itself and on whether our contribution will, in fact, bring the kinds
                    of results we would like to see. We should be very results oriented in our
                    programs. I think the morals are right. Helping the poor and the weak is
                    something we should be doing as a moral matter. But I don't think we're going to
                    get money out of Congress on that basis. I think if we are getting results,
                    Americans will feel very good about it, about what they have given. If they
                    don't get results, don't see results, they are not going to see the point of
                    financing foreign aid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You made a point in terms of European success...? How does
                        that experience apply to other parts of the world?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KAPLAN: Well, we tried to repeat in Latin America under the Alliance, but now the
                    Alliance is more or less disbanded. In other parts of the world it's very
                    difficult. I am unhappy with what we have done in Eastern Europe. I think we
                    have drawn on none of the Marshall Plan experience. I noted that of all the
                    American leaders who were invited to attend the Marshall Plan reunion, only the
                    Secretary of the Treasury, Mr. Rubin, accepted. None of the congressional
                    leaders, nor the Secretary of State, though they were all invited. Nor the
                    President or the Vice President, who were also invited. Now they are all going
                    to celebrate the NATO anniversary on a grand scale, an organization whose
                    usefulness may be nearing its end. If the heads of the Marshall Plan beneficiary
                    governments had been assembled for its anniversary in Washington, as was
                    suggested, the occasion might have been used to get a coordinated, important
                    effort in Eastern Europe. What we have had is what used to be called, I guess
                    still is, “market magic.” The only thing magical about markets is not
                    understanding how they work. There is nothing magical about them if you do
                    understand how they work. Economies are very delicate instruments, resembling a
                    machine with thousands and thousands of interconnected wires. What was done in
                    Eastern Europe was to pull out all the wires at once and hope new market
                    economies would emerge in full bloom. What was needed was progressive repair,
                    not massive destruction. One of my EPU colleagues once used an expression that
                    is appropriate to the way the Eastern Europe economy has been treated. About
                    another proposal, he thought it suggested a leap into chaos and then try to
                    organize it. A chaotic situation has been created in Eastern Europe. Marshall's
                    speech could have been repeated to the Eastern Europeans, including the
                    Russians, with few modifications. It's basic message was still relevant. Get
                    together, look at each other's programs, see what is needed, come and tell us.
                    We will try to help. Instead, we have provided Pepsi Cola and McDonald's,
                    together with ideological sermons.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any other general observations?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>KAPLAN: My ideas are explained in my publications. Obviously, much that I have
                    written is dated. But I think the fundamental ideas are still valid. This is the
                    time when one might legitimately pull the plant out of the ground and inspect
                    the roots. I think we've reached that point with our foreign aid program. I am
                    not optimistic about its occurrence in the near future. However, I remain a long
                    run optimist.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think this is a good point on which to wrap up an
                        excellent interview.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
