<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000017">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Thomas H. Anderson </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR THOMAS H. ANDERSON</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: September 25, 1991</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>[Note: This transcript was not edited by Ambassador Anderson.]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is an interview with Ambassador Thomas H. Anderson.
                        This is being done on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and I
                        am Charles Stuart Kennedy. Mr. Ambassador I wonder if you would give me a
                        little about your background? Where you grew up and were educated, etc.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I grew up in Gulfport, Mississippi and was educated there and then went
                    on to the University of Mississippi where I graduated with a triple major in
                    English, History and Political Science. I very promptly went into the banking
                    world as a career. I was sidestepped there when a very good friend of mine and a
                    fraternity brother decided to run for Congress. When he did he was elected and
                    out of the clear blue sky asked if I would come and be his administrative
                    assistant in Washington, DC. I said I would not do that but would stay in the
                    banking field and in business which was what I really wanted to do. He convinced
                    me that I really ought to take a two year swipe at it. So about sixteen years
                    later...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was who?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It was Congressman Trent Lott. He went on to become the House
                    Republican Whip. It was an interesting two years when I came up here. I was 23
                    years old, his administrative assistant came to Washington without ever really
                    having been here other than as a tourist during a high school senior trip. When
                    I got here I was thrown into really quite an historical era within two year
                    period of time, which was kind of funny to think about.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>He was placed on the Judiciary Committee in 1973—obviously a freshman member and
                    the last one as far as rank was concern. But we were thrown right into the
                    middle of all the turmoil that was going on in Washington during that time. I
                    tell people that in a short two year period I would get to the office at 7:00
                    and leave about midnight because during that period of time we had the
                    inauguration of Nixon, the State funeral of Lyndon Johnson, the return of the
                    POWs from Vietnam. At this point in the Judiciary Committee the actual
                    resignation of Spiro Agnew, the confirmation hearings of Gerald Ford, the
                    impeachment proceedings of Richard Nixon—all of Watergate. From there on, after
                    Gerald Ford became Vice President, the ultimate impeachment of Richard Nixon and
                    then the confirmation hearings of Nelson Rockefeller. All of that was going on
                    in that compact two year period. I got a real indoctrination into Washington and
                    how it works, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you later on get involved with foreign affairs at
                        all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Quite obviously when Trent was elected as the House Republic Whip in
                    1980, it put him in a position of being in the leadership which involved us very
                    much in all of the foreign policy the administration wanted to bring forward. I
                    had some involvement there with just dealing with the administrative officials,
                    not with the committee itself, but dealing with White House and State Department
                    folk as they tried to secure the votes they needed on Capitol Hill.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is designed for someone who is not too familiar with
                        how things were. Here is the House Whip. In the foreign affairs thing you
                        have the White House and the State Department trying to...what sort of
                        things would they ask you as well as your principal to deal with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Well, certainly what they have to do...it is an interesting observation
                    particularly after I got to my post and could look back at what took place...it
                    was interesting as to how foreign policy, for instance, is formulated in the
                    Congress. Many times...and it is going to be a different perspective when you
                    are with a leader than when you are with a regular member. A regular member, for
                    instance, has no constituency except possibly back home if there is a particular
                    interest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Gulfport doesn't have any particular interests.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Not really. We have some Yugoslavian third or fourth generations, but
                    they really don't care one way or another. But that is true, the Polish people
                    in Chicago— where you have background and pockets some times members have
                    special interest in foreign policy. Otherwise, if they have no constituency they
                    can pick out their issue and make their decision on how they want to proceed
                    foreign policy wise.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>When you are with a leader, the leader obviously tries to take the
                    administration's position because that is obviously the foreign policy that we
                    are under at the time. If at all possible they try to back it up. So if the
                    White House and the State Department, which hopefully most of the time they are
                    in agreement on, come to the Hill for a certain position—monies needed for
                    certain things, whatever the activity is—the leadership is usually the people
                    who are responsible for mustering support for the administration's State
                    Department position. They are called on quite often to shore up votes to make
                    sure that the President's position is basically in tact when they leave. At
                    times it is a little more difficult than at others.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Congressman Lott, of course, would be going after members.
                        But what would you be doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Obviously I would be doing the same thing. In a leadership position, a
                    leader has two constituencies, actually he has three: if his party is in power
                    he has that constituency to deal with; then the constituency of his peers, his
                    colleagues, which he has to deal with; and the constituents back home. All three
                    of those sometimes present him with a very real problem; with not enough time to
                    do what he needs to do. So I ended up interacting with other members of Congress
                    if he was at the White House at meetings. I ended up quite often dealing with
                    members on their concerns on what the administration was doing and how they were
                    proceeding. Basically I tried to emphasize what I thought Congressman Lott would
                    want them to know, his feelings, as to how the administration would size
                    something up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any particular foreign policy issue in this
                        period, 1980-82, that really caused a lot of difficulty for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: What do you mean? In a personal sense?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: About rallying support, etc.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Certainly the things that were taking place during that period of
                    time—to make sure that there was support for the way the administration wanted
                    their Central American policy developed. There was a constant problem. You had
                    to deal with it and present positions of the administration to members who might
                    be concerned about it. It was a management problem. A flow of information and
                    how you got it out to members so that you could see to it that the policy
                    itself...and I would say that that was probably the big problem at the time.</p>
                <p>On the other side of it you had the defense buildup and what they were doing
                    there which obviously intermingled with the military situation. And of course
                    that was a very big time consuming thing during that period of time as far as
                    members were concerned.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Having been on both sides of this business, one hears that
                        another branch of the government has developed. That is the congressional
                        staff. The Congressman is very busy and say they have no particular concern
                        about something but there are staff members on a committee for him who
                        really have almost their own agenda and may become ideologs for the right,
                        left or what have you. Did you find this a factor— you had to deal with a
                        staff member who was almost beating his own drum?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Most definitely. I think today that this is one of the problems with
                    Congress. To go back even a little bit further, Congressman Lott was ultimately
                    elected to the Senate and after I left for Barbados and came back here I lived
                    up to a commitment and ended up running his Senate campaign. When he was elected
                    nothing would do but that I come back and I basically said I would do so just to
                    get him established in the Senate. I worked up there for another year and a half
                    and basically saw both sides of it. To be certain, staff members, I know from
                    the long years on the House side, definitely have their own agendas, and many
                    times they pursue it unbeknownst to the Member or the principal. It happens all
                    the time. I never ascribed to the theory that John Connally used to have that we
                    should limit terms of members of congress until after having been there for the
                    number of years I have. I think not only should you limit their terms but staff
                    members terms as well because they become institutions as well. Many times,
                    particularly on the Senate side more than on the House side, a Senator has to
                    spend time courting a particular staff member to make certain that his view is
                    heard. As students should take a look at, something can pass the House floor and
                    the Senate floor and may never see the light of day again because when it goes
                    to conference many times the Senators and Congressmen don't have time to go to
                    the conference, or are in and out, or don't stay there the entire time the bill
                    is in conference. If a staff member has a desire to take something out—now this
                    was passed on the floor of both houses remember—it can be done. Obviously if the
                    member is determined that he wants to see it stay there it will. But there is
                    another branch out there along with the press.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before we leave this, did you go on any overseas
                        congressional trips?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, I never did. I took some independent ones. I went to Taiwan and
                    mostly traveled on my own.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression from people who came back from
                        these things? Did you think these trips were worthwhile for learning what
                        the real situation is? You know sometimes these trips are called junkets,
                        but many of them are very hard working trips.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Of course, you, yourself, know what a CODEL entails.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A CODEL is a congressional delegation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Right. You end up having to deal with it and many times it can put a
                    real hardship on the mission itself. But overall they are very worthwhile and
                    quite frankly I have developed over the years a feeling that one of the reasons
                    that we as Americans haven't done as much international business as we could and
                    involved in international business opportunities is because most people don't
                    experience going outside the continental United States. It has got to be helpful
                    for members of congress, who don't understand business in the first place, to at
                    least get out there and see what the problems are on a first hand basis. It has
                    to be helpful. It is helpful to us in the development of foreign policy. It is
                    good for the exposure of the congressman to enlighten his horizons as well as
                    the country he happens to visit. So, yes, I think they are very worthwhile and
                    we really should have more of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the interviews I have been doing, most ambassadors say
                        frankly they welcome more. Obviously going to Paris, etc. doesn't produce
                        much, but in many of the other countries you really want people to come in
                        on the scene and see what the problem is.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Sure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then we come to your appointment as Ambassador to
                        Barbados, Dominica, St. Lucia, St. Vincent, Antigua...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: And Aruba, St. Kitts and Nevis, and Montserrat. Part of the mission
                    included Grenada after our invasion down there. Our US AID and USIS missions
                    were operated out of Barbados.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did this appointment come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Quite frankly as I told Senator Tsongas at the hearing, I just hoped
                    that the President recognized talent when he saw it. But, really and truly,
                    about the time I felt that it was time for me to go back into the private
                    sector, a very good friend of mine at the time was head of White House personnel
                    and asked if I would be willing to consider service in a foreign country. I said
                    that I would. He had some thoughts on the matter and the President asked if I
                    would be willing to do it. They knew that I had a very strong desire to get back
                    to business.</p>
                <p>They had just come forward with the Caribbean Basin Initiative program and wanted
                    to see it implemented. So they talked to me about doing that.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I take it there was no particular problem with your
                        getting approval?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Well, as a matter of fact, right after the President had asked me to do
                    this I had gone with another dear friend of mine on a weekend trip down to a
                    place he had in West Palm. We got up on Sunday morning and he was delighted to
                    have on the breakfast table a copy of the New York Times to show where AFSA was
                    going to oppose my nomination.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: AFSA is the American Foreign Service Association—sort of
                        the union.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Right. I came back to Washington and did a little research and ended up
                    meeting with the president of AFSA. We had a luncheon and a long discussion
                    about foreign policy, where we were going, the management of missions, the
                    problems associated therein. He left basically saying that AFSA would not oppose
                    my nomination. So after that was over with, it was clear sailing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sometimes you can run into trouble with a member on the
                        Hill. I have just finished this week an interview with Otto Reich who had
                        Senator Helms dumping on him before going to Venezuela. What type of
                        training did you get before you went out there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I went through the entire reading that one goes through when you go
                    into a post like that. I went around to...I think I saw every side of Washington
                    DC that I had never seen before and talked to all of the other people that I had
                    never talked to in the Washington area. I went through the Foreign Service
                    Institute's indoctrination two-week course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How valuable did you find that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I found that that was an extremely valuable tool for someone who had
                    been involved in government and realized that you were going into the executive
                    branch looking at it from a different side as to how they viewed it...the way I
                    had always viewed it from the other side. It was interesting to see it. I
                    thought it was very helpful. I am not certain whether it was the right kind of
                    course for somebody who was coming from the hinterlands.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The focus keeps shifting. But, anyway, you felt it gave
                        you...I mean, you already knew Washington, but from what perspective?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Obviously I knew how agencies worked. From the legislative standpoint
                    in knowing how the laws come about, how they are implemented. I also had day to
                    day contact with the federal agencies so I knew how they worked. I knew how they
                    worked and interacted by helping individuals that needed help from agencies and
                    then what Congress expected of them and what they needed from Congress. I could
                    make agencies work I just never had worked in the executive branch. So it was
                    helpful from the standpoint that I saw it from their side of the equation, if
                    you will. That was a valuable insight.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were American interests in that set of islands?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Well, certainly the situation of Grenada had just ended.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain what that was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: That was during the period of time, and I assume go back to your
                    interview of Sally Shelton while she was there, there was obviously the Castro
                    presence in the Caribbean and all of those islands were so volatile. They quite
                    frankly are so small that each government is so susceptible to all kinds of
                    outside influences. You take Antigua with 7700 people. You can take a government
                    like that and work your will with it in all kinds of different ways be it
                    undercover black market, etc. We were concerned, obviously with the buildup of
                    communism as it was moving throughout these small Caribbean nations. The fact
                    that the drug situation from South America, we could tell, was moving up through
                    the Caribbean and they were using these as launching places. Of course,
                    Grenada's actual overthrow by the communists became a concern of all the leaders
                    in the Caribbean because they are democracies. They have a very strong
                    background in democracy.</p>
                <p>So after we sent our troops in...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We sent our troops in when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It was during the time period between 1982-83. As I went down we were
                    doing the reconstruction and rebuilding in Grenada.</p>
                <p>There were agricultural interests. Of changing their views and ways they were
                    doing things. They were dependent on sugar and in today's environment, sugar is
                    not the right thing. You have a real problem economically in the area because
                    their whole economy is based around sugar. Tourism, of course, is a major
                    industry. It has overtaken sugar as the largest industry. So, with the
                    President's focus after the Grenada invasion on the area...how can we best help
                    these people to develop the area?</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the Caribbean Basin Initiative.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was essentially what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: This is where we get into disputes as to how it should be carried out.
                    AID certainly had some programs which they allowed business people to
                    participate in both on the individual local level as well as some American
                    business people that we tried to get involved to go in and try to develop a
                    business there. The cut and sew business here in the United States has to do
                    with many of the small factories that hired people started looking to the
                    Caribbean because of the cheaper labor, good working environment for the people,
                    and the steadiness and educational level.</p>
                <p>That created problems for Congress on the other hand. They wanted to create the
                    Caribbean Basin Initiative but they didn't want you taking jobs from the United
                    States...to move them down there. So, those were problems.</p>
                <p>I always cite the American Airlines situation. The President of American Airlines
                    said that he wanted to do something in Barbados. His team was sent down in
                    January and reported back that it was great. They reported that the people were
                    well educated, it was a beautiful area, and would be a great place to do
                    business. A couple of months later the President said, “You guys haven't done
                    anything. I told you that I wanted an operation down there to take our coupons.”
                    The coupons you leave at the gate just as you go to get on the plane are
                    collected by American Airlines and flown up to New York and then would be flown
                    to Barbados where all the keyput information would be put in. They would get
                    immediate credit from other airlines which quite frankly helped American's cash
                    flow. If you are ticketed on Delta, obviously you paid your money to Delta and
                    for American to get their money back they had to be able to show that they got
                    their coupon, so this was a way they figured out how to make money, cash flow
                    wise, come back to American quicker.</p>
                <p>Well, the team said, “We didn't really think you were serious.” “Yes, I am
                    serious, so you go down there and let's get on with your trying to set something
                    up in Barbados.” So they went back in April. They came back to the States
                    saying, “You know this is really great. We have had two wonderful vacations—we
                    came in January when it was cold in the United States, and now we are down in
                    April—but we really don't think we should do this.” They wrote a little memo
                    about how they found it would be difficult—they had some electrical problems—and
                    told him all the reasons why they basically felt it wouldn't work.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>The president called them back again and told them to go back down there that
                    week and come back with a report on who they were going to implement it. So they
                    came back and reported how it could be done but we still said they did not think
                    it was the right thing to do. This was after the third trip. The fourth trip—he
                    told them to go in August and stay there until they identified a site, and
                    started the actual preparation to move the business there. They did. And it
                    ended up that the efficiency rating after they finally got the business
                    established increased from about 64 percent accuracy to around 98 percent. It
                    provided wonderful jobs for the people there—the environment they had them in,
                    the people liked their work and were satisfied. And it was good for American
                    Airlines.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This obviously took tremendous perseverance on the part of
                        the head of American Airlines which is not the sort of thing you usually get
                        on this sort of thing. Why was he pushing it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Well, that is where I had a different view of the policy than what the
                    State Department basically felt and, I think even the President. I did talk with
                    some people about how I thought it should be implemented. This is one of those
                    things that truly becomes a management problem. In business the people who make
                    decisions in business are the chief executive officers. The President of
                    American Airlines. Why he was committed to Barbados I can't answer, other then
                    that he had been there and knew the work ethic of the people. That is the reason
                    that the Caribbean Basin Initiative would have worked better if had we
                    been...the State Department's attitude was that you need to take people down
                    there and show them what you have to offer and that was what they wanted us to
                    convince the people in the islands.</p>
                <p>Well, my theory was just the opposite. They should be coming to America. Go to
                    Des Moines, Iowa, or Denver, Colorado, or to New York, or wherever business was
                    that we could have identified, through Commerce, etc., and actually talk with
                    chief executive officers. You could have brought up the prime minister of the
                    country or the minister of finance, someone to go in to talk to them and explain
                    it. Invite the chief executive officer down there and develop it. Those that I
                    was able to convince to do that showed results. They ended up with personal
                    relationships, saw what their businesses needed and how businesses operated in
                    the United States. Wilson Sporting Goods, for instance, in St. Vincent, as well
                    as in St. Lucia, found that the wonderful work ethic of the people was
                    fantastic.</p>
                <p>They also needed to target their tourism a little better. During the winter
                    months Barbados targets DC with ads. The same with St. Lucia. If they would pick
                    out another market say like Dallas, Texas and do that same thing, or Denver,
                    places that they don't always get tourists from they would get a new influx of
                    tourists.</p>
                <p>The CBI could have been far more helpful and it still can be, if we would have
                    been able to say to the people down there, “Come to the United States and let us
                    set up appointments for you to visit with business people here.”</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How helpful did you find the Department of Commerce?
                        Obviously this was a major part of President Reagan's policy and what you
                        were after was to develop business ties. Or was it developed to help
                        Americans sell good abroad?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No. Quite frankly American goods were already sold down there anyway.
                    The Commerce Department, certainly the people that we had in place there were
                    very helpful. I think this is where government causes our foreign policy a lot
                    of trouble when you get out into the hinterlands because it is very difficult
                    when you have to try to coordinate...you have your team in place and everybody
                    is working towards the same goal. There is no doubt about it. It is when it gets
                    back here to Washington that you have the problems with Washington not seeing it
                    the way you do on the ground. You have to constantly massage it trying to bump
                    it up another level in order to get a decision. When you waste your time doing
                    that you are losing valuable time trying to meet your goal. But the people, and
                    once again back to your point about travel, when you got people to come there,
                    be it Commerce folks or State Department folks, could always see your point when
                    they were there and understood more what you were trying to accomplish. The
                    Department was helpful except when people had their own agenda and you spent a
                    lot of time trying to move it up to the next level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you got there how did you find the mission, the staff
                        of the embassy—effectiveness, ability to get around, etc.?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: We were very fortunate in that we had an airplane. We let in
                    coordination everybody use it. So people got around to all the islands, ten of
                    them, on a regular basis. Travel is not a big thing in the Caribbean even though
                    there is a lot of water out there. Islanders go back and forth a lot. Travel is
                    not a problem.</p>
                <p>The staff was like any place. You had some that you were glad to move on, but by
                    in large they were a great group of people. They were very professional,
                    understood the people, understood what our goals were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about back in Washington, did you find that it was
                        hard to get anybody's attention in the State Department which were giving a
                        good deal of attention to Central America?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: That is interesting—yes and no. The focus in ARA was certainly on
                    Central America because of the times and I can't say that the assistant
                    secretary level was as concerned at that moment—they had just focused on the
                    Caribbean during the Grenada crisis—and they were now looking towards Central
                    America, which I think was natural. But the rest of the Department and anyone
                    else you dealt with who had responsibility for the area, you could get them, but
                    it just took time. It was a time consuming thing.Particularly for the mission
                    when we wanted to have a regional treaty with all of the islands. I think that
                    could have been put into effect if the State Department had wanted to focus on
                    that at the time, because we pretty well had most of the prime ministers along
                    with it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What type of treaty was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It was basically an arms type of arrangement, a security treaty, so
                    that there would be a format for the same type of thing that happened in
                    Grenada. It was something that based on what took place in Grenada could have
                    happened very easily and quickly within the first two or three years after it
                    took place. After that you would never get it put together because they are all
                    independent nations. Once you missed that window of opportunity it would be
                    extremely difficult to put such a security treaty together. It would have
                    facilitated us not to have to go through the same type process that we had to go
                    through the last time in making the decisions that we did because it would have
                    been done on a regional level and the governments would have been directly
                    involved all along the decision process as they asked us for assistance and the
                    type of assistance, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find it difficult dealing with these governments
                        because you were located in Bridgetown in Barbados and could only fly out
                        from time to time? Did you keep an ongoing relationship with the other
                        governments the way you could in Barbados—calling on people and all
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes. You know there have been views that we need separate missions in
                    every individual island nation, which I don't subscribe to. It just makes it a
                    little more difficult on the mission and certainly the people there, but you can
                    very easily keep up with all of the day to day activities and relationships.
                    They are warm, friendly people and you can deal with them forthrightly. They are
                    accessible. You never have a problem talking to them. By the same token they had
                    no problem calling you up immediately. I think back to when James Mitchell was
                    elected prime minister in St. Vincent and the Grenadines. He won by a landslide
                    to the point that even some of the other countries were concerned that after 30
                    years under the leadership of Mr. Cato there was going to be real problems. Of
                    course, there were none and he became a great dynamic force in the Caribbean.
                    The day after his election he was on the phone to me and I hadn't even met him
                    at that point. He asked me to come down and talk to him. We flew down right away
                    and spent the evening with him at his home. As a matter of fact we spent three
                    nights with him. We had a very close relationship with him. You could do that
                    with any of the Caribbean leaders.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are always looking at the time that you were there, did
                        you see any problems, particularly with any of these small states? Economic,
                        political, etc.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: You have to bare in mind that this was right after Grenada and we were
                    constantly monitoring very closely the activities that were taking place and
                    taking the pulse of the everyday citizen down there as well as the government
                    leaders about what outside influences were there. That we were very concerned
                    about. It was a very tedious time there in the Caribbean. Their economic
                    situation was one that was not good at that time. They were trying to readjust
                    their economics. There agricultural focus needed to be changed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For the record, I assume the problem was mostly of a sugar
                        economy when we are moving into an era where people are not using as much
                        sugar.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Exactly. It was a difficult situation for them from an economic
                    standpoint. What they were trying to do, or what we were trying to do, was to
                    get them to focus on light manufacturing and cut and sew industries to help come
                    up with jobs when they lost them on the sugar plantations. New machinery to cut
                    the decreased sugar also caused unemployment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A lot of your focus was just on what one could do for
                        these countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Sure, economic development, if you will. That was what we tried to
                    concentrate on. And the opportunities that they had and the things that they
                    could do to make good economic sense and provide jobs for their people.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was thinking of two sort of major dynamos in that area.
                        Obviously there was Cuba. You also had a situation in Jamaica which isn't
                        very good—a lot of crime and anti-American labor movements, etc. Did you get
                        emanations from these two places?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes, and that was part of what was going on. But in the Caribbean
                    nations that our mission worked with there really wasn't anti-American
                    sentiment. It was a wonderful feeling, they were gratified with what America had
                    done in the region, they were very, very positive about America and things
                    American. It really and truly couldn't have been a better time to be there as
                    far as their feelings towards us. Many of the servicemen would come through and
                    tell you it was one of the first time in their lives where the locals would
                    offer to buy drinks and thank them for what they did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get reports or concern that the Cubans were trying
                        to continue doing things there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes. Of course, as I said earlier, that was one of our concerns—Cuba
                    and the aggressiveness that they had in the region. On a daily bases we tried to
                    monitor what was taking place. And because they were such fragile islands in
                    small economies, small governments, the same type thing that would happen in
                    Jamaica with crime, robbery of tourists that were out on the beach...we had
                    those sort of things happen in one of their major industries right there in
                    Barbados. When that happened it hurt the tourism so the government spent a lot
                    of time so that they didn't have crime on the beaches and that sort of thing.
                    Drugs that they felt were basically communist inspired were kept out. They
                    monitored it very closely with lots of our help and they were grateful for
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the drug business? It was somewhat off the main
                        route as far as getting stuff up to the United States wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes, but you know if you look at how they come up from Colombia, they
                    ended up...we had pretty well monitored how they were coming and they switched
                    patterns. They moved from Colombia and started moving over to Caracas. Then they
                    would start coming up through the Caribbean chain. I don't think it got as bad
                    as we thought it might, but the pattern definitely shifted. You stamp something
                    out one place and it pops up in another area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The money is just so overwhelming.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: The money could corrupt a government overnight. They would come in with
                    a $100,000 which is nothing here in the United States, but that is a fortune in
                    a small country like St. Lucia, St. Vincent, or even Dominica. It is just
                    incredible what they could do if they wanted to buy a government off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have the Drug Enforcement Agency person
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes. And monitored all of that very closely. But by enlarge there were
                    not real major drug problems. There were small problems here and there that
                    popped up. I think they have more of a problem today than they did back
                    then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any major drug busts or anything like
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, we really didn't. About the only thing that actually happened was a
                    neighbor of mine from where the Ambassador's Residence was, ended up killing his
                    wife. They went into his house and discovered all kinds of drugs and evidently
                    he was one of the kingpins of the drug industry there in Barbados and he was
                    only a stone throw away. But outside of that they didn't have problems. It was
                    more up towards the Bahamas that they had most of the major problems. But that
                    was when they started dropping back a little bit too. So fortunately I left
                    about the time they really started moving that way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about Grenada? You came in the aftermath. You had the
                        responsibility of overseeing...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Well, for the US AID mission and USIS. What they had done when they
                    actually went into Grenada was to take Grenada out from underneath before I
                    arrived at the Barbados mission and operated it separately and there was a
                    Charg� down there. He coordinated through the AID mission and Information office
                    in Bridgetown and other than that reported directly back to Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was immigration a problem? Was there a tradition of going
                        to the United States or was that more from Jamaica and other places?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, the Caribbean likes to do their shopping in Miami and they go
                    pretty regularly—Miami and New York. There is obviously a very large population
                    of Caribbean people in New York and they move regularly and on a daily basis.
                    Travel for them is like hopping on the subway or metro. They just hop on a plane
                    and take off and do a lot of it. They do immigrate a lot and it was quite a
                    problem.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This must have been one of the major pressures on
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Definitely. You couldn't go anywhere that you didn't get confronted
                    with an immigration problem. But I can say that the consular office did a great
                    job down there. They were very good. Even today, I think, that the Caribbean
                    people feel good about the way they are handled, which I think is a credit to
                    the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about tourism? Do you get people calling up saying
                        they have missed their boat and you need to do something?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: That certainly, because it was a high tourist area, was a problem from
                    time to time. But not any real problems. We had a couple rape problems that
                    didn't happen while I was there but came back to court while I was there. That
                    was something that you ended up getting involved in that was sort of dramatic
                    from both sides when you would see how their law was going to interact and you
                    would try to explain to American citizens that they were under their laws and
                    would have to operate that way. It was a difficult thing to have to handle
                    American citizens who felt that they needed certain kinds of representation and
                    you could only do so much for them because indeed they were in a foreign
                    country. It was hard for them to understand that. You did from time to time hear
                    from folks that their son was on a sailing trip down there and hadn't heard from
                    him for days and could you find him, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All of it was at the manageable level?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes, I don't think that there were any major problems there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No great hurricanes while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Nope. Had a couple of threats, but fortunately they went away.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One hurricane will ruin your entire day.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: That's right. Having lived through one that hit the Mississippi Gulf
                    coast, I know what that is like.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This has been very interesting in giving us your
                        perspective of this. When you left the islands, did you have much of a
                        chance to pass on the information you had gained to your successor, or was
                        it pretty much like ships that pass in the night?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, he happened to be a good friend of mine so I had a very good
                    opportunity to chat with him about the missions, the people that were there, the
                    various prime ministers, their concerns, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you come back to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Well, I came back to the savings and loan industry. As I told you I had
                    made a commitment to Trent that when he ran for Senate that I would indeed stop
                    whatever I was doing and run the Senate campaign and that all happened within
                    about a three month period. So I ended up doing that. I have been involved in
                    investment banking since I left the Senate side, and own several businesses in
                    and around the Washington DC area. But I am primarily involved in investment
                    banking right now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, thank you very much. I appreciate this.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Great. You are welcome.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
