<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000683">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Robert Don Levine </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Information Series</p>
                <p>ROBERT DON LEVINE</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Pat Nieburg </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: December 10, 1988</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>Early Assignment: VOA, Geneva, Paris</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is Pat Nieburg. It is December 10th and I'm at the
                        house of Robert Don Levine. Bob was the Deputy Spokesman for Jess Powell in
                        Saigon during one of the critical periods of the Vietnam War. What we shall
                        discuss today are Bob's experiences during that period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Okay, I joined USIA in September of 1955 as a GS11 newswriter for the
                    Voice of America. I spent five years writing and editing news for the Voice of
                    America, in English of course, four and a half of those five years on what they
                    call the overnight shift. In 1960 I joined the Foreign Service and went first to
                    Geneva as an FSR-4. I spent about three years in Geneva first as the number two
                    man of a two-man USIS operation in what was then called the U.S. Mission to the
                    European Office of the United Nations. That's as far as I got.</p>
                <p>Not too long after I got there I became the number one man in the operation. My
                    boss was transferred, having been there for two tours of duty. My next tour of
                    duty after Geneva was in Paris as Information Officer. I was there for only nine
                    months 1964-1965. And I got caught in the build up in Vietnam and was sent to
                    Saigon directly from Geneva as what wound up being actually the Deputy Mission
                    Spokesman.</p>
                <p>1965 Assignment to Vietnam as Deputy Mission SpokesmanNature of Work</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bob, let me interrupt for just one minute.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Go ahead.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you define a little bit what this job entailed?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>LEVINE: With the build up of American forces in Vietnam in 1965, I arrived there
                    in May of 1965, there was increasing interest on the part of the American media
                    in what was going on in Vietnam and in following what was happening to our
                    troops, what they were doing. And that required more work on behalf of the
                    United States Mission dealing with these reporters.</p>
                <p>Birth of JUSPAO</p>
                <p>Also at about the same time that I arrived there, it may have been a little
                    later, the normal U.S. Information Service operation in Saigon was transformed
                    into what was called the Joint U.S. Public Affairs Office or JUSPAO in Saigon
                    which included both the military and the civilians.</p>
                <p>By the time I left, the daily news briefings which were given at the U.S. mission
                    hosted several hundred newspaper, television, wire service and freelance
                    reporters. So the job was primarily one of helping my boss, Harold Kaplan, who
                    was the mission spokesman, to get ready for this briefing at five O'clock,
                    called the five O'clock follies, and find out what was going on, what activities
                    the mission was involved in and what kind of questions he might have to respond
                    to at the daily briefing. The during the day, of course, we had to handle other
                    queries that came along from newsmen and also make some arrangements for them to
                    visit different parts of South Vietnam where our troops were operating or where
                    American civilians including USIA civilians were functioning also. Of course,
                    State Department people were in the some of the larger cities in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>The five O'clock briefing was a joint military and civilian briefing. I might say
                    that the military handled their part of the briefing and the civilians handled
                    the civilian part of the briefing but basically we controlled what happened
                    there.</p>
                <p>The So-Called Five O'CLOCK Follies: Difficulty Mission Spokesman Had in Getting
                    Adequate Info to Satisfy Press</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Robert, let me interrupt with one question. Would you
                        describe for me a little bit how does one get ready for that kind of five
                        O'clock follies that you had to face everyday? In other words, where did you
                        get the information? Where did you get the basic data that you had that you
                        needed to prepare to answer the questions of the media?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, first of all we had cables to read, outgoing cables from Saigon,
                    incoming cables from Washington. We also talked to mission officers, State
                    Department people, JUSPAO, JUSPAO officers, military officers, to get them to
                    explain certain things that were coming up in the news. We, of course, had the
                    wireless file that we looked at, had some idea from that. I don't recall how
                    quickly we got newspapers there. I don't think it was all that fast. But we did
                    get reports on what the American press and also how the foreign press was
                    playing the situation in Vietnam. And from these reports, press, media reports,
                    we knew what issues were hot. We also knew based on our conversations with
                    correspondents who asked us questions and wanted to know what was going on, what
                    our attitudes was towards, I don't know, whether it was a cease-fire or what
                    have you.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Robert, did you or Harold Kaplan, for example, sit in on
                        mission staff meetings which were either just embassy missions or joint
                        missions with the military. Were you in at the policymaking discussions to
                        get a readout of what was going on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: I never was. Harold Kaplan was to a greater extent than me but not all
                    that much. Primarily it was Barry Zorthian who was then the Director of JUSPAO
                    who sat in on those meetings. This made things a little bit difficult for us
                    admittedly. Although we did find out things through other people at a lower
                    level who were informed, either people in the military or in the civilian part
                    of the operation. I'm talking about the whole entire mission, not just
                    JUSPAO.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Barry share the information that he had with you? In
                        other words, did Barry Zorthian actually brief you and/or Kaplan and tell
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: To a certain extent, not as much as we would have liked. I think that he
                    retained for himself a considerable amount of this information to make himself a
                    better source and a single source for newsmen. That was one of the problems. I
                    always thought that Kaplan did a marvelous job given the fact that he wasn't as
                    privy to all the information that the mission had as Zorthian was.</p>
                <p>I might also say that part of our work as I started to say earlier was arranging
                    for trips, correspondents that wanted to go into the field. They were usually
                    flown around on MACV, Military Assistance Command Vietnam Aircraft, and were
                    able to get into the field quite a bit. Some of them were wounded. I don't know.
                    Maybe some of them were even killed. I don't recall whether— you may recall
                    that, whether any correspondents were killed there. I don't think anybody was in
                    my time. But I know some of them were involved in some pretty hot
                    operations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You may recall Dickie Shapiro, Larry Burrows were
                        casualties in Vietnam.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>LEVINE: That's right. I remember reading about Burrows. I don't think that—that
                    didn't happen when I was there. But he was always—he was a photographer for
                    Life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's correct.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: And I can remember seeing some of his photos in print, particularly one
                    very dicey operation which he miraculously got out of alive with helicopters
                    being shot down one after the other.</p>
                <p>Levine's Work Did Not Involve Much PersonalContact with Combat Operations</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the emphasis? As you remember during those years
                        we had some very famous engagements in '65, '66 when you were there. There
                        were such things as the battle of Ia Drang which was a major battle in the
                        highlands. There was the question of securing the Delta. And then there was
                        the question of pacification. Did you get into all these substantive
                        areas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: I did not. I made a few trips. I read about the Ia Drang Valley battle
                    and some of the other battles. But I did not get close to anything substantive
                    insofar as that was concerned. I did make one rather interesting trip to the
                    Mekong Delta with some Japanese correspondents early on. This was in about, I
                    would say, July of 1965. And with two of our famous Vietnam hands, Ev Bumgardner
                    and Frank Scotton who were then involved in a motivational training exercise
                    which they did with the popular forces and regional forces trying to help the
                    Vietnamese explain to them, the South Vietnamese government, what they had at
                    stake in the fight that was going on. A short part of that trip was by plane.
                    And I don't really remember the names of the towns we went to. And then we
                    proceeded by jeep almost up to the Cambodian border. Scotton knew a lot of
                    Vietnamese along the way and was sure that the road was secure. And it included,
                    I remember, a ferry ride in our jeep. We had to cross a stream or a river. I
                    don't remember the name of it now. But there were no exciting developments on
                    that trip. I was just intrigued by the fact that we could travel as far as we
                    did by jeep in an area which I assumed had a lot of Viet Cong in it. Apparently
                    they weren't around at the time because obviously we would have been easy
                    picking if they had been.</p>
                <p>By Early '65, Mission Had LostCredibility with U.S. and Foreign Press</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>So I didn't get into the big substantive decisions of the mission. I might
                    mention one thing, that before Zorthian got there, and he got there over a year
                    before I did, there was a situation with the reporters who were much less
                    numerous then. The reporters just simply didn't believe the mission. The mission
                    was putting out a lot of very optimistic information about the situation in
                    Vietnam. The reporters didn't believe it. The reporters were guys like Neil
                    Sheehan of UPI first and then later with the New York Times and David Halberstam
                    who was with the New York Times and is now a freelance writer. He's written a
                    number of books including a couple about Vietnam. And the basic thrust of what
                    we were trying to do with the mission press center was re-establish the
                    credibility of the U.S. mission which I think was done to a certain extent. In
                    spite of what later happened, the fact that we really lost the war there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your guiding principles if you want to call it,
                        or your modus operandi, in order to re-establish the credibility of the
                        —?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, first of all it was to make it easy for reporters to travel around
                    the country who wanted to, to view American troops in combat, in other words not
                    hiding things from them. That was number one. Number two was to try to answer
                    their questions as candidly as we possibly could given the requirements of
                    military security. The daily briefing by us, and then there was another one by
                    the Vietnamese, which was not held at the same place at least when I was there,
                    the daily briefing was an opportunity for the reporters to ask us questions, if
                    need be sticky questions, nasty questions about things that either they had seen
                    in the field or that they had heard about in the field. And I think that this
                    strategy did succeed to a large extent.</p>
                <p>Visiting VIPs in Saigon, 1965-66</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In your tenure in Vietnam, Robert, did any of the
                        Washington VIPs come to Saigon and then make themselves available at press
                        briefings? Did you get involved in that type of operation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, yes. Some came. I mean, Robert McNamara who was Secretary of
                    Defense came at least once, maybe more than once while I was there. Secretary
                    Rusk came once. Averell Harriman who was I believe then Assistant Secretary of
                    State for the Far East came with Rusk. I'm trying to think of who else. There
                    were some other VIPs who came there who were maybe somewhat lower down the line.
                    Of course, even the ambassador, who was, I believe when I got there, Maxwell
                    Taylor and later, Lodge on his second tour in Vietnam, were to a certain extent
                    VIPs, Taylor having been Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff and Lodge very
                    well known and having been U.S. Ambassador to the United Nations, and known for
                    other things too. They did make themselves available at news conferences. I
                    don't recall the details of any of their news conferences.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>But usually at this five O'clock news conference, we had the five O'clock follies
                    as I mentioned to you earlier. Any activity that was unusually important and
                    might interest the press was unveiled there. If there was a visitor he would
                    show up there. Sometimes a visitor would give a background briefing to a smaller
                    number of correspondents and instead of several hundred maybe only 20 or so of
                    the key people there. This went on all the time even whether or not there was a
                    VIP there. Then General Westmoreland who was a commander of MACV would see some
                    journalists individually or talk to them on the phone. The ambassador would too
                    occasionally. But I did not have any involvement in that.</p>
                <p>Satisfactions and Frustrations of the Spokesman Job</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But as you look back over this period Robert, tell me a
                        little bit what were some of your satisfactions that you derived from the
                        job and some of the frustrations that you encountered?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, I suppose the chief satisfaction was being involved in what was a
                    very big story. I was there in May of '65 to August of '66, about 15 months. And
                    the story was a hot one all the time. It was on page one virtually everyday. And
                    so you felt that whatever information you gave to reporters who asked you
                    questions was going to be fed into a story was going to be used. That was a big
                    satisfaction. The fact that you were a part, even though a very small part, of
                    something that was big and important. The frustration was the fact as I
                    mentioned earlier that we weren't always, well, we weren't often briefed enough
                    to be able to answer questions. And we would have to send a reporter who quizzed
                    us on one thing or another to Barry Zorthian who was pretty well wired in to
                    everything that was going on. I think that was a major frustration. The physical
                    situation there was quite pleasant. I shared a big villa with my boss Kaplan and
                    living was comfortable. There wasn't any problem like that. Unlike the poor GIs
                    who were out in the field, I'm talking about the infantrymen, who had a very
                    rough and bloody time. There was none of that kind of frustration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about some of the frustrations working with newsmen
                        who are ever demanding and never satisfied?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, I suppose I was to a certain extent used to that. I had started
                    doing it in Geneva. I didn't do much of it in that brief tour in Paris because
                    it wasn't really part of my job, a little bit of it. But that goes with the
                    territory as they say. When you deal with the press there is a funny two prong
                    kind of relationship. It depends upon the individual journalist.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>But on the one hand to a certain extent they are part of the operation. They hate
                    to have this said. But in a case where you are fighting a war and they
                    participate by going out on operations with American troops, they become part of
                    the operation willy nilly. It's very difficult to take the enemy's side when
                    you're with some guys who are getting shot at and you see some of them wounded
                    and some of them killed. You take a certain point of view whether you like it or
                    not.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, of course, there was a lot of objection which was steadily
                    growing in the United States and which I saw later on incidentally in a tour I
                    did in the State Department after leaving Vietnam. There was all this
                    opposition, a considerable amount of public opposition to our policies there,
                    disbelief about the evaluations of how things were going there given by the top
                    officers of the government from the President, who was then Lyndon Johnson, on
                    down. And that created a certain amount of difficulty. But I don't know if you
                    want me to get into what happened after I left Vietnam because I was still
                    involved in Vietnam affairs at the State Department.</p>
                <p>Varying Attitudes, Practices,Attitudes of News Correspondents</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We might follow up on that after we go through the actual
                        period. But there were stories, you must have had what you would call your
                        favorite or more favorite correspondents. You must have had some that were
                        gadflies or a bane to you. I'm thinking of one correspondent who shall
                        remain nameless who used to wander through the offices and look at people's
                        desk and look for classified material. Do you have any anecdotes and
                        stories?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, yes. There was a case of one correspondent, I don't know if he's
                    the same one you're talking about, who was totally obnoxious. I won't name him
                    if I'm saying these nasty things about him. He was a totally obnoxious creature.
                    On the other hand, his copy was very good. He supported us. He had a good
                    relationship with General Westmoreland as a matter of fact. But he looked upon
                    us—I'm talking about myself, Harold Kaplan, the civilians who worked in JUSPAO
                    as sort of civilian hacks who were doing this because we couldn't do anything
                    else. Nevertheless, his copy was always supportive of everything we did. As a
                    matter of fact, the other newsmen actively disliked him.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>On the other hand, there were a few correspondents who visited us. I remember
                    one, I don't recall his name, who took a very anti-U.S. policy view. He was a
                    visitor. He was not stationed in Vietnam. And Frank Scotton took him out on a
                    trip to one of these motivational training centers. And he was, according to
                    Scotton, completely turned around and understood, felt he understood we were
                    fighting the good fight and they were doing something very worthwhile in this
                    motivational training. When he got back to the United States he flipped back
                    again, or flip flopped again, and wrote some very nasty stories. So that's the
                    kind of thing, that isn't something that I personally had to put up with. But I
                    did deal with some correspondents, some of whom were very supportive. One
                    Frenchman, for example, who had fought in Vietnam during the French war. He was
                    a visitor. And I've seen him a number of times since then although I haven't
                    seen him for many years now. I think his name was Pierre Darcourt,
                    D-A-R-C-O-U-R-T. I'm not 100 percent sure of that name. And he went out to visit
                    the first air cavalry division. Of course, if you take a division with 15,000
                    men you're going to find all kinds of people. Like they had somebody there who
                    spoke fluent French. There were people there, he said there were people who even
                    spoke, they had somebody who spoke Turkish believe it or not. They had somebody
                    who spoke I don't know what. Anyway, other languages.</p>
                <p>And when the first air cavalry division arrived, I don't know whether you knew
                    about this or not, there was a massacre of a French unit somewhere on what
                    Bernard Fall called the route without joy, somewhere Route One going up towards
                    the north although it was still in South Vietnam, A French unit as ambushed and
                    virtually wiped out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: North of Tuy Hoa. The French put up some kind of a marker about this. And
                    it was all overgrown. The first Air Cav found the marker and cleaned it up and,
                    I don't know, presented military honors, raised a flag, blew a bugle, or
                    whatever they did. And Darcourt who was really basically on our side anyway was
                    terribly impressed by this. He just thought it was great. He could probably say
                    no wrong about anything that we were doing there.</p>
                <p>Relationship Between USIA and Military</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Robert, tell about the relationship between the civilians
                        or the USIA staff and the military. Here you were in a way mission
                        spokesmen, but you weren't really spokesmen for the military were you? I
                        mean, how did this whole relationship and interaction work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, Barry Zorthian, of course, covered the whole thing. And the
                    civilians as far as the daily briefing was concerned, the civilians really ran
                    it. And Barry organized it. You know what a dynamic guy he is. He organized all
                    kinds of things. He organized backgrounders, backgrounders by Westmoreland as
                    well as by the Ambassador.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>I would say that the relations that we had while I was there in the mission in
                    JUSPAO with the military the relations were very good. If a reporter came to us
                    and wanted to go somewhere out in the field, we would talk to the military and
                    they would see what they could work out, a plane, a ride, what have you. So I
                    think basically our relations were very good. Now, Barry Zorthian being the kind
                    of guy he was I'm sure he rubbed a number of the military information people the
                    wrong way. They didn't like the fact he was civilian even though he was a
                    reserve officer, you know, a Marine Corps reserve officer. They didn't like the
                    fact that he was the one who controlled everything. But I never found at least
                    in my experience there, I never found any difficulty. I remember once when I
                    occasionally did the five O'clock briefing, the civilian side when Kaplan was
                    away. And I remember once I got into some kind of trouble. I couldn't answer a
                    question. And the top military briefer jumped in and helped me out, you know,
                    for which I was very grateful. In fact, I even got helped out once by a
                    correspondent who pointed out something that I had overlooked that was favorable
                    to what we were trying to say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you also had, of course, to work with the military on
                        logistics. In other words, you said they were flying in MACV transportation.
                        So you had a continuous liaison with the military</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: We did. They were in that same building on—what was it? I can't think of
                    the name of the street. I'll think of it in minute. Where JUSPAO headquarters
                    were next to the Rex Theater and whatnot. So we would just go to them and say,
                    look, I've got a guy from such and such a newspaper or whatever who's trying to
                    get to this place and see if they can help. Sometimes a correspondent would go
                    directly to them. But if he was a visitor who didn't know his way around too
                    well then we would intervene.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were these military directly attached to the JUSPAO staff
                        or were they separate? In other words, did they work as part of the JUSPAO
                        team, let's say a transportation officer, a military transportation officer,
                        assigned to JUSPAO?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>LEVINE: I don't think they were part of the JUSPAO staff. But they were expected
                    to cooperate with us. As you know we had many military people in JUSPAO. You
                    asked me about the military-civilian relationship. My experience with it was
                    good. But as you know the general idea of Barry Zorthian was to have an
                    information officer on every single province. I think he almost made it. There
                    may have been one province that didn't have one whose purpose was not to act as
                    a spokesman really, but to beef up the Vietnamese, to give them some ideas about
                    selling their own cause to their own people. What I'm saying now is really
                    mostly hearsay. But it comes from these guys who arrived from all over the world
                    in Saigon, knew nothing about Vietnam. Didn't, of course, know the language. But
                    often didn't know much about the country at all, and had a couple of days of
                    briefings in Saigon and then were shipped out to the provinces to work with the
                    Vietnamese Information Service. All I know is that they had a very difficult
                    time with it. They knew something about Information. But they didn't know
                    anything about the atmosphere of the country, you know, where they were
                    operating.</p>
                <p>Majority of Correspondents Confined Interest to What U.S. Military Was Doing:Only
                    a Few Tried to Look at the Country—It's Background, Culture, Economy, Etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about this proposition? If you send a correspondent
                        to anywhere in Vietnam, would you call up the province or wherever he was
                        going and alert the JUSPAO representative in the province to try and be
                        helpful to that man? Or did you turn them over to the military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, we basically turned them over to the military. Because
                    unfortunately—I say unfortunately although it's normal. These guys are
                    interested in what the American troops are doing in the battles that they were
                    fighting. I am sure I have never seen anybody do this kind of a study. But if
                    you took a survey of what was written, printed, broadcast, what have you, about
                    Vietnam during the years when the fighting was really hot, probably 98 percent
                    of it dealt with military operations, with U.S. military operations, maybe 95
                    percent. Maybe a few percentage points dealt with what the South Vietnamese were
                    doing. But except for a very rare few correspondents such as Sol Sanders who
                    worked for U.S. News &amp; World Report, Dennis Warner who was an Australian
                    whose copy I think also appeared occasionally in The Reporter which was still in
                    existence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Shaplen of the New Yorker.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>LEVINE: I don't recall him. Oh, Shaplen. Yes, Bob Shaplen whom I knew actually
                    very well. But these there were almost unique in trying to describe what the
                    country was all about, what the cultural background of the war, what the history
                    was, what kind of a government the country had, what the social problems were.
                    And now and then there was a Nisei who worked for the Christian Science Monitor,
                    Takashi Oka. I don't know if you ever dealt with him. He did some of that too.
                    But for the others, all they wanted was the military. As a matter of fact, I can
                    remember—maybe you had this experience also. But I can remember groups of
                    editors. I remember a gang from Time Magazine who came over, a bunch of their
                    top editors. And I was at a luncheon talking to one of them. I don't remember
                    the man's name. And I made this pitch. I said, why don't you guys write more
                    about the country and stop writing just about the U.S. military operations. And
                    he seemed very sympathetic. But obviously there was no change discernable in
                    Time's coverage. As a matter of fact, some of the Time reporters that I knew
                    there told me that they would constantly get demands, rockets from New York
                    asking for coverage of this or that military operation and expressing very
                    little interest in anything else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There weren't really in your experience any specialized
                        people, for example, who covered the economy or the AID operation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: No. I mean, there was some writing about some of these things, but not
                    very much. I mean, there was nobody specializing in the economy. With the
                    exception of the three people that we talked about earlier and a possible
                    fourth, I don't recall anybody even wrote about the politics, you know, who
                    specialized in the politics and let's say ignored the military and decided I'm
                    just going to write about the politics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you know, what you say is fascinating. Because so
                        many of the books that have since been written about Vietnam dealt very
                        harshly and probably justly so with the corruption of the Saigon
                        government.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Yeah.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any experience even during the briefing that
                        this subject was raised by correspondents? You mentioned Neil Sheehan whose
                        latest book, of course, is very critical on this particular point. At that
                        point did he raise any do you remember?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: I don't recall him raising that issue. But that doesn't mean he didn't
                    raise it. I'm sure he did. I mean, after all there were Vietnamese spokesmen and
                    they talked to them. I think that when an issue really boils up—for example,
                    while I was there at one point there was one of the perennial Buddhist crises.
                    And it became so big, particularly I believe in Da Nang and—what's the other
                    city?</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hue.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: And Hue, H-U-E, that correspondents had to cover it, you know. I mean, it
                    would just impose itself on them. So there political moves became, got a certain
                    amount of attention. And when there was a coup, just as you know there were
                    many, the coup got attention. But then they quickly slipped back from that into
                    the regular coverage of military operations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned in your past experiences that you had with
                        Scotton and Bumgardner who at one time were rather legendary in USIA also
                        for their counter terrorist programs, and ultimately I think were engaged in
                        the Phoenix program probably after you left. What about some of the other
                        colleagues that you worked with? Who was there? Who impressed you? Or did
                        they know what they were doing? What was it like to have all of a sudden a
                        big build up of many Americans drawn from all over the world and somehow
                        being ignorant of what they were even supposed to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On Several Occasions U.S. Province Representative Sent to Field Without Knowledge
                    of What They Were Supposed to Do</p>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, it's kind of difficult for me to talk about this. I had some
                    contacts. Most of my contacts were just absorbed full time with the daily
                    briefings and dealing with correspondents. In other words, I didn't have too
                    much contact with the other parts of the organization. Now, I did talk at one—I
                    talked to a few province representatives, as I mentioned earlier, who confessed,
                    as a matter of fact, at being chagrined because they were shoved out into the
                    provinces without any knowledge of really what they were supposed to do, just a
                    very general idea. I'm sure that some of them were good and managed to survive
                    somehow or other. And others were not. But I don't have, I really don't have a
                    good fix on what the other people in JUSPAO were doing.</p>
                <p>Levine Arranges for Requisition of Communications Equipment Permitting the Filing
                    of Material Directly From Saigon</p>
                <p>At one point, for example, I had—I don't know whether this is amusing for this
                    project's purposes. But believe it or not, even after there was an enormous
                    amount of copy being filed out of Vietnam everyday with television and radio
                    reporters there as well as print reporters, there was no way for them to get
                    television interviews for example or any kind of film back to the States except
                    by flying it to Manila or Tokyo or what have you. It would always come a day
                    late. And I was given the job of trying to work something out.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>I got a fellow whose name I can't recall now who worked for JUSPAO. He was a real
                    ball of fire, an amusing guy, who was sort of an expediter who used to try to
                    get our pamphlets and propaganda and whatnot shipped out to the field.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bill Ford?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: No, it was an Italian name.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dino Catarini?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: No, it wasn't Catarini either. As a matter of fact he was from somewhere
                    upstate New York I think. I can't think of his name now. It may come back to me.
                    In any case I made the point to several of the wire correspondents, several of
                    the TV correspondents that there's an awful lot of money to be made here if—not
                    for them personally, but I mean their organizations, if they would be able to
                    file their copy electronically out of Saigon. And we finally got something
                    going. And this fellow whose name I can't think of now got MACV to bring in some
                    equipment from Manila which was finally set up so correspondents could go
                    downtown someplace, I don't know where it was, and file directly to the United
                    States via, I think it was via air to Manila, via cable from Manila back to New
                    York so the stuff could be filed immediately.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Robert, just for clarification when you said file you mean
                        written copy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: No, I'm sorry. I don't mean written copy. I mean video stuff. I mean
                    video copy, audio or video. One of the things that was kind of amusing about
                    that, after working like hell to get this thing all set up and getting everybody
                    involved, the equipment supplied free, brought in to be paid for as a result of
                    the fees that would be sent back to the United States. Because it was obviously
                    an enormous amount of traffic. There wasn't any problem of it being paid for.
                    The equipment landed in Saigon from Manila. And the minister for PTT, I've
                    forgotten his name now, Vietnamese.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For the postal service.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>LEVINE: Yeah, for the postal service, postal, telegraph, whatnot. Called me up
                    and said, listen, all this equipment has just landed here. He said, I don't
                    know. There might be bombs in it, you know. After doing all this work—he spoke
                    in French incidentally. He was an old timer. And I really got sore I suppose
                    like many Americans did who were frustrated by the Vietnamese after all I had
                    gone through to try to get this equipment, number one, supplied, number two,
                    transported to Saigon, we run into a roadblock because this guy was afraid to
                    clear the material to be sent into town. Well, I finally did. I exploded. I've
                    never done that before or since to a minister of any government. And the
                    material came in and was set up and used. Whether it benefited what we were
                    trying to do or not I don't know. I suppose some of the negative reports that
                    came out like the famous burning of Cam Ne, I don't remember if that was before
                    or after.</p>
                <p>Sometimes Material Sent to States Via This Direct Communication Equipment Was
                    Detrimental to U.S. Position</p>
                <p>Do you remember about Morley's—well, it was a famous incident that happened while
                    I was there. Morley Safer who now works on 60 Minutes was a correspondent for
                    CBS there. He was with a unit out in the field. And they had taken some fire
                    from the village. I don't know whether they had anybody killed or wounded. But I
                    know they'd taken fire. And the head of this unit which wasn't very big, it may
                    have been a company. I don't even think it was a battalion, went into the
                    village and with a Zippo lighter simply set fire to huts there. Safer got this
                    on film And it was seen back in the States the same day or the next day, I don't
                    know which, including by the President as a matter of fact. And all hell broke
                    loose because of that. So I don't know that my getting that equipment in
                    benefitted our cause or not. But it created a certain amount of good will, I
                    guess, with the correspondents.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bob, do you have any comment—I think tours of duty for
                        USIA officers were rather limited. They were 18 months without home leave as
                        I recall or two years with a break in between and some people left.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Short Duty Tours, Rapid Personnel Turnover HamperedU.S. Efforts, Both Civilian
                    and Military</p>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, there was a problem of continuity with this rapid turnover of USIS
                    JUSPAO officials. It was also I think a bigger problem perhaps even with the
                    military who had a shorter tour of duty, just 12 months. As a matter of fact I
                    recall—you know, I hadn't mentioned this yet, but I had visited Vietnam in 1952
                    when I was a journalist working in Paris for International News Service. And the
                    French were fighting their war at that time. They did not send draftees to
                    Vietnam; they had draftees but they didn't send them to Vietnam. So all their
                    people were professionals, whether they were noncommissioned officers or
                    privates or officers. Their tour of duty was 27 months.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>And I met French officers, and noncoms, who were there on their second tour of
                    duty and some on their third. Obviously this gave them considerable amount of
                    continuity and knowledge. They still didn't achieve what the French government
                    sought to achieve there. But I think it helped them a lot. And we were hampered
                    by this lack of continuity unquestionably.</p>
                <p>Efforts to Bring Representations, Press and Otherwise,In From Other Countries</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a great deal of world interest too. And you
                        mentioned already you went out with some Japanese reporters. Did we do
                        anything to attract or bring people from the USIS posts around the world?
                        Did they send reporters or television crews to Vietnam? What was interaction
                        between JUSPAO and now USIS post or USIA post around the world if any?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, I don't know too much about that. I know in several instances, for
                    example, USIS Tokyo, for example, sent Nat Thayer, who was a fluent Japanese
                    speaker. He's no longer with the agency. And he came down to Saigon to deal with
                    the Japanese press. And the Japanese have media that are so vast, I mean, they
                    have enormous circulation. All their big newspapers are nationally circulated,
                    unlike the United States. And there was a sizeable contingent of Japanese
                    correspondents in Saigon. And Nat came down to deal with them, talk to them,
                    travel with them. So that was one example of it.</p>
                <p>Now, correspondents did come in from all over the world. And there was a certain
                    amount of contact between JUSPAO and at least some of the main posts around the
                    world. I was not involved in that except when people arrived. Sometimes I would
                    help to orient them and maybe fix them up with trips around the country, that
                    sort of thing. So there was a definite attempt to influence public opinion
                    around the world by influencing—well, the attempt was made on various levels.
                    But one level was to influence their media. I think that most of the media saw
                    that this was a big issue. The war was an important issue even in countries that
                    were not fighting it as we were. And so we got quite a few European
                    correspondents, Japanese, Australian. Of course, there were some Australian
                    troops there, not many, but there were some. Some Korean correspondents too
                    because Korea had, I believe, a division there if I'm not mistaken. Anyway, they
                    had a sizeable contingent. So there was contact with other posts.</p>
                <p>Style of Living for Americans Stationed in Saigon</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Robert, let me just go a little bit to the lighter side.
                        You just alluded to it earlier. You said you and Harold Kaplan shared a
                        house and living was quite comfortable. Can you describe a little bit, were
                        you assigned a house? And that also applies to the correspondents. Did you
                        get into logistics with them like housing or transportation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: No.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was it like to live in Saigon? What was an average
                        day like for you? Did you observe weekends? Was life normal outside of work?
                        What was it like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Let me say first of all, we did not get into logistics for
                    correspondents. Aside perhaps from making hotel reservations for visitors. But
                    the ones who were stationed in Vietnam did not benefit from our attempts to get
                    housing for them or anything like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they had access to the PXs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: They had access to the PXs by virtue of being accredited to MACV and
                    that's true. As far as living, those of us who were stationed there, who were
                    members of JUSPAO, as I said, it was comfortable. Kaplan, who got there before I
                    did, he'd been there I think since about February of 1965, had a villa assigned
                    to him. And he asked me if I would like to share it with him. I didn't think it
                    was too good an idea to be living with a guy who was my boss. But it worked out
                    very well. And it was a nice big house on a street there, Phan Dinh Phung,
                    P-H-A-N D-I-N-H P-H-U-N-G.</p>
                <p>And we had, you know, several servants. There was a cook. There was what, I think
                    they call a boyess, who sort of cleaned up, like a maid in other words. There
                    were at least those two that I can recall now. Maybe there was a third person
                    there. It was a pretty good sized house. And we were able to put up at least one
                    visitor there. We had one spare bedroom which was used for visiting either USIS
                    or State Department people who came through. We did a fair amount of
                    entertaining. The cook we had was very good.</p>
                <p>So I would say that, as I said before, that living there was pleasant. All the
                    creature comforts were certainly there for those of us—at least it was my case.
                    Maybe I lived in a fancier house because I was working for a higher ranked boss
                    than would have otherwise been the case. But I think most of the homes that I
                    visited there while I was there were comfortable. There was a certain amount of
                    entertaining back and forth and dinner parties. And we held one big New Year's
                    bash while I was there which was quite successful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How much business did you do at this famous, or rather
                        infamous, whatever you might think of it, Cercle Sportif, which was the
                        sports club, I mean, which was the swimming pool.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>LEVINE: I don't recall really doing business there. I recall going there and
                    swimming and having lunch. Kaplan who was an ardent tennis player played a lot
                    of tennis there. I guess kept his weight down because playing tennis in the
                    Saigon heat would do that. But I don't recall transacting much business there.
                    Most of the business was transacted in the office. And incidentally, the office
                    work was seven days a week. I mean, I remember it being seven days a week. Of
                    course, when I was there I was single. I didn't have a family. So I didn't go on
                    R&amp;R anywhere. I took off at one point in the 15 month tour. I went back to
                    the United States for about a week getting a free ride in one direction on the
                    Secretary of State's airplane.</p>
                <p>Effect of Saigon Assignments on Family Relationships</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now Robert, in retrospect, Vietnam or service in Vietnam
                        also had become a hazard to many USIA officer's families, not only because
                        of family separation, but there were also a lot of family breakups. Do you
                        have any comment on what caused it or what might have been contributing
                        factors?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: You know, as I said to you I was single when I was there. So I didn't
                    face that problem myself. I think anytime you have lengthy family separation
                    that's going to put a strain on a marriage. So it certainly put a strain on
                    marriages there. In other words, a marriage has to be pretty solid to be able to
                    withstand that. And I don't know what the statistics would show about the
                    relative stability of families who were separated in Vietnam versus those that
                    didn't have to go through that. Of course, there were people who said that there
                    were other places in the world where they faced family separation also. But the
                    only thing I can say is if the marriage was solid it would probably endure. If
                    it wasn't solid that would weaken it.</p>
                <p>Saigon Scandals</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were times especially in Saigon when even some of
                        our military people seem to have gotten involved in various kinds of
                        scandals. I remember a Navy person who was there. Did you have to deal with
                        this in relation to the press? I mean, were questions asked about this? And
                        how did you deal with these things? Or did you refer that back to the
                        military or to other people?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, I can recall several scandals there. One was the military. And I
                    don't see any reason not to mention his name because it was a public matter.
                    Archie Kuntze who was a captain, a Navy captain, who was in charge of the PX.
                    Now, that didn't break until after he got back to the United States. And it may
                    have even been after he retired from the Navy. I don't know. But I know he was
                    not in Saigon anymore when he was supposedly, I don't know, finagling money,
                    changing money on the black market and whatnot. The funny thing about that is
                    after that Kuntze left and they got a straight arrow in to run the PX, the stuff
                    that you found there was much less attractive than when Kuntze was running
                    it.</p>
                <p>Now, there was another scandal when I was there that did take place while I was
                    in Vietnam which involved one of the top officers in AID, who was having an
                    affair with a Vietnamese woman. He was married. His wife was back in France, not
                    in the United States; she was French. And I don't remember all the details of
                    it. But it resulted in a murder. That's the reason it became a scandal. This
                    Vietnamese woman who was beautiful had while this AID officer was away on home
                    leave, extended leave that lasted, I don't know, a couple of months or
                    something, quite a bit of time, took up with a younger officer, also an AID
                    officer. When the big boy came back she left the younger man to go back with the
                    older guy, and the younger man shot her and killed her. This became quite a
                    cause celebre. I think we did have to answer questions on that. But then those
                    are the only two scandals that I can recall while I was there.</p>
                <p>Retrospective Look at What Vietnam AssignmentMeant To and For Levine</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bob, looking back on this experience that you have had, I
                        suppose nobody in USIA at that time had much of a choice whether they did
                        want to go or did not want to go. They were sent there. And that was about
                        it. But how would you sum up your experiences? Was it professionally
                        interesting? Was it rewarding? I mean, if you had a choice, I mean looking
                        back now, would you have gone voluntarily rather than been ordered there?
                        What is your summary impression of that year? And what did it do for you as
                        an individual or didn't do for you as an individual?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Well, I suppose I would say number one I would not have gone there
                    voluntarily in the middle of another tour. I had only been in Paris for nine
                    months, a city I knew very well and loved and I spoke the language and all of
                    that. I would have been willing to go there. I would have gone voluntarily if I
                    had been asked at the end of the tour in France. What I got out of it
                    professionally, I got a lot out of it professionally because I learned a lot
                    about dealing with the press which I continued to do to a considerable extent in
                    my career in USIA and even now when I work at the Treasury. I also deal with the
                    press. Of course, the issues are much more low key. They're not hot like that
                    one was.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>But I suppose I got an abiding interest in things Vietnamese. I read a number of
                    the books that have come out about the subject. You mentioned Neil Sheehan. I
                    read his book just recently which I found fascinating, the biography of —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jean Paul Vann.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Of Jean Paul Vann, that's right. But it's the Vietnamese experience built
                    around Vann's biography, on which I thought that Sheehan did a terrific job in
                    that book. Obviously he did a lot of research on it. So I still have— when I see
                    something about Vietnam I read it, I grab it and read it. I don't think it did
                    me any either particular good or harm as far as my career in the Agency was
                    concerned. It did get me the press experience of dealing with a difficult
                    subject.</p>
                <p>1966 State Department Tour:East Asia and Pacific Bureau</p>
                <p>Then I went on. My next assignment was on loan to the State Department as first
                    Deputy Public Affairs Advisor and then Public Affairs Advisor in the Bureau of
                    East Asian and Pacific Affairs. So I used my Vietnamese experience in dealing
                    with that. And I also made one trip to Vietnam in 1967 when I was still at State
                    for the—they had national elections. I think it was around September of 1967.
                    And I went with an observer team that went there that the President and the
                    White House put together.</p>
                <p>1971: Assignment to Phnom Penh, Cambodia</p>
                <p>And then I subsequently also spent a tour of duty in Phnom Penh, Cambodia. So I
                    was in the same area. And the Vietnamese experience first of all probably had
                    something to do with my being sent to Cambodia, the fact that I dealt with that
                    part of the world, both in Saigon and in Washington. And also the fact that I
                    spoke French. Because French was still used a lot in Phnom Penh.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well Robert, let me just ask one more question. And that
                        deals with Cambodia. Were you there during the Khmer Rouge takeover of
                        Cambodia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: No, I left in 19—let's see. We got there in '71 and we left in '72. I was
                    there just about a year actually because they had—families were there.
                    Nevertheless, there were a number of incidents, a few Americans killed, not
                    military, you know. There was one incident shortly after I got there playing
                    softball a Khmer Rouge, I guess he was a Khmer Rouge, threw a grenade there and
                    killed several Americans and several Cambodians who were watching a sandlot
                    softball game. What was your question again? I got off.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there during the Khmer Rouge?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEVINE: Oh, yeah. I wasn't there during the takeover. Because I left in '72. And
                    I think—or what I started to say was that they finally ordered civilian
                    dependents, minor dependents, to leave, children to leave. And my wife, I had
                    two children then one, was just born and one was just about two. She could have
                    gone to Bangkok. And I said this wasn't part of the deal when I came here. And
                    so I left. And they said, okay, just get a replacement. And we got a
                    replacement. But the final days of Cambodia didn't happen until sometime in '75
                    after the last days in Saigon.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
