<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001558">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Ambassador Donald P. Gregg </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2010-04-10"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2010-04-10"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR DONALD P. GREGG</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: March 3, 2004</p>
                <p>Copyright 2008 ADST</p>
                <p>[Note: This interview was not edited by Ambassador Gregg.]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is March 3, 2004. This is an interview with Donald
                        P. Gregg. This is being done on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic
                        Studies and Training, and for the Luce Foundation. I am Charles Stuart
                        Kennedy. So to begin with, I wonder Don, could you tell me when and where
                        you were born and a little about where did you grow up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I was born in New York on December 5, 1927, and raised in
                    Hastings-on-Hudson, New York. My father was in YMCA (Young Men's Christian
                    Association). He was national secretary for boy's work. I had TB (tuberculosis)
                    as a kid, so I didn't really go to school until I was about 12. I went into the
                    army</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you go to school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I was taught to read at home. In those days that is about all you needed
                    to have done. I went in the army at age 17 in 1945 right out of high school, and
                    later went to Williams College.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the army where did you serve?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I was trained as a crypt-analyst and didn't get overseas. I had enlisted
                    for 18 months and they didn't have enough time to send me overseas. So I entered
                    Williams in the fall of '47, majored in philosophy, graduated in 1951. I had
                    been signed up by CIA (Central Intelligence Agency) at that time.</p>
                <p>[Portion of interview missing because the recording is too low to be able to
                    transcribe]</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>GREGG: ?I got in because NSA you know the army having spent a lot of money
                    training me as a crypt-analyst, and the interview was [inaudible] that I was not
                    at all interested, [inaudible] the CIA. I said, “What is CIA?” He said, “Oh they
                    jump out of airplanes and save the world.” I said, “Sign me up.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [inaudible]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Paramilitary, yes. Well that meant planning clandestine operations,
                    [inaudible] on the island of Saipan [inaudible] other people who were
                    paratroopers down the line, all that kind of stuff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go with Bob Dylan and all that stuff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No I was a very close friend of Jack Downey's. He was shot down in front
                    of me some 20 years before.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now, sort of moving ahead because this is going to
                        sort of concentrate on your career. You first went to Korea when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I first set foot in Korea in 1968. I had been in Japan for nine years. I
                    spoke Japanese fluently. I had become very interested in Korea through, as I saw
                    through the Japanese prism. I had become very interested, and some of my CIA
                    friends had been stationed there. I took a trip there in 1968, spent three or
                    four days there, took a train down to Pusan and came back via [inaudible] to
                    Japan, was tremendously impressed by the vitality of the people. It was the only
                    job I ever requested in my CIA career was the assignment to Korea. I was
                    assigned there in 1973.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well you mentioned the Japanese prism. My understanding is
                        the Japanese basically looked down upon the Koreans.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Very much so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean had that, what had sparked your interest. I mean
                        were you trying to see the world through a different perspective?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>GREGG: Yes. I mean I thought of the Japanese blaming the Koreans for everything
                    from crime to pollution to traffic problems, and yet one could see that progress
                    was being made in Korea, I was struck by the fact that the Koreans were so
                    supportive of us in Vietnam. They had two full divisions there for several
                    years, over 300,000 people. So I just wanted to see a neighboring country about
                    which I had heard a great deal from friends who were stationed there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you, were you able to pick up any sort of the culture
                        of Korea at the time, I mean the first visit?/ Did you sort of change your
                        view?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I was just really impressed by the directness of the people, by the beauty
                    of the country, by the strong sense of history. I have always had an interest in
                    pottery and the ceramics are gorgeous. I bought a few pieces of ceramics. It was
                    just a very interesting experience. I still have a letter I wrote to my mother
                    on the way back saying that this was a country that I really wanted to see more
                    of.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well you had also served in Vietnam. Did you have any
                        contact with the Koreans at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No. I was in charge of the ten provinces around Saigon from '70 to '72.
                    They were in I Corps. I occasionally saw a Korean officer, but I did not have
                    any contact with them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of feedback were you getting from your
                        colleagues about the Koreans?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: How tough they were, and how the pacification was really very effective I
                    think they were in a couple of provinces. They were very tough, very
                    ruthless.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then you got assigned to Korea in 1973 and were there
                        for two years. What were you doing there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I was chief of station for CIA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What can you talk about what you were doing at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>GREGG: Well the major issue was North Korea. I had been to North Korea twice now.
                    I told them and I tell others that I think North Korea is the longest running
                    failure in the history of American espionage, because we have not been very
                    successful in recruiting them. My job was to try to cooperate with the South
                    Koreans in learning more about North Korea. It also was a very touchy time for
                    U.S.-South Korean relations because by 1973 we had withdrawn from Vietnam or had
                    been evicted. Park Chung Hee, the dictator, military leader was losing faith in
                    us as a strong ally. He was acquiring weapons systems without telling us. He
                    started a nuclear program which we discovered and stopped. It was a very
                    interesting and difficult time for the relationship. My counterpart was a man
                    named Lee Hu Rak who was the director of Korean CIA. He had gone to North Korea
                    in 1972 and had met Kim Il Sung. In my first meeting with Lee Hu Rak, I took an
                    instant dislike to him. But I asked him how did you feel when you sat down
                    opposite your lifelong enemy. He said, “Oh, very strong. One man rule. Quite a
                    guy.” Full of admiration. I think that he came back and said to Park Chung Hee,
                    if we are going to talk to those people, we really are going to have to tighten
                    up. So there was a good deal of tightening up.</p>
                <p>Park Chung Hee had narrowly beaten Kim Dae Jung in an election in 1971 or '72.
                    There were charges that the votes were rigged, and Kim Dae Jung at that point
                    when I first went to Seoul, he had been in the United States speaking very
                    critically of Park Chung Hee. He had went to Japan and continued his diatribes
                    against his what was going on in Korea. So about two months after I was there,
                    Kim Dae Jung was kidnapped from his hotel room in Tokyo, and this immediately
                    became known. The ambassador to Korea at that time was Phil Habib, a man for
                    whom I have just tremendous admiration. He called me into his office and said,
                    “I know how things work here.” They are not going to kill Kim Dae Jung for 24
                    hours, until I have weighed in, and if you can tell me where he is and who has
                    him, I think we can keep him alive.” So fortunately we were able to do that, and
                    Kim Dae Jung was tied hand and foot in a small boat. He had been locked up and
                    told that he was going to be thrown into the sea. An airplane flew over the boat
                    in which he was, and I guess some kind of message was sent, and he was released
                    or untied.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your role in this? Did you go to your counterpart
                        and say “don't do it?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No I didn't. We were able to tell the ambassador that I can't go into
                    details about that, but it was KCIA that had kidnapped Kim Dae Jung.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then what did he do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: What did he do? Habib made a representation to the Korean government
                    saying it is your own agency that has done this, and you damn well better keep
                    him alive or it is going to be a tremendous spot on your escutcheon and it will
                    do huge damage to our relations.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you arrived there, what was your impression as
                        station chief of dealing with the KCIA. During part of the time when you
                        were doing this, I was in Athens as consul general there. I had you know,
                        very much the distinctive question that we were very much, very close to the
                        Greek junta and their intelligence organization. In fact too close. I mean,
                        could you describe the relationship?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well it was a very difficult relationship because we had KCIA federally
                    penetrated. Which was one of my major jobs because it was an organization
                    basically out of control. I found very quickly that they talked about North
                    Korea as a threat but their real effort was in stemming any kind of dissent
                    within South Korea. That led to one of the major events in my CIA career,
                    because after it became known that KCIA had kidnapped Kim Dae Jung, riots broke
                    out on a number of campuses including Seoul University, which is the leading
                    university in Korea. And the KCIA arrested an American-trained Korean professor
                    named Che, accused him of stirring up these riots on the campus, and either
                    tortured him to death, or tortured him to a point where he jumped out of a
                    window to avoid further torture. We also knew that. We knew exactly what had
                    happened. So I reported that back to my headquarters. I was received and noted,
                    and I then sent a message back saying that I wanted to protest this because I
                    felt that it was absolutely unacceptable.</p>
                <p>I was told that I had a message from a man named Ted Shackley who was my boss.
                    “Stop trying to save the Koreans from themselves. That is not your job. Your job
                    is to report what is going on.” So I disobeyed orders, and I told CIA this. They
                    know it, so this is not a secret from the agency. My other contact was the head
                    of the presidential protective force, which would be the equivalent of our
                    secret service. He is a man for whom I have quite a lot of respect. He was sort
                    of a Korean samurai type. He did not like Lee Hu Rak. I knew that. So I went to
                    him, and I said, “I am speaking personally. I have no authorization to do this.
                    I am just speaking on my own, but I want to tell you how badly I feel about what
                    was done to Professor Che by the Korean CIA. I came here on the assumption that
                    I would be working with the Korean CIA against our common enemy North Korea, and
                    here I find that they are much more intent on keeping dissent under control in
                    South Korea.” I said, “I am very unhappy working with an organization that does
                    that sort of thing.” That is about all I said. He took notes and thanked me. A
                    week later, Lee Hu Rak was fired. He went into hiding, and was found in the
                    Caribbean and was brought back and I think was put into jail. He is now a
                    potter. The replacement that they put in was a man named Chin Shik Su, a former
                    justice minister. He had me over and he said, “Mr. Gregg, I want you to know
                    that I am going to be as much against those who break the law on behalf of this
                    government as I am going to be against those who break the law against this
                    government.” One of his first acts was a proscription against torture. Now I
                    think that is one of the best things I did as a CIA officer. I am very glad I
                    did it and it I think was a major step in the relationship, certainly between
                    our intelligence services and eventually between our countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was probably, Ted Shackley was well know for his time
                        in Vietnam. In fact he was a major figure there. Was he back in
                        Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes, he was chief of the Far East division at that time. I have had
                    trouble with Shackley in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In his book, Ambassador Lilley talks about working with
                        Shackley in Laos. What was your impression of Shackley? Where was he coming
                        from?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well he was a very effective hard line intelligence officer. I think he
                    fully expected to be director until he ran afoul of a guy named Wilson who was
                    more ruthless than he was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But was this almost sort of the ambiance of the CIA-KCIA
                        relationship at the time. You just observed that you didn't get too involved
                        in what they were doing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well our job was to make sure that they didn't do anything crazy that
                    could start a war with North Korea. I discovered and we eventually put a stop to
                    the nuclear program. They got submarines when they weren't supposed to get
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we concerned that Park Chung Hee might lunge to the
                        North?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes. This was you know, five years after the Blue House raid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You might explain what the Blue House raid was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well this incident was where a group of North Koreans dressed in South
                    Korean uniforms infiltrated into Seoul, got close to the presidential mansion,
                    Blue House, and all but one were killed. They tried to assassinate Park Chung
                    Hee, and killed an awful lot of South Koreans before they went down. The North
                    Koreans seized the Pueblo that same year. It is now known that the South Koreans
                    trained a retaliatory force which at the last moment was stopped from going into
                    North Korea to assassinate Kim Il Sung. So it was a very tense tough kind of
                    relationship.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>There were incidents along the DMZ and our ability to defend the peninsula if we
                    had been attacked was very questionable. General Hollingsworth was there as
                    commander of the joint ROK-U.S. I Corps. He and I had been together in Vietnam
                    at the time of the attack in Easter of 1972. He was a tough profane combat
                    general. He and I were very close. I had been his intelligence advisor at a very
                    tough time in Vietnam and had given him a lot of information which he had used,
                    so he and I liked each other immensely. I remember standing with him on the
                    bank, of I guess, the Imjin River. We looked up north and he had a lot of Korean
                    generals with him. He said, “We are going to kill every son of a bitch to the
                    north end of the FEBA. Not one of those bastards is going to set foot in South
                    Korea.” That is what they loved to hear. Then he would get with my by himself
                    and he would say, “Well I wish that were true. We are outgunned, outmuscled. I
                    don't think we have a chance of defending Seoul.” So it was a very tense
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well I think the general feeling in the long run was the
                        might of the West's air power and all that would prevail, but it was not
                        going to be an easy task.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Absolutely not. People forget that when the line was drawn and Korea was
                    divided, the Korean peninsula is quite like the Italian peninsula. You have
                    served there. The North has got mineral wealth and industry and the South was
                    poor and agricultural. When the dividing line was made, the assumption was that
                    North Korea would always be the stronger half. There has been a complete
                    reversal of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the time you were there, this is the '73 to '75 period.
                        How, economically, how was the balance between North and South Korea?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I don't think we really knew. The South Koreans were beginning to make
                    ships. They were beginning to make their first car which looked as though it was
                    going to be a disaster. North Korea was very powerful militarily. They were
                    getting aid from both the Soviet Union and China. Kim Il Sung was a master at
                    not getting drawn in to either orbit totally and was able to play one off
                    against the other. So the term economic basket case was originated in South
                    Korea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Applying to South Korea.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes. So I think the feeling in the early 70's was that the North was still
                    the more powerful half of the peninsula.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well were we getting any reading at all on the mindset of
                        the North Koreans?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>GREGG: No, It was opaque. The North Koreans were almost unapproachable. Few were
                    recruited in dismal places in Africa but it was impossible to communicate with
                    them once they went home. No, it was a very poor insight that we had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there the feeling,?I mean Kim Il Sung? we are talking
                        about 50 years now since the truce. There has always been the feeling that
                        Kim Il Sung might suddenly attack. What was sort of the attack alert while
                        you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: We discovered the first tunnel that was being dug under the DMZ. I don't
                    know how many were dug. It was a monstrous task. These were, you know, going to
                    be invasion channels. I remember on the golf course I used to play, every
                    fairway has poles that would be stuck up at night to keep gliders from landing.
                    There was a curfew in Seoul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. It was great if you had teenage kids, which I
                        did.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes. So there was a constant tension, a feeling that the North might come
                    south.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And there was an air raid alert once a month. Tanks in the
                        street and all that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes, that's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what about the Korean military? Were you looking at
                        the Korean military or was that somebody else's job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well the military attach� that was his primary job. There was, and it was
                    interesting that in both the case of Park Chung Hee and later on Chung Du Won,
                    these were generals who had not been close to the United States. These were very
                    nationalistic generals whom we did no know very much about. There were cavalries
                    of generals that had very strong allegiances. There was always the question of a
                    coup occurring which did occur after Park Chung Hee was assassinated. But my
                    primary focus was on the Korean CIA and on North Korea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did the Korean CIA get its people? Was there a
                        recruiting?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>GREGG: Yes, they had a recruiting system. Some of them, there was horrendous
                    corruption on the part of some of the senior people. They had a couple of good
                    people that I got to know, and they produced a man who later became ambassador
                    to the United States, had come up through the ranks. So they attracted some good
                    people. It was a mixture just as our CIA was but with more bad than good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well were we looking at the opposition parties and all
                        this, I mean from the CIA viewpoint, or was this left to the political side
                        of the Embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Park Chung Hee stayed in office a long time. He was scared by the election
                    that he almost lost to Kim Dae Jung. The election system was fixed so that he
                    was assured of election as many times as he wanted to be president. One of the
                    unforgettable times I had with him was in November of 1974. His wife had been
                    assassinated earlier that year by a North Korean who tried to kill the
                    president. The President ducked behind a bullet proof podium. He was making a
                    speech, and the assassin killed his wife. But Gerald Ford had come through on
                    his way to Vladivostok, and they had a very good meeting. Kissinger was with
                    him.</p>
                <p>So Park invited the ambassador, who was Dick Snyder at that point, and I guess it
                    was General Stilwell who was head of the U.S. Forces Korea and me to play golf.
                    I said a few things to Park Chung Hee. I had told my counterpart in the
                    presidential protective force that I think one of the problems with President
                    Park is he doesn't have a minister of bad news. He is very anxious. He just gets
                    people to tell him what they think he wants to hear. So Park said something to
                    me in Japanese, “I hear you think I need a minister of bad news.” I said, “Yes,
                    I think every strong leader does.” Then at the dinner after the golf, it was
                    astonishing because the minister of defense was there, and the general was
                    there. They all sat like school boys with Pak at the head of the table. There
                    was a long silence. I thought my Lord, what a waste. So I said to the president,
                    I said, “Do you ever equate yourself with Kamal Ataturk of Turkey?” The reason I
                    asked that is that was a man who had all power and he systematically created an
                    opposition party and really dragged Turkey toward democracy, and is their
                    greatest living hero still to this day. So Park sort of looked at me in sort of
                    a rattlesnake might look at a rabbit, and said, “Well I don't know too much
                    about Kamal Pasha, but I want to do for Korea what he did for Turkey, that is
                    keep it militarily secure and make it economically powerful.” Then he went on
                    and said, “I am not going to stay in power forever. Some people have said that I
                    have already stayed too long, and perhaps if I hadn't run for president last
                    time, perhaps my wife would still be alive.” So we all took that as indicating
                    that he wasn't going to run for the presidency again, but he did. He just had
                    worn out his welcome, and it was a subsequent head of the KCIA who assassinated
                    him, an astonishing turn of events.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you think about all the efforts there, were there
                        forces in this '73 to '75 time, were there forces stirring in Korea that
                        looked like they were sponsored by the North Koreans at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>GREGG: There was talk of that. We felt that there were agents from the North that
                    had gone in, that it had been infiltrated. We never felt that they were able to
                    reach out, or if some were caught by local people, the unknown feeling was how
                    much influence they had on campuses because there were riots on campuses.
                    Because the anti-American feeling was quite strong in some student groups, it
                    was sort of blamed on the North. Even when I was ambassador in '89 to '93. So
                    they certainly were trying to influence things in the South, but we never were
                    able to really expose, not at least while I was there, a major successful effort
                    to that end.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved even indirectly in the efforts of the
                        KCIA to operate in the United States on Koreans living in the United
                        States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No, we would be absolutely against that. Absolutely not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean I was just wondering whether the during this
                        particular time you were station chief you were telling the KCIA to cut it
                        out or something. Were things of that nature happening?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: The only think I remember about that is when Kim Dae Jung had been in the
                    United States and speaking critically of Park Chung Hee, he had been harassed by
                    goons who we felt had been stirred up by the KCIA. I think the agency back there
                    through its liaison told them to knock that off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find you fitted within the embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Oh, I had a very excellent relationship. I was a pretty strong tennis
                    player at that point, and I used to play tennis with, Habib and I got along
                    wonderfully, and Dick Snyder and I got along wonderfully. I played tennis and
                    golf with him. I was, you know, I was declared. Everybody in town knew that I
                    was station chief. But I went out of my way, there had been a time when the
                    station chief in Korea was more powerful than the ambassador, and I made
                    absolutely clear that that was not the way I operated. I told the ambassador
                    everything I was doing. I had a really excellent relationship with
                    everybody.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression,?how did Phil Habib operate?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>GREGG: Well, he had a sense of humor. He had a tremendous sense of leadership. He
                    called me and he said, “You know there is only one rule that I have for you, and
                    that is you will not see a man named Tongsun Park.” This was a man who had been
                    given a tremendous amount of money who was trying to buy his way into favor here
                    in the United States, and he had found some willing takers on the part of some
                    Congressmen and so forth. Phil Habib just hated him. (Editor's Note: Tongsun
                    Park was at the center of a corruption scandal investigation begun in 1977 by
                    the House Standards Committee of the 95th Congress which implicated congressmen
                    in taking money or gifts from agents of the South Korean government.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he get involved with Suzie? I think there was a young
                        lady Suzie something or other?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No I didn't. Actually Pak was very, I had a funny invitation to meet
                    somebody very important, and I wasn't told who it was. I went with my antenna
                    up, and it was Tongsun Park. I just said, “Look this doesn't work. The
                    ambassador has said I am not to see you and that is it.” I walked out, and I
                    told Phil. He cussed him out and said, “That son of a bitch.” I thought he was
                    terrific. He was living in the old style Korean house there, and it was about to
                    fall down. He insisted that the embassy residence be built Korean style. It was,
                    and it is an absolutely magnificent residence. Have you seen it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes, I have gone there many times. It wasn't much fun
                        to live in for some of the ambassadors because everything is sort of out in
                        the open.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: We loved it, and I thought it was just terrific. I remember waking up or
                    going to bed after one of the many receptions that we had where everybody was
                    raving about it. I said, “Let's name this house Habib House for Phil.” So I sent
                    a cable into the department. I knew the chief administration. He is a retired
                    navy captain. I said, “Sweep all of the inevitable bureaucratic concerns out of
                    your way, and let's name this Habib, House.” Silence. No response. Three or four
                    months later Phil died, and I sent another message in. I said, “For crying out
                    loud, let's do it so it can be announced at his funeral.” Silence. So I sent a
                    third message in saying “What the hell is wrong with you people there.” They
                    said it takes an act of Congress to formally name a building. So I just put a
                    plaque up on the front door saying “This is Habib House” and I put a plaque up
                    on the gate, and it is now Habib House. I had had huge admiration for him. He
                    had been in Vietnam. He was just deal honest, and a great leader. Everybody that
                    knew him just admired him immensely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you relate to the political section?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I had some very good friends. I am having lunch with a man who was
                    political counselor, Paul Cleveland, today. He and I became lifelong
                    friends.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Give Paul my regards.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Okay, I will. There was really no tension at all. There were some of the
                    FSOs saying: oh you guys, you have much more in the way of expense accounts than
                    we do, the inevitable kind of stuff. I would say look, the way we gather
                    information is the most inefficient, expensive way there is. We are just trying
                    to get what is not being given to us through diplomacy, and in those days, there
                    is a tremendous amount. It was fascinating to me to go back as ambassador in
                    '89. I knew the chief of station very well. In three and a half years there, he
                    did his job very well. I don't think he told me one thing that was of any
                    particular surprise or value, because the relationship had matured. The military
                    and we were much closer. We were working more harmoniously with the Korean
                    CIA.</p>
                <p>We still are not very good at getting people into the North, but they had stopped
                    trying to acquire illegal weapons systems. The nuclear program had been ended,
                    and the relationship had matured. It was a much closer alliance than before.
                    There was a real need for CIA to do its thing when I was there, like stopping
                    the nuclear program and saving Kim Dae Jung's life. I mean those were two big
                    deals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you observe the relationship between Habib and was it
                        General Hollingsworth?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well it was Stilwell. He was the guy in Seoul. Hollingsworth was up north.
                    I think Hollingsworth and Habib would have gotten along just fine. They were
                    both rough cut diamonds in the rough. Stilwell had a very prickly relationship
                    with Habib, because I think there was still remnants of the rivalry between the
                    army, the UN command and the embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find Snyder?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Fine, excellent. I liked him, and I had a very good relationship with him
                    and am still very close friends to his widow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was sort of the prime architect of the reversion of
                        Okinawa as a real Japanese hand. How did you find, did you see anything
                        between Stilwell and Snyder?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes, some of the same under trappings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't the greatest.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>GREGG: No, it was not. I think there was some real sort of mutual hostility.
                    Stilwell, for example, when I reported some things on the Korean army, he would
                    argue with me and say well that is not true. Because he wanted me to think that
                    he knew everything that was being done, and that nothing was being done that he
                    didn't approve of, and that was not the case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feeling for the Korean military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes, I used to play golf with the generals. I liked them. The guys I got
                    to know, I liked because they made them selves accessible to me. They were
                    westernized; they spoke English. I never learned Korean. I could speak Japanese
                    to them, the older ones. But no I made some,?Pak Sey Jik, the guy who made the
                    Olympics, he and I became very close friends. There was a Tuesday Morning golf
                    club. The Korean generals and the American general and me, yes, I got along with
                    them very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Golf was a very important aspect of diplomacy, and frankly
                        a lot of the Far East.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes, very much so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is an interesting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Two of my favorite Korean stories come from the golf course. One, I had a
                    beautiful young caddy who caddied for me every Tuesday morning, rain, sleet or
                    snow. I remember one sleeting morning we were out playing golf and my eyes were
                    watering and my nose was running, and my glasses were just in fog, and she stood
                    there looking as she had just stepped out of a band box. I said to her, “Miss
                    Kim, why is my nose running and yours isn't?” She said, “Because your nose is so
                    big and mine is so small.”</p>
                <p>Then the second one was when I was ambassador, and we were playing. This was a
                    beautiful spring morning. We teed off at the crack of dawn, and there was still
                    a moon very visible in the sky. I turned to this caddy who was 50 years old and
                    plain as a mud fence and I said, “Oh, that moon makes me feel very romantic.”
                    She said, “Okay with me but what will your wife say?” So anyway, but no, I got
                    to know a lot of the military people. General Kung who later became prime
                    minister, was one of my close friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we concerned at the time that the military might try
                        playing games with a naval maneuver? You know what I mean, the naval aspect
                        was always rather dangerous. I mean the North Koreans would come down. I
                        don't know if they had any during this first period, if they had any
                        submarine incursions.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes, there was the Pydo island an extension of the MLL out there, a very
                    complicated piece of water. That was one of the more amusing things because we
                    learned that the Korean navy had acquired a midget submarine from I think it was
                    Germany. They weren't supposed to have any submarines. I went to the admiral who
                    was in charge of our naval forces. His name was Henry Morgan, wonderful name for
                    an admiral. I said, “Well, let's figure out a way to get the South Koreans to
                    tell you that they have this submarine.” I said, “I'll let you know when they
                    are going to exercise it, and you can launch several American aircraft, and then
                    you are obligated to tell the South Koreans that you have spotted an
                    unidentified submarine, and since the South Koreans don't have any submarines,
                    it must be a North Korean submarine, and you are about to attack it.” So that is
                    what we did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was just wondering, being part of the diplomatic
                        community, did you get involved, how were your relations with the consular
                        people for visas, because this is what I was in charge of when I was there
                        some time later?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I didn't really get involved in that. When I was ambassador, I prided
                    myself on issuing visas in Pusan, and we got rid of the lines around the
                    embassy. Then an inspection came just after I left and brought it all to a halt.
                    Ed Wilkinson was my?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: But there had been a man, very suspect, Andy Antippas, who left a very bad
                    reputation behind.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well the whole situation is very dicey. I used to worry
                        quite a bit about the corruption aspect. Well let's move on, quickly, what
                        did you do between '75 and '89?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I went back to CIA and was put in charge of, I was sort of the thrusting
                    point for the Pike investigation of the agency that Senator Church was leading a
                    Senate investigation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Another of our Williams classmates, Bill Miller was much
                        involved with that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>GREGG: I got to know Bill. That was a very difficult job because Pike had really
                    charged his people with bringing the agency to heel. I learned three things that
                    I hadn't known before. We had tried to kill Castro. We had reached out to the
                    Mafia to try to get them to kill Castro, and that we had done some drug testing
                    on some unwitting people. I thought those were all extremely unfortunate. I was
                    shocked by it, but on the whole, what came out was all right.</p>
                <p>Colby had already pulled together what he called the family jewels. He asked
                    everybody to report anything that they knew that the agency had done which they
                    felt was bad. Church and Pike soon learned that these papers existed and so they
                    were turned over. This caused an irreparable split between Colby and Dick Helms.
                    Helms felt that if those were given over, that this would increase congressional
                    oversight to the point where we would really be out of the covert action
                    business. Colby felt that if he didn't turn them over, the agency essentially
                    would be shut down. I think they both were right. But it just was a
                    watershed.</p>
                <p>Then may career fell on difficult days because Jimmy Carter brought Admiral
                    Stansfield Turner in as director, an Amherst man which was part of his problem.
                    A Christian Scientist and a moralist, and a believer that scientific SIGINT and
                    satellites could do the intelligence job antiseptically and that it was people
                    like me who had always gotten the agency in trouble. So I was put up for several
                    of the top jobs in the operations directory and got none of them. My career
                    really went sidewise. I was about to become national intelligence officer for
                    Asia, a job which I would have liked, when I was suddenly offered a chance to go
                    to the National Security Council staff at the White House, because a man named
                    Sam Hoskinson had gotten fed up with Jimmy Carter and quit. They needed an Asian
                    specialist there, and somebody put my name into the hopper. I went and
                    interviewed with Brzezinski and was given the job. So I worked at the White
                    House for the last 18 months of the Carter administration, and was one of I
                    think only two people who made the transition from Carter to Reagan. The only
                    reason I survived was that I was from CIA.</p>
                <p>The Reaganauts came into the White House sort of like the Visigoths at the sack
                    of Rome. The Carter people had fled writing graffiti on their desk blotters. It
                    was a very unpleasant turnover. I was in charge of Asian policy and intelligence
                    at the NSC.</p>
                <p>I got to know George Herbert Walker Bush there. I had met him when he was a
                    congressman, but I had never seen him as director. He asked me to become his
                    National Security Advisor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well while we are on this, on the Far Eastern policy, was
                        there a different thrust to the, from the latter part of the Carter era to
                        the early part of the Reagan era? I mean knowing Latin America there was
                        sort of an earth change, but after the dust had settled, was there much of a
                        difference in policy for other regions?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>GREGG: Well, during the Carter Administration I think that probably the American
                    ambassador who had the most difficult tour of anyone I could think of is Bill
                    Weinstein who has written a book about this, because Jimmy Carter wanted to pull
                    all our troops out of South Korea. This was regarded as a mistake by other
                    neighboring countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All of us. I mean I was in the embassy at the time, and
                        you know, we were horrified.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: So that came to a halt with Reagan. The first foreign visitor or chief of
                    state that Reagan had was Chun Doo-hwan. The price of that visit was Kim Dae
                    Jung's life. He had been sentenced to death for, what is the word I am groping
                    for? Sedition, treason. I had gone out with Secretary of defense Brown to talk
                    with Chun Doo-hwan about Kim Dae Jung. Brown said, “I don't think Chun Doo-hwan
                    is going to bring Kim Dae Jung up.” I said, “Oh I think he will, Mr. Secretary.”
                    It was the first thing that Chun brought up when we went to see him. I have a
                    hell of a problem with Kim Dae Jung,” he said. “Every single general in my army
                    wants him dead. Most of the Korean people want him dead. I know that you don't
                    want me to kill him. I know that if I do kill him, I am going to have a problem
                    with you, so it is a real problem for me.”</p>
                <p>The only thing that we told him that made any sort of impression on him was that
                    we knew the North Koreans were preparing a tremendous propaganda exploitation of
                    this. I told him that. Richard Allen who was Reagan's first National Security
                    Advisor picked up the ball. Chun wanted desperately to be legitimized by a visit
                    to the White House. So the trade off was if he saw Reagan, Kim Dae Jung would
                    be, his life would be spared. That was the trade off. We did everything we could
                    to downplay the visit. We had a lunch rather than a dinner. We used all these
                    diplomatic niceties, but Reagan was such a courteous person, you know there was
                    a picture with his arm around Chun, and Chun got what he wanted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then, when you worked for Bush, what were you doing
                        with Bush?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I was his national security advisor. I started every day with him, reading
                    the President's daily brief. I arranged who got to see him from what countries.
                    I went to 65 countries with him in the 6 � years I worked for him, and wrote
                    hundreds of papers giving him my suggestions on how our policy ought to be
                    implemented, international.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your reading of him in the international
                        world?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Superb. Absolutely superb. I have huge respect and admiration for him. I
                    saw him deal with everybody from Margaret Thatcher to Deng Xiaoping to
                    Mitterrand to Gorbachev. He was superb. His son is a completely different breed
                    of cat. I voted for him, and I am extremely uncomfortable with that vote.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have to say that I see a great deal of the retired
                        foreign service community in doing what I do, and George W. Bush, you know,
                        I really don't find any support for him within this community, which is
                        normally split. We are going through a very difficult patch I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I think it is going to be a riveting campaign.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I do too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: So anyway, after 6 � years with Bush, I got splattered by the Iran-Contra
                    affair. People thought here is a CIA guy in the White House. It is too
                    complicated to go into. I rode it out. I am the only person who was involved in
                    that to seek a job that required Senate confirmation. That was a very tough go,
                    but I got through. I have, Bush to this day, he said, “Thank you. You took the
                    heat for all of us.” That was somewhat of a vindication.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were appointed by George Herbert Walker Bush?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: To be ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To be ambassador. How did that come about? Did he
                        ask?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes. He asked me. He said, you know because of the Iran-Contra business
                    everyone was saying you ought to take Brent Scowcroft to be your security
                    advisor. I said, yes. He is a role model that everybody has. I understood that
                    completely. Bush had defended me during the Iran-Contra thing very well. So
                    people knew that I had been to Korea. They knew I was an Asian specialist, so it
                    was I think a very natural thing to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the preparations and the Senate hearing go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: There was a long delay, and Senator Cranston had a man on his staff who
                    devoted I think six months of his life to defeating my nomination. I have my
                    hearings taped. I am very proud of them. It started out with Cranston dumping on
                    me for 45 minutes. It was sort of like lying at the foot of Niagara Falls
                    looking upward. You know, I was there by myself. I didn't have a lawyer. I
                    didn't have anybody. I was all by myself, and just began to climb up the rope
                    slowly hand over hand, just dealing with the questions and accusations and so
                    forth. I finally got through in September.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the questioning, was it just Cranston or was this you
                        had to make political points?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes, I think so, and to try to embarrass Bush. You know, it was very
                    partisan. My children were all there. The man who leapt to my defense was
                    Senator Helms, a man for whom I have a great many doubts. But it was a very
                    interesting experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During that experience you are always on the tightrope
                        aren't you that you don't screw up your relations with the country you are
                        going to, saying something that might help the Senate but it is not going to
                        help you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: There was no questioning about Korea. The questioning was all about my
                    fitness to be ambassador because the feeling was I had deceived people because
                    of the Iran Contra business.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then you arrived in Korea September '89, and you were
                        there until February of '93, basically the length of the Bush
                        administration. What were the issues you felt you had to deal with when you
                        went out there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well the first issue I dealt with was the fact that we had nuclear weapons
                    in South Korea. We had a nuclear inspection; an annual team came out to make
                    sure that they were stored safely because something awful had happened in Spain
                    or something. They had to report to me when they had finished. Everything was
                    fine, but I said, “Why did this process start.” They told me what had happened
                    in Spain and how difficult that was. I realized, South Korea was already
                    embarked on what they called nordpolitik (Northern Policy). It was based on
                    Willy Brandt's Ostpolitik. The government of South Korea was establishing
                    relations with all of North Korea's friends and allies. They were moving toward
                    an attempt to reach out to North Korea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By this time China and South Korea had relations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No, they were established in September of 1992. So we also were beginning
                    to have suspicions about what was going on at Yongbyon, the North Korean's
                    nuclear interest. So, I thought, my god, if we had nuclear weapons in the South,
                    that is going to become an immediate issue. We will never take them out under
                    pressure. It will become an issue for students in the South. It will become a
                    sticking point with the North.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>I went to USFK (U.S. Forces Korea) and asked, “Why are these here?” “Well they
                    have always been here.” I said, “Are they of any utility to you?” They said,
                    “No.” So I went to President Roh Tae Woo's national security advisor, a man to
                    whom I was very close, and I said, “I think we ought to get them out of here.”
                    So it took some doing because it was part of the security blanket, but I was
                    able to send in October of 1990, a message with the full support of the Blue
                    House and USFK, I recommend we remove our nuclear weapons from South Korea. I
                    had one brief message back from Dick Solomon who was assistant secretary at
                    State. He said, “You will never know how helpful your message was.” About a year
                    later President Bush announced that we were pulling nuclear weapons back from
                    all over the world. In Korea we went through a little dance because we had the
                    “neither confirm nor deny” policy about whether we had nuclear weapons. But we
                    worked out something where President Roh would say there are no nuclear weapons
                    on Korean soil and the White House said we have no reason to object to that
                    statement by President Roh. That is one of the best things I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had these nuclear weapons been something to which the
                        South Korean government kind of hugged to their chest?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Sure. But it was just part of the security blanket. But the relationship
                    was closer. The sophistication of the relationship was greater. I made the
                    point, look if you need nuclear weapons, they can be had in spades. But having
                    these obsolescent things sitting in Osan was just an irritant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well at that time I think I remember General Chapman back
                        when I was there in '76- '79, that every time they did war games, they found
                        that the North got into Seoul and all this, and they at the last day of the
                        games they would call in massive air power to stop it. Had the balance
                        changed by the time you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: It was still iffy. That was the first thing that I asked when I got there.
                    When I left it was very tenuous. The reading at that point was, if we had good
                    weather, we can get air power deployed quickly enough and in large enough
                    numbers to probably keep them out of Seoul. But if we have bad weather it still
                    was doubtful whether we could hold Seoul. The problem of getting the people of
                    Seoul across the Han River was just incredible. So it was still a very touchy
                    defense scenario.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well how about on the economic side. Much had been made of
                        Park Chung Hee's legacy that he had set up a strong economic base there
                        including doing things for the farmers which hardly anybody else had ever
                        done in any other country, that is give them a living recompense for staying
                        and growing rice and other things.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>GREGG: Well, that became a major problem because the price of Korean rice was sky
                    high, just because of the subsidies, and yet there was a tremendous emotional
                    sentimental attachment on the part of the Korean people to their grandma on the
                    farm. Carla Hills who was the Special Trade Representative came out and was
                    pushing for us to let more beef in and rice in and so forth. One of them said,
                    “Well why are you doing this? If the prices are lowered, and the markets are
                    opened up, it is going to be the Australians that are going to sell us the beef,
                    not you, and somebody else will sell the rice.” Carla said, “We know that. We
                    are not arguing for unilateral advantage. We are talking about freer trade.”</p>
                <p>It was shortly after her visit that six students vaulted over the wall of the
                    residence and got into the residence and tried to set fire to it. My wife and I
                    were in our bedroom. They tried the door once but did not try to break in. It
                    took some time for the Korean cops to get themselves organized to rout them out.
                    I didn't feel under any particular threat. I have had people come after me with
                    real malice aforethought, and that was not the case here. These kids I think,
                    were surprised at how easy it was to get into the house. So they were eventually
                    routed out. They did about $35,000 worth of damage to the furnishings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were they after?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Protesting the opening up of the beef quotas. You know, they were making a
                    demonstration. Who knows what they were after. It was actually a very good way
                    to start a tour as ambassador because we behaved rather well. My wife in
                    particular was very gracious. We were on television. We thanked the Korean
                    police who actually had done a lousy job, but we praised them. The Koreans were
                    deeply embarrassed, but we had behaved well, and actually it was a very good way
                    to start a tour. But it showed me just how sensitive these economic issues were,
                    particularly when farmers were concerned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was your role in the trade issue?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I was probably the most active of any ambassador that had been there in
                    terms of trying to sell American products. I had a very favorable article in the
                    Wall Street Journal written when I left saying that nobody had ever done that in
                    Korea. I enjoyed it. I worked very closely with the Foreign Commercial
                    Service.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>Another high point of my tour was a fight between Lockheed and the French on
                    anti-submarine warfare planes. This was fascinating because Lockheed offered the
                    P-3 aircraft, the Neptune, and the French were trying to sell the Atlantique. So
                    Lockheed was in some trouble, and they came to me and said, “We really need to
                    keep this going. What can you do?” I did not use CIA on this because I don't
                    like economic espionage, so I went to the defense attach� and said, “We don't
                    know what price the French are willing to sell their aircraft for. Can you find
                    that out?” So he found that out. I went back to Lockheed with that. They lowered
                    their price. But the sale was still going to the French. I had gotten to know
                    the minister of defense quite well. I played golf with him, so I asked to see
                    him. I said, “Mr. Minister, you know how interested we are in this sale of
                    Lockheed aircraft. There has been a price adjustment and the Lockheed price is
                    now lower than the French price. But I don't think you know that because I don't
                    think your office has been made aware of that.” Dick Christiansen was in the
                    room with me. He is now DCM in Tokyo, absolutely fluent in Korean. He passed a
                    note to me saying the interpreter is not interpreting what I was saying. So I
                    again repeated this. I looked at Dick, and he shook his head. I then thanked the
                    minister for the meeting and said I would like to see you once more before you
                    make your final decision. That was interpreted and he said, “Yes, please.” I
                    requested to see him and said, “I would like to use my interpreter at this
                    meeting if you don't mind.” He said, “Fine.” So we went and I said exactly the
                    same thing. This time it went through. He went right through the ceiling, called
                    a halt, called a review, and the bid went to Lockheed. I was paraded down the
                    assembly line in Marietta, Georgia, one time when I was in that area where they
                    were still very pleased. The French were furious. They never spoke to me
                    again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean you know, to get to the interpreter, I mean other
                        things. It looks like a lot of people were in on the deal.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well I don't think the interpreter was. It was just what I was saying was
                    so embarrassing. That was Dick's interpretation. He didn't think the interpreter
                    had been bought off. But certainly some people down below had been bought
                    off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It does show some of the problems with interpreters. You
                        are not getting your? The president while you were there was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Roh Tae Woo?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find him?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>GREGG: I liked him. He loved to play tennis. I arranged for him to play tennis
                    with President Bush. We, unlike the Japanese who always have it Japan against
                    the United States, we teamed the two president's up as partners, and the
                    opponents including me could make career enhancing decisions as to who won the
                    match. I liked him very much. We helped him. We introduced him to Gorbachev in
                    San Francisco on 1990. We helped get the Chinese to drop their opposition to
                    both North and South Korea joining the UN. He and I were real buddies. He would
                    ask me to come and play tennis at Blue House quite frequently, and also
                    golf.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These tennis and golf things, business could be conducted
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Oh absolutely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was sort of the internal situation in Korea at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well the real political watershed I think, had taken place during Jim
                    Lilley's time where there had been an agreement to have the president elected by
                    a direct vote of the people instead of the rigged system that had been put in
                    place by Park Chung Hee. So Roh Tae Woo had been elected because he had run
                    against both Kim Dae Jung, and Kim Yung San, and there had been a three way
                    split, and he I think got something like 40% of the vote, but he was still in.
                    So he was still regarded as a military figure but he was much less authoritarian
                    than Chun Doo-hwan had been or Park Chung Hee, and conducted I thought, a very
                    sophisticated diplomacy. During my time, when I came I think Hungary was the
                    only eastern bloc country to be represented. When I left, everybody was
                    represented in Seoul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the Chinese recognition go? I mean was this
                        difficult for the Korean side or the Chinese side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: It was from the Chinese side because the North Koreans felt that as a
                    tremendous betrayal. The Chinese ambassador came to see me immediately after he
                    arrived, and we had a fascinating talk. He had spent 15 years at Pyongyang, so
                    he knew the North Koreans very well. He had been with Kim Il Sung when Kim
                    played his last visit to China in 1991, and Ceausescu of Romania had already
                    been killed after having tried to bring?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the '89 uprising.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>GREGG: Right. Ceausescu had been one of the few people that Kim Il Sung had
                    maintained a bit of an interesting relationship. The Chinese ambassador said
                    that Kim Il Sung was very worried about what had happened to Ceausescu, and had
                    said to the Chinese, “I realize that I have to make some changes in North Korea,
                    what is your advice, because he mentioned the situation in Romania.” The Chinese
                    said, “Well do what we do. Keep political control at the center but set up some
                    special economic zones at the periphery where you can have special rules and use
                    them to attract foreign investment. So Kim Il Sung began to move in that
                    direction. He set up a special economic zone way up north in Rajin-Sonbong. It
                    was doomed to failure because it was essentially a dusty parking lot surrounded
                    by barbed wire by a polluted river. It was inaccessible. Nobody wanted to go
                    there. But that is where he really started to try to move to new directions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When the Chinese came in, did they, were they pretty
                        cautious? Did they feel that this was hostile territory? How were they
                        received?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Oh they were received very well, because the Russians or the Soviets had
                    already recognized the South. By that time it was very clear that the South had
                    outstripped the North economically. I think the Chinese saw real opportunity to
                    begin mutually beneficial trade relations with the South Koreans, which they
                    have done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had there been trade relations with China before
                        hand.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: There had been some, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Going sort of through Hong Kong.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well, they had a boat from Qingdao to Inchon that had started when I left,
                    a ferry boat. Yes, there was some trade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Chinese community play any role, I mean there was
                        a small Chinese community.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No. Taiwan had been there for years, and they had to leave. What community
                    there was was more or less in the Taiwan camp I guess, but it is not a
                    significant factor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved with the two Kims?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>GREGG: Kim Dae Jung, and Kim Yung San? Yes, I did. Kim Dae Jung was very much
                    aware of the fact that twice I had been involved in keeping him alive, so he was
                    very friendly to me. Kim Yung San, I always found very unimpressive. Not very
                    intelligent. But he would ask to see me, and we would have long dull dinners.
                    But he was elected president just before I left. Dae Jung and I saw a fair
                    amount of each other. I felt one of the things I wanted to do was to go down to
                    Kwangju where there was tremendous anti U.S. feeling because of the supposition
                    on the part of the people of Kwangju that we had supported the horrible
                    suppression of things there. Kim Dae Jung helped me set that up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: It went tremendously well. It was very controversial. Kim Dae Jung said,
                    “If you are going to go, go in the winter during Christmas vacation when the
                    university isn't open, and so I planned to do that January of 1990, and the day
                    before I was supposed to go, Kim Dae Jung called me up and said, “Don't go, it
                    is too dangerous. There is a kidnap threat.” The national police was aware of
                    this, so I called a country team meeting, and said, “You know there is this. I
                    have the feeling that I really ought to go. What do you think?”</p>
                <p>The country team was split right down the middle. So I decided I would go. I left
                    a memo in my safe saying if something happens to me, it is purely my fault. So
                    off I went, and I arrived, and the press along with a huge bodyguard of police.
                    The press was saying have you come to apologize for Kwangju? I said, “No, we
                    have nothing to apologize for. I have come because we have a cultural center
                    there that is being firebombed, and I want to find out why there is such
                    resentment of us.” So I spent two full days talking to everybody. I had been to
                    Hungary once, and it was long after the uprising of 1956, but there was sort of
                    a feeling of betrayal on the part of the people of Kwangju. On the morning of
                    the third day the press came again and said, “Have you come to apologize about
                    Kwangju?” I said, “Yes, I found we do have something to apologize for, and that
                    is we have kept silent for too long.” That made an impact, and so the people who
                    had been firebombing our?been organizing the opposition agreed to see me. I had
                    been trying to se them and they refused. So I canceled my return flight, and I
                    had about 3 � hours with about six of these guys. It was absolutely fascinating.
                    At first they wanted to meet in secret, and then they decided they wanted to
                    have television. So we met in front of the television and newspaper people.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>The first question was who gave the order to shoot in the streets of Kwangju? I
                    said, “I have no idea. It was a Korean decision and a Korean order, and it is
                    only Koreans who know.” He said, “That's a lie, because we know you have
                    satellites that can look down from the sky and you can read a newspaper from the
                    sky and were watching, and you know who gave the order.” I said, “Well we do
                    have those satellites, but they don't take you inside a man's head. We don't
                    know who gave the order.” Then they said, “Do you take us as a nation of field
                    rats because the general in charge said there is a certain lemming like quality
                    in Korea.” This had not gone over well. I said, “Absolutely not. I have huge
                    admiration for the Korean people. That is why I have come back in this
                    capacity.” Then they said, “Well, we thought you were going to save us.” I said,
                    “What made you think that?” Well you sent an aircraft carrier to Pusan.” “That
                    was a signal to the North Koreans not to get involved.”</p>
                <p>They said, “We know you supported Chung Doo-hwan because he was the first man to
                    visit President Reagan. We know you supported what he did here because you were
                    so close to him.” I said, “Did you know the price of his visit was Kim Dae
                    Jung's life?” That had been said in Washington; it had been said in Seoul, but
                    it had never been said in Kwangju. It caused a sensation. So after about three
                    hours, they said, “Well we don't have any more questions. We thank you for
                    coming. Some of your answers have not been good, but some have been helpful, and
                    we thank you for coming.”</p>
                <p>The interpreter I had, who was a superb young woman, whispered to me, she had
                    just done a magnificent job and really removed the language barrier. She said
                    they are terribly afraid they are all going to be arrested after this because
                    the police are after them. I said, “Thanks for telling me.” So I went out, it
                    was raining, and the cops were surrounding the place as they had and tear gas
                    had been needed to flush some people out at times. So I put my arms around two
                    of these guys and I went up to the very tough policeman who had been my chief
                    bodyguard and said, “You are not to touch these people. You are to let them go.”
                    He sort of could hardly believe. I said, “I mean it. I don't want you to touch
                    these people.” So he barked an order and the cordon gap opened up, and as they
                    passed through each one was either kicked or pushed out into the darkness. One
                    of them turned and waved as he went.</p>
                <p>The fire bombings of our cultural center stopped. We moved to a new place and
                    were able to stay until budgetary? I went four times to Kwangju. I went with the
                    German ambassador, and we talked about the German implications for eventual
                    North-South reunification. I went down with the first Russian ambassador, and we
                    talked about the Russian view of the Korean Peninsula. I consider those visits
                    to be among the most interesting visits of my life. In fact it made me feel
                    quite at home when I went to North Korea because I felt the same kind of
                    resentment in the North that I had felt in Kwangju. I saw it evaporate as the
                    North Koreans found I was taking them seriously and trying to answer their
                    questions in good spirit.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you see the rise of anti Americanism? Had we just in a
                        way, some of these things have outrun their time or something.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: I was never in 3 � years ever able to make a publicized appearance on a
                    college campus. I was invited frequently to make appearances. I would always
                    accept. The word would get out that I was coming, and the campus activists would
                    say “Don't let Gregg come or we will burn the campus down.” So the invitation
                    would be canceled. I got an honorary degree from the Jesuit University there,
                    Sogan, and they gave it to me at night on Christmas vacation. So there was still
                    a lot of that. There were riots around the embassy frequently. So it was still
                    there. It subsided I think, later on, after I had gone. Particularly after first
                    Kim Yung San and then Kim Dae Jung, these were the opposition leaders. The
                    politics were getting freed up. The military was out of politics, so that had
                    removed one source of tension.</p>
                <p>But the Koreans had tremendous historical memory, and they remembered the
                    Taft-Katsura Agreement, which not one American in a million is aware of. I just
                    learned that the 1919 demonstration against the Japanese had been inspired by
                    Wilson's 14 points. The Koreans felt the United States would come to their aid.
                    There was a demonstration of Korean unhappiness with the Japanese occupation. We
                    didn't do that. Then there was the division of the country in 1950 that was
                    resented, and the fact that Truman would not fight to go up to the Yalu and
                    reunite the whole country. So there are all of those underlying resentments
                    which never were really fully cleared up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well were you involved at that time particularly because
                        of the fall of East Germany and all that, in looking at the problem of a
                        collapse in the North and the soft landing and the hard landing and all
                        that. Could you talk a bit about what the thinking was at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: It really didn't start until I had left. Willy Brandt made his only visit
                    to Korea while I was there in October of '89. I was a great admirer of Willy
                    Brandt, and I saw a good deal of him on his visit. He went up to the DMZ, and I
                    had dinner with him when he came back from the DMZ. He said, “That is the most
                    appalling thing I have ever seen. It is a time warp. I am sure that when that
                    DMZ is penetrated, you will find that the psychological dislocations behind it
                    are going to be much more difficult to deal with than what we will cope with
                    when the Berlin wall comes down.” He said, “We hate the Berlin wall. We draw
                    graffiti on it and so forth, but there are gates through it, and people pass
                    back and forth and radio works and television works and so forth, but the DMZ is
                    a time warp.” The Koreans said, “Well when do you think the Berlin wall will
                    come down.” Brandt said, “Not in my lifetime.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was in '89.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>GREGG: Within 60 days it was down. So I think that there was a feeling that
                    unification was going to take place. It was really after I left that they began
                    to try to quantify what that would cost. The feeling was the cost to South Korea
                    would just be more than they could handle. As I say, one of the few things that
                    North and South Korea agree on is that they want whatever process occurs to be a
                    gradual one. I think that is still true.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is tape two side one, with Don Gregg. Don, what about
                        within Korea the, I can't remember the name for it, but the big
                        industrial?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Chaebol.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Chaebol. How did you view them at the time, and what were
                        our concerns and their influence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well, they had been tremendously successful. Park Chung Hee had appointed
                    some very talented men. General Park Dae Jung said, I want you to build a world
                    class steel plant. I will give you land; I will give you loans; I will give you
                    all the help you need. So as a result, Korea is either the first or second
                    largest producer of steel to this day. Chung Se Yung of Hyundai got started, a
                    magnificent man, building ships, building cars, now into microchips. They were
                    given free reign, preferential loans. Laws were passed if they needed to be
                    passed, or pass the regulations just to allow them to grow very quickly. So, you
                    had figures on the landscape, Chung Se Yung of Hyundai, Kim Dae Jung of Daewoo
                    were the two. B.C. Lee of Samsung. These were men who were more or less laws
                    unto themselves. The thought of their collapsing was almost unthinkable at that
                    point. We felt that we wanted a better deal in terms of access for agriculture,
                    that kind of thing, but it was later on, particularly in terms of automobile
                    production that some of them just went off the rails. Daewoo is now essentially
                    defunct. Even Samsung had an ill conceived venture into the automobile business.
                    The banks were weak. Everybody was concerned with market share, not
                    profitability. There has been I think, triggered by the 1997 economic turndown,
                    there has been a real turnaround in the Korean market toward more transparency,
                    and a more profit driven system. I think they are doing very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a corruption factor in all of this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>GREGG: Yes, there was. There were always rumors for payoffs for some of the big
                    military purchases. It was very hard to pin down. The Foreign Corrupt Practices
                    Act, the American business community used to complain about it because they
                    always talked about a tilted playing field. Everybody else pays off, but we are
                    not allowed to and so forth. I would just say, “Look, one of the things the
                    United States stands for is not doing that, and just keep at it.” That is one of
                    the reasons that I became as active as I was in going to trade fairs and pushing
                    American products. I felt that for Korea really to get over the top as an
                    economic entity of continuing viability, they have to move away form the Chaebol
                    oriented, corruption ridden closed kind of economic society where if you didn't
                    pay off, you weren't going to get anywhere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well how about Congress? When I was there, I took Tongsun
                        Park's visa oath and I think Robert Giuliani, a Giuliani anyway came and was
                        taking a deposition from him. This is back in '76 I think or something. You
                        know we had congressmen who, they would arrive and not even talk to the
                        embassy, come and get measured for suits, and young ladies would appear to
                        serve as handmaidens or something. Was that still going on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: It wasn't as bad as it was in the 70's. I think that Lester Wolf was one
                    of the guys that appeared all of the time back then. There were a number of
                    them. But it was less, much less when I was there as ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find, was there much congressional interest in
                        what you were doing there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Not that I remember. Jim Baker was Secretary of State, and he had four or
                    five issues that he paid a great deal of attention to, and one of them was not
                    Korea. So I had the ability to take a lot of initiative, as I did. I never
                    really remember having to take congressional concerns into much consideration.
                    Maybe I have forgotten, but it wasn't a big?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well reverberations from the collapse of the Soviet Union
                        and the whole thing, did they filter down much to South Korea, or were they
                        insulated from this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: They were pretty much insulated. I mean it was seen as because we had
                    moved so quickly to get Roh Tae Woo in touch with Gorbachev, and they sent a
                    very able man as ambassador quickly after the collapse. I think the South
                    Koreans just saw the collapse of the Soviet Union and their recognition by China
                    as indications of their growing success and their growing stature.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about Tiananmen Square, this is in '89. I mean this
                        reverberated certainly in the United States.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>GREGG: Well you know, no. The Koreans are tough, and they have been looking down
                    the muzzles of North Korean artillery for 50 years, and it really takes a lot to
                    shake them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you, speaking of the North Korean threat, how did you
                        feel about the North Korean threat when you came back? I mean was the
                        thought of a lunge south, I mean did it make sense in the North Korean
                        context at this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No it really didn't. Our ability to defend Seoul had improved, as I say it
                    depended on good weather. But the military balance was much more favorable. It
                    was recognized that the North Korean air force wasn't exercising much. Their
                    equipment was getting old, that they didn't have the economic power to maintain
                    a massive invasion. Then as now, it was easy to inflict tremendous damage on
                    Seoul via their artillery was the main threat. I think my feeling was that it,
                    they were not irrational. This wasn't a really very likely event. Now it became
                    very much more dangerous after I left in 1994.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about, I think it was called South Pos?. We had a
                        very large American community, military community right in the heart of
                        Seoul on the wrong side of the Han River. Was that, were we concerned about
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: We were concerned about it in terms of our relations with South Korea. It
                    was as though we still had a British base in New York City's Central Park. Jim
                    Lilley had really embarrassed the military about their golf course right in the
                    middle of Seoul. I played the last round on that golf course, and we shut it
                    down. They built us another course south of the city, not nearly as convenient,
                    but at least we turned the golf course over, and it is now used as a park. We
                    talked at that time, they wanted access to the base at Yongsan. We said, yes, we
                    are willing to move, but you have to pay for it. The cost at that time of moving
                    us down to Osan or Suwan or whatever was 4-6 billion dollars. The Koreans didn't
                    want to cough up that much money. So that has been an issue for some time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were E&amp;E, I mean emergency evacuation plans
                        always?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No, that was really not. My successor Jim Laney, was about to declare that
                    the evacuation of all non-essential personnel, which is sort of the last thing
                    you do before you expect a war to start. That was headed off by Jimmy Carter's
                    visit, but not during my time we didn't talk about that.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With the arrival of the Chinese and then the Soviet and
                        then Russian embassies, were you able to get a little better picture of
                        North Korea?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes we were. Also during my time, the South Koreans had the prime minister
                    level exchanges with the North Koreans, and they signed in early '92, an
                    agreement that still isn't a very good blueprint for the way relations between
                    North and South Korea have been developed. The national security advisor to
                    President Roh Tae Woo said to me when I was about to leave, “If we could have
                    kept everybody in the United States and South Korea and North Korea in place for
                    one more year, I think we could have solved the North-South issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well Kim Il Sung, was he alive when you left?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he a failing force?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No. It was recognized. I mean I have told you what the Chinese ambassador
                    told me about his mind set. Billy Graham had gone to North Korea on two
                    occasions, and Kim Il Sung had said, “You know, I really want to make friends
                    with the United States.” That didn't seem to have much impact. But the power
                    shortages in the North were becoming very noticeable because there is no longer
                    concessional aid form the Soviet Union, and the weakness of the economy was
                    noticeable. The trains in the north ran very slowly because the electric power
                    was so weak. There was a general recognition that the North's economy was
                    imploding. That it was already reports of food shortages; that the feeling was
                    the North really needed to change the way it was doing, changing its economic
                    approach. But that was headed off by the reinstitution of Team Spirit, a sort of
                    a reinforcing of exercise that the North Koreans hated. It brought thousands of
                    U.S. troops in from abroad, and it was sort of a symbolic demonstration of our
                    willingness to come to the aid of South Korea if there was a North Korean
                    invasion. The North Korean alert level was always way up when we did that. I
                    canceled it for one year, and that paved the way for a lot more talks. But it
                    was reinstated without my knowledge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well you say it was re-started without your knowledge,
                        while you were still ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes, the decision was made in the fall of 1992.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this sort of you know, business as usual in the
                        Pentagon, or was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>GREGG: I think it was business as usual in the Pentagon. It was also some hard
                    line South Korean generals who sort of saw Team Spirit as sort of a reassertion
                    of the security blanket. They were very suspicious of talks with the North.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well you left there when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: In the end of February '93.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you left, how were things at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Kim Yung Son had just been sworn in. He was talking about Seigewa,
                    globalization. That was his big thing. He was talking about more economic
                    development. I thought things were good. I think I probably had as easy a time
                    as any ambassador in the post war period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had the computer Internet revolution sort of hit Korea? I
                        think it would be a natural for it later on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No it hadn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well you got involved in Korea again afterwards didn't
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes. I still am. I had talked to the Koreans about the fact that they
                    never had an organization in the United States really dedicated to all facets of
                    the U.S.-Korean relationship. They had tried to do it through Tongsun Pak, which
                    had failed. This had caused them really to draw back. They established something
                    called the Korea Foundation which is going around endowing chairs and various
                    universities. I said, “You need to have somebody in the United States, somebody
                    with some stature who really develops an organization devoted to the
                    Korean-American relationship.” At that point I thought that George Herbert
                    Walker Bush was going to be re-elected. I had some hopes of going to be
                    ambassador to Japan. He lost, and that brought my government career to a halt.
                    So I was offered the job as chairman of the Korean Society, and having said what
                    I said to the South Koreans, I could hardly turn it down. So it turned out to be
                    a very stimulating difficult job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is difficult about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>GREGG: The non-profit world is much more competitive and cut throat than I
                    thought it would be. I have been sued by an African-American employee whom I
                    dismissed for non performance. He is in California. I have dealt with
                    corruption, embezzlement. Managing a Korean organization is in a way like
                    herding cats. But when I took the organization over, it had a net worth of less
                    than $200,000. We now have an endowment of $8.5 million. We have enlarged our
                    office space three or four times. We have a very active program involving
                    business development, involving cultural exchanges, involving political
                    discussions. I continue to enjoy it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the, you have been involved in some business
                        with North Korea haven't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would you like to say about those?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well, Kim Dae Jung had a completely different attitude toward North Korea
                    than Kim Yung San. I invited, I helped pay for the visit of two North Koreans to
                    New York in '95 or '96, something like that. Kim Yung San people never forgave
                    me for that. I was encouraging subversion in their view which is ridiculous. But
                    Kim Dae Jung said to me, “Please try to plant the flag of the Korea Society in
                    North Korea.” So I began to pursue the North Koreans in New York. They have a
                    mission there at the UN. I invited the ambassador out to my home with some of
                    his staff. Introduced them to American businessmen who had an interest in
                    perhaps investing in North Korea. We were approached by Syracuse University who
                    had an IT training program with the former Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: IT?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Information technology. They said, “Do you think the North Koreans would
                    be interested?” I said, “Yes, I think they would.” So we funded an exchange
                    program between Syracuse University and Kim Chaek University of Technology in
                    Pyongyang, which is going very well. The Clinton administration was very open to
                    me. They invited me down to try to assess the Jimmy Carter visit, because they
                    didn't really know what to make of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Jimmy Carter visit being what?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>GREGG: Well he went to see Kim Il Sung in 1994 at a point where we were about to
                    pull out of our [inaudible]. People we were getting ready to re-enforce. The
                    North Koreans said, “We will turn Seoul into a sea of fire.” They pulled out of
                    the non- proliferation treaty. I think next to the Cuban missile crisis, this
                    was the second most dangerous moment in the post cold war era. Jim Laney who had
                    been the former president of Emory University, and very close to Jimmy Carter,
                    knew that Carter had a standing invitation to go to North Korea. Laney got hold
                    of Carter and said, “I think you ought to go.” Carter said, “Well I am not sure
                    how the White House would feel about it.” Warren Christopher was dead set
                    against it, Secretary of State, feeling that that usurped his rule. But Gore was
                    for it, and so Carter was given permission to go. He went to see Kim Il Sung.
                    Kim Il Sung said to him what he said to Billy Graham. I want to be friends with
                    the United States. If you are concerned about my nuclear program, I will turn it
                    down as long as you build some replacement power generating things and give me
                    oil in the interim for the power that I lose for shutting down my nuclear
                    reactor. That was the genesis of the 1994 agreement. They called me to the White
                    House when Carter was still on his trip and said, “What do you make of it?” Bill
                    Clinton was there. I said, “All I can say is Carter had a man there with him,”
                    Dick Christiansen again, who had helped me on the trade negotiations, “who is
                    absolutely fluent in Korean. So there is absolutely no doubt about what was said
                    by both sides, so that you will have a clear record of what was said if you want
                    to look at it.” It isn't like Gerry Ford going to Poland with a poor quality
                    interpreter and not knowing what was said.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “I lust after Poland,” or something like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Something like that. So that worked. That led to the agreed framework
                    established in 1994 where we with funding from South Korea and Japan were going
                    to build two light water reactors in North Korea. That then, the relationship
                    with the North wasn't going very well. I was part of a Council On Foreign
                    Relations task force that recommended a senior person be put in charge of the
                    relationship with North Korea. Again we had to wrestle the State Department to
                    the ground. The assistant secretary felt he was doing a perfectly fine job. He
                    wasn't doing a good job at all.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>The former secretary of defense Bill Perry was appointed. He went to North Korea,
                    and the issue was not only nuclear, but missiles. They had fired a multi stage
                    rocket in 1998 that really rattled the Japanese cage. It was much more
                    sophisticated than we thought they were capable of. So he went to the North and
                    worked very closely in putting out a report saying what the North Koreans could
                    expect from us if they stopped firing missiles and shut down their nuclear
                    program or maintain their nuclear program. So the demarche from Perry was
                    considered by the North Koreans, finally accepted. They sent their Field
                    Marshall Jo, Myung Yok, to Washington in October of 2000. He went to the White
                    House in uniform, invited Bill Clinton to go to North Korea. He was given a
                    dinner by Al Gore. The State Department sent Madeleine Albright to North Korea
                    to check out the feasibility of a visit. In December of 2000, after the
                    election, I was approached by the woman in charge of North Korean affairs for
                    the State Department saying, “Do you think Bill Clinton should go to North
                    Korea.” That was Wendy Sherman. It was one on one. I said, “Well do you have a
                    missile deal?” She said, “No, we cannot get the answer to two or three key
                    questions.” I said, “What are they?” She told me. I said, “Well I think what is
                    happening is Kim Jong Il has the answers to these questions. If Clinton goes, he
                    will get those answers, and he will be given a present for having gone.” So she
                    said, “Do you think we should go on that basis?” I said, “That is way above my
                    pay grade. That is a decision only the President should make.”</p>
                <p>I think with the controversy about Florida and time ran out. But the North
                    Koreans knew that he had come very close. Madeleine Albright, I have spoken with
                    her at the University of Michigan. She is very entertaining on the subject. She
                    said, “You know Kim Jong Il and I are about the same height. We both wear high
                    heels and we both put mousse in our hair. But he is very intelligent. I had
                    eleven hours of discussion with him, and we left a very good hand of cards on
                    the table which the Bush administration has failed to pick up.” So when Kim Dae
                    Jung came to the United States pushing for an early meeting with Bush. It didn't
                    go at all well because Bush said, “I don't trust Kim Jong Il. We are going to
                    have a policy review before we do anything.” He had referred to him as a pygmy,
                    also we should have gotten out. So the policy review was held, and it
                    revalidated the Kim Dae Jung sunshine policy, but it changed the agenda. Kim Dae
                    Jung had structured his sunshine policy around the things that were the easiest
                    to do first, leaving the hardest things for last.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sort of confidence building.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>GREGG: That's right, and the Bush people moved the tough things right up to the
                    front, which is troop disposition along the DMZ and so forth. So they laid out
                    the basis on which they would resume contacting the North, and the North didn't
                    respond, and then came 9-11. So then the North Koreans approached me in the fall
                    of 2001 saying we are getting nowhere with the Bush administration. Why don't
                    you come to North Korea and talk to us. I said, “I can't really anoint myself to
                    do that. Why don't we figure out something better than that.” So we agree to
                    four former ambassadors were going to go, under the leadership of Bob Scalapino,
                    an renowned orientalist from (University of California) Cal Berkeley who had
                    been to North Korea before. It was going to be Jim Laney, Bill Gleysteen?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jim Lilley?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No I don't think it was going to be Jim Lilley.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dixie Walker?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: No. Yes, Dixie Walker. So then we were planning to go in February of 2002,
                    and then came Bush's State of the Union speech in which he made North Korea part
                    of the axis of evil. That trip went down the drain. So I went to a conference in
                    the UK on the future of Japan. This was at a place, not Ditchley, but a similar
                    conference center run in part by the British Commonwealth office. Very good
                    conferences. There were a number of Europeans there.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>I was appalled at their attitude toward 9-11. Not the Brits, but the French, the
                    Dutch, the Swedes, the Swiss, and their attitude was well now you know what we
                    have been dealing with in terms of Bader Meinhof and the Red Brigade. You know,
                    what is the big deal. Don't over react. What is so special about you. For them
                    to lack any understanding of the impact of 9-11 on the United States, I thought
                    my gosh, if these people don't understand where we are, there is no way in the
                    world the North Koreans can know. So I felt motivated to write Kim Jong Il a
                    letter saying that your weapons, missiles and nuclear matters have become of
                    huge concern to us because we have been attacked by people who would love to get
                    their hands on the kinds of things you possess, and use them against us. That is
                    why we are so concerned, and we really need to talk about this. It was about a
                    three-page letter. I took it to one of the, a man named Lee Good who was the
                    ambassador, the number two ambassador to the UN. He said to me, “How dare you
                    write a letter like this to my chairman. Who do you think you are. Very Korean
                    reaction.” I said, “I am writing this letter to him because I think I understand
                    how his mind works, and he needs to know this.” He said, “How do you know how
                    his mind works?” I said, “Well I have talked to George Toloroya who sat with him
                    for several days on a train when he went to see Putin and had a long talk with
                    him. I talked with Chinese who were with him when he visited a Buick plant in
                    Beijing or in Shanghai. This is the kind of thing we have to do in North Korea.
                    I have talked to Kim Dae Jung at great length about his visit with him, and I
                    have talked to Madeleine Albright about her visit. They all add up to a very
                    intelligent man who is trying to lead North Korea in some new directions.” He
                    said, “That is a good answer. I will send your letter.”</p>
                <p>So two weeks later I was invited to go. I had not asked permission. I had kept
                    Rich Armitage informed, He is deputy secretary of state, an old friend. He sent
                    me a perfect little note saying Don, thanks for your note. Keep me informed as
                    you desire, blah, blah, Rich. Perfect. The State Department said, “Would you
                    like to have a Korean speaking Foreign Service officer go along with you.” I
                    said, “I'd be delighted.” So they sent a young woman who spoke fluent Korean,
                    and so in we went.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>In April of 2002 I had about 10 hours of discussion with Kim Le Gwan who was the
                    leader of the North Korean delegation to the recently completed Beijing talks,
                    and a very hard line general named Ree Chan Dok. My meeting with him is very
                    reminiscent of my meetings in Kwangju.. It started out with the same bristling
                    animosity, and ended up two hours later with saying exactly what they had said,
                    “You have come a long way, and I appreciate your coming.” We would up
                    understanding each other. He started out with me saying, “Why are you here? You
                    speak first.” I said, “Well, General, I am here because I think you need to know
                    what our frame of mind is. Yesterday I was taken up your Juche Tower,” which is
                    a tower about the height of the Washington Monument. “It is very impressive. How
                    would you feel if you were looking out your window and saw one of your own
                    aircraft fly into that monument reducing it to a pile of rubble and killing
                    everybody on the plane. We say that twice in New York and once in Washington.
                    How would you feel?” I just looked at him. He said, “I think you have lost sight
                    of the fact that the real fighting spirit is in the heart of every soldier.” I
                    said, “I know that. The last thing we ever want is another war with you in
                    Korea.” He said, “It would be a disaster for you.” I said, “Well look what we
                    are accomplishing in Afghanistan without a single heavy artillery piece or heavy
                    tank.” He didn't like that. But we went on from there and you know, talked very
                    frankly. As I say at the end of two hours we had developed a good deal of
                    respect for each other.</p>
                <p>I came back from that trip and wrote something that I sent to the White House
                    recommending that somebody like Bill Perry be sent to North Korea. Well it was
                    interesting. They said, Kim De Wan said, “Why is your George W. Bush so
                    different from his father?” I said, “Well he is a Texan, and his father is a New
                    Englander.” “Why is W so different from Clinton?” I said, “Well you know in a
                    democracy that happens. You have continuity of leadership, so you don't have to
                    deal with that. Whereas sometimes there is a real turn. I watched one at close
                    range from Carter to Reagan. Clinton to Bush is the same kind of thing.” “So why
                    don't you understand us better?” I said, “Well, I think because you are the
                    longest running failure in the history of American espionage.” I said, “We
                    couldn't recruit you people. We could recruit Soviets; we could recruit
                    Chinese.” He sort of swelled with pride. Then this was funny. He said, “Are you
                    wearing your Ops Center hat when you are saying that?” I said, “What?” He said,
                    “You heard me. Are you wearing your Ops Center hat?” I said, “Are you referring
                    to a very bad book by Tom Clancy?' He said, “Yes, of course.” This is what my
                    wife calls an airport only paperback written by Clancy and another guy named
                    Steve Pieczenik called Op-Center. The leading character is called Gregory
                    Dowell. He is former chief of station in Seoul and later ambassador. So it is
                    clearly based on me. So I said, “Well I haven't read the book. My wife has.
                    Would you like her reaction?” “Yes.” I said, “Well, she doesn't mind that I die
                    an honorable death at the end of the book, but she hates the fact that I had a
                    Korean mistress.” That broke him all up. But I tell you that because it shows
                    the sophistication of these people and the depth of their knowledge about
                    us.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>So anyway I suggested that there was great mystification as to why one president
                    was so different from another. They realized they had almost had Jimmy Carter as
                    a guest and now they were dealing with a man who referred to them as part of the
                    axis of evil among other things. I said that you could recapture everything that
                    Clinton had by sending somebody with a letter to the North Koreans. They are
                    very anxious for a better relationship. You know, absolutely no response, no
                    acknowledgment to that or anything else I sent to the White House on the
                    subject.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well do you sense that on this subject that there is a
                        guiding hand? I mean you have national security advisor Condoleezza Rice,
                        you have Colin Powell in the State Department, both of whom seem to be
                        sophisticated and have been around the block and understand. Is it that this
                        is political or visceral? What is happening do you think?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well I think what is happening is that the philosophy of the Bush
                    administration was shaped by a group of people who called themselves, before the
                    election, they called themselves the Vulcans. That is named for the big statue
                    of the god of fire that is on a ridge above Birmingham where Condi Rice grew up.
                    The Vulcans consisted of Richard Perle, Paul Wolfowitz, Bill Kristol, Scooter
                    Libby, Cheney, Rumsfeld, and Rice. They were intellectual descendants,
                    particularly Wolfowitz, of the Wohlstetter at the University of Chicago, who
                    felt that we should have been much more preemptive against the Japanese before
                    Pearl Harbor. It is also influenced by another professor, whose name escapes me,
                    who felt that Athens should have been more pre-emptive against Sparta. So this
                    is the doctrine that they sold to Bush, that to maintain our role as the world's
                    only superpower, we need to be unilateral if need be. We need to go into
                    pre-emptive action, and we need to engage in regime change. I think those are
                    the touchstones and 9-11 seemed to validate it.</p>
                <p>There is the President has said you are either with us or against us, and he sees
                    North Korea as evil. Wolfowitz recently, in referring to Saddam Hussein, he
                    said, “Saddam Hussein was in the same category as Hitler, Stalin, and Kim Jong
                    Il. Sooner or later those people are not just content to bring evil down upon
                    their own people. It spills over their borders and they have to be dealt with.”
                    Now the president has distanced himself from that kind of rhetoric. He says he
                    is committed to a diplomatic solution. I heard Secretary Powell give a wonderful
                    speech yesterday after flying down here. He was talking about democracy in Asia
                    and the development of democracy in Asia. He was highly enthused about that. I
                    am very thankful that he has stayed as Secretary of State. I think he gives us
                    some credibility and some substance that would otherwise be lacking. I think he
                    has a very hard row to hoe, but I think he has been given more leeway on Korea.
                    Wolfowitz said in my presence last October, “The State Department is now in the
                    lead on Korea.” That had not been the case in the past. But you still have
                    people like John Bolton who is undersecretary for proliferation who is out
                    there. He is as unpopular in South Korea as he is in North Korea, talking about
                    coercion and sanctions.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The North Koreans have said they won't talk to him
                        again.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Right. I don't think they have ever talked to him. They denounced him in
                    no uncertain terms.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right now we are going through a period where the North
                        Koreans are sort of challenging us by going ahead with nuclear developments.
                        Is this, how do we read this? What are they doing? What are they after?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: They are after a changed policy on our part. They are truly concerned
                    about our military intentions toward them. I went to a Track II, six-party
                    meeting in Qingdao last September, hosted by the Chinese. Some of them had been
                    to the previous official six-party talks in Beijing just less then two weeks
                    before. The same ground was covered. The leading Chinese figure there was a
                    woman named Fouying, a very accomplished diplomat. She said, “We all agree,
                    including North Korea, that we want to have a nuclear free Korean Peninsula. We
                    all agree, including North Korea, that where we want to end up is a verifiably
                    nuclear free Korean Peninsula where North Korea's security and economic concerns
                    are adequately dealt with. The problem is we don't know how to get from position
                    A to position B, and that is still the problem because the Bush administration
                    says we will not submit to blackmail. We will not reward that behavior, and the
                    new mantra is CVID, completely verifiably, irreversible dismantlement of all
                    nuclear programs.” They want Korea to do what Qaddafi had done. I saw Kelly
                    briefly yesterday, and Colin Powell had said that some progress had been made in
                    Beijing, but it is going to be a long slow process because we and the North
                    Koreans are staring at each other across a chasm of mistrust. In the meantime
                    the U.S.- South Korean relationship is in the worst shape I think it has perhaps
                    ever been. Because the alliance which has been geared to joint opposition to
                    North Korea as the implacable foe, in the wake of the summit of 2000, no longer
                    works because the South Koreans now see the North Korean, these are the younger
                    people at least, as perhaps a long lost brother who has acquired some bad habits
                    and needs rehabilitation and tender loving care rather than punishment. The
                    older Koreans are still very suspicious of North Korea, but the younger Koreans
                    are very accepting of the North. They think the North would never use nuclear
                    weapons against them. They see the United States, many of them see the United
                    States as a greater threat to their ongoing security than North Korea. The
                    relationship is in very difficult shape.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well you know the great concern is that the North Koreans
                        being hard pressed for money, that there could be leakage of nuclear weapons
                        to a terrorist. That would put the?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>GREGG: Absolutely. That is a red line, and I have written the North Koreans. I am
                    in touch with them, and I wrote them when there was a statement hinting that
                    that might happen. When I went there the first time, I said that it is just
                    imperative that you completely distance yourselves from any form of terrorism.
                    They said, “We have already signed two UN measures against terrorism.”</p>
                <p>So I agreed that could happen and that is our concern. I don't think they had any
                    intention of doing that. The sort of nuclear bazaar that has been run out of
                    Pakistan has been of deep concern on that score.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The North Koreans were at one point you know, selling
                        drugs. Their embassies were selling drugs to maintain themselves. I mean how
                        dire would you say their straits are?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well I think it is somewhat, I have talked at length to people who have
                    been up there delivering food and medicine and so forth. They have allowed
                    market gardens to be cultivated for the profit of the owners. That has improved
                    the food situation to some extent. They had a somewhat better rice crop than
                    last year, but they have cut down all their trees. They have lousy fertilizer,
                    primitive agricultural technique. They are very vulnerable to fluctuation s of
                    temperature and rainfall, and so they have a food, they have had a food
                    shortage, and there has been starvation. It is still bad, but it is somewhat
                    better than it was. There is still a great power shortage. But even in my two
                    trips to Pyongyang in April and November of 2002, I saw improvement in Pyongyang
                    in those six months in terms of food stalls in the streets, more cars, so forth.
                    Now Pyongyang is much better than the worst provinces up along the Chinese
                    border are still in very bad shape.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Japanese factor recently, has that been?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well, I was at another conference in Japan just before Koizumi went to
                    Pyongyang, and we had at this conference, some Chinese who were very
                    knowledgeable of the North Koreans having spent years in Pyongyang. The major
                    concerns on the part of the Japanese were those abductees. The Chinese said,
                    “Oh, they will never admit this.” Well Kim Jong Il did admit it. He apparently
                    thought that that would somehow put the issue behind them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were Japanese citizens?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>GREGG: These were Japanese citizens who were kidnapped by the North Koreans so
                    that they could use them as models top train agents to act like Japanese. Maybe
                    30 were kidnapped. They allowed some to return to Japan. The Japanese have not
                    returned them. The issue has bubbled up. It has backfired, and the North Koreans
                    are furious at the Japanese and make the point that the Japanese never speak of
                    the tens of thousands of young Korean women they kidnapped and forced to be
                    comfort women for the imperial army. So the, you know the thinking is at some
                    point the Japanese will pay reparations to North Korea. Sort of that money that
                    would be in the billions would help kick start the economy. North Korea, I felt
                    quite comfortable there because I was dealing with Koreans, and I understand the
                    Koreans. It is a terrible regime. It is a repressive regime. It is a brutal
                    regime. The question is how do you get them to stop being repressive and brutal.
                    My suggested solution is to let them develop economically, improve the living
                    standard of their own people, give Kim Jong Il a real chance to survive. I
                    suggested that his role model ought to be Fidel Castro who has presided over a
                    decrepit society but still maintains some degree of respect at home. How he does
                    it I don't know. The South Koreans hope he will be a Deng Xiaoping, a real
                    reformer. I am not sure he is capable of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is somebody talking to Kim Jong Il? I mean you were
                        mentioning Park Chung Hee, you know, who brought him bad news? Do you feel
                        that there is contact with him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Well, yes. Putin refers to him as a completely modern person. They
                    apparently get along quite well. He has got some good give and take relations
                    with the Chinese. He has met a number of South Koreans including Kim de Jong.
                    Everybody I have talked to who has talked to him directly says he is a highly
                    intelligent man. For example, he reads the daily press out of Korea on the web
                    site every day. He goes to the web site of the Blue House.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is the White House of South Korea.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Yes. He complimented the minister of unification under Kim De Jung saying,
                    “You know, I really am very interested in your write up of Park Chung Hee,
                    because I want to do some of the same things for North Korea that Park Chung Hee
                    did for South Korea in terms of jump starting the economy. So I think he has a
                    recalcitrant military that he has trouble dealing with. I think he has a small
                    coterie of people around him who are fairly enlightened.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, Don, I think this is a good place to stop.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GREGG: Okay.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
