<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000013">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Donald M. Anderson </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>DONALD M. ANDERSON</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: July 8, 1992</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is July 8th, 1992. This is an interview with Donald
                        M. Anderson. We're doing this on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic
                        Studies, and I am Charles Stuart Kennedy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I wonder if you could give me a bit about your background, where you came from,
                    where educated?</p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I was born in Sioux City, Iowa and went through the public school
                    system there, through high school, went to Louisiana State University for
                    undergraduate school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you majoring in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I majored in government, and at that time LSU had a small, but I
                    thought a very good government department. I ended up getting a fellowship and
                    spending an extra year working on a master's degree. When I went into the
                    Army...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went in when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: That was 1955. I had gotten a ROTC commission, and I was called to
                    active duty so I spent the next two years in the Army, first in El Paso, Texas,
                    and then outside of Providence, Rhode Island in a surface to air missile unit.
                    While I was in the Army, I guess it must have been 1956 or '57, I took the
                    Foreign Service exam, and passed it and was supposed to go into the Foreign
                    Service immediately upon leaving the military. As usual, the State Department,
                    when the time came, had had a budget cut and there was a hiring freeze so I
                    waited for about six months and ended up actually coming on board in the Foreign
                    Service in April of 1958.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you with a class at that time, a basic officer's
                        class?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes. There were 25 in the basic officer's class.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because these things change, what was the outlook? Was
                        this going to be a career, or something to try on for size, would you say,
                        for this group?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Within the group there was a great variety. For me, I think I always
                    did consider it a career. In fact, when I was in high school in Sioux City, Iowa
                    I was thinking about the Foreign Service. I barely knew what it was but it was
                    something I wanted to do, and I must say I was discouraged by my teachers in
                    high school who told me that only people who went to the Ivy League schools
                    could aspire to a career in the Foreign Service. I think for others it was very
                    much a trial. My recollection is that of the 25 who joined in our basic class,
                    within two or three years at least 40% had dropped out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because these things are changing rapidly, I addressed the
                        last junior officer class of 32 and 16 of them, 50%, were women.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: When I joined, there was one woman, and I think by today's standards we
                    were generally a younger group of people. In fact, I think that at the time I
                    joined you couldn't be over 31 because then you didn't make it into whatever it
                    was you had to do. One of the 25 was very near the edge of being too old to be
                    hired. But the rest of us were mostly anywhere from 22 to 26 or 27.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your first job was in the State Department for two years.
                        What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I came into the Foreign Service in the wake of the Wriston program,
                    after the Wriston Report integrated the State Department civil service and the
                    Foreign Service. The State Department hiring rate was up, and basically I think
                    they were looking for jobs for people. People were not going overseas
                    immediately on their first assignment. It was more normal to be assigned in
                    Washington, and I was assigned to the International Education Service—IES as it
                    was known, which was the forerunner of the Bureau of Cultural Affairs, which
                    then got spun off to USIA. I was staff assistant to a division chief and we
                    handled all of the senior academic exchanges, the Fulbright Program, and Smith
                    Nundt. These were professorial exchanges, high school teachers and research
                    scholars.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were these from? All over or...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: All over.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Soviet Union too, or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, I don't think there was any Soviet program at all at that
                    point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression within the State Department of
                        this exchange program? Was it a good thing? Was it working? Were there
                        problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Oh, I think it was an excellent program. Its now administered out of
                    USIA where it probably should have been to begin with. For someone who had gone
                    into the Foreign Service, dreaming of being a diplomat, it was not exactly what
                    I had envisioned as my first job, but it was true of a lot of people at that
                    time. They were in a way creating jobs that probably weren't necessary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the Chinese connection which, of course, ran
                        through your entire career but how did this start? Coming from Sioux
                        City...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I've been asked that many, many times. About the only answer I can
                    think of is that when I was in the third grade, I believe, my third grade school
                    teacher was a former Chinese missionary. She used to read us stories about
                    China, and take us over to her house and show us all of the things that she had
                    brought back from China. Then when I was at LSU obviously there wasn't much of a
                    China program, but they did have a course in Chinese political history, and I
                    took that. And in my graduate year at LSU I started working on a master's thesis
                    on the 1945-47 period of U.S.-China relations, the Marshall Mission, etc. So I
                    had an interest in China, and the April Fool's sheet that you fill out...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the post preference report that came around and
                        due on the first of April, hence the name April Fools Sheet.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: From the very beginning I requested Chinese language training. I
                    remember quite clearly that I got a phone call from Personnel...actually I had
                    been assigned to Munich and was quite pleased with the assignment. I was going
                    to the Consular Section in the Consulate General in Munich. And I got a phone
                    call from Personnel saying that they had noted my application for Chinese
                    language training and that the Chinese program was very overcrowded but they
                    could get me into Cambodian right away. I told them, thank you, but no thank
                    you, and sort of made up my mind that I was going to go on to Munich. It wasn't
                    more than two or three days later that they called back and said that I had
                    indeed been accepted for Chinese language training, which meant another year in
                    Washington which just about broke my wife's heart because at that time we had
                    one daughter two years old, and one daughter six months old, and she was very
                    much looking forward to sailing to Munich. But we did the year in Washington and
                    then went off to Taiwan for the second year of Chinese language training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The school was not in Taipei was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, it was down in Taichung.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was the course conducted there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Well, it was a very informal place. Taichung at that time was, I guess,
                    a city of 500,000 people, but by Chinese standards it was a very small town. It
                    reminded me in terms of size of something akin to Sioux City, Iowa. The school
                    was in a large what had been I imagine a single home. There were about 20- 25
                    students from USIA, CIA, State. That was pretty much it at that time. The
                    classes were basically tutorials. One would have some classes with two or three
                    students in it, but as you progressed into more advanced Chinese it was usually
                    a one on one situation. The latter part of the course was really basically
                    devoted to newspaper reading because reading Chinese is the time consuming part.
                    We gave speeches, and we had lectures, and area studies lectures in Chinese. It
                    was quite a well run program, I think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel that you were absorbing the Nationalist
                        Chinese point of view? Or was it relatively apolitical?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Well, inevitably...being in Taiwan, you were exposed much more to the
                    Nationalist point of view. And most of the teachers had come from Beijing, or
                    from the northeast.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were being taught Mandarin?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: We were taught Mandarin. The dialects vary so much in China that they
                    sought teachers from the Beijing area which was the most standard Chinese. Our
                    teachers were entirely Mainlanders who had fled the Mainland when the communists
                    took over so you did have a rather staunchly anti-communist viewpoint. We did
                    get the People's Daily, and Chinese communist publications because it was
                    necessary to not only learn the standard Chinese characters, that is, the
                    old-fashioned more complex characters which we used in Taiwan, but also you had
                    to learn the simplified characters which the Chinese communists had introduced
                    if you were going to read the Chinese communist press.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that a lot of ideographs had been made up?
                        Sort of communist type words, or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Not the characters themselves, no. That was a pretty straightforward
                    process of simplification based on the logic of the characters. In fact, I think
                    had the Nationalists not lost the war and evacuated to Taiwan, they would have
                    probably introduced a similar expanded simplification system. The language
                    itself, the jargon obviously was influenced by the communists ideology. Like any
                    language it evolves and I did find that when I once became involved with
                    Mainland Chinese, that the language that was spoken on Taiwan—the Mandarin that
                    was spoken on Taiwan—was progressively getting more out of date with what they
                    were using on the Mainland. It was, generally speaking, more formal, not
                    classical. A much more old-fashioned kind of Chinese.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you picking up from your fellow students, and
                        any connections you might have with the embassy about the political
                        situation? We're talking about 1961-'62. The Kennedy administration had come
                        in. Was there a feeling that the Nationalists might actually make a try for
                        the Mainland? Or did we think this was a pipe dream? How did we feel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Well, the period I was in Taichung the first time was really sort of
                    the depths of the results of the Great Leap Forward, there was widespread famine
                    on the Mainland, and the Mainland was really in terrible shape economically. It
                    was probably the one time following Chaing Kai-shek's withdrawal to Taiwan that
                    there was some serious consideration given to the possibility of launching some
                    kind of an attack against the Mainland. I don't think it ever came to anything.
                    I went back for further training in 1965 and one of my teachers at that time was
                    a sort of semi-retired Nationalist general, and he and I used to talk about it.
                    He said that he had been designated in 1962 as the Commander of the Nationalist
                    forces on the Mainland should the invasion take place. Obviously it never
                    did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again, among your group, the recognition of Communist
                        China was a bone of contention that went on from 1948 until really 1977, or
                        something like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: '79.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the feeling there? I was a Foreign Service
                        officer but never dealt with it but the feeling, it's just a political
                        thing, why don't we just get on with it, and recognize them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I think among the group that I was with and certainly my own feeling
                    was that we ought to be moving in that direction. It was not a simple matter of
                    simply switching recognition at that point. It probably would have produced
                    chaos on Taiwan, but a lot of the fiction that we maintained for many, many
                    years really gradually became rather silly. I remember when I went back to the
                    Department—it would have been the mid-'60s— you still really couldn't talk about
                    it. If you used the word “China” without “communist” in front of it, there were
                    people who would question what you were talking about. There was a long time,
                    for example, that you couldn't use the word “Peking”, you had to use the word
                    “Peiping” which was the Nationalist name for the former capital of China. It was
                    a very emotional issue, and the China lobby was still at that time fairly
                    strong. People still remembered what had happened during the McCarthy period,
                    and the whole issue that we lost China, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The China hands, John Stewart Service, and others really
                        suffered from that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I had friends who said, “Why do you want to study Chinese?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again, I'm trying to get back to the time...what was the
                        feeling about a career in Chinese? After all, you had this one not overly
                        significant island where we had posts, and then you had this huge Mainland
                        with many millions of people on it where we had no recognition, and you're
                        starting on a career of this. What was the feeling?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I guess I took the long view. I figured that I had probably another 20
                    or 25 years in the Foreign Service and that things would inevitably change. And
                    then in addition to the view that at sometime we would get to the Mainland, it
                    really wasn't quite as restricted as it might sound, because the embassy in
                    Taipei was quite large. And then we had the Consulate General in Hong Kong which
                    was the premier China watching post for the U.S. Government and was larger than
                    most embassies. At that time there was also a practice of assigning Chinese
                    language officers to a number of our southeast Asian posts because places like
                    Bangkok, for example, had very large overseas Chinese communities, and it was
                    felt that it was desirable to have a Chinese speaking officer to follow that
                    sector of the community. So in terms of career possibilities it was not a bad
                    deal.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Indonesia, Burma...well then you did go to Hong Kong where
                        you served from '62 to '65. What were you doing there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Well, the conventional wisdom when we were finishing up language school
                    was that the career-wise thing to do was to go to Taipei because that would help
                    you solidify and consolidate your language. I decided not to do that, and I
                    tried to get assigned to Hong Kong because I did want to work on the Mainland. I
                    did not want to get locked into being a Taiwan specialist. So I went to Hong
                    Kong first as a consular officer, which is the way everybody went from language
                    school to Hong Kong...in the consular section. I did a year in the American
                    citizen services...actually the passport section, which was a very educational
                    experience because passport fraud in Hong Kong was a major enterprise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you deal with it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It was a fascinating thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you describe how the fraud developed, and how you
                        dealt with it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Basically, the origins of the passport fraud was in the late 19th
                    century, early 20th century. There was a tremendous amount of, not immigration,
                    but travel by people from Guangdong Province just across the border from Hong
                    Kong, to the United States, largely working on the railroads as laborers. This
                    group of people actually came almost entirely from two or three counties, just
                    across the border. And when the San Francisco earthquake occurred, for example,
                    all the birth records were lost, and all one had to do to be certified as a
                    citizen living in San Francisco was to have two people come in and swear that
                    you were born in San Francisco. A lot of Chinese became American citizens that
                    way. Someone did a study once of the population of San Francisco at that time
                    and determined that if every Chinese male in San Francisco had actually been
                    born in San Francisco, knowing the number of Chinese females in San Francisco,
                    that each woman would have had to given birth to 600 children. Their practice
                    was generally to leave the wife back in the village, and go earn enough money
                    that they were prosperous by Chinese standards; then they would come home and
                    maybe spend a year, and then go back and work some more. During that time would
                    sire children. And, of course, the desirable thing to have was boys, because
                    they would then grow up and as soon as they were eligible they would go to the
                    United States and work to continue this process of sending money back to the
                    village. Daughters were an inconvenience, and so what would happen would be that
                    if your brother who had stayed back in China had a son, and you came back and
                    your wife produced a daughter, your brother's son would become your son for
                    immigration purposes.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>They developed an intricate network of fraud and in response the Consulate
                    General in Hong Kong set up a fraud unit which was really quite an elaborate
                    organization. The Chinese traditionally have what is called three generation
                    papers. These are papers on usually red tissue paper, and they have the names of
                    all of the relatives for three generations written on them. These are exchanged
                    at wedding ceremonies. The fraud unit started studying these things, and
                    developed an extensive file and collection of familial relations for these three
                    counties, particularly Toishan county which was the biggest. It reached the
                    point where people would come in...nobody had a birth certificate or any
                    document so you relied on secondary evidence such as photographs taken with a
                    person, work permits, or whatever it was. They would come in and claim to be
                    so-and-so, and the son of so-and-so. We could send the application to the fraud
                    unit, and they would research the names and come back and say, “He is not
                    so-and-so's son. He is his nephew, and this is his father.” We would present
                    this to the applicant and they were usually so stunned that we knew that much,
                    that they would immediately throw up their hands. And then there was blood
                    testing also. Blood testing became quite sophisticated, it wasn't a positive
                    identification, but it was a negative identification. So it was a real job of
                    sleuthing. There was very little legal work or traditional consular passport
                    work. It was trying to figure out the family heritage of somebody.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm sure it gave you a much greater appreciation of the
                        social intricacies of Chinese life too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Indeed. Not perhaps for Chinese life in the big picture, but certainly
                    for southern Guangdong. Cantonese life is frequently quite different than say
                    north or other parts of China. It's very traditional, sort of old-fashioned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about with the language? I've always understood that
                        there's Mandarin and Cantonese, and then a multitude of other dialects. How
                        about Cantonese? Could you get along with it, or were you learning?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No. I must confess that for spoken work in the consular section, my
                    Mandarin was virtually useless. They all spoke Cantonese, and in fact, many of
                    them spoke Toishan which is a dialect of Cantonese. I could read the documents
                    because Chinese is standard all over China. I did not interview people in the
                    language, I used an interpreter. In fact my principal interpreter and assistant
                    knew more about U.S. citizenship law than I ever would.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is so often the case. Then you moved to the political
                        section?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: In those days the political and economic functions were divided
                    differently in the Consulate General because of the peculiar nature of the
                    Consulate. We had a Hong Kong-Macau section, and a Mainland China section, and
                    within each of those two sections we had an economic and political unit. So I
                    was assigned for a time in the commercial section of the Hong Kong- Macau
                    section where one of my major functions was what they called Economic Defense
                    Officer, which was enforcing our embargo on the Mainland. It sort of meant
                    chasing Hong Kong companies around that did business with China, and trying to
                    prevent them from buying American products.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a major effort on our part.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Oh, it was one of the silliest I've ever seen. The Consul General
                    himself got in trouble because he had a love for Chinese export porcelain, and
                    thought that was perfectly acceptable to buy. And we had a Treasury agent in the
                    Consulate who warned him that he was breaking the law. That job only lasted for
                    about six or eight months, and then the State Department contacted me and asked
                    me if I wanted to be the next interpreter for our meetings at the ambassadorial
                    level with the Chinese in Warsaw, Poland. It's something that I had given some
                    thought to because I did fairly well in the basic Chinese language course. I
                    came out of it with an S-4, R-4.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I might for the record say S-4, R-4, is speaking-4,
                        reading- 4, is extremely high in our business. You really have to be born to
                        get the 5-5, which is the highest.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: The job rather appealed to me because at the time the officer who was
                    doing it was posted in London in the political section, and used to fly over
                    from London to Warsaw to do the talks. So I readily agreed that I would like to
                    do it...it involved going back to Taiwan for an additional year of interpreter
                    training, and then on to, I thought, London. And as a result I should add they
                    pulled me out of the commercial section, and put me into the Mainland China
                    political section, reporting on Mainland China's foreign relations. So I did
                    move over to the political section for about the last year and a half that I was
                    in Hong Kong. My stint in the political section in Hong Kong ended up really
                    being devoted in very large part to reporting on the probability of China's
                    entering the Vietnam war. While we were in Hong Kong the Tonkin Gulf incident
                    happened, which produced mass rallies in Beijing and a number of very
                    threatening editorials and speeches about the U.S. aggression against Vietnam.
                    There were a lot of people, particularly back in Washington, who still had very
                    fresh memories of the Chinese entry into the Korean war, and there was serious
                    concern as to what the Chinese were going to do, and, I think basically, how far
                    we could pursue the war in Vietnam without provoking Chinese intervention. I was
                    sitting out in Hong Kong reading everything we could get, and trying to provide
                    an analysis of the probability of a Chinese intervention.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard people say this obvious centuries-long
                        antipathy between the Vietnamese and the Chinese and saying you never could
                        really expect these two to get together.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It was pretty well obscured during the war, though. They were talking
                    about being as close as lips and teeth and all of that stuff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just to get a feel for this. Here you are sitting in Hong
                        Kong reading newspapers, and listening to broadcasts, and this type of
                        thing. How could you get any feel for what's going on? It's a controlled
                        press...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It very definitely was an inexact science. It was almost entirely from
                    content analysis. Looking at the terminology they were using, talking to Chinese
                    about, “What are the implications of this type of language coming from a Chinese
                    source?” Really just gauging whether they were drawing a line and saying, “At
                    this point we will react,” or leaving things fuzzy. It appeared to me quite
                    clear that they were trying to leave things fairly fuzzy. And I pretty well
                    concluded that the United States could bomb, could conduct an aerial warfare
                    against North Vietnam, but if the United States were to cross the 17th parallel,
                    and start driving...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is just above Hui.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes, and start driving toward the Chinese border, then I think we
                    probably would have gone too far.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you went into these analyses, were you using as sort of
                        a test the words that the Chinese were using during 1950 essentially in
                        Korea, and saying, “OK, they were saying this, and we did this...” and using
                        this as the model to look at?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: To the degree we could, but we didn't have that much. Alan Whiting
                    wrote the book on China's entry into the Korean war, but that was later. We
                    really didn't have the ability to do that careful an analysis. We probably
                    should have.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say you talked to Chinese to find out the nuances. Who
                        were the Chinese you'd get the nuances from?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Well, I talked to the Chinese language teachers that we had. We had a
                    Chinese local staff who assisted us with the content analysis, a very bright
                    bunch of people that had an institutional memory of events and pronouncements by
                    the Chinese going back sometimes 15-20 years. In fact, some of the locals that
                    we had at the Consulate back in those days had actually come out of China with
                    us when we left China. So they were a tremendous help. I remember one phrase,
                    xiu xiu pang guan; quite literally it means “stand aside and watch,” and I was
                    trying to figure out whether this was a serious threat or what, and one of the
                    Chinese said, “Well, literally, I think it probably amounts to your saying, 'If
                    you get in a fight, I'll hold your coat.'”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the Consul General at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Marshall Green was Consul General when I arrived. By the time I was in
                    the political section, it was Ed Rice.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were coming out with a sort of a conclusion. This is a
                        very important thing, and there was a lot resting on what the Chinese were
                        going to do, and obviously you were down the line so it wasn't all on you.
                        But still did you feel any pressure as far as how you should call things, or
                        not? What was the atmosphere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, not really. Obviously I was pretty far down the line, and my
                    analyses weren't going out under my signature. It was being vetted by at least
                    two more layers, and sometimes three, and this was only one input into the
                    decision-making in Washington. INR had an input, and CIA had an input to the
                    decision-makers in Washington. But we were looking at it from the Hong Kong
                    perspective, and as I say, largely based on content analysis. I don't know how
                    much impact that had, but obviously the decisions were made to go ahead.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel about, from where you were, about the
                        CIA operations? Were you getting information, and how did that meld in with
                        your activities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: The CIA operation was very important. At that point less so for
                    Vietnam, and for the Vietnam conflict, at least as far as inputs to me. It was
                    important in terms of conditions inside Mainland China. There was a very
                    extensive interview program, and the agency worked very closely with the British
                    who obviously had a much bigger presence and were screening people coming across
                    the border, etc. So it was a very important operation. I remember there were one
                    or two guys that showed up who had just come out of North Vietnam, and we chased
                    them around Hong Kong like they were gold miners, and usually they wouldn't talk
                    to us anyway.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of events in China at the time?
                        The Great Leap Forward had...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It really collapsed, and economic conditions were in terrible shape.
                    This was a period when Hong Kong was just being swamped by refugees coming
                    across the border. I can remember our apartment looked out over the harbor, and
                    then on to the hills of Kowloon. There was a terrible drought during this
                    period, and we got down to water for four hours every fourth day. The brush
                    fires on the hills you could see at night, burning up the hills. The refugees
                    were streaming across the river that separates China from Hong Kong, and the
                    Hong Kong government was having to cope with these thousands of refugees and
                    began a massive housing program. We were very much involved in that as well
                    because some of them did have claims to go to the United States. So it was a
                    very difficult time, and we were focusing largely on the issues of the day. We
                    were also trying to do China watching in the sense of what was happening in
                    Beijing.</p>
                <p>By the time I left to go back to language training in late '65, we were beginning
                    to see some signs that something wasn't right in China, and that there were some
                    new figures beginning to appear. But up until that time the Chinese had been
                    able to maintain a facade of unity. I think people realized rather late that
                    there was a tremendous power struggle going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went back to Taichung from '65 to '66? What was that
                        all about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: That was interpreter training. They had no formal interpreter training
                    program, since they only trained one every four years so I had to sort of make
                    it up myself. I worked with two or three of the senior teachers to design an
                    interpreters' course. We built up a glossary of terms. I would read newspapers
                    and interpret orally what I was reading, and if I saw words that sounded like
                    they might be words that would be useful in the context of the ambassadorial
                    talks in Warsaw I'd pull them out and we worked on a glossary of interpreting
                    terms. Then my wife and I worked on going the other direction from English to
                    Chinese—sort of standard government jargon that one might be confronted with.
                    Then I had my instructors put that into what they would consider proper
                    Chinese.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your wife learning Chinese?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes. At one point about that time she was 2+.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened? I notice you didn't go to London for the
                        Warsaw talks after all this.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: What happened was, the European Bureau in a burst of economy said,
                    “We're sick and tired of funding this position in London for a guy who doesn't
                    do anything for us, and is working for the East Asia Bureau. So unless we can
                    make him more productive, we're cancelling the position.” And the first reaction
                    was to transfer the interpreter to Warsaw itself, where he became chief of the
                    consular section. When they told me that that was what they were going to do, I
                    decided I didn't want to be chief of the consular section in Warsaw. I basically
                    said, “You can take my name out of the running,” and got back a very quick reply
                    saying, “We have been re-thinking the whole thing, and beginning with you we're
                    going to move the position to Washington to the China desk, and that way you can
                    be part of the drafting of the instructions, and the preparations for the
                    talks...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't know what instigated it, but I remember there was
                        a Congressional hearing where all of a sudden someone said...somebody on the
                        Congressional side just to poke at the State Department, made a big fuss
                        about, “What are you keeping a Chinese specialist doing in London?”
                        “Ho-ho-ho,” you know. I don't think the Department of State at that point,
                        whoever was doing it, had a good answer for it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: That's absolutely right. It was one of the poorer showings. I think
                    what he said was, “Well, he uses his Chinese occasionally when he goes to
                    Chinese restaurants.” He was our interpreter. So anyway, I ended up going to
                    Washington, and working on the China desk.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there for four years from '66 to '70. What were
                        you doing? Was this pretty much with the Warsaw talks?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Oh, no. Maybe I should begin at the beginning. I ended up actually
                    doing three jobs in the four years. I started off as the junior officer, the
                    number two officer, in the China Mainland section. The office at that time was
                    called the Office of Asian Communist Affairs, and theoretically covered
                    Communist China, North Vietnam, and North Korea, all the communist countries in
                    Asia. We spent about 98% of our time on China, and 2% on North Vietnam and North
                    Korea. But I was the number two guy for China, in addition to doing the Warsaw
                    talks, which were becoming at that point less and less frequent because China
                    was going into the Cultural Revolution, and they were in total chaos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think you might explain what the Warsaw talks were.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: The Warsaw talks were the ambassadorial level talks between United
                    States and China. It was our point of contact with Communist China that went
                    back to 1955. In the Geneva Conference in 1955 John Foster Dulles and Zhou
                    En-lai agreed to begin these talks in Geneva. They started in Geneva. There were
                    only two agenda items. One was the return of citizens detained by the other
                    side. And the second item was other matters of mutual concern. They resolved the
                    first item, reached an agreement in principal, I would say in about six weeks to
                    two months of discussions in Geneva. And then they began a sort of general
                    dialogue that went on literally from 1955 up through early 1970. The talks went
                    through various periods. There were long periods when they were really pretty
                    sterile, pro forma kind of things, and other periods when there were some real
                    contributions made.</p>
                <p>In 1958 they moved the talks from Geneva to Warsaw. While they were in Geneva the
                    Chinese ambassador representative was Wang Ping-nan, who used to have to come
                    down from Warsaw. Our representative was U. Alexis Johnson, who used to come
                    over from Prague. So they moved the talks to Warsaw, and Wang continued for the
                    Chinese, and Jake Beam did the talks for the U.S. side.</p>
                <p>In addition to that I did Chinese Mainland analysis, and then after a year or so
                    our Hong Kong-Macau officer left, so I became officer in charge of Hong Kong and
                    Macau Affairs for about a year. Then the officer in charge of Mainland China
                    Affairs, the senior position, got promoted to Deputy Director of the Office of
                    Asian Communist Affairs, so he moved me up to his job. I ended up as the officer
                    in charge of Mainland China Affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the Warsaw thing, did you go to any of these
                        talks?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression in the context of the period you
                        were doing it? From '66 to '70.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: As I said, in many ways they were quite sterile. At that point China
                    was in no mood, nor in any position, to entertain very many initiatives, or to
                    take any initiatives. The talks were held in an old Polish palace, a hunting
                    lodge actually of a Polish prince, called Myslevitzy Palace, which was set in a
                    park in a very picturesque setting. The building was thoroughly bugged so we all
                    were conscious of the fact that we were not just talking to each other, but we
                    were also talking to the Poles, and through the Poles to the Soviets. The
                    arrangements for the talks were that each side had four members. There was the
                    ambassador on each side, a political adviser, an interpreter, and a scribe, as
                    he was called—the note taker. We would meet in this meeting room in the palace
                    and we alternated on who spoke first, and each side would deliver a prepared
                    statement running about 15 or 20 minutes. In fact, I used to participate in
                    drafting it, and once it was drafted and approved back in Washington I could sit
                    down with my dictionary and translate it into Chinese. I interpreted from
                    English to Chinese, and their guy interpreted from Chinese to English which is
                    the reverse of normal interpreting situations. And then after the two prepared
                    statements there was sort of a give and take back and forth, oftentimes working
                    from prepared position papers because we pretty well knew what the Chinese were
                    going to say.</p>
                <p>At the conclusion of the meeting—the press almost always came to Warsaw for the
                    meetings, American press, the wire services, etc.—we'd meet briefly with the
                    press, and usually say nothing more than, “We had a useful and productive
                    exchange of views. No further comment.”</p>
                <p>Then the following day, we had an informal arrangement where the political
                    adviser and the interpreter would meet with their counterparts, usually at the
                    Chinese embassy, and we would give them an English text of our opening
                    statement, they would give us a Chinese text of theirs, and if there was any
                    confusion about terminology, or what we meant by something, we would try and
                    straighten it out during this informal meeting.</p>
                <p>I don't know how the Chinese felt about it, but the American side felt it was a
                    useful sort of informal contact where we could talk without the constraints of a
                    formal negotiating session.</p>
                <p>It also turned out to be useful in other ways. At the first meeting I attended in
                    '66, we went over to the Chinese embassy— my predecessor actually did the
                    interpreting, I was there...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the predecessor?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Al Harding. The Chinese gave him a little farewell—they had soft drinks
                    and beer, which Al said normally they didn't do. They normally had tea. But it
                    was rather interesting because we noted that in the meeting room where they
                    received us on the wall over the sofa there had obviously been two portraits,
                    there were two light spots on the wall. When we got there there was one portrait
                    of Mao Zedong in the middle, and it was one of the really first conclusive bits
                    of evidence that Lin Hsiao-chi, the former head of state, had indeed been
                    purged, and was no longer a person. Then as we left the building, on the walls
                    in the halls of the embassy, there were pieces of paper with hand- written
                    slogans which was the beginning of the big character posters of the Cultural
                    Revolution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say a prepared statement, was this just two people
                        talking past each other?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: In large part. In the early days we had a number of concerns that we
                    had to address. One thing we talked about was pilots who were flying against
                    North Vietnam but who strayed and went over into Chinese territory and were
                    lost. We were trying to get an accounting for them. Vietnam was a major factor
                    for meeting all the way up toward the end. But at that first meeting in '66, we
                    did use a phrase which was intended, and I think interpreted by the Chinese, as
                    an assurance that we did not intend to invade North Vietnam and told the Chinese
                    in that meeting that, “we seek no wider war in Vietnam.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This often was a bone of contention saying we should just
                        go in. Was it your feeling, and those with you, that this could really tip
                        things if we landed at Haiphong or something like this. This could bring the
                        Chinese in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes. And that's what we were trying to prevent. On the U.S. side we
                    were trying to promote some sort of informal non-official contact. We were
                    trying to get journalists into China for business, and a variety of what we saw
                    as concrete practical steps that one could take to improve the atmosphere in
                    relations and perhaps lower the tension levels between the two countries. The
                    Chinese were not having any of that. It was a very sterile period. They were
                    primarily berating us on Vietnam. For example, we picked up a Chinese boat that
                    had gotten in trouble in the Tonkin Gulf. It had been in distress and one of our
                    ships picked it up, towed it into port. We gave them food and fixed their ship
                    up, and sent them back. And we mentioned this as something we had done as a
                    humanitarian gesture, and they, of course, denounced us for it.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>During the Cultural Revolution period, most of their people got pulled back to
                    Beijing. This was a period when all of their diplomats were being called back to
                    China to take part in the Cultural Revolution, so that the senior official on
                    the Chinese side was usually a charg� d'affaires, not the ambassador, and their
                    interpreter would come back and forth. As I say, the talks were really pretty
                    dull at that point. The Chinese obviously had instructions that they had to have
                    the last word, so our ambassador would respond to a charge by the Chinese, and
                    the Chinese then felt obliged to answer again. Therefore, the talks sometimes
                    would drag on for three hours or more. I can remember one time the political
                    adviser on the Chinese side, who was really not a political adviser, their
                    interpreter was far and away the more influential and the brightest of any of
                    the group. The charg� turned to the interpreter after the talk had gone on for
                    about two and a half hours, and said, “Can I stop now?” The interpreter said,
                    “No.” So he made another charge about something. So we would usually decide this
                    had gone on long enough, we'd let them have the last word, and then decide on
                    the next meeting.</p>
                <p>But the rather humorous thing about it was, the reporters didn't get anything
                    substantive because we would come out and give them a bland statement. In 1970,
                    toward the end of the talks, we really did make some significant progress. In
                    fact, the two opening statements were sufficiently substantive and significant,
                    and meshed in such a way that neither side felt that they could go beyond that
                    particular point without getting further instructions. So the meeting lasted for
                    about a half an hour, maybe 40 minutes, and the press, of course, interpreted it
                    as indicating that our relations had reached the lowest point ever. But it was
                    finally, a significant and substantive meeting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...looked at each other and said, “What do we do
                        now?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: That's exactly right. So anyway, the talks proceeded through the
                    Cultural Revolution through a very, very difficult period, and then there was a
                    gap of a full year between talks. Basically after Nixon came into office—he had
                    already written an article indicating that he thought the United States should
                    move toward improving relations with China, and there began to be some movement
                    to see what could be done. The Chinese at the same time, I think, were becoming
                    interested in improving relations with us. This was the period of the Brezhnev
                    doctrine and a real concern on the part of the Chinese about what the Soviet
                    intentions were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any feeling that the Chinese...I mean
                        obviously the Polish intelligence service was passing everything on to the
                        Soviets at that time, that the Chinese were using these meetings to stick it
                        to the Russians, or anything like that from time to time, or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Not so much to stick it to the Russians, I don't think, but it was
                    obviously an inhibiting factor. One thing I didn't mention was, well, we haven't
                    gotten to it yet, but when we decided to try and resume the talks in 1970, we
                    decided we would have to discuss the issue of Taiwan, and some of the
                    fundamentals of the relationship, and that we couldn't do that in the Myslevitzy
                    Palace with the Poles and the Russians listening, so we proposed to the Chinese
                    that we change the venue of the talks. We considered several possibilities, one
                    being a third country less under the thumb of the Russians. And the other one
                    that the Chinese finally agreed on was to move the talks to our two embassies.
                    So the meeting that resumed the talks after about a year's hiatus in January of
                    1970 was held in the Chinese embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it sort of the feeling that we were ready and willing
                        to do a lot of things, but was really waiting until the Chinese were ready
                        to make some moves? Was this more or less how things were going? Or were we
                        as disinterested observers say, we were also stalling and not wanting to get
                        anything going?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: We were stalling to a degree, and particularly we were not prepared to
                    do much in terms of recognizing the legitimacy of the Chinese government of the
                    People's Republic of China. What we wanted to do was more, as I said, the
                    concrete practical level of exchanges, and solving problems. They wanted to talk
                    about fundamentals, and that's why we decided toward the end of '69 that if we
                    were to resume the talks we ought to try and address some of these questions. At
                    that point I think Nixon and Kissinger were in favor of that, and we were able
                    to do things for the first time in terms of formulations on political
                    relationships that we couldn't have done under Johnson, and particularly under
                    Dean Rusk.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the feeling this was Dean Rusk who was calling the
                        shots on China policy? Or was this basically the Democrats having been
                        burned on China once weren't going to get themselves caught again?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Dean Rusk played a major role. He had been Assistant Secretary for
                    Asia, he had been in China, he considered himself a China expert. He was very
                    conservative on China issues. It was very difficult to get any flexibility as
                    far as the seventh floor...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The seventh floor being where the Secretary of State
                        dwells.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: And then when the Nixon administration came in and Walter Stoessel, who
                    was then the ambassador in Poland, was instructed to contact the Chinese, and
                    indicate that we would like to resume the talks. Paul Kreisberg was the Office
                    Director. By that time it had become the Office of Chinese Affairs, it was no
                    longer Asian Communist Affairs. We shed North Vietnam and North Korea. Paul
                    Kreisberg was also the political adviser to the talks so he and I worked very
                    closely together on this. We were told to start drafting a new set of
                    instructions for Stoessel for a meeting with the Chinese. As I said, that's
                    where we basically agreed, the two of us who had been working on it, that we
                    should talk about Taiwan and some of the more fundamental issues between the two
                    countries.</p>
                <p>I remember some of the earlier drafts of the instructions that we did. I was
                    quite surprised to find that the feeling was that we hadn't gone far enough.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it a surprise, or not, when the Nixon administration
                        came in...obviously Nixon had earned his name as being one of the most
                        vehement anti-communist early on. Was there a feeling there, “Oh my God,
                        here we're moving farther to the right on this.” How did you feel about
                        this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, there wasn't because while Nixon had made his political reputation,
                    as you say, as a vehement anti-communist, he was also recognized as a very savvy
                    and pragmatic international thinker. He had already announced the so-called
                    Nixon Doctrine of limited U.S. involvement. And he had written in one of the
                    journals saying we had to find a way to improve our relationship with China. So
                    we knew he was inclined in that direction. So there wasn't any worry about the
                    ideological aspect of that particular Nixon anti- communist position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again, the '66 to '70 period, what was our view of the
                        Cultural Revolution? Because I suppose in many ways this was your main
                        preoccupation, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It was. Well, it was very clearly an unmitigated disaster for China. By
                    that time we were getting a lot of intelligence, mostly through Hong Kong, of
                    what was happening in the provinces. There were a number of places in China
                    where it was nothing short of civil war. They were using artillery, and the two
                    factions were engaged in pitched battles. Bodies would come floating into Hong
                    Kong harbor that had been executed. Sometimes multiple bodies all tied together
                    would float into Hong Kong from these factional fights that took place just up
                    in Guangdong province. And, of course, it was a tremendous guessing game as to
                    who was doing what to whom in the upper reaches of the government in Beijing. It
                    was sort of an analyst dream...play the game because so much of the indications
                    of where things were going was done in the press, largely through historical
                    allegories and this kind of stuff. It was great fun to play the game, but it was
                    very, very hard to read.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>We did have very good intelligence on the degree of chaos that was going on in
                    China. I remember Bill Bundy during the '60s—during the height of the Cultural
                    Revolution—set up sort of a Wise Men's Group of some academic scholars. They
                    were the best in the United States...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fairbanks and...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Fairbanks, Bob Scalapino, Barnett. They would come to Washington
                    periodically to discuss “whither China.” One of them finally told me, he said,
                    “You know, we're getting more out of this than you are.” Because we were
                    assiduously collecting everything we could get by way of intelligence from the
                    provinces, and probably knew about as much as anybody, which wasn't certainly
                    enough, but we did have a very good...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did we feel? I mean was this Mao Zedong going off in a
                        rampage? Or was this a breakdown in authority? What was causing this as far
                        as we saw it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: The Cultural Revolution?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I think it was the combination of things. It was a power struggle first
                    and foremost. Mao felt that after the Great Leap Forward had failed certain
                    elements of the leadership— Liu Xiaochi was then head of state, Deng Xiaoping,
                    and a number of others were leading China in a direction of revisionism, or
                    capitalism if you want to put it that way, which they were. They were trying to
                    put the country back together economically from a very dangerous point. And Mao
                    felt he was being shunted aside. He had his own vision of what revolutionary
                    China should be and he decided to mobilize the masses, essentially destroy the
                    system, and then put it back together again. And then obviously there were many
                    people who, for their own purely selfish personal reasons, joined into this
                    struggle for their own personal aggrandizements, or power position, etc.,
                    notably his wife, and the people around her.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Later the Gang of Four. What was our estimate of Mao
                        Zedong? Was he a canny political thing? Or was he sort of a bull elephant in
                        a china shop?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Oh, no. I think Mao was a major political thinker, an ideologue, and a
                    truly great leader. Even despite everything he'd done he's still revered by the
                    people of China. He's probably a leader that should have died about 1951.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which happens so often. Again, and again you run on these
                        people who outlast, outlive their time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: But he brought the revolution to a successful conclusion for the
                    communists, introduced a system which brought a certain amount of hope. There
                    were a lot of excesses, but there was also some hope and a feeling that China
                    was making progress in the early '50s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was beginning to feed itself, and clothe itself, which
                        it had not been able to do under previous regimes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: But really from '57-'58 on, it was just one series of disasters. There
                    was the Hundred Flowers campaign, and then the anti-rightist campaign, and then
                    the Great Leap Forward, then the Cultural Revolution. Basically the Cultural
                    Revolution wasn't really over until Mao died in 1976.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did we view Zhou En-lai? He always seemed to be a very
                        practical person, but yet he survived under Mao. How were we viewing him at
                        this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I think he's a remarkable individual in that...I really can almost
                    literally say, I've yet to find anyone who doesn't admire the guy. He obviously
                    had to be a magnificent opportunist in the sense of knowing where to land, and
                    when to give and when to attack. But he was universally revered. I was in Hong
                    Kong when he died, and in Hong Kong the lines stretched down the street to pay
                    their respects at the memorial service. It was just tremendous, and genuine. I
                    know Chinese today that have fled China, have been persecuted by the Chinese,
                    and who hate the communist system, but one person they can't say anything bad
                    about is Zhou En-lai. It's amazing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we see him...I'm talking about, of course, at that
                        time, as somebody we should keep an eye on because he represented hope? Or
                        did we see him as another one of the boys?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I think he was always recognized as a pragmatist, and someone who, if
                    there was anybody we could do business with, it was probably assumed it would be
                    Zhou En-lai.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for Kissinger? Was he involved? Did
                        you have any contact? Or were you feeling the hand of the National Security
                        Council at this time up until 1970? Nixon came in '69, so it really wasn't
                        much time, but did you have any feel for Kissinger?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Oh, yes. Well, as I say, we had two meetings in Warsaw that were very
                    significant. One was in January of 1970, and the second was in February of 1970.
                    In fact, it was during those two meetings that some of the formulations we put
                    together in terms of describing our views of the relationship between the
                    People's Republic of China, our relationship with Taiwan, and our acceptance of
                    the idea of the unity of China were drafted. Eventually very similar
                    formulations found their way into the Shanghai Communiqu�. So in many ways I
                    feel that Paul Kreisberg, who was the principal drafter in most cases, and
                    myself, made a real contribution to the Shanghai Communiqu� that emerged in
                    February of 1972. In fact, at that point after the February meeting, we were
                    planning to send a delegation to China which would have been headed by a
                    Presidential emissary. I was working on costing it, how we would do it, and what
                    kind of communications we would require. We were planning for a meeting with the
                    Chinese in Warsaw in April, but the President in the interim had decided to go
                    into Cambodia with American forces and...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the spring of 1970. I was in Saigon when they went
                        in so I remember it vividly.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: And the Chinese cancelled the talks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was our planning kept very hush-hush? Or was this just
                        sort of a normal diplomatic progression that you were working on? I mean the
                        idea of costing-out a Presidential delegation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: This was usually done in secret, NODIS. Its all been declassified
                    now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was just trying to get the feel of how we were...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, it was very, very limited. The Chinese cancelled the talks. Paul
                    Kreisberg and I returned to the United States, both of us terribly disillusioned
                    because we thought we were really on the edge of a breakthrough. I decided there
                    wasn't any future in messing around with China for the time being and asked for,
                    and got, an assignment to New Delhi. Paul Kreisberg went off as DCM to Tanzania.
                    Henry Kissinger immediately recommenced the talks with the Chinese in an even
                    more clandestine operation in Paris.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you went to New Delhi where you were for two years,
                        '70 to '72. What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: I was in the external section of the political section. Back in those
                    days...in the bad old days...I think it was Galbraith back in the early '60s
                    decided he needed a China specialist and a Soviet specialist in his political
                    section. So there was a Chinese language officer position in the embassy in
                    Delhi, and I went out as the China specialist, which would have kept me busy
                    about 5% of my time. Actually, my bailiwick, as it turned out, was India's
                    relations with Asia, and the communist world—Soviet-India relations,
                    Indian-Chinese, Vietnam, and Eastern Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This harks back to some time before because you are
                        looking at India. How did we figure...was it '62 the war between China and
                        India where the Chinese gave the Indians a bloody nose for a while and we
                        stepped in and helped with supplies? As a China watcher, but let's say by
                        the time you got to India, what was the feeling? Why did this war take
                        place? It was relatively minor, but it was a little war.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Oh, it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did it take place? And what was behind it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It's a very complex subject, and it's also a very emotional subject. I
                    mean, you could only have one view if you talk to Indians, and you could get in
                    great trouble if you didn't. My own view is that India was basically...it's a
                    very strategic area. It's a very high mountain area, and the British for many
                    years used to probe up into that area. McMahon was up in that area. It's sort of
                    the roof of the world where you are looking down into the other side. And I
                    think the Indians were in a sense carrying on the British tradition of pushing
                    forward into areas for strategic advantage, and the Chinese reacted. The Chinese
                    were much better prepared, and the Indians were really badly prepared. They got
                    a bloody nose and lost some territory— the Aksai Chin. It was quite strategic to
                    China. You have to look at a map, but it connects two parts of China. And they
                    also lost some territory over in the eastern part as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the first place, Kenneth Keating was the ambassador at
                        the time. What was your impression of him, and of the embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Keating was a nice fellow, a good New York...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He'd been senator from New York.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: I would not rate him as a good ambassador. Like many political
                    ambassadors, particularly an ex-Congressman who becomes ambassador, it's a very
                    personal thing, and the relationship is a very personal relationship. But I
                    mean, he didn't do any great harm, and as I say, he was a pleasant individual. I
                    got along with him quite well. The embassy itself was huge, but it's a huge
                    country. I must say, the two years I spent in Delhi were not among the two
                    happiest years in my life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In dealing with the Indians, they in some ways mirror us.
                        They get very moralistic, and preach. Was this a problem as far as dealing
                        with them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes, it was. They are a very prickly people, and have a very strong
                    sense of national dignity. They would get very huffy about what we would often
                    times consider minor things. I found that frequently hard to deal with. I was
                    denounced from the floor of parliament. I was sitting up in the diplomatic
                    gallery at one of their parliament question and answer sessions, and was wearing
                    white pants which is sort of traditional, but it was a very boring day and I was
                    slumped down and the seats were rather small and I'm long-legged, so it appeared
                    that I had my knees on the back of the chair in front of me. And whoever the
                    parliamentarian was that was speaking turned around and pointed at me, and
                    denounced me because the American had no sense of respect for the Indian
                    parliament, etc., etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Caused you to sit up anyway.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I sat up a bit, but I didn't move because I did not have my knees on
                    the back of the chair, and they sent someone around to remonstrate with me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the first place, what was India's relations with the
                        Asian world that you were dealing with? And also, how did you go about and
                        collect information?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It was a very difficult time for American diplomats at that time. The
                    whole Bangladesh thing was developing, and the United States, particularly Henry
                    Kissinger, was tilting very heavily toward Pakistan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The phrase, I don't know where it started, but that we
                        were tilting toward Pakistan.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: The Indians were furious, and when the Indians are furious they can be
                    in their own glorious pompous self. And Indira Gandhi was rising in power, so it
                    was a very abrasive type of relationship. India was neutral but leaning quite
                    heavily toward the north in the Vietnam situation. They had a Consulate General
                    from North Vietnam, and a Consulate General from South Vietnam. The North
                    Vietnamese consulate eventually became an embassy. I used to talk to the South
                    Vietnamese about India's Vietnam policy, and they were trying to involve
                    themselves in some sort of peace process. I used to fool around with the
                    Russians just to try and...I mean they wanted to talk to me because they thought
                    I was a China expert, and I wanted to talk to them just to see what they were
                    doing with the Indians because they were very, very heavily involved. It was
                    interesting, I ascertained who their China specialist was, who, I think a
                    legitimate Soviet Foreign Ministry type who had served in China, but dull as
                    dishwater, and I was very quickly passed off to another, much livelier
                    individual. He was not a China specialist, but he was with the KGB and then with
                    the Indo-Pak war, the Christmas War in December, I also was involved to a degree
                    with Indo- Pakistani relations, and to a degree with Pakistan because curiously
                    the Minister of the Pakistani High Commission was a friend of mine whom I had
                    known in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They kept their missions open, didn't they, during this
                        war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes, they did. But the diplomats were under house arrest. Once or twice
                    we went over and played bridge with the Pakistani Minister in his house. It
                    wasn't a terribly strenuous job. A lot of social life, and a lot of exchanging
                    scuttlebutt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for the, I won't say tensions, but
                        the varying points of view between our embassy in New Delhi, and our embassy
                        in...where was it, in Rawalpindi at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Islamabad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was also a political appointee in Pakistan, wasn't
                        there at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I can't remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get a feel that New Delhi was sending in its
                        thing, and Rawalpindi was sending in its thing to Washington and they're
                        looking at the local, rather than you might say the American interests?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Actually, serving in the embassy in Delhi you began to take on the
                    color of India. Islamabad was writing back to an essentially receptive audience.
                    They were objective in terms of what was happening, and there's no question
                    Pakistan started the war. It was a very difficult time on both sides, and our
                    relations with Pakistan in many respects were strained as well. But basically
                    their support for an independent Bangladesh was viewed favorably...I mean not
                    their support for India, but Bangladesh. Whereas India saw itself as supporting
                    the independence of Bangladesh, and they were taking in literally millions of
                    refugees from Bangladesh and trying to feed them. We did help. We did have C-130
                    flights come in with tents and stuff, but it was getting the Indian perspective
                    on the whole conflict. It was very difficult to get much vibration back to
                    Washington. They didn't want to hear much about India. And, of course at that
                    time, the Indians were saying a lot of very nasty things about us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the very controversial move of putting the
                        nuclear carrier Enterprise into the Bay of Bengal, or something like that?
                        How did that play at our embassy? Were we saying, go away, go away, or
                        something like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes, exactly. The unanimous embassy view in Delhi was it was really
                    dumb.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's a carrier going to do, except to stir up emotions.
                        This was Kissinger, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes, Kissinger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Kissinger wasn't Secretary of State at that time, was
                        he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I think he was still just NSC.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, but very much calling the shots as far as this
                        one.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the Indian Foreign Ministry,
                        and the people there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: The Indian Foreign Ministry is basically quite a good professional
                    corps, and in many of the posts where I have served I've had a good contact, a
                    good friend frequently, among Indian diplomats. They're generally quite
                    professional.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>It's rather interesting...I don't know, maybe this happens to Americans too, but
                    I found that I frequently had very good relations and rather good personal
                    relations with Indian diplomats in third country posts. If I met the same guy
                    back in New Delhi when he was in the Foreign Ministry, he became a pain in the
                    ass.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, we all pick up the coloration of...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: But they're good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for the Indian view of China? Were
                        they still wary? How did they feel, because the Cultural Revolution was in
                        full swing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: The worst part of the violence had pretty well stopped. The Gang of
                    Four was still very much in the saddle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, little red books waving.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: The Indians, I think, view China with a mixture of awe, envy, and
                    contempt. There are some very good China scholars in India, and obviously it's a
                    country that's very poor. So they feel a sense of competition. These are the two
                    huge land masses in Asia, the two great population bases. And I think I
                    mentioned, there's a feeling that China gets treated better than India. That the
                    West, and in particular the United States, doesn't recognize the importance of
                    India and accept India's logical hegemonic position in South Asia, which doesn't
                    make India very popular with its neighbors. The '62 war at that time in '72,
                    still was a very sore point. For example, Taiwan used to launch propaganda
                    balloons from Quemoy and Matsu off the China coast, and the propaganda balloons
                    would sometimes get picked up in the upper air currents and would sail clear
                    across China, and across the Himalayas, and drop in India. Some guy would find
                    one of these propaganda balloons and every time some Indian parliamentarian
                    would get up and give a speech about, “these terrible Chinese are delivering
                    these propaganda balloons to us, and what is the government going to do to stop
                    this?” So it's just a very minor thing.</p>
                <p>In the '62 war all the Chinese restaurants in New Delhi changed their names to
                    Japanese. The first page of the menu would have about five Japanese dishes and
                    the rest of the menu was all Chinese.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just one last thing, and then we can call it for today.
                        You mentioned this fascination, or the Indians felt we gave more attention
                        to China, I talk as a Foreign Service officer serving around, and no
                        particular speciality, but I've always been intrigued by this fascination we
                        have with China, which goes back to really one of our first consuls where we
                        weren't sending consuls to anywhere else, we sent them to China. There has
                        been this fascination about, and great things are going to happen, which
                        have never happened as far as great trade, etc., etc. Did you feel this?
                        That there's a special China interest in the United States which isn't
                        justified by practicality?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I obviously think China is an important place. More important, I think,
                    is an almost unique problem we have with China, and it sort of goes both ways
                    with a similar problem in China. There is this love-hate relationship. When
                    things are going well with China, and China is being good, Americans think China
                    is wonderful. It's all panda bears, and rosy-cheeked kindergarten children, and
                    people going to banquets, and delivering stupid speeches. And then when China
                    does something bad, like Tiananmen, then China can do no right. There is this
                    overwhelming desire on the part of the United States people to somehow punish
                    and correct China, which we're going through right now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This must have been an overlying theme all the time, this
                        reversal back and forth all the time in the United States where we don't
                        really have that much of a problem in relations with other countries.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: That's true.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As a China hand were you aware of this, and thinking, “Oh
                        God, here we go again,” or something like this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Harold Isaacs wrote a book quite a long time ago called “Scratches on
                    the Mind”, where he makes this very clear. We have this problem, partially on
                    the part of Americans because there is this affinity to sort of change China, to
                    make it over into what we think should be the image of China.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had finished your time in New Delhi. You were in Paris
                        from '72 to '73. What were you doing there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I don't know where we finished, but I was in Delhi and got a cable from
                    Washington saying that they wanted me in Paris in two weeks. This was right
                    after the Nixon trip. Actually, the lead-up to the Nixon trip, and the
                    continuing contacts had been conducted in Paris through General Walters...</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Vernon Walters.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: ...who was the Military Attach�, and the Chinese ambassador, and after
                    the Nixon trip the contact in Paris sort of went public and the President
                    announced that this would be the point of contact between the Chinese and
                    ourselves, and that Ambassador Arthur K. Watson would represent the U.S. side.
                    It became rather urgent at the time because Ambassador Watson was flying back to
                    the United States on one of his fairly frequent trips and according to the story
                    that appeared in the press, he got rather intoxicated and by way of apologizing
                    to the stewardesses attempted to stuff $10.00 bills in their blouses which one
                    of the stewardesses duly reported to the press. Of course, the press was all
                    over...the State Department and the White Housasking, “Is this the guy that's
                    going to be handling our contacts?” “Yes, he's going to do it, but we'll have
                    somebody there with him who is a China specialist.” That is why I was suddenly
                    transferred to Paris.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I assume under strict instructions to keep your hands off
                        the stewardesses.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: We got there in May of '72, and as usual in the State Department after
                    turning my family upside down and disrupting their lives, making everybody
                    miserable, we got to Paris and they basically said, “What are you doing here?
                    And we don't really know what to do with you.” Pat Byrne was the Asia officer in
                    the political section and she sort of took me under her wing and took me down to
                    meet the ambassador. I remember that quite vividly because we were walking down
                    the hall and Jack Kubisch, who was the DCM, appeared in the hall on our way down
                    to the ambassador's office, and said in an absolute remarkable way, “Whatever he
                    says, agree.” It was sort of a panicky advice that I should be terribly
                    cautious. I went down and met with the ambassador and he was an absolutely
                    charming man. We had a session, just the two of us, and he said he considered
                    the China contacts one of the most important jobs that he had in Paris, that I
                    was his man for those contacts, and I had access to him anytime I wanted to. If
                    anybody in the front office gave me a bad time just to come right into his
                    office, etc. So I left thinking this was going to be great.</p>
                <p>And then Allen Holmes, who was the Political Counselor, and was very close to the
                    Ambassador—the Ambassador trusted him implicitly, and the Ambassador did not
                    trust most Foreign Service people—spoke to me and said there was a question as
                    to whether I would be Special Assistant to the Ambassador and work directly for
                    him, or whether I would be in the Political Section. And Allen advised me, and I
                    think in many ways saved my hide, that it would be much safer if I were in the
                    Political Section because I would have this buffer between myself and the
                    Ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because at certain points efficiency reports are written,
                        and if you're Special Assistant it depends on the Ambassador. Whereas Holmes
                        being in the Foreign Service among other things...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It was even more serious than that in this case. Anyway, that's the way
                    we worked it out. The job really didn't amount to a great deal. The Ambassador
                    didn't take part in many of the routine things that we did, but I saw the
                    Chinese maybe a couple of times a week, and basically didn't have that much to
                    do otherwise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of things were you dealing with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Largely very routine stuff. At this point there were delegations going
                    back and forth between China and the United States. The Chinese delegations
                    almost all came through Paris. They would usually neglect to get their visas
                    arranged and would come into Paris and would have to have a visa by 8:00 the
                    following morning in order to get to whatever appointment they had in the United
                    States. The first Boeing sale was made, and the Boeing people came through to
                    meet the Chinese who were en route to Seattle and didn't know how to do it, so I
                    took care of that. A lot of that kind of routine stuff.</p>
                <p>The big thing that we were waiting for was two packages, one educational
                    exchanges and the overall umbrella arrangement that we were trying to set up to
                    begin educational and cultural exchanges; and a business package to set up a
                    similar kind of relationship and a structure for beginning business
                    relationships, remembering that at that point we had no representatives in
                    Beijing. We had no diplomatic relations so this was the only way we could do
                    these things in a non-official type relationship. This was the point at which
                    the organization I'm now with, as matter of fact, the U.S.-China Business
                    Council which was then called the National Council for U.S.-China Trade, was
                    designated as the umbrella organization for trade. The National Committee on
                    U.S.-China Relations and the Committee on Scholarly Communications with the
                    People's Republic of China were designated as the educational and cultural
                    umbrella organizations. We were expecting to get these two packages to present
                    to the Chinese, that was probably into around early August and the Ambassador
                    was going home on vacation so I was pushing Washington to get these things. They
                    finally got them out to us, two lengthy cables, and when I came into the embassy
                    that morning the two cables were waiting, and it just happened that the
                    Ambassador was calling on the Chinese Ambassador because he was going on
                    vacation the following day. It was a rather extraordinary meeting because the
                    Ambassador had been out the night before, and was nowhere to be found in the
                    embassy. I spoke to his staff assistant, who was very wise in the ways of the
                    Ambassador, and said, “We've got to wake this guy up, and get him ready. We've
                    got these two things.” He said, “Leave it to me, Don. Don't call the
                    residence.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I take it this was a very ticklish situation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: He was a very volatile individual, he could be absolutely charming at
                    times, but he could fire you on the spot as well. So he went over to the
                    residence, and I got the car and met him over there. He brought the Ambassador
                    down and I handed him the two papers. Each were about, I would say, maybe ten
                    pages long—one on educational exchanges, and one on the commercial relationship.
                    He glanced at them, and tossed them back in my lap and I believe his words were,
                    “This is crap. I'm not going to talk about this penny-ante stuff.” He said,
                    “I'll leave that to you to take care of with your counterparts.” And while we
                    were riding over to the Chinese embassy he said, “What I really want to do today
                    is just talk about global issues, sort of a tour d'horizon,” for which we had no
                    instructions whatsoever. In fact I had been specifically told by the NSC that I
                    was not to do that kind of thing, that this was basically a mail delivery
                    program and I was not to engage in other types of conversation.</p>
                <p>But we did sit down with Ambassador Huang Chen, who was an interesting
                    individual, and Ambassador Watson did indeed proceed to indulge in a tour
                    d'horizon. The most memorable moment of which I remember—this was 1972—he said,
                    “Mr. Ambassador, the one thing that I think both of our countries have to worry
                    about the most is Germany and Japan.” Ambassador Huang, I thought, looked rather
                    surprised at this statement, but we carried it all off, and went back. I wrote a
                    reporting cable which reported mainly what Ambassador Huang said. Ambassador
                    Watson later told me it was the best cable he had seen written in the embassy
                    since he had been there.</p>
                <p>He left very shortly after that and went home, and I am told...I don't know this
                    from my personal experience, that he was met in the United States, and informed
                    that it was time for him to resign. So that was really the last I saw of
                    Ambassador Watson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain a bit about who was Ambassador Watson?
                        What was his background?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: He was one of the sons of Arthur Watson, the founder of IBM. He had
                    been president of IBM International, and as you know, his brother became
                    Ambassador to the Soviet Union and the story was at the time that there was a
                    question of who was going to become chairman of the board, and the senior
                    leadership at IBM did not want Arthur K., so they arranged for him to become
                    ambassador. I was told later that he had told someone in the embassy that he had
                    always considered me to be the State Department spy in this China business, and
                    he considered that I was responsible for his demise as ambassador, which was not
                    true at all because I was very careful about that.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just to get a little feel for somebody looking at this in
                        future times. Maybe you were sort of a mailbox operation there while these
                        other things were happening, but at the same time there still was an
                        official source of communication. Kissinger was head of the NSC at that
                        time. Were you getting instructions, or whatever you want to call them from
                        people in the NSC, “Watch this guy. We don't want him to screw things up,”
                        or anything like that? Were people telling you this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Not really. I was hearing in the embassy, and I think it was generally
                    understood, that this guy was rather volatile, and sort of an unguided missile.
                    But, as I say, the instructions were really that we were a mailbox, and I can
                    remember one instance when Marshall Green came through, he was the Assistant
                    Secretary at the time, and I told him that I was going to try and use these
                    contacts to broaden the discussion. And he said, “That's fine Don.” And the
                    first time I wrote a cable back based on a discussion with my counterpart on his
                    views on Sino- Soviet relations, I got a very fast phone call from Washington
                    saying, “Dr. Kissinger does not want you doing that. Deliver the mail, and
                    that's all.” So I did very little of that.</p>
                <p>My only other job in Paris during that whole period was to fill in for the
                    Vietnam Liaison; actually I did get involved in the Vietnam peace talks which
                    took place at that time, and which involved the Chinese, of course. In fact, we
                    had a meeting with Secretary Rogers who was with the U.S. delegation, and the
                    Chinese representatives at the Paris Peace Conference during that time. There
                    was a period when Jack Kubisch was involved with the talks, then Jack Irwin who
                    was the next ambassador to come out. By that time Henry Kissinger had
                    gone...this would be November of '72, Henry Kissinger had gone to Beijing again,
                    and they had announced that they were going to open a Liaison Office in Beijing,
                    which I think was a very neat diplomatic stroke. They basically had an embassy,
                    without calling it an embassy, and managed to finesse many of the issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Particularly the two Chinas problem which was Formosa
                        and...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I'm convinced that the Chinese, and I think probably Henry Kissinger,
                    reached agreement on the establishment of the Liaison Office with the
                    understanding that this was the first step toward diplomatic relations and the
                    establishment of a full- fledged embassy. I think probably the Chinese expected
                    it to happen, and they expected it to happen much more quickly. In fact, it took
                    from '73 all the way to December '79 when Carter finally announced establishment
                    of diplomatic relations. I think that was a much longer period, but it was due
                    in large part to, on the one hand the Chinese side which was going through a
                    succession struggle with Mao and the Gang of Four; and on our side we had
                    Watergate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was forcing Nixon out of office.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: So what happened was, basically I knew from November of '72 that my job
                    in Paris was going to come to an end because we would be setting up the Liaison
                    Office. Then I was informed by Washington that I would be going from Paris to
                    Beijing. I went on a direct transfer from Paris to Beijing in May of '73, so I
                    was in Paris literally one year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Back to the peace talks. What were your perspective of
                        those peace talks at that particular place and time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I was not involved at the high policy level. My job was basically
                    liaison with the Chinese. We kept the Chinese very well informed on positions
                    that we were taking. Again, I was something of a mail man. I was the guy that
                    Bill Sullivan would send out to the Chinese embassy at night to deliver papers
                    and messages, and talk to the Chinese about what our positions were going to be.
                    I think basically the Paris peace talks were a means for the United States to
                    exit Vietnam. I mean it's a very controversial agreement, but at the time I
                    think, viewed with a great deal of relief by most of the people that were
                    involved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for the Chinese role? Were they sort
                        of passive by-standers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: They were cooperative in the sense that they did not make obstacles. In
                    fact, the atmosphere between our two sides was very good. The Chinese ambassador
                    gave a dinner for...it was a Vice Foreign Minister on the Chinese side. We all
                    went out and I can remember that the atmosphere at the dinner, and at a separate
                    meeting that we had at the American ambassador's residence, basically talking
                    about bilateral U.S.- China issues, was very good. I think at that point they
                    felt the U.S.-China relationship was moving rather rapidly in the right
                    direction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the lips and teeth relationship between China
                        and Vietnam? Did you have any feel that this was almost now a secondary
                        problem for them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes. I think there was very little of that kind of...well, practically
                    none of that kind of rhetoric in our discussion. And, as we found out later of
                    course, the lips and teeth relationship was a rather tenuous one at best. My
                    view of the whole Sino-Vietnamese relationship was one of sort of mutual
                    necessity bringing together two natural adversaries and as soon as the necessity
                    ended in 1975 when the Vietnam war ended, the natural antagonisms came right
                    back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were right in there on the opening up of our Liaison
                        Office?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes. I got there, I believe it was in June of '73. The initial people,
                    Ambassador David Bruce, who was the head of the Liaison Office, and much of the
                    Liaison Office staff had already arrived when I got there. I had to shut down
                    things in Paris, and I went back home for a few weeks. Then went on to Beijing.
                    It was a real honeymoon period. The Chinese were doing their absolute dead-level
                    best to be as cooperative as they could under the circumstances. Believe me, the
                    circumstances were not that good at that time. I mean, the Gang of Four, Jiang
                    Qing and her group were still very much a force to be reckoned with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I suppose in political terms you'd call it the radical
                        left. Mao was still alive, but failing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Mao was still alive, but failing, and Zhou En-lai was very much
                    managing the U.S.-China relationship. But he was failing too. Basically we
                    didn't know that when we got there, at least I didn't. When we set up the
                    Liaison Office, Kissinger came out again in November, and Zhou En-lai appeared
                    in pretty good shape and was at the banquet for Kissinger in the Great Hall of
                    the People. That 1973 visit went very well. My job on that one was as press
                    liaison. I managed the press corps, and the liaison with the information office
                    of the Chinese Foreign Ministry. I thought the visit went smoothly, and
                    Kissinger went away quite pleased with that visit.</p>
                <p>For example, on the Liaison Office itself, the Chinese really went out of their
                    way to do everything that we could possibly ask for. The building that they had
                    picked out for us...the system in those days was that they basically built
                    chancelleries and took you out and said, “Which one would you like?” The one
                    they had for us was too small, and we asked them to put an “l” extension onto
                    the end of it. They literally assigned a work crew that went 24 hours a day, and
                    in something like three weeks, had built the extension onto the Liaison Office.
                    It was that kind of atmosphere of “anything we can do to make you happy.” At the
                    same time, of course, that they were bugging us, and restricting our travel, and
                    other things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Gang of Four the radical left were they able to
                        intrude on the process, or were they kept away?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: At that time, they seemed to be cooperating with the whole process. It
                    was a very strange time. I mean, Jiang Qing, for example...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was Mao's wife.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: ...Mao's wife hosted the Boston Symphony which was one of the big
                    cultural events of the initial period of exchanges. She was very charming, of
                    course, when Nixon was there. She was pushing her revolutionary operas and
                    ballets. That group was a very strange group of people. Jiang Qing, for all of
                    her anti-western attitudes, had a fascination with Western movies. We very
                    quietly worked out an arrangement with Jack Valenti, for example, he would send
                    us movies...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was president of the American Picture Association.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: He would send us out films that she wanted to see, and we would deliver
                    them to Jiang Qing and her friends, and they would return them. We would return
                    them back because the American Picture Association was very, very sensitive
                    about copyrights, and piracy, and this kind of thing. Some of the choices of her
                    movies I found rather interesting. The first movie she asked for was Day of the
                    Jackal, which deals with assassination.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...of Charles de Gaulle.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: She also asked for Z, another movie dealing with assassination.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A leftist movie about Greece.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: We didn't really sense any attempts to obstruct the relationship,
                    although there was a power struggle going on at that time between basically the
                    followers of Zhou En-lai, a more pragmatic group, and the leftists. As long as
                    Zhou was alive, it seemed, the U.S.-China relationship was contained. Kissinger
                    came back to Beijing in, I think it was again November of 1974, and by that time
                    I was head of the political section so I was the sort of overall control officer
                    for that visit. Kissinger saw Zhou En-lai in the hospital. He'd already been
                    diagnosed as having cancer. I don't think anybody knew exactly what the
                    diagnosis was, but he was ill. By that time a discussion with Mao had to go
                    through two interpreters; one who spoke his native Hunan dialect, and then
                    someone who could speak Mandarin. It was therefore screened through two female
                    interpreters, one of whom was his niece, and the other was a lady by the name of
                    Nancy Tang who was one of finest interpreters I have ever met, but who got
                    involved with the Gang of Four and eventually got into trouble with them. So the
                    visit in '74 did not go nearly as well as the earlier visits, and I think it was
                    partially a reflection of the power struggle that was going on in Beijing. Of
                    course, we had our own problems back in Washington with the Nixon
                    resignation.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>We did accomplish a number of things, largely in terms of cultural exchanges—some
                    very significant cultural exchanges; getting the business relationship started,
                    some high level visits, and basically getting the mission up and running and
                    finding a way to function. We started out in the late spring of '73, operating
                    out of a couple of hotel rooms, using one-time pads...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a coding device, very primitive, very...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: ...slow. The Liaison Office moved to another apartment, and we set up a
                    very primitive communication system in the bathroom of one of the apartments.
                    Then finally we got a whole communication system, and the building, and we were
                    able to move into it. One rather humorous aside, the Chinese in their efforts to
                    please us when they built the new wing...that was part of the reason we needed
                    the new wing was to put the communication section in. They did a lovely paneling
                    job of the room where we were going to put the communication system, which
                    involved strips and then wood paneling over it. Of course, the security people
                    said that absolutely positively there could be no wood paneling on the walls of
                    the communication section, so the Seabees had to go in and tear out all the work
                    that the Chinese did. And one of our senior officers, who was very sensitive to
                    Chinese sensibilities, was trying to figure out how we could tear all this
                    paneling out and dispose of it without offending the Chinese. The Seabees built
                    an absolutely beautiful parquet bar which they put in the Seabee apartment as
                    the result of this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the restrictions and the bugging affect your work?
                        More broadly, here you are, the first time in China, we're starting up after
                        30 years or so, how did you go about doing political work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It was difficult. We had the normal relationship with the Foreign
                    Ministry. When I say normal, it was a pretty sterile relationship. They were
                    always willing to see us, and they were always pleasant when we went to see
                    them, but in terms of a dialogue, we had very little. One major fact that I
                    neglected to mention was that of course, after about the first year, David Bruce
                    left as head of the Liaison Office to become ambassador to NATO, and George Bush
                    arrived as the second head of the Liaison Office. So I was in Beijing for the
                    second year with...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to talk about both of those gentlemen
                        afterwards.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: As I say, there was very little dialogue. I think, in fact, that was
                    one of the reasons why David Bruce lost interest very early on. I think he,
                    given his background in London, Paris, and Bonn, that he visualized an on-going
                    dialogue with Zhou En-lai. If my memory is correct, he may have seen Zhou En-lai
                    twice after his arrival, but after that he was relegated not even down to the
                    Foreign Minister, but often times being called in by the head of the American
                    and Oceanian Department, who is about the equivalent of an assistant secretary,
                    and at that time not a very pleasant fellow and I think basically, Mr. Bruce
                    decided this was beneath him.</p>
                <p>We did a lot of China watching which consisted of reading the newspapers,
                    periodicals, and trying to figure out what the historical references were, the
                    implications of rather arcane philosophical discussions that appeared in the
                    newspaper from time to time, getting out on the streets and walking around. It
                    was very difficult to talk to people but occasionally someone would talk. There
                    was a period during that time when big character posters were put up, a form of
                    expression that the Chinese permitted from time to time. We would go out and
                    literally spend hours just standing in front of a wall reading the big character
                    posters. Then exchanging notes with western journalists who were out doing the
                    same thing, and collecting as much information as we could that way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have visions of these big character posters and all
                        these westerners, “Hey, have you seen this one?” “Come over here and look at
                        this one.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: The journalists were much more open about photographing and this sort
                    of thing. So we worked out a deal to acquire those. And then visiting with
                    people who came through, western businessmen, and Chinese-American scholars who
                    would come through oftentimes had better access than we. One of the things we
                    did is attach ourselves to any major delegation, or any delegation at all that
                    we could, that was traveling around China and go with them as escorts. I
                    escorted the first delegation of White House Fellows, for example, on a very
                    interesting trip through China. My wife and I escorted six U.S. governors on a
                    long trip through China. That sort of thing, Congressional delegations, we would
                    go with. It was strange. It was during probably the most restricted period in
                    our bilateral relations in terms of contacts. I travelled more in China in the
                    period '73 to '75 than I've ever travelled in China since. A lot of it was show
                    and tell. We were shown what they wanted us to see and given the standard
                    propaganda line. Then there was a great deal of gullibility in that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There has always been this strain in American view of
                        China since the earliest days. For some reason Americans have a rosy view,
                        or keep thinking that things will work out in China.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Actually, the problem is not exactly that way. It's a two-sided
                    problem. We tend to swing to both extremes. China is either, as you say, this
                    wonderful place with its 4,000 years of culture, and panda bears, and rosy
                    cheeked little kindergarten children that we all love. Or it's the other
                    extreme, the Chinese and the Korean War, and brain-washing, and torture. Right
                    now we're much more on the negative end. We do have a difficult time getting
                    ourselves positioned in the middle where we recognize this is a marvelous
                    country with incredible history, but they're also a bunch of bad guys and they
                    can do very nasty things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the Chinese bureaucrats? I'm told that
                        they're one of the most difficult to deal with.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: In the Liaison Office period, they were difficult to deal with,
                    particularly if you got into substantive issues where they would have to go out
                    on a limb and make a statement about a political issue. They were very, very
                    cautious. On the other hand, I find their diplomatic service very, very able,
                    and they were a very bright bunch of people. If they're not telling you
                    something, they're not telling you because they're stupid. They're not telling
                    you because they're protecting themselves. And at times they could be very
                    skillful in finding ways to accomplish what you wanted to do.</p>
                <p>I don't want to use up too much time but I remember one case when Henry Kissinger
                    was coming and I was handling the press, it would have been '73. Henry had a
                    friend with the New York Times, I can't remember his name now. But anyway, he
                    was travelling in China, and we got this cable from Kissinger saying, “Please
                    arrange to have this guy included as part of the press corps people” the U.S.
                    press corps, the travelling group that came with Kissinger. So I went over to
                    see Mr. Ma, who was head of the International Liaison, and asked if they could
                    do that. And he said, “Mr. Anderson, you must understand that our rules are that
                    only the people travelling with the Secretary on his plane are considered part
                    of the press corps, and that those are the only ones that can be included.” He
                    said, “That is our position in principle.” He said, “You understand now our
                    principled position.” I said, “Yes.” And he said, “Now as a practical matter,
                    since this fellow is a friend of Henry Kissinger's he won't be part of the press
                    corps, but we will include him in all of the banquets, all of the briefings.”
                    And I discovered that the Chinese often times follow this approach. They have a
                    position in principle which if you understand that, and agree with it, then in
                    terms of practical implementation of that principle, they can do the exact
                    opposite.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Back to a couple of the people that you dealt with. David
                        Bruce is one of our preeminent diplomats. How did you find his approach?
                        You've talked a little about him, but how did he operate?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: David Bruce obviously was one of our premier diplomats. He was a very,
                    very decent fellow, and his wife Evangeline was a very nice person. Even though
                    Evangeline still remains very interested in China, I don't really think that
                    they were probably well suited to the job. He was well suited in that he was who
                    he was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a gesture that we're putting a top level person
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes, exactly. The Chinese did the same thing. They sent Huang Chen, the
                    ambassador to France. It was a gesture to show how important this relationship
                    was and how important the Liaison Office was. But as I say, I think David Bruce
                    really expected that he would be communing with Zhou En-lai, and when it didn't
                    work out, Mr. Bruce really, I think, lost a good bit of interest. He spent a lot
                    of time working on his memoirs and other things. But he came through when it was
                    important. Nick Platt was the first chief of the Political Section, who had a
                    fatal accident in China—hit a girl on a bicycle through no fault of his and when
                    he was asked to leave David Bruce was absolutely marvelous in making sure that
                    Nick was taken care of, and it not reflect on him. He looked after his people,
                    had very little patience with children however, which was sometimes a sore
                    point. We had our kids out there...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...and compound living.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: ...and it was very tough living. The compound for much of the time was
                    hotel living, but I don't think David had much sympathy for little kids. In
                    contrast, George Bush was much more conscious of this type of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, tell about George Bush. Now George Bush came to this
                        really...we're speaking at a time when George Bush is President of the
                        United States, but at this time he wasn't a major figure particularly. He
                        had bounced around in a bunch of jobs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Some fairly big ones.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had he been head of the CIA by that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No. He went from the Liaison Office to become head of CIA. He had been
                    a Congressman from Texas, and then ran unsuccessfully for the Senate. I get a
                    little mixed up myself...he was chairman of the Republican Party, and he was
                    Ambassador to the UN. I think he was Ambassador to the UN and then became
                    chairman of the Republican Party, and then came out as head of the Liaison
                    Office.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But still, from Bruce to Bush at that time, he wasn't
                        carrying quite the weight, was he? Or maybe I'm misreading this.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: He didn't really have the same cachet as having been ambassador to
                    London, Paris and Bonn. On the other hand, in many ways politically, he was
                    better plugged in, and probably had more clout in Washington with the Nixon
                    administration and ultimately later the Ford administration, than Bruce. He was
                    not without clout.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you describe how he operated during the time you
                        were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: He's a very energetic guy, and sort of a go-go-go type of approach. I
                    think the first message we got was a message to be conveyed to, I think, the
                    Ghanaian ambassador—it was one of the African ambassadors who he had known at
                    the United Nations. The message was to inform the Ghanaian ambassador he had
                    just become the second best tennis player in the diplomatic corps. They had been
                    tennis rivals in New York. He arrived running; I think he gave a reception for
                    the entire Liaison Office staff the day he got off the plane. One of the first
                    things he did was go out and buy a ping- pong table and move it into the formal
                    dining room of the residence so that the kids could go over and play ping-pong,
                    and he would go over at lunch time and play with them.</p>
                <p>But again, I think he was frustrated by the lack of communication and dialogue
                    with the Chinese. I remember at that time we were dealing very frequently with a
                    lady by the name of Wang Hai-nong, who was Mao's niece and at that point was an
                    Assistant Minister of Foreign Affairs. She was really noteworthy for her
                    clamlike approach to dialogue, and I think it used to drive George Bush up the
                    wall because he would go over and we would have a message to deliver from
                    Washington on whatever issue. Quite literally most of the time the message would
                    take five minutes, and then Wang would sort of sit there, and George Bush would
                    be damned if he was going to arrive at the Foreign Ministry and leave ten
                    minutes later. So he would sometimes tend to launch into discussions of issues,
                    political issues that I wondered about occasionally at the time, because we got
                    no response. Wang, or whoever was her interlocutor would sit and listen but we
                    got very little in response.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any feel for how the policy apparatus worked
                        at that time? In other words, we'd go in and deliver a message which we felt
                        there should be some response, or something like that, you'd get the clam
                        treatment more or less, but did you have any feel what happened to policy
                        things, and how they came back and answered them.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Oh, we would get a response eventually but basically the way it worked
                    Washington would send us a message, we would go over to the Foreign Ministry,
                    deliver the message, and they would say, “Thank you, we will inform the
                    appropriate offices.” And then maybe a week later we would get a phone call
                    saying, “Would you come in?” We would go in, and they would read from their
                    prepared position paper. So we got answers, but it was a process that had to go
                    through particularly the party machinery to get the right answer, or to get an
                    approved answer. What I meant was, in a normal diplomatic situation you could go
                    in and do that, and there is conversation and some back and forth in dialogue on
                    the issue. But there was very little of that. Basically, I think everyone was
                    scared to death. It was a time when the power struggle in Beijing was very
                    intense, so no one was going to stick their neck out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that the situation the whole time you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes. I left Beijing in the summer of '75, and went to Hong Kong. The
                    Consul General in Hong Kong asked me to come down and we amalgated the political
                    and economic section into a China reporting section. We were dealing with both
                    economic and political reporting, and he asked me to come down and run that,
                    which I did. We had relatively little operational kinds of functions, but it was
                    a terribly interesting time from a reporting standpoint. Zhou En- lai died...I
                    got there in early fall of '75, and Zhou En-lai died I believe it was February
                    of '76. I can no longer remember the exact sequence, but Chu De, who was number
                    two to Mao for many years, died. Then Mao himself died. And before that they had
                    the Tangshan earthquake which was the enormous earthquake in the Northeast.
                    Three weeks after Mao died we had the arrest of the Gang of Four. So 1976 was a
                    tremendously eventful year in China, and we were observing from Hong Kong
                    through the Chinese press, through intelligence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The question always comes, Hong Kong was the preeminent
                        China watching place for years, all of a sudden we open an office in
                        Beijing, so what's Hong Kong doing? And why is it still doing its
                        thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: It's because the two bring two different kinds of attributes. In
                    Beijing you have on-the-scenes, you have the ability to talk to people, you can
                    get out on the streets, you're interacting with the Foreign Ministry and other
                    ministries in the government. There is a large political relationship to be
                    managed, which requires an on-the-spot presence of an embassy. Hong Kong, on the
                    other hand, is outside looking in. It has a number of advantages as well. One is
                    resources. There is a Foreign Service national staff there, a local Chinese
                    staff many of whom have worked for the Consulate for 20 or more years, who have
                    followed these developments and have a historical memory that is invaluable. And
                    being Chinese they can get through Chinese materials twice as fast as any
                    American regardless of how good his language is. And then there is the
                    international press, and a whole China watching community there. And a very
                    substantial intelligence operation. There are intelligence resources there that
                    you don't have anywhere else. And its been very interesting that over a long
                    period of time you get a different perspective from Beijing and Hong Kong.
                    Usually Hong Kong, when developments are happening, when events are breaking,
                    Hong Kong tends to be more on the pessimistic side that things are going wrong,
                    or that there is a power struggle going on. And in Beijing, living right in the
                    community, the inclination I think is to see things as being more normal than
                    they look from the outside.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before we leave the Nixon-Ford administration, what was
                        Kissinger's role once he established this relationship? Did he sort of move
                        on to other things? Did you feel that Kissinger was really on top of the
                        China relations all the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Pretty much, yes. He retained a very direct interest in China, and at a
                    minimum Kissinger, I think, sort of set a tone that really shaped the way we
                    dealt with China for a very long time. Essentially Kissinger saw the opening to
                    China as part of a global strategic move, and was very much interested in the
                    triangular relationship. At the same time I think he was very affected by China
                    in his book, and speeches I've heard him give. He was obviously very impressed
                    with Mao and Zhou En-lai, and with their intellectual capabilities, their
                    strategic thinking, and this kind of thing. I think they were people he felt he
                    could commune with. Then there was very definitely an atmosphere in the U.S.
                    government as long as Kissinger was running the show that basically in dealing
                    with China you looked at the big picture and the strategic relationship, don't
                    bother with details which led to, I think, a lot of people...not necessarily
                    myself, but a lot of people feeling that we were giving away things that we
                    didn't need to give to China. In other words, if the Chinese said, “We want
                    this,” in terms of a negotiation, the inclination was to say, “Okay,” rather
                    than have a show-down, and quibble over details, which may or may not have been
                    wise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about in Hong Kong the view there of events and
                        Vietnam and Chinese-Vietnamese relations?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: At that period really Vietnam did not figure terribly large.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was our major preoccupation, and then it just dropped
                        over the horizon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: The Hong Kong Consulate General did not contribute to the Vietnam
                    picture at that particular time. There were the beginnings of Vietnamese
                    refugees, and as a matter of fact, I had one guy working for me who did nothing
                    but Indochina matters. It was not a major focus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there and came back to Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: First you were in Micronesian negotiations for a while
                        from '77 to '78. What were you doing on that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I was the Deputy U.S. representative. The Micronesian operation is a
                    very strange thing. It was called the Office of Micronesian Status Negotiations,
                    and the head of the office had the rank of ambassador. At the time I was there
                    it was Peter Rosenblatt. I was a very small part of a process that had been
                    going on, at that point, for about ten years, and went on again for another five
                    or six after I left. The objective was to negotiate a relationship with the
                    Micronesian states which was called Free Association. The United States
                    objective, in crude terms, was to grant limited sovereignty to these states so
                    they could basically manage most of their internal affairs while we retained
                    control of their foreign affairs, their foreign economic relations, and their
                    foreign military relations because a major player in this whole thing was the
                    Department of Defense, which was looking at Micronesia...I always felt in terms
                    of World War II Pacific.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'd gone to a great deal of effort and blood to seize
                        these islands from the Japanese. And I guess the Soviets were sniffing
                        around in the Pacific.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Then you have to realize Truk, the Marshall Islands, and Eniwetok,
                    these were places where we shed a lot of blood. And there was also in the
                    Marshall Islands another factor which made it very important to us, the
                    Kwajalein Missile Range which was an almost perfect site for testing
                    intercontinental ballistic missiles. We would fire them from Vandenberg Air
                    Force Base in California and drop the warheads into the lagoon at Kwajalein. It
                    was exactly the right depth. So we had some interest, but it was an almost
                    tragic negotiation in many ways. It was a clash of a huge wealthy western
                    culture coming into an essentially native island culture. Right after World War
                    II the Navy ran the Micronesian Trust, and basically took the approach of sort
                    of anthropologically not disturbing the native life. The UN, under which we had
                    the mandate, went in and looked around and said, “These people are living in
                    poverty. You've got to do something to improve their livelihood.” The
                    responsibility got moved to Interior, who then took the approach, “We're going
                    to modernize and bring you into the 20th century, and get all these good things
                    for you.”</p>
                <p>I don't know what the right answer is quite frankly. The result was you had one
                    of the highest rates of government employment I think anywhere in the world.
                    People forgot how to fish, people forgot how to do the things that they had done
                    for generations. Alcoholism became a problem, and economic development was
                    practically zero.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have an interview I've done with Peter Rosenblatt which
                        would bring this up. Then you went to the China desk where you were from '78
                        to '80. This was the Carter administration. Was this different? This was a
                        new world, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It was a new world, but in terms of the U.S. approach to China policy,
                    it was very little changed. The China policy remained very consistent, and as a
                    matter of fact of course, Carter was the one who was finally able to start
                    moving toward normalization of relations, and did so in '79. I'll be absolutely
                    honest with you, I ended up as deputy on the China desk largely because I really
                    wanted to get out of the Micronesian negotiations. They were fascinating in many
                    respects, but I felt like I was kind of out in left field. Our offices were over
                    in the Department of Interior, and I didn't feel that I was in the main stream
                    of what was going on at State. So when I was offered the job of deputy, I came
                    over. And I was glad I did because I ended up being there at the time of
                    establishment of diplomatic relations and the visit to the United States of Deng
                    Xiaoping and some very historic moments in U.S.-China relations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you arrived there, how did you see this relationship?
                        We had a strong relationship with Taiwan, and we were working this other
                        one, the two China policy. How did this work out? What was the bureau
                        suggesting that we do?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: One big problem at this particular time was that the normalization
                    negotiations, and some of the moves that were being made, were so highly
                    restricted, so highly classified, that a lot of the other kinds of lower level
                    measures that needed to be taken to prepare for it were not being taken because
                    you couldn't tell the people that had to do it. For example, the Legal Adviser
                    was called upon to perform heroic service when we were starting to move toward
                    normalization and had to have some form of legislation to take care of Taiwan.
                    Because of the relationship we had with Taiwan, we couldn't just simply say,
                    “Good bye,” and walk away. The Japanese had led the way with their arrangement
                    that they had developed with Taipei after they normalized with Beijing, and we
                    more or less followed some aspects of the Japanese model where we created in
                    effect an embassy, but declared it a private, non-profit, entity. That was all
                    done through the Taiwan Relations Act, and of course, this all had to be done in
                    the context of the normalization negotiations. And as I say, much of it was very
                    difficult to accomplish because the people you needed to do it couldn't be told
                    why they were doing it. Or if they were asked to do it, they would know what was
                    up. I was kept briefed and involved on the normalization negotiations up to the
                    very end. I guess that would have been into November, but then in early
                    December, I believe it was...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would be '79.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: ...'79, Ambassador Woodcock, who had been meeting with the Chinese
                    Foreign Minister, had two meetings, or maybe three, with Deng Xiaoping. That was
                    where the last pieces fell into place. I'm sure it took Deng Xiaoping himself to
                    say, “All right, we will do these things.” Then it was decided that they were
                    going to do it. I was not included in that, and as a matter of fact I remember
                    vividly that on December 15th when Jimmy Carter went on television to announce
                    that we were establishing diplomatic relations with China, it was the day of the
                    East Asian Christmas party. I got a phone call from Bernard Kalb...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A correspondent.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I had known Bernie for a long time, and he said, “Don, what's going
                    on?” I said, “I don't know,” and I added, “I really mean it, I don't know.”
                    “Well,” he said, “the White House had just announced the President is going to
                    make a major foreign policy statement at 9:00 tonight. He said, “There is
                    nothing going on that he would be making an announcement about, nothing in the
                    Soviet Union, and there's nothing in the Middle East.” He said, “Its got to be
                    China.” He said, “Is he going to normalize relations?” And I said, “Bernie, I
                    have no idea, and don't you say that anybody on the China desk had any kind of a
                    clue, because it's true.” He said, “We're going to go with it anyway.” And they
                    did, and they were right. At 9:00 that night Jimmy Carter...</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did someone then brief you on what was happening?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: By the Christmas party things did sort of begin to fall apart, and it
                    was generally understood that that was what was going to happen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the reason for these negotiations of this type, or
                        concern, within the American political environment that this might
                        intrude?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes, I think it was. There were several problems. One, there was
                    concern about Taiwan. Taiwan actually got treated rather shabbily in terms of
                    notification. I think that they did not want Taiwan to know that we were about
                    to make this move because Taiwan at that time had quite a strong lobby on the
                    Hill. I don't think they wanted the Hill to know too far in advance. They did
                    brief, but a very, very short time before it actually became known. And there
                    was a good deal of resentment about that in the Congress as well. But I think
                    that they did not want a big political “brouhaha” blowing up with Congress
                    passing emergency resolutions, and the top people on Taiwan going to their
                    constituencies and so forth, so it was very closely held.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Taiwan was part of the China desk, wasn't it until that
                        point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No. It had been separated. At the time of normalization, there was a
                    Republic of China desk. And quite some time earlier, actually in the '60s, we
                    had split the Mainland off from Taiwan, there was the Republic of China desk,
                    and originally there was the Office of Asian Communist Affairs which included
                    China. And then we dropped North Vietnam and North Korea and it became just the
                    China desk. So the two desks were separate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And as a practical measure they both had been going in
                        such different directions that they could be treated as a practical measure
                        as different countries, couldn't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: In practical terms there was a lot of that, yes. The ROC desk and the
                    China desk worked obviously very closely, and now there is a Taiwan Liaison
                    Staff in the Office of Regional Affairs, again, which works quite closely with
                    the China desk, because almost every major policy impinges on both sides. I
                    don't know if you read the Washington Post today, but there's a sale of F-16
                    fighters to Taiwan which looks like it might be going through which would have
                    some major implications for both sides.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It seems to be more a political move to get the Texas vote
                        for your former ambassador, George Bush.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: There may be an element of that, I'm sure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this China desk period '78 to '80. Any other major
                        events that you were dealing with? One would be the visit of Deng Xiaoping,
                        and how he was viewed by us at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I think his visit was a tremendous success, and he was very popular
                    everywhere he went. I accompanied the Deng party on that trip around the United
                    States. Everywhere he went there was a degree of tension because there were the
                    Chinese Nationalists and some people were out with the Chinese Nationalist flag,
                    etc. But by and large his reception was very warm, and I think personally he
                    handled himself very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he understand the Chinese Nationalists element in the
                        United States? Was he surprised at it, or did you get any feel for that? Was
                        he briefed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I don't think he was surprised. I mean, they're pretty sophisticated on
                    that subject, and they follow it extremely closely themselves. It was obviously
                    one of their concerns, and one of the things they talked to us at the working
                    level about. “We understand there's been a few demonstrations here, and what are
                    you going to do about? Will you make sure that they are kept at a certain
                    distance, etc.” So they were expecting it, and it was managed I think in a way
                    that satisfied them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you feel about, you might say, the High Command
                        dealing with Far Eastern affairs under the Carter administration? I mean,
                        you had Richard Holbrooke who had been sort of a young Turk in the Foreign
                        Service coming in and he was more interested I suppose in Vietnamese affairs
                        at that time. How was he and his immediate subordinates?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Basically, I think, pretty good. I always found Dick a difficult person
                    to deal with. But I think he had the right instincts, and we got where we wanted
                    to go. And he had some very good people in the Bureau, and up the line, dealing
                    with people that I dealt with who dealt with China. I found generally they were
                    quite good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As an East Asian China hand, what was your personal
                        feeling about how our China policy came out, which more or less existed to
                        this day. This was considered quite a bold move on the part of Carter to cut
                        this knot that had been around. How did you feel about how it
                        developed?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Given the emotional involvement in this whole relationship, I think it
                    came out about as well as could be expected. The immediate Congressional
                    reaction was very strong, and in many cases very negative. And the Taiwan
                    Relations Act reflected Congressional feeling that we were abandoning a friend.
                    But we argued at the time, and I think it has been proven historically accurate,
                    that we were not abandoning Taiwan. In fact, Taiwan has prospered mightily
                    since. From a strictly diplomatic standpoint they have become isolated. But from
                    an economic standpoint, cultural standpoint, they have been successful. And I
                    think the relationship we have with them now is a very sound one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there anything else we should cover in that
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I can't think of anything. I'm sure that others have covered some other
                    aspects of it in more detail, some of whom like Harry Thayer, for example, were
                    more directly involved in the beginning of normalization negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...Shanghai as Consul General from '80 to '83. You must
                        have felt this was the culmination of your career, didn't you? To have a
                        major post in China, having been out in the place where one would never
                        would return to China? How did you feel about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I wouldn't call it a culmination but it was certainly something that I
                    sought and wanted to do. I considered it a real challenge. Even when I was
                    living in Beijing with the Liaison Office we travelled down to Shanghai quite
                    often. I had found Shanghai a fascinating city, its history.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Its really a very recent history. It goes back to about
                        the 1830s, or something like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Even later than that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a made treaty port, like Hong Kong.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes, but an absolutely fascinating place. I was delighted when I got
                    the job as Consul General, and particularly because we were setting up the post.
                    We were creating something new, and in a way setting precedents, and
                    establishing a new consular mission, which I found particularly interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to pick up any of the residue of the old
                        consulate which we abandoned and were forced out of in '48? I've interviewed
                        some people who left on ships there. I mean, we went out rather reluctantly,
                        dragging our heels. Was anything of that left at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It is all there, but one of the fall-outs from—I guess you could call
                    it a fall-out— from the Taiwan Relations Act, Congress in its desire to protect
                    Taiwan's interests introduced into the Taiwan Relations Act a provision that all
                    properties in the United States held by the former Republic of China would
                    remain the property of Taiwan. So the former Republic of China embassy, and the
                    residence in particular, a place called Twin Oaks which sits on about 12 acres
                    of beautiful land between Connecticut and Wisconsin Avenues, and a number of
                    other buildings continue to belong to Taiwan. So we have never settled our
                    official claims between the PRC and the United States. We haven't gotten back
                    any of our official buildings, really haven't made much of an attempt. So we
                    were not expecting to go back to any of our former official buildings. And, in
                    fact, the then Deputy Chief of Mission, Stapleton Roy, who is now currently our
                    ambassador, was asked down to Shanghai and shown the building that they were
                    going to lease to us, and came back and...I don't know whether you know Stape,
                    but he is not a terribly effusive kind of person, and he was waxing absolutely
                    eostatic about this building. It was the home of one of the Yung family, who
                    were probably the wealthiest Chinese in Shanghai. It was three acres of gardens,
                    and an absolutely magnificent old mansion that they offered us, which we
                    grabbed, and we're still there. Part of the fun of opening the post was taking
                    this place and converting it into a Consulate General without destroying the
                    beauty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find a contrast in dealing with the Shanghai
                        authorities? One gets the feeling from reading from the periphery about this
                        that they really are a different breed than the people up in Beijing, much
                        more aware of the world, and looser, and easier to deal with? I don't
                        know.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: There is a certain amount of that. As a matter of fact up in Beijing in
                    the Foreign Ministry you'll find an awful lot of Shanghainese. I used to kid
                    them about the Shanghai mafia that used to run the American and Oceanian
                    Department because there are a lot of people who are originally from Shanghai.
                    For example, the current Chinese ambassador. They are a bit different but you
                    have to realize, of course, I went to Shanghai in 1980, and I was in Beijing in
                    '73. In the interim the Gang of Four had fallen, Deng Xiaoping had come back, so
                    it was a whole new atmosphere. So it was a much easier place to live and deal
                    with. But there were still plenty of problems, and Shanghai in many respects at
                    that time, I think, was kept on a tighter leash by Beijing than many other parts
                    of China. Because really the Gang of Four and this whole Maoist clique that
                    attempted to usurp power, their power base was Shanghai.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The mayor of Shanghai, was he part of that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yes, Zhang Chunqiao was one of the Four, and Wang Hongwen, and all
                    three were from Shanghai, and Jiang Qing herself had...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...had been an actress in Shanghai.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: So I think Shanghai for a long, long time was viewed with a certain
                    distrust, and there were a lot of hangovers and holdovers from the earlier
                    period that were still in jobs; frequently not doing much but they had not been
                    dislodged. So that it was a different atmosphere, but Shanghai people are
                    generally much more friendly, and effusive, and sophisticated, than in
                    Beijing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, one, you're setting up this thing, but what else did
                        you do? How did you go about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: We basically set up the whole gambit of things. One important thing was
                    getting the consular operation going. We held off the formal opening of the
                    Consulate until we felt we had all of the necessary infrastructure. The consular
                    section was built, and we had the visa machines and everything that we needed.
                    At the opening ceremony I said, “We will be open for business tomorrow morning
                    and ready to provide a full range of services.” At 5:00 the next morning we had
                    a line of about 60 people waiting to apply for visas. We did a very big consular
                    business. We did a fair amount of trade promotion. Shanghai was one of the more
                    popular places for American businesses to come, and there were a number of
                    things really just getting started that we could...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had they established those economic zones?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, they hadn't come yet. That was later. They were on their way, they
                    were planning them but they hadn't come yet. But Foxboro, for example, which
                    produces electric monitoring equipment for industrial processes, was setting up
                    a joint venture. Nike Shoes came in and tried to set up a joint venture.
                    McDonald Douglas was just beginning what became a major co-production operation
                    building commercial jets. So we had the beginning of a business community, and
                    we had regular meetings of this community to brief them and get their reactions.
                    Finally that grew into the Shanghai- American Chamber of Commerce which now has
                    well over 65 or 70 members.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>There were a lot of things not directly related to the consular operations,
                    things like setting up the school. We had to create the Shanghai-American
                    school. We had a cultural section and a very active cultural and educational
                    program. We got the exchange visitor program going, and I think were very
                    successful there. Often times Beijing couldn't use all their international
                    visitor grants and we were always ready to grab them. And Shanghai has an
                    Institute for International Studies, which is one of their most sophisticated
                    sort of Rand type operation. We sent a lot of those people to the United States
                    on short-term grants, and those people have been friends of the Consulate and
                    friends of the United States for a long time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The great onrush of Chinese students to the United States
                        was probably, I suspect, will be the most significant thing that was
                        done.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I agree with you.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean this back and forth, China will never be the
                        same.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I totally agree with that. I take a certain amount of pride that either
                    on the China desk, or in my jobs overseas, I have always pushed that aspect
                    because I totally agree that the 140,000 Chinese that have come to the United
                    States now, and it's growing every year, will be a tremendously important factor
                    in our bilateral relations and in China's modernization. I was struck by that
                    when I was Consul General in Shanghai because at that time, after the Gang of
                    Four period was wound up, many of the older people who had been in prison or had
                    been under house arrest, or whatever, were coming back and getting responsible
                    positions. And many of these people had been trained either in the United
                    States, or at places like St. John's University in Shanghai which was an
                    American run missionary university.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Yale had some...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Yale was not so big in Shanghai but there were a lot of people who had
                    had extensive contacts with them, and who were American educated. And dealing
                    with them was just marvelous because they understood even after an absence of 35
                    years what we were talking about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any problems on the consular side with
                        protection of welfare, Americans getting into trouble? Or wasn't that a
                        factor particularly?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: We had probably less than many places. People tended to be a little
                    more on their good behavior in China than they are in Tijuana or Naples, or some
                    place like that. We had a few people go around the bend, a few people died. We
                    had several cases of absolutely fascinating individuals who had stayed on in
                    China, American ladies, who had lived in China for the past 30-40 years—in one
                    case for 50 years. She was a Quaker lady from Pennsylvania, had married a
                    Chinese who was studying in the United States and when he got his Ph.D. she
                    married him, and went back to China. This was in the '20s when an American
                    woman, if she married a foreign national, lost her nationality. She had lived as
                    a Chinese all her adult life. We got to know Muriel, and she was a great gal,
                    tougher than nails, and finally decided she wanted to get her American passport
                    and be an American citizen. So we had quite a range, some rather bizarre
                    consular matters.</p>
                <p>Tragically, one of our officers married a young girl from Taiwan where he had met
                    her studying Chinese, and she came over after they were married, of course, a
                    little bit nervous about moving to Communist China from Taiwan. And they were
                    out on a trip, one of the consular corps sponsored trips, died suddenly of a
                    heart attack, age 27. Suddenly we had a dead wife, the family wanted a Buddhist
                    ceremony funeral which we managed to do, and got the body shipped back to Taiwan
                    via Japan. It was a terribly sad thing, but in many ways it was kind of touching
                    because one of the Foreign Affairs Office people, who was helping us with this,
                    and he had on other occasions not been very helpful, came over on a weekend and
                    brought me...they had to do a death certificate, and he said, “I have recopied
                    the entire death certificate because it was printed in our simplified Chinese
                    characters (the modern Chinese characters they use on the Mainland).” He said,
                    “I know they don't use those on Taiwan and I was afraid that they would not
                    accept our simplified characters, so I have redone it in the old
                    characters.”</p>
                <p>A large part of it was getting set up, getting the building fixed, getting the
                    school started, getting the consular program going, getting the commercial
                    program going, and getting the cultural program going. We did a fair amount of
                    political and economic reporting, and it was a good time to be doing that
                    because nobody had ever done it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a Foreign Service officer's dream.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: And then we travelled. The consular district encompassed Jiangsu
                    Province, Anhui Province, and Zhejiang which is really the whole Yangtze basin
                    and includes some of the nicest cities in China, Hangzhou, and Suzhou, and some
                    of the more scenic spots. I used to tell visitors that if my consular district
                    was a country, it would be the fifth largest country in the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the cultural side, here is the ancient Chinese culture,
                        and the very aggressive American cultures, were there problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: The problems weren't between an ancient Chinese culture and a modern
                    American culture. The problems, where we had them, were in the degree to which
                    the Communist government wanted to maintain control. And the degree of openness
                    that they were prepared to permit. We were always pushing for more and more open
                    exchanges, more frank discussions. “Let us bring in more films, and show them to
                    more people,” and the Chinese were always just a little bit nervous. Shanghai is
                    a very western city in many respects, and as you said, Shanghai's history, while
                    they have the 4000 years of Chinese culture certainly, they look back on a 100
                    years. They really do look on themselves as sort of the New Yorkers of
                    China.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I take it you did not follow in the footsteps of one of
                        your predecessors, George Seward, who hung an American in the courtyard of
                        the American Consulate back in around 1863 or so.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, I did take part...he didn't get hung, but we had the first American
                    government ship, it was the NOAA oceanographic ship, I think it was called the
                    Oceanographer, a beautiful white ship that came in along with the director or
                    NOAA. It was an exchange between our two oceanographic societies. The ship, as I
                    say, was a beautiful ship, and it had a co-educational crew...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a fancy term for men and women working on it, which
                        was unusual at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: The captain took out one of the crew, and they both arrived at the
                    banquet with the Chinese...she having not been invited, a bit tipsy, and the
                    Chinese had a bunch of Chinese admirals who did their Chinese number on them,
                    toasting with Mao Tab the Chinese high potency stuff, and they both got
                    absolutely swacked. The director of NOAA fired them both, so we didn't hang
                    them, but we did send them home.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the relations with the embassy? Any
                        problems.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, we had quite good relations actually. We had a good Admin officer,
                    and we set up a courier system—it was illegal, but we used to send a diplomatic
                    pouch up with our classified stuff. We'd send up an officer, so we got back and
                    forth as frequently as possible. I didn't have any real problems that way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you came back for the last two years on the China
                        desk again?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I came back in '83 for two years on the China desk, '83 to '85.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find any difference with the Reagan
                        administration, and China? Reagan came sort of an old line Republican, a
                        very pro-Taiwanese.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Reagan, I think, scared us all to death before the election, and really
                    immediately after the election. The transition team that he sent over to State
                    was pretty shocking. I will give Al Haig really high marks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was Secretary of State.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: He was appointed Secretary of State. He went in and said, “Okay, I'm in
                    charge now. All of you transition people get out of here.” I think he kept the
                    China thing on the trolley and prevented it from taking a real lurch. And once
                    he had stabilized it, and the bureaucracy that was built up around the
                    President, after that there were relatively few problems. We had a tougher bunch
                    than we did in the early days. Paul Wolfowitz was the Assistant Secretary, and
                    there was less empathy with the Chinese. I think he was more interested in other
                    issues, and he didn't see why we were pandering to the Chinese. This F-16 deal
                    that we've talked about today...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...this is a fighter plane.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: ...brings up the issue of the 1982 August 17 joint communiqu� that was
                    negotiated, which Paul Wolfowitz has always thought was a terrible mistake. This
                    is the one limiting our ability to sell arms to Taiwan. On things like that, the
                    Reagan administration was tougher. I think that they took, if you will, a more
                    pragmatic attitude, and were willing to risk offending the Chinese more so than,
                    say, during the Carter period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I suppose looking at these things from a certain
                        perspective and saying, “Well, maybe rightly so.” ANDERSON: Yes, and history
                        changes too. The relationship isn't the same at different points. I guess
                        the big event of my time as Country Director for China was the Reagan trip
                        to China. I quite literally spent much of my time in the two years I was
                        Country Director, either managing trips or managing visits of Chinese
                        dignitaries to the United States. We had the Reagan trip to China, the visit
                        to the United States by Zhao Ziyang, who was then the Premier, an earlier
                        visit by the Foreign Minister which was the first official formal visit to
                        Washington by a Chinese Foreign Minister. Then a number of other high level
                        visits.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the Reagan trip from the press, I mean it's hard to say
                        that one had the feeling that Reagan was not very knowledgeable or engaged
                        on foreign affairs. He tended to see things in rather simplistic terms. From
                        your perspective, how did you prepare him, and what was your impression of
                        how he worked on this. Really, it was a major trip on his part.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: It was a major trip, but there was not major substance. In fact, I
                    don't think there were too many people that wanted any new breakthroughs or any
                    major substantive changes. So it was, it was a big photo operation. It was a
                    chance for the great communicator to go to China, and communicate to the
                    Chinese, but there was a very strong element, I can remember, of a desire to
                    communicate really over the heads of the Chinese to the American people as well.
                    And there was incredible television and press coverage of that trip, and he did
                    it extremely well. It was one of the few times when I have watched him turn it
                    on in person, and he is remarkable. I went to the White House briefings and we
                    did our number, we spoke our piece, the President listened, but I didn't have
                    the feeling that there was any great substance. As a matter of fact, after we
                    finished one of the briefings—I think it was the Cabinet Room, he listened very
                    intently, but at the end his only comment was, he told a story about losing his
                    contact lenses in Hong Kong when he was doing a movie, and so he walked around
                    Hong Kong holding his eyes like this...because that's the way you can see better
                    if you've lost your contacts. He said he didn't understand why everybody was so
                    angry with him. That was his sole comment on the substantive issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In talking about drawing your eyes back to make you look
                        oriental. Then just briefly, you were in the Senior Seminar from '85 to '86,
                        and then you went back to Hong Kong as Consul General for our years from '86
                        to '90. Was there any change in being in Hong Kong at that time? Had the
                        operation matured?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: There were lots of changes, but not as many as many people might have
                    expected. The assumption was at the time of normalization of relations that Hong
                    Kong would gradually shrink, would diminish, and in some respects it did. I mean
                    the political section and economic section was considerably smaller. But
                    strangely enough the Consulate was at least as big, and maybe a little bigger,
                    than I had ever known it to be. One of my roles in Hong Kong was to fend off
                    other agencies that wanted to either set up offices, or add staff to their
                    existing offices. It is a great regional center, I think we had 12 or 13
                    different government agencies represented there, and there was constant pressure
                    to increase. The big thing, of course, that had changed substantively was the
                    1984 Sino-British Joint Statement a time certain had been set for Hong Kong's
                    reversion to Beijing, which affected a whole range of things in Hong Kong, and
                    the attitude of the Hong Kong people.</p>
                <p>Then, of course, the other major development and major tragedy was Tiananmen
                    which occurred in June of 1989.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the quelling of a major student demonstration in
                        front of world television in the main square of Beijing. Let's talk first
                        about the reversion. Did we have a fixed policy when the Hong Kong people
                        would come to you and say, “What's the American assurances?” How did we play
                        this? Because this was only two years after the statement, and people hadn't
                        learned to live with it yet.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: What happened with the statement was that there was great fear, and
                    uncertainty, prior to the statement—in the period '82, '83 and into early '84.
                    Property values were affected, people were beginning to make arrangements to get
                    out, and there was a high degree of uncertainty. My predecessor, I will say,
                    played a significant role in presenting an image of confidence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Burt Levin. Then came the Joint Declaration in 1984, and the document,
                    I still think, was a very good document. It was well negotiated, and if the
                    Chinese abide by the provisions of that Joint Declaration, I think Hong Kong's
                    future is going to be okay. There was a great collective sigh of relief when
                    that Joint Declaration came out. So I came in '86, following a period of not
                    euphoria, but relief, and a renewed sense of confidence that things were going
                    to be all right. But the next phase in the process, as agreed, was to begin the
                    preparation of the basic law for Hong Kong, in effect a mini-constitution. That
                    process was just beginning. My feeling was that over the period that I was
                    there, there was again something of a deterioration of confidence, in part
                    because of the negotiations over the basic law and a growing sense that the
                    Chinese really aren't going to leave Hong Kong alone to the degree that we
                    hoped. And, of course, Tiananmen occurred which was a terrible shock. The
                    democracy movement in China had a tremendous impact in Hong Kong. I can remember
                    one Sunday there were at least 800,000 people marching peacefully down the main
                    street of Hong Kong. There were enormous demonstrations. There was an
                    interesting change that took place during that period because they were
                    demonstrating for our compatriots in China, our brothers in China. This was a
                    whole new attitude because generally Hong Kong Chinese have looked upon people
                    across the border, in the Mainland, as sort of country bumpkins. “We're the
                    smart guys, we're the wealthy, we're the ones who know how to do it, and all
                    those people up in the Mainland are kind of dummies.” And when the democracy
                    movement started, there was all of a sudden in Hong Kong a feeling of being
                    Chinese, of being part of the thing that they were seeing in Beijing. In fact,
                    there was a lot of support, monetary and material support that went from Hong
                    Kong into China during that period. Practically all of those tents that you saw
                    on television in Tiananmen came from Hong Kong.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were people looking to the United States to do something?
                        How did they feel about how we reacted?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: To what? To the 1997 issue?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To the Tiananmen Square.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: Everybody watched in horror. I personally felt like I was watching a
                    tragedy. They recognized there wasn't anything we could do in the short term in
                    the sense of changing things. In the short term we did take actions which
                    probably still can't really be discussed, to provide shelter, and help for
                    people who were escaping who had been involved in it. We cooperated with a group
                    of about five other countries to help some of these young people, and some not
                    so young, to get through Hong Kong and get on safely to the United States or to
                    Europe, or wherever they were going. And, of course, the President immediately
                    announced economic sanctions, and certain steps in terms of cutting off high
                    level visits, etc. Actually, the United States probably took as strong measures
                    as anybody, and kept them in place, or is still keeping some of them in place
                    longer than anybody else.</p>
                <p>One of the very interesting things about the post-Tiananmen reaction was that
                    probably the people who were back in doing business more or less as usual, were
                    the Chinese from Taiwan and from Hong Kong.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You probably left there shortly after Tiananmen...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: A full year later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the Chinese, who were able to leave, beginning to
                        hedge their bets more by getting out of Hong Kong?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: No, the brain drain had already become a serious problem. There is a
                    constant outward migration from Hong Kong, and a steady inward migration from
                    the Mainland into Hong Kong so that the population has remained relatively
                    stable. There are about 22,000 people leave every year, in the '60s, '70s, '80s.
                    It went up to 35,000, then up to 45,000 and the last figures I saw it was
                    running between 55,000 and 60,000, and many of these people are the best and
                    brightest, they are people with needed skills. It's a bit of a dilemma because
                    they want to get out, and Hong Kong is certainly not going to try and prevent
                    them from leaving. We do not want to be seen to be contributing to the brain
                    drain. On the other hand, Canada and Australia, and a number of other countries,
                    were actively welcoming those people because a country like Canada, has an
                    under-population problem, and needed certain types of skills— secretarial
                    skills, skills in the financial field, a variety of things which are more or
                    less mobile. It was an issue that I wrestled with much of the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would you deal with it? Obviously you don't want to
                        shout fire, but at the same time American business people, other people
                        would come and say, whither Hong Kong? Do we have a policy, and how did you
                        handle this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I basically took an upbeat, optimistic approach. I think I must have
                    answered that question several hundred times. Every business executive and
                    business leader that came through from the States, the first question was,
                    “What's going to happen in 1997?” My response was that basically Hong Kong is
                    going to change. There will probably be less personal freedom, more controls,
                    because the Chinese I don't think are capable of accepting the degree of free
                    wheeling operations that Hong Kong has permitted. On the other hand, I don't
                    think the Chinese are so stupid that they're going to upset the business
                    atmosphere to the point where Hong Kong will no longer be a good place to do
                    business, and it has so many natural advantages in terms of communications, the
                    port, the skilled labor force, that it is almost irreplaceable, at least in the
                    short term for China. China depends on it to a tremendous amount. So I told
                    them, “I think we'll still be doing business after 1997.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Maybe we might cut it off here, do you think?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ANDERSON: I certainly do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just one last question. Looking at it today, and maybe
                        they have, if a young Foreign Service officer comes to you and says, “What
                        about a career as a China specialist?” What would you tell them today?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>ANDERSON: I would tell them that if that's their interest, and they enjoy it, I
                    would certainly do it. I have probably specialized in China more than anybody in
                    the Service. Out of 32 years I spent about 25 in China, or China related jobs,
                    and never regretted it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
