<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000577">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Ray E. Jones </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>RAY E. JONES</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Thomas Dunnigan </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: August 23, 1994</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>[Note: This transcript was not edited by Mr. Jones.]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I am today about to interview Ray Jones who had a lengthy
                        career in the Foreign Service and was one of the top secretarial assistants
                        in the service for a number of years. The date is August 23, 1994.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Ray, why don't you tell us first of all how you acquired your secretarial
                    training and what you did with it.</p>
                <p>JONES: Well, after high school, 1940 which I graduated, in the fall of 1940 I
                    went to Lafayette Business College which is in Lafayette, Indiana. During that
                    period, I took a civil service test and in 1941, I came to Washington, DC. I
                    spent a year in Washington, DC, in the Department of the Interior, one year, and
                    then I went into the army, 1942 to 1945. My career in the army involved a lot of
                    secretarial work, mostly court reporting. I was overseas from 1944 to 1945, and
                    was mustered out in 1945. In 1946, I went to Berlin with the Department of the
                    Army and remained there until 1949.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there then during some of Berlin's most exciting
                        times.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: It was terribly exciting at that time because I was there during the
                    Berlin airlift in 1948.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes I was there at the same time, but unfortunately, with
                        all the Americans there our paths never crossed. What were you doing during
                        that period in Berlin?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: In Berlin, I was in the statistical branch, OMGUS.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is that? The Office of Military Government....</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>JONES: The Office of Military Government for the United States, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your impressions of the situation in Berlin at
                        that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Well, I certainly admired the Berliners with all their suffering, and when
                    I first went there, you were not supposed to fraternize or anything else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: However, that was honored in the breach as much as
                        anything else, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Absolutely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your life change at all during the blockade? Tell us
                        about conditions then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I can't say that we really suffered. I think that the main thing was the
                    power outages. You had a lot of candlelight dinners.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But there was no physical danger?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, no physical danger, none whatsoever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then, you were still with the army at that time. How
                        did you get into the State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Well, I should say that after Berlin, I was with, I guess it was ECA at
                    that time, three months in Korea in 1950. I was evacuated from there in June
                    1950.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get to Korea? Did you go with the Department
                        of the Army?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, it was the Economic Cooperation Administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, the ECA, I'm sorry, which today would be known as
                        AID.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: It's AID now. After Korea, I came back to the States.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excuse me, Ray, but tell us a bit about Korea. Those were
                        fantastically exciting days in Korea in 1950.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Tom, I was only there three months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before the attack?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I arrived in March and, in June, the communist onslaught came on, or the
                    north Koreans. I was there when it happened. I was evacuated from there to
                    Japan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there panic at the Embassy at the time? What were the
                        conditions like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I can't say it was really panic, but most of the time was spent on
                    destroying documents before word came to evacuate the place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ambassador Muccio was there I believe?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Ambassador Muccio, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were evacuated first to Tokyo, then to the
                        States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: To southern Japan and I finally arrived in Tokyo. I decided not to go back
                    to Korea. I resigned and came back to the States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Resigned from the ECA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: From the ECA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, pick up the story from that time. This was 1950 and
                        you were then obviously looking for work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I came back to Europe on my own and I had the nibble of a job in Hamburg
                    with the Military Security Board. I was in Hamburg from 1950 to 1952. But at the
                    end of 1950 I was offered a job with the State Department and that's how I came
                    in with the State Department being hired overseas.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you work for the Consul General?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, it was called Military Security Board and it was not with the
                    Consulate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not attached to the Consulate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No. I was very close with the American Consulate General personnel and
                    with the Consul General whose name at that time was Cowan I think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did the Military Security Board do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: They controlled the ship building.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hamburg being the largest port for that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Yes. It was a tripartite organization, French, British, and American.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find the work interesting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me about your attitude toward the Germans. Had that
                        changed or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: It had changed. I had a lot of good German friends and a lot of good
                    British friends, Hamburg being at that time the British zone of Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By this time you were on the State Department rolls.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I was on the State Department rolls and I got a direct transfer from
                    Hamburg to the Consulate General in Dusseldorf.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your job in Dusseldorf?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>JONES: Secretary to the Consul General.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: LaVerne Baldwin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I see. I remember it was quite a happy staff
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Oh yes. He had the best morale probably of anybody in Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that the Consular officers were well
                        managed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Extremely well managed. The Dusseldorf staff was probably the best I ever
                    served with and to this day every five or six years we get together for a
                    Dusseldorf reunion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard of that and I envy you. I think that's a
                        marvelous thing to do. Were you as a secretary included in post events or
                        not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Absolutely. There was no division between officers and staff
                    personnel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This gave you five straight years in Germany. And then
                        came a transfer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: After Dusseldorf I went on home leave and was assigned to Bern,
                    Switzerland which was my first Ambassadorship with Frances Willis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, this is a first for the Service, having first career
                        woman and a first for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Yes, I think I was very lucky to get to be secretary to the Ambassador at
                    that early stage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well I had known her in London and she was quite a
                        remarkable woman. Were there problems in Switzerland?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, Tom. No problems at all. I must say, it was unique to have been
                    assigned to her, because women in Switzerland do not vote.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they accepted her?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: They accepted her. I must say she was old style Foreign Service and I
                    learned a great deal from her. Q: During your period there, I believe, the Big
                    Four meeting took place, did it not? Eisenhower, and Khrushchev, and Bulganin
                    got together. Was that ...?</p>
                <p>JONES: I don't believe so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The spirit of Geneva arose from that? That would not have
                        affected you in Bern? I think that was 1955.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, Geneva was kind of a separate entity. We didn't do too much with
                    Geneva.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there many visitors in Switzerland that gave you
                        problems, or was it routine?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Not in Bern. Maybe Geneva and Zurich.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. Well, after your years with Willis you were
                        transferred to the Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I had illness in the family and I was transferred back to the Department.
                    1956 to 1958 I was on the Israel/Jordan desk. I think we had the 1957 war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The '56 war, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Yes. It was a lot of work. Much, much overtime, but very interesting
                    period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, of course. You were there approximately two
                        years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Two years. Almost two years to the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then in 1958?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>JONES: In 1958, I had the two years and I was ready for a transfer, and I had my
                    first experience in Africa. I went to Khartoum and I had a marvelous Ambassador
                    there who was a real Arabist, James Moose.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. He was one of the best Arabists in the
                        service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Khartoum was a sleepy little post and I had four marvelous years
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, the country hadn't been independent very long
                        then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, it was a British colony I would say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to travel about the country or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, it was impossible. No roads and it was very primitive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Most people remark on the heat there. I believe it's one
                        of the hottest posts in the Foreign Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: In the summertime it can go up to 120, but it is a very dry heat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see, unlike some of the West African posts where it
                        ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Yes, it's different.</p>
                <p>Q; Did you get to know any of the local people? Any Sudanese?</p>
                <p>JONES: Oh, yes. Very, very friendly types.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How important was it for our people to be able to speak
                        Arabic there? Could they get by with English.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No. English was the second language.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was useful to have Arabic, I'm sure.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>JONES: It was useful to have it, but everything at the Foreign Ministry was done
                    at the English level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We all know that in recent years there has been a raging
                        civil war in the Sudan between the north and the south. Was that evident in
                        your day?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, not at all. But they treated the southerners, Tom, like second-class
                    citizens.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. That is the difference in ethnic backgrounds, etc.
                        and religions I guess too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the main concerns of the US with regard to
                        Sudan, if you could tell us? Were we trying to recruit them as allies? Did
                        we want them to stay away from closer ties with the radical Arabs or
                        ...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: At that time, the Sudanese were kind of independent ....</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Since Sudan is a third-world country, we must have been
                        doing something to assist them. Was there an AID mission at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: When I arrived on the 1st of October, 1958, there was just beginning to
                    develop a large, large AID mission.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But there aren't many people in Sudan, are there?. It is a
                        very sparsely populated country.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, it's a very, very poor country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was our AID mission trying to do there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: To help them get on their feet. Exports they do. It's just like Egypt.
                    They raise a lot of cotton. Some of the world's best cotton. It's not as good as
                    Egyptian cotton, but very good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the AID mission a success in your view?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>JONES: I would say no.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why was that? We didn't put enough money in? Or it wasn't
                        well used?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: We put a lot of money in, but I would say it was probably for the wrong
                    projects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. Well, after your four years in Khartoum, Ray, I
                        notice you were transferred to Vienna. Quite a change of pace. Tell me about
                        your assignment there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Yes. I received a direct transfer from Khartoum to Vienna. I was there
                    from 1962 to 1964 and my position there was secretary to the DCM, Bob
                    Brandon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. He had a good deal of background in central
                        European affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Vienna was a delightful spot because our Ambassador there was Jimmy
                    Riddleberger. He was absolutely a delight. The staff adored him. Not only him,
                    but Mrs. Riddleberger who was ha!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As nice as they come.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Anybody who could serve with the Riddlebergers were indeed fortunate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know having been under him in Berlin, I remember well
                        how popular he was there. Did we have many problems in those days in Vienna
                        with the Austrians?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Not at all. Not at all. Anybody who is assigned to Vienna should take
                    advantage of all the amenities. Magnificent opera and delightful
                    restaurants.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is that where you began your well-known art
                        collection?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: It was in the beginning, yes. Vienna was extremely good shopping.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You certainly added to it in subsequent posts. Two years
                        in Vienna and then came another direct change.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>JONES: I was due for home leave and at that time, there was a new team getting
                    ready to go to Saigon. The Ambassador was General Maxwell Taylor, and the DCM
                    was Career Ambassador, U. Alexis Johnson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And did they ask you to go along with them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: And General Taylor, out of my files from the State Department chose me to
                    come to Saigon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I presume you'd not known him in Berlin because he had
                        arrived in Berlin in 1950?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I knew him vaguely but not well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he regard himself as successful in Saigon, one of the
                        most difficult missions in the world at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Well, General Taylor is a very astute general, but he could irritate the
                    Vietnamese, I mean lecturing to them and things like that. His assignment there
                    was for one year only. And I must say, of all my posts, I would say Saigon was
                    one of the most exciting that I had. We went through four or five coups d'etat
                    and it was just work, work, work, almost as events proved all the hard work was
                    for nothing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were there during the beginning of the great
                        American build-up, were you not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: The great American build-up. We came out to replace General Harkins I
                    think it was with Westie, General William Westmoreland. I had very close
                    relations with him. A lot of times on Sunday he would call me up and say: “I'm
                    going out on a little field trip. Would you like to go with me?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this General Westmoreland? It was very kind of
                        him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Yes, General Westmoreland. Of course, he was a prot�g� of Maxwell Taylor.
                    When he was at West Point, he was the number one cadet and that impressed
                    General Taylor who at that time was the Commandant at West Point. Westie was
                    kind of his prot�g�.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the atmosphere you found in Saigon among the
                        Vietnamese? Were they delighted we were there? Were they sullen? Were they
                        helpful?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Not too helpful, Tom. We always thought they didn't pull their weight.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me about the arrangement at the Embassy where you had
                        two seniors such as General Taylor and Ambassador Johnson. Did Taylor leave
                        the running of the Embassy to Johnson? Did they get into each other's
                        way?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No. I believe he and Johnson attended, maybe, Chinese training together,
                    so they were great friends, and Taylor was the one to help Johnson to come to
                    Vietnam. He chose him as his DCM.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Embassy in agreement with ... Policy in Washington
                        was promulgated in Washington or were there differences?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No. I don't believe so. There were no differences.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We saw the situation. Both ends were about the same. Why
                        did General Taylor leave there after a year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: It was agreed between him and President Johnson that he would take the
                    assignment for one year only.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. Did you feel yourself in any personal danger out
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No. None whatsoever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not even on your trips with General Westmoreland?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, although one night during period there we had several bombs. The
                    Embassy was bombed but I was back in the States on a trip with General Taylor
                    when the Embassy was blown up and there were quite a few casualties.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you left with the General and moved to the White
                        House with him, is that correct?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>JONES: Yes. He asked me to come back to the White House with him. I spent five
                    interesting years there from 1965 to 1970.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With the General?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: With the General. He was Special Assistant to President Johnson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then also presumably to President Nixon for a while if
                        it went on until 1970?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: At that time yes. General Taylor was head of the President's Advisory
                    Board. And it was interesting, Tom, during my 1965 to 1970. Every three or four
                    months we would make a trip back to Vietnam, because Taylor was advising Johnson
                    on Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you describe a little more about what the General
                        was doing from '65 till the end of the Johnson administration? Was he
                        concentrating almost entirely on the Vietnam war or was he doing other
                        things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, he was concentrating on the Vietnam war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he see eye to eye with the Pentagon and the State
                        Department or were there differences that you believe in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, no differences.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the LBJ's White House. How did
                        it function? What was it like to work for a man as prominent as he was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I was a great admirer of President Johnson. He had a very, very good
                    staff. The National Security Advisor when I first came back in 1965 was McGeorge
                    Bundy. After McGeorge Bundy was Walt Rostow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Two very prominent people who had a great influence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: And we had very good relations with those people. Many times, I would be
                    typing something and get it right out of the typewriter and Taylor would take it
                    directly to McGeorge Bundy and it would be pushed on directly to President
                    Johnson.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would you say of your time there with the Nixon White
                        House? How great was the difference between that and what had gone on with
                        LBJ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: It was completely different. Taylor being a democrat and he stayed on
                    about a year as the President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board after Nixon
                    came in. I could see the handwriting on the wall and I was about ready to be
                    posted anyway. So I left there and Taylor left there also in 1970.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the General retire from that or did he go to another
                        position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: He went on to another think tank operation. I think he was president of
                    that. I think they called it IDA. I don't know what the initials stand for, but
                    I had nothing to do with that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the General get along with Henry Kissinger in the
                        White House, or did they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I'm glad you brought that up. He got along with Kissinger very well, but
                    it was always difficult to get an appointment to see him. So he kept him on the
                    back burner a great deal of the time, although they were on a first name
                    basis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, you left the General at that time and presumably the
                        Department looked for an assignment for you. What did they find?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Well, there was nothing upcoming. There were two or three posts available
                    and I volunteered to go to West Africa, Monrovia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Monrovia. Well that's a .... I don't think they get many
                        volunteers ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: They don't get many volunteers for a post like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Describe it to us. What was your life like there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Very easy going. The Liberians were at that time extremely friendly, but
                    very sensitive. It was kinda like Amos and Andy land.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was President Tubman alive or had he died?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I was there during his funeral. A big US delegation was despatched there.
                    The interesting things during my period there was having Mahalia Jackson come in
                    for a concert. At the time, they wanted Eartha Kitt, but Eartha was a little bit
                    too much money so they settled on Mahalia Jackson. She gave a marvelous concert.
                    She was a great gospel singer, and the Liberians were pleased to have her at
                    half the money.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your ambassador during that period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: The first time I had ever worked for a black, Sam Westerfield.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, Ambassador Westerfield, I see. Did we have a lot of
                        problems with the Liberians? Was the Ambassador easy to work for?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No. He was very easy to work for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, after your experience there, you went back to Europe.
                        Tell us about that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Well, from Monrovia, I got a direct transfer to The Hague. This was in the
                    fall of 1971.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes I remember it well having been at The Hague at that
                        time. I might add that I know why you were brought there, because the
                        Ambassador, Bill Middendorf, had not had the best rapport with the first two
                        secretaries he'd been given and I think the service was looking for its
                        best. But, anyhow ...Then you arrived in The Hague, and with his reputation
                        which I presume you'd heard of. Did you have any doubt about going
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No doubt, whatsoever. Bill Middendorf was an extremely generous person to
                    work for. Q: Well I think this is partly due to your way of handling
                    ambassadors.</p>
                <p>JONES: I enjoyed his flair and his collection of art and taste. Exquisite.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I know that he reciprocated that because he was very
                        impressed with your art collection. Did you have any problems in your life
                        in The Hague or was it ...?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>JONES: None whatsoever. I enjoyed the Dutch very much. They were very good
                    friends. Q: And certainly a tremendous change of climate from Liberia.</p>
                <p>JONES: Definitely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now I notice that you left The Hague in 1972. Where did
                        you go then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: In 1972, yes. I was due for home leave, having had a direct transfer, and
                    built up time. I had a friend, I guess he was in the Director General's office
                    at that time, (Cleo Noel) who talked me into coming back to Khartoum where he
                    had just been assigned as Ambassador. I returned to Khartoum in 1973 for one day
                    only because during that time he was assassinated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that on the day you arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: It was the night before. I was en route to Khartoum but had had to spend
                    the night in Athens because there was a terrible haboob, a dust storm. We could
                    not land in Khartoum that evening. So I had to spend the night in Athens and we
                    took off the following morning. I think this was about March 4th, because I
                    think he was assassinated on March 3rd, 1973.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you arrived there at that terrible moment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I arrived there and it was complete chaos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because the DCM had been assassinated too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Yes, you're right. It was Cleo Noel and Curt Moore, plus a Belgian Charge.
                    Cleo Noel's wife, Lucille Noel. They were anxious to know what I wanted to do.
                    Stay in Khartoum or what I wanted to do. I said: “I want to return to the States
                    with the bodies,” which I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me. How were the Sudanese at that time? Were there
                        tremendous expressions of regret or were they sullen or...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Sorrowful because Cleo Noel had been assigned to Khartoum two or three
                    times, I think, Tom, during the American interests section which the Dutch were
                    handling during that time. I was always very happy in Khartoum.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know, you mentioned that in your earlier tour. I was
                        wondering because the Sudanese allowed the killers to get away, I
                        believe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: The killers, the Palestinians, escaped to Cairo.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you came back with the body and presumably Mrs. Noel,
                        too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: With Mrs. Noel and well, with both bodies I should say. A presidential jet
                    was dispatched to pick them up and actually the one who was handling all these
                    negotiations was very famous in the State Department. It was Bill Macomber.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: He had been at one time Ambassador to Jordan and during my time, back in
                    1956 to 1958, he was a Special Assistant to Secretary Dulles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So he brought the bodies back?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: He brought the bodies back, and I was scheduled to return to Khartoum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the bodies buried in Arlington Cemetery?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: In Arlington Cemetery. Both of them in Arlington Cemetery. And I was
                    scheduled eventually to go back to Khartoum. Well, friends in Personnel didn't
                    think it was a good idea and at that time we were in the process of establishing
                    diplomatic relations with China which was breaking. That was in 1973. I was
                    chosen to go to Peking, or Beijing they call it today, to be secretarial
                    assistant to David Bruce which I was excited to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, of course, with his tremendous reputation in the
                        service and the fact that you would be out there among the pioneers. It must
                        have been one of the more interesting experiences of your life.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Ah. He and his wife were just fantastic to work for. He was a marvelous
                    person. Both of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he and you and the others get cooperation from the
                        Chinese in opening up the Embassy there or were they difficult?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No. We had very good relations at the time I was there, '73 to '74. We
                    were not an Embassy. We were ... It was called United States Liaison Office,
                    USLO, they called it. I don't think full diplomatic relations were established
                    till about ... After Mr. Bruce left, and the first Ambassador was President
                    George Bush.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. I think it was President Carter who may have
                        established relations but I'm not certain about that. I mean raised it to
                        embassy status.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, all this time it was Nixon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, but I was referring mainly to moving USLO to
                        embassy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: That I don't remember. That we can look up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Ambassador Bruce think that he had been effective in
                        his mission there, doing what he wanted to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I think so. I believe so, but during that time, during our status with
                    USLO, it was kind of unique because the staff accepted no national day
                    receptions or anything else like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And of course they could not perform any of the normal
                        consular functions or anything like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Not at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was largely a reporting unit?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: It was indeed an honor to be accepted because there were about five or six
                    of us. We were the advance party to go into Peking. It was also a unique set up.
                    We had two DCMs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell us about that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>JONES: The two DCMs were John Holdridge who went on to be Ambassador to Singapore
                    and I don't know the other posts. And the other DCM was Alfred Jenkins.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes. They're both Chinese language men, I believe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: They're both Chinese experts. John was on the secret mission when we were
                    establishing relations with China. John was the one who went in with
                    Kissinger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. But how can two DCMs function when one has to be
                        sort of looking after the running of the Embassy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: During this period of time though there really wasn't much work to do
                    because we had no contacts or anything else. The first post I ever had where we
                    called them DCM 1 and DCM 2.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see, and I presume that in dealing with a country like
                        communist China, where everything was centralized, that the most effective
                        representation could only be done at the highest level, by Ambassador
                        Bruce.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: By Ambassador Bruce, yes. During that period of time, you had to get
                    permission from the Foreign Office to travel and that has changed over the
                    years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you personally able to see anything of China while
                        you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Canton on my way. I took a vacation back to Hong Kong and we had to stop
                    overnight in Canton and then proceed the next morning. All of that has changed.
                    It's simplified. Also I got to Tientsin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A seaport.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: A seaport, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you saw the great wall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I must say I did go back for three weeks to China in 1985 and traveled all
                    over the country.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you bothered with high level visitors during this
                        period of your service in the Liaison Office in Beijing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: We had very, very few.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a Kissinger visit at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Yes, we did have a Kissinger visit and that involved a lot of work. That
                    was very interesting because the whole staff was invited to a banquet at the
                    Great Hall and at that time Zhou En-lai was still alive. Very, very interesting
                    time, and also very good food. During the first six months, housing was very
                    difficult and before we all got apartments, we lived at the Peking Hotel. The
                    food there was just absolutely magnificent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So one did not suffer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: China has completely changed since the days when I was there. I think they
                    have enormous staff and maybe too big. I don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, after you left Beijing, tell us how that
                        happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: This was another situation. Mr. Bruce's assignment out there was for about
                    a year only, just like Maxwell Taylor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At his request?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: At his request, yes. I knew that he was leaving and I told him I wanted to
                    leave also when he left, and he said he'd help me all that he could. We did a
                    little soul searching and we found out the only thing good coming up was Berlin,
                    back to Berlin again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You'd come full circle?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I came full circle, yes. So I received a direct transfer in May, 1974 back
                    to Berlin and I stayed there until I retired in 1978. I had two very, very good
                    Ministers to work for. One was David Kline, and the other was Scott George.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. And how had Berlin changed since you were
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Tremendous. Very good housing. I still had a lot of good German friends
                    from my earlier days and the local staff at the US mission there was probably
                    some of the best I've ever seen in the Foreign Service. They could practically
                    run the place. Q: Now, we also had a mission in East Berlin at that time.</p>
                <p>JONES: It was probably about mid-seventies that we decided to establish relations
                    with East Berlin. I believe that first Ambassador was the renowned Senator John
                    Sherman Cooper, and his DCM was also quite au courant with Germany, Brandon
                    Grove.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get to meet these people or were you separated by
                        the wall or ...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No, because being stationed in Berlin, we had what you'd call a yellow
                    card that we could go through Checkpoint Charlie at will, anytime of day or
                    night. Our relations with Ambassador Cooper were very, very good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And what about the mission's relations with the Embassy in
                        Bonn? Were they close?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: They were very close. They left it to the Minister in Berlin to handle
                    everything and we were in constant telephonic conversations with the Ambassador
                    at that time. When I was there it was Marty Hillenbrand. I believe the DCM was
                    Frank Cash. He was the Minister.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know this has always been a problem over the years. The
                        things are seen a little differently from Bonn than they are in Berlin. but
                        if there is a good working relationship you can sort these things out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: There was a very good working relationship. Excellent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then Ray, this brings us to your retirement. Could
                        you tell me why you decided to retire at that time or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Tom, at that time, with all my military and government service I had about
                    thirty-seven and a half years. I retired when I was fifty-six. After that I
                    always thought I should have seen what the Department would come up with as
                    another post, but I think I'd had it. The Foreign Service, I can only say, was
                    very, very good to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You certainly had interesting and varied posts on a number
                        of continents. I must say you never shied away from the difficult jobs,
                        too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: And I had marvelous ambassadors to work for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a story we don't always hear. Well, looking back on
                        those happy years, Ray, did you as a male secretary, did you ever feel that
                        there was any prejudice or discrimination against you, since there were very
                        few male secretaries.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: None whatsoever. I would say, when I came in, I was probably the only male
                    secretary in the Foreign Service. I don't know today how many there are, but if
                    they are any good they should advance rapidly. I would say one thing, just
                    because I was a male secretary, if you look back, usually you'd think you would
                    be available only for hardship posts. Most of my posts were in the fleshpots of
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you did have your Liberia and your Khartoum and your
                        Beijing, etc. But I agree with you, you did fairly well. But you were also
                        serving with very prominent men. Did I neglect to mention Saigon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I will say even some of those posts. Saigon was a deferential post. They
                    called it a hardship post. I don't know, we had every luxury in Saigon, good
                    housing, good food, good commissary, and even Peking. It was a pleasure to be
                    assigned there. It was a 15% deferential. I don't know why. It was great.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the female secretaries resent your presence or
                        not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No. I always had good rapport, Tom, with the secretaries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a delicate question, but I'll ask you. Having had
                        so many chiefs, could you rank order them and say who's the best to work
                        for, and the second best, etc.? And who's the most difficult to work
                        for?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I think I would have to put number one on the list was probably Maxwell
                    Taylor. He was so well organized and he taught me a great deal about
                    administration. Number two I would say would be David Bruce.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Those would be your top choices? Would you venture a guess
                        as to who was the most difficult to work for?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I would say that the most difficult to work for was probably Frances
                    Willis although she taught me a great deal. It was my first post and she taught
                    me a lot about personnel, and everything else, but was one of these persons if
                    you wanted a job done well you had to do it yourself. I used to tell her: “You
                    sound just like my mother!” But she was a great person also.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What you're saying is she didn't delegate a lot.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: She wouldn't even delegate anything to her DCM because she really didn't
                    need a DCM. She did everything herself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One last question on personalities. Of all the ambassadors
                        you worked for, who would you say was the most effective in what he
                        did?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Maxwell Taylor. Tom, you think of the military as just mostly military. I
                    won't say that he was always the most diplomatic, but this general spoke about
                    six or seven languages. He was so educated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Including Japanese.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: And we did draft after draft for the final product. But the final product
                    was a work of art. I helped him, not on government time, but I helped him write
                    three books. And I would say the best drafter I have ever seen is probably David
                    Bruce. What a command of English!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ray, how were your relationships over the years with the
                        ambassadorial spouses? Sometimes I know these can be very tricky
                        particularly for a man in your position as the Ambassador's right hand
                        man.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: Well I find you're making a big mistake if you don't butter them up, but
                    you're making a big mistake if you fight the wife. That's half the battle. If I
                    had a problem I'd usually mention it to the Ambassador and let him take it up
                    with her. It's much better that way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Without going into many names here, could you tell me who
                        was the easiest ambassadorial spouse that you had to work with?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>JONES: I would say Evangeline Bruce. I'm still in touch with her, you know. She
                    lives in Georgetown. I'm invited to her cocktail parties, and dinners, and stuff
                    like this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did any of these ambassadorial wives try to treat you as
                        their social secretaries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No. Not at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And presumably you would not have stood for it for long,
                        had they tried?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Finally, I would ask if you would recommend, these days,
                        that a young man entering the service take up a secretarial career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I don't believe so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's interesting. Please tell us a little about
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JONES: I'm not so sure that I would recommend the Foreign Service today. The
                    Foreign Service has changed since right before I retired. I think you might move
                    ahead quicker in private industry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, thank you very much Ray.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This has been an interview of Ray Jones who had a long career as secretarial
                    assistant in the Foreign Service. This is Tom Dunnigan and the date is August
                    23, 1994.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
