<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000733">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Kenneth MacCormack </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Information Series</p>
                <p>KENNETH MACCORMAC</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: G. Lewis Schmidt </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: January 5, 1989</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ken has had a long career with USIA, and I would like to
                        ask him to start out by giving us a short bio sketch of where he originated,
                        where he came from, what his education was, and then progress to how he got
                        into USIA in the first place. Ken, will you take it from there, staring with
                        your bio sketch?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Biosketch</p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: Thanks, Lew. I was born in Cordova, Alaska. It was before Alaska was a
                    state, before it was a territory. It was only a possession in 1911. I lived
                    there until I was seven years old, upon my father's death. My mother being a San
                    Franciscan, we moved back to San Francisco again, and I went to school here. I
                    went most of my life to Catholic schools, St. Joseph's Academy in Berkeley, then
                    on to Sacred Heart in San Francisco. After that, the University of San
                    Francisco, where I graduated in 1933.</p>
                <p>After that I went to work for the San Francisco Examiner for a couple of years as
                    a reporter, not a very good one. In between times, while going to high school, I
                    used to go to sea. Shipping out of San Francisco in the summertime, I could
                    usually make a couple of round trips to Australia and back, usually getting jobs
                    aboard passenger ships where I would be free in port, and therefore, got to see
                    a good deal of the South Pacific.</p>
                <p>At the outbreak of the war, I was going to graduate school at Columbia University
                    in New York, on leave of absence from the American Red Cross. I've forgotten to
                    mention Red Cross again. I had joined the American Pacific Chapter of the
                    American Red Cross in 1939 or '40. I was on leave of absence from the Red Cross
                    at the time of the outbreak of war in 1941.</p>
                <p>I came back and worked as a field representative in the seven western states, and
                    eventually served as the representative of the American Red Cross in Alaska for
                    a year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was during the war?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>Army Service During War Years and After 1945,Military Government</p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: This was during the war. I was inducted in the Army in 1941 or '42,
                    and after basic training in Monterey and Texas, was shipped overseas to England.
                    There I was assigned to the special service department of the 67th General
                    Hospital for two or three years.</p>
                <p>At the end of the war, I received orders transferring me from England to APO-742.
                    I didn't know where it was, but found out it was Berlin. I was still in the
                    Army, assigned to military government Berlin in the Public Health and Welfare
                    Department. I became a civilian in Berlin; we were civilianized. Then I was
                    shipped out, still in the military government, to the Office of Military
                    Government Bavaria, also in the Public Health and Welfare Department.</p>
                <p>When did the State Department take over?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think it was around 1949.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1944: Suddenly MacCormac Is In Department of StateAssigned to HICOGS Education
                    and Culture Division</p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: I think it was in 1949. All of a sudden, I found myself working for
                    the State Department. One day, somewhere in that time, three Foreign Service
                    officers came. They were looking for people who might be interested in joining
                    the Foreign Service. I thought, “I might as well take the examination.” My
                    German was pretty good, and I had some college French. After an interview, I
                    found out I was in State. (Laughs)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you went to State, were you still with HICOG?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: HICOG. Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you still in the health side of it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>MACCORMAC: No. The department was called Education and Culture Division of HICOG,
                    I guess it was. HICOG started a program of selecting Germans to go to the United
                    States for the three D's. What were they? Democratization, de-nazification, and
                    there was another one. My job was to work on the selection of Bavarians to go to
                    the United States. Originally it was a leader's program, people who were known
                    to our government, but had not been outside of Germany for 12 years. That was a
                    fairly big program. Then it developed into a university student program,
                    selecting students from the several Bavarian universities to go to America, and
                    also we developed the AFS program, together with that, for young high school
                    students to go live in the United States for a year. Then a young farm youth
                    program for young Bavarian farm youth to live with American farmer families for
                    a year. That lasted until 1954. All of a sudden, I received orders transferring
                    me to Seoul, Korea. (Laughs)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this time that you were working with these exchange
                        programs, did you have any occasion to follow up on those who had returned,
                        and find out what their impressions had been? Did you think the program was
                        successful in its goals?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: We had a big follow-up program. As a matter of fact, there was one man
                    in the exchange-of-persons office responsible for follow-up. We kept a good
                    record of who went to the United States, and we saw a lot of them when they came
                    back. As a matter of fact, there was an association formed in Munich called the
                    Columbus Gasellshaft of returnees from the United States. It's still going, as a
                    matter of fact. I was in Munich a couple of years ago, and Columbus Gasellshaft
                    had a luncheon for me with a lot of old-timers who had been in the early
                    exchange programs.</p>
                <p>Then to Korea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel that the program was quite successful? When
                        the people came back, did they seem to be impressed with America, or did
                        they seem to be somewhat weaned away from the Nazi philosophy, if they had
                        previously been infected by it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>MACCORMAC: There was no evidence at all, ever, of their being Nazis. They were
                    Germans, but they were certainly deeply impressed by the United States,
                    particularly the professional people, doctors, dentists, lawyers, other
                    professionals who had been out of touch with professions in the outside world
                    for over 12 years, during the Nazi time. The university students also, many of
                    them received advanced degrees in the United States. Our only loses were some of
                    the young ones who got married, but that was sort of par for the course. You had
                    to expect that. We didn't lose too many. We were always unhappy when we did,
                    because we wanted them back in Germany again. I'm still in touch with many of
                    them. As a matter of fact, last September I was a house guest of a university
                    professor at the University of Munich. This professor was sent to the United
                    States when he was a student at the university in the 1950s. He was sent to the
                    University of Mississippi. He had a great experience, finally came back with a
                    doctor's degree, and now is a full professor at the university. So I'm still in
                    touch with many, many of them, particularly at Christmas time.</p>
                <p>1954 - Assigned to Seoul, Korea</p>
                <p>I arrived in Seoul, Korea, in July of 1954. Bob Spier was the public affairs
                    officer there, and Ellis Briggs was the ambassador. Going to a war-torn country
                    after leaving Bavaria, with all its amenities, was sort of a shock. But
                    actually, Korea was one of the best posts I was ever assigned to, particularly
                    because of my great admiration for the Korean people.</p>
                <p>My job there was in the cultural affairs office, and I was particularly assigned
                    to starting and developing a book translation program. I forget how many
                    American books we had translated and published while I was there, but it was in
                    the hundreds. The way it was done was to contract with young Korean professors
                    who had been to the United States, who were interested in making some extra
                    money by translating books, and then we assisted the publishers by making
                    available newsprint to them of which we had quantities in Korea. As I say, it
                    was a great post. I made many friends their, enjoyed it very, very much.</p>
                <p>Following Korea, I was assigned to Japan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You translated several hundreds of books into Korean from
                        English. Did you have a wide readership then? I presume you put these in
                        libraries after that, but did you have a commercial distribution also</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: We had a commercial distribution. That was one of the big problems.
                    Korea didn't have a book distributing system, but one was developed with the
                    book translation program. The books went all over Korea and were widely sought
                    after. As a matter of fact, the ambassador used to pass out translations of
                    American books, histories, biographies, to his Korean colleagues, as well as to
                    other members of government.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>I think one of the interesting things about my stay in Korea was my association
                    with (Chang Myon) John M. Chang, as he was known. He was a cultural leader and
                    educator. He had a school and was a very prominent Catholic. He was in
                    opposition to the Korean government. As a matter of fact, he was elected from
                    the opposition party to be vice president of Korea while I was there. So Syngman
                    Rhee was president, but his successor was John M. Chang, who eventually became
                    president of Korea, a marvelous man. I'm afraid he's dead now. The morning he
                    was elected, he sent a note to me asking me to get him a bulletproof vest.
                    (Laughs) And I did. I got one from the other agency. Eventually, he was shot at.
                    I don't know if the vest saved him, but he had the vest.</p>
                <p>1956 - One Year Assignment to Japan</p>
                <p>Then on to Japan, which was a one-year tour. The purpose of it was to develop a
                    follow-up program for the many hundreds of Japanese who had been to the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What year was it that you went to Japan? What month, do
                        you remember? It must have been June or after, because I had been in Japan
                        for four and a half years, and I left at the end of May of '56.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: I remember meeting you in Korea one time when you came over on
                    military.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right, I remember that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: It must have been the summer of 1956.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By that time, Johnny McKnight was PAO in Korea, I
                        think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: That's right. He was PAO in Korea. We formed, among other things, a
                    number of American University Alumni Associations in Japan, and I found this was
                    fairly easy to do because the Japanese like to work in groups. For instance, we
                    had a big alumni group from the University of California, from Stanford, with
                    regular meetings, and then we had regular follow-up meetings of returned
                    Fulbright alumni at Fulbright headquarters. I had published at that time a
                    newsletter which went out monthly to 3,000 Japanese returnees, and I think it's
                    still going. As a matter of fact, I have some of the early editions bound and
                    published, and I have them all wrapped up. I'm going to send them back to the
                    Fulbright Foundation in Japan, because they're an interesting history of the
                    Foundation in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you had our meetings, were they primarily social, or
                        were they study groups? How did they function?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: The meetings were primarily meetings with visiting American scholars,
                    professors, political leaders, and that sort of thing. We would select and
                    invite Japanese returnees who we thought would be interested in meeting these
                    individuals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have fairly sizable meetings?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: Oh yes. There was a good deal of interest in it, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Since you don't seem to have very many fruitful memories
                        of Washington, we'll go on to your next assignment.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1960 - Bangkok, Thailand</p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: In 1960 I was assigned to Bangkok, Thailand. I had six months of Thai
                    language training at Foreign Service Institute, and then I continued in Thai
                    language training all the time I was in Thailand. As you know, it's a difficult
                    language. Languages are difficult for me, anyway.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They are for me, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: I had to spend a lot of time at it. But it was worthwhile. I was
                    assigned as deputy PAO at that time to Bangkok. The public affairs officer was
                    Howard Garnish, with whom I'm still in contact and look forward to seeing
                    whenever I go to Washington. He and his wife were very, very kind to me.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>One of the interesting things, as far as I'm concerned, in Thailand was my
                    association with the Siam Society. Through the Siam Society, which is a cultural
                    organization which has been going in Bangkok since 1904, I came in contact and
                    met practically all of the cultural leaders in Thailand, including the king and
                    queen. This was helpful in many, many ways. My great and good friend in the Siam
                    Society was Prince Dhani, who was the king's uncle, a delightful man who was
                    then in his sixties. His grandmother was one of the consorts of King Monqut.
                    When Prince Dhani was a boy, he was raised in the grand palace and carried
                    around until he was 13. When he was 13, he was sent to Rugby in England for an
                    education, and stayed in England for many years. He's was a graduate of
                    Cambridge, and he spoke flawless English in a rather Victorian manner. He wrote
                    beautifully, a highly educated man. He had been under the absolute monarchy, at
                    one time the minister of education. As I say, through Prince Dhani I got to know
                    some of the cultural leaders and, as a matter of fact, some of the cultural
                    leaders became political leaders, among them Kukrit Parmoj.</p>
                <p>A good deal could be done through personal acquaintance with the nobility and
                    aristocracy. Of course, the king in Thailand is greatly revered, as is his wife.
                    Among my other acquaintances at that time was Prince Wan, also a delightful man,
                    English educated, of the old school. When I knew him, he was rector of Tamasat
                    University, and at one time he became prime minister. Then I remember another
                    time somebody wanted an interview with him, and for some reason or other, I was
                    the only one in the embassy who knew him.</p>
                <p>This was during the time U. Alexis Johnson was the ambassador, and he was
                    followed by Ken Young, ambassador to Thailand. It was shortly following Ken
                    Young's appointment there that we had the visit of the Vice President, Lyndon
                    Johnson.</p>
                <p>Vice President Lyndon Johnson Visits Bangkok!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which I understand was something of a disaster.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: Something of a disaster. Right. (Laughs)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you care to make a few remarks about that? I think
                        it would be very interesting to get your impressions and your report of what
                        happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>MACCORMAC: I found it was very difficult to deal with the Vice President's party.
                    We had been planning at that time — “we,” that is USIA. I was Acting PAO at that
                    time because Howard Garnish was on home leave. We had been planning a reception
                    at the Erawan Hotel for the Thai Press Association, which was celebrating its
                    50th anniversary. We had invitations out, and it was going to be a big gala
                    affair of which we, USIS, were the host. We did not know at the time that Lyndon
                    Johnson had refused the Thais' offer of one of the palaces in which to live
                    while he was in Bangkok, and he moved into the Erawan Hotel, where we were
                    having our reception. I thought as long as he was going to be in the hotel, he
                    might like to met the Thai Press Association. So I phoned to members of his
                    party in Taipei and in Hong Kong, and asked if the Vice President would be
                    willing or interested in meeting with the Thai Press Association in his hotel,
                    and was assured that he would be happy to. So all was laid on.</p>
                <p>Our party was going on and on and on downstairs, and I was waiting for the Vice
                    President to come down. The party was half over and he wasn't there, so I asked
                    somebody to go up and get him or see if they could coax him down. It was Carl
                    Rowan. Remember Carl Rowan?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was the director.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: He was the director of the Agency at that time. Carl went upstairs.
                    After a funny story that I can't record, he came down and told the story about
                    the Vice President. Anyway, the Vice President eventually came down and he
                    stayed about half an hour and talked to the Thai Press. It was a big success as
                    far as that went. But I was getting gray hair, wondering if he was coming to the
                    party at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At this point I'd like to ask you why did he refuse to
                        stay in one of the palaces?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: I think he refused to stay in the Phitsanolok House because of
                    security reasons. That's the story they gave, anyway. But it took Bangkok a long
                    time to get over the visit of Lyndon Johnson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was one story going around when I got there, which
                        may be apocryphal, said that he moved into the mansion, didn't like the
                        drapes, and asked the imperial household to change the drapes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: It's a story that could have happened, knowing what he subjected the
                    post to. But I never heard that story. I don't know whether it's true or not. He
                    was a difficult man to please, anyway. That was 1963.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your tour was up in 1965.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Reassignment to Washington: 1965</p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: Right. I was reassigned to Washington. I think it was called IAF, the
                    Far East Division. My job was to be the desk officer for Thailand, Laos, Burma,
                    and Cambodia. We had lots of troubles at that time in Laos, particularly. Of
                    course, the war was going on in Vietnam, but it didn't affect Thailand very
                    much, except Thailand became a great R&amp;R center, rest and recuperation
                    center, for American troops in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>The Washington tour was interesting because having responsibility for these four
                    desks in IAF, I got trips out to the various countries while I was there, which
                    I enjoyed very much. I'd never been to Burma before. I think it was at that time
                    that the Burmese government closed the USIA library in Rangoon, an excellent
                    library, much appreciated by the students and people in Rangoon. But Ne Win, who
                    had become prime minister or president, I guess, didn't want the American
                    influence, though the rest of Burma did. I remember he closed the library, but
                    asked the embassy to give him the books. (Laughs) I didn't see any point in
                    that, so the library was closed, and I moved the books to other countries, where
                    they appreciated them. Zelda Graham, I think her name was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She was the long-time librarian there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She had virtually built that library.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: She had built the library.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She was devastated at the...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: Absolutely right. Zelda Graham had many, many friends in Burma,
                    including Ne Win's wife Kitty, his second wife. But there was nothing that could
                    be done about it. All of my colleagues who have known Burma and lived there have
                    loved the Burmese, have many friends there, and even now look forward to the
                    days when Burma will become an open country again instead of a ruined
                    country.</p>
                <p>MacCormac Returns to Thailand: 1967</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>I was getting old, and I knew that I would have to retire in 1971, so I asked to
                    be returned to Thailand. An opening came up as the cultural affairs officer, and
                    I was assigned back to Bangkok as cultural affairs officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You replaced Frank Tenny.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: I replaced Frank Tenny. I met Frank Tenny last week at Greg
                    Henderson's memorial service in Cambridge.</p>
                <p>It was a job I liked, back among old friends. I got my old house back again. One
                    of the perks in Bangkok was a beautiful old Chinese house which I had leased
                    when I first got there in 1960, on the same street as the USIA office, and it
                    was a great place for entertaining. It was wide open, lots of room, lots of
                    space. I had a number one, which is known as the person in charge of your
                    household, from 1960. Her name was Foo. Foo ran his house with an iron hand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was she Chinese?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: Foo was a Vietnamese, totally uneducated, although she could speak
                    five languages, Vietnamese, Lao, French, Thai, and English. The reason she
                    wanted to work for me, because there was a school nearby she wanted her three
                    children to go to. This little lady who had never been to school in her life
                    arranged that her children got into this very good school near where I lived,
                    and all three of them went on to the university. I'm still in touch with
                    her.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they go to the university in Thailand?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: The university in Thailand. Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tomasat or Chulalongkorn</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: Chulalongkorn.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Phil Damon in Thailand when you were there? Did he
                        return in 1970 or '71?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>MACCORMAC: Yes. Philip Damon, whom I'd known in my German days in Germany, and
                    who had married a delightful French girl who came with the ballet from Nice to
                    Munich, he was in Bangkok when I got there. Phil and Genevieve Damon were very
                    close to the king and queen. They were both fluent in French, and Phil was a
                    big, outgoing guy, a great golfer, but sadly enough, he contracted multiple
                    sclerosis, and he was back in Washington when this developed. He always thought
                    if he could get back to Thailand, he'd get better, but, of course, he didn't.
                    Through agency help, he was brought back to Thailand as an employee without
                    compensation, I think it was called. There he had the use of the APO and the
                    commissary. The king and queen kept him in Chulalongkorn hospital with day and
                    night nurses for the first year he was there, Phil is still living. I go to see
                    him whenever I go to Bangkok. He's totally bedridden. I think he's nearly blind.
                    His only source of happiness is the books on records which he gets from the
                    Library of Congress.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is his association with the king terminated now?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: No. The associations with the king and queen are still strong. As a
                    matter of fact, his wife Genevieve, is a great friend of the Queen, and
                    Genevieve is the only non-Thai that I know of who has been given a title by the
                    king. She's now known as Khun Ying Damon. She runs a small ballet school, and
                    she's been a marvelous, marvelous wife to Philip Damon, who has had this
                    terrible affliction. His three daughters are now married and living in
                    Thailand.</p>
                <p>The Huge Cultural Center, AUA (American University Association) Was Given A Grant
                    to Build Present Building. It is Enormous Success.</p>
                <p>One of the first things I did when I first got to Thailand in 1960, was to
                    deliver a check of $280,000 to the American University Alumni Association, AUA,
                    to build an AUA language center. All the preparatory work had been done by the
                    people who preceded me, but the check just happened to come when I was there. To
                    make a long story short, we got crown land on which to build the AUA building,
                    and I still have pictures of it. It was on three old fish ponds on a very long,
                    long lot, but in a good location. We moved the AUA center, finally, when it was
                    built, from Sarankom Palace, way down the river on the other side of town, to
                    the new location. It's been a big and going concern ever since. When I was last
                    in Thailand, the AUA center was operating from 7:00 in the morning until 9:00 at
                    night, teaching English to Thai. This is something they want, and AUA knows how
                    to do it. Small classes, teaching spoken English. By the time the pupils are
                    through one year of this course, they can really speak English. As a matter of
                    fact, we moved the USIS library and cultural center from Patpong Road, which had
                    become infamous, to the AUA center, and it's now a USIS center, as well as the
                    American University Alumni Association.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When I was there, we closed the American library and we
                        moved all the books, donated them to the center. Is that the move to which
                        you are referring?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: That's right, yes. After the building of the AUA classrooms, another
                    grant was made to build the large library in front of the AUA classroom
                    building, and it's one of the best libraries in Thailand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you said you acquired the crown property, what did we
                        do, pay the crown for it? Or did they donate it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: It was on a long-term lease, which is a nominal amount. I forget the
                    amount which we pay the crown property division every year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So all the major grant went to the construction.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: The major grant went to the construction of the building. Right. There
                    are 35 classrooms, and it's amazing to see them all in use, all the time. The
                    success, of course, was the use of American teachers. We used only American
                    teachers, even though those who had never taught before, we taught them how to
                    teach.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were teaching English with an American accent and
                        American vocabulary.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: Precisely. As a matter of fact, some of our colleagues in Australia,
                    New Zealand, and England were sort of miffed that we wouldn't use them, but we
                    always insisted on using Americans.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Johnson was one of the firm backers of the AUA and all of its
                    activities. I'll always remember him saying, in a country team meeting, “I never
                    put pressure on people to participate in social events, but if there are any
                    events at the AUA center, I want you there.” It was very well attended by
                    Americans. Usually there was an annual show put on by the AUA membership, to
                    which the king and queen came. There were lectures, films, big auditoriums. It's
                    a very impressive and worthwhile institution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard people say they think that the AUA, which is,
                        in fact, our cultural center in Bangkok, probably did more for American-Thai
                        relationships than all the rest of the USIS programs.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>MACCORMAC: I think there's no question about it. It's something we know how to
                    do, something the Thai wanted, both in teaching of English, use of the library,
                    and use of the film center, lecture halls, all that sort of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was directing the center during the time you were
                        there as CAO?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: Gordon Schneider was director of the language center when I first got
                    to Bangkok, and he was the one instrumental in the move to the new location. He
                    was followed by Milton Leavitt, who had two tours as director of AUA. I remember
                    when we were moving the USIA cultural center to AUA, there was some hesitancy on
                    the part of the board of directors, which was headed by a Thai, Phra Bisal
                    Sukhumvit who is still living. He didn't want to have an American propaganda
                    institution. So Leavitt went over all the programs we had at our own cultural
                    center the preceding year, and convinced Phra Bisal that it was not going to be,
                    and never would be, an American “propaganda” center. The programs we put on
                    there over the years are very, very well received by the Thai.</p>
                <p>1971: MacCormac Retires But Returns in 1978 toDirect Thai Fulbright
                    Foundation</p>
                <p>I retired in July of 1971. Then in 1977, I received a telephone call from the
                    Thailand Fulbright Foundation, asking me if I'd come back for two years to
                    direct the Fulbright Foundation in Thailand. I was only too happy to go back,
                    and so I spent '78 and '79 back in Thailand as the director of the Fulbright
                    Foundation, working with a lot of people whom I'd known in the past. For
                    instance, one of our early grantees, Dr. Qasim, was then rector of Chulalongkorn
                    University. A lot of the young Thai we'd sent in the early sixties for advanced
                    degrees to the United States had come back and were in very prominent education
                    and cultural positions in Thailand. So it was easy to deal with them.</p>
                <p>We had good support from the department, not because we were such a good
                    foundation, but because no money could be spent in Burma, Laos, or Cambodia. So
                    we had extra money for the Fulbright Foundation in Thailand, and we usually sent
                    30 or 40 graduate students to the United States every year. Most of them came
                    back with doctorates.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were there on your first tour, I imagine there
                        probably was not much student agitation, but I know that at the time that I
                        was approaching the end of my tour, the students had become quite activist,
                        and a number of them were getting into left-wing organizations. Did you have
                        much trouble with that during your last tour there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: I never did at all, no. I was very much surprised to read and learn
                    about these student riots and uprising after I'd been away from Thailand. To me,
                    it was so un-Thai to have this open rebellion against authority. But nothing
                    like that ever happened while I was there.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned a little earlier that a number of the people
                        who had been patrons and even, perhaps, students at the AUA, subsequently
                        went out and became prominent people not only in the Thai educational scene,
                        but also in the political field. Can you name a couple of them in the
                        political arena? Were these the Pramoj brothers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: The two Pramoj brothers were particularly influential in the political
                    field. Kukrit became Prime Minister of Thailand. He is his own man and quite a
                    mercurial man, sometimes a great friend, sometimes a great enemy of the United
                    States, was manager, owner, and publisher of the most prominent newspaper in
                    Thailand. The Siam Rath, a paper that everyone reads. He was also the man who
                    played the part of the prime minister in the film, “The Ugly American.” We
                    journeyed to the United States on the same plane one time, and I remember, I
                    think it was during the time when he was doing this film, I addressed him as Mr.
                    Prime Minister, in jest, never thinking he would really be prime minister again
                    one day. His brother, an older brother, Seni, had been the Thai minister to the
                    United States in Washington at the time of the Japanese invasion of Thailand, at
                    the time when Thailand declared war on the United States. But we were never at
                    war with Thailand because Seni refused to deliver the Thai declaration to the
                    Government of the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a fascinating country. You spent much more time there
                        than I did, and I know you loved it. Do you have anything further that you
                        wish to add, Ken?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MACCORMAC: No, Lew. I guess that about covers it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, thank you very much, Ken. I will return the
                        transcript of this interview for editing as soon as possible.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
