<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000812">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">A Statement by Hope Meyers</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Program Foreign Service Spouse Series</p>
                <p>HOPE MACBRIDE MEYERS</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Self</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: April 29, 1991</p>
                <p>A Statement by Hope Meyers</p>
                <p>I'm about to begin an interview, very short one, on the experiences leading up to
                    and including the work of the first-named Ad Hoc Committee on Spouses and later
                    the Research Committee on Spouses. This period of time dates from approximately
                    1974 through 1976 for most of that period. I am talking at my apartment in
                    Washington, DC., on April 29, 1991.</p>
                <p>If this record seems very thin and with little documentation, the reason is first
                    of all because I have given most of my substantive records to FLO or to people
                    who were using them at the time and had need of them. Secondly, because the
                    sequence of events occurred so rapidly that there was very little time or even
                    less energy to put down on any paper the records of meetings that were held,
                    etc. Therefore, this will be a very sketchy record that I am putting together
                    here for the first time. I have done it despite paucity of the substantive
                    material simply because I felt that this was, though a very brief interval, one
                    to which very little attention has been paid so far and certainly the importance
                    of which has been much belittled, I think.</p>
                <p>If 1974 seems like a very early date chronologically compared to other dates that
                    have been given for the beginning of the work of the Ad Hoc Committee, I date it
                    from then because it was during that year that Florence Leonhart, known as
                    “Pidge”, who was then president of the AAFSW, asked me if I would act as liaison
                    between the WAO (Women's Action Organization) and AAFSW. I was delighted to
                    accept her offer because I realized that it would give me for the first time
                    some idea of the work that organization was doing and how it was being
                    accomplished.</p>
                <p>It was undoubtedly because I had attended many of those meetings that in the end
                    there was an opportunity to begin the Ad Hoc Committee on Spouses, of which I
                    was one of three co-chairmen; the other two, alas, have gone far afield — one
                    left the Government altogether following her divorce, the other, although
                    continuing her career, I believe, has dropped from my sight and I no longer know
                    how to reach her. I will come to that shortly.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>In any case, I began as quickly as I could attending the meetings of the
                    organization to which I had been appointed as liaison. I immediately realized
                    what an extraordinary opportunity had been offered me, because for the first
                    time I realized how important it was that there should be a group of women who
                    were meeting regularly, literally physically inside the Department of State, at
                    an appointed time, with an agenda, and whose membership, most importantly,
                    included people who from prior experience had great knowledge or at least
                    considerable knowledge of how to get things done and to whom to go to accomplish
                    that purpose.</p>
                <p>Not only that, of course — all of them were professionals and they dealt with
                    problems in a professional way, i.e., rapidly, with no or very little attention
                    to anything other, in terms of assignment of responsibility than to the person
                    who could best accomplish the job at hand. This led to quick results and a
                    minimum of time spent during meetings discussing how, when, where, why, and so
                    forth. These were all more or less known generally to the membership and
                    measurably facilitated the use of time.</p>
                <p>Therefore, much later, in the spring of 1975 when I was approached by Dorothy
                    Stansbury, who had just finished her term as first president of the WAO (Women's
                    Action Organization), I was delighted to take up the opportunity and offered no
                    objections whatsoever. She asked if I would meet with two other people who
                    represented a different aspect of the spouse population at the time. One was
                    Anna Relph, who at the time was taking a course in women's studies at George
                    Washington University but who planned to do substantive work afterward, possibly
                    outside the Government although her husband was then a Foreign Service Officer.
                    The second was Carmen Williams. She was one of the early “tandem couples” and up
                    to that time the Department had done very little, besides establishing the
                    principle of tandem couples, to follow their careers and to make any attempt to
                    regularize the assignment process regarding tandem couples, nor had it spoken
                    with them as a group on how that group felt about the process was going
                    forward.</p>
                <p>So I of course represented the so-called traditional unemployed spouse. I didn't
                    feel myself “traditional” at all but certainly I was “unemployed” at the time.
                    At any rate, a meeting was set using the facilities provided through the
                    auspices of the Women's Action Organization. This meant that the first meeting
                    of the Ad Hoc Committee took place inside the Department and provided easy
                    access to those people both within and outside the Department. Meetings were
                    held at lunch hour and were kept short because the rooms were in great demand
                    and we had very little time to cover our agenda. To my astonishment, having
                    heard by word of mouth or direct solicitation, the first group numbered,
                    surprisingly, about 20 people. This indicated that there were many people other
                    than those immediately present who had an interest in the subject and were
                    perfectly ready to go forward and do whatever was necessary.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>We had only a brief meeting on that first occasion, as I recall, but it was
                    agreed that somebody — it turned out to be me — should provide some kind of an
                    agenda for discussion at later meetings which would cover the various
                    possibilities that we, as a group, might begin to look at. Thinking back on
                    this, I realize that many of those in that group were already employed in the
                    Department of State in various bureaus and were denominated by that great name
                    of PIT (Part-time, Intermittent, Temporary), which meant that they had a
                    particular interest in bettering their own working conditions. All of them were
                    married to Foreign Service Officers and had in addition the concerns of spouses
                    as spouses quite apart from the fact that they were actively interested and
                    concerned with the matter of employment.</p>
                <p>Fortunately, I have copies of the first agenda, I believe, that we used as a
                    basis for discussion. Discussions went on at two-week intervals during a good
                    part of midsummer. The conclusions that we reached were not, certainly,
                    world-shaking but they were of interest perhaps to the record. We concluded that
                    because of the domestic demands on our time — meaning family and so on — as well
                    as professional, our time was so limited that we could not accomplish all that
                    we had wanted or thought we might be able to do. Instead, we decided, I think
                    sensibly, to concentrate on the questions revolving around employment of spouses
                    and the difficulties the Department presented to them in broadening the
                    opportunities open to qualified women whom otherwise it was ignoring both in
                    Washington and overseas.</p>
                <p>This led to the misconception that only this question interested the Ad Hoc
                    Committee. It was by no means their only interest. We realized that there were
                    many other problems involving spouses but we simply did not have facilities to
                    tackle those — at least at that time. Suddenly, in early August I had a letter
                    from the office of what was then called Wives Course Deputy, Joan Wilson.
                    Dorothy Stansbury meanwhile had become head of that organization. Joan told me
                    that she had learned that a rather important paper was being prepared at the
                    request of the then Director General of the Foreign Service, Carol Laise, who
                    had become concerned about some of the questions spouses were raising,
                    especially employment; and that if we as a group were to make any impression at
                    all, it was important, indeed vital, that we have some written paper to present
                    for inclusion in development of the paper that would be forwarded to Ambassador
                    Laise.</p>
                <p>I think that within two or three days between us, Carmen Williams and I — many
                    others having left town because of the holiday season — prepared a paper, a copy
                    of which is in the files that I will turn over with this tape. It is not worth
                    going over point by point at this stage because it exists and can be easily
                    read. What was amusing and perhaps indicative was the fact that I, having
                    prepared the paper in its final form, put it together in a way that seemed
                    logical to me but without reference to its form and with particular reference,
                    as my interest, in the substance. I learned later indirectly that the paper was
                    almost rejected because it had not been prepared in the form prescribed by
                    Ambassador Laise's office for papers submitted to her; and that it had been
                    decided with great reluctance to accept the paper as it stood, the points
                    presented being transferred to the proper form, of course.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>The fact that a paper prepared by a group of women totally outside the
                    Department's purview should have to adhere to a particular format, struck me as
                    amusing and predictably indicative of the attitude of the people who were
                    dealing with the questions that were our concern. Eventually, however, though
                    with great reluctance, apparently some of the points we raised, though they were
                    considered to be unsubstantiated and, indeed, ad hoc observations, were included
                    in the paper that went to Ambassador Laise.</p>
                <p>During this time and subsequently, the president of WAO, a woman from AID named
                    Annette Buckland, and I worked well together because she was interested in the
                    organization as a whole and was quite willing to have a group such as ours,
                    which we had formed spontaneously, work on its own without involving too much
                    the organization of which she was president. We on our side were extremely
                    grateful for all the help that we were given in terms of meeting arrangements,
                    use of facilities within the Department, etc., as well as indications from them
                    of whom to speak to. But we felt that we had no close relationship with the
                    organization, since their concerns quite obviously centered around those who
                    were primarily Officers in the Department and less those of spouses. Many
                    members of their organization were unmarried and concerned about the future of
                    their own careers. The arrangement was very satisfactory and ran smoothly for
                    many months.</p>
                <p>Some considerable time afterwards it was decided that the time had come — and I
                    believe the initiative came originally from Ambassador Laise herself — that a
                    meeting be set up with herself, WAO, AAFSW and the Ad Hoc Committee on Spouses,
                    because through her staff she had become more interested and concerned about the
                    matter of spouse dissatisfaction, and because she was, I think, truly eager to
                    find out more about this. The meeting was to occur in early February 1976.</p>
                <p>It took place and included representatives from the organizations I mentioned
                    above. It was rather — I can't say contentious but certainly some questions were
                    raised and one that had not been discussed in any detail at all, namely, the
                    formation within the Department of the so-called “Skills Bank.” The idea had
                    been suggested by Cynthia Chard, who had become a member of the Ad Hoc Committee
                    and who was very willing to volunteer enormous amounts of time to setting up the
                    possibility for a computerized list of qualified spouses that would be available
                    to not only the Department in Washington but to posts overseas.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>To this Ambassador Laise gave a decided negative, saying that the Department's
                    concern was exclusively employees, i.e., Foreign Service Officers, and could not
                    therefore be extended to spouses under any circumstances. To other questions
                    that were raised she gave less unequivocal answers but to one very definite
                    statement to which the by now renamed Research Committee on Spouses took
                    considerable exception, she pointed out that because of the nature of the group
                    as we were then constituted, we represented, as she said, “nobody in
                    particular,” we simply represented a group of people who had a concern. The
                    organization that really represented spouses in the public eye and within the
                    Department was the AAFSW, and since we appeared to have very little relationship
                    with AAFSW, she considered that until that group officially recognized and
                    espoused the concerns that the Research Committee on Spouses was raising, she
                    was not prepared to deal with any of them either as concerns or as an
                    organization.</p>
                <p>In response to that very definite statement, with the help of the new president
                    of WAO I wrote a letter in reply saying that I thought it unfortunate to
                    maintain that only one organization could appropriately represent the concerns
                    of many different groups of people with many different attitudes and points of
                    view, and that I hoped very much that she would change her mind. I never
                    received a reply to that letter, nor did anyone else so far as I know, but the
                    fact that there was no reply was reply enough.</p>
                <p>As for the work of the Research Committee on Spouses on a recurrent basis, we
                    decided that the important thing to do was to do what, as far as we were aware,
                    had not been done before: to contact various bureaus and areas in the Department
                    that dealt primarily with matters pertaining or of concern to Foreign Service
                    wives. We began, which may seem odd now, with a meeting with Security (SY). The
                    reason we chose that was because the question of passes for spouses to enter the
                    Department was of particular concern, since many wives — not those employed, of
                    course — had reason to enter the Department fairly often ancould only do so by
                    standing in line and waiting for clearance through the security procedure, which
                    consumed a lot of time.</p>
                <p>To our, at least my, intense astonishment, SY's reply though delivered with
                    marked politeness and some understanding was that wives were not automatically
                    cleared to enter the Department, as were their husbands upon being cleared for
                    entry into the Foreign Service. When I say this was a great surprise to me, I
                    assume that perhaps others reacted similarly. It never occurred to me before
                    that the Department in investigating the Officer himself would not, perforce,
                    investigate the wife, since she was supposed to be an integral part of the
                    Department's functions and the Department had made statements about
                    “indispensability of wives” as something that was noteworthy and to be taken for
                    granted!</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>To find, therefore, that in order to be able to obtain a pass to get into the
                    Department, each wife applying for one would have to go through a full field
                    investigation. Not surprisingly, we were informed immediately that this was
                    prohibitively expensive and simply could not be considered. As a result of that
                    meeting we did obtain a mild concession, that those persons who, for example,
                    were members of the board of AAFSW or otherwise had reason to enter the
                    Department on a more or less regular basis, would be given a special pass good
                    for only one year and with very limited privileges. That of course was a big
                    step forward but it was not what we had hoped to achieve.</p>
                <p>The second matter of concern to us was of course the question of overseas
                    employment, because among other things it involved the value of the Skills Bank.
                    In this guise we met with a representative from the Legal section, a very
                    helpful young man named Shamwell who attempted to explain to us the difficulties
                    of providing the basis for any kind of bilateral negotiation with international
                    entities. We had hoped, of course, that if it were possible for the United
                    States to permit wives of other nations' foreign service officers to find
                    employment here, the same facility might be extended to other countries
                    involved.</p>
                <p>It was only very recently that I had this really fully explained to me in writing
                    through the pamphlet, a booklet really, prepared by a member of Georgetown
                    University staff who had suggested that such a book be written dealing with
                    diplomatic immunity. The difficulty, it appeared, lay in the fact that the
                    United States, particularly the U.S., was governed in respect of diplomatic
                    immunity by a very ancient statute called “The Act of Anne” effectuated when the
                    Colonies first established their independence, and it had governed ever since.
                    The Act of Anne contained very, very strict regulations governing the conduct of
                    not only officers representing other countries to the United States but their
                    dependents, and until the Act of Anne could be superseded by a less rigid, less
                    confining set of regulations, it would be impossible for the United States even
                    to consider — which was doubtful from the outset — the possibility of bilateral
                    agreements dealing with dependents of Foreign Service Officers.</p>
                <p>We had several meetings with Mr. Shamwell, who was always unfailingly pleasant,
                    as were all the Department Officers with whom we met, and who tried to do what
                    he could to help us understand the nature of the problem even though he himself
                    had grave doubts about how such a matter could be resolved. Meetings such as
                    these were extended to other aspects and other bureaus of the Department and it
                    was a matter of great interest to participants that, contrary to what we rather
                    expected, there was no hostility toward the time spent and the questions raised
                    but a real attempt on the part of Department Officers to answer our questions as
                    best they could. I don't say that we agreed by any means to most of the
                    responses and answers that we got, but they were certainly in no way delivered
                    in a hostile manner or in any way querulous, raising that question, “What are
                    wives thinking about?” in other words.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>Of course, I don't need to say what has been part of the backdrop, I think, of
                    virtually all of the interviews that have taken place so far on almost any
                    subject, most of the people, in particular in this group, were dealing with
                    family problems of various kinds, some serious, some transitional, but
                    nonetheless the amount of time involved in preparing these meetings, in
                    attending them, and in trying to keep some kind of record of points that were
                    made, proved to be very difficult. And I think that is one thing that many
                    people don't realize was a hindrance to the accomplishments of many of the
                    activities that were undertaken at that particular time and successfully
                    undertaken at that particular time.</p>
                <p>All too soon the calendar year was used up and it became necessary to think about
                    what we would do in the future, because we had pretty much established, if
                    negatively, the problems we faced. Meanwhile, we had had added, or from the
                    beginning actually, one of the very lively and dynamic members of the group,
                    Stephanie Kinney, who decided more or less on her own, and very rightly, that it
                    was time that these concerns be brought to the attention of Congress. So, with
                    one or two friends she simply marched up to Capitol Hill after making
                    appointments with some of the more important and pertinent members of Congress,
                    and sat down with them and talked at some length about the matters that were of
                    concern to us and the fact that we felt very strongly that until some of these
                    matters were taken care of officially, the Foreign Service....(End of tape)</p>
                <p>MEYERS: (continuing) ... esprit and performance, both, would deteriorate rapidly
                    and continuously over time. As in the case of the administrative people in the
                    Department to whom we talked, Stephanie and her friend found the response of
                    members of Congress to be uniformly receptive and hospitable. This raises the
                    very interesting point indirectly, because one of the difficulties that I think
                    the AAFSW encountered was its isolation — self-imposed, I would say, because
                    there were many on the organization's board at that time who were very opposed
                    to moving in any manner or direction that would indicate an “activist” position
                    for the Association. They felt to do so would endanger thorganization's tax-free
                    status, and also that it would raise difficulties precisely in the areas in
                    which the Association had at least some interest.</p>
                <p>During the time that I was active in the Association, I attempted to change that
                    point of view, even going so far as to write various appropriate persons seeking
                    their advice on this matter. I was assured that there was no reason whatsoever
                    that the Association could not within certain clearly defined bounds take a
                    position and work actively toward it. Nonetheless, the result was as I described
                    it, so that both from the point of view of meetings with members of the
                    administration in the Department and members of Congress on Capitol Hill, the
                    Research Committee on Spouses paved the way for later developments in very
                    tangible way in this context.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>Specifically, Stephanie also, by making these contacts, paved the way for later
                    Congressional approval of the Skills Bank and the creation of the Family Liaison
                    Office. I might add that she also did the first survey of wives' concerns about
                    employment, especially overseas of course, thus providing numerical concrete
                    response to Ambassador Laise's statement that the Research Committee was not
                    providing evidence to back up its contention that wives both needed and wanted
                    to work.</p>
                <p>On a personal note I should certainly point out that during this course of time
                    Stephanie also took the Foreign Service exam and was accepted as an Officer, and
                    produced a most gorgeous red-haired baby who, after an appropriate lapse of
                    time, often attended the meetings of the Research Committee!</p>
                <p>I think I should digress now to talk a bit about the organization of the Research
                    Committee, which can be covered in a couple of sentences. One: there was no
                    organization. At the first meeting it was clear that somebody had to be the
                    point person and at least do some of the fronting for the Committee. Needless to
                    say, nobody was enthused about doing this and it became clear that, as the
                    person who was least specifically involved professionally or in any other way, I
                    seemed to have the job.</p>
                <p>I did undertake to do it to the best of my ability, but when I say “chairman of
                    the Research Committee,” it was really only nominally that I served in that
                    capacity, because there was really very little organization. We kept no minutes,
                    we had no dues or fees, either annual or otherwise. When money was needed, which
                    was rare, to accomplish what we wanted to do, we simply took up a collection and
                    people put into it what they felt they could afford. I must say, however, that
                    my own position as chairman was a very delicate one — not relative to the
                    Research Committee or what we were doing but in relation to AAFSW. At the same
                    time that I was working so actively through and under the auspices of the
                    Women's Action Organization, I was also a very active, perforce, vice president
                    of AAFSW.</p>
                <p>This came about because when I used the word “active”, Mary Buell, president of
                    the Association during that year, had many and various responsibilities, some of
                    which took her out of the city from time to time. When I say I was “active” I
                    was indeed very much involved in the AAFSW's work, which many people felt was
                    quite inappropriate. I can understand that view. I responded that the work we
                    should all be doing was such that it didn't make any difference, really, who was
                    doing it or in what capacity it was being handled. That may sound equivocal but
                    I really felt that very strongly, and still do.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>I have made it clear, I think, that from the beginning the Research Committee
                    focused its attention and energy on the question of employment of spouses
                    particularly overseas, but because it existed, it became quite naturally the
                    focus for other concerns that were brought to our attention by individuals or
                    groups of individuals. Two of the most important, which we were very loath to
                    have to turn down, were (l) the question of compensation for divorced spouses,
                    and (2) the concerns of foreign-born wives. In the end, of course, as is well
                    known, eventually both concerns as well as others brought to our attention were
                    dealt with and resolved in a very interesting way in each case.</p>
                <p>I might say here that the AAFSW has rightfully taken considerable credit for the
                    resolution of compensation to divorced spouses. But it should be pointed out for
                    the record, something which very few people realized at the time, that the first
                    interest in this problem came not from members of the AAFSW directly but from
                    the office of Representative Patricia Schroeder, who a long time before had
                    become aware of the problems of divorced spouses and who sponsored legislation
                    that eventually solved the problem not only for Foreign Service wives but also
                    for military wives.</p>
                <p>During this very short time certain other things were going on, one of which I
                    should like to highlight. Joan Wilson and I — she then as associate director of
                    what became the Overseas Briefing Center — were increasingly frustrated by the
                    seeming unwillingness and lack of interest in the AAFSW in the kinds of problems
                    that the Research Committee was dealing with. We decided that possibly one way
                    to pump up enthusiasm for this interest that was so lacking was to make a
                    suggestion that in the end proved to be ever more effective than we had assumed
                    it might be. Our proposal was to in some way bring together a very substantial
                    group of women with Foreign Service experience of some kind or other, whether as
                    spouses or through associations with a Foreign Service group.</p>
                <p>We therefore proposed what was really not named specifically but would consist of
                    a board of trustees to oversee the work of the AAFSW and attempt to bring some
                    new ideas to bear for the Association's board to consider. I don't need to add
                    that the proposal, sponsored by the Women's Action Organization, the Research
                    Committee, and the Wives Course through Joan, caused a furor. It was seen as we
                    had hoped it might — as an imposition on the authority of the Association. We
                    didn't consider it in that context precisely but we did hope that it might
                    encourage the few people then on the Association's board who shared some of our
                    ideas to bring them more forcibly before the general membership.</p>
                <p>Elections to the AAFSW's board were scheduled for the spring of 1976, again a
                    rather critical time. I was approached to serve as president but for a variety
                    of reasons I decided that it was unwise for someone who had dealt with these
                    problems that I had been so clearly associated with to run for president at that
                    time. There were other reasons why I declined but that was a principal one. In
                    the event, Lesley Dorman was both nominated and elected president.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>The final meeting, a very informal luncheon, of the Research Committee on Spouses
                    was held following the AAFSW election. At that meeting the members discussed for
                    the last time, it having emerged frequently during the year that we had worked
                    together, the possibility of creating yet another women's organization that
                    would deal particularly with questions of employment, etc. but would be a more
                    formal kind of organization than the Research Committee on Spouses. Those who
                    favored this felt that there were many who would join such an organization even
                    though they had not indicated thus far any kind of active interest. I was very
                    opposed to the concept of yet another women's organization on, I think, obvious
                    grounds. It seemed to me that it would be simply misuse of talent and waste of
                    time as well as dispersal of that important element to which Carol Laise had
                    alluded, i.e., in this particular case the importance of one organization rather
                    than many. There was of course a very pertinent reason of the Women's Action
                    Organization, but that was another matter altogether.</p>
                <p>In the end some of the more active members of the Research Committee on Spouses
                    joined AAFSW with the hope that in some way, directly or indirectly, they could
                    influence the active work of the organization despite the fact that there seemed
                    to be at that time still so little interest in what we were doing in the first
                    place and so little understanding of our point of view.</p>
                <p>I might say particularly that it is in a sense rather ironic that Lesley Dorman,
                    who had become so closely associated, and rightly so, in retrospect, with
                    AAFSW's accomplishments from that time forward, was initially one of the most
                    ardent opponents of the idea of a Research Committee, of the idea of an overseas
                    board of trustees, and of any need for any change. Lesley, intelligent and
                    energetic as she is, eventually saw the importance of what it was we were doing
                    and became one of the most ardent supporters of every aspect of the
                    accomplishments of the Association thereafter, including most importantly
                    creation of the Forum which produced so many remarkable results including most
                    significantly the Family Liaison Office.</p>
                <p>This description of the work of the Research Committee on Spouses that I have
                    given is, I'm afraid, pretty ponderous and pretty straightforward, and certainly
                    lacking in humor and levity! It reminds me of the response that I got to a
                    question that I asked of one of the people I interviewed in the course of the
                    Oral History project. When I asked her, “Did you have fun in the Foreign
                    Service?” she responded, “It was a lot of hard work.” Perhaps that response can
                    stand for the way most of us, I think, felt about the work that we did. We were
                    very closely associated, we had some wonderful times, and there was no lack of
                    humor in many directions. But we were concentrated on what we were doing,
                    perforce, because of the brief time that we had to work on what we were trying
                    to achieve. So we didn't really spend much time being humor-ful.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>Of course, everyone who speaks the English language in any form or other is
                    familiar with the word “sequel.” The sequel naturally to the work of the
                    Research Committee on Spouses was, as I said, the creation of the Forum and all
                    that flowed from their activities. Thanks to a charming word that I credit to a
                    reporter of the Washington Post, where I saw it first, there is not only a
                    sequel as a concept but there is a “prequel.” A prequel, as you might assume, is
                    a beginning. Naturally it's a word not known to be acceptable but it's so
                    descriptive somehow of the work of the Research Committee on Spouses that I will
                    call this report “the prequel to the sequel.”</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>BIOGRAPHIC DATA</p>
                <p>Spouse: Howard Meyers</p>
                <p>Spouse Entered Service:1955Left Service:1977You Entered Service:SameLeft
                    Service:</p>
                <p>Status: Spouse of Retiree</p>
                <p>Posts: 1956-59London, UK 1959-62Brussels, Belgium US Mission to European
                    Communities 1963-69Washington, DC 1970-72Tokyo, Japan 1973-77Washington, DC</p>
                <p>Spouse's Position: Political Officer, Specialist political/military affairs</p>
                <p>Place/Date of birth: Easton, Pa., August 21, 1917</p>
                <p>Maiden Name: Hope Lewis MacBride</p>
                <p>Parents (Name, Profession):</p>
                <p>John B. MacBride, civil engineer</p>
                <p>Martha E. Kugler, teacher</p>
                <p>Schools (Prep, University):BA, Douglass College, Rutgers University, New
                    Jersey</p>
                <p>MA Public Law, Columbia University</p>
                <p>Date/Place of Marriage: New York City, 1943</p>
                <p>Profession: Research in politics and economics</p>
                <p>Meeting facilitator</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>Children:</p>
                <p>Elizabeth Hope Meyers (deceased)</p>
                <p>Nicholas MacBride Meyers</p>
                <p>Volunteer and Paid Positions held:</p>
                <p>A. At Post: London - President, Embassy wives Brussels - Board, Belgian American
                    Women's Club; Elected board member of International School Tokyo - Board,
                    International Ladies' Benevolent Society</p>
                <p>B. In Washington, DC:First Chairperson, Careers for FS wives; Co-founder and
                    chairperson, Research Committee on Spouses; Vice President, AAFSW 1975;
                    Washington representative Canadian Legislative Visits Program, 1977-82;
                    Jefferson Place Gallery</p>
                <p>Honors (Scholastic, FS ):Phi Beta Kappa</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
