<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001106">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Melbourne L. Spector</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Foreign Assistance Series</p>
                <p>MELBOURNE L. SPECTOR</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: W. Haven North </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: September 12, 1996</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is September 12, 1996. The interview with Melbourne
                        L. Spector, who has been associated with foreign assistance since 1945.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Forty-five.</p>
                <p>Early years and education</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But before we go into that, Mel, let's hear a little bit
                        about where you were born, where you grew up, your education and so on, with
                        an accent on those things that might indicate how you got involved in
                        aspects of international development and foreign assistance.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Well, I was born in Pueblo, Colorado, May 7, 1918 - quite a few years
                    ago. My parents were of Russian-Jewish decent. They were small shopkeepers. My
                    mother was born in Russia, but came over here when she was about five years old.
                    My father was born in Philadelphia. When I was about five years old, we moved to
                    a small town called Walsenburg, Colorado. The reason I'm bringing this up is
                    that it was a great mixture of people. It was a coal mining town, so you had a
                    very heavy Hispanic population, Slav, Italian, so I was very attuned to
                    different cultures when I was quite young. At the ago of fifteen, we moved to
                    Albuquerque, New Mexico. This was the depths of the Depression. My parents
                    really were pretty destitute, but we opened up a small shop in Albuquerque.</p>
                <p>Living in New Mexico was an eye opener to me because there you had three
                    different cultures. You had the Hispanic - very heavy - I think, to this day,
                    they still publish all legislation in Spanish and English in New Mexico. You had
                    the Indian, or the Native American, and you had what we called the “Anglo,”
                    which was all the rest. So, again, you had three cultures, which was very good
                    for someone who eventually ended up in technical assistance work. I did well in
                    high school.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>I went on to the University - one of the reasons we moved to New Mexico was that
                    my parents wanted me to go to the University. It was easy and inexpensive to go
                    to college in the town where you lived and had the state university. I went to
                    the University and decided to get into medicine. I had read Arrowsmith by
                    Sinclair Lewis and Microbe Hunters by Paul DeKruif and was going to be a
                    doctor.</p>
                <p>But, living in Albuquerque - Albuquerque was a regional center for the
                    government. You had the Forestry Service there, the Soil Conservation Service
                    and other federal agencies. I came to know the fathers of the girls that I went
                    with, who were big men in the government and I thought, “God, this is something
                    I'd like to do.” So, even though I was going to become a doctor, I decided I
                    wanted to go into the public health service because then you could combine
                    government and public health and do all those good things. But about the third
                    year in pre-med, and I was doing very well - pre-med was easy - At the same time
                    that I was going to school, I got a job as a lab swipe. That's about the lowest
                    category you can be, working in a laboratory of the U.S. Public Health Service,
                    which was for the Indian Service. It was located at the Indian tuberculosis
                    sanitarium. During the summers, I worked on the Navajo reservation, again as a
                    lab swipe, which is the lowest thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What does a lab swipe do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: A lab swipe cleans out the lab. He or she washes everything up, prepares
                    solutions for the laboratory people to use. For just a moment, I want to say
                    that I had the dirtiest job that anyone's ever had. The laboratory was concerned
                    with doing research on dysentery. What this meant was that the public health
                    doctors would go to the Indian pueblos and gather feces in little bottles. Then
                    they'd bring it back to the lab and the technicians would take the feces out and
                    spread it on the Petrie dish and grow the cultures. When these bottles piled up,
                    it was my job to clean those bottles. I want to tell you, that was the dirtiest
                    job anyone's ever had! So I worked on the Indian reservation for two years, just
                    during the summers. I saw babies come in, dead babies, that were dead of
                    syphilis.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>So the problem came to me to mean not so much medicine, but the social controls.
                    I became convinced that the future lie in the social sciences, not in the
                    physical sciences. Also, I didn't see myself - this was 1938 and '39 - having
                    enough money to go to medical school. And in those days you couldn't go to
                    medical school on the government or get loans. I decided I really wanted to go
                    into government and I changed my major to government. So, I didn't graduate in
                    1939 as I should have. I graduated in 1940. In all this period, I'd gotten to
                    know a wonderful, wonderful woman named Dr. Estelle Ford Warner. She was the
                    head of all the public health for the entire Southwest region. Not just the
                    United Pueblos Agency, where I worked later, or the Navajo and all that, but the
                    whole area. I told her that I'd decided to not continue medicine, but
                    government. When I graduated from college, I got a fellowship there to return
                    for a year to work on my masters and be a graduate fellow. You know, you work on
                    Saturdays, you take the professor's classes on Saturdays and give quizzes or
                    just have good bull sessions, which I enjoyed. That's one way I got to know my
                    wife better. She was one of my students, she was in one of those classes.</p>
                <p>Working in the United Pueblos Agency - 1941</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were teaching?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, well, a teaching fellow. Doctor Warner called me one day and said
                    there was an opening in the United Pueblos Agency for an intern in government.
                    This was a part of the National Institute of Public Affairs, which still goes on
                    now. This was the field program, the Southwest Field Training program. We got
                    paid the magnificent sum of $60 an month, but people could live on it out there.
                    You had room and board for $40 a month. But I didn't need that - I was living at
                    home. The opening in the United Pueblos Agency was in personnel, so I got into
                    personnel. This was technical assistance because you were working with the
                    Indians. I became very much aware of the problem. So I was teaching and doing
                    this, which meant that I never finished my masters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was this program trying to do for the Indians?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: The entire program, the United Pueblos Agency, was over all of the
                    united pueblos up and down the Rio Grande River. Everything that an Indian
                    agency does - which to this day we're not quite sure we've done the right thing
                    by the way, which is a problem of technical assistance or development. The
                    National Institute of Public Affairs was an intern program that existed here in
                    Washington, mainly. People in those days would go in and work for the government
                    for free, merely for the chance to work in the government. They got paid
                    nothing. Some of the names of people who did this is Harlan Cleveland, John
                    Macy, and other people who went on to very top jobs. But out in Albuquerque, we
                    got paid $60 a month. Here, they got nothing. But here, they were allowed to eat
                    at Brookings Institution!</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>So, that summer - this is 1941 now - the federal government decided to try to
                    bring in junior interns. They gave a nationwide exam for junior management
                    assistants or something. I forget the title. I was one of forty some that made
                    the top grades in the western part of the United States. We were hired by the
                    Agency there. So I really began my government service in June of 1941, as an
                    intern, now being paid. That's where I really got my first introduction to
                    technical assistance, because we had lectures. One of the lecturers was a man
                    who was from the Yale Forestry School. He came to be one of the great counselors
                    to the entire Indian Service. He impressed us greatly to emulate the work of the
                    Franciscan Fathers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember his name?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, I wish I did. I tried to look it up before this interview. Wonderful
                    man. We went into detail the way the Franciscan Fathers did. We were supposed to
                    learn the language of the Indians; learned their ways; lived with them; worked
                    with them, rather than try to just impose onto them their own language and their
                    own ways of doing things. It's I think the most fundamental lesson I ever
                    learned. So, I think this was a basis for my interest in technical assistance.
                    But the war was coming on. This was 1941. Something came across my desk that
                    there was an opening in Washington in position classification, which I had done
                    a little bit of.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But your work was mainly in Personnel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: It was still in Personnel. I became the Assistant Personnel officer of
                    the Agency. It was a pretty large agency, second largest Indian agency. The
                    largest Indian agency, I guess to this day, is still the Navajo. The second
                    largest is still the United Pueblos Agency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the kind of programs were across the board?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Across the board. Everything: agriculture, education, housing,
                    everything you can think of.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Health?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: Oh, health was very, very big. But my job was, of course, personnel,
                    handling the people that did all this work. Just an interesting side note: the
                    head of the United Pueblos Agency was a woman again. So, I came into the
                    government not feeling that women were second class citizens, because this
                    Doctor Warner was a very imposing woman. Doctor Aberle, the head of the agency,
                    was both a physician, an M.D., and a Ph.D. in anthropology. So, I had no idea
                    that women weren't supposed to be in government because I'd worked for two of
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any Pueblos in the organization?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Pueblos? Maybe one or two. Very, very few. It's quite interesting.
                    However, you got out to the Navajo, you'd find more Indians working in
                    administrative jobs. That got larger and larger. I must say, it was interesting
                    that many of these Indians in the Navajo were not Navajos. They were Cherokees
                    or other Indians. But it was very interesting, working with the Indians,
                    because... And to this day, I don't have any great ideas on how the U.S. could
                    have done better in dealing with them. I know, all of the people I ever dealt
                    with, they tried, they really cared about the Indians and tried valiantly. I'm
                    not sure that we've ever done a very good job. It makes me wonder how well we
                    can do overseas if we can't do better with our own Native Americans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You have an understanding about what may be the primary
                        problem about being more effective?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, Haven, I wish I did. It's a great puzzlement to me. Maybe we've been
                    too paternalistic. Maybe we've given too much with not enough teaching and more
                    self-help. Of course, there's all kinds of schools. There's universities,
                    colleges. But I really don't know. You go back there today - I drove back there
                    about five years ago. The Navajo reservation looked to me pretty much the way it
                    did fifty years ago. Now they're living in a little better housing. They're now
                    giving up their beautiful hogans, those circular buildings. They're living in
                    trailers, which are much more comfortable and not one tenth as attractive. But
                    they're probably living more comfortably. I came to Washington...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1941?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Assignment with the War Relocation Authority - 1941</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: December 2, 1941. I got this telegram that said, “Would you be
                    interested in a -.” It was a CAF-5 position classification. I felt this was an
                    offer of employment. I got off the train, called the phone number and this woman
                    said, “What are you doing here? That wasn't an offer of a job. It was just an
                    inquiry.” Anyway, they put me to work. But then they found out I'd worked in the
                    Indian Service. This was a central - it was called Office for Emergency
                    Management. It was set up to serve the various war agencies, rather than have
                    each agency have its own. This was a central personnel office that serviced many
                    agencies. Some of them were big enough to have their own personnel offices, but
                    the smaller ones didn't. One of them that needed help was called the War
                    Relocation Authority. This is the Authority that had jurisdiction over the
                    Japanese Americans who had been interned in camps, a very bad chapter in our
                    history. Because I'd been working in the Indian Service, they detailed me over
                    there. And, finally, I transferred to their payroll. So here again, I was caught
                    up with, although I was in Personnel, the problem of dealing with people that
                    had never know of another culture. I learned again that, in the early days,
                    these people were treated so badly: herded together in baseball fields,
                    stadiums, and then they built camps for them all in pretty remote areas. They
                    were called “resettlement camps,” but call them “concentration camps,” anything
                    you want. Great big buildings. Far too many families to a building. No privacy.
                    They were very unhappy.</p>
                <p>So we called on cultural anthropologists from the Indian Service. One was John
                    Embree, one of the great ones who died later. George Leightan from Cornell, who
                    wrote one of the best books on this subject. They said, “Look, you've got to
                    understand their culture. For one thing, you have provided no place for them to
                    worship.” So, they built Shinto temples for them. These people liked communal
                    baths, so they started to build these great big bathtubs. So, there were little
                    things like that that I learned you have to do. But I want to just say one thing
                    here, because I hope we're talking in all of this about administration as well
                    as technical assistance or development. War Relocation Authority was first
                    headed up by Milton Eisenhower, the brother of President Eisenhower, and Milton
                    was then the Eisenhower in town. The other Eisenhower wasn't well known. Milton
                    Eisenhower just couldn't take it. He just couldn't take the job of handling
                    these mistreated Americans. He hated what he was doing. But he had a car pool
                    mate named Dillon Myer. Dillon Myer was a very skilled administrator. He'd been
                    the head of the Soil Conservation Service, former agricultural extension agent.
                    Again, learning to deal with other people, dealing with your clients. He was the
                    best administrator I've ever known. He believed in communication. He would have
                    a meeting once a week, on Thursday, at night, and meet with anybody that wanted
                    to meet. He'd have his top staff there. Anyone could come to the meeting and
                    talk about anything they wanted to talk about. This was 1942, '43. I, in
                    Personnel, could ask the agricultural man, “Why are you doing this or that?”
                    This gave people a feeling of belonging to the organization.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At whatever level?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: It didn't matter. But he would have his top staff there, so you could
                    ask the questions and there would be a dialogue. About once every three or four
                    months, during the workday, he'd close down the Agency for maybe thirty minutes.
                    He'd call everyone together, everyone. We had trouble covering the phones, for
                    example. Including the one chauffeur we had. He'd say, “We've got to work
                    ourselves out of a job. We've got to return these American citizens to their
                    rightful place. We've got to tear down those walls.” That's the kind of man he
                    was. And books have been written about him since that say what an S.O.B. he was.
                    Nobody knows the truth. When he died, Japanese Americans conducted his funeral.
                    That's how he was beloved. Later, I used Dillon in AID, setting up some things.
                    He was a very, very great man and taught me an awful lot. After - well, I was
                    drafted. I don't think this has much bearing on what we're talking about, but I
                    did learn more about organization. I worked in the headquarters of the Army/Air
                    Force, doing organization charts.</p>
                <p>Drafted into the Army / Air Force headquarters and the UNRRA overseas - 1945</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: In Washington. General Arnold ran the Army Air Force with charts. He was
                    a form man. And I kept this big book of charts. He'd sign them off. All that
                    went out to the Air Force overseas: the 8th, the 9th, the 7th, the 3rd, and so
                    on. I tried to go overseas a couple of times. They wouldn't let me go the first
                    time because I had this damn chart business. Finally, I got assigned overseas. I
                    went home, told my parents “Goodbye” in Albuquerque, told Louise “Goodbye” - we
                    were going together, later my wife. And the war was over. There was an
                    organization called UNRRA: United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation
                    Administration, with headquarters in Washington. I knew some people there. They
                    said, “Look, we need people desperately in Personnel. We can get you out.” They
                    got me out. So, by about September 1945, I was working at UNRRA. So, I guess
                    there you can say was the first time I was really working in an international
                    organization - again, in Personnel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: Washington Personnel, yes. Interesting to AID's organization later, with
                    foreign assistance - I love to tell this anecdote. UNRRA was always under fire
                    from Congress for not being run well - first Governor Lehmann, then Mayor
                    Fiorello La Guardia. La Guardia was a little better. But the finances were in
                    disarray, so that the Assistant Secretary of State, Will Clayton, formerly one
                    of the big cotton brokers in Texas, went to Congress and said, “Look, this is
                    important. We ought to set up a controller to have control over all the finances
                    of UNRRA. I'll give you my controller, who's the best man in the world [His name
                    was Howell, by the way].” Congress said, “Okay.” I think that's where the whole
                    controller business started and that's why we had a controller in AID from the
                    very beginning. You see, only a very few years later - two or four or five years
                    later - they wanted to be sure that the Marshall Plan would have the same kind
                    of control over its finances which the UNRRA got over its finances. That's why
                    we've got this Controller. Then, later, it spread to other parts of the
                    government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But prior to that, there was nothing called a
                        “controller?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: As far as I know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then how were finances managed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Well, they were managed by Budget and Fiscal Officers and an audit
                    officer. The Controller reported directly to the head of the Agency, whereas the
                    Budget and Finance Officers reported to an Assistant Secretary. I've talked to
                    various Controllers and I think that's where it got started - in UNRRA.</p>
                <p>After about a year there, and I enjoyed it very much, I once again became aware
                    of the needs overseas. I was in Washington, but I was filling jobs all over the
                    world. Don't get me wrong: I was one of many people doing this, but I was one.
                    And there I want to bring up this name because, later, he comes into the AID
                    picture very greatly. I met a young man. He was a security investigator. I
                    always had the vision of a security guy being kind of a gumshoe or a flatfoot
                    and I was very impressed with this young man. He was bright and articulate and
                    so on. His name was Richard Barrett. I said, “What are you doing? Why don't you
                    go into Personnel?” So, I persuaded him to come to Personnel and work for my
                    boss, who was another woman. (Again, working for women!) She was a very, very
                    able person. Barrett and I became very good friends from that day on. He had not
                    gone to college at that point, because he was 4F and he was supporting a family.
                    But, because I had good connections in Albuquerque (the Chairman of the Board of
                    Regents was a good friend of mine - Federal Judge Bratton), I wrote him a
                    letter. Back in '46, getting into college, unless you were a GI or just coming
                    out of high school, was very, very difficult. So, he went to the University of
                    New Mexico - Richard Barrett. He comes into my story later, especially in the
                    setting up of AID.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>I quit after a year. My parents said, “You've got to come back and take over the
                    businesses,” which was horrible. I didn't want to do it. My mother had two curio
                    stores and my father ran a pawn shop and I didn't want to do either one. I don't
                    like retail. I don't like selling. I still don't. I tried to get into business.
                    I want to tell this anecdote because I had this vision of government being pure
                    and wonderful. A friend of mine and I decided that the way to make a million
                    dollars was to buy a surplus factory owned by the federal government. We got the
                    idea of buying an oxygen plant. We found an oxygen plant was available in a
                    place called Pascagoula, Mississippi. So, he and I traveled to Pascagoula, but
                    the headquarters for that area was in New Orleans. It was called the War Assets
                    Administration. They were selling off all the assets. So, here was this oxygen
                    plant that was worth several million dollars. But they were going for a song.
                    This man who dealt with it said, “You know, I can get that for you.” This was a
                    government worker, a government official. He said, “If you can assure me of a
                    job afterwards.” We just weren't going to play that kind of a game and we told
                    him so. I think we put in a bid of $123,450 - you know, one, two, three, four,
                    five. We were told a couple of months later, when the bids came in, that we were
                    outbid by the big outfit that owns all the oxygen plants in the country, by $10.
                    He was telling us, you see, exactly what happened. Later, we took this to court
                    and we won. But, by that time, I was back in Washington. I didn't care. But that
                    was a shocker to me, that government people could be venal. I just couldn't
                    believe it. I was a starry eyed kind of guy.</p>
                <p>Position with State Department Personnel Office - 1948</p>
                <p>I came to Washington. I was offered a job in the State Department, in the
                    Director General's office. In those days, the Director General was then the
                    Director of Personnel. He had planning and organization and many other things. A
                    new act had been passes, the Foreign Service Act of 1946, which meant that all
                    of the jobs had to be classified in the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>So, a team of us - three of us - went for a two and a half-month trip to Latin
                    America. We'd see the Consulates, Consulates General and Embassies. It was the
                    very best possible introduction to the Foreign Service because we covered every
                    job in the Consulate or Embassy — And we would trade-off. In one Embassy, I'd
                    handle Economic and someone else would handle the Administrative. In another
                    Embassy, I'd handle Political... So, by the time we were through, the three of
                    us were fully grounded in how the Foreign Service was run. We learned, too, of
                    the prejudices of the Foreign Service, which are still to this day, political,
                    in the functional sense. Number one is political. I wrote letters back to
                    Washington, saying that these political boys run the Embassies. When we would go
                    to an Embassy, we would say to the Ambassador or to the DCM, “We want to have a
                    meeting of everybody.” He'd say, “Okay,” and he'd call in the Political staff.
                    We'd say, “No, we want the Economic people.” “Leave out the Administrative?”
                    “No, we want everybody.” And the information, whatever information there was in
                    those days, which was cultural. Finally, we said, “Look, we consider everybody a
                    part of the Embassy.” That was a very good...</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was a pattern all over?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: All over. Absolutely. Still, to this day, I think that, if you want to
                    get ahead in the Foreign Service, you put your major time into the Political
                    Section. Desk here in Washington, Office Director in Washington, Political in
                    the field. You take other jobs just to show, you know - but you stay in
                    that.</p>
                <p>Personnel work for ECA - 1948</p>
                <p>So, I came back to Washington. I was doing classification work. In early '48, the
                    Marshall Plan was being set up. The way it was set up - when you say the
                    Marshall Plan, you're really talking about the Economic Cooperation
                    Administration, but the popular name of the work they did in Europe was called
                    the Marshall Plan. There were other missions under the ECA in the Far East. In
                    setting it up, the President had appointed Paul Hoffman. In those day, he was
                    very well known. He had been the head of Studebaker Automobile Company and he
                    was considered one of the top businessmen in the country. He was the head of the
                    Agency. In the law that had set up the ECA, the administrator was given options.
                    Here in Washington, he had to use Civil Service, except for these 400 excepted
                    jobs. The administrator was given two options overseas. He could either set up
                    his own personnel system completely or he could use the State Department's
                    Foreign Service. Mr Hoffman, in consultation with Mr. John Peurifoy, who was the
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Administration, decided to use the Foreign
                    Service. This meant that you had to set up Foreign Service jobs overseas for the
                    Marshall Plan. The State Department had the appointing authority.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did they make that choice, do you know?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I don't really know. I think it seemed to be easier. I think they
                    thought, “Hey, here's a system we can already use. It's in place.” And he was
                    assured by Peurifoy that he would be flexible and that's probably why they did
                    it. Because they used the Foreign Service, a whole team was sent over to the
                    Marshall Plan, which, by the way, was in the Maiatico Building, on the corner of
                    Connecticut and H Street - 800 Connecticut Ave., NW. We sent over some young
                    man, a Budget and Fiscal, a young man named John Murphy was the Budget and
                    Fiscal guy. I think Orbun Powell. And in Personnel, a man named Everett Bellows.
                    He said that he wouldn't go unless I could go with him, because he didn't know
                    anything about position classification. Then on communications, we had to use
                    the State Department's communication area. So, a team of us went over in March.
                    The building was just being finished. They were putting up partitions all around
                    the place and telephone lines were coming down from the ceiling. You would hear
                    partitions being put up with guns. You were talking on the phone and you'd jump
                    up out of your chair as another gunshot went off, putting a rivet into a wall.
                    We set up a one stop personnel system.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>Let me go back to my own particular job. What we did was, we set up jobs all over
                    the world - Europe mostly. I did not do the organization part. Robert Rupard did
                    that. I classified the jobs. It was my job to decide whether they were FSN-3,
                    FSN-2 or what. I based those jobs mostly on comparing them with jobs with the
                    State Department. Take an industry job and, as much as I could, compare it with
                    a Commerce job or a Commercial Attach� job and use other specifications that you
                    had around the Federal Government. We were keeping them in line as much as we
                    could. I think we were a little bit over what the regular Foreign Service had
                    because the regular Foreign Service was always short of money, which is probably
                    true to this very day. We probably classified the jobs a little bit higher than
                    the regular Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Harder to attract people, I guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Exactly. We had to attract people all over. It wasn't too difficult to
                    attract, because the Marshall Plan had a great cache. People thought that this
                    was the good thing to do, that Europe needed help, and so on, as you know. Wil
                    Clayton had come back in '47 from Europe, saying Europe was collapsing and
                    started all of this ferment towards helping Europe. It was mostly Europe, but
                    other things happened around the world that we picked up to. In Formosa, in
                    China, the Philippines, India, places like that. It was a very heady time. We
                    were working very long hours. One little anecdote I'd like to put in here was
                    when we tried to set up a one stop service. We wanted to be able to, if we
                    wanted the person, bring them in, approve their qualifications, get them a
                    security clearance, give them a medical exam (we had Public Health Service set
                    up a unit there to give them a physical) and issue them a passport, all within
                    our building, the Maiatico Building. All in one day! We had all those things in
                    place except passport issuance, because the Passport Division was being run by a
                    very able, autocratic woman named Mrs. Shipley, a wonderful woman. That was our
                    last point. So, one day, Everett Bellows, my boss, and I went over to see Mrs.
                    Shipley, to try to talk her into sending someone over to issue them physically
                    in our building. First, she kept us waiting for 40 minutes. Then - she was a
                    good looking woman - took off her glasses and said, “You're about as welcome as
                    the flu,” which kind of dates everything. Then we chatted with Mrs. Shipley.
                    Now, I'm patting myself on the back a little bit and I said, “Well, Mrs.
                    Shipley, I know how important passports are. I've just finished reading The
                    Meaning of Treason, by Rebecca West, I knew from that that 'Lord Haw-haw,' who
                    was hanged as a traitor because he had been broadcasting from Germany while
                    holding a British passport. And so she said, “Well, yes, you understand” and we
                    got the authority. In one day, we could hire a person, issue a passport, give
                    them a ticket and send them out to the airport.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you got the security clearance in one day?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes. And we did that for years. That was one of the bad things that they
                    dealt with later - we gave that up. We would clear people based on a quick
                    check, using the House Un-American Activities list and the Attorney General's
                    list of subversive organizations. If they weren't on that, we hired them,
                    subject to a full FBI clearance later. It was a handful, out of hundreds and
                    hundreds, that ever were turned down later. So, you could quickly put them on
                    the job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you'd take them off the job then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: We did, but it was worth it for the 99+ percent that got on the job.
                    Later, Dave Bell stopped that when he became Director, and I don't know why. And
                    we had the toughest security law of any civilian agency in town, except the CIA.
                    Because no one could go to work for us if they'd ever worked in any way for any
                    organization that was on the House list of Un-American activities, or on the
                    Attorney General's list. So, we sent people overseas very, very quickly and did
                    a very good job.</p>
                <p>Our very top people were hired by Tex Moore, who was a brother in law of Paul
                    Hoffman. He wanted to control the very top jobs. To this day, I bet you still
                    have an executive recruiter at AID and that goes back to Paul Hoffman. No other
                    agency that I know of has executive recruiters that I know of, except AID. He
                    hired top flight people: Zellerbach in Italy; Thomas Finletter, former Secretary
                    of the Navy; David Bruce in France; Roger Lapham in Greece. Very top people.
                    We're talking now of '48.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mostly business people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Mostly business people, yes. Under them, though, we had some very, very
                    able economists, lawyers, administrators and so on. In Paris there was Averell
                    Harriman, a Democrat; in Washington, Paul Hoffman, a Republican. It was a
                    non-partisan agency. Under Harriman, you had some of the best brains: Lincoln
                    Gordon as Program Officer; Milton Katz of Harvard Law as legal man. Here in
                    Washington was Najeeb Halaby as a lawyer; you had as your real brains, Richard
                    Bissell, who later went to a top job in CIA. The very top people because we
                    could attract all the very top people. It was a very heady time.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>My job quickly was over in classification, but they kept me on to approve
                    Personnel actions. Here I was a lowly GS-12, approving men who were going to be
                    the equivalent of Deputy Ambassadors, but it was pro-forma really, and that's
                    the way it should have been. I had no real reason to object to any of them. But
                    I did set up a group to draft a Personnel Manual. Our people in Paris (we had a
                    large staff in Paris) wanted their own authorities to hire and handle people,
                    but being very intelligent, good administrators, they knew they needed bases
                    upon which to do it. So, I had two very good women - Jane Ganeshan and Betty
                    Biggis - to write the manual. We had a manual done in 60 days.</p>
                <p>I eventually went back to State, toward the end of '48. Louise and I got married
                    in November. I was number two in the employment section of State. I was the
                    Executive Secretary of the Foreign Service, the Board of the Foreign Service,
                    when I got a letter, asking me to come over and be the Deputy Director of
                    Personnel for the Marshall Plan in Europe. And we went. It was a very happy
                    time. But I want to say one thing about setting up the Marshall Plan, which I
                    hadn't mentioned before.</p>
                <p>It was set up mostly by people who were economists and they had made no provision
                    for technical assistance. It was all just the heavy stuff, worrying about coal
                    and steel and things like that. But Don Stone said, “This is ridiculous. There
                    ought to be technical assistance, too.” (Donald Stone was the top administrative
                    person.) Most of the funds we used for setting up the Marshall Plan here in
                    Washington were administrative funds, which becomes very important later. Don,
                    being very bright, used program funds, which were many more, to set up technical
                    assistance. He used people like William Colman, Jack Forbes, to set up the
                    technical assistance branch and that's where all the participant training was.
                    Oh, Richard Bissell was the big thinker of this and he was very much against
                    technical assistance - “Oh, we didn't need that kind of stuff; these are
                    countries that know what they are doing.” He was right, in a way. This wasn't
                    backwards parts of Latin America or Africa or the Far East. But there were parts
                    of Europe that did need technical assistance - and some to this day - Ireland,
                    Southern Italy, Greece, Turkey.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I understand that even at that time, many of the
                        countries, because of the War, had lost out on the advances in technology.
                        So, they needed updating, which was an important part of the technical
                        assistance process.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes. Although I was not a part of it, you had the Americans and the
                    British on the British-American Productivity Council to start transferring part
                    of that productivity over to England. Then, we built up in Washington and in
                    Paris, a Productivity Staff, which was doing the kind of things that you
                    mentioned to help bridge the technological gap. And the participant training was
                    a great part of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Don Stone have a particular part of technical
                        assistance he was promoting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, just a general part. Don was the Assistant Administrator for
                    Administration. Don was perhaps the first person after Truman dragooned Paul
                    Hoffman into the job of head of this ECA. He called upon the Director of the
                    Budget Bureau to give him a man to give him help. Hoffman knew nothing about
                    government. The head of the Budget Bureau gave him Don Stone. Don brought over
                    some of his people from the Bureau right away to help set up the offices and he
                    knew this new building that was being built just one block from the Old
                    Executive Office Building, the Maiatico Building. It was destined for some other
                    agency, but the ECA had such clout that Don got it for ECA. The building wasn't
                    finished. It was a shell. The floors were in, but there were no partitions, no
                    phones or anything like that. Within a week, he had offices in, phones working,
                    and a place for Paul Hoffman to sit, and Dick Bissell and so on. It was a
                    marvelous job. But Don was one of these dynamos, so just running the
                    administrative part of ECA wasn't enough for Don. He kept two assistants, two
                    secretaries going at all times.</p>
                <p>So, he set up this technical assistance thing. He had a big interest in public
                    administration, but he didn't push that as such. He had gone to Brussels, as you
                    know, but I think this was before ECA. He'd been sent there by Secretary
                    Marshall to reestablish the International Institute of Administrative Sciences,
                    which had been decimated by the Nazis. They had just killed it. Don went over
                    there and reestablished that.</p>
                <p>Assignment with ECA in Paris - 1949-51</p>
                <p>I went to Paris as the Deputy Personnel Officer for the European Region. The
                    regional office was quite large, about 800 people, run by Averell Harriman. His
                    first Deputy was William Foster, who came back later to run the Agency. Under
                    them were very bright and able people. They were able to attract young, bright
                    people. In the Legal Office, for instance, we had Kingman Brewster, a young man
                    who later became President of Yale. We had John McNaughton, who later became
                    Secretary of the Navy under John F. Kennedy. Then, the other thing we were able
                    to do was just hire locally. You had so many people over in Europe on the GI
                    Bill, who wanted to work there and get access to our commissary and PX. But we
                    picked up some awfully good people that later became Controllers, Deputy Mission
                    Directors and finally AID Directors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The structure I understand, from others - the Marshall
                        Plan Overseas Office was separate from the Embassy. Is that right or
                        not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes. They were pretty separate from the Embassy. The Mission Director
                    ranked immediately after the Ambassador, but had a separate office because the
                    Embassies were mostly too small and we had a fairly large staff. We had Industry
                    Officer, a Program Officer, a Labor Officer, an Agricultural Officer, and so
                    on.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And an economist.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Well, the Program Officer was the economist. Of course, this gave the
                    State Department a whole lot of heartburn because you had the other person in
                    town who ranked right after the Ambassador. And, of course, we had money. We had
                    counterpart funds just coming out of our ears.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So relationships with the host government were complex in
                        the sense of the Ambassador's role of vis a vis the Mission Director.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: They were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have to deal with issues like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I personally didn't until later, when I was in a Mission myself. But,
                    yes, the governments often turned to the foreign assistance, to the ECA people,
                    because they knew that they had the money. They didn't think that the Ambassador
                    had an awful lot to say about it. Now, the Ambassador had one last thing. He
                    could declare a person “Non Grata” and get him out if he didn't like him. But I
                    don't think there was ever a case that came to that. We had to get rid of one
                    Mission Director for other reasons, because he was living with his secretary,
                    openly in Austria, where that wasn't looked upon kindly, being a very good
                    Catholic country. On the other hand, the Marshall Plan was very good for the
                    Foreign Service. We were using the Foreign Service Act, Foreign Service Law, but
                    we said, “We're going to base our work on the law, not on the State Department
                    regulations.” The State Department was antiquated because of lack of funds. For
                    example, take home leave. If you were on, say, your two year tour, waiting for
                    home leave - if, for any reason you had to come back to the United States, for
                    compassionate reasons (you had a parent dying, had to bring a child back who was
                    ill), your home leave began again. It was ridiculous. So, you may have had a
                    year and a half and had to come back because your father was dying. Too bad!
                    Your home leave began again. That was ridiculous and we told the State
                    Department that. The reason they did it was money. They were always short of
                    money. But part of it was very bad accounting. They didn't know what they were
                    doing. We would take various things like that and say, “Look, we're going to go
                    ahead and do it.” Next year, they would go to Congress and say, “Look, these
                    darn Marshall Plan people are doing it.” Then the Congress would have to give
                    them the money to make up so they could get up to the level of the Marshall
                    Plan. So, in effect, we were helping State get more money. This was in addition
                    to the money that we gave State on certain support they were getting out of the
                    communications area and other areas, which was always more than they really
                    deserved.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the Marshall Plan staff regular Foreign Service
                        Officers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, they were always our very own staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, they didn't have the career status.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: That was the difference. They never had the (and up until very recently,
                    up until the Foreign Service Act of 1980) security of a Foreign Service Officer.
                    Yet, the Foreign Service Officer, by the way, had a selection up, selection out,
                    which the Marshall Plan people did not have. It was kind of a balance. Also,
                    when we found something in the Act that was really troublesome, that we needed
                    more leeway one, we'd consult with the State Department. Then, using the Foreign
                    Assistance Authorization Bill, get amendments to the Foreign Service Act, which
                    would give them more leeway for all of us, which we used later when we set up
                    AID.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this create tensions between the two, having parallel
                        systems of different character?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, it did. The tensions were always resolved in months, really,
                    because they would quickly catch up with us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There wasn't any attempt to make everybody part of a
                        career Foreign Service and have one Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, but I'll get into that later. Yes, there was and that has always
                    been my dream.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll come to that later then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Right, but you are correct.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were working in Paris, were there particular
                        issues that you had to deal with in the Personnel operations there in
                        Paris?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: The problem that I had to deal with mostly was that we tried more and
                    more to be more efficient, to process faster, to hire faster, to get to do
                    whatever we had to do in a more efficient way. After I'd been there a few months
                    as the Deputy, the Personnel Officer detached me from my regular duties. I did
                    an organizational study of the Personnel Office. We had about 35 or 40 people.
                    That taught me an awful lot because, in dealing with the Office, in dealing with
                    each procedure, we were able to change it right on the spot, being as I was part
                    of the Office. I didn't just do a study, throw it down, and say, “This is it.”
                    And that was the way I always tried to work later.</p>
                <p>We had problems, of course, individual problems. A few of these cases, where I'd
                    said we would hire people immediately based on a brief security check. We had a
                    handful of people that would come through that, when the full check came
                    through, we had to fire them. But we went along pretty well.</p>
                <p>I was in the job for about a year. This is important to me: I got hepatitis and I
                    was in the hospital for several weeks. Somebody gave me a book to read by Stuart
                    Chase called, The Proper Study of Man. This was based on the Alexander Polk's
                    ...the Proper Study of Mankind as Man. In it, I became very much aware of the
                    social sciences again. I decided that, here I was in Personnel and I was using
                    what I call a “cook book” philosophy. You do this, it tells you to do that, so
                    many teaspoons of that, but I had no underlying philosophy of how to deal in
                    Personnel. Here I am dealing with human beings. So I met in Paris a psychiatrist
                    named Mottram Torre. He was a Public Health Officer, but also a psychiatrist. I
                    began psychoanalysis under him, to try to understand myself better and to read
                    more in personnel.</p>
                <p>One of the men in Paris was named Jack Kubisch, a very good friend of mine. He
                    was the head of the Organization and Management Unit. He left to go back to the
                    country to make a million dollars so he could come back into the Foreign Service
                    and not have to take nothing off nobody, which he did. He became Ambassador to
                    Greece, finally. So that job was open and they detailed me to that job. I became
                    the acting head of Organization and Management. I brought Torre in to have
                    sessions with my staff. I guess I didn't know it, but I was beginning
                    sensitivity training. I wanted them to understand better themselves, so when
                    they dealt with our clients - and we were doing studies of both the Missions and
                    Paris headquarters - we would do a better job of it. We would understand their
                    problems. I've carried this out wherever I've been. I've tried to use what I
                    call being sensitized to the other persons needs.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>One of the things that I did when I was in that job- Waldemar Nielsen was the
                    head of our Information operation. We had a huge Information operation. We had
                    all this counterpart money, so we had in Europe, newspapers and magazines and
                    traveling fairs and so on. It was set up beside the State Department, which had
                    a very tiny Cultural Office. I was on my way to Turkey on another problem, which
                    was a secretary who had written us privately that she'd been molested by the
                    Deputy Chief of Mission. He tried to rape her, according to her. I was sent
                    there under the cover of looking into the budget, but to actually talk to her,
                    too. While I was there, Waldemar Nielsen said, “Look, why do we have these two
                    competing Information Offices there? Why don't you talk to the Ambassador and
                    see if we, on a trial basis, could put them together - the Cultural Affairs, the
                    Information Affairs together?” We had an old time Ambassador, a wonderful man
                    who's name I can't remember now, in Turkey and we did. I think this was the
                    forerunner of USIA. This was the first time you had a combined Cultural and
                    Information Office in one of the diplomatic missions. By the way, the young
                    lady, after I got there, recanted. She would not admit that it happened. The man
                    who was accused of the molestation went on to become the head of one of the
                    largest corporations in America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll leave his name out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, well, I don't even remember it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But your role there was that you were working on the State
                        Department side as well as the ECA side, weren't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: When I was in the Organization Management job, Lincoln Gordon was our
                    top Program Officer. He was being sent back to Washington to work for Averell
                    Harriman, who had been sent back to Washington. He went around to all the
                    Missions and he said, “You know, this is ridiculous: every Mission has the same
                    organization. It's like saying, 'Every person wears a size 38 coat.'” He called
                    me and a couple of others into his office and we said, “We ought to try to
                    reform our Mission so they relate to the programs.” It's called “program
                    budgeting.” So, the Bureau of the Budget sent over a man named Hirst Sutton and
                    a young man named John P. Robinson. The three of us worked on trying this new
                    program budgeting system. We worked on it for about three months and then the
                    Korean War came along and blew us out of the water. I don't know why it affected
                    us so much in Paris, but we didn't continue with it.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>There is another anecdote which bears on this whole issue. My wife was a
                    secretary of Americans for Democratic Action, in Paris. We had a nice unit. I
                    was not a member because I felt that I shouldn't get into politics. Mrs. Eleanor
                    Roosevelt came to Paris on a visit. The people wanted to give a tea for her and
                    they did. It was on a Saturday afternoon and I got there early. Of course, Mrs.
                    Roosevelt was always on time. She was there and I had to entertain her for 15
                    minutes. To this day, I do not remember a thing that we discussed. I was in so
                    much awe of her. This was an icon and still an icon to me. But I do remember
                    later, when the other people came into the room- She was then a Delegate to the
                    United Nations. We asked her how she liked it. She said, “Well, in filling out
                    the forms, they asked me to fill out all of the organizations that I'd ever been
                    a member of. That would've taken up too much room, so I just listed the
                    subversive ones.” But the important thing that she said, and this had to be
                    1951, was that, “I think you're making a big mistake in the Marshall Plan.
                    You're selling it strictly on anti-Communism and there's many, many reasons to
                    do the things we do that have nothing to do with being anti-Communistic. You are
                    only aiding and abetting what's happening back in the United States. There's a
                    man named 'McCarthy,' who is building up a lot of interest and furor about
                    Communists and you're just aiding and abetting that.” And I think we've lived to
                    regret how much we made what we did always anti-Communist. So she was way ahead
                    of her time.</p>
                <p>I came back after about two years to the States. I was offered a job as the
                    Deputy Director of Personnel of the entire Agency. This was back in Washington.
                    This included our other Missions - by that time, we had Missions in
                    Indochina.</p>
                <p>Return to Washington as ECA Deputy Director of Personnel and FOA, then MSA -
                    1951-54</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The ECA had Missions in Indochina?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, we had a Mission in Indochina. We had a Mission in the Philippines.
                    Mission in Formosa. And a Mission in India. At least, those are the four that I
                    remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a change in objective of the Marshall Plan,
                        wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, the economic cooperation... There were problems that came up, for
                    instance, in the Philippines. They first sent out a Treasury Group to deal with
                    that. Then they decided that the Philippine Government needed more help than
                    just what the Treasury could do, so we had a Mission there. I guess we wanted to
                    help Formosa. I don't know how we got involved in India, but we had a Mission.
                    We had one in Indochina. One of my problems was getting anyone to go there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: Saigon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1951?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes. We had trouble getting people to go there. We hired secretaries on
                    a worldwide basis because we knew every secretary we hired wanted to go to Paris
                    or London. So, we'd first send them to a place like Vietnam and then we'd send
                    them to Paris after two years or to Lisbon or so on.</p>
                <p>I'll give you one example which led to the kind of organization that we finally
                    came up with. In the Philippines, when I was in Personnel, there was an
                    election. Magsaysay was the man that the U.S. was behind. It seemed that,
                    according to the Embassy, we felt that he would have a much better chance of
                    winning if something was done about a rice blight. And we had agricultural
                    people. They were on the roles of the Department of Agriculture, but being sent
                    there under our aegis. So, the Mission Director went to the agriculture people
                    and said, “Would you please stop doing this and go over and help on the rice
                    blight?” And they said, “No, no. We came here for something else.” And they
                    said, “Yes, but the Ambassador or the ICA Director wants you to do that.” And
                    they said, “No, no.”</p>
                <p>So, I got a cable that said, “Would you remove these people?” And I did, saying,
                    “You don't want to do the work” and we yanked them out. You had that kind of a
                    problem. In the Personnel Office, we did some good things. Part of our problem
                    in sending people overseas was that we did it based on just a brief description:
                    “We need an agricultural expert for Formosa, in rice.” So, what we did was, I
                    had a very excellent man named Ernest Barbour working for me. We set up
                    something called an “AirPar: Airgram Personnel Action Request.” It had details
                    so that you would have details on precisely what it was this job required in
                    terms of relationships, what that person had to do, what the duties and
                    responsibilities were, and the relationships with other people, with say the
                    Agricultural Attach� of the Embassy, with the government and so on. But it was
                    done on an Airgram, which was a faster means of communication.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>A thing I devoted quite a bit of my attention to, working personally with Don
                    Stone - although I was the Deputy, he liked to work with me - was that we wanted
                    to orient people to work overseas. You could hire a person who'd be a perfectly
                    fine accountant. Well, let's not use accountant because that would be internal.
                    Let's say, a perfectly fine agricultural person in Denver or Atlanta, but send
                    them into Southern Greece or Indochina and they wouldn't work so well. So, what
                    we tried to do was give them some orientation. For that, we used the very
                    excellent people they had in the Department of State. In those days, they had
                    cultural anthropologists. They had one man named Edward T. Hall, a fine cultural
                    anthropologist. We sent them for some training there. I myself took courses at
                    the Washington School of Psychiatry in anthropology. We also used people from
                    the Farm Security Administration to help us orient people because they were
                    dealing not with other cultures but, in places like New Mexico, you're dealing
                    with a Hispanic culture. You're dealing with some other cultures in Southern
                    Louisiana and so on. But you had to get at it in the recruiting. So, we set up a
                    joint project of the United States Public Health Service, the Air Force, the
                    Civil Service Commission and ourselves to see how you could ascertain before a
                    person went overseas whether that person would be able to operated in that kind
                    of an environment. We needed some extra money for this. With all of our money,
                    we didn't have money in the budget. We needed $50,000. So, Don Stone and I went
                    up to see the head of the Agency, whose name was John Kenney, who had been the
                    legal man for the U.S. Navy during the War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was the head of the MSA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, John Kenney. By then, we were MSA - Mutual Security Agency. Don and
                    I went up to see him. Don was leading the conversation. He said, “You know, Mr.
                    Kenney, there are other things in life and in Personnel than just how well a
                    person does the job.” John Kenney was the kind of man who would go to the
                    Metropolitan Club every day for lunch, have a couple of Manhattans, smoked a big
                    cigar... He's a wonderful, able man, by the way. I don't mean to denigrate him.
                    He learned back in his chair and said, “Don, I think I know what you're talking
                    about. When I was the Legal Counsel for the Navy during WWII, I had quite a
                    staff of officers, lawyers working for me. And one man, Don, drank.” You know,
                    Haven, that Don did not drink, nor did he swear. Kenney said, “Sometimes, you
                    could smell liquor on his breath. So, I called my Exec and I said, 'You know, we
                    have to get rid of that fellow. Get him out, get him reassigned, but get him
                    out.' Two or three weeks went by and I saw the man was still there, so I called
                    in the Exec and I said, 'Why is he still here?' And he said, 'You know, Mr.
                    Kenney, you know how much trouble we've had finding you a good secretary that
                    you really like? She's been pretty unhappy in Washington and she had threatened
                    to go back to her home, but she fell in love with this man and he's been
                    sleeping with her and keeping her happy. So, in order to keep her, we've kept
                    him.'” And Kenney said, “Now, is that what you mean?” And Don blushed red. Dear,
                    sweet Don nodded his head and we got our $50,000. To this day, Haven, I still
                    don't know whether we have tests that can ascertain in advance whether a person
                    is going to function well in a foreign environment.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did this group produce?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: They produced a study of this, that and the other that I don't remember
                    much about because it didn't- Well, they found that a rigid personality didn't
                    work well overseas. But I had come up really earlier that what you needed to
                    find in people to be a successful overseas person, if you could ascertain it,
                    was whether he had a decent, really solid sense of humor. A person who doesn't
                    take himself seriously, who can adjust to different environments.</p>
                <p>One thing happened during that period which was very interesting. My old boss
                    from Albuquerque, Dr. Aberle, came to Washington. She had a wonderful idea. She
                    went to see her Senator, Clinton P. Anderson, who went to Harriman- By that
                    time, I'd been assigned to Harriman. Harriman came back from Paris to be a
                    Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Assistance Affairs, to kind of
                    coordinate from the White House level, MSA. And by that point, you had TCA, the
                    Technical Cooperation Administration, popularly known as “Point 4.” You had the
                    Institute of Inter American Affairs, which is the old Latin American group, and
                    you had some military assistance coming onto the Defense Department. Truman put
                    Harriman in charge of all that. He had a small staff over in the Old Executive
                    Office Building, where the Vice President has his office now. He had on his
                    staff John Murphy, Ted Tannenwald as his lawyer, Lincoln Gordon as his Program
                    Officer, a man named William Sheppard as his administrative man, and a labor
                    person who later became Ambassador to Korea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was in 1951?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: This was about 1952. I was sent over to be the Personnel man. So, I had
                    two jobs, really. I was still the Deputy of Personnel. So, Dr. Aberle went to
                    Harriman and asked-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were a Deputy in the MSA. You had moved from ECA to
                        MSA.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: ECA had become MSA. Harriman's job was called “Special Coordinator for
                    Mutual Security,” but we still had a Mutual Security Agency and that was headed
                    by John Kenney. Dr. Aberle went to Harriman and asked for my detail for three or
                    four weeks to New Mexico. Her idea was that, here you have these three cultures,
                    the Native American, the Hispanic, and the Anglo. And you had these
                    universities: the University of New Mexico, New Mexico State and so on. Couldn't
                    there be some kind of a consortium put together of these colleges and
                    universities that could be used as training for people going overseas for Point
                    4, for TCA?</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>I went to New Mexico and we worked it out. We got a consortium - all of the
                    schools of higher learning to train people to go overseas for TCA. The only
                    problem was that we never discussed this with TCA. So, I came back, presented
                    this report, and they never used it. They never sent anyone to be trained by
                    TCA. But this was the forerunner. They did exactly that later with the Peace
                    Corps. The Peace Corps did that kind of training, which Point 4 should have done
                    at that point.</p>
                <p>I was consulting with other parts of TCA. TCA was much different than MSA. TCA
                    was just a consortium of agencies. Each had its own budget for overseas
                    activities. Once a year, they'd sit around a table and they would decide what
                    they were going to do generally in Country X or Country Y.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A consortium of government agencies?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: All government agencies. And they all had their own offices. They were
                    all called “Point 4” offices. Agriculture had a Point 4 office that coordinated
                    their work. Interior had its own and so on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ECA had its own staff, too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Of course, they had nothing to do with us. They didn't use Foreign
                    Service. There was Public Law 600 in those days. They could set up jobs at the
                    same level, but they didn't use the Foreign Service. We had talks. Phillip Glick
                    was their General Counsel. Phillip Glick was an old friend of mine from War
                    Relocation Days and we talked about some day trying to put TCA on the same basis
                    as MSA. Later, when Eisenhower became President, he was confronted with this
                    problem. It just smacked him right in the face.</p>
                <p>TCA had an office in Jordan and it had an office in Israel. Part of the Interior,
                    Bureau of Reclamation or something had sent some engineers to Jordan to work out
                    what should be done with the Jordan River. Very complicated - two Ambassadors
                    were involved, and so on. They worked out how the water should be divided in the
                    Jordan River, which would have led, maybe, to some peace beginning between
                    Jordan and Israel. We're talking of early days of the Eisenhower Administration
                    - '53.</p>
                <p>But the engineer working for the Department of the Interior had gone to the King
                    of Jordan and said, “Don't do this. You're being taken for a ride. You're not
                    getting your fair share” and blew the whole thing up. Eisenhower sent Secretary
                    Dulles out. Dulles came back and reported this and Ike just hit the ceiling. He
                    had a fabulous temper, as you know. He said, “Fire this son of a bitch!”</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>This led to Eisenhower's feeling that there should be one arm overseas, and not
                    all these proliferations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that time, TCA had field staff, MSA had field
                        staff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Right, and we had both right in the same country, like India.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a Mission that TCA had?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, these were all Missions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And there was an MSA Mission as well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes. To go back just a minute on this whole business of organizations,
                    the Institute of Inter American Affairs was begun during the War mostly by
                    Nelson Rockefeller, by setting up corporations in Delaware. You had an institute
                    for agriculture, one for health, one for education. This man, Dillon Myer, that
                    we mentioned earlier was made the President of the Institute of Inter American
                    Affairs. He found that in these countries - they were called “Field Parties;” an
                    Education Field Party, an Agricultural Field Party, a Health Field Party - they
                    didn't speak to each other. He, being a good administrator, said, “Look, these
                    three can help each other.” To use a popular word now that I learned in Mexico,
                    they could be “synergistic.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were responsible to the Ambassador, or just to their
                        home office?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: To their home office. Well, they had some kind of a loose responsibility
                    to the - but they kept themselves VERY separate from the Embassy. Very separate.
                    In fact, we could even have recalled our Ambassador, but the Institute would go
                    right on working. They felt, and I tend to agree largely with them, that the
                    technical assistance to go on to help build the institutions of the country and
                    to build the human resources of the country are so important that they ought to
                    go on, and someday they'll lead to democracy. They prided themselves on not
                    being a part of the Embassy. Mr. Myer did not want to put them under the
                    Ambassador. He just wanted them coordinated among themselves to get the biggest
                    bang for the buck. He set up the idea that one of the three would become the top
                    institute in that country.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>I've got an anecdote about Dillon Myer that I think is worth being put down
                    historically. I was having dinner one night many years later with the former
                    head of the Budget Bureau, named Frederick Lawton. We were talking about Dillon
                    Myer and he began to chuckle. He said, “I've got a great story about President
                    Truman and Dillon Myer.” I said, “What's that, Mr. Lawton?” He said, “I went to
                    the President to go over the budget and, as you know, President Truman went over
                    the budget line by line. We came to the Institute of Inter American Affairs -
                    this was about 1946 or '47. The figure we'd put in for the entire foreign aid
                    was $3,500,000 to Latin America. Truman said, 'No, no, $5 million.'” Lawton
                    said, “Well, Mr. President, I don't understand. The State Department and the
                    Bureau of the Budget agreed on $3,500,000. I know that Dillon Myer wants $5
                    million, but we asked for $3,500,000 because the State Department wants to phase
                    all that out.” (State's always been against foreign aid, by the way. Now, maybe
                    they've learned that it's a useful tool.) Truman said, “No, no. I want to give
                    Myer $5 million. He came over to see me personally and he convinced me of it.
                    Besides, I'm going to ask him to take a shitty ass job.” I said to Mr. Lawton,
                    “Did the President really use those words?” He said, “Those were his exact
                    words.” The job that he later asked Dillon to take, which he took, was to become
                    Commissioner of Indian Affairs, which is that kind of a job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was in what position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: He was the head of the Institute of Inter American Affairs, one of the
                    many foreign aid agencies. These were the days of the Eisenhower
                    Administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said that you had a situation where Eisenhower reacted
                        to this multiplicity of agencies overseas.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: He decided that all the foreign affairs agencies would be brought
                    together. He brought in Governor Harold Stassen to be the head of all of that -
                    in essence, first to take the Harriman job. That's how he began it - just moved
                    into Harriman's office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Harriman was the MSA Coordinator and then he was replaced
                        by Jack Bell, was he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, this was later.</p>
                <p>So, Stassen was brought in to be the MSA Coordinator. He called us all in and he
                    said that he wanted to set up an agency. He could do it under Executive Order.
                    He didn't need a law at that point. We started some studies for him.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>I want to go back just a second though, Haven. When Eisenhower came in, there was
                    this great hoorah about security in the government. So, they put in J. Edgar
                    Hoover's closest associates all over town as Security Officers. We had one in
                    AID. His name was Thomas Naughten, a very nice guy. But he was an FBI man. He
                    had only collected information; he had never evaluated information. We had a
                    very good security staff. We had a man named Walter Yeagley. I can't remember
                    the name of his Deputy, another good man. Well, they were gotten rid of, because
                    they'd been there before. Whatever new Administration comes in, they don't like
                    whatever was there before, whether it's Republican versus Democrat or Democrat
                    versus Republican. The interesting thing about Walter Yeagley and his Deputy was
                    that they were then hired by the Attorney General. Walter was made Assistant
                    Attorney General and his Deputy was made Deputy Assistant Attorney General. But
                    they weren't good enough for Mr. Stassen. And they were put in charge of
                    internal security for the country! But he just assumed that all these security
                    clearances that had been given before were not good enough. It was just
                    ridiculous.</p>
                <p>Stassen was given a mandate from Congress to cut personnel paid from
                    administrative funds by something like 28%. He had 60 days to do it in. He could
                    cut these people without regard to any law, including the Pendleton Act,
                    Veterans's Preference, or anything else. Now, we had done this before. We had
                    cut staff before. Congress loves to do this. Congress always felt that the
                    foreign aid program was too big. There was always something called the Ribicoff
                    amendments, named after a Congressman who later became a Secretary of HEW. The
                    Ribicoff amendment was the same thing. The way we'd done it before under MSA is
                    that we would reorganize. For instance, you had a Program Office that had 12
                    people in it, maybe you could get along with 10. Or if you had an Agricultural
                    Office, you could get along with 10 instead of 13. Then we would RIF - Reduction
                    in Force. The usual way, with all the protection, until it hurt. Then if it
                    hurt, the head of the office would say, “Here's a very young person. He doesn't
                    have a lot of retention rights, but he's so bright that I don't want to lose
                    him. I want to keep him.” And then another person would say, “Look, this guy has
                    been coasting for the last 10 years. He goes out and has three martinis for
                    lunch. I want to get rid of him,” even though he could be protected. Those cases
                    would go up to a board, chaired by the top three people of the Agency under the
                    Administrator, usually by a man named C. Tyler Wood, a wonderful man. One of the
                    pillars of the Agency. And they would make a decision. And legally, they could
                    either keep that one person or let the other person go. It worked
                    beautifully.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>Well, we went to see Governor Stassen, Bill Sheppard and I and said, “This is the
                    way we did it before.” He said, “If Truman did it that way, it's not good enough
                    for me.” Truman had nothing to do with it! We said, “Governor, how do you
                    propose we do it then?” He said, “Give everyone an examination. Give everyone a
                    test.” And we said, “But Governor, you don't give tests to people once they're
                    in the Agency. You have other ways you can evaluate them.” “No, give them a
                    test.” Well, I still didn't accept it. I went over to the Civil Service
                    Commission and I got Milton Mandel, who was the head of Examinations. One of the
                    foremost testing people in the United States. He came over to see the Governor.
                    He tried to talk Stassen out of it. Stassen wouldn't be talked out of it. So, we
                    gave everyone in Washington the exam - two exams. One was a general intelligence
                    test. One was an administrative test. I forget them all. The only two exempt
                    from the test were Stassen and myself, except we decided to take it. And we both
                    passed, I want you to know, Haven, with pretty good grades. Stassen was a very
                    bright person, by the way, for all of his other failings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This test was developed by -</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: By the Civil Service Commission. And then Stassen sat down for three to
                    four weeks. We had set up for him in the Old Executive Office Building, a kind
                    of a command center. I personally would have to carry over - we had our offices
                    over in the Lafayette Building - these personnel folders and put them on his
                    table. He had a pot of coffee going on a burner. That's the way he'd learned to
                    do it in the Navy. He'd been Exec under Admiral Halsey during the War. He was a
                    Navy guy, you see. He put together the test scores, plus these unrefined
                    security files. He'd look through the security file, the test score, the
                    personnel folder and decide whether anyone was going to go or stay. He did this
                    on every single individual in the Washington office, except those paid from
                    Program funds, which was a small number. They were in the technical
                    assistance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many people are we talking about?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: Several hundred. Seven or eight hundred. It was a prodigious job. And he
                    had his own formula. And we would talk. He said, “You know, Mel, if I've got 12
                    economists and I find one economist that I can't find anything else on except
                    that he had a bad debt record, then that's the one I'm going to let go.” And
                    that's what he did. If he had the flimsiest kind of security thing, for
                    instance, someone was on the Rolodex of somebody like Alger Hiss, that's the
                    person that he got rid of. On the other hand, if I could go to Stassen and say,
                    “We have a hardship case,” he would keep him. There was one case of a man whose
                    wife called and said, “He's dying. He cannot urinate. The urine's building up in
                    his body. He weighed 125 pounds and now weighs 175 - he's dying.” So, I
                    immediately called my doctor and said, “Is this possible?” He said, “Oh, yes,
                    psychosomatically.” So then I got the head of Health at State to get in touch
                    with the doctor. They confirmed the diagnosis. I then went to Stassen, who said,
                    “Oh, yes, keep him.” The man recovered completely. Governor Stassen would tell
                    me who to keep and who to fire. He'd give me a list. And I'd have to issue the
                    letters. They came out over my name. But I'd push him a little bit. I couldn't
                    push him very much. There would be wives who would go into hysterics, who would
                    have nervous breakdowns, over whether their husbands were going to be fired.
                    Stassen kept a lot of them twisting in the wind until he could make up his mind.
                    I worked a couple of nights all night, 24 hours. I worked seven days a week for
                    maybe five weeks and then I worked nights, in order to get these letters out.
                    And to someone who was in trouble, I would call and say, “Look, the letter's on
                    its way. You're in.” It was a terrible, terrible time. When it was all over, he
                    brought in a new man named General Riley from the Marine Corps. He had served in
                    Haiti way back. Stassen had gotten to know him under Halsey and he was a real
                    Marine Corps type. He called me in one day and he said, “There's 48 more people
                    that the Governor wants you to fire.” I said, “On what basis, General?” He said,
                    “He wants you to fire them, the way you did all these other people.” I said, “We
                    don't have that law anymore.” He said, “Find a way.” I said, “No, General. I
                    won't find a way. If you've got anything against these people, they ought to
                    have security hearings or anything else” and I went home for three weeks. I just
                    walked out. I just couldn't take it anymore. Heck, I had been wanting to quit
                    all the way through. He had fired people that were friends of mine for no good
                    reason at all. He fired Don Stone. That's how Don got out of the government and
                    went up and became the head of a College and began his whole other wonderful
                    career in public administration.</p>
                <p>We had five Controllers and he picked one. He picked Johnny Murphy because he
                    knew him. He was sitting right there. It was a terrible time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any public or Congressional reaction to
                        this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Not an awful lot really. Felix Belair of the New York Times would write
                    it up, but not an awful lot happened. This was Eisenhower and Mr. Nixon gave
                    ideas out: “We're getting rid of people. We're getting rid of security risks”
                    whether they were or not.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These people who were gotten rid of were then tainted with
                        this image.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yeah, they were tainted. Some people were rehired by other agencies. A
                    lot of them went to CIA. Some of them ended up in USIA. Others went to
                    foundations. But, yeah, they were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was limited to Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No. Mission Directors, Deputy Mission Directors and Program Officers
                    were all paid from administrative funds. If Congress had been smart, they would
                    have said “Administrative and Program,” but they didn't. That's why I luckily
                    had no authority over those other programs, because the people he wanted to fire
                    were all in technical assistance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was overseas affected then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: He did bring some people back, but he did not give them any exam. He
                    just had reasons: political reasons, security reasons - or what he thought were
                    security reasons. For instance, the man that I replaced down in Mexico had been
                    yanked by Stassen for the only reason that his name appeared on a list, on
                    someone's Rolodex, who was a suspect.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, this test was really not a significant factor?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, it was a significant factor, too. In fact, at one time, Johnny
                    Murphy walked into Stassen and said, “You know, we can't get our payroll
                    out.”</p>
                <p>Stassen said, “Why, Johnny?”</p>
                <p>He said, “You fired all my payroll clerks.”</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>Now, they were on the test, you see. It was a terrible, terrible time and clouded
                    the Agency for many years. In fact, when we set up AID, that was in mind because
                    it was lingering still in people's minds. But, now I want to go back a few
                    months. When Eisenhower came in, he had a man in his White House named Phillip
                    Reed, the former President of General Electric, to be head of all U.S.
                    Government Personnel. He was also Chairman of the Civil Service Commission. But
                    in the White House, Phillip Reed had two assistants. One on Domestic Personnel.
                    We're not talking about hiring and firing. We're talking about Personnel
                    systems. And one on Domestic, named Joe Winslow. The other named Henry DuFlon.
                    “Hank,” as I called him, was interested in Overseas: what to do about the
                    overseas personnel, the very question that you brought up earlier about “Should
                    they be all under one system or not?” There was a tremendous pressure from the
                    Defense Department to put everyone under Civil Service, to wipe away the Foreign
                    Service, because all of their civilians were under Civil Service. So, Hank went
                    around to see all the Personnel Officers around town. He went to see me, of
                    course. He went to see USIA - everybody. And he gradually was coming up with the
                    idea that there ought to be an all inclusive Foreign Affairs- He did agree,
                    because we all made it very clear, that working in the Foreign Service was much
                    different than working in the Civil Service. In the Foreign Service, you're
                    taking on all kinds of hardships, you were cut off from other opportunities. I
                    mean, if you're fired here in Washington, you go to another agency. You've got
                    friends who you're networking with. You can have investment. You know all the
                    reasons, Haven, why I've always thought that the Foreign Service should have
                    special consideration - better retirement, better health, and so on. And he was
                    impressed with that, I guess, because after I'd been home a couple weeks, I got
                    a call from Hank, saying, “What are you doing?” I said, “I'm doing nothing:
                    waterproofing the basement.” He said, “I need help over in the White House.” So,
                    there I am the next day, working in the White House, and Stassen doesn't know
                    what to make of all this. Here is this guy- Oh, by the way, I didn't tell you
                    that there was a letter about me that went to Eisenhower. There was a woman
                    named Frances Knight. She was then working for USIA. She got the idea that the
                    Democratic personnel officers were thwarting President Eisenhower's work. And
                    then she used me as an example. For example: Mel Spector. Well, I was not a
                    registered anything. At that point, I was not registered. But she said in all
                    these letters, that I'd set up an outplacement service only to take care of
                    Democrats. And who was the head of all this but that notorious Democrat, Tighe
                    Wood. Well, actually it was C. Tyler Wood. She thought it was Tighe Wood, a man
                    who'd been the head of the Federal Housing Administration. In fact the person
                    that I had in charge of outplacement was a woman who had been recommended to me
                    by Senator Robert Taft of Ohio. It was ridiculous, of course, but Hank took the
                    letter in to Eisenhower and Ike hit the ceiling. He said, “Ty Wood? This is
                    ridiculous! Ty Wood is one of my best friends!” He and Ty were bridge playing
                    partners from Paris when Ike was the head of NATO and Ty was then the head of
                    the remnants of the Marshall Plan. So, I was saved.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>There I was working for Hank DuFlon. And our idea was, which I always had been in
                    favor of, was for a combined Foreign Service that would have included foreign
                    assistance (ICA and Point 4), State and Information. Hank had made a
                    presentation to the Chairman of the Senate Operations Committee named Joseph
                    McCarthy, who had approved of it. He'd done presentations all over the Hill.
                    Everyone liked it on the Hill. You then had a Republican Congress, you know, in
                    the early days of Ike. So, we were off and running. We felt that, finally, we
                    were getting something done. And we got a call one day. Someone on the Hill
                    called Hank and said, “Have you ever heard of a man named 'Wriston?'” And he
                    said, “No.” “He's the President of the National City Bank in New York. He's been
                    brought to Washington to work out a new personnel system for the Foreign
                    Service.” Scotty McLeod, who was J. Edgar Hoover's man over in the State
                    Department, and the Foreign Service knew what we were up to. The Foreign Service
                    did not want this all-inclusive service at all. So, they brought in Wriston to
                    head up the Wriston Committee. We were shot out of the water. Then Ike had to
                    choose between two different things. He had to either choose between Walter
                    “Bedell” Smith, who was the Under Secretary of State at that point, or his own
                    man, Sherman Adams, who was his Chief of Staff. Sherman Adams was on our side.
                    We were working for Sherman Adams. President Eisenhower went with his own
                    people: Walter “Bedell” Smith. We had Wristonization. This is not a subject of
                    this paper, but you know what that was: it put everyone into the Foreign Service
                    and ruined the institutional memory of the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Maybe you ought to comment a little bit about specifics -
                        the main lines of what Wristonization did.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: What Wristonization did was they put everybody in State, except the very
                    lowest clerical people, into the Foreign Service. They made them all Foreign
                    Service Officers. Commissioned Officers; not reserves. For a long time, the
                    State Department had Civil Service in Washington and Foreign Service overseas.
                    The Foreign Service came back and served. Very much like the Defense Department,
                    with civilians and commissioned personnel. There was some logic to the idea that
                    the people in Washington had become entrenched with their own ideas and never
                    served overseas. I remember one particular case which I came to know very well
                    later: Mexico. They had a woman named Ruth Hughes, who ran Mexico for years and
                    years and years. She started out as a clerk-typist and rose and rose and rose.
                    Other people came and went. Administrations came and went. Ambassadors came and
                    went. Ruth Hughes ran Mexico policy. So the idea was that you had to get rid of
                    these people. Actually, Ruth got assigned to Mexico later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the Wristonization, though, what was their
                        recommendation vis a vis the foreign assistance types?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: Wriston only involved the Department of State. It didn't involve anyone
                    else. It didn't involve USIA, which had been set up at the same time as FOA. It
                    didn't involve us. So, it put everybody in the Foreign Service and sent people
                    to the field who really didn't want to go to the field.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was really a State Department Foreign Service-Civil
                        Service issue.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Right. And it took an awful lot of people out of the Civil Service,
                    except for the lower grades. And I think they let a few people stay that were
                    various specialists in one kind or another. I think it was bad for the State
                    Department in some ways, in that you ruined the institutional memory that it
                    had. The State Department, and I think AID- I remember many years later, when I
                    became an Executive Director in State, finding very high level officers
                    personally going through files because there was no way to find out what had
                    transpired before. So that was bad.</p>
                <p>But I'd like to talk a little bit more about Stassen. Stassen, of course, took
                    the President's mandate to heart and set up one agency, which he designed
                    himself on the back of a dry-cleaning wrapper. In the old days, they used to put
                    a long piece of paper over the dry cleaning when they brought it home. Well,
                    Stassen one night designed the Foreign Operations Administration on the back of
                    one of those things and gave it to us and said, “This is it.” Of course, the
                    idea was that everything be under one Agency, so that you didn't have any more
                    Jordan River problems or Philippine problems. We abolished all of the Point 4
                    offices in all the agencies around town, because anyone that came to work for
                    FOA would be on the FOA payroll and subject to the policies and directions of
                    FOA.</p>
                <p>The creation of the Foreign Operations Administration - 1953</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the creation of FOA.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: This was the creation of the Foreign Operations Administration. It was
                    called that to distinguish it from the State Department, which would lay down
                    policy. It was kind of ridiculous, because you still have policy in FOA. But the
                    idea was that Dulles would lay down policy and Harold Stassen would operate. And
                    so we had that horrible name of the Foreign Operations Administration, and then
                    we had a name for our Missions which was terrible: United States Operations
                    Mission. Very bad. But that's what we were stuck with.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>Stassen was a very funny guy. For example, he was on a trip with Secretary
                    Dulles. It was their first trip to the Mid East. When they got to Greece, the
                    price of bread had just been raised before their arrival and there were riots.
                    Of course, our Mission there had a lot to do with that. The Mission Director,
                    whose name was Leland Barrows, was on home leave. The acting director there was
                    named Alvin Roseman. Stassen thought Roseman was responsible. He wired me and he
                    said, “Recall Roseman.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was the-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Acting Mission Director in Greece. So, I recalled Al and that was all:
                    just recall him. Stassen, on his return, said, “I want to see him.” Stassen had
                    his office where there is now, I think, the Vice President's office - what used
                    to be General Pershing's office. There was no real waiting room. We had to put
                    couches in the hall of the Old Executive Office Building with reading lamps so
                    people could sit there and possibly read. Al would show up every morning at 8:30
                    and wait until 5:30 to see the Governor. The Governor wouldn't see him, but he
                    wanted him there anyway. He just kept him there day after day after day.
                    Finally, about after six or seven days, he called him in, chatted, and sent him
                    back to Greece. It was a cat and mouse. The same thing with our Deputy Mission
                    Director in France. He called him back. He later became our Ambassador to Haiti.
                    Stassen was a strange guy. And yet he was brilliant. He was one of the most
                    brilliant men I think we've ever had to head the Foreign Aid Program. He really
                    understood it. He was wonderful on the Hill. People loved him. As a friend of
                    mine, Carl Albert, the Whip on the Hill, told me when he came to Mexico, “This
                    man's brilliant.” I said, “Well, Carl, he may be brilliant, but he's a bad
                    administrator.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any sense of what he saw as the mission of
                        the FOA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: As far as the basic mission of FOA, he was for development. Very much
                    for it. And I think he understood it. He was the guy who really pressed the idea
                    of contracting with private institutions. The problem with that was that you'd
                    contract at almost any cost and they didn't do enough evaluation of the
                    contractor beforehand, or the kind of people that the contractor would send to
                    us. But one of the good things that happened- Later, when you would make
                    contracts now with, say, government agencies, you still need the USGS or you
                    still would need various specialists from the government, you made a contract
                    with that agency. That person came onto FOA's rolls. I forget how we did it in
                    those days, but you had a deal with- You knew exactly what that person was
                    supposed to do. They weren't there as independent operators reporting back to
                    USGS. They were reporting to the local Mission Director and to the
                    Ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With the Personnel matter, were there other personnel or
                        organizational factors that Stassen was interested in that you were involved
                        in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, the only thing that-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in the process of cutting staff then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: We cut a lot of staff using Stassenization. We cut over 200 people, I
                    would say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Out of how many roughly?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Eight or nine hundred people. Something like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So when you combined the Agency, you cut these?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: And we cut all the Point 4 people. The Point 4 in their own offices were
                    absorbed. They had nothing to do with this. They were absorbed by their own
                    Agency. The Institute of Inter American Affairs was put out of business after
                    all these years. It became the Latin America arm of the Foreign Operations
                    Administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this a regionally focused organization or a
                        functional? Was it mostly concerned with geographic areas or was it more
                        concerned with-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Well, it had both. And that was always an uneasy relationship. I though
                    it was mostly geographical. Later, when AID was set up, this was a big problem.
                    This was what the people that set up AID thought ought to be done: the focus
                    should be largely regional. Because the man who'd run the Agency for many years
                    was Dr. Dennis FitzGerald.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was in the ICA period. Was he in FOA?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, Fitz was there from the beginning. Fitz came in as a Food and
                    Agricultural Officer under Hoffman. And then he stayed on to become the pivotal
                    man to run the Agency. But, because Fitz had come out of the functional areas,
                    out of Agriculture, he had a very great regard for that. So you can't counter
                    the uneasy balance between the geographic on one side and the functional on the
                    other. Towards the end of FOA, he had two Deputies. One was Herman Kleine and
                    Don McFail. One was the geographic guy and one was the functional guy. That was
                    one reason that, when the Kennedy people came in, they were determined to
                    emphasize geography and also build on research, which I don't think was ever as
                    fully carried out as we had hoped on the research side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved in the transition from ICA to FOA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No. That time I was in Mexico.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you want to talk a little more about your experience
                        with FOA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, I would, Haven. I want to talk in kind of generic terms about two
                    things. One is politics in government, and maybe more specifically in the
                    Foreign Aid or Development Assistance Program. The first five years of the
                    Marshall Plan, I could not see anything that we'd normally attribute to what is
                    called politics.” It's certainly true that, in the best sense of the word,
                    Truman wanted to set up a non-partisan agency. And so that's why he appointed a
                    Republican to head the Program in the United States and a Democrat to head it
                    over in Europe for the Marshall Plan. It is certainly true that Paul Hoffman, by
                    having his brother in law, Tex Moore, do his executive recruitment, they were
                    recruiting people they knew; and they were just generally normally Republicans.
                    But I never saw, in my time, the first five years of ECA and MSA, down at the
                    operating level - and that meant anything under the Deputy Director of the
                    Agency - anything called “politics.” We were importuned many times to make
                    political appointments and I fought them. I went into government idealistically.
                    I read up on the English system, on the Merit System, and believe then, as I do
                    now, always did follow through, I think, without exception, that at the top of
                    the Agency, you certainly should have a political appointee to carry out the
                    wishes of the President and of the Administration. But under that, there should
                    be the Merit System. And I think that's what makes the English system great and
                    our system great and any democracy great.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>In the FOA, after Stassenization, Stassen brought in a young friend of his named
                    Betty Crites. Betty was a beautiful young woman. She'd been a Miss something or
                    other. She came from Minnesota. She was beautiful. She was ambitious. She was
                    completely devoted to Harold Stassen. And I don't mean that in any lascivious
                    way. I don't mean that at all. I think she's one of these young, idealistic
                    women that looked up to the Governor and he was everything that she wanted to
                    see happen in politics and in the government. He put her right outside my office
                    door. I was the Acting Director of Personnel. She had a desk right outside my
                    door and she ordered, under his direction, that every Personnel action had to go
                    over her desk and she vetted it. She was always coming in to me, saying, “Now
                    why are we promoting this person? Why, I have a person here, Joe Blow from
                    Duluth, Minnesota, that could perfectly fill that job.” And I'd say, “Betty, I'm
                    glad to consider it. Let's put it in the pile and if this is the best qualified
                    person we have...” “No, no, no. We need to hire him. The Governor wants him
                    hired,” and on and on and on. And I went to the Civil Service Commission. I went
                    to the Executive Director. This was all oral. I didn't have anything written,
                    but I went to him. His name was John Macy. He's now dead. John later became
                    Chairman of the Civil Service Commission, a big shot in public administration.
                    But he really weaseled right out of it. He said, “Mel, I can't touch it.” And
                    she was breaking laws. She was breaking the Pendleton Act and the Veterans
                    Preference Act and everything else. That really soured me on Governor Stassen
                    and on the whole situation. Much later, when the Democrats came back, Ralph
                    Dungan tried to track down Betty Crites and get her fired out of the government,
                    but she had buried herself in a Civil Service job by then. The very Civil
                    Service that she had tried to circumvent, she then used it for her own benefit
                    to get buried securely into the government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you stuck with having to hire some of these
                        people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, yes. And I didn't want to do it, but I fought it wherever I could.
                    I think, generally, she and I had a pretty good personal relationship. I said,
                    “Betty, you've got to see it from my standpoint.” I don't remember too much of
                    it, but every now and then there was someone stuck in there that shouldn't have
                    been in there. But, after all, the head of the agency has the authority and he
                    delegates it to you. So, if he wants to use that authority- Now what I probably
                    should have done was say, “I'll send these up to the Governor and let him sign
                    them,” but I wasn't that smart, I suppose.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They didn't have these things called “Schedule Cs?”</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: We had Schedule Cs, which could have been used, but these were overseas
                    positions for FOA. And, as you know, Haven, there is no protection, or there
                    wasn't then. You could hire anyone to go into the Foreign Service. Anybody.
                    There was no criteria. Joe Toner did a beautiful job much later in getting the
                    Directors and the Deputies of Missions taken off the Plum Book, but they really
                    are open to anybody's wanting to appoint to them. I bet they still are. I don't
                    know what's been done since my time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's probably true.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: The other thing is this kow-towing to this idea that businessmen know
                    best. Stassen brought in forty to 45 businessmen to fan out all over the world,
                    to look at out Missions and to, inside of a week, decide what had to be done to
                    improve them and so on. These were men like the President of Gillette
                    Corporation, the Chairman of the First National Bank of Boston. Very high-level
                    people. These were all kind of high-level payoffs, you know. Stassen's aide
                    wanted them hired as consultants. So I said, “Fine, but we have to give them all
                    a security clearance.” And he said, “What? You're questioning that these
                    businesspeople need a security clearance?” I said, “I don't care what they've
                    ever done, but I'm saying that the law says that, unless the Administrator will
                    issue a waiver, we need a security clearance.” He and Stassen signed it right
                    off. We brought all these men to town and the first night they were in town, a
                    lot of them were staying at the Hay Adams, right across from the White House. I
                    got a call from the Deputy Chief of Security, Charlie Keating. He was laughing.
                    He said, “I've just been down to the police station to get one of your new men
                    out of jail.” One of them had gone right over to Lafayette Park and had accosted
                    a young man in the urinal there, who was an undercover policeman. He was put in
                    for soliciting. So, after that, Stassen never signed a waiver on security. But
                    this idea that businessmen know best will come up later when we talk about
                    AID.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>Stassen saw later that I was acceptable to the White House. In fact, I was being
                    processed by the White House for a Personnel job, but we were shot out of the
                    water, as I told you, by Wristonization. But I didn't want to go back to
                    Personnel and deal with all that political stuff and deal with Betty Crites and
                    prostitute my job. And I wanted to go overseas. Stassen said, “You can go
                    anywhere you want to. You can be a Deputy Mission Director anywhere.” I said,
                    “Paris?” He said, “Sure.” I said, “But Lane Timmons is there!” He said, “We'll
                    just get rid of him.” I said, “London?” He said, “Yeah, anywhere.” But my father
                    was ill and I wanted to be close to him and I found out that the Assistant
                    Director job in Mexico City was open. So, I said that I would take that. He
                    said, “Well, just take it.” I said, “No, the Mission Director's got to approve
                    me,” so I wrote to the Mission Director, who disapproved me. He didn't want me.
                    The job really called for an economist and, although I had a minor in economics
                    in college, I was no economist. I was pretty blue at that point because I didn't
                    know what I wanted to do. But he came to Washington and he called me for lunch,
                    the Mission Director, Dinty Moore. He was an old Department of Agriculture man
                    and one of the best technical assistance men I've ever known. We had lunch and
                    he changed his mind. So, I got to go to Mexico as the Assistant Director. There
                    was no Deputy. I was really the Program Officer, but they gave it the nice title
                    of Assistant Director. But the man who'd been in that job had been Stassenated
                    and my name appeared at the bottom of the Personnel Action. So, people in Mexico
                    thought that I had gotten rid of this man to take that job. So, you could
                    imagine the kind of welcome I had in Mexico. I had nothing to do with it. My
                    predecessor was Stassenated because he'd been a friend of a man named William
                    Remington in the Department of Commerce, one of the famous McCarthy cases. The
                    man was perfectly fine, a first rate person. But I had to overcome that, believe
                    me.</p>
                <p>The program in Mexico was an interesting one. We had old and new. We had programs
                    in health, agriculture, industry, education, rubber, geological survey and
                    fisheries. Some of these were holdovers from the early days of World War II: the
                    rubber program, and fisheries, too, because before the War broke out, most of
                    the fishing from Mexico was done by the Japanese. They had left and the Mexicans
                    didn't have their own commercial-style fisheries. The Bureau of Fish and
                    Wildlife had sent a man down there to help them with their fisheries. He was
                    still there. He'd been there seven or eight years by the time I got there.</p>
                <p>Assignment to the FOA mission in Mexico - 1954-59</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you get there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I got there about March of 1954. We drove from Washington all the way to
                    Mexico City.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How big a program? What dollar value roughly?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: I'd say it was about $1.7 million. We had some PL 480 much later, but it
                    was all technical assistance. It sets the tone for what happened in Mexico. This
                    should go into some kind of a Mexico archives. In the early days of the
                    Eisenhower Administration, the idea was that there would be no loans to Latin
                    America. Period. Where this came from I don't know. But this was under Secretary
                    Humphrey of Treasury, Assistant Secretary Holland in Inter American Affairs, and
                    Deputy Secretary of State Herbert Hoover, Jr. It was called the “3H Program.”
                    What had happened was the Mexicans wanted to eliminate malaria in Mexico. Now,
                    this was a pretty good idea in our own U.S. interests, to eliminate malaria
                    because the malaria mosquito doesn't know that there's a border there. It can go
                    right over that border. The Mexicans had worked out this elaborate program of
                    getting money from WHO, FOA and they wanted a loan from the United States. The
                    top man in Mexico, the Minister of Finance, came up to Washington to try to
                    negotiate a four million dollar loan. Of course, he was laughed at, but he still
                    went to see Stassen. Stassen was a very bright guy, no matter what else you can
                    say about him, and he said, “Well, can you use local currency?” because Stassen
                    had it coming out of his ears. So, the man said, “What do you have?” And he
                    said, “Well, I've got Danish kroner, Italian lira, and Japanese yen.” In those
                    days, those were all soft currencies. Well, this man said, “Fine.” And Stassen
                    said, “But you'll have to repay it in dollars.” Here we were going to get rid of
                    our local currency, which we just didn't know what to do with, get it repaid in
                    dollars, eliminate malaria in Mexico, which was a threat to the United States,
                    and the Mexicans accepted it. They wanted it in lira for some reason. They took
                    the lira. Stassen was overruled by the State Department and Treasury. So, the
                    Mexicans, you know, said “What the Hell's going on here?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why were they overruled?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Because of no loans to Mexico.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Even in local currency?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Even in local currency. That's how stupid it was, Haven. You can imagine
                    the kind of atmosphere when I went to Mexico. More than that, we had an
                    Ambassador named Francis White. Francis White had been a career Foreign Service
                    Officer. He'd been trained in the Diplomatic School in Madrid in the early 20s,
                    became a career Foreign Service Officer. At the time that Franklin D. Roosevelt
                    became President, he was the equivalent to the Assistant Secretary of State for
                    Inter American Affairs, but then it was an Office Director - the Office of
                    American Republic Affairs, ARA, an out-of-date acronym which we've never gotten
                    rid of. He resigned his commission because he so disagreed with the Good
                    Neighbor Policy. And he became the head of something called the Foreign Bond
                    Holders Association. These were all the people that held bonds in all of the
                    expropriated properties like oil wells and railroads in Mexico, and railroads in
                    Brazil. His lawyer, the man that worked for him, was John Foster Dulles. I think
                    you get the picture now.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>In the interim years, the Ambassador - as a civilian, of course - had been the
                    head of the Republican Finance Committee many times. So, he was a staunch
                    Republican and he reported to President Eisenhower - not to Vice President
                    Nixon, not to the Secretary of State Dulles. He reported to Eisenhower. When he
                    came to Washington on visits, he would go in to see the President and then he'd
                    tell Dulles and the Office Director for Mexico what he and the President had
                    decided. He hated the Mexicans. He looked down on them. This was just a very bad
                    man. He did not believe in foreign assistance. He did not believe in USIA. He
                    just tolerated them because he had to.</p>
                <p>One of the programs we had was with the United States Geological Survey. Now,
                    they'd been there for many years. The USGS had worked very well with the
                    Mexicans. The Mexicans wanted a Mexican Geological Survey. The USGS party head
                    was first rate. He'd worked out this very good program where they'd send men up
                    to the United States to be trained in college and then go on and work in the
                    USGS offices. We were creating an institution: the Mexican Geological Survey.
                    Now, this was a big program and there was a lot of strategic interest in it back
                    here in the United States because we wanted to know ourselves what was in
                    Mexico, what kind of mineral resources, oil resources, and so on. We would have
                    been way ahead of the curve on their oil discovery if this had gone through. My
                    particular job was to negotiate that note. As you know, you sit down and you do
                    drafts to check with Washington. You go back and forth. Then I sent the note up
                    to Washington, where it was being cleared by State, FOA and the Department of
                    the Interior. And, of course, it was being cleared by the Mexican government.
                    Finally, the two governments were completely agreed. And this was agreed to at
                    the highest levels of Washington because of all these strategic interests. In
                    case of war, we had strategic materials that we could get either directly up
                    through by land route or across the Caribbean, the Gulf of Texas very easily
                    from Yucatan to New Orleans. I got the final draft, and showed it to my Mexican
                    counterpart, who was the Number two man in the Foreign Office. He put it in
                    final form. I put mine in final form. I gave it to the DCM. I couldn't deal with
                    the Ambassador. He wouldn't deal with me because I was FOA. I'd never been to
                    his house and he wouldn't deal with me, because I was AID. Week after week went
                    on and the note never came back from the Ambassador. It was getting very
                    embarrassing with the Mexican Foreign Office. Finally, one day, the DCM called
                    me up to his office and handed me the note. It hadn't been signed. I said,
                    “Bill, what's wrong?” He said, “The Ambassador won't sign it.” I said, “But this
                    has been approved by the very highest levels.” I knew it had to be. And he said,
                    “It doesn't matter to him. Mel, he doesn't believe in the USGS at home, so he
                    feels 'Why should we be sponsoring one abroad?'” Well, that was the atmosphere
                    in which we worked.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened to that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: It just dropped. It was killed and that was it. And this was in the U.S.
                    interest. We had a “Health Servicio” and I want to talk a minute about
                    servicios. A servicio was a concept that was, I think, invented mostly by the
                    Institute of Inter American Affairs and we used them throughout Latin America.
                    They were a joint institution between the U.S. and the host government. They
                    were jointly run. They were jointly financed with money from the local
                    government and money from the U.S. But when the money went into that Servicio,
                    it no longer became U.S. funds, so it was not subject to audit by the U.S.
                    Government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They weren't host government funds either, were they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No. We did encourage the host government to audit. I'd like to quote
                    from a very good book here, by Phil Glick, who was the General Counsel of TCA,
                    one of the best men they ever had. He says, “The creators of the servicio
                    believed that they could effectively teach and demonstrate only by working with
                    their hosts daily, over a long period of time, in the same organization on tasks
                    they could share.” That was the whole idea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What book is this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: This is a wonderful book. It's called The Administration of Technical
                    Assistance: Growth in the Americas by Phillip Glick, which, if I am assured that
                    there is going to be a permanent library at the Association of Diplomatic
                    Studies, I'll be glad to turnover to them, but only when I'm assured there's
                    going to be a place for it. It's a wonderful book. It's about the whole history
                    of technical assistance, from the beginning up through Stassen. The servicio
                    could be overdone. The servicio was a wonderful institution in a country that
                    had weak institutions, or where you wanted to try something new and you had
                    bloated bureaucracies that you couldn't deal with. When I got to Mexico, we had
                    a health servicio with about 12 American technicians. It was being run by the
                    American who was a United States Public Health Officer. We, the Mission Director
                    and I, felt strongly that servicios should be turned over more and more to the
                    local governments. It took a lot of arm twisting to get it first jointly run by
                    the Mexicans and the U.S. and then finally run by the Mexican, who was a very
                    able man. I felt that, in certain situations, servicios were an excellent way to
                    help a country to create an institution, or by example, show what could be done
                    with modern administration and technology. One of our great servicio men in Lima
                    - I forget his name - he felt that a servicio was like a hothouse. You would put
                    a plant in it and get it up to a certain point so that it was strong enough to
                    grow on its own and then you took it out and put it out in its natural
                    environment. Another simile: it is like a train. You put a servicio on the
                    train, and then you take them off. But I like the greenhouse thing better.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>They had problems. One of the problems was that we tried to pay higher salaries.
                    So, we'd have people in servicios maybe getting a higher salary than their
                    counterparts in other parts of the same Ministry. This was a problem, but we
                    said, “Again, this shows you what it really ought to be.” When AID was set up
                    and the Alliance for Progress came into being, the servicios were abolished.
                    This was largely due to one guy: Rueben Sternfeld, a first rate man, one of my
                    closest friends. He and I have disagreed on it ever since. He was very close to
                    Ted Moscoso.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did he want to terminate them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Because he believed they were wrong, that the U.S. Government had no
                    control. He'd come from the Bureau of the Budget: you ought to be able to
                    control this, audit it, and see that all that U.S. money is used correctly right
                    to the last penny.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Didn't we have pretty much the primary say in how the
                        money was spent?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, sure we did. But it couldn't be audited by the Controller in
                    Washington or by anyone else. By the way, Sternfeld really ought to be
                    interviewed. I'm going to come to him later. He played a key role in setting up
                    AID. He's a first rate man. He and I happened to disagree on this, but I have
                    the highest regard for Ray. To this day, I'd say right now, that we ought to
                    have servicios in Haiti. That's a perfect candidate for servicios. So is
                    Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, really, it's a situation where there is a very weak
                        government agency or bureaucracy that can't do the job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you see that as a temporary phenomenon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, the thing ought to be temporary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did it then become folded into the government
                        structure?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: They would take it over. I remember that the servicio in Mexico just
                    became a regular part of the Ministry of Health. And it wasn't experimental.
                    They did different things there. But the servicio was finally abolished by the
                    Ambassador because he got into a quid pro quo with the Mexican government. I
                    forget all the things he wanted. And he refused to sign the agreement. Another
                    version of the servicio is a trust fund, which is like a servicio in that the
                    money again became not U.S. funds once it went in there, buy it would go to the
                    Administrator. We set up a joint trust fund to run the Productivity Center,
                    which we had set up in Mexico to help the Mexicans improve their industrial and
                    commercial productivity. We had two men working with him. In this case, the
                    organization was headed by a Mexican from the very beginning. We had a Board of
                    Directors that we worked with, about the equivalent of the Mexican Association
                    of Manufacturers. The American did not run it. He was an advisor. And he had an
                    assistant. They were both advisors. The only control we had was in the general
                    program agreement that we began with, the contract. Contracts are very
                    important, written contracts. And signing of the checks. Either I or the man
                    there would sign the checks. So, that one worked very well. I think the product
                    of these centers is still going on. It had a lot to do with Mexico's growth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there other joint servicios in Mexico?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, just that one at that point. There may have been some before I got
                    there. There were lots of them around Latin America, of course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the program in health? What were they trying to
                        do through the servicio?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: They worked on potable water. They worked on all kinds of things. I
                    can't remember all the details. One of the big programs they had, which was the
                    best, was on vocational rehabilitation, which is a beautiful example of
                    technical assistance. The man that ran it was David Amato, who himself was
                    handicapped. Using the servicio as his base, they first set up within the
                    Mexican Ministry a Bureau or Office of Vocational Rehabilitation. But David did
                    not stop there. He went out and got them to help set up the equivalent of the
                    Goodwill Industries. He went on into the private sector. He got them to help set
                    up courses in vocational rehabilitation in universities and technical schools.
                    He got them to set up a professional association. He was really making technical
                    assistance take when you go through the entire society and all the parts of it
                    that can make some kind of thing like that take. Dave was wonderful.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>The Productivity Center - I want to give you an example of the kind of thing it
                    did. The Mexican government wanted to protect its own commerce and industries.
                    The big department stores in Mexico were apprehensive of things like Sears,
                    which was already there, and having other companies come in that could compete
                    with local stores. They wanted to make it very difficult for more companies to
                    come in to Mexico. Our Productivity Center people said to them, “No, don't do
                    that. Teach your own companies to compete.” So, we brought down people to help
                    them learn how to set up their own modern department stores with credit systems.
                    The Productivity Center made a contract with the American Management
                    Association. They used people who were at the very top of the heap. They got a
                    man down there named Armand Erpf, from a Wall Street banking firm, on the
                    banking side, the whole financial side. They brought down Peter Drucker, the
                    famous management expert. They brought down other people. This was the way, I
                    think, you helped Mexico and you helped American business, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You found the Productivity Center to be very
                        successful?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And does it still exist as far as you know?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: As far as I know, it is still there. We had a couple of other- We had
                    university contracts. These were pretty new in those days. Stassen loved
                    university contracts. He had been President of the University of Pennsylvania
                    before he came to Washington. We were going to do things with university
                    contracts. We had a university contract with the University of Michigan to help
                    set up a training center for the operators of heavy road building equipment. We
                    had sent the man who was going to head the university up to the States for a
                    year or two of training. But the problem we had in those days with the
                    university contracts, Haven, was that we had no say about who was coming down.
                    They'd say, “We'll take care of it in Washington.” And they'd just go to the
                    University of Michigan and say, “Give us a man to go down there and help the
                    center.” What they did at the University was they didn't use one of their own
                    people. They'd go out and hire some guy out of the Detroit school system who was
                    teaching shop. That's exactly whom they sent. A man to help build an institution
                    who knew nothing about institution building! He knew how to train kids to repair
                    an engine or turn a lathe, but not how to train trainers. The first man they
                    sent down was a Mormon and he tried to proselytize everybody. We said, “Look,
                    you're in a Catholic country. Whether there's official religion or not, you
                    don't proselytize.” He tried to do it and we got him out within 48 hours. They
                    sent down another man, who was also a Mormon and didn't try to proselytize.
                    However, he also was not up to the job. We had sent a Mexican to the States - I
                    think he had gone to Yale - to be trained. He came back to Mexico, and he was
                    late to one of the classes our man was conducting. The Mexican was late, 10
                    minutes late. So, our man made him go up to the blackboard and write “I'm sorry
                    I was late” 100 times. We got him out in eight hours, too. We had terrible
                    trouble with our contracts, on the quality of people that they would send down.
                    We had a contract with Columbia Teacher's College. They were sending us all
                    their retirees; none of their young people. This comes up later if we want to
                    discuss it, about what they did in England with the Ministry of Development. Our
                    programs were harassed and fought by Communists, and I say that openly:
                    C-o-m-m-u-n-i-s-t-s. We had a contract between Texas A&amp;M and Saltillo
                    College of Agriculture in Saltillo, Mexico, a beautiful contract worked out by
                    my boss, Dinty Moore. This was to be to build an agricultural school in
                    Saltillo. The usual thing that you know all about: the exchange of professors,
                    the exchange of students. Really build an institution with everything. That
                    means people and so on. Well, there was a student strike. They didn't want this
                    Americanization of their university. The CIA people, whom I was very close to in
                    Mexico, showed us: they had dossiers on some of these so-called students who
                    were in their thirties. Some of them had been trained in Czechoslovakia and
                    other Eastern European countries. We had this Columbia Teacher's College
                    contract with the Instituto Tecnologico, which was a technological institute.
                    And there was another strike and big banners: “Do not Columbiaize the
                    Institute.” And they went on strike for several weeks. Even went into the
                    Rector's office, knocked him down, took down his pants, painted his scrotum
                    blue. Again, we had pictures of these people that were Communist provocateurs.
                    Our people left in the dead of night. They got in their cars and went home. So,
                    they killed the program in Saltillo. They killed the program with the Instituto.
                    When we had programs with strong Mexican leaders, we were OK. We had a training
                    program for the operators and maintainers of heavy road building equipment with
                    one of the biggest men in Mexico. His name was Romulo O'Farrell. Wonderful man.
                    He was the head of the Inter American Highway Commission for many years. Well,
                    he had a lot of clout with the government, so they couldn't touch us. Even when
                    the Ambassador tried to kill that program, he was able to keep it going because
                    of the clout O'Farrell had with the Mexican government. But we finally got rid
                    of the Ambassador - well, not we, but Richard Nixon did. Richard Nixon came down
                    as Vice President to visit Mexico. Conditions were so bad between Mexico and the
                    U.S. that U.S. businessmen got to Nixon and said, “You've got to get him out”
                    and Nixon got him out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the foreign policy interest in having a program
                        in Mexico?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I think the foreign policy interests in having one in Mexico is the
                    interest we have today. It's probably the country most important to us in the
                    world, with a 2,000 mile border. To put it crudely - to “keep them down on the
                    farm.” A developing Mexico is a good neighbor. Even then, we had the problem of
                    “wetback,” immigration, illegal immigration. So, to have a prosperous, growing,
                    developing Mexico was in our interest then in our small way. We should have kept
                    it going. I think we had and have a lot of interest there.</p>
                <p>I want to discuss one other thing about Mexico. We set up there something called
                    a Regional Technical Aid Center, RTAC. What we did was we had a center for
                    preparing technical material in Spanish: textbooks, technical manuals, training
                    films, radio because that's all we had in those days. The reason it was set up
                    in Mexico was they speak the second best Spanish in all of Latin America, in
                    Mexico City. The best is spoken in Bogota, Colombia, according to the people
                    that know. I'm not one of them, but this had been studied by Washington. It was
                    a Washington idea, but it was located in Mexico. It was a wonderful idea. I
                    think it's something where AID has not done enough over the years.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>I was down about eight or nine years ago in a project in Costa Rica, where we
                    were trying to build a Personnel Office in a agricultural research and training
                    center there. Before I went down, I tried to find some books in Spanish -
                    textbooks for human resources management or personnel management. There were
                    two, only two I could find. One was from Madrid, the other was Italian
                    translated into Spanish. There is a great need in Latin America for textbooks
                    that are in Spanish, technical materials in Spanish. We can say today, “Yes,
                    they ought to be learning English,” but they don't. When I was dealing with
                    these people in this training center, very few of them spoke English or read
                    English. RTAC was kept going for many years. I think we had one in Northern
                    Africa somewhere also. Much, much, much later, Haven, when I was-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think it actually ended up in Beirut.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Much later, when I was in Paris doing a consulting job with the Embassy
                    in 1981, I was dealing with USIA then. They had a program, as you must know
                    better than I, of preparing Francophone material to go out to all of the
                    Francophone countries: inserts in weekly magazines, subsidizing American books.
                    The request from all over Africa was “Don't give us translations of Hemingway
                    and Fitzgerald. Give us translations of textbooks.” I would bet it is still
                    needed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm sure. It is.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Another thing about Mexico. We had a cultural anthropologist on our
                    staff. This is a leftover from what I told you about earlier, probably from the
                    days of the Smithsonian. She was a wonderful woman named Isabel Kelly. I believe
                    that, in certain countries at a certain stage of development, every AID Mission
                    should have a cultural anthropologist to deal with the culture, to be sensitive
                    to and deal with the culture. She worked with the health people, especially on
                    such things as training. One of the programs of the servicio was training young
                    Mexican public health officials. Many of these officials we had sent to the
                    States to be trained at Harvard Public Health School. But these were young men
                    and women who'd come from the big cities: from Monterrey or from Guadalajara or
                    from Mexico City and they were going to go out to the villages. Well, they
                    didn't know any more how to deal with those villagers, how to get them to accept
                    new technical terms or new ideas than the man on the moon. But Isabel would
                    train them on how to use- For instance, they would try to bring in potable
                    water. So they would put in a spigot that was an ordinary spigot like you have
                    on the side of a house. Well, that little spigot has no way to hand a bucket.
                    And Isabel had to say, “Look, these people have been getting their water out of
                    wells with a big spigot where they could hang their bucket. Learn what they do.
                    Put in a spigot on which they can hang their bucket. Then they can use potable
                    water.” I was very impressed with Isabel. I was also very lucky when I was
                    there.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>I told you, when I was in Paris I tried to begin some psychotherapy. I also
                    continued in Washington taking courses at the Washington School of Psychiatry in
                    both psychiatry and in cultural anthropology. But when I got to Mexico I
                    understood that Erich Fromm was there, the very famous psychoanalyst writer. I
                    said, “This is great. Here I'm in Mexico.” Through a friend of mine who knew
                    Eric, I approached him and he said, no, he didn't take lay people. He was only
                    training doctors from the University of Mexico Medical School. Fromm himself was
                    not a physician. But he gave me a reading program and for many years I read
                    under Eric. He gave me Freud, his own books, books by Karen Horney. About once
                    every six months, I'd go down to Cuernavaca, which was about 45 miles from
                    Mexico City and as close to Heaven on earth as you can get. I don't know if
                    you've ever been there, but it's just-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I've been there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Eternal spring. And he had this gorgeous house that overlooked the
                    valley and the two volcanoes. I read under Eric and it was very, very good- At
                    least, I learned an awful lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do with that learning? Were you trying to use
                        it in your-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, it was a side interest. It was helping me be more at peace with
                    myself, feeling that I had some insight into how you deal with other people.
                    Also, it was good for me personally. I tried to use it, I guess, intuitively. I
                    always backed sensitivity training because I felt that that was an offshoot of
                    that. I learned in Mexico that- this was '54 to '59, Haven, that the most
                    important thing was the creation of human resources. That was before Ted Schultz
                    had gotten his Nobel or whatever at the University of Chicago. Building
                    institutions, strengthening institutions, and building human resources. And
                    Mexico had a lot of that. Mexico had been sending their young men and women up
                    here and to London for years to be trained. There was a man in the Bureau of the
                    Budget named Mickey Rosen. That's all he did was take care of young people that
                    came in and spent a year at the Bureau. This was, I think, a Donald Stone idea.
                    I'm pretty sure it was Don's idea. These were the people who would then come
                    back to Mexico and fan out into the government. They'd become Sub Ministers and
                    Ministers around town.</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>I should mention that we had a program with the Bank of Mexico. The Bank of
                    Mexico is an extremely important institution. Every country should have
                    something like it. It not only was the equivalent of the Federal Reserve Bank,
                    but it was a training institution. Also, it was a research institution and we
                    had a joint program with them. And we had a research establishment. We had a
                    contract with the Armor Institute out of Chicago and the Stanford Research
                    Institute to give them help. They were developing, as an example, chick peas,
                    garbanzos. They were used as a good crop for Mexico to export because the
                    Spanish love garbanzos - in Spain and other parts of Latin America. And what
                    could you do with garbanzos? They were making pancakes out of garbanzo flour and
                    they even found that the basic molecule of the garbanzo was one of the best
                    molecules to be used in plastics.</p>
                <p>In addition to this research program with the Bank of Mexico, we had a monetary
                    studies program set up by Peter Cody. The Bank of Mexico set up the Center for
                    Latin American Monetary Studies. We brought down people like Triffin from Yale
                    and other people who worked with him and gave them a certain amount of money,
                    but not an awful lot. We helped bring people there from all over Latin America
                    to be trained in central banking, like the Federal Reserve. Our own central
                    Federal Reserve never participated for some reason or other. But the Federal
                    Reserve Bank of New York always sent someone down once a year for a whole year
                    to work with them.</p>
                <p>Another program that I can't take all the credit for - my training officer
                    should, but I certainly backed him - was to use Mexico for third country
                    training. You could use Mexican institutions and save money because in the
                    United States it cost a lot more for a participant than to send him to Mexico.
                    We would not only use things like the Center at the Bank, but we would use the
                    Monterrey Institute of Technology in Monterrey and so on. There I had a
                    wonderful relationship because I got to know the Rector who later became the
                    Federal Minister of Education. We'd have lunch every week.</p>
                <p>What I learned in Mexico I've never lost: you've got to have a great respect for
                    the people that you work with, their country, their mores and so on. To quote
                    Hippocrates, “Try to help and, in all events, do no harm.” After five years-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Mexico for five years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Five years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How big a staff was there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: I think, by the time I left, we had about no more than 15 or 16
                    Americans and maybe twice that in locals. I became a Deputy Director down there
                    after about a year. My good relations with Mrs. Shipley helped me: I got my
                    diplomatic passport in a week. You were entitled to a diplomatic passport if you
                    were Deputy Director. After Dinty Moore left, they sent in another excellent
                    ex-institute man named Vance Rodgers, a wonderful man. One of the best I've ever
                    know. Then he left. I then became Acting Director for about a year. The idea was
                    to phase Mexico out. You know, this country was already developed. What did you
                    need foreign assistance for?</p>
                <p>I feel that we've made a big mistake in that, when we cut off programs with a
                    country, we cut off everything. AID builds up wonderful relations with a country
                    on the technical level, on the technological level, on the institutional level,
                    with government, private, and academic. And then you cut them off. And you've
                    lost a wonderful resource of relationships. I think we should never cut them off
                    completely. In fact, at one time, Haven, back about 1975 or '76, a friend of
                    mine was Assistant Secretary of State for Scientific Affairs. I recommended to
                    him that what we should have abroad are science and technology attach�s instead
                    of just science attach�s. The technology attach� would pick up from AID those
                    technological relationships. At the very end, I guess you want to ask me about
                    my feelings about development. I think development's a two way street.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they terminate here, when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, they were going to. They kept saying that's why- Dennis FitzGerald
                    told me that he could make me the Director. But later, when the Alliance for
                    Progress came in, we expanded the program. We were trying to taper it off. The
                    word from Washington was “Cut it down, cut it out.” Mike Mansfield, whom I got
                    to know in Mexico, kept pushing for cutting out Missions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why was he of that view?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I don't know. Mansfield just always had the idea that aid should be
                    temporary. Although he and I became pretty good friends- I should say that I
                    finally got to get into the Ambassador's house because Mansfield used to come to
                    Mexico for visits. He just loved Mexico. And he spoke Spanish. They assigned me
                    to him because they thought I was the only Democrat on the staff. I never said I
                    was a Democrat, but they always thought I was. So they assigned me to him and I
                    got to know him. Later, this helped us get AID and the Foreign Service some very
                    good legislation just because I knew him. Like anyone would. I'm not saying Mel
                    Spector - anyone that knows a man like that could have done what I did. After
                    five years, I was offered the job-</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before we go on, was there anything more that you thought
                        about the impact of our assistance at that time? What kind of changes you
                        think have been sustained? You talked about the Productivity Center.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I think that must have been, of the program we had, Haven, probably the
                    most important contribution we made. You're dealing with a very large country.
                    It was then 37, 38 million people. Now it's almost three times that or more, 92
                    million. I think one of the good things we did, just generally, was our third
                    country training program. I think the Vocational Rehabilitation Program was an
                    excellent one and could have been a model for many other things that they could
                    do in Mexico. This man I mentioned, Romulo O'Farrell, had been in a terrible
                    automobile accident and they had to amputate his leg. He was so important to the
                    U.S. that the Navy sent down a plane to pick him up, took him to San Diego,
                    amputated his leg, then took him to Oakland, where they fitted him with an
                    artificial limb. He came in to see me and he said, “You know, Mr. Spector, I
                    never realized the problem of the disabled, but now I do. I want to do
                    something.” Well, David Amato, this wonderful man I told you about, who was our
                    Vocational Rehabilitation advisor. Finally, he'd done everything you could do to
                    get vocational rehabilitation going in Mexico, so we were terminating it. He was
                    about to leave and I introduced him to Don Romulo, and it was like putting the
                    two parts of the atomic bomb together. It was a magnificent explosion. They went
                    off and they really did a marvelous job in the private sector of helping the
                    disabled. They got an old monastery and equipped it. This was everything: people
                    that were blind, people that were deaf, people that needed new limbs. They
                    taught them skills. They set up making car radios - because Romulo assembled
                    Volkswagens and later he assembled Jeeps. So the radios for all those cars were
                    made by the disabled people that helped support this venture. So you didn't need
                    any government funds, except the payment of Dave Amato. So, we made some
                    impact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any in agriculture?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything in rural areas at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: No. The only thing we did for rural areas was our helping on the road
                    building equipment. Of course, Mexico has marvelous roads. As you know better
                    than I, roads are so important to the development-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were providing technical assistance in road
                        construction, too?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just equipment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Just the training of operators and mechanics. Not the equipment. The
                    USGS program would have been of marvelous assistance to Mexico, as eliminating
                    malaria would have been- Well, we did help in malaria later. We obtained a
                    specialist for the health servicio who was one of the best men in the world on
                    mosquitoes and we lent him to the malaria elimination project.</p>
                <p>We had one PL 480 program that was interesting. An American railroad had been
                    planned many years before in the early 1900s to go from Kansas City down through
                    Texas and across the Northwestern part of Mexico to the Pacific. It was called
                    the Kansas City-Pacific Railroad. During the 1917 revolution the Mexican
                    government expropriated it. It had only been surveyed before and since 1917
                    nothing had been done to complete it. So, about my last year in Mexico, the
                    Mexicans wanted to finish that railroad (which is now finished; they say it's
                    one of the great sights of the world, the wonderful canyons and so on), and
                    they'd gotten a loan from the World Bank to help do it. They also wanted to use
                    the local currency from a PL 480 loan to complement the World Bank loan. It was
                    a fairly good-sized loan. It was up there - 15 or 16 million dollars. But, as
                    you know, I had to get the concurrence of the Agricultural Attach�. He was a
                    staunch Republican who believed that, “God dammit, these Mexicans took our
                    railroad away from us and we're not going to help them build it.” He was a good
                    friend of mine, and I liked him very much, but I couldn't change his mind. So,
                    finally, I sat down with some people out of the Mexican Office of the Presidency
                    and they said, “Well, it's no problem. What would you like to use your PL 480
                    money for?” So, I went to my friend and I said, “What would you like to use it
                    for?” He said, “Well, grain storage.” So we used the money for grain storage and
                    they used the money they were going to use for grain storage to help build their
                    railroad. So, the whole thing worked out.</p>
                <p>In 1959 we'd just about exhausted Mexico. I mean, exhausted our own stay there. I
                    was at the point either I was going to spend the rest of my life in Mexico or
                    get out because I really loved the country, loved the people and still do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You spoke Spanish as well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Assignment to ICA's Office of Mexico, Central America and Caribbean Affairs and
                    the ICA organization - 1959-61</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: I spoke Spanish but not as well as I should have. I've never been good
                    with languages. But I was offered a wonderful job - to be the Office Director
                    for Mexico, Central America and Caribbean Affairs in ICA. We came back by boat.
                    We went down to Veracruz and took a boat, a Spanish boat, which was half cattle
                    and stuff and half people. On the way, we stopped in Cuba. We spent a day in
                    Cuba. The U.S. still had diplomatic relations with Castro. See, this is early
                    '59. My wife's cousin had been the head of the FBI there, but he had left. We
                    still had an Embassy there. The Acting Head of the FBI took us around for one
                    day and we saw the first vestiges of Castro's taking over of Cuba. We came back
                    to the States-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were some of those?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: You saw the big casinos close down and a big tractor on the lawn or a
                    washing machine or something like that. That's about all you saw in the
                    beginning, all we could see in a short day. But it was interesting because Cuba
                    was a part of my problem when I got back to Washington. As I say, my area was
                    Central America, Mexico and the Caribbean and we still had a program in Cuba.
                    Our Mission Director had left. He was closely identified with the Batista
                    government. His name was Johnny Johnston, who later became my nemesis. We had a
                    couple of programs with Cuba. Again - fisheries - the way it had been in Mexico.
                    Amazingly enough, Batista never built up any kind of a fishery organization
                    within the government. The Cuban Government sent us a woman who was to be in
                    charge of fisheries. We got her with the Bureau of Fisheries. We were going to
                    try to work out a program with the Bureau of Fish and Wildlife and the Cuban
                    government to help the Cubans form their own bureau. We helped them with
                    agricultural reform. We got them some people from the University of California
                    at Davis to go there. But in about six months, the program was killed and we cut
                    off relations with Cuba. We had information given to us by the CIA that Castro
                    was a Marxist, a full blown Stalin Communist. See, in those early days, we
                    weren't sure, but we had information from them that they were and that certainly
                    turned out to be true. I had nothing to say on that because I wasn't directly
                    involved.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>This job- As you know, Haven, in those days, you had the Development Loan Fund as
                    a separate agency. So most of what we did was technical assistance. I enjoyed
                    the job very, very much. I now look back at it as one of the high points in my
                    career - something that I really enjoyed. For one thing, ICA was settling down
                    to really understand what development was all about and had some very good top
                    people. You had it run ostensibly by a Foreign Service Officer named James
                    Riddleberger. He had a Deputy named Leonard Saccio, who, amazingly enough, had
                    been a corporation lawyer, but really learned development. He was first-rate.
                    You had Jim Grant as the head of Program Planning. He had a marvelous staff -
                    Warren Wiggins, Jack Vaughn and Bill Ellis. You had really the pivotal guy
                    running the Agency underneath all that: Dennis FitzGerald, Mr. ICA. He had two
                    Deputies. One was Herman Kleine, first-rate. Another guy named Don McPhail,
                    first-rate. I don't know about all the other Bureaus, but in our own Bureau we
                    had a Foreign Service Officer heading it up: Rollin Atwood, who understood Latin
                    America, spoke Spanish, liked Latin America. He had a Deputy, who had come from
                    private industry, from the Rockefeller people in Latin America, named John
                    Heilman. He was a driver, a go-getter, a great guy, I thought. And also, by that
                    time, there was a whole turnaround of feeling in the Eisenhower Administration
                    about Latin America. Milton Eisenhower had been down to Latin America, Nixon
                    who, you remember, had been spit on in Venezuela. Nixon was a very good force in
                    turning us around; as was Milton Eisenhower. ICA also had a very good
                    relationship with the State Department. An excellent person supervising all of
                    this, ICA, DLF, TCA and military assistance - was Douglas Dillon. His deputy was
                    a first-rate Foreign Service Officer, John Bell. And also on the staff were
                    Graham Martin, Edwin M. Martin, Ray Sternfeld, Jim Fowler and others. I felt
                    that last year of ICA was one of the best periods that I've ever known, where we
                    seemed to know what we were doing and getting full backing from the top.</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>One of the two main things I had going in Central America was Central American
                    Regional Integration. Our idea was, of course, to integrate Guatemala,
                    Nicaragua, El Salvador, Costa Rica, Honduras, and Panama (Panama was sometimes
                    in and sometimes out on that; they don't consider themselves Central American.)
                    You had economic integration happening in Europe. We were going to do the same
                    thing in Central America. The biggest role I played was in helping set up the
                    Central American Bank for Economic Integration. I remember going down to see
                    Fitz (Dr. Dennis FitzGerald). We only asked for several million dollars. The
                    Inter-American Development Bank was already set up, so they did not want this
                    Central American Bank. Development Loan Fund did not want it either. They were
                    going to make loans directly. So, I went to see Fitz. I was going to ask for $3
                    million, but I said, “Why not five?” I could have asked for ten. I got five. So,
                    I went to this meeting, chaired by Thomas Mann, who was then Assistant Secretary
                    for Economic Affairs. You had the Executive Director of Inter American
                    Development Bank. You had George Springsteen representing the Development Loan
                    Fund. And myself representing ICA, with the full backing of Len Saccio, who was
                    then the Acting Director of the Agency. They were all against it, except Tom
                    Mann and myself. So, Tom Mann said, “Okay. You're against it from DLF? You're
                    against it from Inter American Development Bank? Now I'll go back and I'll tell
                    Douglas Dillon-” And they said, “No, no, no. Just a minute.” So, we got this
                    Central American Bank for Economic Integration. It's still there. I don't know
                    how much it's doing. It's still there, thank God.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's the CABEI?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes. The other thing we worked on-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was it supposed to do mainly?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: To finance various kinds of projects that could be used throughout the
                    whole region that you didn't want to duplicate in every little country, the same
                    kind of thing. Hopefully, this bank would have things going that would finance
                    things that would be good for the whole region.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you provided five million dollars?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Five million dollars. I don't remember what the other part was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are there any other projects that you remember anything
                        about?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, I don't, because this was done pretty much towards the end. The
                    other thing that was a big deal with us was West Indies Federation. This I still
                    think is needed. This was a big idea of State, ICA, and the British government.
                    The idea would be that you'd have Jamaica at one end and Trinidad and Tobago on
                    the other. You'd have a federation of all these countries. You know, the
                    individual economies in Grenada and so on - none of them are really sustainable.
                    To this day, I don't know how they really exist. You had some great educational
                    institutions. You had the University of the West Indies in Jamaica. You had more
                    of a technological school down in Trinidad. We worked very hard. This was really
                    Roland Atwood's main baby. He was traveling back and forth, up and down. We were
                    waiting for independence from all those countries to put together this great
                    deal. The Prime Minister in Trinidad was a man named Eric Williams. He said that
                    he would go along. See, we still had a naval base there that we'd gotten from
                    the British - what did we call that when, during the War, we got bases for
                    battleships, for destroyers - the Chaquaramas base. He said that for $50 million
                    - a direct loan or grant, I forget what it was - he would go along with
                    federation. Well, you know, we didn't have $50 million in ICA, but we got it
                    from somewhere. It was very important to get that federation going. And the Navy
                    said that we needed the base. A year or two later, the Navy gave it up. So, they
                    didn't need it anymore after we'd given $50 million. Eric Williams was the Prime
                    Minister's name. This was such a good idea that, even after Kennedy came in, he
                    kept Jock Whitney on, who was the Eisenhower Ambassador to the Court of Saint
                    James, on for another six months to do nothing but work on this creation of the
                    West Indies Federation. But, the minute they got their independence, they said,
                    “The Hell with it.” Trinidad and Jamaica both pulled out. Those other countries
                    would have stayed in, but without Trinidad and Jamaica - it was no go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And your primary motivation for trying to bring this about
                        was what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I think prosperity of another people close to us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you worried about the Communists there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I guess we were. You had Cuba, you had Castro right in the middle of it
                    all. In the Dominican Republic later, the problem-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And in Central America there was the same concern?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, you didn't base it mostly on anti-Communism. Of course, in 1954, you
                    had the CIA, as is generally known now, help overthrow a constitutionally
                    elected man, Arbanz. And you haven't had real peace in Guatemala since. Arbanz
                    was a Leftist, whatever that meant. We didn't put it that much in terms of
                    anti-Communism. I think later - I was just reading in Fulbright's book - when
                    everything got in under the rubric of mutual security, you had that idea of
                    security in a general sense. I think Douglas Dillon was probably called
                    “Coordinator for Mutual Security.” So, you had this tinge again of security when
                    we were really talking more about human concerns, of mutual human concerns. So,
                    I really enjoyed that part of my job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What other countries did you cover? Or those were the
                        primary ones during this assignment in Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: There was Mexico, of course. We built it up into more of a third country
                    training center. There was a big housing program that they needed help with. I
                    forget where that money came from - probably PL 480 money - I'm not sure which.
                    And then Haiti was always a problem. I could go to my desk and know that there
                    would be something on Haiti that day; that hasn't ceased. We never had an
                    answer. We'd throw money in there. We had project after project. We had very
                    good people there and we just never could seem to make any progress. Papa Doc
                    was in charge the whole time I was there. Duvalier. We're now getting towards
                    the time of the Kennedy-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a very functional organization, wasn't it? Were the
                        technical people very dominant compared to the geographic people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes. Well, I wouldn't say “dominant,” but they were certainly equal. You
                    had Fitz running things - the operations day to day. Fitz had come up the
                    technical side and so he tried to balance it with these two men. I forget which
                    was which. Herman Kleine or Don McPhail. One was over the geographic area and
                    one was over the functional area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: McPhail was over the geographic. Herman was over the
                        technical.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: That's true. But I never found it a problem, being on a Desk, on a
                    Geographic Desk. I always found them very, very helpful. You could just work
                    with them and you'd find common ground. I always thought it was great. I think
                    it was a very good organization, Haven. Maybe with DLF it would have been
                    better, I don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ICA was in business all along?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: I don't know how many years. It depends-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, FOA came to an end?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: FOA, of course, came in '53. I forget when ICA came in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think '55. There must have been some sort of milieu or
                        atmosphere of very positive interest in development. Talking about
                        pre-Kennedy now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, it had gotten very much that way. I think having Dillon over at
                    State, who was reflecting this- And you no longer had John Foster Dulles - I
                    think he died. Christian Herter, I think, was then the Secretary of State. They
                    were for development. It was just a very, very, very good atmosphere. During the
                    election, our people were foreseeing a change in administration. Whether it was
                    to Nixon or Kennedy, whenever there's a change in administration, it's the time
                    to move, whether it's the same political party or not. So, Saccio left and went
                    to Brazil as Mission Director. He was very key. In my own area, both Atwood went
                    back to State and John Howman went to Korea, I believe. He offered me the job to
                    go with him as his Deputy. I was about the most senior man in the Latin America
                    area. But I knew Central America and the Caribbean. I didn't know West
                    Coast-East Coast in Latin America. We were waiting for new people to come in.
                    They were bringing Johnny Johnson in to be the Deputy Regional Director, and a
                    man named Ray Hill as the Director. But Ray was coming in from Bolivia. I don't
                    know where Johnny was at that point, but Johnny had not come in yet. I think
                    there was even a short period when I was the Acting Regional Director, for a
                    couple or three weeks.</p>
                <p>Early in 1953, I was sitting home one Saturday morning and I got a call from
                    Senator Mansfield. He said, “How would you like to go to Mexico?” I didn't know
                    what he was talking about. He was then the majority leader of the Senate.
                    Johnson, of course, had become Vice President. What he meant was that he wanted
                    me to go with him on a trip. This was the first Inter-Parliamentary meeting
                    between the two Parliaments - us and Mexico. He was heading a group of twelve
                    Senators and twelve Congressmen. He wanted me as his aide and he said, “You're
                    representing me, not State, not ICA. Me. I don't want you to have anything to do
                    with the Embassy, anything to do with the Department.” Well, you know, he got
                    me. He made a call and boom. That afternoon, I was on my way to Mexico for two
                    weeks as his aide, to help him in any way I could. We spent a week in
                    Guadalajara and a week in Mexico City. I sat in on some meetings. I helped him
                    with some translation. I got to know him pretty well - liked him very much.
                    Still like him very much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of person was he?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: He was very dour, but believed very strongly in a strong foreign policy.
                    In those days, he was more an isolationist than he is now - I mean, than he
                    became when he was in Japan as Ambassador. I have to tell you a story. When he
                    first came to Mexico and I was assigned to be his assistant or bag carrier, we
                    didn't know what he looked like. He wasn't that famous. He was the Senate
                    majority Whip. We didn't have the little Congressional books, where you have
                    pictures. So, the Ambassador, whom I'd never really met before, and the DCM and
                    I all went out to the airport to meet him. We were standing at the bottom of the
                    plane. And everyone came off the plane and no one identified himself to the
                    Ambassador, which really ticked the Ambassador off. You know, here he was, the
                    Ambassador. This was Francis White. We all went into the VIP lounge and the
                    Ambassador sent me into the main lounge and we said over the microphone, “Would
                    Senator Mansfield identify himself?” Nobody identified himself. Finally, I went
                    up to the pilot and I said, “Wasn't Senator Mansfield on the plane?” He said,
                    “Yes.” And I said, “Can you point him out to me?” And he said, “Yes” and there
                    he was standing over there. I walked up to him and I said, “Are you Senator
                    Mansfield?” He pulled his pipe out and he said, “Yes...” I said, “Well, Senator,
                    the Ambassador is waiting for you in the VIP room.” So, I escorted him to the
                    VIP room. This was typical of Mansfield. The first thing he asked the
                    Ambassador, who was more Republican than the Republican Party, was “How's my old
                    friend Bill O'Dwyer?” Well, Bill O'Dwyer was a rambunctious Democrat, a former
                    Mayor of New York, who had been the Ambassador to Mexico. The Ambassador just
                    couldn't stand him! Of course, Mansfield knew that. To set the picture: the
                    tradition in the Ambassador's office was to have pictures of all the previous
                    U.S. ministers and ambassadors hung around the office. In fact, there was a
                    tradition in Mexico that all of the former Ministers, because that's what they
                    were before, pictures were in the office of the Ambassadors. They were all on
                    the wall from the very first one. When White took over the job, his secretary
                    started to put up O'Dwyer's picture, but White said, “I don't want it. I can't
                    stand the man.” And he would not let him in the Embassy. Mansfield knew that.
                    Later, when I got to know Mansfield better, I said, “Senator, when you came to
                    Mexico, didn't you know that White couldn't stand O'Dwyer?” And he smiled. But
                    it was helpful to me later, knowing Mansfield, when we were passing the Foreign
                    Assistance Act. So I went with him to Mexico and came back.</p>
                <p>The beginning of AID - 1961</p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>I wasn't involved in the first work on creating the Agency for international
                    Development (AID). As you know, Kennedy appointed Henry Labouisse as the
                    Director of ICA, a wonderful man. Sweet, calm, a gentleman in every sense of the
                    word. He'd been the former head of UNRRA, the refugee program. Under him, what
                    he did was delegate most of the running of ICA to Fitz, to Dr. FitzGerald. So,
                    you had a group of Labouisse- Douglas Dillon had left State, so Jack Bell was
                    the head of that coordinating mechanism over at State. You had Frank Coffin, who
                    was the head of the Development Loan Fund. And a couple of people from the White
                    House like Bill Dentzer, sitting in deciding what to do about the foreign aid
                    program. On March 22, 1963, President Kennedy had laid out the policies and
                    general organization ideas of a new agency for foreign assistance. Generally,
                    there was to be unified administration and operation, there would be country
                    plans carefully thought through, programs tailored to meet the needs and
                    resources of each individual country; there would be long term planning and
                    financing, special emphasis on development loans that were repayable in dollars,
                    there would be a multilateral approach, there would be a new agency with new
                    personnel, and there would be separation from military assistance - that would
                    no longer be under the coordination of State Department, but it would go back to
                    the Defense Department, which was a very bad thing as far as Latin America was
                    concerned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Economic assistance? Economic supporting assistance?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I think Supporting Assistance was still in ICA, but the Development Loan
                    Fund, of course, had the lending function. But there wasn't much Supporting
                    Assistance where I was, in Latin America, except maybe that $50 million for
                    Trinidad and Tobago was Supporting Assistance. So, then we had President
                    Kennedy's message of March 22, but now you had to implement it. The President
                    appointed Labouisse as the head of a special task force on foreign assistance.
                    On the task force, he had John Bell again, as his Deputy. Under John Bell, there
                    were three working groups. One working group was on Legislation and
                    Congressional Presentation. They brought back on that one a man named Theodore
                    Tannenwald, who I think we're going to interview later, who was a New York
                    lawyer. He had previously worked in the State Department. He chose a young, very
                    bright lawyer to be his number one assistant named John Rehm, whom, speaking
                    today in 1996, is the husband of Diana Rehm of our WAMU. He met Diana there. I
                    never knew her, but she was a secretary in the State Department and John met
                    Diana there. There was a Program Development group. That was under Frank Coffin,
                    who was then the head of Development Loan Fund. He brought around Jim Grant to
                    help him; a man named Jake Kaplan; Lester Gordon from Harvard; Max Milliken from
                    MIT. Milliken and Rostow had done studies on technical assistance for Mike
                    Mansfield when he was on the Senate Foreign Relations Committee. That was a very
                    bright group.</p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>Then, for organization and administration, they brought in a man named George
                    Gant. George had most recently, I think, been with the Harvard program, or the
                    Ford Foundation. And he'd done some work in Pakistan, where he had gotten to
                    know Dave Bell. John Bell had been there at one time, too, so he knew John. Dave
                    Bell at this point was head of the Bureau of the Budget. George had been the
                    Director of Personnel for the Tennessee Valley Authority and thought everything
                    should emanate out of Personnel. Later, he had become the Director of the
                    Tennessee Valley Authority before he went to work for the Ford Foundation and
                    for Harvard. George, as I got to know him, brought in as his Chief of Staff, a
                    man from the Bureau of the Budget named Richard Barrett. I think I told you that
                    I met Dick way back in 1945 when Dick and I were both in UNRRA. We'd kept our
                    friendship all these years. So, I was kind of an unofficial advisor to Dick on
                    organization and administration. Dick had never served overseas. He knew nothing
                    about aid. He got a lot of his ideas from me. One of them, of course was, I felt
                    your emphasis should be, because I'd come from the geographic areas, that it
                    should be on the geographic bureaus and everything else should be staff to that.
                    What the Program Committee under Coffin did was they would ask for testimony
                    from each of the Regions and from other people. I'm sure Herman testified and
                    all the others. In the other Regions, the new Regional Directors had not been
                    appointed yet, so these were career people. You had people like Carter Ide
                    testify. Jim Fowler testified for the Far East. Maury Williams testified as
                    well. But in my case, there was neither a Director nor a long-time Deputy.
                    Johnny Johnson had just come in and they were suspicious of Johnny. He was
                    pretty well identified with the Republicans. He was close to Nelson Rockefeller.
                    So, they asked me to represent Latin America, which put me in a very bad
                    position. Here my boss, Johnny, wasn't being asked to testify like all the other
                    Deputies were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Testifying to-?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: To the Program group. Coffin, Jim Grant, Jake Cantor, Max Milliken,
                    Lester Gordon. When I was testifying on my area, I knew what I was talking
                    about. This was Mexico, Central America, the Caribbean. They loved the idea of
                    Central American integration. They loved the idea of the West Indies
                    Federation.</p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>I was at a loss when it came to East Coast-West Coast of Latin America. I came
                    back to my office about the third day. I came in on a Monday and I didn't have
                    an office. Johnny had taken it away from me. I didn't have a secretary. I didn't
                    have a desk. I had nothing. And here I was supposed to give my view to this new
                    team about what we should be doing in Latin America. So, I went to see Fitz and
                    Fitz fizzled out. He didn't do a God damned thing. He said, “Well, there's
                    nothing I can do.” So I didn't have an office. Well, finally, I went to - I
                    forget who. I got an office. I don't know if I ever got a secretary. My old
                    friend Mat Torre was in town. He said, “Why don't you rent an office and hire a
                    secretary. You know, go into an office building?” I put up with this for about a
                    week. People like Jim Fowler had been the Deputy. He had his whole staff behind
                    him - Program Office and all the Office Directors. I had nothing. So, I just
                    finally gave up. I just said, “Look, I can't do a decent job” and so I left.</p>
                <p>George Gant took me on to do the personnel side of the reorganization. On the
                    personnel side, he had brought in two people to decide what should be done about
                    the personnel of the AID organization. He brought in Jim Mitchell. I think Jim
                    then was with the Brookings Institution. And Don Fowler, who was Director of
                    Personnel at The World Bank. Two excellent people - happened to be two old
                    friends of mine. They had spent about three or three weeks on it and they were
                    ready to go back to their jobs, back to Brookings and back to IBRD, so I took
                    over from them. Their proposal was that we should move very quickly to integrate
                    the personnel systems of this new foreign aid agency with State and USIA and
                    really to have a personnel office that would be part of the State Personnel
                    Office. This is what I inherited.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean, to have a unified Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes. I'd been for that and I am for it and I helped bring it about many
                    years later, but I wasn't for it at that time. I've always felt that you should
                    have a separate development agency, that it should not be a part of State. Maybe
                    it should be under some kind of policy direction, but not a part of State. If
                    you immediately set up right then the system, you would almost put the whole
                    damn thing under the State Department. I was for integration. I told you
                    earlier: I helped Hank DuFlon back under Eisenhower. We were looking for an
                    overall personnel system. But not right then. I felt we should have our own
                    personnel office, that we shouldn't be an adjunct to the State Department. So, I
                    wrote some language. I don't want to bother reading it to you. Well, maybe I
                    will read it.</p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>What I wrote was, “After a careful review of features of the current personnel
                    system, it has been decided that the development of a separate career system for
                    AID personnel is unnecessary and undesirable. Instead, it's proposed that the
                    authorities in the Mutual Security Act be retained as an interim step in the
                    development of an integrated foreign affairs system and basing both the
                    assistance and non-assistance parts of the State Department. In the meantime,
                    the personnel systems of the State Department and AID will be administratively
                    integrated in such a way as to secure consistency of policies and standards to
                    facilitate interchange of personnel (I felt strongly about interchange of
                    personnel and I still do). To provide the decentralized operations necessary to
                    accommodate the requirements of each interchange of assignments among State and
                    AID personnel will be increased.” We took out the phrase “administratively
                    integrated,” and we changed it to “integrated.” The legislation went to the Hill
                    and the one thing that I kept insisting on is that there not be another
                    Stassenization. That had been a very traumatic thing for the Agency. It was
                    remembered on and on in ICA and DLF and it's still going on. But the Kennedy
                    Administration was very much for a brand new organization. But Jack Bell, God
                    bless him - he was the key man on this - was really the chief person against
                    “disintegration.” It was Jack that was the mover and shaker. He knew so much and
                    he was so dynamic. I remember him at a big meeting we had with everybody there -
                    White House people and everyone else - saying, “We're going to have a lot of bad
                    people from the old outfit and, God, we need new, vigorous people.” And he'd
                    say, “I don't care if you get 100 bad people if one good person is axed.” The
                    idea was you'd set up a new agency, and under existing laws, there was a law
                    that said that when there was a new agency set up, if it is using any of the old
                    agencies, even though it's been abolished, those people have a right to jobs in
                    the new agency. Edna Boorady had researched the laws thoroughly. She was, as you
                    know, a first rate lawyer, and she said it could be done. So, the idea was that
                    we would do what we had done under the Ribicoff Amendment: that you would apply
                    the standard reductions in force. With that in mind, I felt happy.</p>
                <p>Appointment as Director of Personnel of the new agency, AID - 1961</p>
                <p>About that point- During this period, I'd been assigned to the National War
                    College and I wanted to go very badly. But Labouisse called me in and he said,
                    “I want you to become the Director of Personnel of the new AID agency. I'll
                    promise you that a year from now, you and Bill Parks-” Bill was scheduled to go
                    to the Industrial War College. He said, “I'll promise you you'll go” and he gave
                    us letters to that effect. So, I agreed to take the job. The Personnel Office
                    was much too big, more than I wanted, but we'll go into that in a minute. As a
                    matter of fact, I think Bill Sheppard and I took the first day off that we'd had
                    in several weeks and we went to play golf over at Kenwood. We were about at the
                    fourth hole when somebody came out from the clubhouse and said, “You're wanted
                    back at the State Department.”</p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>What had happened- This - “the Ripper,” as we call it - was not in either bill of
                    either the Senate or the House. When it went into conference, somehow they put
                    the same language in there that was there under Stassen, that we could get rid
                    of people without regard to any other law. And it had passed. I still think it
                    was Ralph Dungan that put it in there, the White House Boston Mafia guy. I had
                    promised Labouisse I would do personnel and here I was stuck with the same God
                    damned thing! In the report that was written, the study about the whole thing,
                    they said people were afraid of the “Spector” of Stassenization - he spelled it
                    S-P-E-C-T-O-R. Here I had to run this awful thing. Later, I was called up on the
                    Hill with Dave Bell and had to testify and had 150 wives, children of these
                    fired people sitting behind me. I couldn't stand it. That's why I transferred to
                    the State Department later.</p>
                <p>So, I Director of the Office of Personnel Management. The Office of Personnel
                    Management was just not personnel. It had organization and management in it. It
                    had security, both physical and personnel security. It had evaluation, whatever
                    that meant, which kind of impinged on the type of work you once were in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was personal evaluation though.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, well, personal evaluation. But the way George Gant looked at it-
                    See, he'd come from Personnel in TVA. You could run the Agency with the
                    Personnel Office, which is kind of ridiculous. Personnel are very important. I
                    wouldn't concede that to any man, but still- So, it was a rough job and we did-
                    The first person to be appointed to the new organization of AID was Jack Bell.
                    The lawyers had figured out somehow how to do that. Then he appointed me. I was
                    the second person appointed to AID as Director of Personnel. Then I signed all
                    the other actions for everyone else that was brought into AID. My name appeared
                    at the bottom of the journal.</p>
                <p>I tried to do some things that first year. One thing we did was, I felt so
                    strongly on training that I appointed a committee, with Jim Mitchell as the
                    Chairman, Donald Fowler on it, Sam Hayes from the University of Michigan, Ford
                    Lukhart, Clarence Thurber from the Ford Foundation, Mark Torre, who was my old
                    psychiatrist friend, and a wonderful man named Karl Mathiasen as the Executive
                    Director and we got this out. To really train the people in AID- In my early
                    incarnation in AID, I felt that development was a very special thing. It took
                    special consideration of cultures and so on and that there would be research for
                    the improvement of training. I felt training was a very important thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Particularly when you're setting up a new agency. Were you
                        faced with having to fire a lot of people?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, we fired about 200 people, which later, one way or the other I
                    understand Dave Bell allowed back in. They all appealed one way or the other and
                    a lot of them came back in. That isn't the way to run- You do it by attrition.
                    There ought to be better ways to do it, but this mass bloodletting is not the
                    way to do it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were they selected?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: We did it based on their efficiency rating. We had committees set up and
                    it went up again to a Board that finally made the decisions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Foreign Service and Civil Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yeah. For the very top people, the people that are the excepted
                    appointments. There were over 100 of those. These were the people that were
                    going to run this new agency. They came from military assistance and the
                    Development Loan Fund and ICA and all that. I appointed a board under Dillon
                    Myer, for whom Tom and I had a great respect. It was called the AID Evolution
                    Board. On that board were myself, Jack Bell, and a man representing the White
                    House, Bill Dentzer (who represented Ralph Dungan) and one or two others. We
                    went over the every Personnel file of every one of the top executives and
                    decided who would go and who would stay of that group. Most of them stayed.</p>
                <p>We had a pretty good bunch of people. But there's one case that's kind of
                    interesting. We were going over Mission Directors and we had a man in Ceylon. I
                    think he'd been the Deputy there to Jim Grant earlier. He was the Deputy and the
                    Ambassador was a lady: Frances Willis, wanted to make him the Director. His name
                    was Jack Kubisch. Dentzer, who was the political guy, looked at this and he
                    said, “Who's this guy Kubisch? He came in here in 1960. He's got to be an
                    Eisenhower guy.” I said, “Bill, I've known Jack since the Marshall Plan days,
                    when I replaced him in Paris. He's one of my best friends. To this day, I don't
                    know what his politics are, but he's a very able man. He's gone out and made his
                    million dollars in private industry. He came back in. He loves foreign aid.”
                    “Well, let's bring him back to Washington and take a look at him.” So, I sent
                    Jack a wire to come into Washington. The first guy that interviewed him was Bill
                    Gaud, who was the head of that region. I got a call from Bill Gaud, saying,
                    “Now, I've been thinking about replacing Carter Ide. Do you think you could get
                    me Jack Kubisch as my Deputy?” I said, “Well, I don't know. I'll see what we can
                    do.” Then Dungan wanted to interview him. Dungan, the big guy over in the White
                    House. So, I sent him over to the White House and I get a call from Ralph,
                    saying, “Mel, I've just found our new Mission Director for Brazil: Jack
                    Kubisch.” The guy that they were going to fire was the guy that they thought was
                    Mr. Great. Jack went on to become a Foreign Service Officer and an Ambassador to
                    Greece. There was the tycoon fiasco.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Operation Tycoon.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Here I am, Director of this great Office of Personnel Administration. I
                    didn't even know it was happening, but Dungan over at the White House, had been
                    talking to General Lucius Clay. Clay had said, “You ought to bring in
                    businessmen. Businessmen know how to run this outfit. Businessmen.” So, Ralph
                    got in touch with someone from IBM, the Director of Personnel and Deputy and
                    they decided to bring in all these executives - I think there were almost 40 of
                    them - to take over this new agency and run it. I wasn't consulted at all about
                    this and here I am, Director of Personnel. So, I have to go to the Hill to
                    testify with the Deputy Head of AID, who was a man named Jake Lingle, who'd come
                    from Proctor and Gamble, a very nice man. We testified before the House Foreign
                    Relations Committee. We were getting a pretty rough time. We got around to one
                    of the senior Congressmen, who's name was Walter Judd. He was a medical
                    missionary, so you called him “Doctor.” We got around to Dr. Judd. He said, “Mr.
                    Lingle, I understand you're bringing in all these businessmen to run AID.” And
                    he said, “That's right, Sir, we're going to put it on a business-like basis.
                    We're going to make this a really business-like outfit.” Judd said, “Well, you
                    know, I don't know if you know, Mr. Lingle, but I am a physician. And if I had a
                    brain tumor, I would want a tumor specialist to remove it, not some businessman.
                    You've got people who really know development and you're firing them and
                    bringing in people who know nothing about development.” I wanted to kiss Walter
                    Judd. You know what happened to Operation Tycoon. One person out of the whole
                    group finally stayed with the Agency and made it and he went on to The World
                    Bank or IMF. I forget his name.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bob Neuter.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Right. You know what that cost the Agency, to the morale of the Agency,
                    to the people that were there that had worked and strived to bring in a bunch of
                    guys who knew nothing about it. Part of the time I was in that job, I was
                    offered the job of Vice President of the Asia Foundation. I went out and looked
                    at it and, for a variety of reasons, turned it down. But I suggested Bill
                    Sheppard, who had had a stroke many years before and he couldn't stand
                    Washington's winter. Bill was the Assistant Administrator of AID for
                    Administration. Bill got the job. So, I was appointed Acting Assistant
                    Administrator of AID for Administration for about a month. I don't know whether
                    you're going to approve of this or not, Haven, but I was the guy that approved
                    the first Joint Administrative Services for AID in Africa. Who was the guy in
                    Africa who had lots of ideas about having regional offices in Africa and this
                    and that and the other? But I approved the first JAS.</p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>The other thing that happened was that the Alliance for Progress was being set
                    up. The idea was it was to be kind of a part of AID that had a special aura. It
                    was under a man named Ted Moscoso from Puerto Rico, who had been the key man of
                    Operation Bootstrap, that had brought so much development to Puerto Rico. We had
                    an office building for them on Pennsylvania Avenue. I think about where the
                    present Mexican Embassy is. We had a big logo being built to hang outside the
                    building show that this was special. The Alliance for Progress was very near and
                    dear to President Kennedy's heart. They were scheduled to move over a weekend to
                    these brand new offices. I got a call late Friday afternoon that George Ball,
                    the Under Secretary of State, had been to see Kennedy and had scotched the whole
                    thing. The idea was “No, they were not going to move at all. They were going to
                    go back to back with the State Department's Latin America bureau.” So, over the
                    weekend, we had to reschedule the move, have other people move into the office
                    space we'd already rented, that were being displaced in the State Department to
                    open up room for the AID people. We put State and AID back to back for Latin
                    America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the reason for starting it that way? That was the
                        only Bureau that was set up that way, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why was it-?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I don't know. I don't know where Ball got the idea. He felt that there
                    was too much division between AID and State. The head of my Bureau when I was in
                    ICA was a State Department man. There had been a closer relationship of State
                    and AID in Latin America, I guess, than most other places. He just thought it
                    would be better organization.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Within the context of the Alliance for Progress
                        though?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: This was still the Alliance for Progress. You still had Ted as the head
                    of the Alliance, but he was now working with State, next door to the Assistant
                    Secretary. Later, under Tom Mann, when I was Executive Director of the Bureau,
                    we actually integrated those offices so that they were combined. They were no
                    longer just back to back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find that worked?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: Well, I wasn't there that long. You ought to do some interviews. The
                    State people thought it worked very well. The AID people I'm not so sure thought
                    it worked as well. That's just a generalization. I still believe that there
                    should be an interchange of personnel. That's very good for both, to learn each
                    other's points of view. I think development is such a major part of what's going
                    on that it ought to continue. One other thing that I did when I was Director of
                    Personnel. The head of the TIAA-CREF. You know what the TIAA-CREF is. It was
                    organized by the Carnegie Foundation. Many of the teachers in this country and
                    many foundations - like the Ford Foundation, the National Academy for Public
                    Administration - and universities are under this system. It's a retirement
                    system mainly for education people. It was set up under the Carnegie Corporation
                    because teachers in small communities didn't have any pensions. And so, by
                    having this overall pension fund, they could be a part of it. Many, many
                    universities are under it. It's a very, very big outfit. The problem that this
                    Mr. Pfieffer brought to me was that - he was talking about Africa mostly -
                    people would go to Africa in technical jobs and serve in Nigeria or wherever it
                    was and their counterparts, here they were with all this money and cars and this
                    and that and higher salaries. But here were their counterparts with “nada.” The
                    idea was that we could appoint people somehow to go to Africa - let's say
                    Africa; it could be anywhere. They would still have their pensions and their
                    TIAA-CREF back in the States. You could incorporate this corporation that would
                    hire these people under, say, the State laws of New York, where they would have
                    workman's compensation and you could pay into their accounts but keep the
                    majority of the pay at home. But, locally, they would look like no more than the
                    local people. They wouldn't get paid much more than their counterparts. I
                    advised him on this and I don't know whether it ever came to pass or not. I
                    don't know whether you know or not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember there were discussions but I don't recall. I
                        don't think so.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: But it was an interesting idea and we tried different things like that.
                    I finally left the Agency. I was so unhappy about this-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the principle driving force in this restructuring
                        of the, or the creation of AID at this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: It came out of the White House. Rostow was over there. Sorensen. The
                    President himself. The top person - I've mentioned him a couple of times - was
                    Ralph Dungan. Ralph eventually had three jobs. At that point, he was the
                    President's primary person on top personnel appointments - Secretaries and
                    Assistant Secretaries. He was also the White House man on AID. Later, he also
                    had Latin America. McGeorge Bundy, who just died, had all of the world as
                    National Security Advisor, Special Assistant for National Security, except Latin
                    America. Dungan had Latin America. McGeorge Bundy had Cuba and the rest of the
                    world. So, the force came mostly out of the White House. Then there had been
                    some force on the Hill. One of the bad things under this was that they took
                    military assistance out and gave it to the Defense Department, which gave us
                    problems in Latin America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the driving rationale for the creation of AID?
                        Why did they want to bring it all together?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: They thought they could get the most bang for the buck - to bring
                    together development loan funds and technical assistance was the main thing,
                    which I think made sense. You can't exclude loans from it, although my interest
                    has always been technical assistance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you find those operations very different?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I wasn't involved. I was in Personnel and I was no longer an Office
                    Director. But I think that it worked better. I also deplore the use of the word
                    “aid” and I know we're never going to get rid of it, but I think the old days of
                    “technical cooperation” was a much better term, or “development” or
                    “international development cooperation” is even a better term. I hope that
                    someday we will come to that. Later, if you want my overall ideas on all of
                    this, I'll be glad to give them to you.</p>
                <p>Return to the State Department as Executive Director, Latin America Bureau -
                    1962</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you went on to the War College?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: No. Herman Pollack of State and the Under Secretary for Management -
                    Bill Crockett - called me and said, “Why don't you move over to the State
                    Department?” I was so sick of Stassenization and this whole business. AID had
                    offered me the of being the AID liaison at the UN, which Herman Kleine took
                    after I turned it down. Pollack and Bill Crockett had said, “If you come over to
                    State, we've got some very interesting jobs as Executive Director of the
                    Bureaus, which we're going to make Deputy Assistant Secretary jobs. We have a
                    job open for Europe.” I thought, “My God, Europe! Paris, London, Rome!
                    Beautiful.” “And then you'd have an opportunity to apply to become a Foreign
                    Service Officer, a commissioned Officer. It was not guaranteed. You had to go
                    before a Board and all the rest. So, with that in mind, to become a Foreign
                    Service Officer, a commissioned Officer, and just to get out of AID- To this
                    day, Haven, I'm not sure I did the right thing, because I've always loved AID.
                    You can take the boy out of AID, but you can't take AID out of the boy. But I
                    did it and I went off on a vacation to Florida and I came back and they said,
                    “The job is no longer in Europe. It's in Latin America.” Well, the man who was
                    Assistant Secretary for Latin America, Edwin Martin - one of the best men I've
                    ever known - and his Deputy was Dick Goodwin, who was a Kennedy man, a speech
                    writer. I knew all about Dick Goodwin. I finally said, “I'll take the job, but I
                    won't report to Dick Goodwin.” Ed said, “You won't” and I didn't. Dick stayed on
                    as Deputy, but I had very little to do with him except cleaning up after him and
                    his messes that he'd leave around the world. There's not much in that job that's
                    related to AID. I don't know how much you want me to go into this, but-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing? How long were you in this job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I was in there almost two years. As Executive Director of the Bureau,
                    you're concerned with the management of the Embassies, finance, personnel,
                    relations with AID, and so on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was still during the Alliance period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes, during the Alliance period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you interacting with AID? How did you see the issues
                        from that side?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: I felt that AID was niggardly in the way it treated the State
                    Department. I knew the money AID had and I knew the little bit of money that the
                    State Department had. For example, Bill Parks was my counterpart. He was the
                    kind of Executive Director for the Bureau of Latin American Affairs of AID. We
                    had two offices with a common lobby. He came into my office one day and said,
                    “Mel, I'm ordering some new carpeting for the lobby. Do you mind if I carpet the
                    whole thing, yours, too?” I said, “No, that would be great” because in State I
                    had an office, I was Executive Director of personnel with a rank of FSR-1. They
                    Deputy Assistant Secretary never came through. And I didn't even have a rug on
                    my floor. I said, “That would be great to have a rug out there. I don't have one
                    in here, but it would be great out there.” We had old, beat up typewriters and
                    all the rest. Bill left and went to Brazil and a new guy came in named Harry
                    Hinderer. When the new rug came in, they started to lay it down all the way, in
                    front of my office door. Harry saw that part of it was going to go in front of
                    my office. He stopped it. Cut it off.</p>
                <p>One thing Ed Martin and I tried to do was to bring new blood into the Latin
                    America area. Ed was just first rate. Ed, too, had worked for Dillon and he knew
                    foreign aid as well as anybody. Ed and I felt strongly that we ought to bring
                    new blood into Latin America. You had the old Latin types, some very good
                    people, but getting too set in their ways. I'm talking about the State
                    Department now. So, we tried to bring in new people. We brought in Jim Fowler
                    from AID-Far East and made him AID director and economic counselor. Our idea was
                    to bring them in and then make them DCMs and then from DCM they could go on to
                    become Ambassadors. One of the first ones we worked on was Len Saccio. Remember
                    Len Saccio had been the Republican Deputy of ICA. He'd gone to Brazil, done a
                    first rate job, but he was very bad on Congressional relations. He had a lot of
                    hubris dealing with Congressional delegations. Some Congressional delegation had
                    gone down to Brazil and they felt he had treated them with the back of his hand.
                    They wanted to go up to Northeast Brazil. He wouldn't let them go. Some of the
                    delegation went to see Rusk and he was yanked out. He came back to DC and saw
                    Graham Martin, who was then the deputy to Ted Moscoso and Graham would not even
                    see him. Graham went with the political winds whichever way they blew. So he
                    came to see me and I said, “I think you'd be a great DCM.” We tried to send him
                    to Jamaica. Ralph Dungan said, “Oh, no, I'm not going to send a Republican to
                    that beautiful place.” Ralph had never been in Kingston. If you've ever been in
                    Kingston, we're not talking about Ocho Rios, we're talking Kingston. So, we
                    said, “Well, Salvador.” He said, “Okay, Salvador.” So we sent him to Salvador.
                    We had a marvelous career Foreign Service Ambassador there who just thought Len
                    Saccio was the greatest thing to ever come down the pike. He accepted the idea
                    of a non-FSO as his DCM, even a person from AID!</p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                <p>See, every Ambassador, when he takes over his job, has to issue a kind of a
                    ranking. In other words, if he was incapacitated, the DCM becomes the Charg�. If
                    the Charg�'s incapacitated, then who else will be in charge. It is almost always
                    the head of the Political Section, throughout the world, believe me. In
                    Salvador, the Ambassador designated the AID Director to be second in line.
                    Before Ed and I could bring this about, we had to get approval from State. I
                    went to see the Deputy Director of Personnel at State and I said, “We'd like to
                    have Len Saccio go to Salvador as the Deputy Chief of Mission. Well, Haven, it
                    would have been as if I had called his mother a prostitute! He just said, “My
                    God, an AID guy to be DCM?” The DCM position is a very crucial job in the State
                    Department because that's the way you keep control. As a matter of fact,
                    generally it is a good policy. Often, a career person has to back up a political
                    ambassador who doesn't know what he or she is doing. I reported the turn-down to
                    Len Saccio and Len said, “Gee, Mel, I don't know what to do. I love this
                    business. I love foreign aid. You know, I've never used this before, but should
                    I go see Doug Dillon?” Dillon was the Secretary of the Treasury at this point.
                    He'd known Mr. Dillon from the ICA days when Dillon was the Coordinator at State
                    for foreign assistance. Dillon was beloved by President Kennedy. He was a
                    Republican, Secretary of the Treasury who helped the President a great deal.
                    Well, lo and behold, next day, the top of the State Department almost came off.
                    The Director of Personnel called me. He said, “What did you tell Len Saccio?” I
                    said, “Well, I told you that you wouldn't approve him.” He said, “Oh, no, no!
                    Tell him it was a mistake!” Len was appointed DCM to El Salvador.</p>
                <p>We tried to bring other people in, too. We were on our way to doing it before
                    Kennedy was assassinated. I truly believe we had the very best policy towards
                    Latin America we've ever had. Ralph Dungan, whom I didn't like at all when he
                    was my b�te noire on Personnel matters, had an excellent point of view on Latin
                    America. His view on Latin America blended with that of Ed Martin, the Assistant
                    Secretary. I think Ralph and Ed were a perfect team, backed by the President
                    himself, who just loved Latin America. You know, when Kennedy was assassinated,
                    Johnson did not move into the White House the next day after the big funeral
                    because Mrs. Kennedy wanted to give a reception for just the Latin America heads
                    of state who came to the funeral. I was in charge of the State Department part
                    of that. As each one went by to shake hands with Mrs. Kennedy, she said to each
                    of them, “Jack loved Latin America. Jack loved Latin America.” It meant a lot to
                    me. On a minor, personal front, the assassination meant a lot to me because, the
                    day before Kennedy was killed, Ed Martin announced that I was going to be pulled
                    out of my job and detailed to set up a special task force to work under the
                    general guidance of him and Averell Harriman on reorganizing the Organization of
                    American States (OAS) which would have been a great job, but I'm sure would have
                    been impossible! It was just as well. Then Johnson came in and appointed Tom
                    Mann, who was Ambassador to Mexico, to be the head of Latin America. Tom was
                    determined to integrate State and AID. It was just a given with him and he
                    wouldn't hear of anything else. I assembled a team of Dick Barrett, Bob Sayer,
                    Jules Sugsuman, and Jerry Pagano to work on it.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was just the Latin American part?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Yes. Well, Tom was just over Latin America. What happened was, before
                    Kennedy died, someone had gone to Kennedy to say that he should appoint an Under
                    Secretary for Inter American Affairs. And he had written a memo to Dean Rusk,
                    which I saw, which I did not keep a copy of, saying, in effect, “I want to set
                    up an Under Secretary for Inter American Affairs.” (Everyone else would be an
                    Assistant Secretary - for Far East, for Europe, but Inter American Affairs would
                    have an Under Secretary. That's how Kennedy felt about Latin America.) As you
                    usually do, don't tell me I can't do it.” Kennedy did note didn't want Kennedy
                    like Dean Rusk. This was in October. Of course, he was killed in November. So,
                    when Johnson became President, here on his desk was this wish of the former
                    President to upgrade everything in Latin America. He talked to Fulbright about
                    it and Fulbright said, “My Lord, what about your relationships with NATO and
                    with SYNCPAC and this, that and the other?” So, instead, and I'm not sure to
                    this day where he got the idea, he decided to combine everything on Latin
                    America and to set up a kind of a Poobah for Latin America. This was Tom Mann,
                    whom he hardly knew. Everyone thought he knew him, but he didn't. Tom was
                    recommended to Johnson by Hubert Humphrey. So, Tom Mann would have three hats.
                    He would be Assistant Secretary for Latin America. He'd be the head of the
                    Alliance for Progress. And he'd be the “Ralph Dungan” in the White House. He'd
                    get it all. I just thought this was wonderful because I was all for upgrading
                    Latin America.</p>
                <p>I was especially interested in getting control over the military. What was
                    happening was that the military in Latin America - our military - would go right
                    against the Ambassador's orders. So, the Ambassador would be recalled and the
                    AID Director would be recalled and in three months, they would be back and be in
                    control. And when we would withdraw the Ambassador and the AID Director and the
                    USIA Director - not Peace Corps; that's different; we didn't go into that - they
                    would say, “But the military wouldn't leave.” So, Ed Martin would have to call
                    Ralph Dungan, who would have to call Bob McNamara. Bob McNamara called the Joint
                    Chiefs of Staff and they'd remove him. And the military were revolutions in
                    Latin America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was actually-</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: Oh, yes. This happened just before the assassination in Honduras. When
                    Tom Mann came in he was just riding awfully high. His face was on the cover of
                    Time, he was the first new big appointment of Johnson. I said, I had this group
                    under me of first rate people like Bob Sayre and Rodger Abraham and so on. We
                    went to Tom and said, “Look, this is your chance to get control of this whole
                    thing. Take away the control of the Inter American Development Bank from the
                    Treasury Department. Take control of the military assistance programs from the
                    Defense Department. Take control of the Panama Canal. Put that under State and
                    get it away from the military.” I went over to the White House myself. Got him
                    an office over there. Got him a White House car. I knew the trappings of power -
                    that if he called and said, “This is the White House calling,” that's a big, big
                    difference than saying “This is the State Department calling.” He wouldn't
                    accept any of it. He never used the office at the White House. He never used the
                    car. He had lunch with Bill Bundy, who was then the Assistant Secretary of the
                    Department of Defense for International Affairs, we had urged Mann to take over
                    the military, which he could have done. Johnson would have given him anything.
                    Mann came back and said, “I know Bill Bundy and we can always get along. I don't
                    think we have to do this,” so we didn't get that. Later, Bill Bundy became
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Vietnam. Then we said, “Well, you ought to take
                    over the Inter American Development Bank. That ought to be a part of the
                    package. If you're really going to run Latin American affairs.” He said, “I'm a
                    good friend of Douglas Dillon. I get along with Douglas Dillon. I'm not going to
                    take it out of Treasury.” We got none of that. The only thing he took over was
                    the Alliance for Progress. Tom Mann liked Rodger Abraham very much, as well he
                    should have. Rodger had been his Admin Officer in Mexico, so it became pretty
                    clear to me that he liked Rodger more than he did me as executive director.</p>
                <p>I think a lot of our problems with Latin America stem from Tom Mann. For example,
                    Ed Martin and I were going to make Murat Williams Ambassador to Guatemala. Jack
                    Bell was Ambassador to Guatemala, but he was being PNGed by the Guatemalan
                    government. These were papers we had going before Kennedy was assassinated. Tom
                    said, “I don't want- No, not him.” I said, “Why?” He said, “He was against the
                    fourteen families in Salvador.” The fourteen families in Salvador who had been
                    behind this whole problem we'd had down in Salvador for the last umpteen years.
                    He was an anti-democracy kind of guy. We also disagreed a little bit on
                    organization. He wanted a separate office for every country. An Office for
                    Mexican Affairs, an Office for Honduran Affairs. And I said, “We would need 20
                    or more office directors!”</p>
                <p>So, finally, I went back to AID for six months. I became the Assistant Director
                    for Administration for Latin America, whatever that title is, working for Bill
                    Rogers, a wonderful guy - not the Secretary of State, but the man that became
                    Under Secretary later under President Ford. I enjoyed that very much, being back
                    in Latin America working for AID.</p>
                <p>Special assignment in AID on Latin America - 1963</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a special task that you had at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Just being the usual - whatever that person does. The one thing I tried
                    to do there, which had no direct relation to my job, was I worked with a very
                    bright young woman named Ann Brownell, (now Ann Brownell Sloan). We tried to
                    develop the idea of a profession of development administration. There should be
                    a degree in development administration. There should be courses in development
                    administration. She and I were working on that before I had to leave.</p>
                <p>One thing I did do though was to get even with Harry Hinderer. When I became
                    Executive Director under Tom, I also had the AID Latin America bureau
                    responsibility. I knew they had money. I'd see people walking down the hall and
                    they'd say, “Hey, Mel, I'm going to Brazil tomorrow. Is there anything we can do
                    for you down there?” There'd be about three of them. As the State Department
                    executive director, I used to have to approve every single simple travel order
                    for Linc Gordon. You could never bring a DCM to town for a consultation in their
                    whole assignment, or anyone else. And there'd be three guys going down to Brazil
                    for AID. So, I went back to the office and I said to my people in AID-Latin
                    America, “I didn't approve those orders.” “Well, no, you don't have to, Mel.
                    They have their own money. We have so much money for travel, you don't have to
                    worry about that.”</p>
                <p>So I ordered all new furniture for everybody, new IBM Selectric typewriters,
                    carpeted all the floors. We had the money. So, I got a call from Bill Hall, who
                    was the Assistant Administrator for Management of AID overall, a great guy. A
                    career Foreign Service Officer. But he was then serving in AID. He said, “What
                    are you doing, using AID money to carpet floors for the State Department?” I
                    said, “Bill, these are joint offices. This is not just AID. It's AID and State.
                    They're joint.” He said, “I just don't think it's right.” I said, “Bill, do you
                    want me to discuss this with Tom Mann?” “No, no, that's quite alright.” And we
                    carpeted all the floors. So I got even.</p>
                <p>One other thing I did get accomplished to give contracting authority to the AID
                    missions was, Dave Bell was then the Administrator. I felt strongly, as did many
                    people that the Missions should have the right to contract. I had a conference
                    with Dave on a Saturday afternoon and he agreed to give a Mission authority to
                    contract up to $10,000 or $25,000 on their own. The first test Mission was in
                    Guatemala. I think that was the wedge. If anyone looks up the record, I think
                    that began it. I think Dave did it, among other reasons, because Jack Bell was
                    still Ambassador down there. But that was the opening wedge, I think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What other changes occurred during this period - ICA, AID?
                        Was the decision to eliminate direct hire technical assistance and go almost
                        exclusively to contracts? You talked about university contracts and so on,
                        but in those last days of ICA and the early days of AID, I believe there was
                        a very large direct hire technical group. What was the reasoning behind the
                        shift away from using direct hire technical assistance? That was part of
                        Personnel, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: No, not when I was there. I think I know what was behind it. You can
                    contract for a project, get it done, and when it's over, you can easily get rid
                    of the people. They are there only on contract. You don't have to worry about
                    them. You don't have to have a reduction in force or a bloodletting, or a
                    Stassenization. But I think contracting has gone too far. After I retired, I did
                    some consulting for AID in the field. I observed contracting here and there. I
                    think it has gone much, much too far. One thing I learned when I served in
                    Mexico from Dave Amato was this: you need long term commitments of technicians
                    stationed there, that stay with the program or project, who know the people, who
                    know the political, economic, and social aspects of the country and can really
                    do a job and can follow a project all the way through. What I found in AID was
                    that one contractor would design a project and another would actually get the
                    contract and implement it. You had no continuity. And I think that's awful. I
                    think, sure, contracting is good and I think contracting ought to be continued,
                    but there should be many more career people to supervise those contracts in the
                    Missions and in Washington and that contractors carry through projects from
                    beginning to end.</p>
                <p>The one area which I know has not been very popular with AID, but that you know
                    so well, is public administration. There's no real Public Administration Office.
                    I think public administration has been downgraded by AID, especially over in
                    Eastern Europe, where you need a good basis of a government before you can have
                    democratization and you can have a decent market economy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have some impression of the character, of the
                        quality of the public administration programs that AID or predecessors
                        had?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Just peripherally. I think we tried in the early days to duplicate or
                    replicate what we had in Washington. If we had a Budget Bureau, then they ought
                    to have a Budget Bureau. If we had a Civil Service Commission, then they ought
                    to have a Civil Service Commission. I think this did not go down very well and
                    was not based on the recipient country's own situation and history. I think this
                    is one reason that the public administration people were displaced. I did like
                    that phase in AID's history during McPherson's regime - institutional
                    development. I believe strongly in institutional development. So, if you look at
                    public administration more under the rubric of institutional development, with
                    all its facets, then I think you've got something.</p>
                <p>Special assignment as Counselor for Administration, U.S. Embassy India -
                    1964-66</p>
                <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                <p>I went to New Delhi in '64 as the Counselor for Administration. I went there
                    because Chester Bowles, who was the Ambassador, wanted to combine the two
                    administrative staffs of AID and the Embassy. With my background in both AID and
                    State, Bill Crockett sent me out. I tried to put them together. I think it would
                    have worked there. It would have gone even better later, when you had one
                    overall, comprehensive Foreign Service system. But I brought out a man named
                    Orbun Powell, who was one of the best in the business to help me do it. We
                    proposed the first head of the operation be an AID guy, not me. The efficiency
                    ratings of all of the people working in the combined operation would first be
                    done by the AID man and then reviewed by the Ambassador, so that the staff would
                    feel they had just as much obligation to take care of the AID people as they did
                    of the Embassy. But I could never get it approved back here. Again, it was Bill
                    Hall. It was Bill who was the Foreign Service Officer, Assistant Administrator
                    of AID, who blocked it. The local AID people approved it: a first rate AID
                    Director, John Lewis. So we didn't bring it off. But, once again, AID had
                    enormous resources of physical stuff that they would not let the Embassy
                    use.</p>
                <p>A year in the Senior Seminar - 1966-67</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there for one year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: One year: '66-'67. One of the things you can do in the Seminar is you
                    can take a trip anywhere in the world - you could then - I think you still can -
                    and study anything you want, with the agreement of the Director of the Seminar,
                    of course. What I wanted to do was study the various ways that technical
                    assistance was being administered by other countries. I went to Israel, France,
                    England, Germany, Sweden - about a three or four week trip. I wrote a paper. If
                    you want to, you can attach it to this-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, we'd like to have it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: It's called Expansion of U.S. Technical Assistance and Lessons Learned
                    from Other Donors and a Proposal. I did learn a lot. It was and is a fascinating
                    topic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's the main thought you had in this paper?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: The main thought was to set up a new kind of organization for technical
                    assistance, government corporation - to administer technical assistance that
                    could use both government funds and donated funds. You'd call it a foundation,
                    call it whatever you want. What I was really trying to do was one: make it
                    permanent; two: get it out of politics; and be able to use different methods of
                    technical assistance.</p>
                <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                <p>I found, for instance, that in Germany, the Germans used non-governmental NGO
                    organizations or provide technical assistance. They hardly did any of their own.
                    They did a lot of their technical assistance through churches. I'm talking about
                    '66 though. It may have changed a great deal.</p>
                <p>I found in Sweden that Sweden they were doing the great majority of their
                    technical assistance through the UN. But the government found that the Swedish
                    public didn't like that. The public wanted to be identified with their programs.
                    So, when I went to Sweden in '66, they were beginning to set up their own
                    bilateral programs. By the way, the language they used overseas was English
                    because they knew very few countries could speak Swedish.</p>
                <p>In Britain, they had a very interesting idea. We talked earlier about contractors
                    hiring a person from the outside to do a job and not using persons from the
                    inside. The British had found the same thing. So, their idea was that they would
                    endow seats in various universities, especially the red brick ones like Sussex,
                    so that, when the government asked for someone from that University, they'd get
                    someone who was a part of the regular faculty and not somebody hired just for
                    the purpose of going to do the particular project. It was a fascinating
                    study.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the French?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: I can't remember. But I do remember the Israelis. They very candidly
                    said that they provided technical assistance primarily for political reasons -
                    to gain international support. Secondly, for humanitarian reasons.</p>
                <p>Observations on international development</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a good point to talk a little bit about what your
                        own views are about what works or what doesn't work in technical assistance,
                        what's the merits of it in the context of developments in foreign policy
                        interests. Or do you want to reflect on that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0077" n="Page0077"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: I have reflected on it some. Let's go back to the whole subject of
                    development - the word. Generally, I think “development,” quote, is good. But I
                    hate to hear the news that someone is going to develop a new piece of land,
                    which means taking away some land and building some houses. But the way we're
                    using the word means the development of a country. What's come into being the
                    last few years that I think is very good is the idea of sustainable development:
                    development that does no harm, that can be sustained and doesn't harm the
                    institutions or the people or the environment. In that type of development,
                    technical assistance is a very vital part. Technical assistance is the way to
                    help development. I think that we ought to go back to the old days of TCA -
                    Technical Cooperation Administration. But call it “cooperation” and not
                    “assistance” because I really do believe that it can be cooperative, that we can
                    learn from other countries and they can learn from us. By the way, it can be
                    used internally. It can be used within our own country. What we learn from other
                    countries can be used in helping the ghettos and I think AID's doing some of
                    that now. I tried to work on that about fifteen years ago, but you had no basis
                    to go on.</p>
                <p>With that, I think, there ought to be a profession of development assistance,
                    “development cooperation” let's call it. Let's get away from that word
                    “assistance.” I think, in any of these cases, it's just common sense: you have
                    to have respect for the people that you're working with, for their institutions,
                    for their point of view, that you don't go in there and tell them what to do.
                    You work with them to find out what you can learn from them. Harold Sideman, our
                    buddy from the National Academy, who has done a lot of this, says that, “When I
                    go to a country, I don't tell them what to do. I ask them what they're doing and
                    what they want done.” I think that's basic. I think it's worthwhile. I think
                    it's good for the world. And I think it ought to be a permanent part of our U.S.
                    foreign policy. It should be a domestic policy as well, that there be
                    development cooperation in HUD on the ghettos and so on.</p>
                <p>We might have fewer ghettos. To go on to that a little bit, Haven, I don't know
                    to this day how much research is being done on what works and what doesn't work.
                    My God, we've had over fifty years of governmental experience. It began in '39.
                    There have been little projects and big projects. I don't know about the big
                    stuff. I don't know about macroeconomics. But even there, there ought to be
                    studies being done. Why is it that Hong Kong, Singapore, Formosa are developing
                    like mad? Why is it that Latin America isn't? Why is it that the Philippines
                    right next door is not doing as well as the other Far Eastern countries?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you think?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0078" n="Page0078"/>
                <p>SPECTOR: I think it's partially cultural above everything. Let's take those
                    countries. I don't want to be pejorative here, but I think that the Western
                    European Protestant ethic works. I think the Chinese ethic works. I think the
                    Jewish ethic of hard work and education works. But look at a lot of these
                    countries. I have to say it: a lot of these have the Latin Catholic ethic. I'm a
                    great defender of the Catholics. I think the Franciscan Fathers were the great
                    developers of the United States Southwest and of the West Coast. But there's
                    been too much suppression of thought and of creativity. You know, the banned
                    books and all that. I think Larry Harrison has some good ideas. That is a
                    Hispanic-based culture. And a few thousand miles away, you've got Formosa. Look
                    at the difference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you do anything about those cultures?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPECTOR: Well, I think maybe something's being done, I guess. I don't know. Look
                    at Ireland. Look at Southern Italy. They haven't developed as well, but
                    Ireland's coming along now as they're taking on some of those old prohibitions.
                    Ireland now has a woman President. They're taking on abortion. They're taking on
                    divorce. Those things are happening.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
