<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001726">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Mr. Eshaam Palmer , 2011: a machine-readable
                    transcription.</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2012</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2012-06-24"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2012-06-24"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>ESHAAM PALMER</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Daniel F. Whitman</p>
                <p>Interview date: February 15, 2010</p>
                <p>Copyright 2011 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It has been five days after the twentieth anniversary of
                        the releasing of Nelson Mandela. It has been a very exhilarated week here. I
                        am fortunate to have Eshaam Palmer here, who visited the United States in
                        1986 with Operation Crossroads and is Director of Environmental Compliance
                        and Enforcement in the Department of Environmental Affairs and Development
                        Planning, also the former Chief Parliamentary Legal Adviser, and Chief
                        Director of Legal Services and the Office of Premier of the Western Cape.
                        Dr. Palmer, tell us first- this is history. Tell us a little bit about your
                        origins, your childhood, and your education; how it is that you fit into
                        this very complicated society and your early professional development.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: My name is Eshaam Palmer, I am the son of parents of mixed race - you can
                    term them colored people - a specific sub-group of the colored people that was
                    classified as being of Malaysian origin. Essentially it is this group that
                    follows the Muslim faith amongst the colored groups in South Africa. I had a
                    normal childhood in Cape Town, went to a junior school and then a high school.
                    We were an average working class colored family. My father was a carpenter and
                    my mother was a dressmaker who worked from home. They have three children, two
                    boys and a girl. We are all completed high school. My father worked to support
                    us, and we had our own house. My mother worked to give us the extra bits that
                    the other people did not have. So we did not have a deprived childhood, we had
                    most things, we had a domestic worker, we had food every night, we had a car and
                    a house. So we were a little above the average colored family. My dad opened up
                    his own small construction company - which made life a little easier for us. But
                    we were restricted since we were colored, and we did not get the opportunities
                    to attend universities since they were beyond our financial capabilities.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>When I completed high school I had little motivation to study further. I feel
                    that I wanted to work so I got a job as a clerk in a government department. I
                    worked there for nine years. The Department does not exist anymore as it was
                    part of the “apartheid” administration, but compared to now it would be the
                    Department of Social Welfare and Pensions. We dealt with welfare organizations
                    and grants, and assisting them in establishing welfare organizations. After one
                    year of being employed, when I was 19 years old - I realized that I couldn't
                    work as a clerk for the rest of my life. So I decided to study on a part time
                    basis. I registered for evening classes to study public administration in order
                    to rise in the ranks of my employment. I completed a 3 year diploma course in
                    public administration, and one of the subjects I took - was law. Immediately
                    after completing that diploma, I again embarked on part time evening classes to
                    gain a diploma in law. And after three years of part time study, I decided to
                    continue my education in law by correspondence tuition. I continued working
                    full-time whilst studying by correspondence. Eventually I spent 23 years at
                    various universities studying part time. In this manner I acquired a B.Juris and
                    B.Proc degrees in law in addition to the two diplomas I mentioned earlier. I
                    also completed as BA in criminology, an honors degree in criminology, a masters
                    degree in criminology, and ultimately a doctorate, in constitution law and
                    criminology - looking specifically at punishment and how the new constitution in
                    1996 changes the whole “ethos” of punishment in South Africa by the abolishment
                    of the death penalty and corporal punishment and also examined ways of
                    alternative remedies - especially for juveniles.</p>
                <p>Essentially UNISA's (University of South Africa) faculty of criminology supported
                    the death penalty. I tried to get help publishing an article, but they would
                    not, because it was not in line with their view on the death penalty. So they
                    advised me to go to the University of Cape Town because their faculty of law and
                    criminology were more supportive of the abolishment of the death penalty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you yourself have a strong opinion one way or the
                        other?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Well, from a religious perspective, I support the death penalty in a
                    sense that there are certain crimes and criminals for whom the alternative for
                    imprisonment places a heavier burden on society than on the victim. I look at
                    examples like murder and rape, especially committed by psychopaths for whom
                    there are no possibilities of rehabilitation. It would mean a great state
                    expense, and society in general, but also the danger to co-prisoners and warders
                    who have to care for them. Many warders have been killed over the years by
                    people who have psychopathic tendencies and who harbour no sense of remorse.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say victims I guess you mean the families related to
                        the victims.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, the victim spectrum is broad, because it is not only for the person
                    who was killed or raped, but also the family of the perpetrator. They are also
                    victims because every perpetrator has parents and families. And surely the
                    parents did not teach or encourage them to commit serious crimes, and the
                    parents loved them. Most of them probably had brothers and sisters and cousins -
                    and those people loved them too. Those people are equally hurt when a crime like
                    that is committed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What inspired you to write a paper about the death penalty
                        imposed by error?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: It was the Christy murder in London in the mid- to late 1900s. Christy
                    was a manipulative serial killer who convinced a simple minded boarder in his
                    house to confess to one of the murders he committed. And this person was then
                    subsequently found guilty of murder and executed on the basis of his confession.
                    It later transpired that Christy himself had murdered the woman, and that the
                    simple-minded person who confessed to the murder which he did not commit was
                    someone who could easily be influenced to confess to anything if the right level
                    of pressure was brought to bear on him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Someone said that if the death penalty is implemented in
                        error, that in itself is reason to be against the implementation of the
                        death penalty. Yet, you do not draw that conclusion?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: I think what I was trying to argue is that there should be greater
                    safeguards, and that people should not be convicted or executed only based on
                    confessions, as often happened during the “apartheid” era. And that the evidence
                    should be so strong that is it not only beyond the reasonable doubt, but that is
                    beyond any doubt. Not all cases of serious offences, like murder and rape would
                    automatically (go to death penalty), but there would be certain cases where it
                    would be absolutely no doubt that the person was the perpetrator.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I am sure people have asked you what you mean by
                        “absolutely no doubt”.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: You see, one can with modern-day technology exclude certain people if you
                    have, for example, forensic evidence like DNA profiles. In earlier days it was
                    only blood tests, and a limited blood typing, but now with DNA and more
                    sophisticated skin tissue type testing - one can eliminate certain people or one
                    can implicate others, because if a person has raped a woman or murdered a person
                    there may be blood or human bodily fluids that could lead to the identification
                    of the perpetrator. In that way one can eliminate almost all other suspects.
                    There has to be some scientific evidence, and it should not be based on
                    confessions, or on evidence from persons who could have a motive to implicate
                    the suspect. Scientific evidence can eliminate all other possible suspects. The
                    death penalty should not be abolished, but it should be imposed only in rare
                    circumstances where there is water-tight evidence.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We have gone a long distance in a very short time, we had
                        you as a clerk, and in the social welfare department, and then you later -
                        after many years of study- you acquired a doctorate in constitutional law
                        and criminology. Now, always in the Cape?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Mainly in the Cape, although, while studying at UNISA for a period of 23
                    years, I also studied at other institutions, and took shorter courses, for
                    example, a two year course in labor relations at the Institute of Labor
                    Relations. I also took a course in Business Management at the University of
                    Stellenbosch, as well as a course in Criminology at the University of Cape
                    Town.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You are a professional student, in addition to the many
                        other things, study is apparently a passion?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Well, I believe in the principal of life-long learning, and that one
                    never reaches a point where you could have learned everything you need or wish
                    to know. Life changes so quickly and what you have learned during your
                    university days has changed and adapted to changing circumstances and practices.
                    If you are a lawyer, medical doctor or an engineer, that which you have learned
                    at a university in the earlier years has changed dramatically within 20 to 30
                    years. Unless you stay up to date, and you keep abreast of changes, and
                    technological advances - you will remain mediocre or even stagnate. And I mean
                    Einstein and so many people have said that you use just a little part of your
                    brain's capacity, and we reach a point that we feel that once we have a degree,
                    once we have studied then we are finished and we can go to work. I believe that
                    once you have completed you degree is actually the beginning of your education -
                    because then you will find out so much more of the little that you already know.
                    It does not have to be formal; it just means you have to increase your knowledge
                    and your skills base as you go through life.Q: As you have done, in shifting so
                    many things - you are professional. You are now Director of Environmental
                    Compliance and Enforcement - does that deal with Criminal or Civil law?</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>PALMER: After the nine years of working as a clerk had it advantages because it
                    wasn't mentally taxing or stressful - I had evenings free to study. It was
                    during that time that I completed about three degrees. After that because of my
                    legal qualifications I was transferred to the Department of Justice to become a
                    public prosecutor. I worked as a public prosecutor for four years before I was
                    identified as to become the first colored magistrate in South Africa along with
                    Pamela Sickle in 1984. I stayed as a magistrate for a year, and the reason being
                    that it was a tumultuous political period in the Cape in 1984 when public
                    violence and political violence was mostly confined to black townships. But in
                    1984 - it extended to colored townships as well. That then embroiled people I
                    lived with daily, and as a magistrate of course you were requested to preside
                    over political trials of students who were protesting. And when I realized that
                    I had no choice as a magistrate to preside over those trials people who had
                    similar political views as I had I resigned from the bench. I resigned into
                    unemployment, but immediately thereafter I was recruited by a law firm, and then
                    decided to complete my articles, and, as such, I spent two years at the law
                    firm. During this period I spent a lot of time defending the very students I was
                    expected to punish and sentence. I defended a lot of young school students who
                    were drawn into this whole sense of 'freedom was close by' and that education
                    should come after liberation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your opinion of that notion about liberation then
                        education?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Well, it sounds nice, but it is a short term goal, which could have long
                    term negative consequences, because once you have liberation you must have
                    education to manage that new found responsibility. And if you are not
                    educationally ready then even though you are free politically, economically you
                    are not free. Because you will remain an 'underdog' and will only be able to do
                    menial tasks. And those who had the opportunity to educate themselves would
                    retain economic and employment positions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were asked to be a prosecutor and a magistrate, but
                        it was implied that you needed to prosecute people accused of violence, but
                        they shared the same political views as you, therefore you resigned to
                        rather become a defendant?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, remember this is South African law in the “apartheid” era, and at
                    that stage had a legal principal for a common purpose for it had a specific
                    interpretation. The common purpose doctrine means that if a group of say a
                    hundred people, or part of that group committed an act of violence, then anyone
                    associated with that group, by their mere geographical location could then be
                    found guilty on the basis of common purpose, as they are presumed to have
                    associated themselves with the act of violence. Especially young students in big
                    groups were charged, because often when the police arrived at the scene the
                    actual perpetrators would be long gone, because they stand the greatest danger
                    of being arrested. So the police, not wanting to leave empty handed would arrest
                    those persons close-by who they felt associated themselves with the group,
                    whether they were by-standers or on-lookers or maybe they associated themselves
                    with the event. Drawn into these events were many students who would have their
                    career severely impeded if they were to go to prison because the only sentence
                    they could get was imprisonment. Boys and girls of 16-18 years, who were in the
                    beginning stages of their career and life, this would be significantly severe
                    for them. I must mention that most of the cases they would be charged would
                    prevent them from remaining in school. The majority in the judiciary had a very
                    firm policy that those children who got involved in what seemed to be acts of
                    violence should take the consequences. Many of them went to jail for a year or
                    two.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The system had many paradoxes and contradictions, so the
                        principal of common purpose has to do with geographic location? The people
                        were obliged to be there, they had no choice but to be there, if they
                        violated various acts. So the system almost didn't permit the person to be
                        innocent ever?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: To give you a very simple example, there could be tyres burning in the
                    road in front of your house, you could come out to have a closer look and to see
                    what was happening, and it could be viewed that you associated yourself with the
                    act. Because it is not about your mental intention, it's about you being
                    physically present when something wrong is happening. It was freely used as a
                    way of making examples of people whose only crime it was to be present when an
                    offence was being committed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is not a perverse version of the legal system?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: I think it is a rational legal doctrine that comes from the Roman- Dutch
                    law, and if properly used could have a just outcome, but it's also open to
                    abuse. So you can extend the ambit of the doctrine, whereas the doctrine says
                    you should be in very close in proximity, the court could say 'well, close could
                    mean 20 meters away', so depending on the views of the judge and the prosecutor
                    they could give it the necessary weight that would make them get the conviction
                    they wish for.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>There were some judges that would not use it, such as Judge Didcott of
                    KwaZulu-Natal, and there were other judges that used it depending on their own
                    political feeling.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So seeing that with you legal experience, you preferred
                        not to be a part of it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, I made a decision of conscience in that I was not going to be making
                    to any contributions to society. I would not put those people into prison. I am
                    not saying that by defending them, I would be justifying any criminal actions.
                    What I did feel was that these young people got swept up in this sense of
                    freedom being around the corner, and to show the government that there were
                    other ways of dealing with them. If, of course, they committed serious criminal
                    acts like murder, arson, assault, etc, then the law must take its course. Most
                    of them were swept up due to their adolescence, and their lack of knowledge and
                    understanding of consequences.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You implied that people got sucked up to the sense of
                        imminent change. Many people in the 1980s could not predict that there would
                        be, in fact that the changes from 1990. It was said in the 90s that it was
                        difficult to predict any of this. Your sense is that the youth - there was
                        something intangible feeling, that something really was imminently
                        changing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, because remember that in the colored community this type of
                    resistance was not prevalent at that stage. It was mostly in the African
                    townships. In the mid and late 80s they became prevalent in the colored
                    townships, and the sense that people got was that the un-governability of the
                    country was weakening the government's resolve. The government may decide that
                    'okay let's close up this African township and not allow the violence to
                    spread'. Colored townships were a little bit different, they were closer to the
                    main centers, and the white communities, and they were closer to the country's
                    resources were. So it was a bit different when other groups got involved in the
                    struggle for liberation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So in the 1980's you went to the US?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Well, after I resigned from the bench as magistrate, I went into private
                    practice as an attorney, and it was then that Frank Sassman contacted me and
                    said that they were going to nominate me to go to the USA on an OCA scholarship.
                    I had one interview which was unsuccessful, and I had another interview, and I
                    think the chairperson was a man called Samir Qutab. I was successful after the
                    second interview. I went in November 1986 to January 1987.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you know Frank Sassman?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>PALMER: I said in my two years of private practice, I dealt a lot with students
                    who had got involved in political unrest and he was on one of the committees
                    where we tried to prevent 17-18 year old school kids from having to go to jail,
                    and to appeal these matters to the Supreme Court. Frank was on that committee,
                    and that is where I got to meet him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What committee was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: I think the committee was simply called 'Campaign to save Bradley'.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, so it was the Ed Heart committee?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, to rally around the boys' parents and I think he was around
                    seventeen at the time. He was found running away from broken school windows and
                    the police arrested him, and he was sent to a year in prison. We were rallying
                    to get support to get an appeal to have the sentence suspended.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So there was a committee formed for that particular
                        case?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: As there were many committees in the community to try and raise funds
                    public awareness around young people being imprisoned for public violence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Seeing Frank step out of his role as an employee of the US
                        government, did that make a favorable impression on you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: People I found who have worked in institutions like that, they don't only
                    make themselves available in their free time, but also access to resources that
                    we would never be able to reach. And I think one of the people that Frank
                    Sassman got us into contact with was a British Lord who was temporarily in
                    Africa. His name was Lord St. John. It was also a way of getting a member of the
                    House of Lords to issue a small statement to say that 'young students shouldn't
                    be in prison'. So he gave us access to people we wouldn't normally have access
                    to because of his employment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you met a visiting member of the House of Lords, and
                        introduced to you Frank?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>PALMER: Frank Sassman was part of a group that spread out its feelers to contact
                    influential people who would rally to our cause. Frank was not necessarily the
                    specific individual who introduced us to the Lord, but he was a part of the
                    group that was looking at influential voices. The name of the Lord was St. John,
                    but it is pronounced Sinjen. He stayed in South Africa for a few months; he is
                    now back at the House of Lords.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At this time, South Africa was not part of the common
                        wealth?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: No, they were not, but in addition to him being a member of the House of
                    Lords, he was also a director of Shell International which made him very
                    influential in the business sense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The government of South Africa did certainly not
                        appreciate this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: No they were unhappy with it, and I think that he was a person who spoke
                    his mind. And his view was that young people should not be in prison especially
                    when they are around 17 years old, and if it's not a very serious crime, like
                    you know in a political sense, breaking school windows. He spoke his mind, and
                    the government publicly criticized him for meddling with South African affairs.
                    But he stood by what he said, and he eventually left for Great Britain.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This adds to a story of international pressure?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, part of the international pressure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the one hand is the stick, but also the carrot of the
                        bursaries that were provided by various contributors and programs, like OCA.
                        Was there any difficulties of a political nature in the UK when you came,
                        even being here if the South Africa had been exiled ...from the common
                        wealth?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Easy for him to come here, and difficult for South
                        Africans to go there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Well, he lived here for a while; he spent his childhood here, because he
                    is a hereditary Lord which means that his grandfather was a Lord. So he grew up
                    in South Africa, and then he went over to Great Britain, and then he came back
                    as a result of being stationed here by Shell. It was during that period that we
                    got to use his expertise.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So his grandfather was here during the Boer War. So this
                        brought into contact was context where one thing leads to another, and he
                        encouraged you to apply?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: It was a nomination, he nominated me. And then I had to fill in
                    application forms.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These six weeks must have been disrupted to your
                        work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: No, what I had done then, I had just completed my two years of articles.
                    And then I got permission to get unpaid leave for that period. So it wasn't
                    disruptive to my work. I decided that when I came back I would not continue in
                    private practice, but instead lecture in law at a tertiary institution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So this was a break from private practice as you might
                        have had anyways?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Because, remember I wasn't young at that stage, I was in my late early
                    30s, I had a wife and three children.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you understand what you were getting into when you
                        became a candidate for the OCA trip, did you want this? Did you understand
                        what is was all about before going?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Well, at that stage I had never been outside of South Africa, and due to
                    my relationship with Frank and with other people who had been to the USA,
                    especially in the field of juvenile corrections, I had a yearning to visit
                    foreign countries, including America and to see what the rest of the world
                    looked like. At that time, South Africa was reasonably isolated, and we did not
                    have much foreign exposure. After that I was lucky, I got to go to the USA, on
                    two later occasions to go and study. They were not through scholarships, but
                    through employment related opportunities. I went to New Orleans in 1996 for a
                    few weeks to study legislative drafting at Tulane University. And I also went to
                    an IBA conference in San Francisco in 2001 for a week. I was a member of the
                    International Bar Association (IBA).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Focusing on the OCA trip, the point was to see America,
                        where did you get to go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: I started in Boston with a little orientation, from there to the
                    University of Nevada, in Reno, Nevada. The University of Nevada has a faculty
                    that actually specializes in teaching judges, and magistrates all over the world
                    in the art and principles of judicial sentencing. And that was what eventually
                    my masters degree and doctorate.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So that is a direct result perhaps from you're your trip
                        to the US?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, absolutely! It widened my understanding of the importance of
                    punishment and appropriate penalties. It was a unique faculty, because you don't
                    get faculties that specifically train judges and magistrates, it's usually left
                    to trial and error.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the US?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: No, all over the world. But in the US, the University of Nevada had this
                    program with some faculty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, those where the luxurious days when people had six
                        weeks, now it is three weeks I think. So did you spend a week or two in
                        Nevada?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: A week, and then we spent five days in Washington D.C., five days in New
                    York, two days in Salt Lake City in Utah, and a brief weekend visit to a farm in
                    the South. It was a southern farm, owned by a black farmer in Mississippi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Most Americans don't even get to see that much of the
                        country. And this was a mixture of professional, cultural and social. Which
                        aspects of it were most appealing to you, or was it equally appealing to
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: The University of Nevada, was the best place for giving effect to my
                    intention to pursue a doctorate in punishment and constitutional law, but the
                    visits were not only sightseeing, we visited institutions that dealt with
                    juvenile delinquents. In New York, the House of UMOJA fascinated me - and the
                    lady, which I don't think is alive now, her name was Falaka Fattah. She managed
                    the institute and what they did was, diverting young people from the criminal
                    justice system. So if they were found guilty of theft, for example, instead of
                    sending them to jail, they were sent them to the House of UMOJA and essentially
                    what they did was to teach them responsibility. They went into the poor areas,
                    and they would choose a house that was dilapidated, and they would rebuild the
                    house to make the inhabitants feet like they lived in a decent house. The
                    program included repairing and upgrading abandoned house for their own use. Then
                    they lived there and paid rent, and the money went to the institution to further
                    its program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So instead of prison terms, they did work that the
                        community would benefit from? Discipline and environment outside of
                        prisons.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>PALMER: They had to be, of course, suitable candidates, so there had to be some
                    sort of review and assessment. And once they were found to be suitable, they
                    were sent to this half-way house for about six months. Essentially they were
                    taught levels of responsibility by having to build a house, and it was extremely
                    successful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Have you seen anything of that sort before?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: No, that was the most practical manifestation of giving people the sense
                    of belonging by actually having them build houses and apartments that they could
                    eventually rent and live in and get the sense that they made some contribution
                    to society. And the level of recidivism was extremely low. I don't think anyone
                    of those who had actually been a part of the problem that built apartments and
                    lived there went back to lives of crime.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is remarkable. Was this a model that was useable at
                        all in South Africa? Theoretically or practically?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Well, aspects of it. One of the aspects was the aspect of getting
                    ownership of projects. Often you are a part of a project then you leave. And
                    there is no lifelong sustainability involved, whereas this could be a project
                    where people are given some land and are allowed to farm and own parts of the
                    land, so they can develop a sense of ownership and responsibility. A lot of the
                    principals and aspects of the program can be used in similar projects and
                    programs in South Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could there be such an establishment, and do you think it
                        should be in South Africa? Of offenders, and let's say the lesser offences.
                        Who could do this type of constructive behavior rather than being in
                        prison?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, but such programs are in its infancy in South Africa. NICRO
                    (National Institute for the Prevention of Crime and the Rehabilitation of
                    Offenders) and other organizations do have diversion programs, and now with the
                    South African Child Justice Act - which was passed 2-3 years ago. There is now a
                    formal process of which children can be diverted from the criminal justice
                    system into programs, similar to those that I saw.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fascinating, where there any other models, obviously the
                        sentencing specials that you know led to your doctorate - that's an amazing
                        story. And then your farm stay was that a weekend or a long weekend?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>PALMER: The farm stay was a little bit of relaxation and getting to meet the
                    average American family.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So this is a vast experience and you hadn't left your
                        country prior to this trip, how did this change things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: I think being exposed to a sophisticated, well developed and financially
                    strong country was crucial. Also to travel with many other people from Africa
                    and the Caribbean, because although South Africa in comparison to America is not
                    nearly as developed, in comparison to the rest of Africa it is reasonably well
                    developed. You just have to look out and see.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah, it's amazing. South Africa is really a first world
                        country in Africa, particularly this part of Cape Town. What did you gain by
                        meeting other participants from the Caribbean and other African
                        countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Well, to see how far South Africa has progressed, even without being a
                    democratic society, and how much further we have progressed from other African
                    countries, merely because there was a will, even if the will was not always
                    politically correct, to develop South Africa economically, into a stable
                    environment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So this put your own native country in a more favorable
                        light in some way than it had been previously?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, and if you look at some of the African countries, even that time
                    Sudan, Zimbabwe and Angola, they had favorable natural resources but they
                    weren't being used to develop the country in a sense of education and economic
                    development. South Africa - despite the fact that it had abhorrent political
                    policy, nevertheless developed its people, although the white elite that ruled
                    the country did not politically give people rights, but they certainly developed
                    it economically to be a model that Africa could emulate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were you accepted in the OCA group... sometimes South
                        African were considered different by the general group of people from Mali,
                        Nigeria, Senegal and Sudan as you said. Did people easily integrate you into
                        the group of an African?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>PALMER: Besides the language differences because certain African states, that
                    speak French - only speak French, and there is a language barrier there, those
                    who speak Portuguese - only speak Portuguese, and no English. The Francophone
                    and the Portuguese tend to group together, but the English speaking African
                    states were much easier to converse with, like Zimbabwe and Zambia. And they did
                    view South Africa as being a little bit of a big brother, being developed and
                    not having to go through the same pain and suffering that they did, although
                    they went through political pain too, they go through economic pain and
                    suffering, because of their poverty. Even under “apartheid” there wasn't the
                    level of poverty amongst the black that you see amongst the rest of Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They either admire you or envy you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, especially on the educational level that we had a very good school
                    system in South Africa, even under “apartheid”. The African schools certainly
                    had the 'thin edge of the wedge' in this regard, although some former colonial
                    countries had good education systems, like Zimbabwe and Zambia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did other Africans consider you privileged? Did they just
                        perceive South Africans as “monolithic giant?” Did they appreciate these
                        differences that you just mentioned.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: I don't think they understood the differences, they saw South Africans as
                    generally being economically privileged.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where there other South African in the group you where in
                        86? Sometimes more than one, usually OCA gathers 30 or 40 people at a
                        time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Not in my group. Because I certainly would have hung out with a South
                    Africa, but my friends were from Ghana, Zimbabwe and Somalia. In order to
                    prevent people from the same countries from congregating together, formal groups
                    were made up from different countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Somalia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, she was a doctor, a medical doctor. She spoke many languages,
                    Italian, English, Somalia and Arabic. Her name was Nurta Hassan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Those were they good days. When Somalia had a government,
                        not a good one, but they had a government.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>PALMER: Siad Barre was the president, and he was a dictator, but at least he kept
                    Somalia together.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, Somalia - it seemed so promising in the 80s. One
                        wonders, what might have happened with your friend?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: I often wonder what happened to her, she worked for Siad Barre, I mean
                    she was connected to that political elite. So politically she might not have
                    been in order, but she lived outside of Somalia for many years, so maybe she
                    went into exile. Her husband was a businessman, and she was a medical doctor,
                    they lived in Italy for many years, and that's also why she could speak Italian.
                    So maybe she is living elsewhere, but she gave me a book when she left - an
                    English version of the Quran. The reason why she and I became friends was
                    because we are both Muslim.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: OCA divided up in little sub-groups; she spoke English,
                        and you did too so was it possible that you were in the same sub-group?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, she was in the English group too, and then the French were in a
                    different group.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again, the theme of this study is outsmarting apartheid.
                        In what ways do you think you were able to do that? With or without the
                        exposure to the United States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: I think that the way in which I could by-pass the “apartheid” limitation
                    - was by educating and skilling myself, even though it might have been
                    window-dressing by getting blacks into to the justice system, without that
                    education and exposure we would not be able to get into the justice system, so
                    by educating ourselves and exposing ourselves to different cultures and
                    different ideas, I think that made me bypass the rigid restrictions of
                    “apartheid”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell us about what is happening with you and the country
                        since '87?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>PALMER: I think that what the government feared was that people would see that
                    people of all races could live together in the same neighborhood without killing
                    each other. And those are the things we saw, though America still has racially
                    divided communities, if you go to New York, in the suburbs for example, almost
                    all the suburbs are racially exclusive. People were not forced to live there;
                    people lived there because they wanted to or because they were forced to due to
                    economic circumstances, as opposed to South Africa - where we didn't have
                    another choice. I think South Africa has come a long way, and has gone through a
                    steep learning curve, so much so that we have almost surpassed a lot of
                    countries in its nation-building. Although the one thing you do notice when you
                    are in America - is that people do have - especially amongst blacks -
                    unhappiness over the economic lot. There is a sense that if you are American,
                    that in itself is a big plus, and a bonus in your life, the sense of being an
                    American. The Africans are starting to develop that sense of nationhood, and you
                    know, we think that these things are not going to happen over night. And when I
                    met with a Danish group one day when I was lucky to study the parliamentary
                    system in Denmark, they said that South African transformation, would take at
                    least 75 years. And I don't think they are completely wrong. I think it will
                    certainly not take 20 years, but it will be a long process. It's going to take
                    many years before South Africa becomes an equal society.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Danish government invite you to come?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: I worked at the South African Parliament; I was the Chief Legal Adviser
                    for a number of years, and as part of my work, parliament sends people to
                    different parliaments to see how they work, and to bring back some of the ideas,
                    so I went to Denmark for about a week, to study the committee system, and to see
                    which aspects of it we could introduce, cause at that time South Africa
                    parliament was now developing. And that's one of the reasons I went to New
                    Orleans as well - to study legal drafting, so we could implement some of the
                    methods and programs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Go back to Denmark for a minute - did you find a committee
                        system comparable to what you saw in Washington? You were not studying that
                        in Washington per say, but you must have had a sense?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Well, yes there is a contrast between the committee systems in the
                    American system that separates it from the European systems. And that is - that
                    in the American system the committees are very powerful, and they can make or
                    break legislation and politicians. And if you look at sub-committees that
                    interview people for senior positions, sub committees, or committees (the
                    European and especially the British system are at a much more docile level, and
                    they really look at the technical aspects of legislation. And in the American
                    system there are certain powerful committees whose power derives not from
                    Congress, but from the committees themselves.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A judge appointment will go forward and there can be
                        political distractions. Which of the two does South Africa resemble
                        more?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: The South African system is a bit of a hybrid, and certain committees
                    have developed a level of power like SCOPA (Standing Committee on Public
                    Accounts), that monitors government spending. But other committees have become
                    merely just mechanical, for examining legislation, corrections and otherwise,
                    but they don't have and any independence from parliament. So not all committees
                    have a level of independence. It also depends on the power of the minister,
                    he/she pushes through legislation, it takes a strong and independent committee
                    to withstand the ministry and properly interrogate legislation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So the executive has the greater role here?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Yes, that is true, and I think that it depends on the role and style of
                    the President. Under President Mbeki, the executive was strong and power was
                    centralized whereas the committees were weak and merely rubber stamped
                    legislation. President Mandela allowed committees to speak their minds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think in any system, the personal strength of the
                        individual who is a head of executive does affect the system. Lyndon Johnson
                        knew about committees and understood how they worked in Congress in a way
                        that other presidents did not. I think that it's a personality thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: Absolutely, it does have an effect.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is all rich information, do you have anything to add?
                        This country has come to an enormous decision as you have said. It's an
                        unrealized mission as any country I guess who's doing some good things, it's
                        not perfect.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>PALMER: Well, Also on my trip to Denmark, we met with the minister of
                    Environmental Affairs, and what we saw there was that Denmark does not have many
                    of the problems that many other countries have. Crime and poverty is low, the
                    government is stable, so they excel in the area of protecting the environment,
                    and that made me realize that at some point South Africa and other countries in
                    the world must reach a point where protecting the environment becomes 'top of
                    the agenda'. Because ultimately a good environment will lead to a good economy,
                    because if you destroy the fields - you are not going to have corn growing, and
                    if you destroy the rivers - you will not have any fish. Although environment
                    sounds a little bit fluffy and up in the air - it is also very practical. And
                    now when you see what global warming has done , you realize that it actually
                    makes you spend money on repairing things, rather than see what the climate
                    could do and then take preventive and rehabilitative measures, and use the money
                    in a wiser way. And by using the power of the sun, and the power of the water,
                    you could create jobs and energy at the same time!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the Copenhagen Conference in December 2009 - if you
                        remember there was a leaked memo and some people were saying that there is
                        no scientific basis to say that there is global warming. I believe that this
                        is only a tiny minority, and very few scientists believe that. As a person
                        deals with environmental issues yourself, is there any doubt that we are
                        seeing a climate change? Do you have an opinion of that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: There are good examples of climate change. Millions of years ago there
                    was an ice-age, and after that the world's climate changed to what it is today.
                    The question is about whether or not the activities of human beings contribute
                    to weather changes, because we moved from ice age, to a dry age and all
                    different ages. So, yes - but the questions are: are we speeding it up, and are
                    we doing so to our detriment? At the end of the day - you need to protect the
                    environment for future generations, they are going to have to be able to plant
                    on soil that is usable, and if you misuse the soil and the sea, then you might
                    as well decide not to have children, because if you have children those children
                    will suffer the consequences of whatever you do to the environment. So whether
                    or not we contribute to global warming, we should ensure that we ourselves in
                    our old days live in a world that is sustainable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is now your fulltime position, did this occur from
                        your trip to Denmark?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: No, well the seeds were planted there, but I have reached a point where I
                    have practiced law and I understand that I can perhaps use my knowledge of law
                    in the area of the environment to ensure and to regulate compliance with laws
                    that have been drafted to ensure that we have sustainable development and
                    sustainable economic policies</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where does South Africa stand on the Charter of Nations in
                        terms of self-abuse and self-correction?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: In South Africa that happens more as a result of poverty and ignorance
                    than as a result of government wanting to develop like perhaps, China - who is
                    pushing the level of development to the extent that it is going to hurt the
                    environment. Whereas in South Africa I think they do it on a much more logical
                    and rational basis. But poor people will cut down trees and fish in rivers if
                    they are hungry. Unless you can educate them, or you can try to rehabilitate the
                    land, ignorance and poverty is probably what causes a lot of the degradation of
                    the environment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you have shifted three or four times in a major way in
                        your profession. It was administration, then the penal system, then you were
                        an advocate and now an environmentalist. What is the next step for Dr.
                        Palmer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: I try not to plan far ahead, and I take life as it comes, and this
                    opportunity presented itself. I didn't look for it, it was said to me 'look
                    there is a position there as they are trying to fill' because there are not many
                    environmental lawyers around, and I said: “Well I can learn.” So I took the
                    challenge and now I am in the deep end and I enjoying it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is fantastic. This brings us up to the present
                        moment. Any other thoughts that you want to have on record?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: It is heartening to see that America - which has so much economic power,
                    and such a beautiful and vast country - is also starting, or the government is
                    starting, to reflect the American peoples' concern about the environment.
                    Because although the American government has the image of not being adequately
                    concerned about the environment. Clearly the people of America are very
                    concerned about the environment; you just have to look at how the Americans look
                    after their gardens, after lakes, rivers, hybrid cars...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My personal politics is that the subject has been
                        neglected and I think it can be said that previous executives did not assist
                        the Environmental Protection Agency, in fact, quite forcibly limited the
                        powers of EPA, whereas now some of those powers are being restored in what
                        appears to be hopeful.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>PALMER: I think the focus of the previous administration was driven a lot by what
                    happened at 9/11, it almost consumed the administration with the consequences,
                    and the causes of 9/11, that environment was not a top priority. And I think as
                    more pressure groups in America raised their voices and people all over the
                    world, probably tried to make America understand that there will be no dramatic
                    change on the protection of the environment unless America also does its
                    part.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So your perception is that the American public is actually
                        driving policy in the US?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: I think there is a greater understanding for the need for environmental
                    correctness amongst the people of America than amongst the government over the
                    past 10-15 years. That's just my perception.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fascinating, that's what we are here to discuss. Sometimes
                        the perception of a country includes certain accuracy that comes from
                        outside the country because when they are emerged in a sort of information
                        overloads, and inevitably they're biased because of constantly being swept
                        inside the Petri dish.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PALMER: One image that I left America with was the significant and strong love
                    Americans have for their country. Americans cannot be adverse to a good
                    environment, because they love their country, they love the gardens, and they
                    love their rivers that flow by, so Americans have a very strong sense of the
                    environment. And the fact that the government hasn't expressed that doesn't mean
                    that the American people themselves haven't had that strong feeling for the
                    environment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, thank you very much, you comments have been
                        great.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
