<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000599">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Correspondence of Bernette Chase Kemp and Anna Durkee
                    Kemp</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Program Foreign Service Spouse Series</p>
                <p>THE CORRESPONDENCE OF BERNETTE CHASE KEMP and ANNA DURKEE KEMP 1915 - 1925</p>
                <p>Letters edited by Janet Kemp Doell</p>
                <p>THE EARLY YEARS OF THE E.C. KEMP FAMILY - Part I - Introduction</p>
                <p>The story of my mother, Anna Smith and of her friendship with Bernette Zoe Chase,
                    later Bernette Kemp, and of her own eventual marriage to Carl Kemp and their
                    early years together in a Europe ravaged by the first World War is too
                    interesting and indeed dramatic a history to be forgotten in a generation or
                    two. For some time I have considered writing it down for my children and nieces
                    and nephews. Upon Anna Kemp's death I found a treasure trove of letters in her
                    trunk, written during the war years and up to 1923. Suddenly the old stories I
                    had heard again and again took on a new dimension, and I became determined to
                    put this story on paper, using excerpts from the letters to make the people come
                    alive once more.</p>
                <p>Now in my new life, traveling by sailboat for weeks at a time with my husband
                    Richard, I have the time to undertake such a project. Let me start with some
                    background narrative.</p>
                <p>Anna Smith, from all she told us, had a privileged and happy childhood. This in
                    spite of the fact that her mother died three weeks after she was born. She was
                    the youngest of six children one of whom, Margaret, had died as a young child.
                    Her early years were spent with her sister Mary, or May as she was called, nine
                    years her senior; her brothers Ernest, Carl and Burnell (Uncle Bun), her father
                    and her grandfather Durkee. Most of the time there was also a housekeeper and a
                    maid. Her maiden aunt, Abigail Imogene Durkee (Aunt Jean), taught school nearby
                    and she was the one that made sure everyone was being raised properly and knew
                    their P's and Q's. A St. Bernard, Tige, also played a part in her life until he
                    died in her 13th year.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>The house was large and comfortable, supported by her father's wholesale butter
                    and egg business, the A.M. Smith Company of Boston. The grounds of the Melrose
                    home were spacious, and their life was what might be called genteel. On Saturday
                    nights the clean white tablecloth was put on the table and she always remembered
                    with pleasure the look of everything clean and fresh, and the good dishes, The
                    tablecloth, incidentally, was turned over on Wednesdays. I have never understood
                    how a large family could use one white tablecloth for a whole week. I think Aunt
                    Jean's teaching must have paid off.The friends Anna made in her first years at
                    school remained so throughout their lives, even though they were separated for
                    thirty years while she traveled with her husband. Upon graduating from high
                    school she declined the opportunity to go to college as her sister had done. She
                    did however go on a long trip to Europe with May and her friend Jennie Prescott.
                    Hearing it from the other two it was a hilarious and inspiring trip, but as far
                    as Anna was concerned, plagued with homesickness and other illness as well, it
                    was a pretty grim experience which she did not want to repeat.</p>
                <p>But I am getting ahead of my story. During her high school years a gentleman
                    moved in down the street who became friendly with Grandpa Durkee. For part of
                    every year his niece, Bernette Chase, came from Florida to visit him. I don't
                    recall if she came for the summers or for longer periods of time, or if perhaps
                    they both came for parts of the year only, but, however, that was how the two
                    households became acquainted. Anna and Nettie, as she was called, became fast
                    friends. Nettie was about five years older than Anna and the latter was fifteen
                    when she first met Carl Kemp, then Nettie's suitor. The year was 1904.</p>
                <p>Carl Kemp was a young man who had a hard time finding the right slot in life. He
                    had tried various careers, including four years at sea, and eventually took up
                    osteopathy, graduating in one of the early classes at Kirksville, Missouri. He
                    married Nettie in 1909, and they had an infant daughter, Dorothy, in 1911. He
                    found he could not support his family with his meager practice. Although he
                    never finished high school, he was self-educated, and it was about this time
                    that a friend of his who had retired from the Foreign Service suggested he try
                    the exams for entry into that profession. He read extensively in preparation and
                    passed the exams. I believe he said there were only about sixteen or eighteen
                    other applicants whereas today the exams are taken by thousands.</p>
                <p>His first post was St. Pierre and Miquelon, tiny French islands off the coast of
                    Newfoundland. In the meantime little Dorothy had died in a crib accident, her
                    head having been caught when the side came down accidentally, Nettie had a hard
                    time recovering from this tragedy and suffered from depression for some time,
                    However, 1914 found Carl and Nettie, penniless but hopeful, heading for his
                    first post as vice consul. They stopped in Melrose to see Anna on their way.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>The first of the letters from which I shall quote excerpts was from Nettie to
                    Anna from St. Pierre et Miquelon. Carl had been transferred to Marseille,
                    France, and had already left when the letter was written. Nettie was pregnant
                    again and under discussion were the arrangements being made for Nettie's
                    approaching confinement. What with a war raging in Europe, Nettie was to go to
                    Melrose until after the baby arrived some six months later, and then rejoin Carl
                    as soon as they could travel. Apparently, Anna had wanted her to stay at the
                    house on Porter Street but Nettie preferred to stay elsewhere.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Sunday, June 27, 1915St. Pierre and Miquelon</p>
                <p>Anna Dear,</p>
                <p>You poor child! And I wouldn't have hurt your dear feelings for worlds, because
                    honestly I think more of your friendship than any I have outside of Carl... Carl
                    said when he left that he was sure I would be happy near you because you seemed
                    to be a husband to me anyhow. I think sometimes he is a little jealous of you,
                    which may seem ridiculous but may be quite true.</p>
                <p>Now my dear I'm more than grateful to you for all your trouble and worry about me
                    and by all means I'll go the room on Hillside Avenue and be glad to. Not that I
                    know where that is but it doesn't matter just so long as it's near you.</p>
                <p>After this letter is written I shall add the date I shall leave. I think next
                    Saturday as the packing is about all done, and it fogs all the time in July as
                    it has in June and things are not very gay. However I'm quite cheerful and
                    everyone wonders at it; but I'm so glad Carl has this glorious chance that I
                    can't find it in my heart to be as lonely as I aught. And I'm so much stronger
                    now and no nausea for a week that I feel very happy.</p>
                <p>I wonder if Carl had time to run out to see you. I hope so ...</p>
                <p>P.S. You are a dear child to want me with you but I couldn't consent to visit
                    anyone, I'm too disagreeable to be anyone's guest what with too great a desire
                    for personal comfort, a greedy appetite and fits of sleepiness which overcome me
                    at odd times and seasons I couldn't think of visiting.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>***The next letter is dated more than a year later. In the meantime Marjorie had
                    been born on January 3, 1916 in Melrose. Anna was her Godmother, not without
                    some misgivings on her part as she was not too enthused about organized
                    religion, or any other kind either for that matter. When Marjorie was nine
                    months old Nettie packed her up and took her to Marseille. In the fall of that
                    year Carl was transferred to Tunis and there followed an active correspondence
                    between Carl and Nettie and Anna, and the first of the two bundles of letters I
                    found in Anna Kemp's trunk consists of letters from Tunis to Melrose. From these
                    yellowed pages I was able to extract several strands of narrative. There are
                    charming descriptions of Marjorie and her development, which together with other
                    expressions of concern of one kind and another attest to Nettie's warm and
                    affectionate nature. Second, there is the interesting progression in Carl's
                    expressions of affection, and the increased familiarity in his letters to Anna.
                    She had always maintained to us that she didn't know him at all before she
                    married him, having just seen him briefly two or three times. But these letters
                    show that a friendship of sorts had developed between them, however brief their
                    encounters had been.</p>
                <p>Third, there are interesting descriptions of life in Tunis, with weather being a
                    regular subject of discourse, and a declining interest in the area becoming very
                    noticeable.</p>
                <p>Finally, there is the constant talk of Anna's coming to visit them, an invitation
                    repeated enough times to become tedious and therefore was edited for the most
                    part in my quotations. In the very last letters, talk had switched to discussing
                    their return to the States, then uppermost in their minds.</p>
                <p>***Nettie's first letter from Tunis, dated October, 1916, shows great enthusiasm
                    for their new environs:</p>
                <p>... (Marjorie) is laying on the steamer rug in the garden and I am sitting by her
                    trying to write but she's so very interested in the process that it's almost
                    impossible ... I never remembered dreaming that I dwelled in marble halls but
                    this house is almost one. Lots of marble about and no extra charge. The Arab
                    messenger of the Consulate in his very gorgeous uniform sits in the hall and
                    admits callers, runs errands between times and is generally useful about the
                    house. We've an excellent cook and Emma for the baby and a sort of second girl
                    and everything runs nicely. I've an excellent appetite again and there are lots
                    of good things to eat ...</p>
                <p>The weather is wonderful, even better than Florida, and the city the most
                    fascinating I've ever seen. When we are really settled and have more time I'm
                    going to explore it thoroughly with Carl. Wonderful things to buy in Arab town
                    and I see where the money will go. In short I'm delighted with it all and the
                    winter will be very happy if we all keep well ... I do hope you'll get over to
                    see it all. This beats Europe I think ... Almost any jaded globe trotter would
                    be pleased here I should think ...</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>Letters written late in 1916 refer to Anna's surgery for an ovarian cyst, no
                    small undertaking in those days. Carl writes just before that event, commenting
                    on her failing health;</p>
                <p>Dear Anna,</p>
                <p>Nettie has probably written all the news although there is no news particularly.
                    The Arabs amuse themselves raising cain until day break on the occasion of
                    marriages and other celebrations, but that is hardly news. I find myself with
                    plenty to do but fortunately have a clerk to help me now. The weather continues
                    beautiful — why aren't you here to enjoy it? — and Marjorie is growing up all
                    the time.</p>
                <p>I shall be glad to hear of improvement in your personal health. It's slow I know,
                    having seen such cases before, but they are a long time coming on, and one can't
                    expect to cure them in a week, like a cold. You are lucky in having means to aid
                    you in your recovery. So your D.O. (Doctor of Osteopathy) is one of those “damn
                    drunken Drs.” I wonder if he belongs to the Alpha Chapter. Tell him my number is
                    108. My impression is that Drs. coming from Missouri(as I did) are perhaps a
                    trifle more disreputable than the others — better osteopaths but rougher
                    characters, especially in the earlier classes. The Bucket of Blood where Rat
                    Rodgers got knifed and the professor of surgery got a bullet through his ear and
                    where the lay reader of the Episcopal church drank his whiskey, was closed my
                    second year in school, much to the regret of the lower classes. When Nettie came
                    out there with me I used to point out the place to her and turn my head to hide
                    my emotion.</p>
                <p>To show how strong a hold one's early habits have, I have only to tell you of
                    having purchased a bottle of boukha, Arab whiskey made from rotten figs, which
                    is particularly potent — and forbidden. I have also purchased pipes and hashish
                    wherewith to ruin my soul. You must surely come over and see this interesting
                    country. The climate is beautiful now and seems like home.</p>
                <p>But I must get on the job and so will close,</p>
                <p>Most sincerely yours, ECK</p>
                <p>***A little later Carl writes again:</p>
                <p>Dear Anna,</p>
                <p>I am indeed sorry to hear of the necessity for an operation, not that I consider
                    it so much a danger as a nuisance. If it were a brain tumor or some other
                    ticklish job it would be different. I took ether once and it was an interesting
                    experience.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>I do certainly hope that circumstances will permit a trip over here at not too
                    distant a date. The change should do you good, and tho it gets hot here in the
                    middle of the summer, the rest of the year appears to be delightful. I suppose,
                    and hope, that I may be allowed to remain here for awhile, long enough to get
                    myself together ...</p>
                <p>I wish I could think up more to write about, but my ordinarily magnificent
                    intellect is not in evidence at the moment. I haven't been keeping a notebook
                    lately, or I might have something brilliant to remark.</p>
                <p>I must close, as it's bad form to write on the back of one's letter, I believe.
                    With best wishes for health and recovery, I am</p>
                <p>Most happy to be included in the “all”. [ Referring to a “love from us all” in
                    Nettie's letter.]Carl</p>
                <p>***.A couple weeks later, on December 5, both Carl and Nettie write to Anna
                    following the operation. First Nettie's:</p>
                <p>My Dearest Anna,</p>
                <p>I've been hoping we'd get another word about your progress but nothing as yet but
                    Mabel's [One of Anna's old friends from kindergarten days] note saying you were
                    out of ether... Carl is writing too sitting at the opposite side of the table in
                    baby's nursery which is more comfortably warmed than any room in the house. We
                    are having another cold spell now and a little heat goes very well. The houses
                    are all colder than the out of doors when the sun shines brightly every day. We
                    are just through dinner and Marjorie has been in bed since six. She plays so
                    hard up until the last minute that she sleeps soundly all night and awakens all
                    rosy and rested and full of “pep” as Carl says, in the morning ...</p>
                <p>... We do wish you and yours a happy Christmas with all our hearts. Marjorie is
                    going to hang up her stocking and have a tree all her very own. I wish you could
                    have seen how happy she was with her Thanksgiving turkey bone. Our two old
                    American ladies had a beautiful time, too, having been here seven and nine years
                    respectively without an American festival of any kind to break the monotony.
                    Neither had they ever met each other before and they seemed quite delighted with
                    each other.</p>
                <p>I hope May's circus will come off before Christmas so you'll all be off your
                    nervous strain and all happy together ...</p>
                <p>***The befriending of the old American ladies was typical of Carl's approach to
                    his job as Consul. In all our European posts we entertained American ladies and
                    gentlemen who either lived in that city or who were stranded in their
                    travels.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>May's “circus” to which Nettie alludes is the expected birth of twins. Now Carl's
                    letter, written at the same time, in a somewhat different vain:</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Dear Anna,</p>
                <p>Your letter received and soon after one from Mabel received saying that you had
                    survived the gas attack and everything promises all right. We all were glad to
                    hear this although I didn't worry greatly about you, knowing how accidental all
                    accidents are. Some people can't really help accidents, like a poor chap who was
                    badly run over by an engine when I was at Mansfield. They put him on a special
                    train for Boston which ran off the track. Then they put him on a regular one,
                    loaded him into an ambulance which ran into a fire truck, killing a horse and
                    breaking both legs of the driver. Such things do happen, but they are rare and
                    if everyone kept their minds on the accidents no one would get out of bed in the
                    morning for fear of stepping on a tack and having lockjaw by noon... The house
                    we inhabit promises to be a cool one, much cooler than the ones down in the
                    center of town. I must admit the sirocco is really hot but there are only two or
                    three per season and they last only two or three days. You could plan on coming
                    in October or late September and spend the winter here ...</p>
                <p>Nettie is on the other side of the lamp scratching away furiously at her own
                    letter to you. She will probably express her affection as love, or whatever you
                    call it, in her particular way. As for me, I can only say most sincerely
                    yours,(Nettie says I can send my love. Hurray! )</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>A [few] days later Nettie refers once more to the surgery:</p>
                <p>Anna Dear,</p>
                <p>Your first little note showing that you were really convalescing was received
                    this morning, and brought joy to our hearts ... I know just how hard it was for
                    you to make up your mind to it and fully realize all that it has meant to you —
                    that is, insofar as anyone can realize what things mean to other folks — I shall
                    be glad now to hear that May is safely over her troubles and that the twins are
                    arrived as by schedule ... Hope May will decide in the end to go to the hospital
                    as she seems to have good help at home, and I know how restful it is. Am glad
                    that you found it rather less disagreeable than you expected ...</p>
                <p>With a large amount of love and good wishes from us all for speedy recovery.</p>
                <p>Yours more than lovingly,Nettie</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Before Christmas Carl wrote again:</p>
                <p>Dear Anna,</p>
                <p>It is only five days to Christmas and rather late to write a Merry Xmas letter
                    but it may get to you for a Happy New Year or a Truthful Washington's Birthday.
                    Anyway it carries the best of wishes, not to put it stronger. ... My only real
                    worry is that our Uncle Sam may make a difficulty about your coming here next
                    year, but a lot may happen before then, even such a strange thing as the end of
                    the war, though I admit I can't see that yet... I think you would like our
                    winter climate here. Chilly on cold days, and the house is not really properly
                    heated for real cold weather, but today, for instance, the door is open on the
                    garden, a lot of song birds are making a fuss in the trees, the wall is purple
                    with bougainvillea flowers and Marjorie is asleep in the midst of it, the really
                    choicest blossom of the lot ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>A typical Nettie note was included in the letter:</p>
                <p>Anna dear,</p>
                <p>This morsel of filet I bought with the $1.50 I owe you. As there are now six
                    francs in the dollar you get a good deal for your money. Thus do you profit from
                    the war we all deplore — the more so that we feel it keeps you from us. Put this
                    into the center of an embroidered cushion cover, cover the cushion with pink
                    satin and put your dear head on the pillow and think sometimes of me. You'll see
                    how pretty it will all be, including the head! Loving you,</p>
                <p>Nettie</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Starting with an excerpt from one of Nettie's early letters we can get a glimpse
                    of life in the consular corps at that times:</p>
                <p>December 5, 1916</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>... I got reckless this morning and went to the best ladies' tailor in town and
                    ordered a very handsome dress, one piece with coat of same material. I shall
                    make my calls with Carl the first of January and my calling clothes are too
                    light and bright for his weather. It's colder than Florida and people dress as
                    warmly as in Boston. It seems to me more people wear furs here than in a city in
                    New England, and in April it will be hotter than Tophet so everyone says ... I
                    shall try to stay here next summer with Carl unless baby feels the heat too
                    much. It's so difficult traveling in Europe now I should prefer your coming here
                    in the fall ...</p>
                <p>... We are beginning our calls this P.M. The wife of the resident General is in
                    mourning and not receiving but we're commencing with the next in rank and going
                    down the lot. No one outside the necessary officials and the Consular Corps.
                    Otherwise we'd have 150 to make. And I'm going to make my health a reason for
                    not making the others. Although as a matter of fact I'm better than for a long
                    time and fat for me, everybody here thinks I look delicate so I'm going to work
                    it for what it's worth. All the women here are working themselves ill in
                    hospital work etc. Two young American girls have just come over to nurse in the
                    French military hospital here. Come from New York and seem very nice — not
                    trained nurses but belong to the auxiliary service and have been working in the
                    American Ambulance at Paris for ten months. They say they only have one trained
                    nurse there for every ten beds and use Auxiliaries for the real work. I imagine
                    they got tired of doing the scrubbing etc. and came down here to see if they
                    couldn't be bigger toads in a smaller puddle.</p>
                <p>Of course over here I keep my past history dark but it amuses me to keep up with
                    these amateur nurses and their troubles. [Nettie was a nurse by profession, or
                    had been.]</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>A couple of weeks after the last excerpt, Nettie continues:</p>
                <p>... We've been working away at our visits and next week will be the finish of
                    them I think. The ladies of the Consular Corps are giving tea parties each week,
                    in succession and we shall get in on that when our calls are finished. That will
                    be rather fun. I'm glad they're doing it so I can get acquainted with the bunch.
                    Meeting them casually they seem charming. The wife of the Consul de France is
                    about my age, lives very near us, speaks English perfectly and I shall doubtless
                    be chummy with her if she'll have me. Her husband also speaks English and Carl
                    likes him very much. The other Consuls are all Consuls General, being much older
                    men. The vices we have not finished calling upon yet — they will doubtless be
                    more our age. Our Consul should be a Consul General here to hold his own with
                    the rest but the Department does not yet realize the importance of the post — as
                    they will before Carl finishes firing reports at them ...</p>
                <p>Tomorrow we're going to take our two American nurses out to call on Miss Bacon,
                    our nicest old American lady ...</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>One month later:</p>
                <p>We've had quite a busy week with our colony. Miss Bacon's man servant fell down
                    stairs and broke his head, being drunk at the time. And is now in the hospital
                    suffering from a combination of D.T.'s and brain concussion. He's been in her
                    family for 24 years and as her people are all dead she feels than when he's gone
                    she will be really alone in the world ...</p>
                <p>Have just finished a piece of filet a half yard square and am trying to gather up
                    the courage to start another piece of “fond” the same size.</p>
                <p>We Americans spent last Sunday with Mrs. Ernst in her Arab villa by the sea and
                    had a perfect day. Marjorie gets out of the garden so seldom that she was
                    perfectly delighted with the trip and ran about Mrs. E.'s garden bending over to
                    sniff at the flowers by the way.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>In the meantime, Nettie was also interested in Melrose doings, especially the
                    birth of May's twins. In mid-January she wrote:</p>
                <p>...Your nice letter telling about the twins arrived a few minutes ago ... The
                    Jackson twins! That sounds odd but doubtless the ear will become quickly
                    accustomed.</p>
                <p>Later — The birth announcement received this A.M. They weighed a lot, didn't
                    they? Poor May, no wonder she felt bad ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>And a couple weeks later:</p>
                <p>... I'm longing to hear about your twin nephews ... I don't wonder Anna J. [May's
                    daughter] thought she couldn't take care of them. I suppose that by this time
                    she's more than delighted and busy with them. She has something in the family
                    that Elizabeth Small [Girl next door] hasn't, at any rate ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>And a little after that we hear the first about Anna's father's illness:</p>
                <p>... We regret very much to hear of your father's illness ...</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>And then another reference to May:</p>
                <p>... Glad to know May got home from the hospital without complications and hope
                    she has gotten strong again by this time. How I'd love to see the two little
                    boysies — love them for me hard please — hard as they'll stand at this age
                    ...</p>
                <p>... Marjorie continues to blossom as the rose. Truly she's so sweet and dear I
                    don't see how she can improve upon herself and yet she does each day. She sends
                    lots of love to Aunt Anna and so do her mother and father ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>As the spring progressed and the hot weather started we hear more about
                    Marjorie:</p>
                <p>...She doesn't suffer at all from the heat, pads about all day long in belly band
                    [Babies were thought to absolutely need bands of flannel or other soft cotton or
                    wool around their middles to prevent colic. Later on, in the event of any
                    indisposition in young children, belly bands were an important factor in their
                    cure. At least that is the way it was in the Kemp family.] and diaper — cool and
                    comfy. Then when the sun goes down she goes out watering flowers in the garden
                    with her little watering pot. Her rabbit scampers along in fear of the showers
                    she descends upon him, and our little chickens, ducks and turkeys, just hatched
                    out, come out to scratch with their mothers in the hot earth. Our roses have
                    just about stopped blooming because of the heat, but I've carnations in bloom
                    and other flowers so the garden is always petty ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>No long after this letter, before the heat really descended on them, Nettie
                    writes:</p>
                <p>... I am writing in the garden where it has been lovely all day long these last
                    few cooler days. Marjorie is very busy in the corner feeding pea pods to her
                    rabbit ... it's such a pretty bunny and they have such good times together
                    ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>As the summer approached we read more and more about the heat, along with some
                    domestic narrative. Nettie writes in mid-May:</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>... The heat has come with a rush and we have to shut up this big cool house in
                    the morning and stay in it until the sun has set. In this way we do not feel the
                    heat at all but the first few days were trying until we got used to being shut
                    up all day. Marjorie fussed to go out in the garden and we all wanted to. It
                    came all at once. Nothing gradual about it. And at the same time I let our good
                    cook depart because I couldn't stand the scrapping that went on eternally
                    between she and Emma. We were without a cook for several days and now we have
                    another almost as good if not quite. A French girl from France — the Tunisian
                    French are not at all the same thing — and she and Emma get on swimmingly both
                    being Catholics and having the same ideas on all subjects ...</p>
                <p>You needn't expect much from me for the rest of the summer. It's not that I feel
                    hot, as I pass the day comfortably enough and keep under covers at night — but
                    the heat outside has its deadly effect nevertheless and takes the life out of me
                    as it used to do in Florida. The difference being that the heat is much greater
                    here and that in Florida summers I always had a lot to do while here I've
                    nothing. So it ought to even up and will I think after I get used to it ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>A couple weeks later we learn that the change in domestic help was working out
                    well:</p>
                <p>... Happily we are better off than we were before ... I feel that our meals are
                    better prepared, even though they are not so attractive to the eye. Carl accuses
                    me of regretting Louise, and I do in some ways, but I think I realize the house
                    is better off without her. She was so much smarter than I am ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Things were not all bad, however:</p>
                <p>... There's a very attractive open air cinema here where we go for distraction
                    when life gets too awfully monotonous. Also, incidentally, one gets cooled off
                    there to the point of needing a fur, which seems impossible when we leave the
                    house ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>And a month later:</p>
                <p>... Going to hear Carmen tonight but unfortunately it's not Geraldine who sings
                    it. Heard Faust last week. Not badly done either — over here they catch the
                    singers before they get old or fat and it's much more romantic, if not as well
                    sung.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Later — Carmen very well sung only the tenor is very tired after three weeks of
                    every other night singing in this heat, and he shows it in voice and manner.
                    Season is over now and we'll settle down to cinema twice a week ... Our little
                    colony here are beginning to make surgical supplies for the American Red Cross
                    in Paris getting ready for our boys. I hate to think of such things being needed
                    but I suppose it's inevitable ...</p>
                <p>However:</p>
                <p>... All of our friends have gone out of town for the summer and have settled down
                    to what will no doubt be a very monotonous summer, but comfortable enough the
                    way we live ... Baby looks even better than in the winter ... She talks a lot —
                    English, French, and Arab — and it's such fun to hear her ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Mind you, this tri-lingual child was only one and a half. With the above was
                    included a poem which Nettie sent to Anna and which I found as applicable to the
                    ladies in our society in 1984 as in 1917.</p>
                <p>Reference was also made in Nettie's spring and summer letters to goings in
                    Melrose. A couple times she refers to Anna's father being ill. In one she
                    writes:</p>
                <p>... I am glad you have a “flivver” [Refers to a sports car] and hope you'll get
                    out in it a lot. It will do you heeps of good. I always knew Bun was a nice
                    brother and now I'm sure of it.</p>
                <p>Glad to hear the Jacksons are going on nicely. I do want to see those twins most
                    awfully. Does Brother [A family name for Willard Jackson, older brother to the
                    twins. His nickname eventually became “Brud”] love me just the same? ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Not infrequently, concern was expressed about Anna's overdoing:</p>
                <p>... A short note received yesterday told of your housekeeper's leaving and of
                    your commencing again with a new maid. I do hope you won't overdo. It would be
                    much better that all the family should take their meals out than that you should
                    do that ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>The danger of Anna overdoing was always with us. She finally did “overdo” in 1937
                    and sort of fell apart at the seams in what was then called a nervous breakdown;
                    perhaps still is. So it wasn't an empty threat.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>Before we get into Nettie's letters of the fall and winter of 1917, let's see how
                    Carl is progressing in his expressions of affection. In March he wrote:</p>
                <p>... The winter climate here is neither cold nor hot — just that bleak, chilly,
                    rainy kind that stirs up all my profanity.</p>
                <p>I'm glad you found the Vie Parisienne [A magazine he apparently sent to liven up
                    her life] interesting ...</p>
                <p>By the time you get this I suppose war will be declared against Germany. Will the
                    Campfire Girls come here if we do? [It always seemed incongruous that Anna had
                    been a Campfire Girl, but she was.]</p>
                <p>I'm glad you like the snaps of the baby. It is fun taking them and getting more
                    so as she develops. She certainly is a live wire which she doesn't get from
                    either of her parents. ... If Nettie were here she would want to send her love,
                    but as she isn't I'm compelled to send mine.ECK</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>In summer he wrote:</p>
                <p>... Just now we are experiencing the Sirocco season which Nettie suffers from
                    more than I. It is like a very hot day down on Washington Street and much more
                    difficult to bear than the heat in Florida.</p>
                <p>On the 14th — big day — [Bastille Day, a French national holiday] I attended a
                    military review, and wore the unique combination of a morning coat and cork
                    helmet. I was decorated, by the way, and by the Bey, as grand officer of the
                    Nichen Iftik'har, but as I am forbidden to wear it have notified the Department
                    and am waiting to hear what they want me to do about it.</p>
                <p>It is now the month of Ramadan, and all the Arabs go hungry and thirsty from
                    sunup to sundown. It is over Friday and I have to dress up in evening clothes
                    and go to a reception at 11A.M ....</p>
                <p>As I am telling Nettie continually of my devoted affection for you why shouldn't
                    I sign myself</p>
                <p>With love,Carl</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>The end of August bought some respite from the heat apparently, and Nettie writes
                    her first letter in a couple months:</p>
                <p>... The worst of the heat is over, at least I feel that it is and I have rarely
                    been more thankful for anything ... there's just about enough of me to make a
                    grease spot of and not a very large one either. Just thank goodness it's over,
                    or most of it, and we can begin to live again ...</p>
                <p>The Arabs from all over North Africa are now gathering here for the annual
                    pilgrimage to Mecca. As every tribe and district has its own costume, the
                    variety of gay and beautiful colors and stuffs made into the flowing garments
                    one sees in the course of a promenade is very interesting. Many of them are very
                    handsome men and walk with a swinging graceful carriage that comes, no doubt, of
                    generations of bootless ancestors and long marches in the desert.</p>
                <p>I can understand the fascination these men have for many American women tourists;
                    but I shan't go so far as some of them have. My racial instincts are too strong,
                    and after all they are not white men. The handsomest are only mulattoes. But
                    enough of Arabs for this time. I wonder what you'll think of them when you come
                    over. I shall keep a very sharp eye on you knowing your preference for harem
                    life. ... [Anna's search for an eligible Maharajah was sort of a family joke.
                    Quite an old one as it turns out.]</p>
                <p>And a little social life to add interest too:</p>
                <p>... I don't believe I've written you since the dinner at the Governor's summer
                    residence. Twelve covers and very delightful people. Carl suffered with the heat
                    because his dinner coat is too hot for African summers, but I was comfy and
                    enjoyed myself immensely ...</p>
                <p>But in the fall, a year after arriving there, some of the charm seems to be
                    waning:</p>
                <p>...We have just had a few minutes of rainfall, our first in 135 days. Except for
                    the gardens, which are few and far between, the city is as dry and parched as
                    the desert. Our water supply comes from a mountain distantly visible and the
                    heat has been so great and no rain for so long that they have been obliged to
                    shut off the water every night at seven for weeks, turning it on in the morning
                    before we are up. Ahmed waters the garden every morning and our rosebushes are
                    full of buds, so we shall have some flowers soon. All summer long we have had
                    none, and I wondered how the plants and trees kept alive in the blistering heat.
                    We had to put my ferns out at night and take them in before the sun was hot in
                    the mornings because the house was so dark all day they were dying for want of
                    light — and one day the maiden hair was forgotten and was out all day in the
                    Sirocco — late that afternoon I found it burnt and shriveled and quite dead, and
                    no wonder.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>As the fall of 1917 progresses we hear more and more about going home. From
                    Nettie:</p>
                <p>...We are still hoping to see the war end this winter so we can get home next
                    summer — that would help Carl more than anything I think — and I do want Mother
                    to see Marjorie. But at any rate we shall go as far as France and up into Savoy
                    to get some milk and cream that I hanker for and let Marjorie see what real life
                    is like ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>And a little later:</p>
                <p>... We have just heard that consuls and their families can travel on our
                    returning transports at a very low rate, almost nothing at all. But Carl says he
                    won't ask for leave while the war in on, as it's unpatriotic — and Nettie says
                    she won't make the trip alone again so we are no better off than if there were
                    no nice big comfy transports going back empty. Such is life in the service
                    ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>In the meantime Marjorie is growing in wisdom and stature:</p>
                <p>... Marjorie is making great progress in French. Chatters all the time and very
                    good French too. When we go home next year we shall have to speak French to her
                    so she won't forget it. She doesn't talk baby talk at all and says everything
                    correctly and entirely. Her nurse is a good stickler for that and insists that
                    she speak properly if at all. She talks to Marjorie as though she were a young
                    lady of eighteen and Marjie plays up to what is expected of her...</p>
                <p>... She has cut a stomach and an eye tooth this week and has taken matters into
                    her own hands; refuses her baby diet and demands vegetables and plenty of them.
                    She's very grown up indeed and is twenty months. I an enclosing a print —
                    haven't been able to make any myself lately because the sun is too hot and melts
                    the film — some sun! ...</p>
                <p>... I asked Marjorie just now if she wanted to send “un gros baiser” [A large
                    kiss] to Aunt Anna and she gave one immediately and said “Oui, Mamma.” And took
                    me by the hand and pulled violently wanting to tart off at once to see you. And
                    I told her that I should like nothing better but that it was too far to go
                    today. Malheureusement. [Unfortunately] Why must good friends be so far
                    separated when there are so few in the world? ...</p>
                <p>Marjorie is beginning to need a brother now to take her mind off herself, but I
                    don't feel able to have one in Tunis. The climate isn't good enough and all the
                    doctors are mobilized and there never were any nurses; not as we know them
                    ...</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>... (Marjorie) has had a spell of growing and is now a little girl. Decidedly I
                    have no baby any longer. She still sucks two middle fingers of her right hand
                    when she's tired and Carl won't let me do anything, about it until she gets her
                    teeth. But that's the only bad habit she has. She graduated into cunning little
                    panties the first of the summer and Emma has made her the daintiest little
                    chemises to wear under her little corset waist. She talks all day long in French
                    and Emma doesn't allow any baby talk either. I am beginning now to insist on
                    English when she is alone with me. I haven't wanted to bother her while she was
                    getting her French so easily, but now she knows so much there's no reason why
                    she shouldn't slow up a little ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>A little later that fall:</p>
                <p>... I am delighted to hear such good news from the twins; how I should love to
                    see them and you, and see Marjorie play with them! She'd love them to death! She
                    loves the photo of Anna and Brother [Anne and Willard Jackson] in the wall in my
                    room and kisses it and talks to them in French. The poor child needs children to
                    play with but among our very slight and limited acquaintance there is only one
                    child of her age and she is very weak and often ill so that Marjorie can see her
                    but seldom... It is a distinct effort for her to speak English but we are
                    insisting a little more every day and it's coming easier now. She seems to
                    understand that everything has two names and uses them interchangeably ...</p>
                <p>... Marjorie is so interested in life now that she keeps all of us busy answering
                    questions. Her Christmas tree will delight her soul this year, and I can't wait
                    to get it ready for her. For a time she was dead set against speaking English
                    and would close her eyes and shake her yellow head and say, “Non, veux pas dire
                    ca.” [No, don't want to say that.] You will admit that was discouraging, but now
                    she speaks English often and without so much effort so we have hopes for the
                    future ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Now let's leave Marjorie for a while and see what has been going on in Melrose
                    that Nettie was commenting on. There is a reference to Anna wearing overalls
                    which seems a bit out of character (for Anna, that is):</p>
                <p>... In view of the nationwide popularity of the overall at present it seems to me
                    that you should have some public recognition of your services to female humanity
                    in having introduced this costume. I really doubt whether it will ever be given
                    up. If you wish, I will get Carl to write you up for a “Sunday Edition”
                    illustrated with a photo on the general plan of the enclosed (enclosure missing)
                    ...</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>By the very simple expedient of examining the boxes in which the tubes of
                    toothpaste were packed I discovered about what I owe you and am now looking for
                    something I think you'll like for the price. How would you like a filet
                    brassiere, or would you rather have an embroidered cushion with filet inserts?
                    ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Later: “Glad you like the idea of a filet brassiere and I shall look one up right
                    away.”</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>On the Melrose front, Grandpa Durkee was taken ill:</p>
                <p>My dearest Anna,</p>
                <p>I have been paralyzed in my letter writing centers for some weeks now and am
                    doubly sorry to have been so neglectful when Grandpa Durkee was so ill. ... He
                    is a wonderful old man and has so much enjoyed being active that it would be a
                    great cross to him to be long in bed ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Grandpa died shortly after that was written; around the beginning of October:</p>
                <p>... Mail is at last arrived bringing your little note about Grandpa. What a dear
                    child you were to write when you were so tired, but you must not try your
                    strength like that. You know how much I regret it all for you and yours ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Before getting into the letters written during the winter of 1917-18, it is time
                    to review Carl's Fall correspondence:</p>
                <p>Dear Anna,</p>
                <p>I told Nettie I was going to write you a very affectionate letter, which I hope
                    will not prove too much for you. I shall try and not make it too awful soft.</p>
                <p>The idea was raised in my mind by the wonder if you knew just how much you and
                    the New England, which you are the living spirit of, meant to both of us. After
                    a long hot summer which leaves us living in a dry and parched land, our minds
                    revert to dreams of apple orchards, blueberry pastures, Melrose, and you as
                    queen of the domain. If the war should end before we do, we hope to see all this
                    in reality once more.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>Since the 13th the weather has really been quite perfect, with the effect on me
                    personally of making me sleepy as after a long nervous strain. After having been
                    dragged through a knot hole one desires repose in which to regain one's natural
                    shape ...</p>
                <p>The last few days have been marked by the bleating of numerous sheep, brought
                    into town for the annual sacrifice and feast of the Id al-Fitr which occurred
                    yesterday. At the same time I had to dress up in my evening clothes again at 10
                    a.m. and visit the Bey at the Bordo Palace. My decoration, a silver star as big
                    as a saucer, which was presented to me on July 14th, has to be turned in to the
                    Department which I am busy doing today. Next year they will all wonder where it
                    is — and I shall have to spend a stupid time giving one explanations which they
                    won't at all understand ...</p>
                <p>Life here is not very exciting and subjects to write about consequently rare. I
                    am holding my description of the country until you can come and see it for
                    yourself some day. And I don't want to overdo the affection for fear you might
                    misunderstand or grow tired of it. Perhaps you are already, in which case,
                    therefore, there is no hope.</p>
                <p>Nettie and the baby send their love. Perhaps I do too.</p>
                <p>Affectionately, of course,ECK</p>
                <p>And a couple months later:</p>
                <p>Dear Anna,</p>
                <p>This is just to add a line to Nettie's note to tell you that my boundless
                    affection continues in spite of all reports of “tubbiness” — which says a great
                    deal.</p>
                <p>I am really delighted to hear of your continued better health and hope you will
                    take every precaution to preserve it ...</p>
                <p>As I have already expressed my affection, you may think I do not mean it if I
                    mention it again, so will close</p>
                <p>Simply,Edwin C. Kemp</p>
                <p>Carl's December letter refers to the death of Anna's father:</p>
                <p>... We were indeed grieved to learn of your father's passing away and there is, I
                    hope, little need for words in expressing our sympathy. Words are, as we both
                    know, of little value at such times...</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>I wish you could see (Marjorie). You would be proud of your work ...</p>
                <p>I am glad if my “affectionate” letter was of any use. I stand always ready to
                    fill up any small gaps of affection which Nettie may leave. As I have to keep
                    her posted, I do not think you need worry until she makes warning signals. Most
                    sincerely, Carl</p>
                <p>Nettie wrote the same day:</p>
                <p>... My dear my dear, what can I say to you? Carl has just brought up your letter
                    written from Brandon. I feel too badly myself to be able to comfort you. I do
                    wish I could fly to you and I should if the sea were not so unsafe.</p>
                <p>I do hope Ernest will live at home. He will fill the house with his big wholesome
                    self and he's good for you.</p>
                <p>What a hard winter it has been for you all. It seems to me now that that is why I
                    felt so bad when I left you because I had a presentiment of all that might
                    happen before I saw you again. I don't immagine you have any idea how dear you
                    are to me, you and yours. If I may only be allowed some day a chance to show
                    you, it's all I ask ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Not long after, Nettie writes again:</p>
                <p>My dearest Anna,</p>
                <p>We had a letter from you yesterday. It sounded as if you were very brave. Too
                    much so I fear. How hard Thanksgiving must have been. I had thought of it and
                    had hoped you would all go away somewhere for the day ... How I wish you could
                    come straight to us for as long as you were happy to stay. Carl and I have a lot
                    laid up against the Kaiser because he has kept us so long apart ... Please don't
                    sell quite all the cows! If you knew how I long for some Smith's milk. The milk
                    here is absolutely undrinkable and we don't have it in the house, using only
                    Nestle's canned for the baby and cooking. It's getting harder all the time to
                    get things we want but so far the necessaries are all forthcoming ... Compared
                    with life in Europe we are in clover as this is a farming country ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Summer's heat forgotten, they now had to contend with the cold:</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>... We are frozen half the time with wood fires going all over the house, but we
                    are all of us much better for the cold; I realize that, only if anyone tries to
                    tell you about the beautiful climate of Tunis and Algeria don't you listen ...
                    We are all spending New Year's day with Mrs. Ernst and are praying for a nice
                    day as she lives in an old Arab palace on the edge of a cliff overlooking the
                    sea and we are likely to be frozen stiff if the wind blows. Marjorie is out for
                    her afternoon walk in her ermine furs looking very luxurious and warm ...
                    Marjorie has just come in with pink cheeks and kissed the letter for “Poor Aunt
                    Anna.” She knows and loves you quite well In spite of her age when she last saw
                    you ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>The day at Mrs. Ernst's villa was well spent because:</p>
                <p>... We have rented Mrs. Ernst's villa for next summer so I don't have to worry
                    about the heat here in town. The nights are so cool there by the sea that she
                    sleeps under a blanket all summer so you know I won't have to walk the floor
                    nights as I did last summer. It's a big old Arab palace of thirteen rooms so we
                    can spread ourselves out and keep cool ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>There was some social life that winter:</p>
                <p>... Carl has joined the most select club in town and spends an occasional hour
                    there before dinner. I am glad because he needed new friends and didn't seem to
                    know it. Our colony of two old ladies is rather tiresome at times and we get to
                    feel as old as they are ...</p>
                <p>However:</p>
                <p>... We have had quite a gay week — so far. Saturday evening Miss Bacon had a
                    dinner party for all the colony with hand painted place cards and menus — very
                    well done indeed. Sunday p.m. we went to a tea given at the residence of the
                    Governor General. About three hundred people present. A fine concert with tea
                    served in l'entre act. I was very much interested to see how it was all done
                    ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Christmas was apparently a success, and introduces another section on Marjorie's
                    development:</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>... We had a very nice Christmas — We had the colony in to Marjie's tree as last
                    year and we had high tea while the candles were burning. Marjie had a beautiful
                    time as did we all I think. She behaved as though she were used to having
                    Christmas trees every day but her eyes danced with joy. Everyone remarked on her
                    self-possession and her excellent behavior. Emma is certainly bringing her up in
                    the way she should go. I should never succeed in having her nearly as well
                    behaved. She's not afraid of anything in heaven or on earth, but when Emma
                    speaks she obeys. I know I spoil her but “Que voulez-vous?” She's the only
                    little girl I have.</p>
                <p>I'm beginning now to want 'Brother' but Carl won't let me have him here and yet
                    if the war keeps on two or three more years there will be too much difference in
                    their ages. I am very well now and if it were not for next summer, from which we
                    cannot escape on account of those villainous submarines I would be tempted to
                    try it ...</p>
                <p>... I wish you could walk in now and see Marjorie busy serving tea in her brand
                    new tea set spread on a little table just the right height and she makes a very
                    sweet picture. She is waiting for a little friend, the daughter of the Belgian
                    Vice, to come. This little girl is just Marjorie's age, eight days older.</p>
                <p>Marjorie is the most fascinating thing I ever saw. Her imagination is working at
                    a great rate now and she burned her hand very badly putting one of her sand
                    cakes into her imaginary oven. She came running to tell me about it and have it
                    kissed and of course I laughed and hugged her tightly ...</p>
                <p>... Marjorie is absolutely the sweetest thing that ever happened... Carl loves
                    her most to death and lets her go into the office and mix things up in his
                    pockets in a way that would never be permitted to anyone else. She has an
                    especially sweet little note in her voice when she calls “Papa”...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Speaking of whom, what kind of letters has he been writing? At the end of the
                    year he opens his letter with:</p>
                <p>Dearest Anna,</p>
                <p>Don't be startled by the adjective. As the only other Anna know is my
                    step-grandmother, it is literally correct.</p>
                <p>Your last letter received quite cheers us up with prospects of
                    nursery-governesses etc. If it were not for the Kaiser, the cause of most of our
                    troubles these days, we would suggest your coming over this spring, but as it
                    is, I cannot recommend foreign travel either for comfort, or safety ...</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>By February of 1918 life in Tunis seems to have lost its enchantment for him:</p>
                <p>... There really isn't anything phenomenal to write about except perhaps on the
                    subject of my, and our affection. The climate certainly is not a fit subject for
                    conversation just at this time. Marjorie grows in size and intelligence but
                    retains her sweet disposition. We read the war news, which is not very exciting,
                    and call on our Colony at regular intervals, which is no more so. We are simply
                    marking time until the warm weather comes, when it will probably be too warm and
                    there will be nothing to do but mark time until the weather gets cool again. You
                    will probably think I am bored which is perhaps true, but still I am better off
                    here than anywhere else I can think of, so I am not kicking at all ...</p>
                <p>With love from us both,Carl</p>
                <p>Two of the last letters from Carl to Anna were written in April and May of 1918.
                    The first one refers to a fine or duty which Anna had to pay on one of their
                    gifts:</p>
                <p>... Your letter to Nettie came in on the last mail and I am very glad to see that
                    you are more rested from the weariness of sorrow, and settling down again to a
                    daily routine of cow, pig and horse.</p>
                <p>I'm sorry to learn of your “fine” but am very glad you let us know so we will not
                    get any more of our friends in bad. Rules evidently differ at different offices,
                    as some of our presents, although opened, were handed over without protest. I
                    should say practice rather than rules for of course the rule is the same for all
                    p.o.'s — and perhaps the soldiers in France are rather overdoing the lace
                    presents to home folks. The lace people here say they cannot get orders filled
                    because the Americans in France are buying it up so fast.</p>
                <p>I am glad the rule does not extend to the Vie Parisienne which I shall try to
                    send you from time to time ...</p>
                <p>I wish Nettie could go over and spend a while in Melrose with you, as long as you
                    have elected to be “Anna sit by the fire” instead of a globe trotter. Perhaps I
                    should like to come and sit there for a while too, but my restless disposition
                    would not let me stay too long....</p>
                <p>With unquenchable affection,Carl</p>
                <p>The second seems to indicate a lapse in correspondence from Anna:</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>... We both want to hear from you, as you, almost more than anyone else, mean
                    “home” to us. Now that spring rains bring out leafy smells from the garden that
                    remind us of June and syringia in Melrose, certain poignant sensations stir
                    within us, which may be nostalgia, if not neuralgia ...</p>
                <p>The baby and I are as thriving as we ever were. The latter individual is looking
                    for his letter though, and closes to lay at your feet the choicest bouquet of
                    affection,Carl</p>
                <p>Nettie continues to take Carl's affection for Anna in what was doubtless the
                    right way. She closes a letter to Anna with:</p>
                <p>... with all my love, and naturally I don't like to add all of Carl's, but you
                    are welcome to half — I always was generous you know, but seriously I don't know
                    of anyone we both love so much ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Carl's final letter, written imid-July, shows that their summer residence on the
                    sea has made the summer more bearable, and hints at a reluctance on the part of
                    Anna to continue their correspondence:</p>
                <p>Dear Anna,</p>
                <p>I had just brought the enclosed letter from Nettie down to the office to mail
                    when your welcome letter with the snapshots arrived ... I do not remember ever
                    having seen a picture of your brothers before... The Smith nose seems to be in
                    the same class with the Kempand Chase varieties. I do not believe that noses,
                    like philosophers and hard cider, have been sufficiently noticed as a
                    characteristically New England production.</p>
                <p>Tunis has been viciously hot recently, 113 degrees day before yesterday, and we
                    are delighted to be able to escape it at Sidi Bou Said. The Arab house is
                    delightfully cool, even at noonday. I go out at noon and remain the rest of the
                    day, as the work at the office is not particularly heavy just at present.</p>
                <p>Tomorrow morning I have to come in early and attend a military review. It is the
                    14th and a repetition of our 4th, which was celebrated here as a national
                    holiday and as enthusiastically as their own. I enclose some photos of the
                    ceremony, which included a short speech by me — my first attempt at public
                    utterance in French.</p>
                <p>You — and Nettie — need have no worry about the corruption of my morals. Even the
                    corruption has turned to dust and been blown away, and unlimited Vie Parisiennes
                    can have no effect whatever. That is perhaps why I send them to you — I do not
                    realize the terrible harm they could do. Shall I send some more?</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>I appreciate your difficulty in writing to me, and therefore appreciate it the
                    more when you do write. I too have my difficulties, for if you feel that perhaps
                    you hadn't aught to, I have to be careful that I do not give you any reason for
                    being sure you hadn't aught to. Nettie says she doesn't worry, however, so you
                    shouldn't. So I feel free to sign with love from all, and particularly from</p>
                <p>Carl</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Mid-February of 1918 finds Nettie with domestic troubles once again:</p>
                <p>... I have had to give Suzanne (the cook) three weeks off as she could hardly
                    stagger about the kitchen. She has an aunt in the country who takes care of her
                    after a fashion. She is very anemic and aught to go to France to work but
                    doesn't like to risk the journey. So we have been doing without, Emma doing most
                    of the cooking and serving at table, I taking care of Marjie (who has chosen
                    this time to cut her four molars) doing what cooking Emma can't, and the scrub
                    woman has been staying all of every day to do the rest. Cooks are a rare article
                    around here and that's the only reason I've been worrying along with Suzanne
                    ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Soon after that letter Nettie writes that their house has been sold and have to
                    vacate the first of June, a month before they have leased the summer villa from
                    Mrs. Ernst. Therefore:</p>
                <p>... we shall move our furniture all out there and go to a hotel for June. What we
                    shall do next fall we have not decided. Who knows if we shall be in Tunis
                    then... Personally, I'm tired of keeping house, as I get about every two years
                    anyway, and shall be glad of a few months boarding, so we shall see what we
                    shall see...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>The end of April finds Nettie suffering from homesickness, and her patience
                    becoming a little thin:</p>
                <p>... Marjorie is as full of the old Harry as usual and more so. Really, if she
                    hadn't a nurse to keep her in order we should be lost ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>The move to a bearding house in Carthage cheers Nettie up considerably:</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>... Nous voici, at Carthage, where we are most comfortable and suffer more from
                    the cold than from heat. Carl has the worst of the proposition going back and
                    forth in the heat. But he protests that he doesn't mind and I hope that it
                    doesn't tire him too much... I haven't slept so soundly for years and have a
                    Melrose appetite. You know what that means.</p>
                <p>Marjorie is eating a much more varied diet here, something she needed at home and
                    I hated to commence, for she is 2 � years old now and growing fast so she needs
                    strengthening food. I have never seen her so gloriously happy and gay as she is
                    here. It's real country and seaside combined and a lot of nice children to play
                    with on the beach... Saw in the morning paper that another transport has been
                    sunk. Glad we were not on her. Dry land seems the safest at present. But I do
                    get very impatient to go home at times... It's simply ages since we heard from
                    you ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>But by mid-August that lift has been lost, and thoughts are all on going
                    home:</p>
                <p>... Carl has asked for leave in October and if nothing happens, we shall be in
                    Florida for Christmas. I am homesick to see them all and to have some real food.
                    I shall probably stay longer than Carl can and spend the winter down there.
                    Won't you come and spend it with me? ... I believe there's a good automobile
                    road all the way down now so you can make the trip in your car if you want to.
                    If Howard [Howard Jackson, May's husband, a doctor who joined the service at
                    this time] has gone to war you can safely leave your brothers and home in May's
                    care and go on a spree with me...</p>
                <p>Carl is all tired out with the terrific heat and needs the change badly... We are
                    as comfortable here in Sidi Bou Said as it's possible to be anywhere in North
                    Africa in summer but I think it would be the death of us all three if we stayed
                    long enough... We shall return to the hotel in Carthage about September 15 and
                    await a chance to go home... We shall go on a convoyed transport from France as
                    a consul's family will be allowed to travel that way. Few, if any, other
                    passengers so we'll stand a better chance of being saved if torpedoed. I can
                    hear what you are saying just as if I were there ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>So we come to Nettie's last letter, written August 23, 1918:</p>
                <p>... We were glad to hear from you again and such a nice letter too. Sounded more
                    like your old self and quite cheered me up.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>I shall write and congratulate May on letting Howard go. It was fine of her and I
                    know he thinks so too ... No indeed, Marjorie isn't all we need. She is
                    clamoring for a brother or sister all he time and I want her to have one or
                    both. This life in foreign lands without children would not be bearable. And as
                    long as such a good nurse as Emma is procurable at $15.00 a month we can have a
                    family in peace and quietness. I shall miss Emma very much on the trip and after
                    we are home. But in some ways she would be a white elephant. Speaking no English
                    she would be very unhappy I am sure ... Your garden and your milk and cream make
                    my mouth water. I think I could drink gallons of Melrose water without stopping
                    to take a breath ...</p>
                <p>Our boys are doing finely and they are adored in France, so my friends write me.
                    They brought into the struggle the enthusiasm and young strength that was needed
                    and just at the right time. Everybody feels that it will be over soon now.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>It must have been a couple months later that Nettie and Carl and Marjorie left
                    Tunis for the States, but Nettie was never to enjoy any of the things she was so
                    looking forward to. Weakened by seasickness and pregnancy, she fell victim to
                    the flu epidemic of 1918 and died a few days after they landed in New York.</p>
                <p>There must have been a lot of discussion about what to do with Marjorie, and the
                    decision was made to send her to Florida where she had a lot of aunts, uncles,
                    and cousins. I do not know if Carl visited Anna at all during that winter of
                    1918-19. But he went on alone to his next post, Bucharest, Romania, and sent for
                    Anna to join him in the fall of 1919.</p>
                <p>The next bundle of letters are from Anna to her sister May telling of the trip
                    over and of the early years of marriage.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Part II</p>
                <p>Years ago when young consular officers were sometimes unable to return to the
                    U.S. for years at a time, the problem of finding an American wife was one of
                    considerable magnitude. Although not a requirement, such a wife was a great
                    asset in creating a home which reflected American tastes and customs. Also, the
                    children of such a marriage were more apt to grow up with some sense of national
                    identity than were those with foreign mothers.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>Carl was not a man who enjoyed living alone. He also needed a mother for
                    Marjorie. His affection for Anna, so often expressed in the letters from Tunis,
                    made her a likely choice for a marriage partner. Anna didn't save the
                    correspondence between Carl and herself in the weeks and months following
                    Nettie's death, and I do not know how much persuasion on his part it took to
                    convince her to travel to Europe to marry him. From what she told me over the
                    years I got the impression that she didn't have too much trouble deciding to go.
                    The fact that her father and grandfather had both passed away probably aided her
                    in this decision; although she had found partial fulfillment in keeping house
                    for her brothers. When I commented once that that couldn't have been much of a
                    life she replied, “Why, what better thing can one do than make a home for one's
                    menfolk?”</p>
                <p>Anne Jackson Armstrong, the oldest of May's children, told me that her earliest
                    memories are of the commotion caused by Anna's taking off alone for Europe.</p>
                <p>In a recent letter to me she wrote:</p>
                <p>My mother supported your mother strongly on this proposed marriage and trip to
                    Europe. I can still see Uncle Ernest pacing the floor telling my mother it was
                    dangerous and unwise for your mother to go. My memory tells me that Mother told
                    them not to be so fuddy-duddy about it and altogether gave your mother great
                    support so that they (your and my mother) could override the objections.It
                    really made a strong impression on me to hear my mother stand up to our
                    uncles.</p>
                <p>The only letter from Carl that Anna saved from that period was the one giving
                    traveling instructions. I have included it in its entirety to show how detailed
                    his instructions were. The other letters in this second group, with the
                    exception of one to her brother Bun, are written by Anna to her sister May. Anne
                    Armstrong remembers her mother putting all else aside when it was time to write
                    a letter to her younger sister. The devotion these two sisters had for each
                    other was deep and long lasting; lasted, indeed, until May's death at the age of
                    93.</p>
                <p>I have copied the letters that follow with very little editing, deleting only
                    small passages which were repetitious or which referred to people of no interest
                    to anyone likely to be reading this narrative. The first of these letters
                    (following the one of instructions) describes her trip across the ocean on the
                    “Patria.” She wasn't sure when she left where Carl was apt to meet her. The
                    general plan was for her to sail to Constantinople, with the outside chance that
                    he might be able to meet her in Marseille.</p>
                <p>TRAVELING DIRECTIONS</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>Apply immediately to Cooks or American Express for reservations to Marseille, on
                    Fabre Line steamer, preferably the PATRIA; the Captain Dechelle knows Mr. Gross,
                    and may remember me. Explain you are coming out to meet me, as it may help you
                    get earlier sailing. Also ask them to reserve, if possible, sailing on the
                    Romanian steamer from Marseille to Galatz, and buy your ticket clear through, if
                    they can sell it. Cooks has an office in Marseille, and they may be able to
                    handle the whole thing. If not, buy to Marseille only. Do not let them sell you
                    sailings to Trieste, or train to Paris.</p>
                <p>Upon assurance of sailing, telegraph as follows: AMERICAN CONSUL MARSEILLE NOTIFY
                    KEMP SAILING (month,date) SMITH. STEAMER (name) DUE MARSEILLE (month, date)
                    SMITH. Also AMERICAN CONSUL PARIS NOTIGY KEMP CONSUL BUCHAREST DUE MARSEILLE
                    (month, date) SMITH.</p>
                <p>Apply immediately for passport for Romania via Marseille and Constantinople, for
                    the purpose of joining Edwin C. Kemp, American Consul, Bucharest, as wife, and
                    attach the enclosed letter to Mr. Hengstler to the application. Have a dozen
                    prints made of your passport photo, as you will need the balance over here. If
                    the necessary visas are not made before your passport is delivered to you, use
                    the enclosed cards when calling for your visas. If the offices are crowded, have
                    no hesitation in elbowing your way to the clerk and present my card. You had
                    better go down to New York the day before the ship sails, to give yourself
                    enough tine to get your passport.</p>
                <p>Though just barely possible, it is hardly probable that I can meet you in
                    Marseille. Don't look for me, anyway. I shall write to the Consulate there to
                    meet you, but if they fail to, take a carriage and drive to the Consulate, 10
                    Cours Pierre Puget, hours, 9-4. If the door is closed, pound, as they are often
                    there later. If it is Sunday, or for any other reason no one is there, you can
                    drive around the corner to Mac's boarding house, opposite the Palais de Justice,
                    on the chance of finding him there. If not, drive to 8 Rue Jaubert, where you
                    will be almost sure to find Mr. or Mrs. Gross, even if you have to wait for
                    them, and they will be glad to help you. She understands a little English, he
                    speaks it. You can also go to Mr. Gaulins villa 331 Avenue du Prado (Mrs, Gaulin
                    is away, but he or Eugene, the servant, may be of assistance. If all these fail,
                    Mrs. Cummings at the British Sailors Home in the Rue de la Republique can help
                    you find Mac, and Mr. Burnett, of Budd &amp; Co., Rue Beauveau, or the American
                    Express Company opposite, or Cooks, will help. There is also Emma Mercier, 11
                    Rue de la Fausse Monnaie, quite a ways out, who would take you over to Mrs.
                    Davis, who lives near by, or to Mrs. Burnett, whom I do not know so awfully
                    well, but would help in a pinch. The idea is to get in touch with some one of
                    the Consulate, who would find you a place at one of the hotels, the Hotel du
                    Louvre, Hotel Regina, or Hotel Splendide. They speak English at all these
                    places, and you can be comfortable until the Romanian steamer sails. If the
                    people from the Consulate meet you, you will have no difficulty with the
                    customs, and if they do not, present the enclosed card. You could leave your
                    trunks while hunting up the addresses given. The Consulate will take you in hand
                    when you get there, and will help you get your ticket on the Romanian steamer,
                    and get away comfortably.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>As soon as you know the date and name of the steamer sailing, have the Consulate
                    telegraph as follows: AMERICAN CONSUL CONSTANTINOPLE NOTIFY KEMP CONSUL
                    BUCHAREST SMITH DUE CONSTANTINOPLE (month, date) STEAMER (name) also AMERICAN
                    CONSUL PARIS NOTIFY KEMP BUCHAREST SMITH DUE CONSTANTINOPLE (month, date)
                    STEAMER (name).</p>
                <p>The Romanian steamer is said to have fair accommodations, but you had best carry
                    some tea, sugar, and an alcohol (solid) burner, with a couple candles. Enquire
                    about food before sailing. I understand the purser boards you at about 25 fcs.
                    per day. You will probably have some women passengers aboard with you. The
                    daughters of the Romanian minister at Rome went home this way he told me. I
                    believe the steamer stops at Naples, Athens, Constantinople and Galatz. I expect
                    to meet you at Constantinople, if I know what boat you are coming on. If I do
                    not, send a note to the Consul General, Mr. Ravndal, asking him to notify me as
                    quickly as possible, so I can be at Galatz. You could also have some one
                    telegraph me at Constantinople. Do not go ashore at these places, but send a
                    steward, unless you are with some Americans or British who know what they are
                    doing. If I do not even get to Galatz, go to the American Red Cross people there
                    and have them telegraph the Legation here, and if for any reason I was unable to
                    travel, you could come up with some of the Red Cross people, who frequently make
                    the trip, leaving your trunks at Galatz, as traveling with heavy baggage is very
                    troublesome.</p>
                <p>The trip takes about 12 days to Marseille, and about 10 to Galatz. People who
                    have made the trip say it is quite possible, and even interesting.</p>
                <p>Cash check, and buy 200 francs in French money before sailing, for change when
                    you arrive. At Marseille, change the rest, left after buying ticket, into French
                    money, which will be good the rest of the way, and you can probably get a better
                    rate than in the U.S. Tips on the Fabre Line would be about 5.00 to the
                    stewardess, 5.00 to waiter, and 2.50 to the deck steward, but your fellow
                    passengers will give you an idea of the usual amount.</p>
                <p>If Cooks can guarantee you a comfortable and direct sailing to Constantinople, it
                    might be advisable to take it. In such case cable Paris and Constantinople to
                    advise me of date of arrival, so I can be there to meet you. Upon arrival, if I
                    do not meet you, go to The Consul General or the Embassy, or if they are closed,
                    to Cooks, or the Pera Palace Hotel, or the Tokatlian Hotel, or the American
                    military headquarters. You will probably find a lot of Americans, and certainly
                    British, who will gladly help you out.</p>
                <p>It will be more advisable to go to Constantinople direct, and certainly simpler,
                    than via Marseille, if you can get sailings. I do not know, however, as there
                    are any direct boats yet.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>In case I failed to meet you in Constantinople, I would write the Consulate
                    General where to send you, either overland with the courier - a hard trip - or
                    by the Romanian steamer on to Galatz.</p>
                <p>Don't get worried by these detailed instructions. I have tried to cover every
                    possible slip, to save you worrying, but as a matter of fact, I have no doubt
                    but what the Consulate will meet you at Marseille, and you will have no trouble
                    at all; and it will certainly take an earthquake to prevent my meeting you at
                    Constantinople. Neither must you let the sound of these places unduly impress
                    you. They are only stations and boat landings along the line, when you come
                    right down to it, and their interest varies only with their facilities for the
                    traveling public. You will probably have Americans or British with you all of
                    the way, to help you out and help pass the time. Certainly I would not advise
                    the trip if I did not think it could be done with a reasonable amount of
                    comfort.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>On Board the Patria, 11 November, 1919</p>
                <p>... After we left the harbor Thursday we ran into a storm and for three days were
                    on end all the time.</p>
                <p>I spent Friday and Saturday flat on my back and didn't care what happened.
                    Everything fell over that wasn't hitched and even the stewardess was ill. One or
                    two appeared at table each meal but not more than that. Saturday night in the
                    night we commenced to roll instead of pitch and I was able with many
                    interruptions to make the deck on Sunday morning.</p>
                <p>Monday was quite comfortable and yesterday as calm as a mill pond. Today it has
                    been choppy and many squalls, due, they say, to our passing the Azores soon. No
                    one could get any service at all when they were ill. The food is impossible and
                    everyone much disgruntled with everything. ... The bells in the rooms are never
                    answered and all the help retire at ten and you can't possibly get anything done
                    after that. It is a very good introduction to what I shall find from France on,
                    I suppose. During the storm a man from the steerage jumped overboard but it was
                    so rough they made no attempt to get him. Two people went insane and one man who
                    was confined got away and caused much excitement one night. So you see life is
                    hardly dull.</p>
                <p>Thursday — Very rough again this morning but we all have our sea legs now and
                    don't mind it. ... It seems ages since I left home but it is three weeks
                    tomorrow. This boat is due at Palermo on Wednesday and Marseille the following
                    Saturday. I will send a line from Naples but wait and mail this at Marseille for
                    I think it will go through quicker. It seems a long trip from there on and you
                    may tell Aunt Jean I did think the first day of turning back at Marseille but
                    now I feel that even being headed for home will have no effect. I certainly
                    wouldn't want to go back on this boat.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>November 17 ... We passed the Azores and Gibraltar and have been following the
                    African coast ever since. ... After that we had more rough weather, the boat
                    standing on end day and night. Saturday it calmed down and another man jumped
                    overboard. It seems to be the habit on board this ship.</p>
                <p>They stopped, made a circle several times, threw over life buoys etc. but no one
                    appeared.</p>
                <p>The next night the crazy boy nearly finished his parents so they had to put him
                    in a straightjacket.</p>
                <p>The food and service still continue poor. Mr. Smith and Mrs. Brooks and one or
                    two others are all that make life bearable ... We have very exciting movies on
                    board. The films date back to the first productions years ago.</p>
                <p>Afternoon tea has just been served and after washing my cup and spoon myself I
                    managed to drink some today. It improves the flavor to have the china fairly
                    clean. I'm in hopes the next trip won't make me a bit seasick for I am quite
                    accustomed to rough weather now. This old tub either has no cargo or is a very
                    wobbly ship. We had such a list at Gibraltar I was all worn out holding it down
                    on the other side.</p>
                <p>There are three “vamps” on board. Donald [Donald Durkee was a distant cousin and
                    a prot�g� of Uncle Ernest] will explain to you what they are. The Captain is
                    very attentive to one.</p>
                <p>The ship is getting very gossipy now and the people at my table are all worn out
                    trying to find out why I am roaming around alone. They ask all the direct
                    questions they can and then try the indirect method. Finally they wanted to know
                    if I were a Romanian princess traveling incognito.</p>
                <p>November 20 — Naples. We arrived at Palermo about seven yesterday. I went ashore
                    with Mrs. Brooks and Mr. Smith and wished afterward I had stayed on the boat. I
                    would certainly have had a better impression of Palermo if I had.</p>
                <p>It was very picturesque from the landing but horribly filthy as you know. We had
                    luncheon, visited several churches, the palace, etc. The land was most unsteady
                    at first after such a rough trip. ... Nearly everyone is getting off at Naples.
                    Only a very few go on to Marseille. I am too happy to exist today anyway for I
                    received a wire from Carl here saying he was waiting for me at Marseille. You
                    can't imagine what that means to me! I will cable you on landing and you need
                    have no more worries about me. Perhaps we will go by train to Bucharest. I do
                    not know.</p>
                <p>This boat is really dreadful. We have no water while in dock and I have to wash
                    my face with the drinking water. If we don't all die of typhoid it will be a
                    wonder. One of the steerage did and I am not surprised.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>I forgot to mention Mr. Smith had his pocket picked yesterday and a camera with a
                    sixty dollar lense taken. Naturally he isn't very fond of the Sicilians either.
                    They are a bad lot. The boat is full of guides etc. today. One man offered to
                    drive me out to Pompeii and back, an hour each way. No one wants anything but
                    American money over here. They scorn their own money and clamor for dollars. It
                    seems very strange. ... Everyone who has been over before nearly faints at the
                    high prices. They don't realize it is as expensive to live on this side as the
                    other now. ... The stewards are all very affable now. Two of them tucked my feet
                    up for me this morning but when I hadn't the strength to go on deck or even
                    reach the telephone they were all useless. Even the phones work the last two
                    days.</p>
                <p>The Dante A[inaudible] is next to us and evidently expects to go out soon as the
                    steerage are all on board. All headed for New York and yet I don't want to take
                    it the least bit. I haven't been one bit homesick all the way even when the boat
                    behaved so badly. It is when I am settled down and have a chance to realize I am
                    not just touring the country that I shall feel it.</p>
                <p>Sat A.M. November 22</p>
                <p>Just a line to let you know I am okay. Carl at the pier. Have just sent you a
                    cable. We leave for Paris tomorrow night — to be married there on Monday. Will
                    write more later.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>The marriage did take place in Paris, on November 26. Anna said later the
                    ceremony was all in French, and she never did know what all she had promised to
                    do, having just said “oui” in the appropriate places. She always had warm
                    feelings for Paris and frequently said she wanted her ashes scattered from the
                    Eiffel tower. Her next letter is from</p>
                <p>Bucharest, Romania</p>
                <p>December 1, 1919</p>
                <p>... I will try to explain the household arrangements but they are most
                    complicated. The trip from Paris was a very tiresome one but in spite of dirt,
                    filth, and delay of twenty-six hours in arrival I am still cheerful, very glad
                    to be here and not too weary.</p>
                <p>The trip through Switzerland was wonderful, our only clear day. The food on the
                    train was really very good indeed. I enjoyed all my meals with the exception of
                    not having water to drink. I had just enough wine in the mineral water to take
                    the curse off.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>From Trieste on we lost time at each station and the food ran out so we couldn't
                    get breakfast this morning. Last night they had candles stuck in bottles in the
                    diner, their supply of gas having given out too. The ride through Yugoslavia was
                    most uninteresting, just plains of corn and wheatfields for miles and miles.</p>
                <p>Carl had to leave at every frontier and watch the trunk — my big one — to see
                    they didn't steal it. They have a great habit of stealing the whole baggage car.
                    I never could have come through alone on the train. It is fearfully complicated.
                    Carl's card is useful over here and makes them stand around. Our baggage wasn't
                    touched and when we entered Romania my big trunk was safely in the baggage car.
                    I saw it myself. The steamer trunk is coming by a freight boat to Galatz.
                    ...</p>
                <p>Carl wired for a month's leave hoping the Patria wouldn't be too late for him to
                    meet me. His leave is up today so we just made it.</p>
                <p>Now about the place:</p>
                <p>Downstairs the Romanian lady who owns it lives by herself. She speaks English
                    with an accent but it's a great deal to have her speak at all.</p>
                <p>Then “Amaryllis”, or Miss Shaw, treasurer of the Red Cross, has a room on the
                    second floor where the dining room and this small salon are. Also a toilet on
                    this floor. The bath being way down in the cellar, 'as 'twere'. It is all
                    furnished by the madame. I don't know her name. On the next floor are our rooms.
                    A sitting room not heated, for summer use, and a smaller one for winter with a
                    stove. A large bedroom opening out onto a balcony with a dressing room; the
                    latter is not on the balcony as it sounds. We have running water in the dressing
                    room but it only runs certain hours. There is a dressing table, two wardrobes, a
                    chiffonier, chairs and a comfortable couch.</p>
                <p>Madame runs the servants, there are three in all. Cook, maid and laundress.</p>
                <p>The Vice Consul, a Mr. Whitney, and a Miss Bateman, Red Cross worker, take their
                    meals here but I don't know whether they will continue to or not. It is almost
                    impossible to get a place of any kind here in Bucharest. I shall start in on
                    French and enough Romanian to get along with the servants for Carl has his eye
                    on a house by ourselves in the spring. Mr. Whitney said this noon Romania was to
                    sign before tomorrow or all aliens would have to evacuate by tomorrow night. No
                    one knows where. I hope and pray they sign for I at least am happy to be settled
                    in one spot for a while. [I assume that what was being signed was some kind of
                    international agreement connected with the armistice.]</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>... The luncheon, at one, was excellent. Chops, peas, and something came first I
                    didn't recognize but it was very good. Custard with sauce, fruit and Turkish
                    coffee in the salon afterwards. The other ladies all enjoyed a cigarette but I
                    felt I would rather wait for a little private practice ...</p>
                <p>The water here Carl says is safe to drink and that helps out a lot. The city is
                    dirty and just at present very muddy, it being a foggy dismal sort of day.</p>
                <p>They all feel dreadfully to have me land under such conditions but it doesn't
                    affect my feelings any. I told Carl coming down that if we could live together
                    peaceably in a two by four compartment with all the discomforts and weariness of
                    foreign travel now I thought it was a pretty good test. One isn't, of course,
                    supposed to quarrel on their honeymoon I suppose, but you do have a chance to
                    see each other at their very worst on board a Wagon Lit rolling across Serbia
                    nearly four days and four nights. I shouldn't advise anyone to make the trip
                    just for a sightseeing tour. Romanian is not a very pretty language as far as I
                    have been able to observe. German is spoken a great deal, but French goes
                    anywhere. I shall be glad when I can converse in it.</p>
                <p>Loving you all and wishing you didn't have to wait three weeks to know how happy
                    and well I am.</p>
                <p>Anna</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Bucharest</p>
                <p>December 13, 1919</p>
                <p>Dear Sister,</p>
                <p>I can't understand why I don't hear a word from any of you for mail from Florida
                    has come in, written a week after I left. Have you disowned me altogether?
                    Perhaps you are waiting to hear of my arrival but I hope not, and I hope
                    something may come soon ...</p>
                <p>It rains so much it takes ages to get laundry done here. Some part of every day
                    is rainy — something like England when we were there.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>I have an iron, an ex-electric one someone left here. It is loose and wiggles so
                    when I try to use it I hardly accomplish anything. What wouldn't I give for a
                    couple of our old fashioned ones. They have gas here instead of electricity so
                    my electric one would not have done any good in this house. Last night we were
                    invited to dinner at the place we hope to get in May. It is very attractive. A
                    house by itself with a garden fenced in, as all the places are here. The rents
                    are awful and this one is unfurnished. That is, the people want to sell the
                    furniture and everything that is in the house.</p>
                <p>We had a very nice dinner (with six Red Cross workers). The men all pass me
                    cigarettes and say, “No, not yet, but you will soon”... [Anna never did take up
                    smoking]</p>
                <p>I haven't yet become accustomed to not knowing what is going on in the outside
                    world and papers dated before I left home look good to me. If anyone wants to
                    send anything let them do up a newspaper or a magazine. I read the Journal of
                    Commerce with much interest, understanding very little of it.</p>
                <p>My French lessons haven't begun yet but I think in a week or so we will be able
                    to settle down to it. Most people are not interested in foreign languages so
                    soon I guess. They say they speak English in some of the shops but I haven't
                    noticed it yet. My shopping experiences haven't been very many. Carl very
                    unwisely showed me where he bought candy. It is good, too. That's the trouble
                    over here. One can get anything by paying for it. Though the candy is only
                    ninety cents a pound at the present rate of exchange. The lei, usually worth
                    five to a dollar is worth thirty now ...</p>
                <p>I think Carl was quite worried at first for fear I would be homesick and lonesome
                    after the newness had worn off but the longer I am here the better I like it. I
                    had my heart so set on being homesick perhaps that is why I am not and I had no
                    idea in my head that Bucharest would be more wonderful than anything we had at
                    home. Carl owes a great deal to that first trip I had across.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Bucharest, February 2, 1920</p>
                <p>Dear Sister,</p>
                <p>I am enclosing our ticket to the Grand Ball on Saturday evening or to be more
                    correct Sunday morning. Carl and Mr. Whitney took a box so we could see this gay
                    Romanian life that is so raved about. Mr. Whitney invited a Red Cross girl and
                    we asked Miss Shaw.</p>
                <p>We went to bed right after dinner, setting the alarm clock for eleven. Then we
                    dressed and started out about twelve. It was an awful effort to get up at that
                    time of night and go out into the cold world but nothing to the way I felt
                    yesterday.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>All the people on the floor were in costume or masked and the boxes were filled
                    with spectators in all degrees of undress. Still no more extreme than I have
                    seen at the opera. The most common form of costume was pajamas and kimonos. Old
                    cotton crepe affairs I wouldn't wear in the privacy of my room.</p>
                <p>I suppose it being bed time they came as they were?</p>
                <p>They had dancing at the stage end of the opera house but most of the people just
                    walked around among the crowd. People were coming and going all the time so it
                    didn't get monotonous.</p>
                <p>After we had watched them a while we went down through a long dark passage-way to
                    a queer little buffet. There was a large one upstairs but they told us this one
                    was more fun. A gypsy orchestra played weird music and (don't tell Aunt Jean)
                    but our waiter talked German instead of French. We had cold turkey, salad,
                    pickles, bread and champagne. All very good. I was nearly starved and didn't
                    dare eat all I wanted. The Romanian officers and the gay girls came in, had a
                    few drinks, much love making, and then would go up to wander around again.</p>
                <p>We went back to the box and watched the crowd until four when we all nearly fell
                    asleep and decided there was nothing to this Romanian night life. I was glad to
                    have seen it, but once is enough. We were all dead to the world yesterday. This
                    week, Saturday, we are going out for a steak dinner at the Elysee, the best cafe
                    here I guess. That is the best decent one. Then to see “Phi Phi”.</p>
                <p>Opera opens up February 23 with Aida. I think an Italian company. Last night I
                    dreamed I was home for a few minutes. I couldn't even stop long enough to sit
                    down but told Mrs. Scribner I just ran over to see how you all were and get my
                    mail ... I had my passport and came back on the next boat.</p>
                <p>So you see I must be happy or I wouldn't want to come back again.</p>
                <p>I was singing very joyfully yesterday, you know what it sounds like, and Carl
                    felt overjoyed to hear some outward signs of my being happy. He thought I was
                    from my appearance, but I hadn't mentioned it. 'That's me all over.'</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>The next letter was written to her brother Bun (Burnell Smith).</p>
                <p>Bucharest, March 16, 1920</p>
                <p>Dear Bun,</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>... I wish you would please call Aunt Jean up at once and tell her that I shook
                    hands with the Queen last evening, did not have to curtsy and did not sprain my
                    ankle backing out. It was not a court presentation and I fear she won't remember
                    she ever met me. The minister gave a dinner to the government officials and
                    foreign ministers and “Leur Majesties, Le Roi et La Reine”. We didn't come in on
                    that but later he had a reception or ball, more the latter I should say.</p>
                <p>About eleven we started out and it was just four when I crawled into bed. There
                    was such a crowd and all they did was wander around from room to room meeting
                    everyone one ever met before (sic) until after the queen left. Then the crowd
                    thinned out so they could dance.</p>
                <p>At first the Queen was in one room and the King in another. The minister asked me
                    if I wouldn't like to meet her, and Carl met the King. Then they placed their
                    chairs in the center of the Ball Room and the crowd formed in back of them to
                    watch a Russian dancer perform. They had a band and an orchestra so the music
                    was continuous. When we left the band was playing “Row, Row, Row”. Now don't
                    laugh, that's the honest truth! Their favorite piece over here is “Tickle Toe”
                    from “Going Up”.</p>
                <p>Of course they had eats and an unlimited amount of champagne. The gowns were not
                    very startling. May will want to know I wore my pink dress [Still in existence
                    in a box in my attic; a real gem], white slippers etc. I know you won't
                    care.</p>
                <p>If I could see you all, I could tell you lots more I can't write about, about the
                    affair. Little things that are interesting but it's too hard for me to go into
                    detail. You know how it is?...</p>
                <p>The movies are, well, you know how I liked them at home and these are worse. The
                    theatres are not yet back to their pre-war days and the opera, which has been
                    postponed week by week, is still to come. That leaves nothing but the cafes and
                    I haven't yet seen a “real” one so I can't say. All I ask for is a nice steak
                    dinner now and then and they do have them ...</p>
                <p>The lilac leaves are coming out fast here and the grass under this last snow is
                    very green ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>The next letter, written in the later spring of early summer of 1920, finds Anna
                    making preparations for her expected baby. She mentions Mrs. Green, another
                    American lady there whose baby was due shortly after hers. It was her son Tommy
                    who gave Ernest Kemp the nickname Kempie, which remains his family name to the
                    present day.</p>
                <p>Bucharest, Spring 1920</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>Carl had a cable from the Department promoting him to Class 4 which made us both
                    very happy for it's only a year since his last promotion. If we could only find
                    some way of having Marjorie come over before winter we could settle down very
                    comfortably and happily for the next year. ... I do hope the shirts and bands
                    come and as soon as you hear that the baby is here and alive do send the next
                    size necessary for this is an impossible place to get anything for babies ...
                    Nothing but outing flannel for didees over here and no slips or dresses
                    whatever. Mrs. Green's party [another euphemism for giving birth] isn't until
                    December so any duplicates I may have she stands ready to relieve me of. Miss
                    Spellman, the head Red Cross nurse left here, came to our rescue and presented
                    us with layettes. How I wish you could see them! However, some of the things
                    will be useful if not ornamental and will do for patterns. My layette came from
                    the Boston division of the Red Cross and I looked carefully for a note from
                    someone I knew tucked inside somewhere. Perhaps some of Aunt Jean's knitting.
                    There were several bonnets and two very pretty jackets. Two teddy bear blankets
                    and one heavy pad will be most useful. Then later I received a nice basket of
                    bandages and medicines and a raft of washcloths ... I'm sure the Red Cross never
                    did anymore good in their lives and I shall pass the things on to some Romanian.
                    Miss Spellman is a conscientious soul and felt a bit guilty about letting us
                    have them I think. I'm sure I think we deserve most anything if we are willing
                    to have children in this far off land.</p>
                <p>We went into a Paris shop the other day and asked for five or six different
                    things, all simple articles but they didn't have one of them and what is more,
                    didn't care either. They follow you around as if you were a shoplifter so you
                    can't take any comfort looking about. Carl says that is because they have lost
                    things and are suspicious of everyone. I know I do look like I had half the
                    store with me but it's all mine.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>In March of that year Anna is sounding very enthusiastic about setting up
                    housekeeping. As she stated earlier, the house was for rent unfurnished, but the
                    furnishings then in the house were all for sale, so in the end they had to buy
                    all the furniture in order to get the house. I was surprised to read this
                    description, because I had pictured it as much less attractive. Maybe her
                    descriptions were less glowing years later than they were when she was all
                    enthused about setting up a home. That was an occupation she excelled in.</p>
                <p>And she set up a lot of them in the years to come.</p>
                <p>March 19, 1920</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>... The Red Cross [who had been living in the house] left us some provisions and
                    a bed all ready to make up (to repay us for any) breakage and for use of the
                    furniture for a month. We kept the man who has been on the place eight years and
                    does everything. Also his wife who will launder and clean, and Minna, who is now
                    cooking for us until our cook comes on the 21st. Then Minna will do the upstairs
                    work, serve and answer bells. At present the man is doing that and gets along
                    very well, considering. I unpacked slowly and have one case still to do but we
                    are using our own things now and how good it seems. My table linen looks very
                    pretty and the silver is lovely. I just left out enough for our every-day use.
                    They say the servants are absolutely honest but it makes it easier for them to
                    have a little to keep track of.</p>
                <p>We have a full dinner set of Austrian china and an everyday set which is more or
                    less broken up. A set of cut glass, including all the wine glasses one could
                    think of and five decanters ... I never was so well supplied with china and
                    glassware.</p>
                <p>I have been tired but my digestion straightened out as soon as I began exercise
                    and I feel so much better to have something to do and a place of my own to roam
                    around in.</p>
                <p>Minna does the marketing and I try to plan the meals but it's hard when one
                    doesn't know the language. ... Our four servants will only cost us sixteen
                    dollars a month at the present rate of exchange but it's going down fast and I
                    don't know what we would do if it reached normal ...</p>
                <p>We have two bedrooms upstairs. One is large and very airy with double doors out
                    onto a porch. It's just like sleeping out.</p>
                <p>Every window looks out into trees for there are so many everywhere. Yet it isn't
                    dark in any of the rooms. They all have sunshine some part of the day. We have
                    water here all day long which is a great blessing and although there is no gas
                    we can have a hot bath anytime by building a little wood fire under the boiler
                    in the bathroom. It doesn't heat up as I feared it would wither.</p>
                <p>Our only drawback is lamps and we hoped to have electricity put in. When the gas
                    and electric strikes and shortages are on, lamps are fine but otherwise they are
                    awful. Some of our furniture is really very nice. The dining room set — square
                    table and twelve chairs, one large sideboard and one smaller one with glass
                    doors — are of heavy carved oak. I never saw anything like them at home. I
                    didn't like it at first, it was so ornate and heavy but I'm getting to like it
                    more and more. The library has a long heavily carved desk, chair and bookcase to
                    match, also in the oak. Here in the salon we have the glass backed piano, a very
                    pretty desk of imitation ebony I guess with inlaid mother of pearl and bronze.
                    This I claim as mine. I've always wanted a desk with secret drawers so I'm quite
                    happy. ... Lots of nice comfy chairs and silk hangings for the windows. ... Oh
                    yes, we have more clocks than I ever saw in one house. All Austrian and German
                    and a safe made in Vienna. One of the clocks is a mahogany grandfather clock;
                    keeps excellent time. I'm beginning to think I shall hate to leave here for a
                    new post.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>If we can get Marjie out and the baby safely here I know I shall be happy in
                    spite of wanting to see you all. Only two days have I been the least bit
                    homesick and I think that was because I didn't feel well and spring was coming
                    and made me want to get outdoors. The large back porch looks out onto the garden
                    and there is where I shall live as soon as Johannie has time to clean it up.
                    ...</p>
                <p>All the other Americans are envious and want to go to house-keeping now, though
                    when I spoke of going they didn't want any part of it. The care and worry of
                    servants etc. Having a home is worth everything to me, and to Carl too. Our only
                    worry is getting Marjorie out. Mr. Whitney expects to go home in the fall and he
                    will be able to see that Merril [a cousin of Marjorie's, about ten years older
                    than she] and Marjie come through safely. ... Carl said the other night that
                    Marjie would soon be able to come alone. ...</p>
                <p>Have just been down to unlock the supply closet for Minna to get her daily
                    supplies of coffee, sugar, etc. which we keep under lock and key. I never saw so
                    many keys as I have. I found keys to every door in the house. By locking the
                    supplies the servants have no chance of supplying their relatives and
                    friends.</p>
                <p>I forgot to mention our beautiful bronze chandeliers. They really are awfully
                    messy but at night with the candles all lighted the rooms look very pretty. It
                    costs too much to use them except on state occasions. ... I do hope you aren't
                    worrying about me for I'm so well and happy. ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Bucharest</p>
                <p>April 13, 1920</p>
                <p>Dearest Sister,</p>
                <p>Your long letter of March 25 came Saturday and I intended to answer it at once.
                    Everything has been tied up here for Easter so I doubt if it would have gone on
                    anyway. No deliveries for three days and no banks open.</p>
                <p>How thankful I am you have the home place to go to for a rest now and then and
                    I'm so glad Mrs. Scribner helps out so much. I do think it's a shame you have so
                    much illness. I'm worried for fear you won't take care of yourself but goodness
                    knows how you can. [Anne Armstrong writes, “That was the year of disaster for
                    the Jacksons. One or the other of us children had an operation every Thursday
                    for six weeks - mastoid or sinus. How mother ever lived through it I'll never
                    know.”]</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>If we ever are sent to a hot climate you must pack up and come too. It's lovely
                    here now, just like our month of May. There is also an east wind so much like
                    ours at home I can almost smell the salt air. This comes from the Black Sea I
                    suppose.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Eirich, Mrs. Interiden and Mrs. Green are coming for tea this afternoon so I
                    may stop this any minute. Carl wanted to know if it were an announcement party.
                    My silk dress with the blue bib is a blessing. My corsets nearly kill me and
                    with that I don't look too bad. ... This week I shall try to get some material
                    and have two dresses started. I think I shall ask Mrs. Eirich to help me. My
                    side view in shirt waist and skirt is — well — you know what.</p>
                <p>Saturday night the (Easter) services were, instead of Sunday night. We went about
                    eleven with Mr. Whitney and some friends of his. Such a crowd I never saw in a
                    church and I could only stand it about fifteen minutes or so. Standing up and
                    the bad air were too much for me and I just got outside in time.</p>
                <p>We sat on the porch and watched the crowd come and go — all carrying wax tapers.
                    It was really very picturesque. The peasants in costumes of course. Across the
                    river rockets were going up and truly it seemed more like the Fourth of July
                    than Easter. Sunday I was too all in to go to church again so we stayed around
                    home and went for a walk in the afternoon.</p>
                <p>Oh yes, I remember they gave us so much to eat at noon we could hardly wiggle.
                    For breakfast we had cosnac — like our coffee rolls only different — and Easter
                    eggs; beautiful colors too. At luncheon I can't begin to remember the variety,
                    and dinner too. Yesterday Carl went to the office in the morning to work on
                    accounts and in the afternoon we went to the movies — The Redemption — then
                    walked through the Cismigen, the principal park, and had tea on the way
                    home.</p>
                <p>My trunk check came and the trunk itself should be here. They say they have
                    received word it has left Braila. Perhaps after the holidays are over it can be
                    located. They never have just one day off here. They take several for they
                    realize they need one to recover from the holiday. A saint is celebrated every
                    few minutes.</p>
                <p>I truly think I have sleeping sickness. This morning I couldn't wake up when
                    Paraschim came to do the room and slept through it all. I did manage to get up
                    in time to have my bed made before Carl came home.</p>
                <p>Wednesday</p>
                <p>I had such awful gas last night I couldn't finish this. It didn't let up until
                    Carl gave me a treatment. It's all gone today but I've kept quiet and left my
                    corsets off until now. ... It is lovely out here on the terrace tonight, very
                    comfortable with only a sweater.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>I'm wondering about the flannel, whether to send home for it. ... Carl says there
                    is a large supply of diapers in the freight en route from Tunis but I've lost
                    all faith in freight. There are some white baby shoes in my cedar chest and I
                    want that blue coat too. I'll find out this week just what I can get here and
                    what not and send some money providing we have any. Getting Marjie out and
                    buying furniture makes a hole in our finances. The exchange isn't as favorable
                    for us as it was a month or so ago.</p>
                <p>We had a nice time yesterday, or at least they all seemed to. Mrs. Interiden is a
                    Russian married to an American and had some wild tales to tell of her trip out
                    of Russia. Her mother died two years ago and she has only just received word of
                    it.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Green loaned me a lot of American magazines and books. One I have just
                    finished — Christopher and Columbus — you would like it I think ...</p>
                <p>I do hope you are all well again for keeps. Have you any help at all besides
                    Foss? [Miss Foss - May's helper and nurse for the children. Anne Armstrong
                    describes her as a “treasure, a gentle competent soul ... I have never seen her
                    equal since.”] All these strong healthy peasant girls could do so much good at
                    home.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Bucharest, June 14, 1920</p>
                <p>... Thursday I shopped from four o'clock until half past seven. Mrs. Eirich went
                    with me and we accomplished quite a lot. [The following items were purchases for
                    the baby.] I bought a clothes basket, small basket for toilet articles and the
                    lining and dotted swiss for both. We have five four legged stool affairs which
                    will be just fine to set the basket down in any room. I'm thinking of making a
                    cretonne cover for the stool. I found some batiste after a hard hunt but no
                    flannel.</p>
                <p>On Friday Mrs. Green was here for luncheon — our first guest in our new home. ...
                    She lives in Philadelphia or New Jersey and does not want any of her people to
                    hear about her affair [euphemism for giving birth, like circus and party used in
                    past letters] until it is over.</p>
                <p>... Mr. Greble leaves for Paris today, hoping to find his wife and young son
                    waiting to come to Bucharest. He has rented a place a mile out from here. We are
                    already a mile from the center so he hopes to have a car soon. Also a cow which
                    interests me more than anything. I would almost be willing to go out and milk it
                    twice a day for him for the sake of having good milk.</p>
                <p>All the Americans now are anxious to go to housekeeping. It's funny because when
                    I first spoke of it they thought it very foolish. After they see how nicely
                    situated we are and what a comfort a house is, they find a hotel room lacking
                    many comforts they hadn't thought of.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>This morning I set Johannie to scrubbing the dining table. It is warped a bit in
                    the center and the felt was all stuck on to it. He managed to get it off and
                    polished it up so I can now use my luncheon cloths. He insisted they wanted to
                    go straight instead of corner-wise but I told him that was American. Elena is
                    washing in the backyard in a long wooden trough affair and has the boiler set up
                    on a couple bricks. The clothes were nice and white last week but I don't see
                    how she does it. She didn't iron the table cloth well so I'll try and show her
                    tomorrow how to do it.</p>
                <p>... The weather is lovely, neither too cool nor too hot. I surely like this
                    climate so far. Our phone they promise to put in this week and Carl is making an
                    appointment with a doctor to come out this afternoon. He has been recommended as
                    the best obstetrician and as long as he has to be a Romanian we just have to try
                    him out. I'll know better after I have seen him myself. Carl went to see him and
                    said he looked intelligent. There is a woman physician also well spoken of but
                    I've a horror of them for some reason. I am more anxious about the nurse myself
                    and hope that I can stay here so Carl can keep an eye on things and not let them
                    abuse the child. I certainly can't complain so far for I have been so well
                    through it all. It is nearly lunch time and I must pick some fresh lilies for
                    our table. The garden is lined or edged with tiger lilies all in bloom ...</p>
                <p>Housekeeping in the Romania of 1919 was the subject of many of Anna's stories
                    over the years; about the lack of proper lighting, the barefoot waitress serving
                    food in the semi-darkness of candlelight and about the pig the cook kept in the
                    basement kitchen.</p>
                <p>Bucharest, June 18, 1920</p>
                <p>Dear Sister,</p>
                <p>I had to celebrate the 17th [Bunker Hill Day, an important holiday in Boston] all
                    alone yesterday. No one from Boston is here just now except Miss Spellman, a
                    nurse, and she is too busy to celebrate.</p>
                <p>SaturdayJune 19, 1920</p>
                <p>... Tuesday morning Mrs. Green invited me down there to have a shampoo. She has
                    the girl come to her hotel room and do it which is ever so much nicer in every
                    way. We both had a shampoo and wave, drying our hair on the balcony of the best
                    hotel in town, facing the main street. Can you imagine hanging your hair out of
                    Fremont Street? That's what makes this such a queer city. [Aunty May once told
                    me how embarrassed she was as a young woman when a caller happened to see her
                    with her hair down. It was apparently something done only in private.]</p>
                <p>So far I haven't seen any baby carriages on the Calea and I told Carl I should
                    certainly walk down to meet him every night this fall and let him push the baby
                    home. The street is very narrow, the sidewalks more so, and such a crowd of
                    people from five o'clock on.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>Monday the 21st. I am having a dreadful streak of laziness the past few days.
                    Even writing this is an effort. Am feeling alright though and the doctor said
                    everything was okay so far. He's a queer little man and speaks no English. His
                    midwife is a Pole, speaks French and German and stays on the case a month. He
                    promised to be on hand himself and comes again July 1 to see how things are
                    progressing. September 1 is his date and very appropriate it would be to wait
                    for Labor Day I think.</p>
                <p>... This place has been sold again we find and our present owner wishes us to
                    move so he can occupy it. Fortunately our lease holds good for two years. He
                    offered a premium but Carl said nothing but another place as satisfactory as
                    this would induce us to move now. Then he wanted a few rooms — in the basement —
                    anything to live in for the city is dreadfully overcrowded.</p>
                <p>(last part of this letter missing)</p>
                <p>I had always had the impression that Anna suffered considerable bad health before
                    the baby arrived. She referred to it as gastritis. Perhaps that explains the
                    lack of letters for the next four months. Of course it is also very possible
                    that those letters were just not saved. Charles Ernest Kemp arrived on August
                    27. The doctor who had promised to be there was away and they settled for
                    whoever they could find. It was not a pleasant experience. Not being able to
                    converse with the doctor didn't help the situation any, although I believe Carl
                    was able to do a little interpreting with his French. After it was all over,
                    Carl, Anna, and the doctor had a spot of brandy, which seems a nice touch.</p>
                <p>Bucharest, October 22, 1920</p>
                <p>Dearest Sister,</p>
                <p>I thought that after the baby came I would do nothing but write to all my family
                    and friends but — there's no need to explain to you.</p>
                <p>It isn't because I am so dreadfully busy either, but there is always something to
                    look after or I'm too tired to write. Fraulein has been a great blessing. I
                    don't know what I would have done without her.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>We got the baby all over his navel trouble. Then I had a hard cold... After that
                    the baby's colic grew worse and worse. He cried day and night until we were all
                    worn out so yesterday we had another baby specialist. He really showed signs of
                    intelligence and is the first one who has handled the baby as if he knew how. He
                    gave him a thorough examination to see if there was any other cause of his
                    crying, examined his stools etc. (I'm a connoisseur on the latter now.) He said
                    the baby was getting too much to eat, to weigh at each feeding and give only 90
                    grams. He has a little cold and I was afraid last night would be croupy. Crying
                    so much aggravated it too — but he wasn't and is a bit better this morning.
                    Fraulein has gone to bed for a rest and I have him here in the library sound
                    asleep after his bath. My clothes basket is very easily carried around from room
                    to room, but I want a carriage now so I can take him out. Just to make things
                    more interesting Carl came home with chills and fever Tuesday noon; would go
                    back in the afternoon to keep an appointment so when he came at night was
                    feeling miserable. I got a hot bath and hot drink ready for him but that was all
                    he would do for it. Wednesday he stayed in bed all day and was out again
                    yesterday rain and all. It has been very cold and now I guess the rainy season
                    has begun. A general strike has been advertised all this week but so far things
                    are still going. Johannie came in with a stove poker over his shoulder this
                    morning to show me the soldiers were out.</p>
                <p>Saturday — Last night the baby slept from ten to five and is better this morning.
                    I gave him a bit over this morning for Anna came in while I was feeding him and
                    I didn't watch closely enough. Consequently he's been fussy since.</p>
                <p>Our laundress all but asphyxiated herself last night. She lives in the little
                    house in the back yard and when she didn't appear this morning Anna tried to get
                    in. She must have managed to open the door. I couldn't quite make out whether it
                    was unlocked or not. She was certainly in a dreadful state but Fraulein pulled
                    her out of it. It was cold so she built a fire out of charcoal right on the
                    cement floor, no outlet for smoke or anything. I wonder she didn't die before
                    morning. There's one thing about this life over here. It's always full of
                    excitement. Mrs. Breble's servants are always shooting around or chasing each
                    other with carving knives. (She) has had enough of housekeeping and goes back to
                    the hotel when the Greens leave.</p>
                <p>We received one doctor's bill — Jaharesco 7,000 1ei or $150 for the delivery and
                    two weeks care of me. What Dr. Lions' will be for the baby I don't know; and two
                    specialists since. Colonel Amint inquired around for us what the Romanians paid
                    and found he had more than doubled the price for us. That's the way with
                    everything over here. They think because the exchange is favorable for Americans
                    they can do them.</p>
                <p>Monday — The baby is so much better; sleeps and eats as he should. Also is
                    beginning to talk and smile something beside a sickly gas grin. Of course he is
                    beautiful and no “squalling brat” at all. What a dreadful remark to make. [No
                    clue as to who made that remark. Possibly her brother.]</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>I suppose you are reading dreadful tales of conditions over here but don't worry.
                    Things are running very smoothly and the strike seems to have failed completely.
                    Carl is tired out and needs a rest for he's been running the Legation for
                    several weeks in addition to his two consular offices and home cares.</p>
                <p>... We have dinner at eight and by the time Anna has brought up her daily account
                    and received the menu for the next day it is time for bed.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Bucharest, Thursday, November 18, 1920</p>
                <p>... I wish we could be over there with you on Christmas. Ernest is almost large
                    enough for a turkey bone. Uncle Bun will have to buy another turkey when we all
                    get together again. Much love to you all. I shall think of you up home as usual
                    on Christmas day. No one knows how I long for some of Mrs. Scribner's cooking.
                    Carl says he wishes the enclosed check were 100 instead of 10 but he'll use the
                    other ninety bringing me home next year.</p>
                <p>BucharestFriday, November 19, 1920</p>
                <p>... I sent you a letter yesterday via pouch but didn't have time to tell you all
                    the things I know will interest you. I'm ashamed to own up to some of them
                    anyway and have been waiting to see how everything was going.</p>
                <p>The baby lost weight and was really sick from being starved to death. That was
                    one trouble I had hoped to avoid but after Dr. Lion took her scales I had to
                    guess at what he was taking and didn't give nearly enough. He cried day and
                    night for so long that Fraulein and I were both nearly sick. Carl found some
                    scales at last and I discovered I had only half enough milk for him. That was
                    why I was worn out. It tired me out every time he nursed and I lost my appetite
                    etc. We sent for the baby specialist again and he said at once we must get a
                    “doica” or wet nurse. You can imagine how that pleased me but it seemed to be
                    the only thing to do. The doctor said it was so much better than to try the
                    bottle with prepared foods or cow's milk. Bottles can be had I guess but we
                    aren't sure how long the cow will give milk or what care it has before it
                    reaches us. So I buried my feelings after one long weep and Carl went out in
                    search of a nurse. The first didn't pass the blood test but one came the next
                    day. I only wish you could have seen her. We took the baby too so she wouldn't
                    lose her milk. It was only eleven days old and she had been out of bed since the
                    second day. Came direct from the hospital here. That's what I call excellent
                    care. Fraulein cleaned her up a little and we installed our new family upstairs
                    next door to Fraulein's room. At present we only number ten in the
                    household.</p>
                <p>Later: A raging snowstorm outside; real old northeaster. We just came in from the
                    Greens. The wind blew so I could hardly get my breath all the way home.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>I am feeding (the baby) twice a day still and have begun to pick up already. I
                    doubt very much if I can keep it up long but he is gaining on the Doica's milk
                    so I don't worry. I was weighed last week and only weighed 107 pounds. I never
                    was so thin before ...</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>That was the last of the letters from Bucharest which were saved. Shortly after
                    that Carl was transferred to Budapest, Hungary. Fraulein apparently went with
                    them, but the Doica was left behind. I recall that there was some problem
                    finding canned milk, which was finally obtained through one of the relief
                    agencies. By the time the following letter was written, it had been decided that
                    the whole family would travel to the U.S. and get Marjorie.</p>
                <p>Budapest, June 10, 1921</p>
                <p>Dear Sister,</p>
                <p>Your letter arrived yesterday and just saved your life for I was really feeling
                    quite deserted. The package was here on our return from Vienna and I'm most
                    grateful to you.</p>
                <p>Everything was okay. It's been so hot I put socks on Kempie so the stockings will
                    wait until we are on board boat I guess. I am glad indeed to have the things,
                    especially watch ribbon and silk stockings. I've put so much money into them
                    here and all for nothing for they don't last a minute.</p>
                <p>I screwed up my courage, left the baby with Fraulein, and went to Vienna with
                    Carl last Friday. We went up by train, five hours on the hottest day we have
                    had. It just about discouraged me for the trip home. The Fosters (Vienna consul)
                    put us up there and we had a very nice visit. I wouldn't have missed it for
                    anything. Vienna is an improvement on this city in some ways but the location
                    here I like much better. They have much nicer apartments, quite palatial, but no
                    help. The more I go around the better I realize how fortunate we are and have
                    been in the help question. Saturday we visited Schonbrun, the former palace, and
                    Sunday we were out in the woods all day. You know how much better that appealed
                    to me than doing museums and public buildings. I couldn't help worrying a little
                    about the baby but we found everything fine when we got back. He had gained and
                    had another tooth. We came back by boat Monday, a very pretty trip.</p>
                <p>We are talking some of sailing from Hamburg, taking Fraulein as far as there,
                    then sending her to Berlin. If we do that she'll have to wait until then for her
                    operation. [An operation for rupture which was postponed due to overcrowding at
                    the hospital.] We may be able to get someone who is going over to help with the
                    baby. I would like the best suite on the Olympia sailing August 3, but I think
                    we'll do well if we get there steerage. We have sailing lists now from all the
                    different companies and I 'm getting quite excited.</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>You spoke of condensed milk for the baby and that is what we are going to try.
                    The doctor has some Dutch preparation we can get here. He is eating all sorts of
                    vegetables besides his soup and cream of wheat once a day. I do hope the trip
                    won't upset him. He is so well and happy now.</p>
                <p>I'm so glad Bun is back at the old place. You don't know anything about how I
                    long to be there ...</p>
                <p>Kempie rolls around anywhere he wants to go but doesn't creep. I hope he will
                    wait and walk without creeping. If nothing happens we'll be leaving before very
                    long ...***</p>
                <p>They did make it over to the U.S. that year, with a nursemaid along for Kempie a
                    Hungarian named Mitzi whom Anna thought was part gypsy. Anne Armstrong remembers
                    her as being quite a sensation “who flitted around on her toes, almost danced
                    whenever she walked, and was very good with Kempie.”</p>
                <p>Anne also recalls that Marjorie, two years her junior, was a very quiet and
                    subdued little girl when she came to Melrose to meet her new mother and rejoin
                    her father, and that Anna was most anxious to do the right thing to put Marjorie
                    at ease. She never stopped trying, but they were two very different
                    personalities and although they came to appreciate each other they never did
                    understand one another.</p>
                <p>In order to make the change easier for Marjorie back in 1920, Carl and Anna
                    brought back to Europe with them Marjorie's older cousin from Florida, Merrill,
                    and “Grandma Mann” the widow of the retired consular officer who had been
                    influential in getting Carl interested in the Foreign Service. They stayed in
                    Budapest for six months. Marjorie was five by this time.</p>
                <p>The flat in Budapest faced right on the Danube River, close to the Elizabeth
                    Bridge, a well known landmark. The exchange rate was still in their favor, and
                    they continued to live very comfortably.</p>
                <p>Budapest, February 14, 1922</p>
                <p>Dear Sister,</p>
                <p>Don't you like the careless way I write and ask you to buy me things and forget
                    to send a check? That's foreign style.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>Please forgive me. I'm trusting to your not having time to shop before this
                    reaches you. There's no special news except that I am growing so stout it's
                    painful. Since the flu I have been gaining steadily and am about ready to weep
                    over it. I'm going to walk it off if the weather ever improves but now we have
                    been having a long cold spell. The river hasn't been clear for weeks. Sunday we
                    went out again to see them skate. I do like to watch the dancing. Then we took
                    in the Art Museums as they are nearby. Carl and I get along beautifully together
                    there for we walk through as quickly as possible and enjoy the same things —
                    landscapes. Grandma Mann and Merrill have to go to church every Sunday to see if
                    the British Consul won't by chance be present. There's a British chaplain here
                    for a few months but I'm waiting for Easter before I go.</p>
                <p>Sunday P.M.: The Wilsons had us all out for tea. Marjorie too so she could see
                    the baby. Saturday evening we saw “The Hamburg Girl”. Horthy was also present
                    with his family. And afterwards we had dinner at a cabaret. Very disappointing
                    after Bucharest. I do wish Aunt Jean would come over, she would so enjoy it all.
                    Opera seats have gone up so we've taken to light operas and movies. There's a
                    tiny movie theater nearby. Yesterday we saw Elsie Ferguson and “Fatty Arbuckle”.
                    Of course I realize he is taboo but I had never seen him before.</p>
                <p>My new cook and maid come tonight and Sunday I hope to have eight for dinner. I
                    trust this maid can serve without dropping everything she touches. I'm trying to
                    have some new clothes but the dressmaker is slow as usual. ... The children are
                    both well and getting fat like their mother. Marjorieis learning to read but
                    it's some effort for her still ... Kempie says some German words, no
                    English.”</p>
                <p>Budapest, June 13, 1922</p>
                <p>"... We have taken to bathing at Margit Sigi in warm sulphur spring water. They
                    made a pool last fall and it certainly is fun to spend the afternoon there. I
                    bought a bathing suit which is conspicuous because it has a skirt so next time I
                    shall try out Carl's one piece one. I was weighed the other day. At present it
                    is about 10 pounds too much. Our cook is too good. I never ate such good things
                    in my life. Marjie says, 'Why Mama, we never had three courses every noon in
                    Florida.' I have cut out dinner at night. Carl has oatmeal and I have a
                    vegetable and strawberries and cream. It costs us more to live than it did when
                    we first came back ...</p>
                <p>Kempie is getting to be a real boy. I feel quite proud of him for he is wearing
                    pants and waists and so far few accidents. I thought we never would train him
                    but have at last. [Poor kid wasn't even two yet.]</p>
                <p>One of my maids was a bit “Bolshie” but a few old clothes have changed her
                    attitude and things are okay again. Fraulein is just fine...</p>
                <p>I'm afraid the children will be grown up and married before we get back again. We
                    are feeling dreadfully poor just now ... “</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>Tatra MountainsAugust 9, 1922</p>
                <p>“I know you'll be wondering if we came or not for the last time I wrote I wasn't
                    sure I could make it. We left home the 31st with the Wilson contingent. She has
                    her brother visiting her, making quite a party in all.</p>
                <p>The mountains are different than any I ever saw, something like the White
                    Mountains. No snow on them now except in patches.</p>
                <p>The hotel is passable, the food not very good and it's costing us more than we
                    can afford to pay. The exchange up here is only 40 to the dollar and prices are
                    high besides. I'm afraid we are spoiled for things are lots cheaper with us. The
                    grounds all around the hotel are lovely, woods and grassy slopes so the children
                    can ramble around safely ... “</p>
                <p>Budapest, August 18</p>
                <p>Our trip did us good in spite of poverty incurred and now I feel able to settle
                    down to a winter of simple life ...</p>
                <p>We came back Wednesday leaving the hotel at six A.M. and arriving here at seven.
                    A long hard trip for the children but they stood it beautifully. I decided
                    however that next year we would try to find some reliable person to leave them
                    with and take a trip by ourselves if possible. While the air up at Tatra was
                    fine both Kempie and Marjie lost weight because of the food. They eat like
                    little pigs here at home... I've been wonderfully well, no active nausea at all
                    but am beginning to lose my sylphlike form. Isn't it aggravating! I hope it's a
                    boy, in which case it will be Edson Burnell or Stuart Burnell. [It wasn't a
                    boy]</p>
                <p>It's no use, I think you and Toss will have to come to the rescue...</p>
                <p>Carl told Mr. Hegstler that a transfer later than fall would be inconvenient so I
                    guess we are here for another year anyway.</p>
                <p>Budapest, September 13, 1922</p>
                <p>... I've some more wants as usual but I'm afraid to have them sent... I don't
                    know of anyone coming out so I guess I'll have to risk it. I want some first
                    size bands and shirts — silk and wool — probably I aught to have three of each.
                    If they are too expensive I'll try to get along with two.</p>
                <p>I don't believe I've written since Carl was away at Belgrade for the ball game.
                    He was gone from Friday night until Wednesday night. Budapest wasn't so
                    dreadfully beaten this time and they had a fine time.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>I was feeling very frisky all the time so Mrs. Wilson and I spent the day
                    together at her house. Out to the Ritz for tea one afternoon etc. It doesn't
                    take much to keel me over and I was deathly sick the day Carl came back. Every
                    so often I have to take the day off.</p>
                <p>Kempie had a nice birthday. The Wilsons were here for lunch with Diana or Dinah
                    as Kempie calls her. She's getting awfully cunning now and Marjorie is anxious
                    for a wee baby. She tried to exchange Kempie for Diana but if she waits long
                    enough she won't need to.</p>
                <p>... We get lots more visiting Americans here than we did at Bucharest. Yesterday
                    we saw Geraldine in the movies. I don't know the name — it was all in Hungarian
                    of course. It was the first time I had ever seen her ...</p>
                <p>I wanted a brown velvet coat for Marjie for best — the material alone came to
                    over twenty dollars so I think we'll have to have other material. I think I
                    shall have my serge suit made into a dress for I have to have something warm in
                    the house this winter... It's been quite cold and one thinks of winter fires.
                    Our coal and wood is in and now I have only to get the stoves in order.</p>
                <p>We had an accident in front of the house not long ago. They are painting the
                    bridge and one of the men fell into the river and was drowned before the boats
                    could reach him. We all saw it and Kempie still talks about the “arme Mann”.
                    [Poor man] Another one fell in at the beginning of the work but knew how to swim
                    and kept himself up until the boats arrived ...</p>
                <p>Marjie and Kempie were glad to hear from Anna and I meant to answer her letter
                    before this. Marjie is laboring over her reading with her father just now.
                    Studying comes hard for her for she cannot keep her mind on anything for any
                    length of time. Are the twins in school this fall? Schooling is going to be a
                    great problem with us especially with so much difference in the children's ages.
                    Most of the people send their children to England or Switzerland as soon as they
                    are old enough ... Oh dear I dread the next few months more than I did the first
                    time. I didn't know what I was dreading then. Do write as often as you
                    can...</p>
                <p>We had a queer pair for tea yesterday. The lady had found the sweetest
                    “atmosphere” in Budapest, especially one day in the street car. Believe me I
                    can't recommend the atmosphere I have found. It's usually so crowded one can't
                    breathe. I had all I could do to keep from smiling ... Aren't you coming over to
                    visit us next spring? I shall never have the courage or money to get to America
                    with three children ...</p>
                <p>Janet Kemp made her appearance on March 15, 1923, and three months later the
                    family moved to Danzig, then a free city, now Gdansk, a Polish one.</p>
                <p>The last two letters in this collection were from Danzig.</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>Danzig, May 5, 1924</p>
                <p>Dearest Sister,</p>
                <p>Bun should be arriving in England now and I can hardly wait for him to arrive in
                    Danzig.</p>
                <p>The last week has been most strenuous. They did find us an empty apartment in
                    Danzig proper — eight rooms besides kitchen and maid's room. We piled out on the
                    30th for I didn't care to be on the streets on May lst. [The day celebrated each
                    year by the Communists] The crowds gathered here in front of our house but all
                    was quiet. You should see us move all our belongings, we are a picture. It's
                    some work to have to live in one place up to the last minute as we had to,
                    though of course the other was furnished. We bought beds and what we absolutely
                    had to have and are really quite at home already. I've just sent to Ernest to
                    please transfer sone funds for us so we can really settle down. The difference
                    in rent will soon pay for the furniture.</p>
                <p>We are on the Commonwealth Avenue of Danzig — three long flights up and no lift.
                    I think I've lost several pounds already. We've a small balcony for Janet praise
                    be for I don't know how I shall ever get her up and down.</p>
                <p>Our rooms are lovely and large, sunny, quiet and warm.</p>
                <p>Buying furniture takes all our savings and then some so our trip home will be
                    delayed another few years I guess. ...</p>
                <p>My last maid left me without notice on May 1st and I was so peeved. Anna is my
                    only help besides a cleaning woman and we are both all in every night. The place
                    had to be thoroughly cleaned besides the unpacking. ... We've an add in
                    tonight's paper and I should have some applicants tomorrow.</p>
                <p>It's colder than Greenland though they say it's May. ...</p>
                <p>Marjorie's Aunt Maude visited them the following summer.</p>
                <p>Danzig, June 22, 1925</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>... Maude wishes to be remembered to you and says to tell you this is just the
                    right place to come for a rest. She seems very happy and is having her first
                    rest in many years. We have been to most of the points of interest but the
                    weather has been dreadful. We never did have a heat wave and have suffered with
                    the cold, not having any Franklin stove. I've introduced Maude to our various
                    friends. Not speaking anything but English she enjoys the English people most.
                    The other crowds are all interesting to watch but speak a number of languages —
                    mostly French — together. Today Maude heard Marjie's lessons, examined her books
                    etc. and says she is way ahead of her age at home. I'm so glad for I had no way
                    of comparing and wondered sometimes if I were doing all right. If I can educate
                    the children at least as far as high school I shall feel quite happy. Teaching
                    is not my forte and I hate it but if I know it's giving them what they need [I]
                    am willing to do it until we are sent to some place where they can get proper
                    schooling. [Anna taught Marjorie using Calvert School until she was eleven years
                    old, when she started school in Danzig. It was after that that she came to be
                    called “Mani”, because her German friends had a hard time with “Marjorie”. Anna
                    also taught Kempie for a couple years, and I was exposed Calvert School
                    kindergarten materials. We all attended schools when we moved to France,
                    although I was taught at home after a fashion until I was eight.]</p>
                <p>Another one of the things I said I never would do...</p>
                <p>We are getting poorer all the time and if something doesn't happen soon I don't
                    know what we shall do to make ends meet. Prices are terrific here and they have
                    just put new duties on most foodstuffs. Maude has been to market twice and
                    wonders how we manage. Carl tuned all the cash over to me some months ago to see
                    if I could make it last any longer but I can't seem to help any ... (Maude) has
                    made me a blouse and pongee skirt since she came. Sews just as you used to — all
                    done in a jiffy and with apparently no effort. Marjorie made a dress for herself
                    which Maude cut out for her. Did very well indeed so I tell her she will soon be
                    able to sew for me.</p>
                <p>We are all well and how I wish you could see the children. Janet is talking now
                    and sweet as she can be ...</p>
                <p>On that happy note the bundles of letters come to a close. With them the first
                    person accounts of the early years of the E.C. Kemp family also end. However
                    there is much more to this story which may or may not get written up in the
                    years ahead. In the interim it is appropriate to include the eulogy given by
                    Ernest Kemp upon his mother's death at the age of 89. In it he captures the
                    spirit of what Anna Smith Kemp accomplished in her long and eventful life.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Anna D. Kemp 1889 - 1978 A Eulogy by C. Ernest Kemp</p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>There are many stories and anecdotes that I could recount which would give an
                    indication of my mother's character and her philosophy of life. Her family was
                    always the center of her existence and she devoted all of her energies to
                    providing a home for my father and instilling in us children those
                    characteristics of thought and behavior which have stood by us all these years.
                    In order to better understand my mother's complete devotion to her task and the
                    strength of character with which she faced many unusual situations I thought it
                    most appropriate at this time to briefly review her life. So many of the
                    successes we children have had are attributable to her and to her devotion to
                    the one task she considered most important, that of raising another generation.
                    Without such a background any tribute to her would be only partially
                    complete.</p>
                <p>My mother, Anna Durkee Smith Kemp, was born in Melrose, Massachusetts to Albert
                    M. Smith and Mary Anna Durkee Smith. Both her mother and father came from
                    Vermont and settled in Massachusetts. Melrose was always home to my mother, even
                    though she spent most of her life traveling to various parts of the world.
                    Mother was the last of five children but never knew her own mother, who died in
                    childbirth.</p>
                <p>She married Edwin Carl Kemp on November 26, 1919. My father had been previously
                    married to one of mother's best friends, who died during the influenza epidemic
                    of 1918. He was stationed in Bucharest, Romania as American Consul. The American
                    Embassy and the Consulate had been closed during the war and it was my father's
                    job to reopen these offices in the war-torn capital of Romania. He wrote to
                    Mother a year after his first wife died, and even though they had never had the
                    opportunity for courtship, he asked her to marry him, to which she agreed.
                    Because my father could not take enough time off to come all the way back to
                    America, they agreed to meet in Paris where they were married and then went
                    immediately on to Bucharest. Although this sort of a whirlwind courtship would
                    not be so surprising today, at that time it was practically unheard of, and is
                    some indication of my mother's character. Although extremely conservative in
                    almost everything she did, and always proper to a fault, she had a deeply buried
                    streak of adventuresomeness which would show up from time to time and which was
                    largely responsible for the interesting life that she was to lead.</p>
                <p>Coming from the well-ordered existence in New England to beginning her life as a
                    married woman in Romania in 1919, was a very difficult adjustment for her to
                    make. Conditions there were terrible, and most of the conveniences that we call
                    necessities today were unattainable luxuries then. I was born the following
                    year, by candlelight, on the kitchen table in a rather elegant but run down
                    third floor apartment. Mother and Dad have told me many stories about our life
                    in Romania, some of them hard to believe.</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>From Romania we were transferred to Budapest in Hungary, and there my sister
                    Janet was born in 1923. This was the post that mother remembered with the
                    greatest fondness. She had been sickly for a good share of the year before but
                    in Hungary she regained her health and was able to enjoy the many advantages of
                    living in one of the most beautiful and cultured capitals of Europe; and this at
                    a time when the American dollar was better than gold and Europe was rapidly
                    recovering from the ravages of war. It was in Budapest that we were joined by my
                    stepsister, Marjorie.</p>
                <p>We then moved to Danzig, on the Baltic Sea, and it is here that I first remember
                    my parents. These were still the years when raising a family was a precarious
                    and chancy business at best, and raising a family in a foreign country presented
                    even greater problems. It is here that I remember the care and love that my
                    mother bestowed on us children, though at the time I don't suppose I really
                    understood the sacrifices in time and worry that were involved. Colds, which
                    today pose no threat, thanks to antibiotics, in those days could turn into fatal
                    pneumonia, and it was not uncommon to hear of some childhood acquaintance that
                    had succumbed to a childhood disease unheard of today. Mother nursed us through
                    our illnesses and watched over our health with meticulous care. And here she
                    also taught me how to read and the rudiments of writing.</p>
                <p>From Danzig we moved to Le Havre, France, and here my younger sister and I
                    started school. Our family life was always very close-knit, and I still vividly
                    remember the weekend drives we took together in the French countryside. It was
                    here, also, that I first came to realize that Mother's role, as she saw it, was
                    to run the family and to provide the proper background for the position my dad
                    held as a representative of the United States. She filled this role with
                    enthusiasm, understanding, and dedication.</p>
                <p>In 1933 we moved to Canada, and for the first time we were able to live a life
                    more characteristic of what could be considered the normal American way. Two
                    years in Moncton, New Brunswick were followed by two years in Winnipeg,
                    Manitoba. Here the family first split up; I came to college at Michigan Tech, my
                    older sister moved to Florida, and Mother, Dad and Janet moved to Bremen,
                    Germany. Although we split up physically, the family remained very close due to
                    the ties that Mother had forged during out many years of travel together. Janet
                    soon left the family to go to college in Vermont and Mother and Dad remained in
                    Bremen.</p>
                <p>While in Bremen, war broke out in Europe and it was here, again, that Mother's
                    character became evident. While most of the wives and families of American
                    Foreign Service Officers stationed in Europe left for home Mother decided to
                    stay, because, as she so often told us, her mission in life was to provide a
                    family life for Dad and us children and as we children were all settled in
                    college or in jobs in the United States, she felt her place was to stay with
                    Dad, no matter what the consequences might be. After spending over a year in
                    wartime Germany, being bombed by British aircraft and spending many nights in a
                    basement bomb shelter, Dad was transferred to Halifax, Nova Scotia and of course
                    Mother came too.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>The trip across war-torn Europe was a long and harrowing one, but with Mother and
                    Dad's remarkable ability to make the best of any situation, they arrived safely
                    in Canada where they remained until the war was over.</p>
                <p>From Halifax they moved to Jamaica, which was Dad's last post before he retired.
                    Mother always spoke well of Jamaica, where she lived in considerable comfort. By
                    this time all her children were well established and as Consul General, Dad's
                    income was sufficient that they could now enjoy the rather sumptuous living that
                    was possible in Jamaica in those days.</p>
                <p>After retirement, Mother and Dad moved to Melrose, and with the exception of a
                    couple of years in Florida, they remained there until my father's death in 1971.
                    My older sister had died in 1966, but Janet and I made frequent trips to Melrose
                    and the family ties remained as strong as ever. It is here again that a facet of
                    Mother's character comes through. After all the years of travel, and the many
                    experiences she had had, she returned to what had always been home to her. Two
                    of her brothers and her older sister were still living in or near Melrose, and
                    she again became part of her original family. Her high school friends, with whom
                    she had corresponded all the years she was away, were still close by and this
                    circle of friends again became a major part of her life. In 1974 failing health
                    and the loss of Dad and all her brothers and sister induced her to come to
                    Michigan to live with us until her health required that she move to the Long
                    Term Care Unit at War Memorial Hospital here in Sault Ste. Marie.</p>
                <p>During the many hours of reminiscing that Mother and I did after she had moved to
                    the hospital, her one recurrent theme was how deeply she felt that she had had a
                    really wonderful life. Therefore as the end came closer and was more and more on
                    her mind she made it plain she could leave with very few regrets.</p>
                <p>Her going will leave a gap in our lives, but the memory of her sense of humor,
                    her innate kindness, her strong sense of duty, and above all her considerateness
                    towards others will remain forever with those of us who knew her.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>BIOGRAPHIC DATA (Anna Durkee Kemp)</p>
                <p>Note: Bernette Chase Kemp and Anna Durkee Smith Kemp were dear friends. Bernette
                    married Edwin Carl Kemp, who entered the Consular Corps in 1914. After Bernette
                    died November 2, 1918, in the influenza epidemic, Edwin Carl Kemp married Anna.
                    The correspondence of the two women was presented to the Foreign Service Spouse
                    Oral History, Inc. by Anna Kemp's daughter, Janet Doell.</p>
                <p>Spouse: Edwin Carl Kemp</p>
                <p>Spouse entered service: 1914Left Service: 1947; Died 1971 <pb facs="0058"
                        n="Page0058"/> Bernette entered service: 1914Left Service: 1918 (died) Anna
                    entered service:1919Left Service: 1947; Died 1978</p>
                <p>Spouses Position: Consul General (1935-47)</p>
                <p>Posts:</p>
                <p>1914St. Pierre and Miquelon, French possession (islands) 1915Detailed to
                    Marseilles, France 1916Tunis, Tunisia 1919Bucharest, Romania 1920Detailed to
                    Budapest, Hungary 1923Danzig, Free City of 1929Le Havre, France 1933Moncton, New
                    Brunswick, Canada 1935Winnipeg, Canada (Consul General) 1937Bremen,
                    German(Consul General &amp; Sec. in Diplomatic Service) 1941Halifax, Nova
                    Scotia, Canada (Consul General) 1945Kingston, Jamaic(Consul General)</p>
                <p>Maiden Name: Bernette ChaseParents:</p>
                <p>John Frank Chase</p>
                <p>Maria Merrill Chase Place/Date of birth: Augusta, Maine; January 5, 1884
                    Date/Place of Marriage:Saluda, North Carolina; September 11, 1909 Profession:
                    Nurse, and a Foreign Service spouse for four years, 1914-1918.</p>
                <p>Maiden Name: Anna Durkee SmithParents:</p>
                <p>Albert M. Smith</p>
                <p>Mary Anna Durkee Smith Place/Date of birth: Melrose, Massachusetts; December 27,
                    1889 Education: Melrose High School Date/Place of Marriage: November 26, 1919;
                    Paris, France Profession: Foreign Service spouse</p>
                <p>Children of Bernette and Edwin Kemp:</p>
                <p>Marjorie K. O'Mara (born 1916; deceased 1966)</p>
                <p>Dorothy Kemp (born 1911; deceased 1912, age 1 year)</p>
                <p>Children of Anna and Edwin Kemp:</p>
                <p>Ernest Kemp (born 1920)</p>
                <p>Janet Kemp Doell (born 1923)</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
