<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001204">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Leonard Unger </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR LEONARD UNGER</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 10, 1989</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mr. Ambassador, how did you become interested in foreign
                        affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I started my career in Washington as a geographer and with emphasis on
                    problems in the United States, at an organization then going called the National
                    Resources Planning Board.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I came down to Washington directly from college. Graduated in the spring
                    of 1939 from Harvard. I was a geography concentrator, a rather unusual field, at
                    least for Harvard it was. But I was sent down to a geographer who was working at
                    the National Resources Planning Board, as well as to some people in the
                    Department of Agriculture who were working in similar fields. The geographer was
                    Gilbert White who was working closely also with a political scientist named John
                    Miller in the National Resources Planning Board. They were working on
                    development problems all focused on the United States.</p>
                <p>This was an era of national planning, national resources planning, industrial
                    planning, planning for agricultural development, that kind of thing. But it
                    initially focused on the United States. I was in this work for a period of
                    years. This agency I'm speaking about was the National Resources Planning
                    Board.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which came under whom?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: It was directly under the President. It was the President's uncle,
                    Frederick Delano who was Chairman of the Board, and Charles Eliot, who was the
                    active head of the organization and the head of the Board of overseeing
                    governors that included a number of prestigious people.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>In those days, before World War II, planning initially meant something derived
                    from city planning and landscape planning. They had only begun to deal with
                    planning in the broader sense that it took on with the National Resources
                    Planning Board and with some other U.S. Government agencies. This was one of the
                    high moments of the New Deal, you know, when this kind of thing was new and
                    developing.</p>
                <p>It, of course, was cut short as World War II began and as U.S. involvement in the
                    war grew. So a lot of that activity was curtailed and eventually terminated.
                    Many of the people involved in it, myself included, were moved into the
                    international field. I was asked to come over to the State Department to work in
                    the Office of the Geographer.</p>
                <p>The Officer of the Geographer, at that time, was working out a whole series of
                    essentially post-war plans for use by the people who would ultimately be
                    attending a peace conference and working out a post-war peace arrangement.</p>
                <p>At this point, the United States was not even in the war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were we thinking about? How did we view the war? I
                        mean this was before we came into it. Were we looking toward an ultimate
                        Allied victory?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. There had been lend lease and there had been the transfer of
                    destroyers to the British. There was no question where Franklin Roosevelt stood
                    and his Administration, namely, totally sympathetic with the Allied war against
                    the Axis. Of course, this was a hundred times magnified when the United States
                    itself became involved immediately after Pearl Harbor. So a lot of this planning
                    was taking place. Thinking back to post-World War I, and the studies that were
                    developed by a very well known Johns Hopkins professor, who was a geography
                    professor and later became President of Johns Hopkins. (Ambassador Unger later
                    identified this man as Isaiah Bowman). Anyway, the State Department had the
                    records of the studies made at that time, and the plans that were made for the
                    Treaty of Versailles and all of the various economic and territorial provisions
                    of that sort. So prior to the United States becoming involved in the war
                    directly, this kind of planning was moving ahead and studies were being brought
                    up to date. Then, of course, it took on a much more specific and much more
                    immediate aspect once the United States was involved.</p>
                <p>I was sent over to the old State Department building. A group of us were involved
                    in this activity. We were asked to be excused from direct military service
                    because it was felt that this was something that was required to be done. Those
                    of us who had been involved in it, by that time for quite a number of months,
                    should continue and get this done against the day when the war was won and
                    people would be sitting down for peace negotiations.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>So I was involved in that. The first meetings of the Foreign Ministers took
                    place, first in London and then in Paris, and led in the summer of 1946 to the
                    negotiations for the Treaty of Paris. I was at each one of the negotiations
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your particular responsibilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I was pretty much low man on the totem pole. I was doing research on
                    boundary problems, on economic functioning. In other words, if a new boundary
                    was to be drawn, as it was drawn between Yugoslavia and Italy, between Italy and
                    France, between Italy and Austria—those happened to be the areas that I was most
                    involved in, as well as some of the Balkan situations—the question was, what
                    kind of a boundary could be drawn that would do least violence to ethnic
                    situations but at the same time also not be an economic nonsense?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any sort of imperatives that were working
                        there? At your level, people say, “Well, never again will we do this. We saw
                        the mistakes.” Were there certain things that, at least, in your thinking,
                        that we've really got to avoid this or that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Oh, yes. There was a great deal of feeling on the part of people who had
                    studied the Treaty of Versailles and all the related treaties that some very
                    grievous errors that had been committed. Of course, one such case was the
                    economic burden put on Germany, but also some of the territorial decisions were
                    considered mistakes. For example, whatever any American may have felt, the
                    Yugoslavs obviously felt bitter that the head of the Adriatic had been lost—the
                    two good outlets to the sea, namely, Trieste and Fiume, which had been taken
                    over (illegally, in the case of Fiume) after World War I, taken over by Italy.
                    The Yugoslavs felt that this was territory, including the territory going north
                    all the way up into the Alps, that was inhabited by Yugoslav people and it
                    should be ceded to Yugoslavia. They felt the Port of Trieste was a natural for
                    them and that it should be ceded to them as their major outlet. Also, they felt
                    that the population in Trieste was either Yugoslav, or Yugoslav converted to
                    Italian after World War I. So these were all the kinds of issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the German-speaking people up at the
                        Italian-Austrian border?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Right, like the Alto Adige, “Trento e Trieste and all of that.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>Well, to jump ahead a little bit, when the war in Europe had come to an end, a
                    Four-Power Commission was established (in 1945 or early 1946), British, French,
                    American and Russian to visit, in anticipation of a peace conference, the
                    Italian-Yugoslav and Austrian border areas. The task was to consult the
                    population and come to a conclusion as to where the new boundary should be
                    drawn. When everybody on that Commission got to London and then subsequently
                    moved over to Paris for the Peace Conference, needless to say, the Russians drew
                    a line far to the west, practically out on the Venetian plain. The Americans, on
                    the other extreme, drew a line that was only a little bit west of what had been
                    the post-World War I boundary. The French were closer to the Russians. The
                    British were closer to the Americans. But there were four lines.</p>
                <p>Ultimately, after a great deal of negotiation in Paris, and sending further
                    groups out to investigate specific situations, the decision was made—as you can
                    read it in the Italian Peace Treaty—to set up a Free Territory of Trieste which
                    would be an independent entity, neither under Yugoslavia nor under Italy.</p>
                <p>I'm trying to remember precisely why that solution was never realized. It was to
                    go ahead and a governor was to be appointed, but with the 1948 elections
                    impending in Italy it became a very sensitive political issue. It was the
                    conviction that these were crucial elections that could spell the difference
                    between Italy remaining essentially western-oriented and eventually not only a
                    part of the Marshall Plan, but a part of NATO, et cetera; or Italy might go
                    Communist and become essentially a part of the Eastern bloc.</p>
                <p>The elections were crucial. One of the political steps taken, in anticipation of
                    the election, was the Tripartite Declaration by United States, France and
                    Britain of March 20, 1948, saying that Trieste (without being too specific as to
                    area, etc.) should be returned to Italy; it was said to be basically Italian. In
                    spite of what was provided in the Peace Treaty, namely setting up a Free
                    Territory Trieste, this Italian city “should be returned to Italy.” The
                    presumption is that this declaration had considerable impact on the voters in
                    Italy, reduced the pro-Communist vote, and Italy stayed with the west and
                    eventually joined NATO, et cetera.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it was a very practical, almost a tactical, decision
                        because of the immediate situation, the concern that Italy always has had a
                        very strong Communist party. But in 1948, there seemed to be the possibility
                        that it would join the Eastern bloc.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: The conviction was that, once this had taken place, if it did, there was
                    no turning back. The Soviet Union would make very sure that it would remain
                    securely Communist. Now, of course, with all the things that subsequently have
                    happened, starting with Yugoslavia, and now much more broadly, none of that took
                    place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You became Assistant Chief of Southeast European Affairs
                        in the State Department.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>UNGER: As time went on, yes. But in the immediate peace negotiation situation in
                    1946, I was in London as part of that delegation, having been on delegations
                    that actually visited the area in order “to consult the population.” I was on
                    two commissions. One was the commission that was sent prior to the peace treaty
                    negotiations in Paris in the summer. Then, once the decision was made for the
                    Peace Treaty with Italy to set up the Free Territory of Trieste, it was
                    recognized that Trieste would be a kind of economic monstrosity. Therefore, a
                    Four-Power Economic Commission was set up to go to Trieste and analyze the whole
                    area, analyze the economic situation, and see what could be done and what kind
                    of outside assistance was going to be required, particularly during an initial
                    period, to get the new FTT on its feet.</p>
                <p>I was the U.S. Commissioner on that Four-Power Commission. That was in January,
                    or perhaps early February of '47.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any sort of marching orders when you went out
                        there? Was the American attitude, at that particular time, to see what's
                        fair?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: There were general marching orders, yes. One I've already mentioned.
                    Namely, that as far as the United States was concerned, for very broad political
                    reasons, Italy must be kept in the western orbit. Trieste was a crucial factor
                    in this. If Trieste were lost to Italy and awarded to Yugoslavia, this would be
                    an impossible situation. The Communist party in Italy would be able to exploit
                    any such decision so that Italy might well join the Eastern bloc. Now,
                    specifically—I'm jumping around a little bit—but on that point, a declaration
                    was made in anticipation of the crucial Italian election—this was the Tripartite
                    Declaration (already mentioned) that stated that Trieste should be returned to
                    Italy and, therefore, there would be no “Free Territory of Trieste.”</p>
                <p>But in the meantime there was the possibility that the Free Territory would be
                    set up and would face serious economic problems. So there was appointed an
                    Economic Commission to try to decide what kind of help a Free Territory would
                    need, once it was set up. I was the International Secretary of that Commission
                    that went out in February of '47.</p>
                <p>Then, on March 20 of 1948, at the time of the crucial Italian election, a
                    declaration was made recommending the return of Trieste to Italy. Once the
                    declaration was made, it was perfectly clear that, whatever happened, a Free
                    Territory of Trieste, as provided for in the Italian Peace Treaty, was not going
                    to be realized. Therefore, the economic study that had been made was more or
                    less irrelevant. But it was, of course, not until many years later, namely in
                    the fall of 1954, that the thing was finally settled and the City of Trieste was
                    in fact reincorporated into Italy. Much of the remainder of the Free Territory
                    was incorporated into Yugoslavia. That was as a result of secret negotiations in
                    London from February to October in 1954, where I took part as assistant to the
                    U.S. negotiator, Ambassador Llewellyn Thompson.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To go back to this time when you were out there. When you
                        say you consulted the people, can you give a little idea of how you went
                        about it? After these consultations—obviously, we had political reasons for
                        doing this, thus and so—but how did you personally feel? What was your
                        personal judgment and the members of your Commission?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: There was definitely a mixed feeling. As I said, Professor Philip Mosley
                    of Columbia Univ. was the leader; I'm talking now about the 1946 Boundary
                    Commission. This was, for me, a new part of the world, in the sense that
                    although I had become familiar with it in Washington, from all the documents and
                    talking to people, et cetera, I had never been out there. So when we went out
                    there, certainly objective number one was to learn as much as possible, to get
                    as objective a view as we could of—in the first place—the ethnic situation.</p>
                <p>We knew, for example, that once Mussolini had taken over in Italy any kind of
                    study, ethnic survey, census or whatever, would certainly be distorted to suit
                    his purposes. So we had to discount that kind of thing.</p>
                <p>We knew at the same time, that, with anything that had been done post-World War
                    II in the area occupied by Yugoslavia, which was most of the area in real terms
                    if not population, the inhabitants would be told pretty well what they were
                    supposed to say in response to any kind of a census. So we had a difficult task.
                    We had a lot of statistics that we had to evaluate, looking wherever possible
                    for legitimate and valid indications of the sentiment of the people in the area.
                    We had all kinds of linguistic and ethnic information which we had to evaluate
                    it as to how valid it was. The idea was to draw a line—I think that was the
                    instructions of the Boundary Commission—to draw a line leaving the minimum of
                    the other nationality on the “wrong” side of the boundary.</p>
                <p>I think this was an education for me in “real politic.” It became clear,
                    certainly, that given British, French and American objectives with reference to
                    Italy, namely, to keep Italian politics from going over in the Communist
                    direction, that we were certainly going to be working for a settlement that
                    would be at least acceptable in Italy, and not be exploited by the Communist
                    party in Italy to win a lot of votes for its side.</p>
                <p>At the same time, as the Boundary Commission put under way in '46, Yugoslavia was
                    an ally and Italy was the defeated enemy. And so there were definite limits as
                    to how much and how far our Commission could go. I don't know how familiar you
                    are with boundary problems and population problems and ethnic distributions and
                    so on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I lived for five years in Yugoslavia so I know about the
                        ethnic overlap in that area.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. It's almost impossible to draw a fair boundary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There is no way you can draw a fair boundary.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: That's right, because among other things, urban areas are predominantly
                    Italian. Even though you know the names of people who profess to be stoutly
                    Italian, you know that in many cases they have to have had Yugoslav origins,
                    remotely, somewhere and sometime.</p>
                <p>(Well, I'm glad you were in Yugoslavia because you know what kind of a situation
                    this was!)</p>
                <p>Anyway, the Peace Treaty ultimately set up the Free Territory of Trieste as a
                    compromise measure. Initially, pending the time when the provisions setting up
                    the Free Territory would come into force, the Allied military government
                    continued to govern in the northern part, including the city. The Yugoslav
                    military government continued to govern in the south.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The British put troops in very quickly because of the
                        dispute there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: There was a very, very tense moment right at the very end of the war, well
                    before the Peace Treaty. There had been no decision as to what would be the
                    ultimate fate of this area. As far as the Yugoslavs were concerned, it was going
                    to be part of Yugoslavia. And Tito moved his troops very rapidly, a contingent
                    of them, to arrive in Trieste before the Allied Forces got there. The Allied
                    Forces were working their way up the Italian Adriatic Coast, to Venice and
                    beyond, and eventually they arrived at Trieste. There was a confrontation which,
                    fortunately, never turned into an active battle. But it was a very tense period
                    and initially Trieste was occupied by both Yugoslav and Allied Forces, but the
                    Yugoslavs ultimately agreed to withdraw from the center of the city.</p>
                <p>When I went to the Trieste area with the Boundary Commission (sent by the Council
                    of Foreign Ministers) in '46, the Yugoslavs were still all over the place, and
                    certainly in force up on the Carso, the high plateau behind the city (the Karst
                    is the way the Yugoslavs would refer to it). So it was still very tense and the
                    Yugoslavs were still determined to remain physically present to support their
                    claim. Of course, where the boundary was ultimately drawn, all of Zone B, the
                    southern part of what had been intended to be the Free Territory of Trieste, was
                    in fact handed over to Yugoslavia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll come back to Trieste a little later for the final
                        settlement which was in the mid-50s, I guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes, 1954.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After that work, you came back and were dealing with
                        Southeast Europe?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. I was the Deputy Assistant Secretary for Europe, under Livingston
                    Merchant. The head of the Office of Southern European Affairs was Walworth
                    Barbour and his immediate deputy was Walter Dowling. I was sort of a second
                    deputy with responsibility for the Trieste problem and the Balkans. The Southern
                    European Division at that time included Italy and the Balkans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Two questions: How did we view the Balkans at that
                        particular time, this is '48, '49. It's not in our area and we're sort of
                        mildly interested, but that's a Soviet problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I think that point of view eventually and reluctantly was adopted, but not
                    initially. In each of the defeated countries, in Hungary, Romania and Bulgaria,
                    there was something called Allied Control Commission, just as there was also
                    such a Commission in Italy, (and I guess later in Germany and Austria).</p>
                <p>The Allied Control Commissions were, quadripartite: Soviet, American, British and
                    French; each nation was represented by a commissioner. In Hungary, Romania and
                    Bulgaria, I'm sure the chairman was Soviet; in Italy, it was probably an
                    American.The idea was that these were charged with the faithful execution of the
                    Treaties of Peace, although, they had already been established, on a more
                    strictly military basis, prior to the coming into force of the Peace Treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From your level, did the people around you see any
                        leverage or working?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Oh, yes, we worked a lot on that. I'd cite Hungary in particular; in
                    Hungary, there were very prominent figures who were anxious to work with the
                    British, French, Americans and in general, with the West. They were realistic
                    about the fact that the Soviets were in charge, but they wanted to keep channels
                    open. I'm sure those names are familiar: Nagy, and others in Hungary, who at
                    very considerable risk to their person, took positions insisting on a continued
                    British, American and French presence in the Allied Control Commission.</p>
                <p>In due course, those Commissions came to an end; their job was over. And little
                    by little, in each one of the three countries mentioned, the Western Allied role
                    became more and more circumscribed. There always was the possibility of doing
                    something intended to protect the individuals who wanted to speak out for more
                    than just total Soviet domination. But those people often didn't last very long
                    and there wasn't a great deal of protection that could be provided.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>The Soviet contention was that precisely the reverse was true in Italy. But I
                    think it's fair to say it wasn't; there was an active, flourishing Communist
                    party in Italy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel at the time—we're talking about the '48, '49
                        period—whether the State Department could work with the Soviet Union?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: We thought so initially, yes. This was the whole idea: we were allies.
                    Obviously, we had a different form of government from theirs, but we had all
                    been very much opposed to the Nazis and the Fascists and the Japanese. We were
                    all working for a different kind of world order. There was—I'm sure you know
                    this from your own reading, although I don't know how far back your
                    recollections go—there was an era, shall we say an “era of good feeling”, of a
                    lot of illusion in the United States about the Soviet Union and about the
                    possibility of working with them, and so on. Particularly, of course, when this
                    was put up against attitudes about the Nazis, the Fascists and the Japanese.</p>
                <p>The change of attitude came only through the experience, for example, of these
                    Allied Control Commissions, i.e. the activities of the Italian Communist Party,
                    and so on. And in the Central European situation there was again a quadripartite
                    government and a Russian role in that: the Russian role, in their sector of
                    Germany and their sector of Austria. The fact was that these Soviet-administered
                    areas were essentially forbidden territories for Allied officials, whereas the
                    Russians were quite free to come and go on the other side.</p>
                <p>What had been a wartime alliance and an era of good feeling obviously
                    deteriorated fairly rapidly under these circumstances and tensions rose.
                    Ultimately, of course, this new situation was reflected in the creation of NATO.
                    In the earlier situation and prior to NATO there was the Marshall Plan. (I don't
                    know if you know, but at one point Czechoslovakia was going to be included in
                    the Marshall Plan but was excluded, presumably on Russian insistence). Then the
                    security and military threat to Western Europe developed and it became more and
                    more sharply recognized. That's of course, when people began to talk about
                    military cooperation, and NATO was the result. I was very much involved in that;
                    I was one of the ushers for the first NATO session down on the Mall in
                    Washington!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: This is a little hard to be precise; I would guess the spring of '47. I
                    think that's when NATO was first brought into existence but I'm not sure of my
                    dates.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is again because you were dealing with Europe in the
                        State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. I was, by that time, totally out of the Geographer's Office and was
                    in the European Bureau in something called European Regional Affairs (no longer
                    working on Southern Europe alone. Lane Timmons was my boss at one time and
                    Livingston Merchant was the Assistant Secretary. The European Regional Affairs
                    Office was unlike all of the other offices which were related to a particular
                    area, whether it was Eastern Europe or Southern Europe or Western Europe. In
                    Regional Affairs we had an overall mandate for a number of special problems,
                    which included the Marshall Plan and NATO, and various politico-military
                    agreements.</p>
                <p>For example, I'm not sure of my year, but it probably was '49, I was sent to Rome
                    as head of a group that was to discuss, with the Italian government, the
                    military aid program and to work out a bilateral agreement on that subject.
                    There were several outstanding problems that needed to be ironed out. It was not
                    until 1950 that I was sent to Trieste as Political Adviser to the (British)
                    Commanding General.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to get a little of your experience. You were with
                        the area that was dealing with Italy, among other things, in the '48
                        election. Was this, in a way, a bad experience? If we wanted to we could
                        pull out all stops to support a country. In the first place, how were you
                        involved? How did you see it at the time? In retrospect, was this a bad
                        lesson for us?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I guess not—I would say “no”. We sought a good answer among some very
                    stark alternatives. Remember, this was an era when, after our wartime alliance
                    with the Soviet Union, we became persuaded the Soviet Union was out to get all
                    it could get in Europe, to dominate the European scene and move beyond the areas
                    where it was initially established. Of course, Italy was a prime target. A lot
                    of us had been enthusiastic comrades of the Russians in the wartime period. When
                    we went to Paris to begin to negotiate the peace treaties and, prior to that, in
                    fact, in the operation of some of these Boundary Commissions I was involved in,
                    we were pals with our Russian counterparts. We had fought the war together; we
                    had defeated the Axis; so then we were in an era of good feeling and peace.</p>
                <p>Then we began to find out how they functioned internationally, and that to them
                    objective facts were a matter of total indifference. [Laughter] And, of course,
                    it was particularly disturbing because some of the people that they sent—they
                    obviously had to be chosen at random, often including people who had very little
                    experience abroad—were perfectly decent, honest types. They knew what they were
                    saying was a lot of “baloney”! But their orders, of course, were very strict.
                    Every once in a while, over quite a number of vodkas in a hotel bar somewhere,
                    one of these guys would take his hair down and even cry. They were realizing
                    what it was they were being ordered to do, and we were realizing the true nature
                    of the Soviet government, in terms of its international functioning and its
                    policies and objectives.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>This, as I say, came as a gross disappointment. But, of course, once the pattern
                    was set, it was only many, many years later that those of us who had been
                    through this experience were ready to begin to think about a more reasonable and
                    constructive relationship with the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm not using this in pejorative terms but a real true
                        hard experience, a real mindset had been developed by people who went in
                        with relatively goodwill and realizing what they were up against. I mean
                        maybe this is the wrong term but the “Cold Warrior” mentality was based on
                        experience.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Oh, absolutely. It was not a point of view that any of us wanted to adopt.
                    Even once it was adopted there were some of the practitioners, who as far as I
                    and many of my colleagues were concerned, were going much too far. But we all
                    had to become realistic about what the Soviet system was, what their objectives
                    seemed to be, how they were prepared to try to implement them, what their plan
                    was for Eastern Europe and as much of Western Europe as they could gobble up.
                    The pressure points are perfectly well known, and Trieste was one of them;
                    Greece and Turkey, to some extent were; Austria certainly was—also Berlin.</p>
                <p>And then, of course, this began to have its expressions in the Far East. But I
                    didn't get to the Far East until my assignment to Bangkok in 1958.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went to Trieste as a political adviser which was in
                        1950?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. This, of course, was after the Peace Treaty had been settled.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing as a POLAD, which is a political
                        adviser?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: These weren't the first POLADs. There had been a POLAD to the various
                    military commanders. Bob Murphy, for example, was a POLAD in North Africa when
                    the Allied invasion took place there. Then I think he, and others following him,
                    were POLADs in Rome, when we still had a Military government in Italy. There was
                    a POLAD in Germany. Doug MacArthur—not the General, his nephew—was a POLAD at
                    SHAPE. I was Doug's counterpart after I moved from my POLAD activities in
                    Trieste to my POLAD activities in Naples, which were of a totally different
                    order. But again, I was Political Adviser because at that time—and I think it
                    still is true—where we had a military government or a NATO Command, we usually
                    had attached to them a political adviser.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's a political POLAD still in Naples.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>UNGER: Is there still?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. My last post overseas was Consul General in
                        Naples. What were you doing in Trieste as POLAD?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: In the first place, I was the channel for relaying State Department
                    opinions and instructions. Also, I was the channel for keeping the State
                    Department informed of what was taking place in Trieste. I was a Political
                    Adviser, in that case, to a British Commanding General. He had an American
                    deputy. He also had an American general who was in charge of civil affairs. This
                    was all under Allied military government. I served as a POLAD, in effect, to all
                    of them; I was the person who was supposed to convey to them State Department
                    instructions. To be sure, they weren't being instructed by the State Department
                    so my instructions were to tell them our point of view, to discuss with them
                    steps that we felt should be taken, or changes that should be made in some of
                    their decisions, or the way they were administrating the area.</p>
                <p>I also had responsibility for being in touch with as many good sources as
                    possible, to gain a feeling for the local political and economic situations.
                    Were there crises building up? How was the Military government accepted and seen
                    by the local leaders and people? What was it doing that was damaging to our
                    collective U.S. and British policies? Also, by this time, the American
                    commitment to the eventual return of Trieste to Italy was well established. The
                    British tended to be a little bit more on the fence on that one; they had a very
                    sharp eye on Yugoslavia at that time and wished to be conciliatory with Tito. So
                    these things had to be resolved in our working out what kinds of decisions we
                    would make; this meant civilian-military compromises and American-British
                    compromises.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying you were not acting as a professor, that
                        you were having to deal with real problems that had to be resolved. How did
                        you find the Military responded to you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: It depended a great deal on the individual situation. There were definite
                    British and American differences, to say nothing of differences with the French,
                    the Yugoslavs, and the Italians when we had to deal with them, which we did from
                    time to time.</p>
                <p>The British were old, experienced hands at this kind of arrangement. To have a
                    British General administering was situation that they had had a lot of
                    experience with before. Also, the British Political Adviser, who was from the
                    British Foreign Office, had a very clear and well understood relationship with
                    his superior.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>The American General, who was deputy to the British Commanding General—and, of
                    course, I worked with both generals—the American General was a hearty military
                    man who was very sharp and very perceptive, but sometimes quite impatient of
                    some of the political considerations that I felt I had to bring to his
                    attention. He saw it more as an exclusively military task. I believe that I had
                    a very good relationship with the British commander as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was that, do you know?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Terence Airey was the first one. He was really out of British Intelligence
                    and had served in Switzerland some of the time during World War II. He was
                    followed by a totally different individual, General John Winterton, who was a
                    bluff British military type-a combat soldier. We got along famously, but he had
                    a totally different approach to everything from Airey. Airey was extremely adept
                    and he really didn't need political advisers; he was his own political adviser!
                    Winterton badly needed political advisers, and, by and large, he was responsive
                    to our advice. They were two very different people.</p>
                <p>My next “political adviser” job was in Naples.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did that involve?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: That is the headquarters of the Southern command of NATO.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was 1952 to 1953?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I guess that's right, yes. NATO had, of course, not very long since been
                    set up and had started functioning with its first headquarters in Paris. Then
                    three regional NATO headquarters were established: one for Northern Europe,
                    somewhere in Scandinavia, one for Central Europe and one for Southern Europe, in
                    Naples. The commander—I don't think he was the first, I think it had already
                    been set up for a while—the second commander was Admiral Carney.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's always been an admiral there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: In the Southern Command, that's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Admiral Forrest Sherman was the first.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>UNGER: I think you're right—he was the first and he either came from, or then
                    went on to Spain; I'm quite sure he didn't have a political adviser. But then
                    Admiral Carney came; Carney was a very political type and had very good feelings
                    for the political situation. He realized that his command was going to be
                    involved willy-nilly in a number of circumstances, all the way from the Middle
                    East, then particularly Greece and Turkey, Italy and Yugoslavia, Spain,
                    Portugal, Gibraltar, et cetera. Even North Africa. He felt that he needed, if
                    nothing else, information and, perhaps on occasion, political advice.</p>
                <p>So I was assigned to the embassy in Rome but to be resident in Naples, as adviser
                    to him. I got, from Rome, telegraphic material and dispatches and a variety of
                    reporting from many sources, which I sorted, referenced, organized and passed on
                    to him, to keep him informed as to what was going on in his region. When he
                    would have visitors from around that region, political leaders and military
                    leaders from all the various Mediterranean countries, he would usually have me
                    come for lunch and/or a meeting. I traveled with him to Athens and Istanbul and
                    once to Spain. He was very conscious of the political factors and very anxious
                    to be as fully informed as possible. He obviously enjoyed the political side. So
                    that was my job with him, and he was Commander all the time that I was
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the view of Turkey and Greece? Were they both
                        with NATO at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because I know much later that was certainly a thorn in
                        the side of the NATO commander, the relationship. How was it at your
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: It was just developing. In both cases, there were some tricky problems.
                    But the sharp tensions between the two countries hadn't yet developed. Everybody
                    knew that there were problems and there were territorial disputes, et cetera.
                    Cyprus was, I think, still administered by the British. So the differences were
                    not all that acute. Turkey was just beginning to get used to being a part of the
                    European world, the Mediterranean world. They had people at the command and they
                    had a great deal to learn. But they were anxious to learn.</p>
                <p>For example, we went to Ankara; there, of course, my first contact was with the
                    American Embassy to get a good reading on the situation. Then I went with Carney
                    to call on the various political figures in the Turkish government. Then we went
                    to Istanbul and similarly talked to people. He went, at one point, I think, to
                    Izmir. I never did; Izmir was a NATO subcommand, just being set up.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>As I say, I often went with him to Rome. He, in fact, also had a POLAD seconded
                    to him by the Italian government, who was half of the time in Rome and half of
                    the time in Naples. I worked very closely with him.</p>
                <p>I'm trying to think if there were any other POLADs—I don't think so. There may
                    have been some later on but I don't think there were any others at that
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wonder if you could maybe skip ahead to your involvement
                        in the final Trieste negotiations. What were you doing? What were the
                        problems that you saw at the time? This was in 1956, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: No, 1954; we settled the problem on October 8th, 1954, I think. I have
                    recently been into those files at the Archives; as a matter of fact—I don't know
                    whether I brought it—I've just written a study on that subject which is going to
                    be published. It's one of a series at Johns Hopkins, SAIS, they're doing on
                    negotiating histories.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One can refer to that for the details. What was your
                        viewpoint of this and how were you involved?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I was asked by Ambassador Thompson, who was then our Ambassador in Austria
                    and who had been assigned, as a secret mission, the task of representing the
                    U.S. in a negotiation to resolve the Trieste problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thompson?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Llewellyn Thompson. He was our Ambassador in Vienna. He had previously
                    been Counselor of the Embassy in Rome, so he knew the Trieste situation. These
                    were secret negotiations in London that began in February of '54.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With whom?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>UNGER: First, with the Yugoslavs, and then with the Italians; we were working
                    jointly with the British. In other words, the first meetings took place when
                    Thompson and Geoffrey Harrison, his British Foreign Office counterpart, met with
                    Vladko Velebit, the Yugoslav Ambassador to London. Then, after extended
                    discussions, they met with Manlio Brosio, the Italian Ambassador. Those
                    individual discussions went on for a while; then it became a matter of moving
                    back and forth, trying to narrow the differences. Eventually, the four parties
                    did arrive at an agreed solution, which was announced on October 8th, 1954. And
                    that was the settlement of the Trieste problem, which represented, essentially,
                    a compromise division in which the city of Trieste was returned to Italy, after
                    all those years, and most of the remainder of the territory was ceded to
                    Yugoslavia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the first place, your role must have been “Mr. Trieste”
                        through that period. You spent a great amount of your Foreign Service life
                        dealing with Trieste.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Of course I had, at one point, branched out to the whole southern European
                    and Mediterranean scene, particularly when I was in Naples as Political Adviser
                    to the NATO Commander and had to be conversant with the situation in that entire
                    region. Then I had gone back to Washington and became much more involved in the
                    whole European picture. Specifically, NATO and the Marshall Plan. That's when I
                    was with the European Regional Bureau which had responsibility for these
                    regional activities.</p>
                <p>Then, because of my past association—Tommy Thompson knew me when we had been
                    together when he was Counselor at the Embassy in Rome and he knew of my having
                    been on the Trieste Commission—so when he was selecting his group to go and work
                    on the negotiations in London, he asked me, or asked my superiors to release me,
                    to go with him to London, which I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was in it for the Yugoslavs? Apparently, in the
                        public's awareness, it seemed they made the biggest concession.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Well, the Yugoslavs, at that point, had fallen out with the Russians; this
                    had happened only a little while before. Although they certainly had never said
                    so in so many words, except in very confidential circumstances, they were
                    looking for help from the West. They figured the time had come to make their
                    peace with the United States and with the Western Europeans, and specifically
                    with the Italians.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>At that time, there was a lot of talk about an Italian-Greek-Turkish Alliance.
                    This, of course, was when the Soviet Union and its Allies in Eastern Europe were
                    considered an active threat. The Yugoslavs, having broken away from Stalin and
                    Tito having taken his independent stand, led some to think that this three-power
                    arrangement might be expanded to a Four-Power Association of some sort,
                    including Yugoslavia. In any event, Yugoslavia was clearly intent on getting rid
                    of any problems and situations troubling its relations with the West,
                    particularly with the British and Americans, and also with the Italians.</p>
                <p>Trieste was still the outstanding bone of contention; there was always trouble
                    there. Even when I was there as Political Adviser there were frequent
                    demonstrations and occasional riots, even though things had calmed down a good
                    deal. The conviction was that, if there was to be a constructive relationship
                    between Yugoslavia and Italy, this problem just had to be put out of the
                    way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned Ambassador Thompson conducted the secret
                        negotiations. Why is it, that in the popular mind, Clare Boothe Luce, our
                        Ambassador to Italy, had sort of been given the public credit for this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: That's the way she wanted it. She was a very articulate and vocal person.
                    She knew how to get to the press. Tommy was not out for publicity. I wouldn't
                    say he was a retiring person, but, in a sense, he didn't give a damn. His
                    objective was to get settled what had been a very troublesome and potentially
                    very explosive issue. He knew that the people he wanted to impress knew what he
                    had done. I mean, Mrs. Luce was helpful, as was Jimmy Riddleberger, our
                    Ambassador in Yugoslavia. He had to do everything he could to put the Yugoslavs
                    in a frame of mind where they would accept a compromise settlement. So she had
                    to do that at the Rome end and she worked quite hard for that.</p>
                <p>But the real genius in this thing was Tommy, without any question.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was also the great negotiator for Austria, too. Really
                        looking at the art of diplomacy, as one thinks of it. Really sitting down
                        with people and doing it. His finger was in two major pies.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Absolutely. Well, then, of course, he had a lot of other negotiations that
                    he had a certain amount, if not a major responsibility for; for example when he
                    was ambassador in the Soviet Union. He was involved in quite a number of things
                    there, as he was also when he was in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Working with him, what was your impression of his method
                        of operation?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>UNGER: Well, it was a very personal method. He was leery of institutional
                    approaches. He was a diplomat of the old school, but thoroughly alert and aware
                    of the modern age. It wasn't that he didn't understand how things happened in
                    1954—at that time, and all the years afterward, as long as he lived. He was very
                    much alive to how things had to be done. But he had strong convictions about the
                    personal role.</p>
                <p>A big splash in the newspapers, and all of that, was something he didn't want to
                    have any part in. And, in fact, as I say, I think the Trieste negotiation,
                    because of the way he conducted it—and the British went along with it—and
                    because of the very special relationship he had with the newspaper people—in
                    other words, he didn't ignore the newspapers—he knew how to work with them. He
                    knew how to get their loyalty, how to persuade them how to handle with a given
                    story. If it were to break, it would make it impossible to get any kind of
                    constructive solution on the problem that he was working on. The press accepted
                    that.</p>
                <p>We began talking early in February. It was June before any press leak that had
                    any real validity came out. And, of course, it wasn't until October that the
                    solution was announced publicly. The press were willing to be circumspect about
                    it and not “spill the beans”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was probably an attitude that would be impossible to
                        maintain in today's world.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I suspect so. You may find the occasional old newspaper type who
                    understands these things. He, on his own, might go along. But he would probably
                    be scared to death that headquarters would fire him if they knew that he was
                    sitting on a story. So it's extremely difficult today to do this kind of
                    thing.</p>
                <p>But it was, I think, even in retrospect, indispensable to the process; if the
                    word had come out, both countries would have had to take very inflexible
                    positions and the compromises that were worked out never could have been
                    reached.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Skipping over your time in the War College, we'll move to
                        your assignment to Thailand as Deputy Chief of Mission, DCM, 1958. How did
                        this assignment come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I imagine the principal factor was that there was a new appointment as
                    Ambassador to Thailand, namely Alexis Johnson, succeeding Max Bishop. Johnson
                    was appointed early in '58. He was looking for a DCM. He didn't propose to keep
                    on the man who had been Bishop's DCM. He had been asking around and, I think, it
                    was probably Marshall Green who had mentioned my name to him. Marshall and I had
                    been working on this worldwide survey of overseas deployments and bases, for
                    which Marshall had been the East Asian man. When we traveled to East Asia, I was
                    on all of the trips. Marshall and I got acquainted and hit it off very well. I
                    think he mentioned my name to Alexis Johnson.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>So I was in the middle of my War College year that Johnson was getting ready to
                    go. He suggested we get together and I invited him down to Fort McNair for
                    lunch. We talked and he told me what he had in mind. I was very pleased because,
                    of course, at the end of my War College year, I would be looking for a new
                    assignment. I had expressed an interest previously in serving in some different
                    part of the world. All of my experience, up to that time, had been European. I
                    said I would like to go out to this area Thailand, he was looking for a DCM and
                    so that was it!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was willing to take somebody who had not served in the
                        Far East? I mean was this a detractor? Did he feel that this was
                        necessary?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: He knew that I had accumulated a certain amount of background on that
                    region by virtue of my participation in this worldwide bases survey, when I had
                    worked with Marshall. Of course, at the War College, we had obviously picked up
                    a number of the outstanding East Asian problems at the time, and had studied
                    them. But I had not served out there. He apparently decided, nevertheless, that
                    somewhere along the way, I would learn enough to be able to be a useful
                    assistant to him. He, obviously, was the experienced person in that part of the
                    world and he was going to be calling the shots.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how did he use you? Some ambassadors use DCM's in
                        different ways.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I would say that he identified a certain number of sectors in which he
                    expected me to take responsibility. If I had to make some kind of a distinction,
                    I would say that the political aspects of the job, and particularly the more
                    sensitive political ones, he very definitely kept to himself. But some of the
                    less complicated political things, and a lot of the economic things, he was
                    ready to have me take over, always under his supervision. I was the first to
                    recognize that this was, for me, a new part of the world and I had an awful lot
                    to learn. Until I had an opportunity to get some of that behind me, I obviously
                    would have to move a little slowly and cautiously.</p>
                <p>But there was a great deal going on at that time in Thailand, the Thai-U.S.
                    relations. They were becoming more and more significant as time went on. We, the
                    Thai, the Philippines and Pakistan, which at that time, of course, still had its
                    Eastern Branch, we were all in SEATO. At that time SEATO had a certain role and
                    reputation. It didn't last very much longer but at that time it was active.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel SEATO, at that point, was something other
                        than a paper treaty?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>UNGER: We doubted that it was ever going to be a close treaty in the same sense,
                    for example, as NATO, identifying committed forces, setting up joint commands,
                    assigning forces to an identified SEATO commander, etc. SEATO never went that
                    far, and I think it probably was not intended that it would.</p>
                <p>I had worked a lot on NATO and it was much more a matter of a difference than a
                    similarity. I think SEATO was seen as primarily political, a means of providing
                    some reassurance to the Filipinos, and particularly to the Thai, who at that
                    time were living in an atmosphere where there was a fair amount of hostility and
                    uncertainty in the region. The French Indochina period was not very far in the
                    past. China, of course, was a distinctly hostile power.</p>
                <p>In Malaysia for example, at that time (it was British Malaysia still) there was
                    essentially a Communist insurgency. Indonesia was, certainly in the Sukarno
                    days, in a good deal of trouble. The Philippines had the Huks problem. And, of
                    course, in Vietnam, there was the North/South conflict, which was hotter or
                    cooler, depending on the time, but always potentially a very active military
                    situation.</p>
                <p>So SEATO was seen as not so much an active instrument, but as a means of
                    reassurance, particularly to the Thai and the Filipinos, to reassure them that
                    their links with the United States and with some other Western countries was not
                    going to be a serious endangerment to them. That if they were in trouble, their
                    friends from outside were prepared to come and lend a hand, give them
                    support.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were American interests in Thailand at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: That's a tough one. I would say that, approaching it negatively, the
                    United States felt that it would be dangerous if, one by one, the countries of
                    that area were either taken over by Communist powers or fell so much under
                    Communist influence that they were responsive only to orders out of Moscow and
                    perhaps, to some extent, out of Beijing. Little by little, many significant
                    interests of the United States in the region would be threatened.</p>
                <p>One of the most serious questions, of course, was the Straits. The Straits of
                    Malacca, where Singapore sits and across the way, Sumatra; and the Sunda Strait
                    in Indonesia. The absolutely critical nature of those two straits was clear for
                    all sea communications between East Asia and the Indian Ocean and, beyond, i.e.
                    the Mediterranean and Europe. The feeling was that if things began to fall apart
                    in Southeast Asia, in due course, Communist power would be established in
                    Malaysia and then in Singapore and perhaps Indonesia. In fact, each one of those
                    countries already had its own internal subversion problems.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>When the British were still there, in what was still called Malaya, there was a
                    serious Communist problem and there was a very active Communist movement in
                    Singapore itself. There was not such in Thailand, but there certainly was in
                    Vietnam, in Laos and Cambodia, too. Those situations were somewhat chancy.</p>
                <p>So there was a feeling, that we now look back on and don't particularly approve
                    of, or agree with, that saw all these issues as black and white: “they're either
                    for us or they're against us!” And a fear that both the Philippines and Thailand
                    might be engulfed and lost. These indispensable sea routes, indispensable to
                    countries like Japan and Korea, between Europe and East Asia, would be cut off
                    and all the resources of the area would be cut off and all the population. This
                    would make India dubious about any kind of connections with the United States;
                    even Australia might feel an obligation to change its policies. In effect, that
                    part of the world would be completely under direct or indirect Communist rule.
                    The balance would be a dangerous one for the United States, Western Europe and
                    Japan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the Thai see the situation at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Well, the Thai governments were by and large Western and U.S.-oriented.
                    They certainly were anti-Communist. There was a new young King and series of
                    dictators who were the real bosses. Sarit, for example, had taken charge in
                    Thailand about six months before I came there. He had taken charge about the
                    time that Alexis Johnson got out there, or shortly before. We developed a very
                    close relationship with him. He was looking for American support and assistance,
                    including economic assistance and military assistance. He argued for this on the
                    basis that he was a friend of the United States and of the West and that he was
                    an enemy of Communism. He would be doing what he could do to see that the
                    Communists didn't have any further successes in his region.</p>
                <p>This was kind of a black and white era-”you're for us or you're agin' us!” There
                    were rulers in the Philippines, at that time, who were taking a similar line. In
                    the Philippines, of course, the United States had a much more direct stake
                    because of what are now two bases, Clark Air Base and Subic Bay, but then were
                    proliferated far beyond that. There were, I don't know how many, American
                    installations of one kind or another, which were considered vital to our
                    position in the western Pacific. And there was a feeling that Japan, and its
                    friendly orientation, was dependent on keeping those sea lanes open and
                    preserving a reasonably secure situation in East Asia.</p>
                <p>There was also a feeling that it was important to hold on to this last little
                    friendly Chinese foothold, namely Taiwan. And there was a very definite
                    apprehension that mainland China might try to move against Taiwan. It was at
                    that point that it was announced that the American Seventh Fleet would be
                    regularly circulating through those waters in order to inhibit any intention of
                    the Chinese to make a move of that sort. This is, of course, also the period of
                    the Korean War and subsequent years.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the aftermath is still lingering on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. There certainly had been a sharp division in our American official
                    thinking about China. But the Korean War, of course, had been one of the
                    circumstances responsible for setting U.S. policies for East Asia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did we look toward the People's Republic of China at
                        that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: With tremendous misgivings and distrust. The feeling that they were
                    hand-in-glove with the Soviets and they were even less amenable to reason. They
                    had taken recently over in China and Chiang Kai-shek had moved across the
                    Straits to Taiwan. We had interposed the Seventh Fleet to protect Chiang
                    Kai-shek who was our man in those days. We were intent on preserving what there
                    was left of what we called “Free China”. And we were intent on preserving South
                    Korea with the kind of government it had, having fought off the North's attempt
                    to take over the South.</p>
                <p>All of those events were not very many years in the past. I went out to East Asia
                    in '58. The Korean War was a little bit in the past; it began in '50 but it was
                    only finally over about '53. And the Taiwan Straits crisis was '54. So these
                    were all live issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Vietnam was in '54 or '55, that the division
                        came.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. Vietnam was kind of on and off; the South was holding its own at that
                    time, but the pressures from the North were beginning to be felt more and more.
                    A grave defeat had already been suffered at Dien Bien Phu.</p>
                <p>In 1962, there was a new accord on Laos. There was an apprehension that Laos also
                    was about to be swallowed up by the Communists. So there was a conference called
                    with the British, the Russians, the Chinese, the French and ourselves. A new
                    accord was worked out in 1962. Once that was worked out, the new neutral,
                    tripartite Regime was set up, in which you had representation from the Far Left,
                    the Far Right, and Souvanna Phouma in the center. At that point it was deemed
                    important to start over with a “clean slate.” I was sent from Bangkok, where I
                    was DCM, directly to Laos, having been sworn-in in Bangkok, as Ambassador to
                    Laos. (Almost always a new Ambassador is sworn-in in Washington where he gets
                    his instructions before taking up a new assignment.)</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the first place, when you were in Thailand when the
                        Kennedy Administration came in 1961, did you feel, just from your position
                        as a Foreign Service officer there, a change in mood toward the area or
                        not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes, I think so. There was less of a disposition to accept some of the
                    attitudes that had been established and running by then for a fairly long
                    period. The sort of black and white attitude of John Foster Dulles about how you
                    can't have anything to do with the Communists; their intentions are invariably
                    evil and aggressive. The only thing to do is to build up secure defenses and
                    military arrangements, and work with the countries that are friendly to gear
                    them to share the same anti-Communist attitude. (Some people referred to this as
                    “pactitis.”) In that particular area, the SEATO pact and ANZUS, and perhaps
                    several others, were already in force.</p>
                <p>This situation I think, in a way, was what led to the Laos settlement of 1962,
                    which was intended to substitute a neutral solution for the dangerous East-West
                    hostility which otherwise prevailed. Presumably, some of the initial discussions
                    on this were between Khrushchev and Kennedy. When the new arrangement was worked
                    out to provide for a neutral Laos, the idea was to wipe the slate clean, send in
                    a new ambassador who was going to be there to work with not only his British and
                    French, but also his Russian colleagues. (We Americans couldn't work with the
                    Chinese because they wouldn't talk with us!) But we meant to try to make a
                    success of this neutral solution, with the idea that Laos might lie as a buffer
                    between western-oriented Thailand and Communist-oriented North Vietnam. It was
                    also intended that a neutral Laos would not be used by North Vietnam to
                    infiltrate troops into South Vietnam.</p>
                <p>In Cambodia, you had kind of a neutral position of Sihanouk. If you could have a
                    similar neutral position in Laos, perhaps you could isolate and insulate the
                    Communists who were in charge in North Vietnam, and also the Chinese,
                    particularly from Thailand. And Thailand could continue its existing western
                    orientation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the nomination come as a surprise to you? Had anybody
                        talked to you before about it or prepared you for it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I knew it might be in prospect because I knew about the Geneva Conference;
                    I knew it was going to be necessary to appoint somebody to Laos. And several of
                    the people who had come through Bangkok, had been working in Geneva with
                    Harriman, who was our principle negotiator there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was then Assistant Secretary for the Far East.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes, which was an interesting job for him to accept because with his
                    standing he could have aspired to be Secretary of State.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Or President.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Or President. He was so interested, and so determined, to work something
                    out on Southeast Asia. He was very much opposed to the Dulles policies. He
                    totally disapproved of them and felt that we had made a lot of mistakes. And I
                    suppose he was sure he could work out a better solution, partly because of his
                    experience in the Soviet Union, his contacts with the Russians, and his
                    considerable exposure to the European point of view, the British, but others as
                    well. For example, he was our first Marshall Plan administrator. He had a
                    feeling that Dulles had made a botch of our whole East Asian policy, including
                    Laos. He was not very sympathetic to the Thai but he knew that they were Allies
                    and he had to work with them. But he was especially intent on making this
                    compromise on Laos work.</p>
                <p>I don't know who it was that had mentioned my name to him—it may have been Bill
                    Sullivan who was working very closely with him at the time. (I had known Bill
                    when he was my assistant in Naples.) It may have been Bill, knowing that I knew
                    the story out there reasonably well, from the experience I already had had in
                    Bangkok. There were two people—we used to call them the “Gold Dust Twins”—Bill
                    Sullivan and Michael Forrestal, James Forrestal's son—both of whom were working
                    to find solutions for the critical problems in this part of the world. Both of
                    them were very much trusted lieutenants of Harriman, and I'm sure that they gave
                    him advice about ambassadorial appointments and all kinds of other things as
                    well. It may have been that they had something to do with that appointment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any instructions before going? Did Harriman
                        take you to one side and tell you what he wanted?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Oh, absolutely. He couldn't do it in Washington until several months had
                    gone by. I didn't get back to Washington initially, and as I said, I was sworn
                    in out there in Bangkok which was quite unusual. But the idea was to get me on
                    the ground right away. The idea was also for me to get acquainted with my
                    Russian opposite number and establish an effective working relationship with
                    him. There was no pretense that we would agree on everything, by any means, but
                    at least we should talk and look for a way to live together. Everything I did
                    should be very loyally in support of this compromise solution for Laos, with a
                    government that was made up of representatives from Far Right, Far Left and
                    Center, with Souvanna Phouma in charge and coming from the Center.</p>
                <p>My job was to do everything that I could to make Souvanna Phouma's Administration
                    a success and constructive, also from a U.S. point of view.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the Russian ambassador at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Oh, boy. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how did you get along with him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Quite well. We saw a fair amount of each other and we talked pretty
                    frankly. Actually, I was introduced to him in Geneva when all of these
                    arrangements were still being worked out. (You know, there was the Conference in
                    Geneva, the Second Geneva Conference, in '62). While I was still stationed in
                    Bangkok I returned for a consultation in Washington; at that time I was DCM to
                    Kenneth Young, who had taken over as Ambassador from Alex Johnson.</p>
                <p>Harriman asked me to come to Geneva where the Second Geneva Accords were still
                    being negotiated. He introduced me at that time to Souvanna Phouma and various
                    other people from Laos. And one day, when we were there in Geneva, he and his
                    Russian counterpart (Pushkin, I believe) got together; Pushkin pulled an
                    individual over, who up to that point was unknown to me, and Harriman pulled me
                    over and put the two of us together to shake hands. He was going to be my
                    Russian colleague in Vientiane when I took over as ambassador.</p>
                <p>The idea was that, however we had to do it, we were going to make the accords
                    that were then being worked on in Geneva—and were almost ready to be
                    signed—function successfully; those were the accords that were going to
                    neutralize Laos. They were going to provide for the withdrawal of all foreign
                    forces. They would (I think, in the accords themselves) develop this idea of
                    installing a coalition government which would represent all shades of Lao
                    opinion, all the way from the Far Right to the Far Left. They would establish an
                    ICC, International Control Commission, with an Indian chairman and a Canadian
                    and a Polish associate. The ICC would be there to be sure that the Geneva
                    accords were properly carried out. That neither we, nor the Russians, nor the
                    Thai, nor the Vietnamese nor anybody else, would trespass on the provisions of
                    the Accord.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What control did the Soviet man have over the Vietnamese,
                        the North Vietnamese, for example?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Considerable control. I'm not sure my memory will tell me exactly to what
                    extent the North Vietnamese, at that point, were dependent on Soviet aid, but
                    probably to a considerable degree. I'm sure the Chinese were involved in it as
                    well, but the Chinese didn't have a great deal of resources to spare at that
                    point. In other words, roughly speaking, the Soviet role in North Vietnam was
                    like the American role in South Vietnam.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>When I got to Laos, and when I was able to assess the situation and learn more
                    directly what was going on, I discovered what the whole world has known about
                    ever since, that the North Vietnamese, who were not able to penetrate South
                    Vietnam directly, were using Laos as a route of passage for men and material.
                    The idea was to try to prevent that from taking place. In other words, there
                    were caravans moving across into Laos, from North Vietnam, traveling down the
                    eastern edge of Laos, and then moving back into areas in South Vietnam that the
                    Communists controlled. This, of course, was the central issue. It meant that the
                    neutralization of Laos—which Western countries including the United States, and
                    Thailand also, had all favored in the expectation that it would cut the North
                    Vietnamese supply route off from supplying their forces attacking South
                    Vietnam—obviously was not being achieved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll come back to that. How did you deal with the
                        government of Laos? Was it really you and the Soviets talking things over
                        with the three Princes? How did this work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: We dealt almost always directly and officially with Souvanna Phouma. The
                    Soviets were in very close touch, as were the North Vietnamese, with the left
                    wing of the coalition government, Prince Souphanouvong, a half brother of Prince
                    Souvanna Phouma, was the leader of that wing. Actually Souphanouvong was the
                    front man for the left wing; the real figures were just the same people that we
                    keep hearing about who are now heading the government in Laos, Nouhak and
                    Kaysone. But at that time, they were in Hanoi or Sam Neva province of Laos (on
                    the Vietnam border) most of the time and were not visible in Vientiane.</p>
                <p>Their instruments were available in the government in various roles. E.g., Phoumi
                    Vongvichit and various other people, who were associated with Prince
                    Souphanouvong and the left wing, were in ministerial and other positions.</p>
                <p>The right-wing certainly had definite ties with the Thais and with us; Phoumi
                    Nosavan was the most active figure there, but the nominal head of the right-wing
                    was Prince Boun Oum.</p>
                <p>So you had three princes: Boun Oum on the right, Prince Souphanouvong on the left
                    and Prince Souvanna Phouma in the middle.</p>
                <p>Souvanna Phouma and Souphanouvong were half brothers; I believe they both had the
                    same father.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With Souvanna Phouma, did you have much to do with
                        him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Oh, sure; he was my principal contact.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was he to deal with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: He was, by and large satisfactory, but he had a very tough row to hoe.
                    There were all kinds of things that were happening in Laos that were not
                    pleasing to Western powers, to the Thai, to the U.S. Government, et cetera. But
                    I had to recognize what a difficult task he had, and I had to recognize that,
                    above all, we wanted to preserve this tripartite, neutral government. This was
                    our policy and we believed this was our best hope of getting Laos through a very
                    difficult situation and preserve it as a neutral country. So there were many
                    things, including many things that Washington wanted me to do, that I didn't
                    feel I could do or that Souvanna Phouma would say, “No, I can't” or “you
                    shouldn't.” I was on the telephone with Bill Bundy, sometimes almost everyday
                    (usually in the middle of the night in Laos), just trying to work out all kinds
                    of critical issues.</p>
                <p>The Thai were very impatient with Souvanna Phouma—their man was Boun Oum—because
                    they felt that Souvanna Phouma was playing into the hands of the Communists and
                    not doing the things that they considered important, or right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you directing or being involved with American
                        Military or CIA operations? Again, this is an unclassified interview. But a
                        lot of time has gone and a lot has been published.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Basically, I was in a role which relatively few ambassadors are put in,
                    and most of them don't want. But we couldn't have any military people in Laos
                    under the neutral solution, so whatever happened there I had to, in effect,
                    supervise.</p>
                <p>One of the kinds of things we felt we had to do was to continue to keep alive and
                    protect various highland tribal groups. You've undoubtedly heard about the Meo,
                    more recently referred to as the Hmong (but they're the same people). Those were
                    people who were strongly anti-Communist and anti-Vietnamese and who had been
                    very much committed to the United States and to the Thai and to the earlier
                    governments in Laos, governments that were very friendly to us. The Meo had, you
                    might say, stuck their neck out very far and they were well known enemies as far
                    as the Communists were concerned.</p>
                <p>Souvanna Phouma tried to handle it in a very fair and dispassionate way. But as
                    far as the Communists were concerned, these (i.e., the highlanders such as the
                    Meo) were people to be eliminated. Of course, the Vietnamese, in particular the
                    North Vietnamese, hated their guts; they would do anything they could to cut
                    these people off from supplies and take any action just to get rid of them.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>We had a supply route which, of course, couldn't go through Vientiane. It was
                    pretty much an air supply route that fed essential food stuffs and ammunition,
                    and so on, up into that highland area. On a few occasions, I went up there to
                    talk to General Vang Pao, who was the leader of the Meo, about what our position
                    was, what we were prepared to do, etc. We definitely told him that we would not
                    put up with any activity, on his part, that was prejudicial or hostile to
                    Souvanna Phouma. We insisted that the neutral solution was our solution, too,
                    that Souvanna Phouma was the man in charge and that he was to do nothing to
                    undercut Souvanna Phouma's position or anything that was hostile to Souvanna
                    Phouma. That wasn't always easy to enforce.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did he want to do? Did he want to put a more Rightist
                        government in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: The Rightist government that had been in office up until the time of the
                    second Geneva accords, had been friendly to Vang Pao and supported him. He was
                    very, strongly anti-Communist and he felt that the center in Laos, the
                    neutralists, were really playing into the hands of the Communists. He said, “No,
                    I understand they're not Communists but the Communists are just going to use
                    them and our whole country will go Communist as a result. Therefore, it is I,
                    Vang Pao and my people, who certainly have to keep the Vietnamese from moving
                    into and taking over our country.”</p>
                <p>He acknowledged that he had to support the neutral, Geneva solution, but he was
                    obviously dubious about various aspects of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is an area where the CIA was very active. How much
                        did you work with them or were they working with you but not with you? What
                        sort of control did you have?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Well, I insisted (and, in this case, Harriman was, of course, my
                    supporter) on knowing essentially everything that was going on, and having a
                    veto power, at least. I think that for the time that I was there that was pretty
                    effective. I had a very different kind of CIA Station Chief from the people who
                    had been there before. The ones who had been there before were great activists
                    who had practically picked up their rifles and joined in on the fray.</p>
                <p>My CIA man was very circumspect and moderate. He knew the situation very well but
                    understood that he had to work with me. My own opinion—I've never had any
                    evidence to the contrary—was that he did work very loyally with me. Although
                    things changed as time went on, for the time I was there that was pretty much
                    the situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from '62 to '65.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: To the very end of '64.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this a time when we were doing much to interdict the
                        Ho Chi Minh Trail in Laos?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: More and more as time went on. Initially, we were not doing a great deal.
                    Souvanna Phouma was very, shall we say “allergic”, to any action we might be
                    taking in that regard. He felt that this was going to immediately undermine the
                    neutral solution and Laos would be right back in the same old mess.</p>
                <p>But we were quite convinced and, little by little, the evidence became quite
                    concrete, that the North Vietnamese were doing exactly what we thought they were
                    doing. On occasion I would take photographs and show Souvanna Phouma a truck
                    convoy moving by road, out of North Vietnam into Laos, to go down whatever kind
                    of routes they could find to feed eventually back into South Vietnam. Of course,
                    the roads were atrocious, but there were routes that could be used. To be sure,
                    sometimes things had to be carried by porters down the Ho Chi Minh Trail. But it
                    was my task to demonstrate to Souvanna that the Ho Chi Minh Trail was not
                    interdicted, was in active use, and that it obviously was a means by which the
                    North Vietnamese were putting military pressure on the South.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we doing anything? During your watch in Laos, were we
                        doing anything regarding interdiction?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes, as time went on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The reason I ask is someone I know, who is a historian at
                        the Army Historical Center here, is working on MAGV. That's the Military
                        Assistance Group Vietnam. He asked me to ask you what were your relations
                        with MAGV. He mentioned two things. I'm not sure whether these were during
                        your time or not. One was an operation called Barrel Roll. Then there was
                        Steel Tiger.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. I remember both of those.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wonder if you could comment on that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>UNGER: Well, needless to say, the U.S. military who had the responsibility they
                    had in South Vietnam, believed they were aware of what was taking place. And I
                    think they were undoubtedly right; the task of protecting South Vietnam against
                    the pressures, actual military pressures, from the North was very considerably
                    complicated by the moving of supplies down the Ho Chi Minh Trail to North
                    Vietnamese forces, whether on the Laos side, or as you got farther south on the
                    Cambodian side, and eventually back over into South Vietnamese territory.
                    (Whichever place I can show you on the map here).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're pointing to a map of Vietnam down toward the bottom
                        of Laos.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Anyway, the route the Ho Chi Minh Trail took, through Laos, was fed by
                    convoys that came over the mountains out of North Vietnam, by a number of
                    different routes. Then it turned south in Lao territory, just to the west of
                    Vietnam, and then moved back into South Vietnam from Laos. Sometimes it stayed
                    in Lao territory all the way down to the northern boundary of Cambodia, and then
                    moved into Vietnam from there. But there was a whole string of routes and
                    feeders into Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were we doing about it? Let's take the Barrel Roll
                        business. What did that consist of?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: We wanted very much, as I've said several times, to keep alive the neutral
                    solution in Laos. On the other hand, the U.S. Military were very insistent, and
                    the South Vietnamese were very insistent. It was, of course, quite
                    understandable, that they insisted that Laos not be used as a route of passage
                    to support the Communist pressures against Vietnam.</p>
                <p>As time went on, I found myself in the position of informing Souvanna Phouma and
                    asking him, in effect, to acquiesce in our bombing of the Ho Chi Minh Trail, in
                    those areas where we knew the Vietnamese were crossing over into Laos, where we
                    knew that there was a supply line functioning, in order to inhibit the movement
                    of those supplies to the South.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was his reaction?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Well, at first, of course, he hoped very much that somehow Laos could be
                    kept pure and pristine and out of this conflict, and that the Geneva accords
                    would continue to prevail. As time went on, evidence was presented to him by me.
                    And, of course, it wasn't only what I showed him in the way of aerial
                    photographs, and so on, but he also had reports that came from some of his own
                    people up in the Plain of Jars and elsewhere (some of this came via General Vang
                    Pao and his people). Although Souvanna didn't always trust those reports, some
                    came from people he knew he had to believe.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>As time went on, he, of course, became more and more outspoken in opposition to
                    this abuse. He would call together his top council and send Prince Souphanouvong
                    over to Hanoi to tell those people to stop doing what they were doing. Whatever
                    Prince Souphanouvong told them, I don't know, but it certainly never worked.
                    [Laughter] Nobody really expected it was going to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you call up MAGV and say, “All right, bomb such and
                        such.” Or would they say, “We're going to bomb.” Or would they say, “Can we
                        bomb?” How did that work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: As long as I was there, there was no bombing carried out, unless they had
                    explained to me what they intended to do. Certainly, initially, it was a case by
                    case review. I had to be satisfied that it was not, in a serious way, going to
                    interfere with things in Laos, with Lao population, even though it was Lao
                    territory. In any case it was Laos territory not under the government's
                    jurisdiction, but under Communist administration.</p>
                <p>Basically, the idea was to be sure that things didn't go to the point where the
                    Geneva Accords were going to be seriously jeopardized. Even though we knew this
                    Vietnamese infiltration was taking place, the idea was to try to keep Laos as a
                    country, and most of its territory, out of this Vietnam situation. On these
                    matters I used to be in regular communication, mostly with Bill Bundy in
                    Washington; he was then Assistant Secretary for East Asia and the Pacific.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But there was MAGV headquarters. Would they send somebody
                        over or were these bombing things called out of CINCPAC in Honolulu? Where
                        would this come from and whom would you talk to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: A lot of it came directly out of Washington. My communication was often
                    with Washington. Now and then, I would go down to Saigon when there was a
                    pertinent meeting taking place there; I remember one time, for example, when I
                    went down because Dean Rusk was there. This is just one of those anecdotes but
                    it's interesting as it relates to what was taking place: I flew down there
                    because there was a meeting down there and there because there were so many
                    things to talk over with Rusk as to how far to go and what could be condoned and
                    what should be reported, what should be my position with Souvanna Phouma, with
                    Souphanouvong, with Boun Oum, et cetera. I mean there were just all kinds of
                    outstanding issues and I really needed to talk with the Secretary.</p>
                <p>So I flew down and I had some time to talk with him; then I had to get back
                    promptly. I got into a plane and they flew me up to Vientiane. When I got to
                    Vientiane, I couldn't land. General Kouprasith, who was one of the right-wing
                    generals, was pulling a coup! He was going to take over and throw out the
                    Tripartite Government and put in a right-wing government and go on from
                    there.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>My deputy, Phil Chadbourn, was well aware of this and telegraphed, or telephoned
                    me, in Saigon just as I was about to leave. Of course, there had to be clearance
                    for my plane to land in Vientiane. They wouldn't give clearance because they
                    were afraid of what I was going to do to undo Kouprasith's actions, if I got on
                    the ground! Chadbourn fought them to a standstill and eventually got permission
                    for the plane to land. At that point, Kouprasith had called together the
                    National Assembly and was about to announce the fact that the Geneva Accords
                    were a dead letter and that the right-wing was taking over the government. At
                    the airport Phil told me what was taking place.</p>
                <p>So I went immediately to the Assembly. First I got together with my fellow
                    ambassadors in our little balcony seating area to get their assessment of the
                    situation. The most pertinent of my colleagues, were the Thai, British, French
                    and Indian ambassadors. (The Indians, with the Poles and the Canadians, were on
                    the International Control Commission). All of these people were there, as well
                    as a few others and they overheard. At the same time I asked somebody to send a
                    message to Kouprasith saying that I must see him. When he came out of the
                    Assembly session I met him in the corridor and told him that if he carried
                    through his plans, that there was going to be no U.S. support for Laos and he
                    was going to be in deep trouble.</p>
                <p>In due course Kouprasith backed down and didn't declare an end to the Geneva
                    accords or dissolve the coalition government. So we went on for a while,
                    continuing to try to make them work.</p>
                <p>Kouprasith, incidentally, also had arrested Souvanna Phouma and on that occasion
                    had put him under house arrest. It was essential that Souvanna Phouma know what
                    had taken place because there were good indications that this was kind of a last
                    straw, as far as he was concerned; if Kouprasith were successful in pulling this
                    coup and installing a right-wing government, Souvanna Phouma was going to get on
                    a plane and get the hell out of Laos!</p>
                <p>So I had to get to Souvanna Phouma to tell him what had happened. As I say, he
                    was under house arrest, so I drove over to his house and I tried to drive up his
                    driveway, but Kouprasith's soldiers wouldn't let me. Souvanna's house was set
                    well back from the road and I noticed that the next-door driveway, immediately
                    parallel to Souvanna's, with only a fence in between, was not guarded. So I had
                    my driver just move over one and drive up that driveway. I got up more or less
                    abreast of Souvanna Phouma's house, and by that time, he began to know what was
                    going on. He came out on his balcony and I stood there at the fence and shouted
                    to him, you know, “don't give up, don't resign.” [Laughter] “We're with you and
                    stay with it.” So he did.</p>
                <p>Of course, by that time, my diplomatic colleagues were all there, and a large
                    press contingent as well. And the French ambassador provided the “bon mot,”
                    saying, “Mmhmm-ala, la diplomatie, � la Romeo et Juliette.” [Laughter]</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>So the Souvanna Phouma government survived and went on for sometime. But, of
                    course, it ultimately folded.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to go back and talk about your relations with the
                        American Military in Vietnam. MAGV, the Military Assistance Command
                        Headquarters. You were there during the period when the big build up began.
                        You were in Laos in about '64, when we started to really insert troops in
                        and play a more active role. Did you find yourself under any pressure from
                        the American Military in MAGV to call for more air strikes, to do more. Did
                        you find yourself trying to find other solutions while they were pressing
                        for bigger and better strikes of the Ho Chi Minh Trail?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. Our objective was to preserve the 1962 solution for Laos and to keep
                    Laos out of the struggle. Of course, we had to acknowledge that Lao territory
                    was being used to move men and materiel from North Vietnam South, but we were
                    initially very hesitant to have any bombing. But, as I say, at one time, I
                    showed Souvanna Phouma this photograph of a Vietnamese truck convoy moving into
                    northern Laos. Souvanna made it perfectly clear; he didn't say yes or no and I
                    didn't expect him to, but I felt that he undoubtedly understood what the issues
                    were and why we were doing what we were doing. Given the situation in Vietnam,
                    there didn't seem to be much escape from trying to interdict the supply route.
                    Nevertheless it never was effectively interdicted in spite of the large numbers
                    of men and the carpet bombing used in the effort.</p>
                <p>There were all kinds of other solutions that people put forward. For example,
                    there were those who felt that the United States should move militarily from
                    Thailand, right across the waist of Laos to Tchepone near the Vietnamese border.
                    Then push right on in and seal off South Vietnam from the North. My task was to
                    do what I could to preserve a neutral Laos and keep it from becoming embroiled
                    in the struggle. But, of course, that became, as time went on, more and more
                    difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would it play out if the American Air Force wanted to
                        put in a series of strikes on the Ho Chi Minh Trail and you felt it would be
                        too much. This would be upsetting as very precarious neutrality. The Air
                        Force insists, you say no, would this go up to the Joint Chiefs of Staff or
                        to The White House?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Well, sometimes to The White House. Kennedy was President at the time and
                    he was committed to the neutral solution in Laos. Of course, Harriman was his
                    principle instrument in that regard.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>I remember, when I would come back to Washington, I would not only check in and
                    talk to the Secretary and, on a few occasions also to the President, but also
                    the Chiefs (Joint Chiefs of Staff) would ask me to come and sit down in their
                    room to talk about the situation as I saw it in Laos. I got into some pretty
                    good arguments with Curtis Le May who wanted to bomb the hell out of everybody.
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He's still the man that talked about “bombing the enemy
                        back to the Stone Age”. Were you also saying, look this isn't working very
                        well, the bombing. Were you getting reports?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: It was very hard to get a reading. In other words, the bombing would take
                    place, but we had very limited possibilities of seeing to what extent it was
                    inhibiting the use of the Ho Chi Minh Trail. As you know, that debate went on
                    for years, long after I left Laos.</p>
                <p>Clearly, there was no highway and exactly how things were moving was kind of a
                    mystery. We had different sorts of intelligence reports and there were
                    innumerable solutions proposed as to how we might interdict the Trail.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was something called SOGS, Study and Operations
                        Groups or something? We would put down teams to put down sensors. Were they
                        doing that at your time, too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. That was beginning at that time, yes. To try to get a much more
                    precise feel for what kind of traffic there was and how much there was and where
                    it was going, and so on. We did drop a lot of sensors in the zone of the Ho Chi
                    Minh Trail.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned Kennedy. But Johnson came in late '63
                        obviously. Was there any change in attitude or your point of view of a
                        neutral Laos or the situation there with Johnson in instead of Kennedy? Or
                        was it about the same?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I'd say, as far as that area goes, it was more of the same. The people
                    around Johnson, of course, were very different from the people around Kennedy.
                    You didn't have any people like Arthur Schlesinger, for example. Or if they were
                    there, Johnson wasn't listening to them. Johnson was, as time went on, certainly
                    more intent in taking a strong stand.</p>
                <p>I'm trying to remember. Let's see. I was there from July of '62 to spring of
                    '64.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excuse me, '65.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: '65? Maybe so. I don't know why I find this very hard to reconstruct.
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm looking it up in my handy-dandy little book here. It
                        has you presenting your credentials in July 1962. You left the post in
                        December 1964.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: That's right. I had to report, in Washington, in January '65, as one of
                    Bill Bundy's deputies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During the time you were in Laos, did you have any direct
                        dealings with Johnson or Kennedy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Oh, yes. For example, at one point, after I went to Laos in July of '62, a
                    delegation of Lao leaders—Souvanna, Ngon Sananikone, Qunim Pholsena, et al—and I
                    were received by President Kennedy in the White House. Then in the mid-winter of
                    '63—Kennedy had already been assassinated—Souvanna Phouma with a group of his
                    ministers, including some of the Communist ministers, came back to Washington. I
                    accompanied them and I remember that we were in the White House calling on
                    President Johnson. The obvious objective of all of this was to strengthen
                    Souvanna Phouma's hand, to make him feel that the United States was still behind
                    him and the neutral solution for Laos.</p>
                <p>I did see Kennedy but I guess that must have been earlier, but after I had been
                    appointed to Laos. I was in Washington at some point and, in effect, the
                    President and Bobby, who was always around, told me what they expected was going
                    to be achieved; Harriman, of course, was there too; the objective was to remove
                    Laos from the list of U.S.-Soviet differences.</p>
                <p>When I brought Souvanna Phouma to call on Kennedy, that may have been when I was
                    already appointed but hadn't yet gone to Laos and Souvanna Phouma was in
                    Washington before he went over to the Geneva meeting that I referred to earlier.
                    Then he went back to Laos and when he went back to Laos, I went up to Laos
                    directly from Bangkok. It was on the earlier occasion that there had been a
                    meeting in The White House with Souvanna Phouma and Jack Kennedy and Bobby and
                    Harriman were there as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Kennedy was quite conversant with the problems of Laos. I
                        remember his giving a television talk. He got himself much farther into an
                        obscure area.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes, February of '63 I think that was. Nobody in the United States had
                    given two thoughts to Laos; they mostly didn't know where it was or if it was.
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you told that he was going to give a speech?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>UNGER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this have any repercussions on what you were
                        doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Not specifically and directly. But it meant that Americans were alerted to
                    the fact that the President considered this an important issue. They were made
                    familiar with what our approach to the problem was. I think I was still in
                    Thailand when that took place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That might have been just before the Geneva Accords. How
                        about in Vientiane? How did you find your staff? Was it an active staff,
                        knowledgeable, not so knowledgeable? Or was it some of the backwater type
                        staff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: It was a pretty good staff. It was essentially a clean sweep from the
                    staff that had been there before. As I say, Winthrop Brown had been my
                    predecessor; he was a very fine, very competent ambassador. But it was thought
                    that with the whole new situation, the new Geneva Accords, etc., that there
                    ought to be a change in ambassadors.</p>
                <p>My DCM was Philip Chadbourn. I think Phil had been there with Win Brown for at
                    least a while, and then stayed on with me. He went through much of my time, and
                    was succeeded by Coby Swank. My political counselor most of the time in Laos was
                    a fellow who is living in Arlington now, Bill Hamilton.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You thought you had a good solid team there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Very good, yes. Phil was a very realistic fellow, an activist, who was
                    prepared to do essentially whatever he had to do in implementing U.S. policy.
                    For example, I mentioned the fact that I had had that airport-landing problem
                    after meeting with Rusk in Saigon. When I flew back to Vientiane, the
                    authorities didn't want me to land. But Phil went out to the airport and made it
                    very clear in no uncertain terms that they were to let that plane land!
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression, as far as Laos was concerned, of
                        Dean Rusk's interest in that area?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>UNGER: He was very much interested. His associations, before he became Secretary,
                    had been with that part of the world—with East Asia. I think he felt that the
                    United States had a great deal at stake in this whole Southeast Asian situation,
                    including the idea of setting up a neutral Laos and taking Laos out of the
                    East-West struggle, if it could be done. Of course, he had been very much in
                    support of the program in Vietnam. As I said, he was in Saigon to chair a
                    meeting of the U.S. Chiefs of Mission of the region. At this point, the
                    situation in Vietnam was becoming more and more difficult. He was discussing and
                    supporting with the U.S. Chiefs of Mission and other American officials the
                    various measures that were being formulated and initiated in Washington.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, he was very strong for the kind of solution we were trying to
                    make work in Laos, which was very different from our approach in Vietnam. We
                    were trying to take Laos out of the East-West struggle. I don't think he and
                    Harriman were particularly congenial; they obviously had to work together a fair
                    amount, but I don't think that they were soulmates. But to the extent that they
                    had to work together, they did.</p>
                <p>Harriman probably aspired to be, and thought he should be Secretary of State; it
                    was his conviction that this Southeast Asian problem was a serious one and
                    needed to be worked out but in a peaceful fashion, removing it from the list of
                    U.S.-Soviet issues. He was prepared to take the job under Rusk as Assistant
                    Secretary to do just that, to work on that problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the time you were leaving in December of '64 from Laos,
                        how did you think the situation in that country would work out? Were you
                        optimistic, pessimistic? How did you feel about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I thought that it coming to depend more and more on what took place in
                    Vietnam. If we could stabilize the situation in Vietnam, so that the North
                    Vietnamese realized that using the Ho Chi Minh Trail was a losing game for them,
                    then they would probably be prepared to leave Laos alone. They would have their
                    influence there, but we were never opposing that. In other words, there was
                    agreement on a Tripartite Government with a left-wing component, which obviously
                    was very responsive to Vietnam. That was okay, but we felt that only if they
                    gave up in South Vietnam, and stopped trying to use Lao and Cambodian territory
                    to take over South Vietnam, only then could the Laos solution work. If it did,
                    that would be to everybody's benefit, not only to the Lao, but the Thai would
                    have an insulation from an aggressive North Vietnam, and also from an aggressive
                    China (as we saw it then). And we believed that then the situation in Southeast
                    Asia would have a much better chance of being stabilized. But, of course, the
                    Vietnamese didn't see it that way. So the situation became more and more acute
                    as time went on.</p>
                <p>I went from Vientiane back to Washington where I became, as I said earlier, Bill
                    Bundy's deputy for Southeast Asia. Then I went back to Thailand in August of
                    1967.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We've now reached the point where it's 1965 and you have
                        become a Deputy Assistant Secretary dealing with Far Eastern affairs in
                        Washington. What were your responsibilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I'm trying to reconstruct the situation in Washington, i.e. who was where
                    and doing what at that point.</p>
                <p>Bill Bundy was the Assistant Secretary for East Asia and the Pacific. At least
                    that's what we call it now. I was his deputy for Southeast Asia. That meant that
                    I had pretty much direct supervision over the pertinent desk officers and for
                    the work of the Economic Deputy Assistant Secretary which related to that
                    area.</p>
                <p>This was a period of considerable turmoil in Southeast Asia. I'm trying to
                    establish the setting as of that particular moment. The situation in South
                    Vietnam was beginning to become more and more active in a military sense as the
                    struggle with the North became more and more acute.</p>
                <p>In Cambodia the government was becoming more and more disturbed about the use of
                    Cambodian territory by both of the factions in Vietnam. The South occasionally
                    trespassed on Cambodian territory and, of course, the North by this time had
                    established its infiltration route; northeastern Cambodia was being very heavily
                    used for that.</p>
                <p>The Thai and the Cambodians had long-standing differences, including differences
                    over small, but to both of them, important, geography along their boundary.</p>
                <p>The Thai and the Burmese were having occasional little dust-ups, sometimes with
                    relation to the situation in the Shan States, Burmese territory just north of
                    Thailand and northeast of central Burma. Sometimes there were problems with
                    reference to some of the frontier areas down south in the Malay Peninsula, the
                    area of the Kra Isthmus and so on.</p>
                <p>It was a period of constantly deepening crisis, with its focus principally on
                    Vietnam, but with repercussions and expressions all over the Southeast Asian
                    area. It was an era when U.S. relations with the People's Republic of China were
                    very strained, and when there was constant tension in the Taiwan Straits. And a
                    period when Sukarno had just been ousted in Indonesia, which had been a critical
                    moment there. This is an era when the Southeast Asian Treaty Organization was
                    still functioning, but it had lost a good deal of its credibility and
                    importance. Pakistan had, I believe by that time, been separated from India, and
                    Bangladesh had been separated off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bangladesh was Henry Kissinger's time. We're talking about
                        '65 to '67. So Bangladesh was still part of Pakistan. Did you have prime
                        responsibility through Bundy for Vietnam or were you really dealing more
                        with the other parts of Southeast Asia?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>UNGER: Well, at that time, and increasingly from that time on, Vietnam became not
                    just the responsibility of a desk officer or of a Deputy Assistant Secretary or
                    of an Assistant Secretary. It moved right up to the very top echelons in the
                    Department because it was becoming a more and more serious matter. The United
                    States involvement, including the military involvement, was constantly
                    increasing.</p>
                <p>So I guess you could say that my position, as far as Vietnam goes, was for a time
                    the desk officer for it. I had a fairly large staff, including a number of young
                    FSO's, some of whom had served out there. We were trying to handle the problems
                    relating to Vietnam without letting them become prime international issues.</p>
                <p>But there was a high level of interest right up to the top, including the
                    President. So what would have been a usual country desk officer kind of
                    responsibility had changed into a very special operation, in which much
                    higher-level interest was constantly involved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your attitude at the time? How did you see the
                        Vietnam thing? We had just started the build-up, starting really inserting
                        combat troops for the first time. How did you see what we were doing there
                        at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I would say that I was apprehensive about our turning this into a major
                    military contest. I think that was the concern that I know I felt, and I think
                    that some of our people in Vietnam and, certainly many of the people working in
                    Southeast Asia, either in the field or in Washington, felt. It would be a
                    mistake to try to turn what was essentially a political problem into an
                    essentially military problem. There was a feeling that if the government in
                    South Vietnam could pull itself together, operate more effectively, take more
                    account of the kinds of internal measures that needed to be taken, that there
                    was a much better chance of getting some stability in the South and frustrating
                    any efforts of the North to move in and take the country over.</p>
                <p>But there was, as you know, a succession of Vietnamese governments, with one
                    leader after another. First, the unhappy history of Diem. And then finally Ky.
                    There didn't seem to be a capacity on the part of the government in Vietnam to
                    recognize what we saw as the central problems. Or, if they did, to organize the
                    government resources and the bureaucracy to deal effectively with these
                    problems, in order to enlist a much fuller support from the population.</p>
                <p>The debate raged as to how much the Vietnam War was, in a sense, a conventional
                    war, with the North simply being an invader with perhaps a number of superior
                    arms and no inhibitions. Or the extent to which it was a situation in the South,
                    in which government was steadily losing support, in which it was not effective
                    in many areas of the country, and in which either direct military pressure from
                    the North, or all the subversive activities engineered and carried out by the
                    North constantly weakened the South, until it finally was clearly unable to
                    protect itself.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>The debate raged also over what the U.S. role should be. A military commander
                    like Westmoreland was devoted to what we thought of as generally conventional
                    ideas of warfare. Whereas many of the people who had served out there (including
                    quite a number of Foreign Service officers who had been stationed in a lot of
                    the outlining areas of the country, and who had had a pretty good chance to get
                    a feel for the positions and the political problems in the villages and out in
                    the countryside, as well as in Saigon) considered that the problem was one of
                    poverty and of their government's lack of attention to improving their
                    situation. Also there were the problems of corruption in government, not only at
                    the center in Saigon, but throughout the country and, there was the view that
                    for these reasons as well, the South Vietnamese military were not effective. The
                    North was able to infiltrate into many areas and destroy the stability that the
                    country needed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to get these officers talking to William
                        Bundy and move their thoughts up the line? Was there a good flow of
                        communication of, you might say, the ones who saw this as political rather
                        than Military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. I think, certainly as far as Bill Bundy was concerned, there is no
                    question but that he interested himself and became involved. There were many
                    sessions in which he had a pretty good opportunity to hear what these people had
                    to say.</p>
                <p>One of the people who began to show up in the scene in those years was a
                    professor from Harvard who came down and was fairly well acquainted in certain
                    circles in Washington and was sent out to the field, in Vietnam, at the time
                    that I was concerned on the desk with that country. He usually spent several
                    weeks out there and he was already well acquainted with a group of French
                    political scientists who knew the area from an earlier time, and who had some
                    perspectives on it worth listening to, even though one couldn't, by any means
                    buy the whole analysis that they presented. This fellow was named Henry
                    Kissinger and I found, when he went out to the area and saw a number of contacts
                    he had in South Vietnam, and occasionally some others in the area although
                    mostly right in South Vietnam, that he usually had a very perceptive and useful
                    analysis to pass along to us. He had suggestions that were definitely worth
                    listening to about our programs in Vietnam and how they might be altered to make
                    them more effective.</p>
                <p>At that time Kissinger was still teaching at Harvard and he would make these
                    occasional visits to Washington when he came by and we talked. I tried to give
                    him a thorough briefing of the situation, as it had changed from the last time
                    he had been out there, always on the understanding that when he came back, we
                    would debrief him and get his judgment on the situation. I would say this
                    probably happened about three times in the course of my dealing with
                    Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was his message that he was bringing back? Was it a
                        political, rather than a military war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I wish I could reconstruct with any reliability. I'm sure that there are
                    places where this sort of thing is on the record. But he certainly tended to
                    emphasize the political, as opposed to the strictly military approach, but not
                    to the extent that some of the officers in the embassy in Saigon were doing. In
                    other words, as I recall, he felt there had to be some military strength to back
                    up the political program when it was necessary. There was no question that the
                    North Vietnamese, either directly on the frontier, i.e. the 17th Parallel, or
                    pushing in and probing from Southern Laos or Cambodia, were using military
                    means. They also had an extremely widely proliferated network of operatives,
                    intelligence and people who were working for them clandestinely throughout South
                    Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel that there was a solid debate going on
                        between you and what the others on the desk at the Bureau were saying about
                        yes, it's military, but mainly political? Those in the Pentagon were saying
                        just give us more forces and we can take care of this problem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: You're asking if I felt there was a debate going on?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A debate between the defense side and the state side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes, there was no question that these were issues that were being debated
                    and argued passionately and quite continuously, as I recall it, through this
                    period. This is the period when people talked about “the hearts and minds”, a
                    phrase that recalls the U.S. Colonel Ed Lansdale, who developed programs for
                    Vietnam and who had earlier worked very effectively with President Magsaysay in
                    the Philippines. When the State Department people, who had been sent out there
                    and had served in the various provinces, put their emphasis on the economic and
                    the political. There were very few that denied there was a military aspect to
                    it, but I guess you could say they felt the South Vietnamese forces could handle
                    the North Vietnamese with the pressures that were being exerted, if the
                    situation within the country in South Vietnam were a stable and a secure
                    one.</p>
                <p>But that wasn't the case; this was primarily because of the actions and the
                    policies of the government in South Vietnam, which never figured out an
                    effective program to assure the loyalties of the population, particularly in
                    rural areas, of the country. (This is an awfully big subject. It's one where I
                    would like to refresh myself on some of the communications at that time).</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As a matter of fact, we are hoping to get an oral history
                        program concentrated on the Foreign Services role in Vietnam. Hence, I'm
                        going to just touch this one lightly because it is big and it is major. So
                        at this point I think we might move on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>How did you see William Bundy? How did he operate?</p>
                <p>UNGER: He operated effectively at upper levels. In addition to his own
                    considerable reputation and valuable connections, he also obviously had a very
                    close relationship with somebody who was right there in The White House, namely
                    his brother Mac. The communication between Bill and Mac was practically
                    continuous; I can remember innumerable occasions when I would walk into his
                    office and he was on the phone with Mac.</p>
                <p>So I guess going back to the Kennedy days, and certainly also into the Johnson
                    period, there was a very close and immediate connection with The White House.
                    Those of us who were working in concentrated fashion on Vietnam, although we
                    were in State—and I guess Dean Rusk was Secretary at that time—we were
                    frequently called over for meetings and discussions at the White House.</p>
                <p>When Johnson was President, meetings were held in his office on a number of
                    occasions. He was very deeply concerned and distressed about the situation. He
                    wanted to be briefed and took a very direct personal role in many of the
                    decisions that were being made. (I'm trying to reconstruct the period and relate
                    it to the events that precede it. When I was first back in Washington, Kennedy
                    was President, and then Johnson, following Kennedy's assassination).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '65 when you went there, of course, Johnson had been
                        President for more than a year at that point.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. Kennedy was killed in the fall of '63.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were ambassador in Laos from '62 to '65.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>UNGER: I finished up in Laos, I think, in December of '64 and came back to
                    Washington. I hadn't been there more than about ten days or two weeks, when one
                    of the kinds of trips that became fairly routine was getting organized,
                    involving Robert McNamara (Secretary of Defense), Mac Bundy, Bill Bundy and
                    several others of us who flew out in McNamara's plane; it was non-stop from
                    Washington to Saigon. We spent about three or four, maybe five days at most, in
                    Vietnam; went up to Pleiku, which about a week or ten days before, had just had
                    a very disastrous incident in which the Viet Cong had moved in and assaulted
                    what had been regarded as a rather secure post. They killed a lot of people,
                    including some American military, and generally terrorized the population. It
                    was a typical action of the Communists, just to demonstrate how insecure the
                    country was and how uncertain was the hold of the government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this the action that a number of Americans were killed
                        too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And this was really, in a way, what triggered our response
                        almost from that point on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: When we came back to Washington, the debate began as to what should be the
                    U.S. role. Should we continue as we had been in the past, with a lot of
                    advisers, a tremendous amount of military and economic assistance, but without
                    any U.S. forces, or at least any considerable number of American personnel,
                    beyond advisory groups. That debate led—and this is a matter on which I'm not
                    too sure of my recollection—to a decision made, probably in March, to send about
                    10,000 American military to Vietnam—and the following summer, a very much larger
                    number. This was Lyndon Johnson reluctantly going ahead with something I think
                    he very definitely had not expected, or wanted to do, i.e. to authorize such a
                    degree of American military involvement in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>He was looking for advice from every corner that he could get it. He was
                    dependent on Mac and on McNamara. I'm trying to remember to what extent Henry
                    Kissinger was involved at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Probably only at the peripheral of things.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>UNGER: I think so. I don't remember his being central at that point. He was
                    certainly becoming a State Department central figure. But I would say, that
                    although he was always there, always had something to say, he was not much of an
                    activist, not as far as McNamara. And always somewhat cautious as to what he
                    felt should be done. But on the other hand, not ever, that I can recall, taking
                    a very strong and determined position in opposition. I think whatever his own
                    personal thinking may have been, the impression one got was that at that time he
                    was unprepared to be the President's informant and adviser.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you feel about the embassy? There you were on the
                        desk; did you feel that you were getting good information? Did you feel that
                        you had a strong embassy there or was there a concern?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Earlier there certainly had been a concern; I'm talking about back when I
                    was in Washington before my assignment to Laos. And also we felt more confident
                    of our judgments by the time we had got this whole company—I don't remember how
                    many there would have been; 20, 25—young Foreign Service officers who were
                    trained in the language and were sent out to work in the provinces in Vietnam in
                    order to give us good reporting directly from the field. By that time, I felt
                    that we were getting a pretty reliable picture.</p>
                <p>There was, of course, tremendous competition on the Washington scene for getting
                    nearer to the President to press various proposals, positions and points of
                    view, various courses of action. There were groups like Ed Lansdale's, in
                    Saigon; his group included some Foreign Service officers but was a special,
                    “hearts and minds” group. They had their ideas about countering insurgency,
                    which Lansdale developed from his experience in the Philippines.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's the understanding.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: And he was thinking of applying in Vietnam some of the kinds of concepts,
                    programs and approaches that he felt had been successful there. I think he
                    introduced some ideas that were adaptable to Vietnam and useful, but by and
                    large I don't think he had a major impact. I think what happened, was that the
                    military were more and more in control of the situation, and by the time this
                    was happening I was on my way out of Washington and going on out to Bangkok. In
                    the “grass roots” situations, in the small towns and rural areas these groups of
                    young Foreign Service officers were sent in order to provide Saigon and
                    Washington with an informed judgment of what were the problems in this country;
                    they tried to identify what were the kinds of programs that were effective; what
                    ought we to be doing? Obviously, what was being done was not succeeding.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>Those people, more and more, got caught up into the kind of military network.
                    Also, given the rapidly expanding numbers of military in the country and the
                    various roles they were to play, they were inevitably a major source to whom the
                    President and Defense, and to some extent State, had to look for information
                    about local situations; as time went on they were more and more the qualified
                    Americans, on the spot, more than anybody from the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>They were good and bad and indifferent. Some of the reporting that came from
                    those young military figures was first class, and some was very unreliable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the CIA? Were you in competition with the CIA?
                        Or did you feel the CIA had their own point of view? How did you feel about
                        it? We're talking about the '65 to '67 period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Looking at it from a Washington point of view, I would say the
                    relationship was reasonably good. I remember Bill Colby and George Carver and
                    others in the CIA with whom we were in close touch. The feeling was that the CIA
                    and the State Department were not very far apart in terms of analyzing what
                    needed to be done, and in putting less of an emphasis on military actions than
                    did the U.S. Military. To be sure, there were those in the Military who also saw
                    it as a problem with a very heavy civilian aspect, as something that could not
                    be handled or solved on a purely military basis.</p>
                <p>The CIA people had much more in the way of resources and flexibility to work
                    with. They had a lot of people who had had experience living in villages and so
                    on, or they had access to such people. But my recollection is of a fairly good,
                    cooperative feeling with the CIA. We in the Foreign Service had to depend on
                    their resources in some areas and when it came to the Embassy in Saigon, they
                    would depend on our resources. There were certainly some areas where there was
                    keen competition, for example, some of the places where we had consuls. I think
                    we had a consul in Da Nang and Nha Trang and probably in Da Lat.</p>
                <p>My recollection is that even though there were differences in interpretation, and
                    differences in opinion, by and large the cooperation was pretty good. They both
                    had, of course, a much more political element in their analysis, political and
                    economic, than did the Military who tended to see it as either a large scale
                    military operation or a military subversive and local village problem, but
                    always with a military emphasis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to move on now to your assignment to Thailand as
                        ambassador. How did this come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I suppose one of the reasons they asked me to go out to Bangkok in the
                    fall of 1967 was because of my earlier experience there and in Laos. Let's see,
                    did I follow Ken Young?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was Graham Martin.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Excuse me, Graham Martin. Yes, that's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You presented your credentials in October of 1967.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I think I arrived at the very end of August and presented my credentials
                    in October. Again, I think my name probably got thrown in the hopper by a number
                    of people, including again, Bill Bundy. I think Bill was still Assistant
                    Secretary for East Asia and the Pacific. Could that be correct?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. He was there until 1969.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Right. This was a period when the United States had a rapidly mounting
                    number of Americans in Thailand. The predominant group was the U.S. Military.
                    There were five or six air bases in country, which were being used to support
                    the allied forces in Indochina. There was a major logistics base at Sattahip, in
                    southeastern Thailand. That was the base that had been developed to facilitate
                    the movement of supplies in country, from abroad, for two or three purposes: one
                    was moving supplies up country to support the then five, or maybe six, Thai air
                    bases where the United States had substantial forces.</p>
                <p>Also, to supply what we were taking into Laos and, to a minor extent, Cambodia,
                    as well as what was still being provided for Vietnam. Obviously, most of that
                    last was moving via other routes, but the port at Sattahip, which was initially
                    a Thai Naval Base, became a very important supply base also for the United
                    States forces through that whole area, in Thailand and Indochina.</p>
                <p>Under those circumstances, a large share of my responsibilities related to the
                    situation in Indochina. There were several situations: the most time consuming,
                    the most troublesome, the most difficult, of course, was Vietnam. The Thai were
                    very much committed to joint action with the United States, Korea, Australia, et
                    al. The Thai sent ground forces to South Vietnam to support the government in
                    Saigon and they were engaged in the land war especially in the northern coast
                    area. I don't remember precisely which places, maybe around Da Nang and north of
                    there.</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>Moreover, the military effort in Vietnam was very substantially supported on the
                    supply side through the Port at Sattahip. As for the U.S. air activity which was
                    principally over North Vietnam (the bombing of Hanoi and all of that) and also
                    along the Ho Chi Minh trail, most of that was based in Thailand, utilizing bases
                    like the ones I mentioned in the northeast, mostly, but also Thakli.</p>
                <p>This meant that the United States had, in five or six locations in Thailand,
                    substantial numbers of Americans in residence. Most of them were Military. There
                    were all the local community relations situations that come out of such a
                    situation. By and large, our presence in Thailand was free of critical tensions
                    but every once in a while there would develop an unhappy jurisdiction situation,
                    or the U.S. Air Force would feel it had to acquire some real estate. This might
                    impinge on a lot of agricultural or other important land uses. By and large, the
                    relationship was smooth; nevertheless a great deal of my time, in that early
                    period, was taken up with trying to resolve a multitude of problems of that
                    sort.</p>
                <p>If I remember my chronology correctly, it was only about five or six months, or
                    even less, after I got there, namely late October or November, that . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You presented your credentials in October of '67. So this
                        would be the spring of '68 or so?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: What I'm trying to recapture is the year; I seem to remember that it was
                    October or November. It was when Thanin Praphas were eased out and the
                    government was taken over, first by a caretaker, and then Seni Pramoj, and then
                    Kukrit Pramoj and others.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a coup by Premier Kittikachorn in November of
                        '71. Or maybe it was '70?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: A coup by Thanom?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean his forces. I have a note here. He was the Premier,
                        but apparently his group took over. I'm not sure exactly about this.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: He was the Prime Minister who took over from Sarit when Sarit died. It was
                    a coup against Thanom that I was thinking about, but that was in October or
                    November, 1973.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are now restarting. We've just gone and done a little
                        research. Mr. Ambassador, let me ask you first, how did you deal, when you
                        first arrived, at the end of 1967—and you were there for almost five
                        years—how did you deal with the Thai government. Whom would you see and who
                        were the major players that you dealt with? And, could you spell the
                        names.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>UNGER: When I returned to Thailand as Ambassador, in the fall of '67 (having been
                    out there earlier as Alex Johnson's and then Ken Young's deputy), Sarit had died
                    and Thanom had succeeded him as Prime Minister. I had known Thanom from that
                    earlier time when he was Deputy to Sarit. We had what seemed to me and, I
                    believe, seemed to him likewise, a good relationship. It was easy for us to
                    communicate. He was available to receive me if there wasn't something critical
                    going on; I could go in and see him and talk to him quite informally. He
                    accepted that I was able to bring him reliable word of U.S. Government opinions
                    and policies.</p>
                <p>I think it is fair to say, that I had perhaps a better understanding of his
                    country than some other American ambassadors, if for no other reason than that I
                    had already served there for a number of years, and that I had learned their
                    language, which wasn't true of very many American ambassadors out there. Also, I
                    had served elsewhere in the region, namely Laos, specifically. Also I had been
                    working in Washington on the region before I came out there. I had been with
                    Bill Bundy in the East Asian Bureau as his Southeast Asian deputy. Earlier I had
                    been very much involved in the activities of SEATO, even though SEATO was by
                    this time on its way out. But nevertheless, I was familiar with the history of
                    that and other important earlier situations.</p>
                <p>Also I spoke Thai. For example, with Thanom's wife, both Mrs. Unger and I could
                    communicate with her only in Thai; she didn't speak any English. Thanom's
                    English was limited. I wouldn't have pretended to do business in Thai, except
                    when I had to, particularly if I were traveling around the country in more
                    remote areas. But nevertheless, Thanom knew that I knew it.</p>
                <p>So I think we had developed a pretty good relationship. At that time, in
                    Thailand, there were really two powerful people. Thanom was out front: he,
                    himself, plus his wife, plus various people closely associated with him, were
                    one sort of power center.</p>
                <p>But a much more adept and much more skillful operator was his Deputy and Minister
                    of Interior, General Praphas. Praphas was more than Thanom in the old line of
                    Thai General-politicians, people who came up through the Military ranks but who,
                    in the process, had accumulated to themselves a very considerable body of
                    supporters, and they had brought those supporters along with them into
                    relatively high places. Whether in the Military or in the Ministry of Interior
                    or in other important places, there were key people who were “Praphas men,” and
                    they were ready to support him. I think they expected that Thanom, as sort of a
                    genial and kindly father figure, would in due course be prepared to move aside
                    and that Praphas, who was younger, would move into the top position. This whole
                    hierarchy of Praphas supporters would then benefit from his being in the number
                    one position.</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>This was pretty much the expectation. I don't think it was Thanom's expectation,
                    but it certainly was that of many people in political positions, including many
                    of the Military, many of whom were Praphas's men. He was not only an important
                    figure in the Thai Army but he was also the Minister of Interior; therefore, the
                    police were very much a part of his group as well.</p>
                <p>This was the power scene as it had developed following the death of Sarit some
                    years before. Thanom and Praphas had moved in as a kind of team. I think one of
                    Thanom's sons or daughters was married to one of Praphas's daughters or sons, or
                    something like that. [Laughter] It was an alliance, and an effective one. But it
                    ran into growing opposition. Sometimes for special reasons, but sometimes just
                    because I think it's in the nature of such things: as people in power “overstay
                    their welcome” and other people who want power are anxious to move in.</p>
                <p>Anyway, little by little, their situation became more tenuous. There began to
                    develop, in Thailand, a much wider political participation and involvement of
                    various groups, particularly the students. There was resentment over the machine
                    that was primarily under Praphas's direction, but from which Thanom benefitted
                    too, in which very substantial amounts of funds were diverted to personal bank
                    accounts; that very familiar pattern that has happened many places in the
                    world!</p>
                <p>It had been true in Thailand, certainly of Sarit. But Sarit had been a very
                    determined and effective leader and, perhaps also, had chosen to die at an
                    appropriate moment, before some of these things caught up with him!</p>
                <p>Furthermore, Thanom was less effective than Sarit and Praphas was perhaps a
                    little more outrageous than some, in terms of the kinds of deals that he was
                    engineering and the amounts of money he was diverting!</p>
                <p>Also, this was a time of some stress with the war in Vietnam, not far away, and
                    something like 50,000 foreign, albeit allied, forces in country. There was
                    growing uncertainty as to what was going to be the outcome in Indochina. (That
                    situation in Indochina, particularly as it might directly affect Laos and
                    Cambodia as well as Vietnam, was always a very central concern for the
                    Thai).</p>
                <p>At a certain moment, the unhappiness with Thanom and Praphas boiled over. There
                    was a student demonstration; in the past these had usually been quite
                    effectively controlled and never had represented any kind of a serious political
                    problem. But in this atmosphere that I've been describing, the demonstration did
                    get out of hand and in October of '73, both Praphas and Thanom were ousted and I
                    guess they both flew to the United States, fairly directly. The King appointed,
                    not on a permanent basis, but essentially as a caretaker leader of government, a
                    very much respected Chief Judge of the equivalent of our Supreme Court, Judge
                    Sanya Thammasakdi.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>Judge Sanya was someone I knew well. Given what had happened, he asked me (even
                    though at that time I was just about to leave) to stay on for some additional
                    time, over the transition, as he was beginning to get things in place for a new
                    government. Washington agreed to let me do that. So I stayed, as I recall, about
                    another month beyond what I had planned to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we play any role in the change of government
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: We, the United States, in any official sense?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: No, I don't believe so. I think that from top to bottom, both on the U.S.
                    side and on the Thai side, contacts were extremely numerous and very frank. Many
                    of them of long duration. People talked to each other and compared notes and
                    passed on opinions and had numerous discussions of situations. I'm sure that it
                    was clear, particularly, that the kind of graft and corruption that Praphas
                    represented was something the United States felt was a real disadvantage to the
                    Thai. And it was something that was inevitably going to cause them problems.
                    While they had had a pretty stable internal situation and relatively little in
                    the way of political dissent, that kind of leadership was going to breed the
                    kind of opposition they hadn't had before.</p>
                <p>The stability of the country and the stability even of the monarchy could come
                    into question, if that were to take place. I think there were many Thai,
                    including people in responsible positions, who, as time went on, became more and
                    more disturbed particularly with Praphas. They realized that Thanom was not a
                    strong figure and that even if they removed Thanom and Praphas remained in
                    place, they wouldn't have accomplished very much. The important thing was to get
                    them both out and to bring in a more democratically organized and a more
                    responsible kind of government that would be better able to start handling some
                    of the problems in Thailand that needed to be solved.</p>
                <p>All of that might suggest to some people that the United States played some kind
                    of a role in the change, which was not the case. In fact, there were many
                    official Americans, and I would say particularly Americans in the military, who
                    were very apprehensive about the kinds of changes that took place. They feared
                    that this might bring an end to the kind of position and privileges that the
                    United States military had in country.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>And, of course, account had also been taken of American people in the Thai
                    business world, although the American business presence in Thailand was not all
                    that great at that time. But they were afraid of a revolutionary spirit and
                    instability that they believed might follow.</p>
                <p>When Judge Sanya took over, he was a respected but certainly a conservative
                    figure. The general disposition of His Majesty the King was also well known; it
                    certainly didn't suggest any desire to move in any radical direction. It was
                    anticipated that there would be a transition to a more responsive government and
                    that, hopefully, there would be less corruption. Clearly it was not going to be
                    a government that was going to bring any kind of radical overturning, either on
                    the political or the economic scene. And this is, in fact, the way it turned
                    out.</p>
                <p>While I can't speak out of direct experience with the subsequent situation, since
                    I left Bangkok at just about the end of '73, I certainly tried to keep track of
                    it. I was back in Washington and was, of course, closely in touch with what was
                    taking place at that time. As anticipated, there were some rough times in
                    Thailand as time went on with the Pramoj brothers and their governments,
                    followed by Thanom. Nevertheless, fundamentally it was a stable situation as it
                    has continued to be and remains so today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying you had the 50,000 Americans. When we have
                        large bases, we tend to insist and have what amount to extraterritorial
                        rights. Were you concerned about this being a destabilizing factor? Not only
                        because of the servicemen, but also the money that you bring in. This could
                        not help a country by doing this.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: We were very much concerned about it. When it became clear that there was
                    going to be this much larger deployment to Thailand, a lot of measures were
                    undertaken to find a way to handle problems as they arose and even anticipate
                    problems, and to try to avoid the development of any kind of critical stress or
                    strain.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>Of course, I was not yet there when this big deployment took place. That was, I
                    think, primarily during Graham Martin's time. But when I got there, I had a good
                    basis for judgment given my past familiarity with the situation. I had talked to
                    all of my Thai friends, including people in the government, including some
                    discussion with His Majesty to learn how he saw the situation. I reviewed the
                    situation with people in the Thai Government and a lot of people that I knew,
                    who had perhaps been in government, or people who were not directly concerned
                    with this issue, but whom I knew to be perceptive, sensitive people. While I
                    knew most of them to be friendly to the United States, They also would be very
                    ready—if they felt our actions had been high-handed or improper or incomplete or
                    whatever—to give me a frank opinion. So when I went out there, in the early fall
                    of '67, it was very important to reestablish contacts and try to get a feel for
                    how the Thais perceived the situation. By and large, in the Thailand of that
                    day, the U.S. presence was not resented. Most of the Thai in leadership
                    positions—I'm not saying this was necessarily true of the Thai body politic as a
                    whole—were themselves concerned about the situation in Vietnam. The fact that
                    the United States was concerned, and involved, and intended to defend South
                    Vietnam, fitted with their policy as well. This is what they wished to see. They
                    were afraid that a North Vietnam, moving into a dominant position in Indochina,
                    taking over the South and exerting control over Laos and Cambodia, meant trouble
                    for them. They felt there was hostility there that would mean pressures on
                    Thailand and make life difficult for them.</p>
                <p>Of course, in the light of what's happened in the last year or so, we know that
                    the Thai have adjusted well to the situation at the same time that Vietnam
                    itself has been adjusting. But that's modern history and things looked somewhat
                    different then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there during the critical period when our
                        relations with the People's Republic of China went through a very dramatic
                        turn from being absolutely opposed to establishing a form of relationship
                        there. How did the Thai view this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Remember, of course,—as would be true in the United States too—there are
                    Thai and there are Thai! [Laughter] And, certainly, there were university
                    people; and there were some business people, who for rather special reasons,
                    regarded this PRC-U.S. rapprochement favorably and anticipated Thailand's
                    following suit somewhere along the way.</p>
                <p>There were those who were ideologues (and this included quite a number of people
                    in top government positions), who were dubious about this. They felt the United
                    States was mistaken in its perception of China and that a country that they saw,
                    by all odds, as the principal menace to Thailand's independence, was perhaps
                    going to be given a free hand to operate as it wished in Southeast Asia: this
                    would be very dangerous from a Thai point of view. Now, of course, we know that
                    none of that happened the way they anticipated, but that was the kind of thing
                    that they were worried about.</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>Remember one thing, and this is very important anytime you talk about China and
                    Thailand: Thailand has one of the largest Chinese minorities in all of Southeast
                    Asia or anywhere else. There are some countries in Southeast Asia like Singapore
                    where the Chinese are not a minority; they are a majority—three quarters of the
                    whole population. But in Thailand, they are a very significant minority and a
                    minority that has an extremely important position, particularly on the business
                    and economic side.</p>
                <p>But unlike Malaysia, where the Chinese element is often in almost a hostile
                    relationship with the Malay Muslim population, in Thailand the Chinese have
                    adjusted and assimilated in remarkable fashion. The Chinese minority is nothing
                    like the problem that it is in the Philippines, in Malaysia, in Indonesia and
                    many other areas.</p>
                <p>The usual pattern is that the first generation dresses as Chinese and lives in
                    the Chinese part of Bangkok or maybe in one of the other big cities. Maybe even
                    in the next generation somebody will go out and become a rice miller in a
                    relatively small town or be in business in Bangkok with children with Thai
                    names. Possibly they will change their own name and take a Thai name; and the
                    next generation, to all intents and purposes, is Thai.</p>
                <p>One of the most interesting cases that I always have cited is a family that I
                    knew pretty well—I think there were something like a dozen children. The oldest
                    was a very respected gentlemen who still had his Chinese name and perhaps
                    dressed Chinese. He came from China when he was a young man and he was the head
                    of one of the most important Chinese societies in Thailand. He was a very
                    wealthy businessman and was respected as such by the Thai. But there was no
                    question that he was a representative of the Chinese community, an immigrant
                    community. It was a big family and his youngest brother—who was quite young when
                    he was brought to Thailand—had a Thai name. In due course he was also given a
                    Thai title—Phya—when he became a very close adviser to the King. He was thought
                    of by everybody as a Thai; he married a Thai woman; he had the name Phya
                    Srivisarn which was a good Thai name. And so in the course of just one
                    generation, however many years that entailed, they went from the old pattern of
                    identity as Chinese immigrants to a new pattern of essentially total
                    assimilation as Thais!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One last question before we move on to your next
                        assignment. How much did narcotics play a role in your work as Ambassador at
                        that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>UNGER: The second time I was in Thailand, it was an extremely important aspect of
                    the work. For one thing, we had begun to have a problem in the United States. I
                    can't remember exactly the status in America at that time, but certainly drugs
                    had been recognized as a growing problem in the States. And Southeast Asia was
                    perhaps the principle source of opium and its derivatives, morphine and heroin;
                    this came primarily from the “Golden Triangle.” Territorially speaking, this
                    meant primarily Burma and Laos, but with some production in northernmost
                    Thailand. Thailand, however, provided the principal route of exit for these
                    substances.</p>
                <p>That wasn't always true. For example, even in the days that I was still in Laos,
                    it was frequently reported there were French or other free-lance pilots who knew
                    the wild areas of Laos and knew where they could land and take off
                    unapprehended. They were operating mostly in the northwestern corner of Laos
                    where they loaded up heavily with opium (or perhaps heroin which had been
                    refined in one of the Burmese refineries) and flew over Thai territory, high
                    enough so that they weren't intercepted and then dropped their cargo to a ship
                    at sea in the Gulf of Thailand. This was one of the ways to get the heroin out
                    without being interfered with and thus engage in a very lucrative trade!</p>
                <p>But at the same time, it was known that there also were overland channels through
                    Thailand (as well as through Indochina and Burma) that probably came down the
                    western side of Thailand, in relatively remote, mountainous areas. They
                    delivered their product to rendezvous along the Thai coast; again, that was
                    primarily heroin.</p>
                <p>Going back to our discussion about Thanom and Praphas, there were recurrent
                    rumors that Praphas who, as Minister of Interior, was responsible for the
                    police, but also had a military position, and was the person we had to talk to
                    and work with, principally, to try to get the narcotics problem under control.
                    At the same time we were talking to him, we were from time to time receiving
                    reports that he was carrying on his own narcotics operation! So it was a
                    somewhat discouraging picture. I never had any reason to think Thanom was
                    personally involved, but we definitely thought that Praphas was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to come now to your appointment as Ambassador to
                        Nationalist China, Taiwan, around the spring of '74.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: The appointment was perhaps made in March and I went out in May.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did this come about and how did you view this
                        assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I think, at that point Kissinger was Secretary of State. Are my dates
                    right?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think about that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Where was Al Haig at this point?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Kissinger was Secretary of State from 1973 until
                        1977.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: So he was Secretary of State at that point. Kissinger was determined to
                    switch our relationship with China so that we would have diplomatic relations
                    with the People's Republic of China, Where we already had some kind of
                    less-than-formal representation. We would terminate our Embassy in Taiwan and
                    follow it up with whatever less formal arrangement we could mutually work out
                    with them. So I believe that at the time I was appointed to Taiwan there was
                    pretty much of a conviction, you might say almost a commitment, in many quarters
                    in Washington, to work toward this change, whenever and however it could be most
                    effectively be brought about.</p>
                <p>There were many people in Washington, in the Congress, in the State Department,
                    and for that matter, elsewhere in the Executive Branch, people who definitely
                    were not in favor of this move. They were very loyal supporters of Chiang
                    Kai-shek and his government on Taiwan as representing the continuing Republic of
                    China recognized by the U.S. as the government of China.</p>
                <p>Anyway, I was appointed and succeeded Walter McConaughy, who had been U.S.
                    Ambassador in Taipei for several years. I was not sure whether or not I was
                    going to be the last ambassador, but recognized that there was a pretty good
                    chance I would be. In some fashion or other, we would be working out a new
                    relationship with Beijing which would oblige us to reduce our representation in
                    Taipei.</p>
                <p>I think by that time we had a liaison mission in Beijing. There was George Bush
                    in charge there at that point or soon thereafter. It was the spring of 1974 when
                    I went out; I don't think he was yet in Beijing at that time, but he took over
                    not too long thereafter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, Bush. It was David Bruce until September of '74. Bush
                        came in October of '74.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. So less than six months after I took over in Taipei, he took over in
                    Beijing. Now we're in the Nixon Administration. There was still a
                    commitment—whatever people may have had in the back of their mind for the
                    future—there was still a commitment to Taipei.</p>
                <p>Was it Leonard Woodcock who was prior to Bush?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, it was David Bruce.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes, David Bruce. You just said it was. That's funny, I can't see David
                    Bruce in Beijing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was there a relatively short time. He was there from
                        March of '73 until September '74. Then Bush, then Gates, then Woodcock.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: In any event, I think my communication with David Bruce was minimal; I was
                    still getting myself installed. I had never, prior to that time, been in China.
                    I don't think I had ever been in Taiwan, except on brief business visits, to say
                    nothing of the mainland.</p>
                <p>I don't think anybody knew when I went there just how long I would be there. How
                    long it would be until they felt it was politically acceptable to switch our
                    representation to Beijing—how long before the Administration would want to make
                    that kind of change.</p>
                <p>So I became involved with what for many years had been a very special political
                    phenomenon on the American scene, namely, the group that was very loyally
                    devoted to Chiang Kai-shek.</p>
                <p>UNGER: Anyway this was, of course, already a considerable political issue in the
                    United States. By that time, many important people, including people of a
                    generally conservative identification, were feeling that trying to maintain an
                    embassy in Taipei and not give credence to the existence of the PRC was no
                    longer acceptable; they came to believe that the U.S. should appoint some
                    prestigious individual to be present in the PRC and be able to deal with the
                    government in Beijing. It was pretty clear that, barring some international
                    crisis, in which we and the PRC might be at odds with each other, in due course
                    we were going to have an Embassy in Beijing and we would be obliged to close
                    down our Embassy in Taiwan. How we would do it; what kind of continuing
                    representation we would have in Taiwan; what the PRC would insist on in the way
                    of our future relations with Taiwan, if we wished to establish relations in
                    Beijing; all of these were questions that people were working on in
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had not particular instructions on this. Everybody
                        knew this was in the cards?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: That's right. No, I was instructed that my job was to go and continue the
                    U.S. relations with the Republic of China and Taipei. Of course, inevitably, I
                    had to take into account their attitude about the mainland, but obviously, in no
                    way seeming to agree with it or support it. But nevertheless, I realized that it
                    was a fact of life and that whatever I did, however I managed my mission in
                    Taipei, I had to take account of how they felt about the mainland. Of course, at
                    that time, it was totally negative. It causes me to look with some considerable
                    interest, and some amazement, at the lady who's just gone to Beijing, whom I
                    knew in Taipei.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She's the head of the Trade Delegation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Yes, I think that is what it was: trade and/or finance. There was a big
                    international meeting-the A.D.B., I believe-to be held in Beijing. She went in a
                    kind of special category; she took part in some things and didn't in others.
                    Shirley Kuo is the person I'm talking about.</p>
                <p>Shirley Kuo I knew as a fairly high-ranking person in the economic, financial
                    field in Taipei. Someone exceptionally attractive and talented. So I have to say
                    that I'm very pleased that she's still in that position, and that she was chosen
                    to carry out this mission.</p>
                <p>Her husband was, as I recall, the head of the Elected Parliament; I don't know
                    whether he still is; she was a good deal younger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find, within the State Department, and really
                        almost within the Foreign Service, a group of officers dealing with China
                        who felt we should get on with it and in a way, jump completely into
                        relations with the PRC and to hell with Taiwan? And other groups that were
                        saying no? Could you talk a little about this relationship within the
                        professional ranks.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: It might be that such a view was increasingly held, as we were moving into
                    the last chapter in what had been a very divisive issue in the United States as
                    a whole and particularly in the Foreign Service. This issue was posed in
                    sharpest fashion once the Communists had taken over on the mainland in 1949 and
                    Chiang Kai-shek had fled to Taiwan.</p>
                <p>Of course, for many, many years, the United States Government had no intention
                    whatsoever of any relationship, any official relationship with the government in
                    Beijing, and it very loyally kept up its connection with Taiwan. By the time I
                    was sent to Taiwan, however, I think we already had our liaison mission in
                    Beijing with David Bruce then Leonard Woodcock, and then George Bush. This was
                    seen by many as sort of the beginning of the end of the old pattern and that
                    there was going to have to be a readjustment.</p>
                <p>The opposition to that, in the U.S. Congress, and in the Foreign Affairs
                    community was still very strong. I'm not sure I can relate these things
                    precisely, but the mainland had just gone through some pretty unhappy periods of
                    cultural revolution and that kind of thing. So anybody who was taking the
                    earlier line about how Taiwan was a dictatorship, and how the mainland was a
                    model democracy, obviously was being laughed at at that point. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, one had to acknowledge that the real China, was the China with its
                    capital in Beijing. And that important as Taiwan and Taipei was, particularly in
                    a number of special ways, it couldn't any longer represent China as a whole.</p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>So there was certainly an expectation in many quarters that a change in “China
                    policy”, change in representation, was going to be coming before too many more
                    years went by. Nobody knew exactly when. Nobody knew what political situation in
                    the United States would permit it. Nobody knew when the discussions with the
                    government in Beijing would reach a point where some of the issues that were
                    very difficult for the United States to face, would begin to be resolved. And
                    also nobody knew when the opposition in the U.S. Congress and in fairly
                    important political circles in the United States, would reach a point where the
                    switch could take place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was the greatest opposition? You're saying important
                        political circles. Can you name any people or areas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Taiwan then, as it has continued to be, was a remarkable locus for
                    American business in numbers of firms and dollars invested and business done and
                    so on. Remarkable particularly when one considers how small an island it is. And
                    yet it's one of the top several—I'm not going to remember precise figures, but I
                    think it was number six—in trade carried on with the United States in recent
                    years. And this was a time, remember, when the mainland presented a very sorry
                    picture of repeated upheavals and cultural revolutions and uncertainties about
                    the future...and certainly of sharp hostility toward the United States.</p>
                <p>Also China had had a very close relationship with the Soviet Union; I can't
                    remember exactly when that went on the rocks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right now, I think they're having a summit today in Peking
                        and this is the first one since something like '53 or '54, '57 maybe. I'm
                        not sure. But we are talking about 30 odd years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Anyway, there was growing sentiment in the United States that whatever we
                    thought of the PRC, it was just too important a factor in the world for us not
                    to have representation there, not to be in some kind of effective communication.
                    And, of course, this had already had its expression in the setting up the
                    liaison mission. Needless to say, Chiang Kai-shek had thought that decision it
                    was shocking and disloyal to our relationship with him. But we were still not on
                    the verge of the switch that did not take place until December 31st, 1978.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Chiang Kai-shek still the leader at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>UNGER: Chiang Kai-shek was the leader in my first year in Taipei but he was in
                    very, very poor health, and in April, 1975, he died. By that time, his son,
                    Chiang Ching-kuo was in charge, with Madame Chiang Kai-shek's efforts at very
                    close supervision; Ching-Kuo had pretty much moved into the position of
                    leadership, not in name, but in fact. When I first went to Taipei, Chiang
                    Kai-shek was still nominally President. And the Parliament, which by now has
                    become a body of real political significance, was still made up very largely of
                    people who had come across from the mainland, with very little Taiwan
                    representation. They were mostly superannuated individuals who had come over in
                    '49 and who held onto their positions, but were certainly out of the
                    picture.</p>
                <p>And there was still a very marked hostility to the Communist government on the
                    mainland. There was also marked hostility to any other government that had
                    recognized and chosen to establish relations with the mainland government, as
                    opposed to Taiwan. There were still, I would guess, 30, maybe even 40
                    governments that still had relations with Taiwan, that had not switched. The
                    number now is something like a dozen (although a few small nations have recently
                    opted for Taipei). And everything that took place on Taiwan, except the most
                    strictly internal matters, anything in the international field, anything in
                    relations with the United States, was heavily colored by this concern about
                    maintaining the position of the Republic of China as the only government of
                    China recognized by the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any feeling that the knowledgeable people in
                        Taiwan were sort of preparing, even within the government, for the time when
                        we would have full representation? Or, were they sort of shutting their eyes
                        to the inevitability of this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I'm sure that individuals who were reasonably perceptive and honest with
                    themselves and well informed were certainly thinking about this eventuality. I
                    think that even among those who were reasonably realistic, given the position of
                    the United States for so many decades as well as that of some other major
                    countries, there were those who had the feeling that somehow or other they would
                    be able to hang on, that their government would continue to be recognized as the
                    government of China by many countries. And that given all the internal conflicts
                    and instability on the mainland, their day and their opportunity would come
                    when, God knows, maybe they thought they might even be invited back. I don't
                    think very many of them any longer thought in terms of military action to retake
                    the mainland, but they felt there might develop a chaotic situation there, in
                    which it would be possible for them to move back in and reassume charge.</p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>Of course, as time went on, and as the mainland began to pull itself together and
                    overcome some of its internal difficulties, these dreams faded. Prospects grew
                    steadily dimmer as countries that had maintained relations with Taipei, little
                    by little severed them, and were willing to send a consul or somebody to Taiwan
                    but were not willing to have their regular diplomatic relationship with China
                    any longer in Taipei—they were moving over to Beijing. As this went on, of
                    course, it became clear that eventually Taiwan and the Republic of China would
                    be recognized and accepted as China by very few nations.</p>
                <p>The disposition of the Government of the United States at that time was such that
                    they were fairly confident that the United States would continue its
                    relationship for some time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had left by this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: No, I left . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1976.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: Let's see. I went there in the spring of '74.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, excuse me. You had left the post in January 1979. You
                        came in 1974 and left in 1979.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: December 31st, 1978 was the last date we recognized Taiwan. And January
                    1st, '79 was the first day we recognized Beijing. And so, obviously, my official
                    status came to an end on December 31st. I didn't leave for several days
                    thereafter, although I was under very strict orders to leave immediately. All of
                    this had happened very quickly and I was determined, as far as possible, to
                    remain in Taipei long enough to help the government on Taiwan adjust to the new
                    situation and establish what was going to be the new type of Taiwan-U.S.
                    relationship from that point forward. (We are still there, of course,
                    essentially in that capacity, with our liaison mission).</p>
                <p>But the word from Washington became sterner and sterner. I did, in fact, leave
                    something like the 13th of January. I wasn't in Taipei all of the time from the
                    1st of January to the 13th. I went to a meeting in—I can't remember whether it
                    was Bangkok, but I think it may have been. That was a kind of Chiefs of Mission
                    meeting that I attended. I attended it partly because this whole development had
                    just taken place and everybody wanted to know what had happened, and what was
                    foreseen for the future, and what was going to be the impact of this on
                    Taiwan?</p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>So I went to the meeting with that in mind. Then I returned to Taipei by about
                    the 13th or 14th and left Taiwan for good soon thereafter, leaving in charge
                    Bill Brown, who had been my deputy. He was there in a sort of special capacity
                    and I think he remained until about April or May, by which time the Taiwan
                    Relations Act had been passed by the Congress. This relieved some of the most
                    acute apprehensions of the people on Taiwan as to what would be the future
                    relationship with the United States. And Brown did a splendid job in that
                    interim period when, as you can imagine, feelings ran very high in Taiwan.</p>
                <p>The Taiwan Relations Act went a good deal farther toward meeting the concerns of
                    Taiwan than many people in the Carter Administration wished. But it did go
                    through the Congress and was incorporated in law and is now the law. It made it
                    possible for the United States to continue a quasi official relation with
                    Taiwan, and one that Beijing has not worried about unduly.</p>
                <p>So this new pattern was developed, essentially in that period, between our very
                    precipitate action in November '78 and the spring.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel you had much input into the change of
                        relations or was this something that was being called from Washington? This
                        was, of course, the Carter Administration. You were just off to one side on
                        this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: No, not entirely. Anybody who knew the temper of the U.S. Administration,
                    in regard to China, knew that there definitely was a desire to make the change.
                    It was, of course, also clear to anybody who had a feel for American internal
                    politics. It was equally clear that this was a move that was going to raise a
                    lot of eyebrows and a lot of opposition; it was going to be a politically
                    difficult move in some respects, but nevertheless, one that I think Jimmy Carter
                    and Secretary Vance were determined to carry through.</p>
                <p>I was back in Washington in the early fall of 1978; I had a fair amount of
                    discussion with Secretary Vance about what would be the new kind of relationship
                    that could be worked out. He had his staff working on this; Dick Holbrooke was
                    Assistant Secretary at that time and Roger Sullivan was also involved in the
                    problem. They were at work on a whole set of new charters and relationships that
                    would be put into effect at the time.</p>
                <p>There was, however, no discussion of when this was going to take place. The
                    impression was that it was still fairly far down the road, since a lot of
                    planning had to be worked out. It was going to be carried out in a rather
                    gradual way. In this way the impact, to say nothing of the political problems
                    that Cy Vance would have to face in the Congress, would be minimized.</p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>But, in fact, it moved much more rapidly than that. I guess a public statement on
                    the matter was made about the 13th or 16th (or thereabouts) of December, 1978.
                    As soon as that statement was made and I broke the news to President Chiang and
                    opened the discussion of what was to follow, a mission was put together in
                    Washington to come out to Taipei, to work out with the government in Taiwan what
                    would be the new relationship with the United States.</p>
                <p>Warren Christopher came out and Dick Holbrooke and a number of other Far Eastern
                    types from the Bureau East Asian came out with him, with a blueprint of a new
                    U.S. relationship to be worked out with Taiwan. There were a lot of questions
                    that were inevitably going to be raised not only by the Chinese government
                    there, but also the U.S. business community and others.</p>
                <p>There was a massive demonstration on Christopher's arrival at the Taipei Airport.
                    On leaving the airport he and I found ourselves in our limousine caught right in
                    the middle of a wild protest demonstration. We'll probably never know exactly
                    how and by whom this was engineered. By that time our coming change in relations
                    and all the rest was public property; it was known that it was going to take
                    place although at that time, I don't know that we had a specific date.
                    Washington was the culprit and Christopher came out representing Washington. As
                    we left the airport building, it was clear that we were moving into a
                    demonstrating crowd and obviously not very friendly. I wanted to take a
                    particular route which I knew would get us out of the airport by a back road and
                    then get up to my place up on the hill behind Taipei and thus get away from
                    demonstrations. But the driver was instructed by someone from the local
                    government as to how he was to go. At first I didn't have any reason to be
                    concerned about it; I just felt the other route would be more direct and away
                    from crowds and thus easier to move right along and get to my home.</p>
                <p>But what we were directed into was a real mob scene. We were preceded by a truck
                    that had a TV camera on its roof and the TV camera was pointed at our
                    procession. We were the lead car and then, of course, there were several other
                    cars following. As we moved along, and got into the middle of this crowd of
                    demonstrators, the truck stopped so that we couldn't move. There was no way to
                    go back; there was no way to go ahead. It was just a narrow little road and it
                    was lined by a mob of demonstrators on both sides shouting anti-American and
                    other slogans.</p>
                <p>We, of course, talked to the driver and asked him whether he couldn't get the TV
                    truck to get on the way and let us move on. But he couldn't and as time went on,
                    he was not even willing to leave the car. Not only was the crowd demonstrating
                    but they began pushing their sticks through the windows of our limousine, and
                    broke our windows if they were closed. Christopher and I didn't really know when
                    this was going to end and what the consequences were going to be.</p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>About at the point when things were beginning to be a little big chancy, and when
                    both of us had been bloodied—not in any serious way, but a little bit—at that
                    point the TV truck began to move. As soon as we got out of that little impasse,
                    I directed the driver, by a back route that I knew, up to our place up in Yang
                    Ming Shan, in the high area behind the City.</p>
                <p>We didn't really know that anything serious had happened to us; we didn't feel
                    physically hurt at all. But when my wife saw us, she gasped. Apparently, we were
                    bleeding profusely without knowing it, but only from superficial cuts. That was
                    the end of the demonstration. I will probably never know just exactly how this
                    was engineered. I think I know at least one individual who was ultimately
                    responsible, namely the Foreign Minister, Shen Chang Hwan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After seeing Vance in the fall of '78, when you said you
                        anticipated this would probably be a fairly gradual process, had you come
                        back and sort of conveyed this in some way to the Nationalist government and
                        then, of course, you were caught to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I couldn't convey it to them in any concrete way; any discussion of the
                    subject was immediately a matter of very acute unhappiness. I was not in a
                    position to say just this or that is what the United States government was going
                    to do. I told them my reading of the sentiment in Washington and of the Carter
                    Administration, i.e. that over time, in Washington they would be looking for a
                    way of establishing relations with Beijing.</p>
                <p>I couldn't say, because I didn't really know for sure, (although I strongly
                    suspected this was so) that this would mean an end to diplomatic relations with
                    Taiwan. When I had been in Washington early in the fall, and just prior to that,
                    when Vance actually paid a visit out to the region (I think in August) and
                    visited Taipei, he wasn't in any position to be at all specific as to what could
                    or would be worked out.</p>
                <p>What did happen, of course, was that once the announcement was made on December
                    16th (something like that) the group then came out from Washington, headed by
                    Christopher. We Americans sat down with the people from the government in Taiwan
                    to develop a new pattern of U.S.-Republic of China relationships. It was
                    naturally a traumatic situation; the Chinese on Taiwan were deeply distressed
                    and not much disposed to talk about it, yet they knew they had to in order to
                    avoid a chaotic situation once regular diplomatic relations with the U.S. were
                    broken. It was clear the United States was going to take that action, and it had
                    already become public knowledge. So they had no choice but to work something out
                    with us, angry and distressed as they were.</p>
                <p>What we worked out was the set of arrangements and mechanisms that are now
                    operating and have been successfully functioning for quite a while. Leaving
                    aside the political distress they felt in Taiwan, from every other point of view
                    it has worked out quite well.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Earlier on, George Bush, who has now just become our
                        President, was the Liaison Officer in Peking. Did you have any dealings of
                        him and what was your evaluation of him at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I didn't have a lot of dealings. I saw his telegrams and he saw my
                    telegrams. I did have a very specific dealing with him at one time at his
                    initiative, which I welcomed. At one point, after he had been appointed and was
                    in Beijing—I don't remember how long he had been there—I had been in Taipei for
                    sometime. We were both scheduled to go to Honolulu where we were having a U.S.
                    Chiefs of Mission meeting. Honolulu was where those meetings were often held, at
                    the Military Headquarters, CINCPAC. People came out from Washington and all of
                    the Ambassadors and Chiefs of Mission, in the East Asian area attended. We all
                    went to Honolulu, and we had two or three or four days of discussion.</p>
                <p>We were both going to attend that meeting, George Bush and I. I got a telegram
                    from him mentioning that we were both going to be going to Honolulu, and given
                    the fact that we were both in China, and obviously had common problems and
                    situations to face, he asked what I would think of our meeting and flying
                    together at least part of the way so that we would have a good chance to have
                    some discussion. I said I thought that was a great idea.</p>
                <p>We agreed to meet in Tokyo, which we did, and then flew the rest of the way
                    together and talked, talked, talked, all the way from Tokyo to Honolulu. Then,
                    of course, we both attended the Chiefs of Mission meeting. But all of that gave
                    us a very good chance to talk about our respective situations, all in the
                    context of the pertinent American policies. It meant that we had a very good
                    chance to compare notes and for each of us to learn what was the other's
                    assessment of the situation.</p>
                <p>From that point forward, we kept in pretty close touch. I don't think we ever
                    actually talked to each other again directly until I came back from Taipei in
                    '79. Then, when he became Vice President and I was back in the States, he asked
                    me to come around and meet with him and I did so. I had been teaching at the
                    Fletcher School in Boston; he, by that time had been in office at least six
                    months, maybe more. So we had a further talk because he was interested in
                    carrying through on the Taiwan/China situation, up to the time I left. He was
                    also interested in various situations and programs with relation to Southeast
                    Asia, where I had spent a lot of time. So we did have that additional
                    contact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he seem knowledgeable and knew the right
                        questions?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>UNGER: Yes. All of us in the Foreign Service business, at one time or another,
                    have been thrown together with political appointees. I would say we always talk
                    about whether “somebody has done his homework”. I would say George Bush gave
                    evidence of having done his homework a good deal more than many. Certainly, more
                    than Ronald Reagan, “who didn't know from nothing.” I mean, he had all kinds of
                    opinions and convictions, but he certainly didn't have much knowledge.</p>
                <p>I saw Reagan when he and Nancy came to pay a visit to Taiwan when I was
                    Ambassador there. He was Governor of California at the time. He was 150 percent
                    pro-Taiwan and terribly accusing and negative about those terrible people across
                    the Straits.</p>
                <p>Jimmy Carter, on the other hand, seemed to me serious about his responsibilities.
                    I did have an opportunity to talk with him and brief him. I can't remember
                    exactly when; I guess when I came back to Washington once, I found him with a
                    very responsible attitude, even if not terribly well-informed.</p>
                <p>Nixon, of course, considered himself a real expert on that part of the world, and
                    very much interested in it. So I had a number of occasions when I talked to him,
                    and he was well-informed. He had a lot of strong opinions, some of which I
                    didn't agree with. But he at least had made it his business to know what was
                    going on in that part of the world. When I was Ambassador of Thailand he had
                    come out there on a visit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I hope we'll talk more about Vietnam and China in a
                        different series of interviews which will be concentrated on those two
                        subjects. So at this point, I'd like to thank you very much. We'll be
                        getting back then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNGER: I think it's perfectly clear that it's a process that I'm very much
                    interested in, too. I regret to have to say what I think becomes evident in this
                    kind of an exercise, i.e., that a memory on which I once prided myself is in
                    rather bad shape! Reconstructing some of these things and relating them properly
                    to other events and so on, doesn't come as easily as it once did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We can reconstruct this and build a timeline at some
                        point. So you can edit this thing any way you want. Thank you very
                        much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
