<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000755">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Edwin Webb Martin</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR EDWIN WEBB MARTIN</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: William Johnson and Harold Hinton </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: December 9, 1987</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ambassador Martin, you are the author of a very fine
                        recent book based upon documentary research and dealing with divergent
                        American and British policies toward the emerging People's Republic of
                        China. I'm happy to say that I am one of the people who read that manuscript
                        at the University of Kentucky Press and finally recommended publication. But
                        apart from that, since you were in China at the time that you deal with in
                        that book, I was wondering if there was anything you could add from personal
                        experience to what is in the book. Your book is very scholarly, but you
                        don't say anything about your own experience. I thought perhaps there might
                        be some additional information or experiences you could add.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Thank you very much for your kind words about the book. It was a book
                    that I wanted to write because I felt that the existing literature on the
                    subject of especially Chinese-American relations left out some things. It was
                    often difficult, I think, in some of the books to follow the chronology, and
                    there is a kind of logical sequence, I think, to the developments that I
                    describe there. I wrote the book in a way that might be a little boring to some
                    people, because there are a lot of quotations from documents, but I wanted to
                    let people see what actually was said by American and British diplomats on the
                    spot and let people draw their own conclusions.</p>
                <p>Of course the interpretation of, and the selection of, materials and documents in
                    my book are a result of my experience in China at that time and subsequently in
                    the State Department on the China desk. But I didn't put much of my own personal
                    experience in there mainly because I was a rather junior officer at the time and
                    I was never stationed in the embassy. Therefore, I was not on the inside of any
                    kind of decision-making.</p>
                <p>I was first of all in Peking for about a year and nine or ten months doing
                    Chinese language study. I'd started at Yale. My first post, really, in China as
                    a reporting officer, was in Hangzhou, now part of Wuhan. Hangzhou is on the
                    Yangtze River, about 600 miles up the river. There I had sort of a grass-roots
                    view of what was going on in China.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>The consular district, which I covered as the Chinese language officer and
                    reporting officer, consisted of five provinces in Central China. They had a
                    population of about 100 million people. To put things in perspective, how many
                    countries in the world in 1948-49 had a population of 100 million? But this was
                    just part of China. I was the only political reporting officer covering that
                    territory.</p>
                <p>I might say that in China, as you gentlemen know, at that time, and it had been
                    so for decades, political reporting from the consulates was more important than
                    in most countries, because it was a country where power had been in the hands of
                    war lords and of regional political factions. Even as late as 1948, when I went
                    to Hangzhou, there was a faction, you might say, in control of Central China—not
                    in control of it, but it was very important there, namely the Guangxi clique,
                    sometimes called the Li-Pai clique, lead by Li Tsung-Jen and Pai Ch'ung-hsi. It
                    was around early '48, as I recall, that Pai Ch'ung-hsi was installed in Wuhan as
                    the commander of the Central China area. Pai Ch'ung-hsi and Li Tsung-Jen, of
                    course, were not the best of friends with Chiang Kai-shek, and we had the
                    feeling that Chiang was often reluctant to call on Pai for support. For example,
                    I think in the Huai-Hai campaign in the winter of '48-'49, Pai Ch'ung-hsi either
                    refused to come to the aid of Chiang or Chiang didn't call on him. There were a
                    lot of troops there that could have perhaps (probably wouldn't have) made a
                    difference, but in any case there was a significant lack of cooperation.</p>
                <p>As far as what I could bring to shed light on what was going on, I think perhaps
                    what I call the grass-root reporting that I did was a useful input to the
                    embassy in Nanking and also to the State Department. We could send our reports
                    directly to the State Department with copies to the embassy, and I was rather
                    flattered when I got back to the State Department on a home leave in '49, that
                    Walt Butterworth, who was then in charge of the Far Eastern Department, asked to
                    see me. I came in and we talked about what had been going on in that part of the
                    world. Nowadays, the State Department is such a large bureaucracy that a vice
                    consul coming in from the field would be lucky to see the office director, to
                    say nothing of the Assistant Secretary. [Laughter] Those are the ways things
                    have changed.</p>
                <p>I was just going to ask you if you'd like me to describe the kind of field trip
                    that I did and the people that I saw to get information. I don't think I'd have
                    anything substantive to contribute that would enlighten you particularly as to
                    what you already know, but I think it might give you an idea of how we political
                    reporters went about doing our job.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>Of the last couple of trips I took out of Hangzhou, one was to Sian. This was in
                    the fall of '48, and Sian was the headquarters of General Hu Tsung-man, who was
                    a veteran military commander of the national government, and I called on him,
                    had dinner with him. I called also on the governor of Shaanxi and on the mayor
                    of Sian, who was a man named Wang, a rather interesting person who had studied
                    for eight years in the Soviet Union, had once been a member of the Communist
                    Party but was a renegade now, a very strongly ideological anti-communist. I went
                    up to him primarily, at least on the consular side, to try to help some American
                    missionaries there whose property had been occupied by one of the government
                    offices. I went up there to try to help them solve this problem, get their
                    property back, so they could return it to the use they had acquired it for. I
                    called on all the newspaper editors, and on the president of the university and
                    several department heads. I talked to people like the head of the agriculture
                    department of the province of Shaanxi and of the commerce and industry
                    department. I talked to, of course, the missionaries and the few other
                    Americans. There were some oil people up there.</p>
                <p>In other words, I tried to get an idea of what the situation was from a broad
                    spectrum of people ranging from General Hu Tsung-man at the very top, down to
                    private individuals in universities, in business, in the newspapers, the media,
                    and in this way gather a general picture of how people viewed the situation and
                    particularly how they felt about the government and its activities and how they
                    felt about the prospective arrival of the Communists. And by that time, most of
                    the people that I interviewed were convinced that it was just a matter of time
                    before the Communists would take over, and there was speculation about how they
                    would behave, and whether or not one could carry on. There was no real consensus
                    on that.</p>
                <p>The last field trip I took out of Hangzhou was down in the other direction, down
                    south through Jiangsu province and Hunan province. There I was accompanied a
                    good deal of the time by a Standard Vacuum oil person, because on the consular
                    side I was trying to help with getting this American company's properties
                    released from the occupation, usually, of Army troops. So, even as the
                    Communists were coming down from the north—this was the spring of '49, this was
                    March of '49—we were still in the business of trying to get our properties back
                    and help American business. But at the same time, this was also a great
                    opportunity to try to take the pulse of people, look at the economic prospects,
                    political and so forth.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>Again, I saw a fairly broad range of people. But the thing that I remembered
                    about that trip was that in Hunan, the governor, Ch'eng Ch'ien, unlike other
                    governors that I called on and mayors, refused to see me at all. It wasn't
                    outright refusal, just a put-off—”He's too busy,” and so forth and so on. Well,
                    we had a feeling that I'd gotten from talking to other people that Ch'eng Ch'ien
                    was deliberately distancing himself from this American official (me) and that he
                    would not be one on whom either Li Tsung-Jen or Chiang Kai-shek could depend. As
                    it turned out—I think it was in the summer of '49—that Ch'eng Ch'ien just turned
                    over the whole province of Hunan to the Communists. This made the position of Li
                    Tsung-Jen and Pai Ch'ung-hsi, who had retreated down to Guangxi and Kwanglung,
                    untenable, and led to perhaps their earlier defeat than might otherwise have
                    occurred. Ch'eng Ch'ien was duly rewarded, as were other people who turned over,
                    like Fu Tso-Yi and Cheng Chih'chung, with various sinecure positions in the PRC.
                    Ch'eng Ch'ien seemed to have lasted longer in these positions than some
                    others.</p>
                <p>So I can't say that what we did was all that important, but in this case, I think
                    we did get an advanced signal, for whatever it was worth, at least to our
                    embassy, that here's a governor that is very soft and already showing the
                    direction which he'll probably go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you witness the Communist troops entering
                        Hangzhou?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: No, I didn't. Of course, our consulates stayed on there in Wuhan, but I
                    happened to be overdue for home leave for almost a year. I had been separated
                    from my wife and two girls for six months, and during that period my wife gave
                    birth to twin boys in Manila. We were only able to communicate by cable. So I
                    was mercifully granted home leave and transferred to Taiwan in May of 1949. So I
                    got out of Hangzhou just a few days—literally a few days—before the Communists
                    took the city. The situation was, as it was in many places in China at that
                    time, one where it was anticipated that the Communists would take the city. The
                    Nationalists had produced a lot of prefabricated pillboxes, which they put along
                    the railroad line going north, and these were obviously sitting ducks for the
                    mobile tactics of the Communists. In fact, the Communist guerrillas were
                    operating south of Wuhan between Wuchang and Changsha, and I was going to drive
                    a jeep down to Changsha, hoping I could get through. The very morning I had the
                    jeep ready to go, the very morning that I was going to get out, I got word that
                    there was a CAT plane over on the airfield at Wuchang, and if I went there I
                    might be able to get a ride. I might add that all regular airline service had
                    stopped into Wuhan by that time, and, of course, our own military assistance
                    group which had been stationed in Wuhan had long since been evacuated.</p>
                <p>Anyway, I went over to the airport, and there was an American pilot. I said, “Can
                    I hitch a ride out to the coast?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Where are you going?”</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>I said, “I'll go to any place that will take me to the coast.” [Laughter] “I've
                    got orders to go down and fetch my family in the Philippines and go home on
                    leave.” So he gave me a ride. He was going to Canton, which was actually the
                    most convenient place for me to go. That's how I got out. But I was not there
                    when the Communists came in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If I can just go back over some of this fascinating
                        material with sort of a different angle, while you were still at a junior
                        position by this time. You were there in Peking and Hangzhou at a rather
                        decisive period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From '46 to '49, was the period, after all, when there was
                        apparently some hope of settlement.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And a decisive turnaround, however you date it, at least
                        by early 1948 or mid-1948. I'm just wondering, even while you were a
                        language student there, do you recall what your own personal assessment of
                        the situation was concerning the conflict between the KMT and CCP, how that
                        might likely turn out, sort of what the mood was among you junior
                        officers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, yes. I think that the mood was one of general pessimism, as far as
                    the government was concerned. I think you're right, at the very beginning—well,
                    when I got there in September of 1946, the Marshall mission, the Executive
                    Headquarters was still in existence, but General Marshall wasn't very active at
                    that time, and yes, we hadn't given up hope that there might be some way of
                    solving this thing peacefully, entirely. [Laughter] In other words, Marshall
                    went home in January of '47, and he sort of said that his mission was really
                    hopeless and he blamed both sides for their intractability.</p>
                <p>As I say, I wasn't active in political reporting or making contacts or anything
                    like that, but there were so-called Third Force people there. Around the
                    universities and so forth they tended to be fairly optimistic about the
                    possibility of doing business (with the Communists) or setting up some sort of a
                    coalition government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have the impression that the group that you worked
                        with or the official staff there in Peking placed much confidence with the
                        sort of Third Force group?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, looking in hindsight, of course, it's very difficult, after 40
                    years, to put yourself back in that period. But I would say that yes, we had
                    more faith in them—that's a strong word, “faith.” We had more hope about the
                    possibility of some sort of a coalition with these chaps in it than was
                    justified, I think, by subsequent events. But anyway, I think so, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any particular Chinese you remember? Did you
                        associate with that group? This is a long time to remember.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes. No, as I say, I really can't remember names now. I'm sorry. I'll
                    tell you about my own experience. I did a thing which none of my language
                    officer colleagues did that gave me a rather interesting entree into the
                    university, Peita. I attended, audited, a course taught in Chinese, and, I'm
                    ashamed to say, I can't even remember the name of the professor, though I
                    thought he was very good; he was a Chinese professor, of course. It was a course
                    in diplomatic history, really—Chinese relations with foreign governments. It was
                    an eye-opener to me, because it was obviously from the Chinese point of view,
                    and none of the stuff I had read before was from the Chinese point of view. I
                    found it very interesting.</p>
                <p>But perhaps the main value of this to me was that as a student who sat there at a
                    desk with other students, all of whom were Chinese, and I was a little older
                    than most of them but not that much older, I had a chance to become acquainted
                    with a number of Chinese students. I visited them in their dormitories and had
                    some over to the house. My wife was born and brought up in China, and her
                    Chinese accent is beautiful, so that was a great help in talking to people.
                    Certainly the strong impression I had of the Chinese students was that as far as
                    the Kuomintang was concerned, it was just beyond the pale; there was no hope for
                    it really. This was due, in part, to the fact that the economic situation was
                    very bad, and they had very poor prospects for getting jobs and so forth. On the
                    other hand, a number of the students actually left the university and went over
                    the hill to the Communists, where they got some sort of a job. I used to have
                    arguments with these people. Of course, they were very critical of American
                    policy, which was seen as supportive of the Kuomintang, and I think we did give
                    about $3 billion in aid to the Nationalists after the war. We used to have
                    arguments about that and whether American democracy and the capitalist system
                    was applicable to China and so forth. They generally felt that it wasn't, that
                    socialism was the only way for China to go. As far as I could tell, the students
                    that I knew and talked to on a very friendly basis were not doctrinaire
                    Marxists; in fact, I think they were fairly illiterate, as far as Marxist
                    literature was concerned, but they looked at it from a point of view of
                    nationalism. To them, the Communists represented Chinese nationalism more than
                    the Nationalists. They also represented what they felt was a hope for the
                    future, but the idea that China would be independent, stand up and be a power in
                    the world was the main attraction, and they felt the Communists offered that
                    more than the Nationalists did at that particular time.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever discuss with them the possible relationships
                        between a Communist China and the Soviet Union?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, yes. I think that it came up in the discussions about which was the
                    better way to go for China. Naturally, I tried to put forth the merits of the
                    American system, which they generally would not argue about, except in this
                    sense, that they would say, “Well, it's all right for America, but it really
                    doesn't apply to China and our situation.” I wouldn't say that any of them were
                    strongly pro-Soviet, neither were they strongly anti-Soviet. Their view was, it
                    seemed to me, very nationalistic and also, in terms of their own future, they
                    felt that the Communists offered them, as young people, a future, whereas the
                    Kuomintang offered them no jobs, depression, and an appearance of weakness,
                    corruption, and really sort of doing the bidding of the United States. I think
                    it's important to realize this, because I think there was a period, as we all
                    know, when China and the Soviet Union were very close, but eventually the sense
                    of Chinese nationalism came out. It's much more complicated than that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned Li Tsung-jen and Pai Ch'ung-hsi and the
                        Guangxi clique. I believe by January, Chiang had resigned, January of
                        '49.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Li becomes the president of the republic and is trying
                        to save the situation one way or the other. Certainly much of the literature
                        suggests that there were persons in the American diplomatic establishment
                        who had probably more confidence in the military abilities of Li and Pai
                        Ch'ung-hsi than they did in Chiang. Were there any efforts while you were in
                        Hangzhou, or did you make any recommendations to the effect that the United
                        States should try to really support in any operational sense or aid? Did we,
                        in other words, identify in any practical way with Li Tsung-Jen, once he had
                        become responsible for the situation in China? Or did we ignore him, in
                        effect? Were you satisfied or dissatisfied with what we were doing in that
                        regard?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: I guess I'd better just be frank with you and say that as a vice consul
                    concerned with this 100 million population and consular duties and what was
                    going on there, that I really don't think we got into that at all. I would try
                    to report the best I could on what the local situation looked like, and I would
                    occasionally get a chance to get some perhaps stories or rumors or reports of
                    what Li Tsung-Jen was thinking or doing. But by that time, things were getting
                    pretty fragmented. The Communists had been on the north bank of the Yangtze, up
                    at Nanking since—what?—for some time. In April they actually crossed the river.
                    In March I was away about two or three weeks on this field trip, and I was
                    concerned with the local situation. So I can't say that we got into this.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>I might also say that the consul general in Hangzhou was a very fine old-line
                    consular officer, Leo Callanan. But as far as any feel for the politics of the
                    situation in Central China, he really didn't have it. That wasn't his bailiwick.
                    So we really didn't get into that sort of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If I could ask one last question. As a political officer,
                        a reporting officer in Hangzhou, did you get requests or instructions to
                        seek out particular kinds of information?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: No, I can't remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From the State Department at all? Was there any indication
                        that they were interested in finding out certain things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: No, I don't remember getting anything, especially on the political side.
                    We had our required reports we had to send in on economic business, and I was
                    covering economic stuff as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So that was on your own initiative, what you did or did
                        not report?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: That's right. It was really on our own initiative. Yes. I don't recall.
                    Undoubtedly there were some specific things that happened that the embassy might
                    send us a query on or something like that, but as far as the—of course, Li
                    Tsung-jen, by the spring of '49, was, as you know, the acting president. He was
                    in Nanking. I don't recall anything significant, really.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were in Taiwan, you must have witnessed something
                        of the transfer of the Kuomintang. Can you say something about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes. Well, by the time I got there, which was September of '49, most of
                    the troops and so forth had come over. The government was still in the mainland.
                    I don't know whether by that time they were still in Canton or whether they'd
                    gone up to Chungking. In any case, they were over there. The American
                    establishment was very small in Taiwan at the time. In fact, I have a memory—it
                    may not be accurate—that the number of Americans on Taiwan was less than 100,
                    including women and children. Bob Strong, who was the designated charg� of our
                    embassy to follow the national government around, arrived, I think, in December.
                    He was just one man, and he just came and camped on our consulate, which was
                    quite small at that time. I was there in the capacity, incidentally—it didn't
                    make much difference what you did then, because lines weren't that rigid —but I
                    was actually there as an economic officer, the only assignment I had in the
                    Foreign Service as an economic officer, although my undergraduate major was
                    economics and my graduate work at Fletcher School was primarily in economics,
                    too.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>But what I do remember about that fall of '49, particularly, was several things.
                    One was the fact that the Communists failed to take Quemoy. That, I think, is
                    something you can't blow up too much, but perhaps hasn't been given enough
                    attention. That was a real morale boost. After all, the Nationalists, in the
                    last six months, had been swept so easily away. When they got to Chungking, they
                    didn't last very long, and even a shorter time at Chengdu. But you had an
                    American-trained general, in whom we had a good deal of confidence, Sun Li-jen,
                    a graduate of V.M.I. [Virginia Military Institute]. We had some of the, I guess,
                    best equipped troops there in Taiwan and then on Quemoy (or Chinwen). And the
                    Communists obviously underestimated either the will to fight—maybe it was the
                    combination of will to fight plus the difficulty of making this rather short but
                    still amphibious attack. And they were beaten back, and they didn't try it
                    again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Sun Li-jen actually in command of the defense?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: I'm not sure he was in command of the defense, but he had been in Taiwan
                    for some time, and he was responsible for training these troops. I think he was
                    given a good deal of credit for the victory there, whether he was in actual
                    personal command or not.</p>
                <p>Another interesting thing that happened—I'm trying to fish back in my
                    memory—during that period in Taiwan was a rather ambiguous message which came
                    from the State Department at the end of October, effect, which we were supposed
                    to go to Chiang Kai-shek with, which said, in effect, that we thought that the
                    Nationalists had enough materiel and equipment and so forth on Taiwan to defend
                    the island adequately. As I say, the message was sort of mixed, because, on the
                    one hand, it was the first communication we had sent from Washington to Chiang
                    Kai-shek since he'd retired. It was sort of an acknowledgment that he was the
                    head man, although at that time he had not yet actually reassumed his title. He
                    was really sort of unofficial. This was a formal message to him, and so in a
                    sense, it was a kind of a boost, because here we were saying, “Okay, you're it,
                    and we're going to deal with you.” On the other hand, it wasn't a very clear-cut
                    statement of just what we were going to do. [Laughter] It more or less said,
                    “You've got enough materiel here and we have confidence that you're going to
                    defend the place.”</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>Jessup came over. Ambassador Jessup came over. I think it was in January of '50.
                    It was right around in there. He had an interview with Chiang Kai-shek, in which
                    I was present. Chiang did most of the talking. He thought it was a matter of
                    time before Japan went Communist, and Southeast Asia was bound to go the same
                    way. War between the U.S. and the Soviet Union was inevitable. Conculstion: the
                    U.S. must support his anti-Communist fight. Our own military estimates were that
                    it was just a matter of time before the Communists would attack Taiwan and that
                    they would be able to conquer it. The earliest estimate, as I recall, was
                    something like March of '50 and all the way up to the spring or summer of '50.
                    March may be a little early, but there was a lot of reporting about the fact
                    that the Communists were massing junks on the Fujian coast and things like that.
                    Another indication of what the State Department anticipated, I think I mentioned
                    this in my book, or at least in a footnote in it, was that we evacuated
                    dependents, especially families with children, like mine, and in my case, I was
                    transferred to Rangoon, because we wanted to cut down on the staff in
                    anticipation that there would be an invasion, trouble, and so forth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why do you think the Communists did not actually attack
                        Taiwan during that period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: I think that they were, as I said, surprised by their failure on Quemoy,
                    and this was a heck of a lot bigger operation. I think they felt they needed to
                    accumulate a lot of transport and get a lot more training and perhaps try to get
                    air superiority. I don't know, but I think they were primarily military
                    reasons.</p>
                <p>Another reason might have been that, after all, they had launched their offensive
                    across the Yangtze at Nanking in April of 1949, and in the next six months they
                    had taken all of South China, and by the fall of 1949, late fall, they had taken
                    most of West China as well. It was enormous territory. And then they had set up
                    their government, of course. It was set up on the first of October 1949, as you
                    know. In other words, they had a lot of things that were preoccupying them and
                    having been set back at Quemoy, I think they probably just hadn't been able to
                    organize and prepare well enough. The outbreak of the Korean War of course, and
                    the intervention of the Seventh Fleet, changed things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said that you accompanied Jessup.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To have a discussion with Chiang Kai-shek, in which there
                        was this rather mixed message.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: That's my memory. I would have to go look at the documents.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he request a firmer statement of assistance?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: He probably did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From the United States at this time, do you know?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: He probably did, yes, but I cannot tell you exactly. I'm sure you can
                    find that in the documents. That was their general request, always for aid.
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you puzzled at the time by the rather uncertain
                        stance by persons like Jessup, while, at the same time, perhaps the military
                        estimates are that the Communists would take the island and that the
                        dependents were being reduced?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, that I remember very well because it's an impression rather than a
                    specific fact. It's something I remember, that we were puzzled. We didn't really
                    know what the signal was supposed to be. It was sort of, you know, “We wish you
                    all sorts of success, and we think you can defend the island. You've got enough
                    materiel here and so forth,” but we were very cautious about any kind of support
                    we were going to commit ourselves to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did those of you representing the United States in Taiwan
                        at that time take issue with this, make a counterproposal, a recommendation
                        back to Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: I don't think so. I don't recall. Wasn't it in January of '50 that Truman
                    made his statement? I think we felt rather unhappy that we were getting such
                    mixed signals, that we were not getting more clear-cut—it sort of left us in a
                    difficult position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel you were in any position to in any way
                        influence policy from Washington at this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, Bob Strong was in charge, and I was the economic officer in a small
                    outfit. Bob Strong was a person who was quite outspoken. He didn't hesitate to
                    express his views. Bob Strong had also been up to Chungking, and he had seen the
                    collapse of the GRC, of the Kuomintang. I think Bob Strong was very skeptical of
                    the capabilities of the GRC to do any better and to hold out. In fact—and I
                    think I mentioned this in my book—at the time just before he left—and this is
                    before the Korean War in May 1950—he recommended drastic reduction of the staff,
                    even more reduced than it was. He had, I think, very little faith that Taiwan
                    would last. Of course, that was before the Korean War and our Seventh Fleet
                    intervention. So the mood, in other words, I think is well reflected in Truman's
                    statement that the U.S. would keep hands off Taiwan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ambassador Martin, while you were on Taiwan, did you
                        formulate an impression of how well or badly the Kuomintang was
                        administering the place?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, I think that we didn't feel that they were administering it too
                    well, but there was an improvement as compared to the time of Governor Chen Yi,
                    which was, I think, in '47, when they had the riots and so forth. You still got
                    overtones of that—or undertones, whichever they are—from the Taiwanese. But in
                    fact, due in large part, I would say, without appearing to boast about my
                    country, to our stimulus, there was under Governor Ch'en Ch'eng (who was the
                    governor in '49, replaced by K.C. Wu about the end of that year or beginning of
                    '50) there was a land reform program going on there which, I think, was one of
                    the best land reform programs that I know of anywhere in that part of the world.
                    And under this land reform program, large landowners were deprived of the land
                    which they had over the minimum, and I forget the exact amount, but it was a
                    fairly reasonable one. They were compensated partly in rice and partly in
                    industrial bonds. This was administered by a joint Chinese-U.S. organization,
                    the JCRR. I think the Chinese side's man was Chiang Mon-lin. He was the
                    Chairman. On the U.S. side there were people like Hunter and others. No, I don't
                    think Hunter was one. Ray Moyer was the principal U.S. member.</p>
                <p>I think this turned out to be a—we didn't know how successful it was going to be,
                    but I was impressed with it at the time. It seemed to me a sensible thing. It
                    gave the Taiwanese a stake in the industrialization of Taiwan, and we all know
                    how successful that's been in the long run. It led also to an increase in
                    agricultural production in Taiwan. So I would say that the program was well
                    administered, and it was probably because the Kuomintang, the Nationalists, were
                    fairly desperate then. Certainly land reform on the mainland, if it had been
                    carried out like this, might have been quite decisive in the future of China.
                    But by the time we came to Taiwan, as I say, the Nationalists were pretty
                    desperate. They were more amenable to do what we advised, and also Taiwan's a
                    small place, and it's much easier to do it there than it was in a very large
                    land mass with a huge population.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Under the Japanese, of course, Taiwan had become more developed than probably any
                    single province in China. I remember being impressed when I first went there by
                    the fact that electricity was very widely available in small towns and that it
                    was so cheap that people would keep the lights burning in their little shops and
                    so forth all day. I guess they didn't have any meters or anything, so they might
                    as well. [Laughter] They charged by the bulb or something; I don't know. But the
                    whole place was better developed. I think you have to be very cautious about
                    saying, “Well, if they'd only done this on the mainland.” [Laughter] It was a
                    lot easier in Taiwan. But they did do it; I think that's important.</p>
                <p>But on the other hand, as far as the administration is concerned, perhaps they
                    didn't really have time, they hadn't been there that long, I mean, to try to
                    recover from the very poor administration that they'd had under Chen Yi. I was
                    rather impressed with Ch'en Ch'eng. I thought he was an able guy and, of course,
                    with K.C. Wu as well. I think they were lucky to have people like that there at
                    the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned earlier that you got to know Chiang
                        Ching-kuo.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes. Chiang Ching-kuo was an enigma in a way. He came there from Shanghai
                    with a rather bad reputation, and at that time—I'm talking about '49 and '50,
                    January, when I left, the latter part of January of '50—I forget exactly what
                    Chiang Ching-kuo was doing. I think it was something to do with the veterans or
                    something like that. He was a fairly young guy, of course. He had studied in
                    Russia, as we all know, and he had a Russian wife. I didn't have a great deal of
                    business to take up with him, and I can't even remember the occasion on which I
                    got acquainted with him, but I found him fairly easy to talk to and less
                    dognamtic, I thought, than his father seemed to be, although I can't say I ever
                    got really well acquainted with Chiang Kai-shek. Ching-kuo was a person that
                    seemed to me to be more realistic about going back to the mainland and so forth.
                    Naturally, that was the line, and nobody was going to undercut it, but he struck
                    me as being a fairly down-to-earth, practical sort of guy. Obviously, he was
                    prepared to execute people, and he did. [Laughter] but he wasn't a dogmatic
                    tyrannical person at all. That was not my impression of him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't want to interrupt, but what led you to believe he
                        was less doctrinaire about the return to the mainland position? Were there
                        any specifics that you recall that he said, a general tone? That is, I must
                        say, rather surprising that you gained that impression.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes. Well, let me say two things. One is that he was not directly
                    concerned with that. In other words, whatever his concern it was local and had
                    to do with the veterans and so forth, and that's what we talked about. The other
                    is that the last time I saw Chiang Ching-Kuo was in 1968, when I stopped in
                    Taiwan returning to Hong Kong from home leave and we had breakfast together. By
                    that time, he was in a much more important position. The impression that I
                    had—and I can't give you specifics that I had from that early acquaintance with
                    him—was maintained in this private breakfast I had with him. Perhaps it's
                    because we didn't talk about it. He didn't give me the line. I think that's the
                    thing. I'm trying to remember. I think it's that I didn't get a kind of set line
                    from him that I often got from other officials when I visited. We seemed to be
                    on a more practical basis. He just struck me as a guy who was more in touch with
                    the realities of the situation, and I think his record of Taiwan indicates that,
                    at least—I don't know how much, because I haven't really been in touch with this
                    in the last ten or 15 years, how much you can give the responsibility for the
                    obvious prosperity of Taiwan and the fact that it hasn't gone into reckless
                    adventures and so forth, I'm not sure how much you can give credit to Ching-kuo,
                    but he's gone up and up until he finally became the top man. So he's obviously
                    been influential. I think his influence grew. I always felt that his influence
                    would be on the side of realism, a more realistic appreciation of the facts of
                    life and the relative impotence of Taiwan compared to the mainland and so
                    forth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Given what you said about him, I imagine you've not been
                        surprised that he's spearheaded a movement toward some degree of
                        Taiwanization of Taiwan in the last year or so.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: No, no, I'm not. As I say, I put these views forward simply as
                    impressions, because I got to know him during this period, and I made subsequent
                    visits to Taiwan and he was always very cordial to me and everything, but I
                    found that his—I don't know. I don't think I can say anything more useful about
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could we pass on to the period when you were at CA—Chinese
                        Affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That must have been very fascinating. I would assume that
                        roughly the first half of it was dominated mainly by the Korean War in some
                        form or other. Could you tell us what struck you, perhaps something that is
                        not public knowledge?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean to include the negotiations, by the way.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, as far as we were concerned, since the Korean War was in full
                    swing—perhaps I'd better date this so we'll know what period we're covering. I
                    reported into the China desk in December of '51, and by that time things had
                    been pretty well set in Korea. The Chinese had been in it for over a year.
                    Actually, it was January of '52 when I really got into my slot in the Office of
                    Chinese Affairs, so I had a year under the Truman Administration, approximately,
                    and then Eisenhower came in in January of '53.</p>
                <p>I guess there's one thing that I could contribute, perhaps, and perhaps not. It's
                    in itself not really new. But the difference between the China policy under
                    Truman in his last year—and it's the only time of which I can speak, because I
                    was there at that time, that last year—and the Eisenhower policy toward China
                    was very little, it was mainly cosmetic, and I can illustrate that point. My
                    first job there was chief of political section, and that was during the Truman
                    year. The next year I became deputy director. It had nothing to do with the
                    change in administration; it was just internal bureaucratic things. We drafted
                    an NSC paper on China policy in that last year (of Truman), and there was
                    nothing new in it. It was as many NSC papers are. It was simply a description of
                    what the policy was, and you put it down on paper and you get it approved, the
                    way the policy developed. There was nothing basically new in it, but it did
                    describe, I think, reflected accurately what the policy was that year, that last
                    year. And for some reason or other, it never got through the whole NSC process
                    until the following year, which was the Eisenhower Administration. Basically the
                    same paper went through the NSC, and there was really no basic change.</p>
                <p>This business about Chiang Kai-shek being “unleashed” by Eisenhower, again, that
                    was simply when the Eisenhower Administration said, “We will no longer prevent
                    them from attacking the mainland.” Well, as you can find in the documents,
                    actually we made very sure that the Chinese on Taiwan understood that we would
                    not support them and we would very much oppose their going to the mainland
                    without our approval, and we had no intention of approving it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lend-lease.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>MARTIN: [Laughter] So there was really no basic change there. Having been in the
                    Department and on the China desk during that particular transition period, the
                    rhetoric got a lot tougher, but the basic policies—and, of course, there wasn't
                    much we could change. [Laughter] I mean, we were already committed by Truman to
                    defend Taiwan. I never saw any indication that Mr. Dulles, let alone President
                    Eisenhower, any time were willing to back any kind of mainland invasion. But
                    getting somebody like Walter Robertson in there, who was a very nice guy but a
                    fairly hard-liner, but not an extremist by any means, you had somebody who could
                    go down there and talk to the right-wingers who were pretty strong in the Senate
                    at that time. Dulles' line was pretty hard, but when it came right down to it, I
                    don't think you could find any real difference in the policies. It was because
                    our China policy had been set by the Korean War and by our response to the
                    Korean War, basically, and especially after the Chinese intervened.</p>
                <p>I do think that later on, in the mid-Fifties—and this is pure speculation—that
                    under Dulles and Robertson and Eisenhower, our response to some Chinese
                    overtures was tougher than it might have been under another administration. But
                    at that particular time, because of the war, we were locked into a situation
                    where there really was no flexibility, and I think that was recognized. But
                    since China policy was a political issue on the Hill, the Republicans had to do
                    whatever they could to make it look like they were pursing a different
                    policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There have been two main periods. One was in the
                        mid-Fifties, around the time of the Dulles “brink of war” statement and the
                        other period more recently since the publication of the Foreign Relations
                        volumes covering that period, a lot of discussion of the use of nuclear
                        threat by the United States to compel the Chinese to sign an armistice. Do
                        you have anything to say about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: No, I wasn't in on that at all. No, I'm sorry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm sorry to hear that. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: [Laughter] Sorry. That would be an interesting subject. But I guess it
                    was, perhaps, either too sensitive for someone of my position to be in on. I
                    don't know to what extent anybody, even my boss, who was Walter McConaughy,
                    would have been consulted on something like that. I really don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were involved in the discussions with the Chinese at
                        Geneva and later Warsaw talks.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes. And also at Panmunjom. I was the only person to be—it's really of no
                    significance, but I happened to be the only person that was involved in the
                    Panmunjom, the Geneva and the Warsaw talks. So I was in at the very ground
                    floor, you might say, of our first diplomatic contacts with the Chinese
                    Communists after the Korean War, which was at Panmunjom. I don't think there's
                    anything special about that history that isn't known.</p>
                <p>The thing that struck me rather strongly when we got together with Arthur Dean,
                    who was our leader and, as you know, is a lawyer, a New York corporation lawyer,
                    not a diplomat, (although he had diplomatic assignments before, going back,
                    apparently to Mexico in the Twenties and Thirties) was that he was very strongly
                    convinced that we must get an agreement with the Chinese for the sake of the
                    Eisenhower Administration. He felt it would be a real feather in their cap. I
                    thought that our chances of getting an agreement with the Chinese was very slim.
                    He was telling the press we could do it in two weeks. Well, he finally walked
                    out, as you may recall, of the talks. He walked out in December, and I don't
                    think he ever forgave me for being right about that. It wasn't that I wanted
                    them to fail, it's just that I didn't think the situation was one in which the
                    Chinese had that much flexibility. This particularly was true because, after
                    all, we were negotiating there in the DMZ, and also going on the DMZ were these
                    prisoner interrogations. It was pretty obvious, once the prisoners began to opt
                    not to return to China, that the Chinese couldn't let this go on, so there were
                    all sorts of disturbances which prevented the interrogation. Finally, as you
                    recall, in January of '54, the prisoners were released. The Indians were in
                    charge of this under General Thimayya, who was a very, very interesting, very
                    pleasant guy and a very capable guy. He said, “That's the way south; that's the
                    way north,” and most of them went south.</p>
                <p>Well, all during this hassle in the fall of '53, where the Chinese and the North
                    Koreans were accusing us of sabotaging the armistice agreement and everything,
                    it was just not the kind of atmosphere where they're going to reach an agreement
                    implementing the armistice agreement. It was sort of inevitable, I think, that
                    the thing would just be stalemated, and it was. I think Dean might have handled
                    it a little better, although I think basically he was right. When you're at a
                    negotiation and the people you're negotiating with start attacking your good
                    faith, attacking your credentials and your ability to negotiate, then you might
                    as well fold up. As a minimum in a negotiation, you have to have both sides
                    saying, “Okay, you do represent the other side, and we'll negotiate with you.”
                    That's where we got at that particular time. I think that Dean did contribute,
                    because he was a very good briefer and a very good lawyer, to an understanding,
                    to giving a public explanation in his press conferences after the various
                    sessions, which made the U.N. side, the U.S. side, look more flexible, which we
                    were—there's no question about it—than the Chinese. I think that's about all we
                    could get out of that. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of agreement was Dean actually hoping to reach?
                        Was it a peace treaty with the Chinese?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>MARTIN: No, no. This was very limited. This was a very limited negotiation, and
                    maybe that was why he felt we could accomplish it. Under Paragraph 60 of the
                    armistice agreement, the two sides were to meet, to discuss the future of Korea
                    and arrive at some political settlement. Well, our negotiations in Panmunjom
                    were merely to make arrangements to set up the conference: it was not the
                    conference itself, just to make arrangements to set up the conference. And as
                    far as we were concerned, there were only two things to talk about: when would
                    the conference be held and where would it be held. The Chinese and the North
                    Koreans wanted to discuss the composition of the conference. We felt the
                    composition of the conference had already been settled by Paragraph 60 of the
                    armistice agreement, and actually, that language about the two sides was
                    originally introduced by the Communist side. So one wouldn't expect that they
                    would make an issue of this, but they did. They wanted to have neutral
                    countries, and they wanted to have the Soviet Union there. We said, “We don't
                    object to the Soviet Union being there, but we can't call it neutral. It's
                    completely on your side.” So this is what we wrangled about, and we eventually
                    divided into two committees.</p>
                <p>We did come to one agreement that was on the agenda. [Laughter] But then we
                    divided into two committees. I was in charge of the subcommittee which was
                    discussing the time and place of the conference, and naturally that was just
                    marking time, because the real issue was the composition, and we never got
                    anywhere on that. But I think it should be pointed out that in Berlin, in
                    January of '54, an agreement was reached to have a conference on Korea and on
                    Indochina to convene in Geneva in April of 1954. Most books refer to this as the
                    Geneva Conference on Indochina. They totally ignore the fact that Korea was
                    discussed. But, in fact, there was a conference of the two sides as provided in
                    the armistice agreement, and Zhou En-lai was there. The only time that I'd ever
                    seen Zhou En-lai in action was at this conference. It was interesting to watch
                    him.</p>
                <p>But anyway, that Panmunjom exercise was an exercise in complete futility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Forgive me, but my curiosity will not let me let you get
                        away with referring to Zhou En-lai as interesting to watch. Can't you tell
                        us more than that about Zhou En-lai? [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, he had been a Chinese opera actor as a student, you know, so he was
                    a dramatic fellow, and he had this high-pitched voice which was perhaps a little
                    . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Women's parts.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, perhaps that's why he did women's parts. But that came across when
                    he was making his points. I don't know what else to say about him. What he said
                    and so forth was pretty much to be expected. Our main problem at the Korean end
                    (and that's why I was an advisor to the U.S. delegation, because of my
                    experience in Panmunjom), was, as it often was, of getting the South Koreans to
                    go along and to present a united front. We finally succeeded in getting a
                    position which we could offer as the U.N. side's position, and it was rejected
                    by the Communists, which wasn't surprising, and the conference went on to deal
                    with Indochina, where they really did something. So it's not surprising that
                    people forget about the Korean part because nothing came out of it at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the South Koreans actually represented in that
                        conference, the brief conference? Because they had not signed the
                        armistice.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: No, they had not signed the armistice, that's true. No, I don't think
                    that they were officially represented, but we didn't want them to denounce our
                    proposal, because it would look very poor: the Communists could always come back
                    and say, “Well, look, the South Koreans don't agree to this.” We finally got
                    something or we got them to be still or agree not to denounce our proposal.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>Of course, the thing that interested me as far as our relations with China was
                    concerned at the Geneva conference, was that we sat down and had bilateral
                    discussions with the Chinese on the question of the Americans detained in China
                    and the Chinese who had not been allowed to leave the United States. Those two
                    issues really weren't comparable, because we had never imprisoned any Chinese.
                    There had been some who had been refused permission to leave because,
                    (interestingly enough the same argument that is being made by Gorbachev on why
                    he won't let some Jews leave), because they knew secrets. Well, we said, “These
                    people know secrets.” During the Korean War whether that was a valid thing or
                    not I don't know: but certainly after the Korean War it was no longer valid, so
                    we had no interest whatsoever in keeping them. In subsequent years we even went
                    to prisons to try to get Chinese that had been convicted of crimes to say they'd
                    go back to the mainland if we let them go. [Laughter] We just couldn't find
                    anybody. [Laughter] They'd rather stay in this country. In other words, we went
                    to great lengths to try to get Chinese to go back to the mainland. We didn't
                    force anybody, obviously, but if they wanted to, even if they were in jail, they
                    could return. Having bilateral discussions with the PRC at Geneva was a
                    breakthrough. I actually drafted the telegram that went to Dulles. Dulles, by
                    that time, had left the Geneva conference, and Smith, the Under Secretary or
                    whatever he was then at that time, Bedell Smith was in charge, and Robertson was
                    still there. I drafted the telegram which went back to the Department, saying,
                    “We have to sit down and talk to the Chinese.” We wanted to try to do it through
                    the British, as we'd done before, but they would have none of it. They said,
                    “You're here talking to us. We're in the same conference with you, and you won't
                    even sit down and talk bilaterally,” so we had to talk bilaterally. We brought
                    in Trevelyan, the British charg� at that time, as sort of an umpire to begin
                    with, but then we wound up with bilateral talks. So that was the beginning, sort
                    of a preliminary act to the Warsaw talks on the Geneva talks which began
                    later.</p>
                <p>In the telegram we just laid it out that, “We're either going to talk to the
                    Chinese or we're not going to get anywhere on the prisoner issue. It's not going
                    to read very well at home, you know, if you say, 'These guys are detaining our
                    citizens and we refuse to talk to them about it.” Of course, we had tried to
                    talk to them before when we were still in China, and they wouldn't talk to us
                    then. So as I say, I drafted the telegram. It was approved by Robertson and by
                    Bedell Smith, and sent to Dulles. Although he seemed to be a little reluctant,
                    he did eventually agree we would do it, so we went ahead. [Laughter] That was
                    the beginning of that. Alex Johnson was, of course, our secretary general. Wang
                    Ping-nan was the secretary general of the Chinese side, and it was interesting
                    that they were the two negotiators in '55 when the talks restarted. [See FRUAS
                    1955-57 on China for further details]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the reluctance, in your judgment, on the part of
                        Dulles?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, it was because the background of the Geneva conference. It was
                    agreed at Berlin that the Chinese would be there, the Chinese Communists, and we
                    knew Zhou En-lai would be there. Peking obviously played it up: “This shows
                    we're now a great power. We're sitting down with the Soviet Union, the United
                    States, Britain, and France.” The PRC at that time were trying to get as much as
                    they could in gestures of recognition from the United States. Our policy was
                    very rigid on that, and people like McConaughy and others would make speeches
                    saying , “Just because we're sitting down with them in a conference with a lot
                    of other people doesn't mean we're recognizing them.” But sitting down with them
                    bilaterally might seem like a step forward to recognition, at least an
                    appearance of an acceptance, of the PRC. That's why we tried to get the British
                    involved, , and we had Trevelyan there for two sessions before to bow out. the
                    talks were finally reduced to the consular level; but the PRC did release some
                    of our people. Then the talks sort of petered out. That was the background to
                    the Geneva and Warsaw talks. You used the word “Warsaw talks,” and that's
                    usually what's referred to, but people forget that for two and a half years it
                    was the Geneva talks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you go over very briefly the issues in the Geneva
                        talks other than the exchange of prisoners?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, that was the only thing we were interested in. Well, I shouldn't
                    say that. That's the first thing we were interested in, and the second was the
                    renunciation of force in the Taiwan Strait. No, the Chinese weren't about to do
                    this. They felt that this was an internal affair because Taiwan was part of
                    China, so they could not enter formally into an international agreement,
                    renouncing force against their own territory. So it was a built-in, total
                    impasse there. That went on. The Chinese used the talks to try to get us to
                    change our policy on travel to China and on trade and so forth. At that time, we
                    were very rigid. I participated in the talks only at the very beginning, in
                    August '55, because I had been assigned to the National War College spent a year
                    there, and I was really out of Chinese affairs for that year.</p>
                <p>Then I went to Britain, to London, and at first I was assigned to work on NATO
                    affairs, but then a fellow named Ringwalt, who had been in London for six or
                    seven years working on the Far East, finally departed, and they put me in his
                    place simply because I was available and had the background. Then I worked on
                    the Far East, but not so much on China, really, until '57, when I had to make a
                    flight to Geneva every month, almost every month, to participate in the ongoing
                    Geneva talks. By that time they had been pretty well stalled.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>Alex Johnson was the principal negotiator, and I was his assistant. In December
                    of '57 we were instructed to inform the Chinese that Johnson had been assigned
                    to Thailand as ambassador and would be leaving, and I was going to take his
                    place. Well, at that time, I had the rank of first secretary in the embassy at
                    London. So the Chinese said, “These are ambassadorial talks, and we like Mr.
                    Martin, we can't accept him because he's not an ambassador.” We had deliberately
                    tried to downgrade the talks; there's no question about it. We felt we weren't
                    getting anywhere. After returning to London, I had some correspondence with the
                    Chinese side trying to get talks going at my level, but it didn't work out. The
                    only signficance of that, I think, is that we and the Chinese both decided that
                    these Geneva talks were getting nowhere. We were the ones that took the
                    initiative. I don't know whether they honestly thought in Washington that the
                    Chinese would accept this; I never thought they would.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Accept the downgrading?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Accept the downgrading of the talks. Yes, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned one of the issues was the United States'
                        effort to persuade the Chinese to denounce the use of force.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then we jumped up to '57.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: That's because I wasn't connected with the talks in between those
                    times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But in '54, in other words, did you have the first
                        discussions with the Chinese, urging them to denounce force?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: No, no.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When was that first? Was that before the Taiwan Strait
                        crisis or after?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: In June '54, we started these bilateral talks at the Geneva Conference.
                    By agreement they were reduced to the consular level. The Chinese released a few
                    American prisoners, and I think we told them we had some Chinese who were
                    leaving and so forth. These talks were held intermittently, I think, for four or
                    five weeks in Geneva at that level. Now, that's the background of the Warsaw
                    talks.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So there was no discussion of renunciation of force by
                        that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: That was strictly limited to exchanges.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So there's really no discussion of renunciation of force
                        until after the first so-called Taiwan Strait crisis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '54 or '55.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: As you recall the background of the Geneva talks was that in April of
                    '55, there was a conference of non-aligned countries in Indonesia, and Zhou
                    En-lai said he would be willing to talk to the United States. That put us on the
                    spot, and we agreed. We had communications through the British, and set up the
                    Geneva talks at the ambassadorial level. The renunciation of force then became a
                    theme song of ours. “You can't do anything else until you renounce force.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That emerges out of the first Taiwan Strait crisis,
                        probably.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Probably did, yes. Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Back to the background of the first Taiwan Strait crisis.
                        Can you give me a feel for who was in charge at the time of the first Taiwan
                        Strait crisis and your position? You were deputy director?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>MARTIN: That was '54. I became deputy director in '53. Okay. Walter McConaughy
                    was the director, and Walter Robertson was the assistant secretary. I forget who
                    was his deputy at that time. This was something that also got into the U.N.
                    Well, I should back up further. After the Geneva conference, the Nationalists,
                    of course, were quite unhappy about the fact that we sat down with the Chinese
                    Communists there and actually were having consular-level talks. The Korean War
                    was over, we'd had the Indochina agreement, and so the decision was made in the
                    Department, which obviously was supported by Eisenhower, to substitute for the
                    Truman declaration of, “The Seventh Fleet will protect Taiwan,” a treaty, mutual
                    defense treaty, this was signed by the Republic of China and the U.S. in
                    December of '54. Of course, it came out that we were negotiating this treaty. I
                    don't know to what extent this triggered the bombardments of Chinmen and
                    offshore islands by the Communists, but nevertheless, they were attacking. We
                    were negotiating the treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm confused here. My history is not very good. Are you
                        suggesting that the intention on the part of the administration in
                        negotiating mutual security treaty preceded the growing escalation of
                        tension in the Taiwan Strait?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: They went along together. I can't remember exact dates of when the
                    shellings began. Was it August of '54?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: September 9th.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: September 9th. You're asking me a question I can't answer, whether we had
                    intention of negotiating the treaty before this began or not.</p>
                <p>I came back from Panmunjom in February, and I was back in Washington for about
                    six weeks and then went to Geneva. I came back from Geneva in June of '54. So
                    that was a long separation from my family. As I recall, in that period of March
                    and early April, between the Panmunjom negotiations and the Geneva Conference, I
                    was pretty well focusing in preparing for the Conference. I don't remember any
                    discussion about the possibility of the treaty. (The treaty was first considered
                    in March, 1954, but put off because of the impending Geneva Conference.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To avoid possible confusion on the record, Ambassador
                        Martin, you referred a minute ago to reassurance of the Chinese. You meant
                        the ROC on Taiwan.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, yes. I meant the Nationalists, the ROC, reassurance that we really
                    intended to support them, and that was policy. That was written into the NSC
                    papers, and it was publicly declared. There was no secret about it. I can't
                    remember whether anybody seriously argued against it. I think doubts were
                    raised, and perhaps legitimately, that, you know, “Do you want to go this far?”
                    But in CA, we supported the treaty, because we felt that if it is, indeed—and it
                    was—U.S. policy to defend Taiwan and the Pescadores, let's make that completely
                    clear to everybody, including the Chinese Communists, so they won't make a
                    mistake and feel that we really don't mean it.</p>
                <p>Now, Dulles, as I recall, was not opposed to it, but he was somewhat skeptical
                    that Chiang Kai-shek and the Nationalists would accept a treaty under the
                    conditions of which we would have to impose, which would be that it would be
                    strictly limited to Taiwan and the Pescadores, and, as I recall, he said words
                    to the effect of, “Well, you know, this puts some limitations on them. Why would
                    they accept it?” Our judgment in CA, which turned out to be completely right for
                    a change, was that, “He'll accept this. As far as he's concerned, a guarantee by
                    the U.S. for his protection in Taiwan is the most important thing he can get.
                    Despite all the talk that's going on, Chiang Kai-shek, basically, in his whole
                    military history had been a very cautious person, and the idea that he is going
                    to go back to the mainland without some sort of support from the United States
                    is just not a practical one, and he knows it.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I feel a little unclear as to whether you think—and there
                        may be no basis for a judgment—that the Chinese might have started the
                        crisis in part as sort of retaliation, in an effort to create alarm and
                        prevent the signing of such a treaty.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, yes, I think it's possible. I think it's possible that they did. I
                    don't know whether it's the chicken or the egg here, but the more I think about
                    it, the more I'm convinced in my own mind that we had this idea of a treaty for
                    the reasons I've mentioned before any specific attack on the offshore islands,
                    because, after all, the Chinese Communists' position, the Peking position, was,
                    “We're going to liberate Taiwan, and we're going to do it by force.” They had
                    continued to say this, so there was no question that there was a threat. Now,
                    the offshore island business is always a very, very tricky one, and all I can
                    say is—and, again, I don't want to say like, “I told you so”—but we in CA
                    constantly felt that the dangers of the offshore island position were
                    exaggerated by the critics, and maybe it's just luck, but it turned out here
                    it's more than 30 years later, and there has not been a war resulting from the
                    offshore island position.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>But as you recall, we signed the treaty in December, and then, of course, the
                    Communists understandably made a tremendous stink about it, and there were
                    further threats. We took it to the U.N. I must confess I'd have to refresh my
                    memory, but in January '55 was the New Zealand resolution, which I hesitate to
                    even mention, because I can't remember the contents of it. But it had to do with
                    the offshore islands of January '55. We helped the Chinese to evacuate the
                    Tachen islands, and they evacuated another island which we felt was beyond air
                    cover and beyond their ability to really protect. They did it. But, of course,
                    Quemoy and Matsu were always the focus of this offshore island contention,
                    because they're right in Amoy harbor, practically, and they have great political
                    symbolism, of course, for the Nationalists.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: May I ask you one question? The Nationalists later claimed
                        that in exchange for their agreement to evacuate the Tachen islands, we'd
                        given them a private pledge to defend Quemoy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: I don't know anything about that, I really don't. I'm very skeptical.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I am, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: I think that we have never gone beyond the congressional resolution or
                    whatever it was that said it's in the area. We've always deliberately left it
                    vague; we never gave them a specific pledge. I don't think we ever did. I'm sure
                    we never did. (There is documentary evidence to partially support the
                    Nationialists' claim of a pledge.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just to see how things were being done in the government,
                        the procedure and process, you said, for example, that you always felt that
                        the critics' concern about policy toward the offshore islands was somewhat
                        exaggerated, that there was not the danger they had envisioned.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: There was a danger, obviously, but they would say, “It's going to drag us
                    into a war with the Communists and everything else.” Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the cost benefits of the evacuation of Quemoy and
                        Matsu sort of broadly and widely considered within the Office of Chinese
                        Affairs at this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, I would say this, and, again, my memory is trying to dredge
                    30-year-old—more than 30 years ago. But I think that our position was—again, I
                    would consider it a pragmatic position, and that is that, yes, if we had our
                    way, we'd get off the offshore islands. They are dangerous. They're not as
                    dangerous as people say, but they're not a good place to be. But the only way we
                    could get the Nationalists off would be possibly even some resort to force, to
                    force them off. They were determined to hang on. It meant a great deal to them
                    for its political symbolism, having a little toe on the mainland. We had no
                    commitment, and we felt that—and I think this was expressed to the Nationalists
                    on a number of occasions, “You've got far too much out there. You're risking too
                    much. This is not a good thing to do.” So I think definitely we did not feel
                    that it was a good policy as far as the Nationalists were concerned, but it was
                    their policy, and we were not willing to take our opposition to the point of
                    using force or some drastic leverage against them to pull out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it actually discussed in those terms, let's say within
                        your office, that, “It will require us to go to that point”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Oh, I think . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you recall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, something like this, of course, let me say this, especially under
                    the Eisenhower Administration, and that's when I spent most of my time on China
                    desk, the NSC—a thing like this, we would perhaps make an initial draft of the
                    policy, but all of this sort of thing was handled by NSC committees. I chaired
                    one on China, but it had representatives from the Pentagon, the CIA, even in
                    some aspects of China policy, the Treasury Department. In other words, these
                    decisions and these discussions took place in the context of NSC papers, NSC
                    meetings, subcommittee meetings, and that sort of thing.</p>
                <p>The funny thing is, just on a personal note, that my last 12 years in the Foreign
                    Service, I was never stationed in Washington, so I can't compare how it was
                    under Johnson and Nixon and so forth. But my feeling is that in the Eisenhower
                    years, there was more sort of committee work, there was more interdepartmental
                    exchange and working than there was under subsequent administrations. But that's
                    just a personal thing. Certainly in my time, there was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this lead to a reduction in the direct influence upon
                        policy formulation of the Office of China Affairs, for example?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>MARTIN: No, I don't know. Again, I don't think so, because we chaired the
                    committee, we usually drafted the stuff, and then it was just a question of
                    getting through. But in the years that I was in the Department in Washington, we
                    had two very strong Secretaries, Acheson and Dulles. That basically is what gave
                    our State Department more clout than I think it's had recently. I was in a
                    number of meetings in Dulles' office when he would call up Eisenhower, while we
                    were having a meeting, to discuss something with the President. My feeling is we
                    had as much clout as we've ever had in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You speak of two very strong Secretaries. Did you feel
                        that someone like Secretary Dulles relied upon your office for a source of
                        ideas or did he have other sources?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: I'll give you an example. I can't remember whether it was this offshore
                    island crisis or the one in '58. Let's see. Dulles died in '59, didn't he? He
                    was still there in '58. Anyway, to give you an example, in the particular crisis
                    situation, I remember being in a meeting. I used to go up there and back up
                    Robertson. He certainly had a lot of trust in Robertson, but at this particular
                    meeting on the offshore island crisis—I guess it was probably '58, because he
                    turned to his Counselor at that time, Freddy Reinhardt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: MacArthur?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>MARTIN: No, it was after MacArthur. Anyway, people were supposed to produce some
                    sort of a position for him, and he would say to Robertson, “You do so and so.”
                    Then he'd say to his counselor, “You do so and so.” And so forth. What happened,
                    Robertson would call us up and say, “Will you do this for us?” And the counselor
                    would call us up and say, “Will you do this for us?” So Dulles didn't turn to us
                    as an office directly, but Robertson, the Counselor, and there was somebody
                    else—I remember there were three people calling us. He thought he had about
                    three different people to do it, but we had the expertise, so they all asked us
                    to do it. That was one of the problems in a crisis like this, because we'd get
                    tremendous overload, and then we'd have the press, the press people. Our press
                    office would want us to be available to answer questions. In other words, the
                    power of an office like Chinese Affairs was in its expertise and the fact that
                    it had been following the details and keeping track of it. So to come up with a
                    paper or a position, you had the input. To that extent, we had influence. Now,
                    you know, it had to go through the counselor, and he may have changed it with
                    Robertson and so forth. But it seemed to me that the committee system, which
                    perhaps did become a little cumbersome, the OCB committee and subcommittee
                    system under Eisenhower, did have the advantage of getting a lot of input
                    from—we called ourselves working level—from the working level at Pentagon, at
                    CIA, and so forth. The working level types, we maintained good contacts with
                    each other, and naturally, on our intelligence estimates, I suppose there were
                    estimates that I wasn't cleared to see, but I saw some pretty sensitive stuff
                    and so did other people. We were getting all these inputs. So I think we had
                    about as good a basis as anybody could have for making judgments. As I say, our
                    judgments on some of these things, I think, not necessarily on policy, but of
                    what the situation was, what was going to happen, that the offshore islands
                    weren't going to lead to war and so forth, I think those judgments have stood
                    the test of time pretty well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could we perhaps move on to the 1958 crisis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you like to add something?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes. I would like to point out that—let's go to July first. Well, let's
                    go back to December '57. I was appointed the U.S. representative to the
                    Communist side. The Chinese said, “You're not an ambassador,” so we did
                    deliberately downgrade it. Washington, I think, didn't give a damn, really, at
                    that time for continuing the talks, although, as I said, I carried on some
                    correspondence under instructions of Washington from London with somebody—I
                    can't remember his name—who was my opposite number on the Chinese delegation,
                    saying, “We'd like to get the talks going.” I knew they weren't going to do it,
                    and I didn't blame them, really.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>But in July of '58, we did send a message saying we would like to resume the
                    talks. We did take the initiative, and I think that should be kept in mind. We
                    informed the Chinese that we would like to resume the talks at the ambassadorial
                    level, and we appointed Ambassador Beam, who was our ambassador in Warsaw to
                    represent the U.S.. That's when the Warsaw talks began. But in August of '58,
                    they started very heavy shelling of Quemoy, the largest and heaviest shelling
                    that had taken place anywhere in recent history, it was said. I was just being
                    transferred back from London. I was on home leave before taking up my job as
                    Director of CA, and I was called back because of the crisis. I remember a number
                    of meetings, particularly with Herter, who was Under Secretary at that time.
                    “What are we going to do about this offshore island crisis?” The estimates were
                    really quite pessimistic as to the Chinese Communist capabilities. I was rather
                    surprised at the—I wouldn't say panic, but they were almost pushing the panic
                    button. “What could we do in this situation?” And it turned out that—and I can't
                    remember the exact decision, but I think we decided we would convoy, but that's
                    as far as we would go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To the three-mile limit.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, to the three-mile limit. That's right. The Nationalists would pick
                    it up there. Well, a fairly decisive development was that the Nationalist Air
                    Force, using our heat-seeking missiles, knocked down a number of the Communists'
                    planes, and I think that probably had quite a chastening effect on them. I think
                    after the experience way back to '49, they felt they needed air superiority. So
                    the Communists agreed to resume the talks in Warsaw, and from then on they were
                    the Warsaw talks. That crisis calmed down, but there was an aftermath which was
                    rather interesting, and that is that Dulles and Robertson—I think McConaughy,
                    too, yes, because I was in charge of the desk—no, let's see. They went out to
                    Taiwan and talked to Chiang Kai-shek and got him to agree that he would not use
                    force against the mainland. Here again, I think Dulles might have been surprised
                    that he would agree to this, but, again, I think it shows his basic caution. In
                    other words, despite all their talk and everything, the Nationalists really knew
                    that they could not get back on the mainland unless they had active U.S.
                    support, and that they would do it without our support was never a serious
                    threat. But that's the kind of threat that people kept worrying about. Maybe you
                    can't blame them. But as I said before, the whole military history of Chiang
                    Kai-shek, if he erred on any side, it was on the side of caution rather than the
                    side of boldness.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember talking to one of your colleagues in the CA
                        when the offshore islands crisis of '58 was at its height, and he was
                        convinced that the Soviet Union was absolutely behind the PRC and was facing
                        a serious sort of monolithic threat there. Was that the general
                        perception?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>MARTIN: No, I don't think so. We were perhaps rather slow in seeing the beginning
                    of the split, but certainly one of the factors—and I didn't mention this—that
                    may have made the Chinese back down on this was the Soviets gave signals that
                    they were not going to get involved. This may, in turn, have exacerbated the
                    coming split between the two partners, the two allies. Yes, I think that we
                    eventually did pick this up, because I remember it quite clearly, but it took a
                    while. We had been, of course, seeing them as pretty monolithic. It took a
                    while, perhaps too long, longer than it should have, to see that the frictions
                    were getting very serious between them. We were entertaining the possibility,
                    but were cautious about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have a sense of when this perception did begin to
                        dawn to the working level at State and maybe other agencies?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, I think probably about the time of the Great Leap Forward, because
                    it was pretty obvious. The Russians—was it early '60 that they pulled out all of
                    their technicians, and they were obviously not happy about the Great Leap
                    Forward? I remember one reaction we had, and it may have been a good one or it
                    may not have been a good one, there's sort of a doubt about it now, but I gave a
                    lecture at the National War College on China in January of—in fact, it was on
                    inauguration eve, January of 1961—and the thrust of my lecture, which I think,
                    looking back on it, seems to me to be somewhat exaggerated, but it seemed like a
                    good thing at the time to me, was, “Just because there's a Sino-Soviet split,
                    don't underestimate the threat of the Chinese.” And I went on and on about the
                    terrible threat of the Chinese.</p>
                <p>The idea was, I think it was exaggerated; I don't think it was completely wrong,
                    but the thrust of my thesis was that the Chinese are really more dangerous than
                    the Soviet Union, not because they're more powerful, but because they're more
                    uncertain. You don't know what they're going to do, they're more unreliable,
                    they're having these problems internally that might affect their external
                    policy, and if you look at their propaganda, they're very belligerent and so
                    forth. But it was to offset the idea that because there's a Sino-Soviet split,
                    not to worry about the Chinese anymore, you see. So we were at that time
                    definitely aware of the split. I would say the thing that stands out in my mind
                    is when the Soviets pulled out their technicians and so forth. It was pretty
                    obvious then, perhaps.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have a lot more, but I think we should stop.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: My voice begins to give out after a couple of hours.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You have really given us a wealth of information and
                        insight, for which we certainly are very grateful.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>Kennedy: Today is March 17, 1988. This is the third of a series of interviews
                    with Ambassador Edwin W. Martin concerning his Chinese experiences. This
                    interview is being conducted on behalf of the Foreign Service History Center of
                    George Washington University and the Association for Diplomatic Studies.
                    Professor Harold Hinton will be conducting the interview.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ambassador Martin, I think we've now reached the point
                        where it's appropriate to begin talking about your tour of duty in Hong
                        Kong, 1967. And you were Consul General at that time. I myself visited Hong
                        Kong during that period more than once. Of course the period coinciding with
                        the Cultural Revolution, at least the heroic days, so to speak, of the
                        Cultural Revolution on the mainland, but first I'd like to ask if you could
                        tell us something about your view of the utility of Hong Kong as a listening
                        post with respect to China. If I may add, we now of course have an embassy
                        in Beijing which we didn't then, and yet we still maintain considerable
                        listening facilities in Hong Kong. Why is this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, let me go back to my time there before we had an embassy, before we
                    had any kind of office. Before we even had the liaison office that we set up
                    after Henry Kissinger'svisit to Beijing in the spring of 1973, Hong Kong was a
                    kind of window on the world for the Chinese and it was one that those countries
                    such as the United States which did not have any official representation there,
                    really any private representation of any kind in China, it was a window that we
                    could look through to see what was going on in China.</p>
                <p>And we got our information there through interviews, some very extensive
                    interviews, with people coming out of China, refugees, people who were able to
                    go in and out on business, and also the diplomats of other governments who were
                    stationed there. And we were able during the Cultural Revolution — as you
                    pointed out, I went to Hong Kong during the height of the Cultural Revolution —
                    we were able to expand our sources of information because there was an increased
                    flow of refugees. There was a lot of factional fighting among Red Guards and
                    other communist groups who delighted in exposing what they would consider past
                    crimes of the Party. They published their own little papers, they published
                    documents. So there was a real explosion of information at that time about what
                    was going on in China. And we also were able to supply even some of our
                    diplomatic friends in Peking with information which they didn't have.</p>
                <p>They were of course fairly restricted in the information they were able to obtain
                    in China. And most of them had fairly small establishments in Beijing at the
                    time. We had a very large establishment in Hong Kong. Our consulate there was
                    larger than most embassies in terms of numbers of personnel, and we had a lot of
                    people who were specialists in China, spoke the language, and we were able to
                    monitor radio and monitor newspapers.</p>
                <p>So on the whole this was a, especially when I was Consul General there, was a
                    very fruitful source of information. And of all the sources that we had, it was
                    the most important.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>Now I don't know as much about, from personal knowledge, about the value of Hong
                    Kong as a listening post now since we have an embassy in Beijing and we have
                    consulates, but I can still imagine that there are certain types of information
                    which we can get from travelers, and we maintain an expert staff there. I think
                    we've considerably reduced, and we should have reduced, the size of the China-
                    watching staff in Hong Kong, but we still have them there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: May I ask whether you found the British authorities in
                        Hong Kong helpful in getting information?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, they were. The British were helpful. And they could supply
                    information from first-hand observation, of course, which we didn't have. That
                    was helpful. They could talk to Chinese officials, Chinese government, PRC
                    government, and so they could get a certain angle that we couldn't get on the
                    news. On the other hand, we could get a certain volume of information which they
                    didn't have access to, or if they did they didn't have the facilities to utilize
                    it, as we did. I'm speaking here of British officials from Beijing who came
                    through Hong Kong.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In view of all the controversy we've heard in recent years
                        about CIA, is there anything you could say about CIA as a source of
                        information.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, as you can imagine, I can't get into detail, but it was, the
                    operation there in Hong Kong was an intelligence collection operation. It wasn't
                    a covert operation. And naturally they played an important part in the
                    information that we got.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was quite a lot of radical activity in Hong Kong
                        while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you either personally or did the consulate general in
                        general feel threatened at any time physically?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, I don't think we did except in this sense—and I'll give you an
                    illustration. When I arrived, which was the beginning of October in 1967, to
                    take up the post of Consul General, we went to the residence from the airport by
                    a rather circuitous route. And I recall that on the road when we were going to
                    the Consul General's residence, there was a paper bag in the road and the driver
                    of our car very carefully skirted this because the radicals or the terrorists or
                    what you want to call them, were sort of randomly leaving bombs around on the
                    roads and on the trolley tracks and so forth. And a number of people were
                    killed.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>I recall specifically that a police inspector who was trying to defuse a bomb was
                    killed and the British in their inimitable style staged a very showy funeral
                    with the bagpipes and the slow march and all the rest of it, learning from their
                    long years of imperial experience how to put on a show like this. And of course
                    the British stiff upper lip and all the rest of it. But there was another person
                    who was murdered in a rather gruesome way, kind of a talk-show person on a Hong
                    Kong radio and the Communists didn't like him for some reason or other, or the
                    radicals didn't like him, so he was wiped out.</p>
                <p>I think there was a certain feeling of insecurity, but there were never any
                    direct threats against us or against the American consulate. When I went over to
                    Macao, because I was also accredited to Macao, to the colonial government there,
                    I remember seeing the vestiges of demonstrations there. The governor of Hong
                    Kong at that time was David Trench, Sir David Trench. And the Colonial
                    Secretary, sort of the number two man in the government, was a fellow named
                    Gass, and there were slogans painted on the wall, “Hang Trench and Burn
                    Gass.”</p>
                <p>Of course there had been a good deal of fright in Hong Kong during '67. And I
                    think perhaps my predecessor, Ed Rice, experienced more of that than I did,
                    although things were still pretty hot in the fall of '67. But one thing that
                    rather brought this home to me—well, perhaps I should say first that quite a few
                    people evacuated Hong Kong and there was a good deal of capital flight in '67. A
                    couple of personal experiences: My wife was asked by the International Rescue
                    Committee to supervise a number of daycare centers for refugees children, which
                    she did most of the time we were in Hong Kong. And the reason she was asked to
                    do it, partly it was because she had the background in this profession, but the
                    person who had been doing it before was one of those who had left Hong Kong. The
                    other illustration is one of the first official public acts that I was requested
                    to do in Hong Kong was to open a small oil blending plant that Mobil Oil had
                    constructed. And it was one of these things where I was asked to go and make a
                    little speech and cut the ribbon. This was played up, it made headlines in the
                    Hong Kong papers. There are something like a dozen papers in Hong Kong. And it
                    was played up as an expression of American confidence in the future of Hong
                    Kong. And that really brought home to me the extent of the jitters there.</p>
                <p>And as a matter of fact, this was, I think, mainly coincidence but in '68 there
                    was a steady recovery of confidence in Hong Kong and the number of incidents
                    tapered off. And of course in China, I think, the army was beginning to crack
                    down a bit on the radicals. But of course this oil blending plant had been
                    planned and financed long before the panic, but the fact is that Mobil went
                    ahead with it, while some other companies didn't go ahead with plans that they
                    had. Early in '68 another American company, insurance company, asked me to come
                    and do the same thing, cut the ribbon, and I did that. And that again was played
                    up as an example of American confidence. So the Americans were among the bolder,
                    more confident people of Hong Kong.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think it's rather obvious that Hong Kong could have been
                        taken over by some combination of internal and external pressures, say in
                        '67. I realize this is a simple-minded scenario, but why didn't this happen,
                        in your opinion?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, pure speculation of course. The one thing that I used to emphasize
                    to America businessmen — and in '68 and '69, I don't know how many dozen
                    presidents and vice presidents of corporations and so forth would come to my
                    office and ask my opinion about whether they should invest in Hong Kong. And I
                    would say, I certainly cannot make up your mind or the mind of your company
                    whether you should invest, but I can try to give you a picture of how we see the
                    picture in Hong Kong and on that basis you can make up your mind. And the main
                    thrust of it was that Hong Kong is very important, at least at this stage, to
                    China for economic reasons. Ninety-nine percent, roughly, of the people of Hong
                    Kong are Chinese. Most of what they eat and what they wear comes from China. And
                    Hong Kong's currency is a good hard currency. And China makes a great deal of
                    important foreign exchange out of Hong Kong. Also I think Hong Kong is important
                    to the PRC because of what I mentioned earlier, it's sort of a window on the
                    world. And they had there the Bank of China, they had the people who sort of
                    took the place of diplomats or consular officials — the NCNA people, the news
                    agency people. And it's a place that is obviously valuable to the Chinese, and
                    it's so valuable, as a matter of fact, that although one would think that in
                    this radical period particularly that Hong Kong would have been a target, even
                    then they left it alone.</p>
                <p>Now I think, however, that if the radicals had prevailed that they might have
                    —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean prevailed in Beijing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: In Beijing, yes. That's what I mean. If they had prevailed in Beijing
                    conceivably they would have gone for Hong Kong, I think they might well have.
                    But they didn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course they did in fact burn the British mission in
                        Beijing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: They burned the British mission, yes, and there were incidents like that
                    all over the world, as a matter of fact. But that was the radicals who did it.
                    Not only that, but they even took over the foreign ministry for a short time in
                    Beijing. So things were pretty haywire as far as China's foreign relations were
                    concerned. But of course they were also very preoccupied with their internal
                    affairs, which may be another reason that Hong Kong survived.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If we could go for just a minute beyond your experience in
                        Hong Kong down to the present, since obviously Hong Kong is still important
                        to the Chinese for the reasons you mentioned, this hasn't really changed,
                        why have they been so insistent on taking it over when presumably that will
                        degrade some of its utility?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes. Well, that's a good question. I would say that in—what was it, '86
                    they decided this?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '84.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: '84, okay. As long ago as that, time goes so fast. Probably the main
                    reason was that they were sort of on the spot. The 99-year lease which they made
                    for the New Territories in 1898 expires in 1997. And there was a lot of
                    speculation, has been for some years, what are they going to do then. It was a
                    kind of deadline that they had to face. And they would have had to have some
                    kind of excuse if they hadn't done anything about it. So I think perhaps that
                    was the thing that triggered that.</p>
                <p>Another reason is that comparatively, I think, Hong Kong is probably not as
                    important on the economic side — it's still important but not as important as it
                    was in the earlier years. They've developed their trade much more elsewhere and
                    so Hong Kong doesn't have quite the relativeimportance. And the same thing goes
                    for the window on the world function of Hong Kong. They've gotten into the U.N.,
                    they've expanded trade. They've expanded their diplomatic relations. And so it
                    just isn't that important. Whether or not the Taiwan situation had anything to
                    do with it I'm not sure, but of course Hong Kong is a piece of Chinese
                    territory, just as Taiwan is, and if they hadn't done anything about Hong Kong,
                    one wonders if they could have pressed the Taiwan issue as much.</p>
                <p>The other side of that is that they say they're going to treat Hong Kong in a way
                    that will show the people of Taiwan that they have nothing to fear. So—and I
                    must say, I think this is pertinent, during my time in Hong Kong I asked,
                    especially toward the end — I left there in 1970 — some of my British friends in
                    the government about the future and what would happen. The Chinese presumably
                    would take it over eventually or want to take it over. And I was told that the
                    British at that time would have been glad to negotiate for the turnover but the
                    Chinese were not interested. The Chinese simply were not interested.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If I could go back to Hong Kong as a listening or watching
                        post with respect to the Mainland, you witnessed the hectic days of the
                        Cultural Revolution, what would you say was the major turning point, as you
                        saw it there in Hong Kong. For example, the rise and fall of the Red Guard
                        movement. Were you able to chart that with some accuracy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, pretty well. I really can't remember very many specifics. The things
                    that stand out in my mind are that we felt that the Cultural Revolution more or
                    less came to an end in '69 with the Ninth Party Congress in April of '69 and Lin
                    Piao's ascendancy, and that the army really was then pretty much in control. And
                    we wrote in this—in fact I think this was fairly widespread—that after '69
                    people talked about the Post-Cultural Revolution activities and so forth. And so
                    it came as a surprise to me, and maybe to other people, when the Chinese began
                    talking about the Cultural Revolution ending in '76. So to go back to '69, I
                    would say that it really seemed to us to be a turning point internally with the
                    army really assuming a very large role and Lin Piao being proclaimed the heir
                    apparent.</p>
                <p>And then another turning point in a sense, although it was sort of a culmination,
                    was the 1969 Ussuri River Sino-Soviet clashes. That really triggered almost a
                    panicky reaction in Chinese media. And I think that as far as the PRC was
                    concerned they really began to feel frightened about the possibility of a war
                    with the Soviet Union. So I would say that the spring of '69 was a real turning
                    point. It was from then on that in Hong Kong we began to see minor signs of the
                    Chinese being interested in getting into some sort of contact with us. It was at
                    a low level, nothing at my level, but several of our China experts on our staff
                    were invited to parties where the NCNA people would be and so forth. It was all
                    very low level, but nevertheless you could see that the Chinese in Beijing were
                    reacting to the perceived threat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember having a friendly argument with your successor
                        in Hong Kong in his office a couple of years later. He was quite convinced
                        that the Chinese opening to the United States, whatever one chooses to call
                        it, was motivated overwhelmingly by a desire to get concessions in Taiwan. I
                        said, all well and good, but they've got the Soviet problem, which I think
                        is primary.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: I think the Soviet problem was primary. I also think that by 1970 the
                    Chinese were observing our interest in getting out of Vietnam. And this also
                    provided somewhat of an opening. And just to give a footnote to this, following
                    my assignment as Consul General in Hong Kong, I went to the Claremont colleges,
                    specifically to Claremont Graduate Center, in Claremont, California, as a
                    diplomat in residence and visiting professor. And of course this academic scene
                    you know a lot better than I, but in the early '70s, in the spring of '70 it had
                    been pretty bad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cambodia.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, by that fall things had calmed down a lot but I went to a faculty
                    meeting—it wasn't a faculty meeting, it was a meeting of some members of the
                    faculty who apparently had been meeting and were very upset about the Vietnam
                    situation. And they were carrying on about it as though nothing had really
                    changed. And I said, well, I just came from Hong Kong. And for the last three or
                    four years we've had between 350 and 400 U.S. naval vessels a year in Hong Kong
                    harbor — I mean visiting Hong Kong—and we've had a great deal of R &amp; R and
                    so forth. And I can assure you that the Vietnamization is going on and the
                    statement of the Administration that they wanted to pull out of Vietnam is the
                    policy. Those at the meeting were saying, oh, that's baloney. I said, it's not
                    baloney, it's true. This is happening and I've seen the concrete evidence of it
                    in the last few months that I was in Hong Kong. So the Chinese are not dumb,
                    they could see it, too. So I think that was a factor. Now I really don't think
                    Taiwan had anything to do with it, at least very little. It was primarily—after
                    all, you know better than I, just as well anyway, that during the Cultural
                    Revolution how isolated the Chinese were. There was one point where they only
                    had one ambassador in a foreign post, and that was Huang Hua in Egypt. In this
                    situation the realistic and hard-headed people in the Chinese government (and
                    they still continued to be there despite the radicals), especially with the
                    Ussuri River clashes, obviously have to look around for some way to break
                    China's isolation.</p>
                <p>So I think those are the factors, and that was our judgment there, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it your feeling that Zhou En-lai genuinely wanted some
                        sort of relationship with the United States really for its own sake, but
                        number one perhaps used the Soviet threat, which of course was real, as a
                        way of levering his colleagues into it and perhaps the colleagues like Mao
                        were more resistant? Or did you have any way of forming impressions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: It's hard to know what the internal situation was there. I don't know
                    whether we speculated on that. What we did do was act on the belief that the
                    Chinese would be more receptive. Of course the Nixon administration when it came
                    in immediately said we must do something to try to get China more involved in
                    the world. We certainly weren't ready for anything like recognition, but we were
                    willing to take small steps. And we in Hong Kong as early as the summer of '69
                    began to recommend, and into '70, recommend the kinds of steps that actually
                    were taken, such as allowing tourists to buy Chinese-origin goods in Hong Kong,
                    which had always been a real headache for us. And eventually allowing
                    American-subsidiary companies to trade with China. That had been a very
                    difficult thing, of course. And easing up on travel restrictions. I'm not saying
                    that we were the ones that recommended them and the government acted on it,
                    that's not true. Because they were also thinking the same things in Washington.
                    And as you know, there were a whole series of small steps that occurred in the
                    latter part of '69 and early '70 of the kind that I mentioned which preceded the
                    famous invitation to the American ping-pong team.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>I'm sorry, I really didn't answer your question because I don't know what the
                    internal situation was there and I don't remember that we speculated on that
                    much. We just saw what was happening.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think the point you just made is very important and
                        interesting, more so than the one I was talking about earlier, because there
                        still seems to be an impression in American China-watching circles, I mean
                        academic China-watching circles, that the opening really came wholly from
                        the Chinese side. Which is obviously not true.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, if they just look at the record there and see the things that we
                    did. And another sort of footnote, in August of '69 the new Secretary of State,
                    Bill Rogers, came out with Marshall Green and a small entourage, Mrs. Rogers, to
                    visit Hong Kong among other places. And we had a very good session at my house
                    after we gave them a dinner one night, about what things were happening, things
                    that were changing, our relation with China, what we could do. And we had a
                    discussion, he was very open about it, and so were we, and Marshall, and we all
                    agreed. So these kinds of steps that we took were concrete steps. And the
                    Chinese could read them as such and did.</p>
                <p>It's funny. I don't know what it is, academia or the press, but they picked up
                    the Chinese invitation and they sort of ignored the steps that we'd taken. I
                    really think that we took the initiative. But on the grounds that we thought the
                    Chinese would be receptive, whereas in the '60s the Chinese really weren't
                    very—not that we did very much, but in the Warsaw talks we offered things like
                    exchange of correspondents and easing up on travel restrictions. At one point we
                    offered pharmaceutical supplies and grain and so forth. This was all turned down
                    by the Chinese because in the '60s they were in no shape to do anything like
                    this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In May of 1970 the Chinese interrupted the Warsaw talks
                        that had just resumed earlier that year, with a great blast over Cambodia,
                        I'm sure you remember that. Was it the feeling of yourself and your staff at
                        that time that this was a very serious and possible termination of the
                        process, or did you expect it to be resumed later, or did you have any sense
                        of it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, I don't think I did. And there again I must say that the Warsaw
                    talks were something that we were not, and I think this was a mistake, but we in
                    Hong Kong were not kept informed about them at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>MARTIN: No, we were not, which I think was too bad. We should have been. But in
                    any case, the Cambodia thing I don't remember much about except in a kind of
                    personal way. In the spring of '70, I don't know, maybe March or so, I was
                    invited by Art Hummel, who was then ambassador in Burma, to come over to Rangoon
                    and to brief, or to talk to, some of the Burmese officials about how we saw the
                    situation in China. Because the Burmese, as you know, are very nonaligned
                    nonaligned people and we didn't ever get very close to them on an official
                    basis. They kept us at arms length. But he thought, well, if I have a visiting
                    fireman come in it might provide an opening to get across our point of view.
                    Well, as a result of his invitation, the department asked several other
                    embassies if they wanted me to visit. Besides Burma, I went to Malaysia, to
                    Singapore and on to Djakarta.</p>
                <p>And the Chinese press picked this up when I got back and accused me of being the
                    guy that was responsible for this Cambodian business. And I didn't know a damn
                    thing about it, I hadn't gone near Cambodia or anything. But it was just one of
                    these—they picked up the fact that I visited these countries, although there was
                    no publicity about it. Obviously they were able to do that without much trouble.
                    And they said I was a conspirator responsible for Sihanouk's ouster—was that
                    what it was?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right. That started it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: I had somehow engineered this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It sounds as though your trip to Burma in early '70 might
                        have had something to do with your appointment as Ambassador the following
                        year.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well it might have. But of course I had served there before, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, that's right. Of course. Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: I'd been there before. But I think that was just because I had—you know,
                    as Consul General in Hong Kong, it was a much more demanding and important job
                    than Ambassador to Burma. And it was considered by the department a Chief of
                    Mission assignment. It's only because Hong Kong is not an independent country
                    that you have to be a Consul General there, but in terms of the department, you
                    get all the perks of a Chief of Mission, such as flying first class and all that
                    stuff. Of course all consulates general, practically, have to report to an
                    embassy. In other words, they're under the supervision of their embassies, but
                    in Hong Kong you are as independent as any mission, you report directly to
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To the bureau. Did you report to London?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: No, never reported to London. Had nothing to do with London. Unless it
                    was something to do with British policy. But otherwise we had no more connection
                    with London than we had with Manila or Paris or any other place. It was a
                    totally independent post. And much larger than most embassies at that time. I
                    had 400 people on my staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is big.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, another thing. It wasn't just, of course China-watching. That was
                    important and I was the last Consul General there before we had some sort of an
                    office in China. But in '68 or '69, we became the second largest immigration
                    visa-issuing office in the world, because the U.S. had changed immigration laws
                    so that more Asians could immigrate. So we had a huge visa staff. And while I
                    was there, they established an American Chamber of Commerce for the first time
                    in Hong Kong's history. I was the first honorary president. And for the first
                    time our two-way trade with Hong Kong went over $1 billion U.S., so there was a
                    big trade expansion, big—as I was saying, I myself didn't have much opportunity
                    to do much China-watching. I was engaged in dealing with all these visiting
                    firemen from businesses, from the military, Seventh Fleet ships in there all the
                    time, and we had an awful lot of congressmen, many more than usual because the
                    Vietnam war was still going on. And Congressmen would go down there and they'd
                    come up to Hong Kong to get a breather or to do shopping before they went back
                    to the States. So I really had a seven-day-a-week job on that kind of thing. I
                    had some good people on my staff. Allen Whiting was the deputy my first year and
                    then Harald Jacobson took over. And they were both very good on
                    China-watching.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is there anything else you think we should cover from your
                        Hong Kong days?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: No, I can't think of anything in particular. I might say just as a
                    footnote that among the visiting firemen I had and entertained were Ronald and
                    Nancy Reagan and their two children. He was then governor of California. And
                    California having the largest Chinese population of any state, he had a special
                    interest in Hong Kong. He was on his way to Manila as a representative of
                    President Nixon to be present at the inauguration of President, I guess it was
                    Marcos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: President Marcos, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Marcos at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Shall we move on to Burma?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, sure. But before we do, I would like to say a word about an
                    important aspect of the work of our Consulate General in Hong Kong that I have
                    neglected to mention: its publications. It published a daily survey in English
                    of the China mainland press, and, less frequently, a translation of important
                    Chinese documents called Current Background. These publications were not only
                    widely used by China-watchers in the U.S. government but by many private
                    individuals, especially academics, both in the United States and in other
                    countries. Monthly publications in English and Chinese were also put out without
                    attribution to the Consulate General. Its Chinese publication was said to have
                    the largest circulation of any Chinese language magazine in the world outside of
                    China itself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Burma must have been kind of a rest after Hong Kong.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes, well I had that year in between as diplomat in residence. And that
                    was an interesting year. I did some lecturing for the Council on Foreign
                    Relations at various West Coast foreign affairs groups. That was a fairly good
                    rest for a year.</p>
                <p>I remember being at a conference in the spring of '71 and talking about how you
                    could see the relaxation and the easing of relations between the PRC and the
                    United States beginning to take place. One of the professors at the conference
                    was absolutely incredulous. He pointed to all the wicked things that the Nixon
                    administration was doing and said, how do you expect the Chinese government to
                    improve relations with such a reactionary administration? His question showed
                    how some people don't realize that the Chinese Communist leadership is pretty
                    hard-headed when it comes to what they think is in their interest. They're not
                    swayed by some things that people think they're swayed by.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Henry Kissinger has called Mao Zedong the most realistic
                        statesman he ever encountered except de Gaulle.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Sure. Well, I think Zhou En-lai was, but I don't know whether de Gaulle
                    was or not. But they are. They are capable. It's amazing how people can be
                    ignorant of this fact, and that they are willing to deal with anybody if they
                    think it is in China's interest no matter how ideologically opposed they may
                    be.</p>
                <p>Okay, I can't think of any more Hong Kong at the moment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, about Burma. Something in general perhaps to begin
                        with?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>MARTIN: Well. Burma was interesting. Of course I had been there before and it was
                    now a rather sad place to be because Ne Win had been a virtual dictator since
                    1962, and I went there in '71. And a lot of people we had known in the early
                    '50s when we were there had been thrown in jail. I thought in the early '50s
                    Burma was in the hands of rather naive people and people certainly who were
                    socialists, but nevertheless people who were generally convinced of the
                    importance of democracy. And they were people who were willing to treat the
                    minorities, who make up about 28% of the Burmese population, with a certain
                    amount of respect. The president was a Shan and the foreign minister was a Shan.
                    When I went back in '71, I learned that a lot of these people had been thrown in
                    jail. Most of them were out but still they'd been cowed. Minorities were not
                    treated with the same respect. And the Burmese military junta which had taken
                    power in '62 under Ne Win had invented a kind of Burmese version of socialism,
                    actually they called it the Burmese Way to Socialism. And it was kind of a
                    mixture of Marxism- Leninism, Burmese nationalism and Buddhism. There were some
                    nice people in the government but they really were not very competent. Ne Win
                    himself so cowed everybody that the government was more or less at a standstill,
                    and still is.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He's recently admitted that he made some mistakes, which I
                        think is encouraging.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Oh, has he? I didn't know that. He certainly has. But of course it was an
                    interesting place it wasn't particularly interesting for China-watching, but I
                    was there at the time when Nixon went over to China and that was a big
                    breakthrough. So instead of ignoring each other at social events, the Chinese
                    ambassador and I exchanged pleasantries. We never really got well-
                    acquainted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wonder whether since to Burma China is by far the most
                        important external problem and since you were reasonably fresh from Hong
                        Kong and an experienced China watcher, whether they showed any interest in
                        learning from you about this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: No, none whatsoever, or from anybody else as far as I could see. Ne Win
                    had no interest in that. And furthermore the Burmese—of course they had kind of
                    a special relationship with China. They had the longest border with China of any
                    country in Southeast Asia. They were the first non-Communist country to
                    recognize the PRC. So they had maintained diplomatic relations and they had
                    visitors back and forth. China had an aid program there.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>But on the other hand the Chinese, as in other Southeast Asian countries, had
                    backed an insurgency, the White Flag Communists, the BCP. And so on the one
                    hand, the Burmese felt they needed to get along with the Chinese the best they
                    could. On the other hand, they were very unhappy about the fact the Chinese were
                    supporting insurgency there. And the best they could do with that was to try to
                    fight the insurgency. But they were too timid, I guess, in a way, and maybe
                    understandably so, to really do anything about it in a diplomatic sense or to
                    get any support from us.</p>
                <p>Now I will tell you something which perhaps will surprise you. I really only saw
                    Ne Win a few times. I saw him when I presented credentials, I saw him when we
                    had some visiting firemen on narcotics business and at big receptions, but he
                    made a practice of not seeing foreign diplomats, very deliberately, on a private
                    basis. When I made my farewell call on him he indicated that he was concerned
                    that the United States—he never put this on the public record—continue to
                    maintain an interest in Southeast Asia. He obviously realized that for a country
                    like Burma to pursue its neutralist, nonaligned policy you have to have a
                    balance of power. And he made it pretty plain he was concerned lest the United
                    States reduce its power in the area. Again what he says in public and what he
                    says in private are two different things. I think anyone who runs a small
                    country with a border with a powerful country like China is going to have that
                    concern. And the Burmese actually in various nonaligned conferences, I must say,
                    have been among the purest in their adherence to nonalignment. I don't know
                    whether, I haven't followed any recently, have they had nonaligned conferences?
                    You don't seem to read about them so much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They have them, but the Burmese have withdrawn from the
                        movement.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: They have withdrawn?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After the '69 meeting in Havana, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At various times in the history of U.S. relations with Burma, the so-called KMT
                    irregulars have been a big problem. Was that also true during your tenure?</p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes. Well, it was during my first tour in Burma.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Primarily the first tour, not the second?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>MARTIN: The second tour, no. They were of concern mainly to the people who were
                    fighting the drug problem, the narcotic problem. And as a matter of fact the
                    priority during my mission there was to try to get the Burmese government to
                    cooperate in fighting drugs. And I won't go into all that, I've got that on
                    another tape. But I think we were quite successful at the time. It took a long
                    time, a good deal of persuasion to get the Burmese to cooperate on the narcotics
                    problem. One of the keys to this success was something that we had nothing to do
                    with, and that was that, especially after the U.S. pulled out of Vietnam, they
                    began to have trouble with the drug dealers selling their heroin to some of the
                    what in Burma passes for middle class young people. And so when the Burmese
                    authorities began to see that some of their own people outside of the hill
                    tribes (they didn't give a darn about them) were being menaced, then they began
                    to get very much interested in the drug problem. But the remnants of the KMT
                    troops in Burma, some of them anyway, were very much involved in this drug
                    smuggling business. As a matter of fact, a number of the other insurgents groups
                    there were also involved because this was one way they could finance
                    themselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever see any evidence of the PRC's involvement in
                        the narcotics trade? Any direction?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: No. But I would qualify that to the extent that there was evidence, I
                    think, that the BCP was involved, as other insurgent groups were. Opium was
                    grown in areas along the China border that they controlled. And opium was coming
                    out of those areas. At that time, and when I left Burma, the BCP was being
                    trained by the Chinese across the border. And there were reports that there were
                    actually Chinese cadres with the BCP on the Burma side. So it's possible that
                    the Communists were involved, but we didn't have any evidence beyond what I've
                    told you.</p>
                <p>I might say, give you one sort of anecdote because of your interest in
                    Sino-Soviet relations. I can't remember the name of my Soviet colleague,
                    unfortunately. You probably wouldn't have heard of him, I'd never heard of him.
                    But he had been stationed in China, in Peking, during the Cultural Revolution.
                    So he had gone through a good deal; there were anti-Soviet demonstrations, too,
                    as you'll recall, in Peking. And he knew who I was, which was not surprising. I
                    made my initial call on him. The new ambassador makes the calls first. Before my
                    call we had just gotten word about Lin Piao's disappearance, and I thought he
                    was being purged. I mentioned this to the Soviet ambassador, and he was
                    absolutely incredulous because at the time he was in China Lin Piao was the
                    bigshot, the heir, and all the rest of it. He didn't think Lin Piao could
                    possibly have been arrested. When he returned my call some weeks later he said,
                    “You were right about Lin Piao”. That was interesting to me, that we knew
                    something of such importance he didn't know. At our diplomatic corps dinners
                    which we had to say farewell to a colleague, I would carry on some conversation
                    with the Chinese ambassador in Chinese. He couldn't speak any English, or very
                    little, And the Russian ambassador couldn't speak any Chinese, so on a very
                    superficial level I acted as interpreter. [laughter].</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Trying to establish an American triangle?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good. Well thank you very much. That ends this
                        session. Thank you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a continuation of our interview. I'm Charles
                        Stuart Kennedy, the director of the Foreign Service History Center, and
                        Ambassador Martin and I were talking at lunch. It's still the 17th of March.
                        And we thought there might be one other question or series of short
                        questions, we might put. And that's concerning the Kennedy years and our
                        attitude towards China.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador Martin, what job did you have during the Kennedy years, dealing with
                    China?</p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, when Kennedy was inaugurated in January of '61 I was, and had been
                    for several years, director of the Office of Chinese Affairs. And there was some
                    expectation that with the new party coming in, the Democrats, and with JFK of
                    course the youngest president and so forth, there would be new things happening.
                    And of course there were new things that happened in his administration. But in
                    the China posture of the United States, not as much changed as some people
                    thought might change. The innovation which occurred during my few months as
                    director of the Chinese Affairs during the Kennedy administration—.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the dates, about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Well, as I say, Kennedy came in on January 20.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '61.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>MARTIN: We're talking about '61. And I was the director until that summer. That
                    summer I went to become political advisor to CINCPAC [Commander in Chief,
                    Pacific]. Well, the innovation I was talking about was apparently Bowles',
                    Chester Bowles' idea. Bowles had been appointed by Kennedy as the Under
                    Secretary of State. And the Secretary, of course, was Dean Rusk. And the idea
                    came down, I think, from Bowles' office that we should now recognize the
                    People's Republic of Mongolia and this initiative did not come from the Office
                    of Chinese Affairs, the Far East Bureau, which actually opposed it although not
                    very strongly. And I think the reason for opposing it was that we didn't think
                    there was really much to be gained by it and it would simply succeed in
                    antagonizing the Nationalists.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Nationalist Chinese?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: The Chinese, yes, with whom we had diplomatic relations of course. In any
                    case, it got to the point where I was instructed to go down to the Hill and
                    brief Chairman Morgan, Chairman of the House Foreign Affairs Committee, which I
                    did. And as I recall, Dr. Morgan was not particularly disturbed by this, didn't
                    think there would be any real problem on the Hill with it. And then I was
                    transferred out of Chinese affairs and later on I gathered that this whole idea
                    was squashed, presumably in the White House, and that it was not one that had
                    White House backing. Apparently it had been Chester Bowles' pet project. I think
                    one thing that did come out of it was the admission of Mongolia into the U.N. We
                    obviously did not veto it. As I was saying to you at lunch, one casualty of this
                    whole episode was that George Yeh, who was the Chinese ambassador to the United
                    States at the time, was fired by Chiang Kai-shek apparently because Chiang was
                    unhappy that Mongolia had been admitted to the U.N. But this happened after I
                    left.</p>
                <p>But also, I'm sure that this was just one illustration of the way Bowles was
                    reputed to operate, which was rather independently. I'm not exactly sure but I
                    think he lasted less than a year as Under Secretary of State. And I think this
                    was perhaps an example of the kind of thing that he initiated that he had
                    obviously not cleared with his bosses.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Chester Bowles is described as what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: As a—and I don't know who said it, but it's one that sticks in my mind
                    because I thought it was an apt description, as a giant flywheel that went round
                    and round without any real connection with the rest of the departmental
                    machinery.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One further question on this. Rusk has been reputed to
                        have been very much an Asia-centric person. He looked towards Asia and left
                        Europe in the hands of George Ball for the most part. But did Rusk make any
                        noises that you know of about recognizing Communist China?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>MARTIN: No. I don't think he did. And the business—I'm not sure, I didn't operate
                    very much at the Rusk level as an office director, but I don't think there was
                    any real pressure. I think there might have been a public expectation, which
                    obviously wasn't very well founded, that Kennedy would do things differently.
                    And even as late as the year after he'd been in office, people were surprised
                    that our ambassador, who had been appointed by the Eisenhower administration,
                    Everett Drumright.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As ambassador to Taiwan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: Our ambassador in Taiwan, our ambassador to the Republic of China, was
                    still there. And again I can't give any inside information because I don't know.
                    I wasn't privy to any. But the speculation was that the Kennedy administration
                    had other fish to fry and did not want to move on the China thing in any
                    decisive way or any radical way because they didn't want to upset the applecart
                    or they had other things that they gave greater priority to.</p>
                <p>And, as a matter of fact, of course during the Kennedy administration while the
                    Warsaw talks continued and there was a certain amount of flexibility there on
                    our part, nevertheless they didn't get anywhere. And that was mainly due to the
                    fact that in the '60s, first with the “Great Leap Forward” and then after an
                    interim period, with the Cultural Revolution, the People's Republic of China was
                    in a very radical period. And it was not a period in which they would have been
                    very receptive to any moves. So I feel that whereas certainly from the mid-'50s
                    on the United States had a—well, from the Korean War on, from '51 on, the United
                    States had a pretty rigid position on China, in the '60s we had a more flexible
                    position (we could have been more flexible), but the Chinese simply were not in
                    a position to respond and didn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have, being in charge of Chinese affairs, did you
                        have tucked in your lower file cabinet drawer a plan for recognizing China
                        in case somebody called upon you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MARTIN: No, no we didn't. I don't think it ever came close.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just as a professional foreign service officer, you didn't
                        even think this was worth making a contingency plan?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>MARTIN: No, I don't think so. Now there might have been more thinking along the
                    line, and I think that would have been a more appropriate place in some ways, in
                    the Policy Planning Staff. They were supposed to be thinking about long-range
                    plans and so forth. We were all bogged down, as many desks were, with handling
                    day-to-day things and reporting and briefing. Certainly we didn't see anything
                    like recognition close enough to make any plans. As I said earlier on this tape,
                    it wasn't until after the '69 Sino-Soviet clashes and what looked to us then as
                    sort of the end of the Cultural Revolution and various other developments that
                    we thought now is the time when we can start changing our relations with China,
                    and the Nixon administration of course coming in January of '69, said right off
                    the bat that they felt our relations with China should be adjusted. As I said
                    earlier, the Chinese weren't in any mood for change with the Cultural Revolution
                    and so forth, and the United States after all, from '64 on was more and more
                    deeply involved in Vietnam and the Vietnam war and the Chinese were backing the
                    North Vietnamese. So again our preoccupation was with Vietnam. China was on the
                    other side. We were certainly not, I was not in the Office of Chinese Affairs at
                    this time, I might add, but just looking at it from this perspective, you might
                    say that in the '60s neither the United States nor China were in a posture where
                    recognition was going to be seriously considered. It just wasn't in the works,
                    that's all.</p>
                <p>I might say one other thing while we're on this tape that is of interest, again
                    as sort of a footnote. One of the things that I did in May of 1961 when I was
                    still director was to make an around-the-world trip with Lyndon Johnson and his
                    wife and several other people. He was then vice president. And I was told off to
                    go and brief Johnson about the trip. As a matter of fact, we weren't sure it was
                    going to be an around-the-world trip when we started out. It was supposed to be
                    just a trip to the Far East mainly. But I recall particularly his reaction when
                    I said we were going to Taipei. And he really balked at that suggestion. Now the
                    Democrats were just back in office after being out of office for two terms, for
                    eight years. And Johnson obviously remembered the very controversial China
                    policy and so forth, in that he thought that going to visit Chiang Kai-shek was
                    not going to be very good for his political career. And he really balked at this
                    idea. And I tried to explain why under the circumstances—he was going to visit a
                    number of countries—that he ought to go to Taiwan. And he interrupted me and
                    said, “You know, Ed, I want to tell you a story about the man in Texas who had a
                    drinking problem. And he also had a hearing problem. And he went to his doctor
                    about the hearing problem and the doctor said, 'how much do you drink, Joe?' And
                    Joe said, 'I drink about a pint a day.' And the doctor said, 'You better cut
                    that out if you want your hearing to improve.' So about a month later the doctor
                    encountered Joe on the street and he was reeling a bit. And he said, 'Joe,
                    didn't I tell you to cut that drinking out?' And Joe said, 'What did you say?'
                    He said, 'Didn't I tell you to cut that drinking out or it was going to affect
                    your hearing?' And Joe said, 'Oh, yeah, well I did that for a while, Doc, but I
                    found that I like what I drink better than I like what I hear'.” So that's how
                    Johnson felt about going to Taiwan. But we finally persuaded him to go. And he,
                    as he was in other places, was more interested—the thing he was interested in
                    most as soon as we got to a place was what the joint communique was going to be
                    like. But he did meet with Chiang and we had a dinner party at Chiang's
                    residence.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>It was interesting to me in a way because I don't think Lyndon Johnson—of course
                    he was a Roosevelt prot�g� in a sense, I suppose, but I never thought of him
                    being particularly a liberal Democrat, I guess he was, but that sort of
                    reaction, almost visceral reaction—I don't want to be associated with Chiang
                    Kai-shek—I thought was rather interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's interesting. Okay. Thank you. We'll close this once
                        again.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
