<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000296">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Thomas J. Dodd </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR THOMAS J. DODD</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 9, 2001</p>
                <p>Copyright 2003 ADST</p>
                <p>Q: Today is May 9, 2001. This is an interview with Thomas J. Dodd. This is being
                    done on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training, and I'm
                    Charles Stuart Kennedy. Tom, let's start at the beginning. Can you tell me when
                    and where you were born and something about your family.</p>
                <p>DODD: I was born on March 29th, 1935 in the District of Columbia. I'm a native
                    Washingtonian born at the old Georgetown Hospital. I'm a rare species.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me about your mother and your father.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: My parents, Grace Murphy Dodd was from Rhode Island, and my dad was a
                    Connecticut native. He was then working in Washington with the Department of
                    Justice. He was working in the area of civil rights. You couldn't call it the
                    civil rights division, but that was the area where he specialized and as a
                    matter of fact tried a couple of cases in Arkansas. One of them was the mayor of
                    Little Rock for lynching. My dad went out there and tried the case and won it
                    before a jury. Those were difficult days I'm sure. He tried several of those
                    cases around the country, lynchings and so forth, but that was his work in the
                    1930s when I was born in the District.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about the background of where your parents
                        familiecame from.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: My father's family was from Ireland, his grandfather, as well as my
                    mother's. My father's family settled in Norwich, Connecticut, and my mother's
                    family settled in Westerly, Rhode Island. My grandfather ultimately became the
                    wholesale paper business. My father's father was a contractor in Norwich. They
                    used to say in Norwich, “Who made the world? Tom Dodd and his horses.” My mother
                    was educated in Rhode Island but came to Washington and graduated from Trinity
                    College in 1928.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, obviously of a Catholic family.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>DODD: Yes. My father went to Providence College and Yale Law School and also, as
                    I say, joined the Department of Justice in the 1930s as one of Herbert Hoover's
                    earlier FBI agents.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So he was a part of the FBI?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, he was. He was probably one of the first agents, then waactive in the
                    pursuit of Ma Barker and John Dillinger and so forth.</p>
                <p>Q: I'm surprised in a way, knowing Herbert Hoover's proclivities, that we would
                    have we would have the equivalent to a civil rights unit there. He was pretty
                    much a small-town southerner from DC, wasn't he?</p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, as a matter of fact. Homer Cummings was the Attorney General from
                    Connecticut and actually brought my dad to Washington. That's how my father
                    ended up working for the Department of Justice in the 1930s in the Roosevelt
                    administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever get any stories about Hoover in the
                        family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: There are many stories about Herbert Hoover. He supervised his FBI agents
                    very closely. We learned early on that my dad was a rather independent agent.
                    While he liked the service, I'm not so sure he really loved the discipline that
                    went with it. But he certainly participated in some very significant work in
                    Wisconsin, Little Bohemia, the Battle of Little Bohemia. Where John Dillinger
                    was sought but not found. My parents then lived in St. Paul, Minnesota. Ma
                    Barker also lived in St. Paul! So those were interesting days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you mother have a job, or was she a housewife?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: No, I'll tell you an interesting story. She graduated from Trinity in 1929
                    and with a group of young women, three or four of them, went to New York and got
                    an apartment on the west side, and found work. She kept a newspaper headline
                    that said, “9,000,000 out of work” the day she was hired in an insurance
                    company. She always used to brag about it. But after she married my dad - they
                    raised six children - my mother worked at home. But she always maintained a
                    very, very active writing career, not necessarily as a published scholar, but
                    wrote articles for newspapers. When my dad later was in public life, in fact all
                    the years he was in public life, my mother wrote a column for Connecticut
                    newspapers from Washington. She was a painter, and led a very active, engaged,
                    busy life and not just simply trying to discipline a brood of six children.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel ties to Connecticut while you were in
                        Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes. In fact, I always have. My wife still chides me a bit about 'going
                    home' someday. I'm one of those people born in Washington but raised in
                    Connecticut. I came back to Washington in 1953 to school. But since then, even
                    though my parents lived in Connecticut and came to Washington, I always
                    considered myself really a “nutmegger,” a Yankee from Connecticut, and I still
                    do. I've always felt Washington is a very difficult place to say is home. It's
                    very hard. In fact, most of my friends that I know today are from somewhere else
                    and have always been from somewhere else living in the District. My wife, who is
                    a native Washingtonian, has lived there all her life and feels very much part of
                    the city.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For schooling where did you start school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I started to school, went to grammar school, in Lebanon, a small town in
                    Connecticut. There was a cluster of small towns called Lebanon, Basra, all had
                    Biblical names. This was in the 1940s, and I remember that most of my classmates
                    were DPs (displaced persons), children who had no parents, were refugees during
                    and after the Second World War. So I grew up conscious of the cultural
                    differences of people. But the most important thing was they were my friends. I
                    had a wonderful exposure at a very early age, exposed to a diverse world and
                    suffering people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the business of Lebanon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Lebanon historically was George Washington's New England war office. It was
                    a lovely old town, about 800 to 1,000 people. I mentioned George Washington's
                    war office. He lived in a home that was right across the street from us. Our
                    home belonged to the son of Jonathan Trumble, the artist.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What brought your father back to Connecticut?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: To practice law. He practiced law actually in Hartford, which is about 32
                    miles from Lebanon, so it was considered a long commute then, with chickens,
                    pigs, and sheep. We were really city dwellers in a rural Connecticut town.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you recall any of the teachers?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>DODD: I recall them very well. In fact, maybe the older you get, the better you
                    remember. I recall two or three who were sons and daughters of Eastern European
                    refugees, which made for wonderful classes then in the fifth and sixth grade.
                    Geography, I always remember, was important. Again, I want to emphasize I wasn't
                    conscious of the fact that I had people from that part of the world as teachers,
                    but I look back now and I think how extraordinary because I knew so much about
                    the world when I entered high school. I think it was a direct result of the
                    influence of those teachers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about at home? You say you had five brothers...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Five brothers and sisters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you all sit around the table, and was this one of
                        these thingwhere you get together and discuss things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Looking back over the years - and I think my siblings would agree - we
                    spent most of our lives debating and arguing politics and world affairs that my
                    dad was interested in. He always either evoked or provoked debate and
                    discussion. We didn't talk about real estate or the stock market; we talked
                    about politics and world affairs, because in 1945...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You would have been 10 by that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: My dad went to the Nuremberg trial with Robert Jackson. That was a turning
                    point, I think, for me and my sister, Carolyn, and brother, Jeremy. We're close
                    in age; we were 10, nine... My dad would talk a great deal about the trial. He
                    made us very much aware of the horrors of the Second World War and the
                    Holocaust. Subsequently we used to meet many survivors of the Holocaust at home
                    in Lebanon. So it was a turning point for me, 1945 and '46, because my dad was
                    away at the trial, became then executive trial counsel when Justice Jackson
                    returned home. My dad was, of course, away for about a year and half. His
                    letters to my mother and her to him, daily letters, have been preserved. We've
                    edited and published them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good, because that's something you don't want...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: It's a great treasure, because in those letters we've come across some
                    extraordinarily interesting things, notes written between several of the
                    defendants at the trial to each other. Those letters are now at the University
                    of Connecticut along with my dad's Nuremberg papers. That period was an
                    interesting turning point for me. I became more curious and interested in world
                    affairs, international affairs.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did the family, from the time you were aware of it,
                        wherdid it fall politically?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: My parents were Roosevelt and Truman Democrats. I always remember in 1948
                    my dad seconded Harry Truman's nomination in Philadelphia at the Democratic
                    Party Convention. They couldn't find a Democrat in New England to do it. My dad
                    remembers seconding his nomination about two a.m. in the morning. I heard it on
                    the radio. Of course, most of the country had gone to bed when Truman gave his
                    acceptance speech. My dad said that night when he delivered the speech, he
                    electrified the delegates. My father was walking out after his speech and Truman
                    said to him, “You know, I'm going to win this,” and my dad said, “Well, I hope
                    you do,” but most people didn't think so. Then, of course, in the subsequent
                    campaign in '48 they both traveled the country. Again, we were Roosevelt and
                    Truman Democrats, a rare breed in Lebanon, Connecticut.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your father then ran for Congress?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: No. He was certainly interested in politics - there's no question about it
                    - in 1948, and there was a lot of discussion that he might run for governor in
                    that year, but he did not. He ran for the House of Representatives in 1952, and
                    that began his Congressional career in the House. Then he went to the Senate in
                    1958. He was in Congress until a year before he died in 1971.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He ran for Congress when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: He ran for Congress in 1952.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you would have been in high school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, I was in high school. I was a junior in high school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go to high school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I went to a wonderful old school, Cheshire Academy, founded in 1789. I say
                    a wonderful old school because it had a large number of students from abroad. In
                    fact, just next week I'm going to give the commencement address there
                    commemorating the arrival of the first foreign students in 1812. It continued my
                    interest in international affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Let me get my dates straight here. I was there from 1949 t'53.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I just went to my 55th reunion.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: A great old school. I'll always remember the headmaster there, who was a
                    remarkable human being. His name was Arthur N. Sheriff. He always made a point
                    of having students from abroad room with U.S. students. I had a Cuban roommate.
                    This was before the Cuban revolution. He was a wonderful guy. He spoke no
                    English and I spoke no Spanish. But over the months, we began to pick up our
                    separate languages. That was the start of my interest in Latin America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were at Cheshire what sort of things were you
                        interestein? Were there any particular areas that you became interested
                        in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, there were several of them, two areas: first, as I mentioned, the
                    Foreign Relations Club, which was interesting. But I also got very interest and
                    remained active in the theater, amateur acting. I used to do some summer stock
                    theater, too. Donald Towers was director of fine arts and theater. I also
                    enjoyed very much playing soccer and fencing, maybe because there were Spanish
                    speaking Latin Americans on the teams.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about reading? Were you a reader?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I was. Again you point to teachers. My history teacher was George HoughtoHe
                    was a great lecturer. Of course, it was European history, and I used to read
                    biographies. I loved biographies of European historical figures and remains so
                    to this day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With your father running for Congress, did you get
                        involved in thcampaign?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>DODD: I did get involved in the campaign. I actually did throughout his career.
                    Let me be specific. I would be given a schedule and speak in high schools around
                    the state. Often people said, “Well, there are no votes in high schools.” No,
                    but the point was really to get out and explain what an election was. There were
                    teachers, and, of course, parents who might have heard about my talks. But I do
                    remember several times debating with representatives of my dad's opponents in
                    high schools, some colleges. I went out on the road with a schedule and covered
                    different parts of the district then and the state later when he went to the
                    Senate. But I loved it, I thoroughly enjoyed it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any drawbacks, people who were emotionally
                        involved ithe other side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: There always were. But I must say in all honesty I don't ever remember in
                    all of the years doing any campaign for him ever running into any unpleasant
                    experiences. People, of course, disagreed with you and did so publicly and
                    openly. But it was very civil. I don't ever recall being embarrassed,
                    humiliated, or feeling especially uncomfortable discussing and arguing points in
                    politics. There were some contentious issues in that decade of the fifties,
                    McCarthyism, the Cold War, for example, but there was a climate of civility and
                    I liked it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned McCarthyism. How did that fall out, because
                        youfather, coming from the J. Edgar Hoover school...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I'll tell you a very interesting story. McCarthy was very, very critical of
                    Abe Ribicoff, who was then governor. I always remember my dad went on radio and
                    condemned McCarthy for criticizing Abe Ribicoff, condemned him frequently. So he
                    was an oddity in a way, being an Irish Catholic condemning the tactics of a
                    Catholic member of Congress. But my dad felt his actions were horrendous,
                    destructive. And I always had a great deal of respect for him, because it took
                    some courage. He was criticized for that, very, very harshly criticized for it.
                    That was one of several stands he took on things that I admired tremendously,
                    because he thought they were right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were at Cheshire, did you know what you wanted
                        to do,where you wanted to go to school?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>DODD: This is an interesting thing. When I was invited to go up to Cheshire
                    several months ago, the headmaster wrote me and said, “We've been spending a
                    year now commemorating some 150 years of foreign students here, and we've
                    invited several visitors from abroad. We'd like to have someone who graduated
                    from the school who's gone abroad and had some experience abroad, too.” And he
                    said, “By the way, your class picture says 'Professional interest and
                    occupation: To go into the U.S. Foreign Service.'" It was kind of interesting.
                    And so I'm going to pick up that theme.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Obviously you were not in an isolated community. You'd
                        lived in Washington; you'd had all this experience. So many people who get
                        this never heard of the Foreign Service until much later. Did you know about
                        not the Foreign Service so much but diplomacy and...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, I did. Let me explain, and I think I can be precise for you. When my
                    dad was at Nuremberg, he met two people that had a tremendous impact on him and
                    I got to know. One was a man named Edmond Walsh, formerly of Georgetown School
                    of Foreign Service. He did a lot of interviewing of several German political
                    scientists and a man named Leon Dostert, who set up the simultaneous translation
                    system at Nuremberg and later established the Institute for Language and
                    Linguistics at Georgetown, later the School of Linguistics. But through them we
                    met people who were in the Department of State who were at that trial in
                    different functions. I remember meeting a lot of them, and I thought their work
                    was fascinating. Of course, it was the end of the war and many Cold War issues
                    were emerging. These were people who spent a lot of time at our house and it
                    added to my interest and curiosity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your teachers at Cheshire sort of add onto this talk
                        abouthings that were happening?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Some did, yes. I always remember George Houghton, my history teacher. Yes,
                    many of them did. Arthur Sheriff, the headmaster, was always interested in
                    international affairs. We used to meet at his house on weekends, I remember. He
                    always seemed to create an environment where there was a lot of mixing of
                    students from abroad, from all over the world. That was a foundation, my dad's
                    interest and people he met and knew at Nuremberg at the end of the war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you know where you wanted to go to university?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>DODD: Yes, I knew exactly where I wanted to go, and that was to Georgetown's
                    Foreign Service School. I wanted to study languages, and I applied and
                    registered at the School of Languages and Linguistics, again the Institute of
                    Language and Linguistics, which was downtown here in Washington on Massachusetts
                    Avenue. When I arrived in Washington in the fall of 1953 to go to the Institute,
                    my parents were upset because the Institute and most of its students were
                    downtown. They were older, much older. So I switched to the School of Foreign
                    Service, which was on campus. Many were my contemporaries in age. I remember
                    Melissa Wells, who then joined the U.S. Foreign Service, was a student there.
                    She was a night student because women weren't admitted to day courses. But she
                    took day courses anyway. It was an older, more mature student body than college,
                    so I had a nice mix on campus: my classmates in the Foreign Services School were
                    more, as I said, mature, more professionally oriented - they wanted careers in
                    international service - and then my college associates and friends on the
                    campus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Father Walsh, was he quite a presence then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Father Walsh had suffered a stroke about a year before I entered, so he was
                    infirm and he was no longer running the school. But he lived on the campus and I
                    used to go visit him. But he was quite ill, referred often to the Nuremberg
                    trial, but he was really quite ill and died while I was at Georgetown. I believe
                    it was 1956, '55 or '56.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any teachers at the School of Foreign Service that
                        particularlgrabbed you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Oh, yes, there were some that were really well known. I suppose if you ask
                    any graduate of Georgetown's Foreign Service School since 1945, the name of
                    Carroll Quigley would come up; Jan Karski, who headed up the Polish underground
                    in the Second World War and first reported the Holocaust.</p>
                <p>Q: President Clinton...</p>
                <p>DODD: Clinton referred to him on several occasions. Jules Davids, who helped John
                    Kennedy write Profiles in Courage, taught United States diplomacy. Carroll
                    Quigley taught world civilization. It was called Development of Civilization -
                    really the development of Western civilization actually. I don't remember him so
                    much for the content of his course, but he taught us how to think and how to
                    think historically, which led me to the study of history, the discipline of it,
                    the approach to it, the schools of historical thought, methodology. I remember
                    those things. He was quite an orator and a dominant force in the classroom. You
                    didn't disagree with him very often or easily.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the student body at the School of Foreign Service
                        dividitself off from the government, the business group, in different
                        ways?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: No, as I recall, we were all of a caste. We all took basically the same
                    course work. It was very rigid all the way through and there were very few
                    electives. I remember I went to Spain to school, to the University of Barcelona
                    and the University of Santandare for a period. I'll always remember I didn't get
                    permission to take any courses over there for credit. I wrote the regent, Frank
                    Fadner, said, “I'd like to get some credit.” He wrote back and said, “Thank you
                    for your run-on sentence paragraph,” and so on and corrected my English and
                    said, “I'll give you credit for some languages.” I'm told by the registrar and
                    the dean of the Foreign Service School that I may have been one of the first
                    Georgetown students to get credit for studying abroad. To answer your question,
                    basically we were all required to take foreign language and be competent in it -
                    that is, for writing and speaking. Some students were interested, yes, in
                    international trade, but those weren't really majors or concentrations when I
                    was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why Spanish?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: That goes back to Cheshire, my prep school, my roommate, a Cuban,
                    introduced me to Venezuelans, Mexicans, and Peruvians, and the list goes on and
                    on. So I learned Spanish, pursued it, then Portuguese. When I went to Georgetown
                    I'll always remember my prep school roommate said, “Be very careful of Puerto
                    Ricans. They're dangerous people. They steal and so forth.” So I asked roommate
                    from Spain. I remember one day the door to my room opened shortly after I
                    arrived and in walked a blond, blue-eyed fellow. I said, “Oh, I'm glad your
                    Spanish and not Puerto Rican.” “Well,” he said, “I am Puerto Rican.” That was my
                    second lesson in diversity of the Hispanic world. We became great friends and I
                    met many people from the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico and other Latin American
                    students. So my interests in Latin America really did not follow a discipline,
                    history, language, or culture. It was friends. The first course I took as an
                    undergraduate with the InterAmerican System offered by William Manger, the
                    former Assistant Secretary General of the OAS.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were at Georgetown from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I was there from '53 to '57.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were Eisenhower years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: These were the Eisenhower years, exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How Catholic a school was it? Today, as we both know,
                        it's....</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Georgetown was a Jesuit college - the School of Language and Linguistics,
                    the Foreign Service School, the College of Arts and Sciences. It was a Jesuit
                    university, no question about it. If you were in the Foreign Service School and
                    lived off campus, students lived relatively independent lives, that is, no
                    restrictions on attending mass and so on. But if you were on the campus, you
                    wore a coat and tie. You sat in a dining room for a breakfast, lunch and dinner
                    that was served. Maids cleaned your room and made your beds. It was a young
                    gentlemen's hilltop institution. But my experience in the Foreign Service
                    School, I think, was more maturing, because the Foreign Service School did have
                    students of other faiths, several students from abroad, so it was broadening for
                    me. A Jesuit university like Georgetown was truly one of the first international
                    institutions of higher learning in the U.S.</p>
                <p>Q: I was born in 1928. I'm not a Catholic, but I grew up with the feeling of the
                    dominant force in the United States in the Catholic world being Irish Catholic
                    and it was sort of anti-intellectual and a lot of rules: you eat fish on Friday,
                    you don't go to this movie, you don't go to that. For a young kid it seemed
                    pretty intolerant.</p>
                <p>DODD: It was not easy. I come back to my response to one of your earlier
                    questions. Both of my parents, grandparents and my great grandparents lived in
                    small New England towns - Westerly, Rhode Island, was a small community;
                    Norwich, Connecticut was a small community. Their friends and relatives lived in
                    farms. So most of their contacts and mine growing up were with non-Catholics.
                    When I went to Georgetown, my interest generally tilted towards my colleagues in
                    the Foreign Service School because there was more of a diverse community. But
                    again I emphasize it was an experience I remember vividly that living on that
                    campus with college students from the more traditional Irish Catholic was also a
                    great window of interest for me. I didn't know them before. They were called
                    lace-curtain Irish. They went to Canterbury and Portsmouth Priory. There was an
                    elitism there. They didn't graduate from local parochial high schools. That was
                    kind of a shock for me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your father by this time when you were in there, was he
                        already iCongress?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, he was in Congress.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you find yourself getting involved, or were you disagreeing with your
                    parents as most kids do?</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>DODD: I used to go down to the Hill a lot and listen to sessions of Congress. I
                    enjoyed it, and I used to bring my friends down. They enjoyed sitting in the
                    gallery or going to committee meetings, hearings, and so forth. But I didn't
                    really make a habit of it, and I don't remember really focusing on it. I thought
                    my life was more important obviously, but I did pay attention to what was going
                    on there. I remember evenings in my parents' Georgetown home with Eugene
                    McCarthy, Phil Hart, and others.</p>
                <p>Q: The Cold War was really going hot and heavy at that time. At the School of
                    Foreign Service how was the Soviet Union or the “Community menace”
                    portrayed?</p>
                <p>DODD: I will always remember a fascinating course I took in Russian history. It
                    was fascinating because it went way back to pre-medieval Russia, the expansion
                    of Moscow and so on. We would read about and listen to great discussions on
                    Soviet expansion. But I also remember the lectures were particularly good in
                    describing earlier Russian czarist expansion in Eastern Europe, Slavic
                    nationalism, and so forth. We received a very intelligent approach studying
                    history and reading daily newspapers on the Cold War. It was not necessarily
                    considered a barracks or a battleground for the Cold War but rather rational
                    interest on the part of historians who taught it and personally experienced the
                    onslaught of Soviet expansion in Eastern Europe. We looked at it. I'll always
                    remember getting a lot of understanding of Russian history, its expansion, the
                    Westerners and the Slavophiles, as they were called.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your reading on Latin America while you were
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: My idea of Latin America was twofold. One was mariachi bands, cigars, and
                    frijoles. The second was a course called InterAmerican Issues. It was taught by
                    a man named William Manger, who was the Deputy Secretary General of the
                    Organization of American States. It was on a Friday at six o'clock in the
                    evening. I'll always remember my roommate saying, “Why would you take something
                    on Latin American on a Friday at six o'clock?” But I'll always remember hearing
                    all of these friends from that part of the world talk about their homelands.
                    This was the only course that was connected to what William Manger taught.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which is significant in today's....</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>DODD: It's significant. And I remember Georgetown had a Latin American Studies
                    Program. It was a graduate program and maybe one of the first in the United
                    States. We undergraduates were allowed to take the courses. So I just took the
                    plunge, took the course, and remained friendly with William Manger for the rest
                    of his life. He died a few years ago. So I crept into Latin America ever so
                    slowly with friends, colleagues, and even sold the Encyclopedia Britannicas (the
                    Spanish edition) in Mexico to raise some money to pay for my graduate school
                    tuition. But I edged into it more through experiences and than to study the
                    discipline of Latin American history and then into the profession, the
                    historical profession.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You'd gone to Spain to study Spanish. This was in
                        college?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: This was in college, exactly. You could take a semester or two.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for the Franco regime?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I sure did. I went to the University of Santander, which was in the Basque
                    country, and I'll always remember visiting the homes of fellow students. They
                    spoke Basque, but all the classes at Santander were in Spanish, which of course
                    made it much easier and possible for me. Of course, Basque was not allowed to be
                    spoken or used in schools. Yes, I did get a feel of the Franco regime. It was
                    harsh, no question about it, and there was not much political debate there.</p>
                <p>Q: I don't know how it was in the late '50s, but for a considerable period of
                    time Franco was seen to be sort of a good, strong, good man within some of the
                    Catholic community, because the left that he fought...</p>
                <p>DODD: Republicans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...the republicans, very anti-clerical.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Very much so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A lot of killings on both sides...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Very much so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...of priests and nuns and commissars.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>DODD: You could see the scars on both sides in that civil war back in the 1950s.
                    But it was a harsh regime. But later I paid attention, later on when Franco
                    brought back Juan Carlos, the grandson of the last king, and placed him in the
                    military academies and so forth. Of course, that was his strategy to bypass any
                    political parties. Ultimately, I think it probably was quite an extraordinary
                    approach, and it worked. The incumbent king, occupant of the throne, is a
                    democrat. He respects the constitution.</p>
                <p>Q: When you came back, at a Catholic university did Franco come up, or was this a
                    matter of your saying, “I was there and it's not so great?”</p>
                <p>DODD: I don't recall it really being an issue when I returned. The great debate
                    over the Civil War, at least among historians, hadn't really emerged yet,
                    although - now you press me on this - I remember there were a couple of faculty
                    members who were very critical of Franco. They may have been of Spanish ancestry
                    or maybe partisans of the republican forces, the loyalists. But it did come up,
                    I remember, at Georgetown among a couple of economists on the faculty who were
                    particularly critical of the Franco regime and the lack of human rights, civil
                    rights. But while a student there, I don't remember, in fact I don't recall,
                    student getting caught up in any debates.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was not a time of acting....</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: No, no, no, it was not a time of acting, no, it certainly wasn't, although
                    I remember much later, later on in 1966, I was in Portugal on a Gulbankian
                    fellowship and Salazar was still prime minister, very old and ill, but I
                    remember then there was a lot of unrest at the University of _______________
                    among students and of course in Africa, Portuguese Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you get your first taste of setting foot into
                        this aresouth of the Rio Grande?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: South of the border, it was when I was an undergraduate at thUniversity of
                    Iberoamericana in Mexico City in 1955 and '56.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about the Army before we get to.... This is
                        '57.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: This is '57. I was commissioned a second lieutenant in
                    thCounter-Intelligence Corps.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you been in the ROTC?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>DODD: Yes, I was in the ROTC for four years. I was commissioned a second
                    lieutenant in the CIC, the Counterintelligence Corps. I went to Fort Holabird. I
                    was assigned to the school, a first tour there, and when I left I started
                    graduate school, and then I was called back up again in 1961 when the Berlin
                    Wall went up, I was assigned to the 49th Armored Division at Fort Polk,
                    Louisiana. I was assigned to a military intelligence detachment there as a first
                    lieutenant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you went in, you were in the Army initially from when
                        to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: It was six months initially. Then you had extensive Reservduty to
                    perform.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Six months, so you really didn't get much....</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: No, not until the second tour. I was what you called Reservist and then I
                    filled a slot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's finish up the military career. This was when the
                        BerliWall went up?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: The Berlin Wall went up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Kennedy activated the Reserve.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: National Guard units, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a rather tense time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: It was, very tense. It was the Texas National Guard, and they were
                    activated, federalized, whatever you want to call it, and sent to Fort Polk. We
                    assumed we were going to West Germany and got ready for it. We stayed right
                    there and had war games in the old Fort Polk reservation where Eisenhower and
                    several of his contemporaries back in 1940 earned their stripes. But it was
                    interesting work, counterintelligence as a military intelligence detachment. We
                    were a good corps of hard-working people. Of course, we had many different
                    assignments, but I was primarily in charge of division security. That meant the
                    physical security of classified information. Also, we offered courses, training
                    courses, on security. It was an interesting assignment that ultimately helped me
                    decide to enter academia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I always think that the military really got you out to mix
                        anmingle with a lot of people.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>DODD: It sure did, no question about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's unfortunate, the ideas, turn you into a war machine,
                        but it'damn good experience for young people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I'll always remember the G2 - the G2 is the intelligence officer - calling
                    me in one day and he said, “I want you to teach the division a course on
                    counter-intelligence” - I couldn't spell it - and he gave me five or six
                    manuals. So I had about 9,000 people to teach counter-intelligence. I read up on
                    the subject as much as I could, prepared my lectures, and discovered I
                    thoroughly enjoyed teaching. When I left there, I decided that's what I would
                    do. I'd go back to graduate school, which I had already started. I decided to go
                    on for a Ph.D.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your M.A. was in what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Latin American studies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: George Washington University.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you compare and contrast, from your experience,
                        George Washington from Georgetown at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: George Washington University was basically a trolley car university,
                    downtown. Most of my classmates, colleagues, there, worked full time. They were
                    from different parts of the country. I met a few from Central America. It was a
                    far more diverse group than I remember at Georgetown. I also recall George
                    Washington then in the early '60s was well along the way in promoting or
                    encouraging interdisciplinary studies, much further along than Georgetown. I
                    found this very valuable and interesting, extremely interesting. You took
                    literature, political science, history, all in a Latin American studies
                    curriculum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were getting your master's, was there a
                        concentration?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>DODD: Really you took courses in political science, history and economics, so
                    they were evenly distributed. I ultimately concentrated in history with a
                    William Columbus Davis. He was the resident Latin Americanist at George
                    Washington. So I concentrated in history and then I took the next step. I
                    continued on in Latin American history. But in those days, you had to have a
                    minor in American diplomatic history and European diplomatic history, because it
                    was assumed that when you got a teaching job in the United States then, you had
                    to teach a European survey or an American diplomatic survey, then you were
                    allowed to teach your Latin American history.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With Latin American history, at that time did it divide
                        itseloff? In a way, Mexico always seems to be on its own.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: It was Mexico and Central America, and then you took the Caribbean, the
                    Spanish Caribbean. You took Cuba and the Dominican Republic and then took French
                    Haiti. Then you studied South America. You took the Andes, a history of the
                    Andean countries, and you took a history of the Southern Cone and then
                    Brazil.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When were you going after your doctorate, what years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I was going after my doctorate from 1961-62 to '66, about fouyears.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were doing this, looking at this, with Castro
                        takinover Cuba, did that play much of a role at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: That was 1959, but I'll tell you: by the time I finished my Ph.D. in Latin
                    American history, Castro had created an extraordinary opportunity for young
                    Ph.D.s in Latin American history, because there was a great deal of curiosity
                    about this fellow and his challenge to the United States. So when we entered
                    departments with Latin American history, students wanted to study Cuba. Fidel
                    Castro was a great boon to Latin Americanists of my generation, like the
                    Sandinistas at the other end of, '79. But Castro was not really a contentious
                    figure at first, but more, I think, an object of great curiosity and fascination
                    for us as we were going through academic programs, no question about it. Most of
                    us admired him tremendously. I remember going down on the mall when he came here
                    (Washington, DC). But we weren't ready to put on bands and carry rifles to go to
                    Cuba. Curiously but maybe not so curiously, when you're a Ph.D. candidate, it
                    may be something like studying medicine. You shut out the world. Your colleagues
                    are only those who are studying with you, and I've often been fascinated by
                    that. We weren't in the streets.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the subject of your dissertation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: My dissertation was on the United States' intervention in Nicaragua in 1927
                    in which the United States Army supervised presidential and congressional
                    elections, 1928 and 1932. One of those figures, a young officer there, was a
                    fellow named Maxwell Ridgeway. I worked on the records here on the archives and
                    then went to Nicaragua and did a lot of research there. When I finished the
                    research in Nicaragua in 1965, I stuck my thumb out and went to Argentina,
                    hitchhiked several months traveling through Central America, Colombia, and down
                    the west coast to Argentina. That was probably one of the most enriching
                    experiences of my entire life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression? You'd been studying this area,
                        and alof a sudden there you are.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: What impressed me the most and struck me the most were two things: one, the
                    enormous diversity among these Latin American states that we call Spanish
                    speaking. That was my first shock. From Costa Rica to Peru, those are light
                    years away in people ethnical, racial characteristics. The second most important
                    thing that struck me was the great divide between the Indo-American world and,
                    if you call it, the modern world of the city of Latin America. I was astonished.
                    I remember spending several weeks in an Indian village in Peru hearing no
                    English and no Spanish. What struck me was the enormous divide between those
                    two, the Indo-American and the Hispanic America, the Spanish world, the urban.
                    That shock just struck me by its enormous and profound differences. At the end
                    of the long trip was the fact that these people hadn't really risen up in
                    rebellion more often or sooner. I was curious. The poverty was so extreme, the
                    illiteracy, and it was a painful shock, because most of my friends in college,
                    graduate school, were from middle to upper middle class families. They nor I
                    heard anything about the poverty, illiteracy, or the Indo-American world.</p>
                <p>Q: What about when you were in Nicaragua? What were you picking up about, one,
                    what was the residue of the American experience there and then about Somoza?</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>DODD: There were two parts of the residue of the American experience. There was
                    the Somoza regime which you could feel as a dictatorship. You could see Iacho
                    Somoza anytime you wanted to. He was not president when I was there. A fellow
                    named Rene Shick was president; he was a hand-picked Somoza candidate. But you
                    could meet anyone in the administration, the Somoza regime, if you wanted to,
                    and they were, of course, very pro-United States. I was a graduate student
                    researching elections and got help from the minister of education to get in the
                    archives. But once I set out in Nicaragua to talk to old Sandinistas, old
                    followers of Augusto C�sar Sandino - and there were many of them - I had many
                    interviews, too, with Emiliano Chamorro. When I moved away from officialdom, you
                    began to feel the intensity of the dislike for the Somoza regime. I met students
                    in the National University. You could see the origins, the beginnings, here, of
                    discontent. It was nowhere near the FSLN organized stage, but they
                    weredissidents and they were being pursued. They were not effectively organized,
                    but they were there. And then, of course, a lot of the names came up later,
                    during the '70s. So it was a three-tiered thing, Somoza officials and family,
                    those who had memories of the '28 to '33 period of U.S. intervention, and then
                    those who were forming the nucleus of the anti-Somoza period. So I got a taste
                    of it right across the board.</p>
                <p>Q: Was there a feeling when you were there in Central America - this was some
                    years after the Arbenz business - that the United States was keeping its finger
                    in the pie?</p>
                <p>DODD: No question about it. The United States ambassador was a proconsul in that
                    period. We were everywhere. Stability, of course, was more important that
                    democracy in the Cold War era. But very interesting - the caveat to my story -
                    there was a career Foreign Service officer named Aaron S. Brown, who was the
                    U.S. ambassador in Managua. He was a wonderful human being. I used to check in
                    with him every now and then because he was very helpful in helping me understand
                    political parties. There were so many of them. But when I saw him, I could only
                    see him, or only chose to see him, in a barber shop right on Avenida Roosevelt
                    on every Thursday afternoon. He was well liked and well respected. He was a good
                    man. He understood the country, and I think he was greatly admired and
                    respected, respected by the Somoza regime. I also remember a lot of Nicaraguans,
                    the shopkeepers, always expressed a great deal of respect for him. And then, of
                    course, in 1965, Lyndon Johnson went into the Dominican Republic. Of course, I
                    felt it. In fact, I was on the road in Ecuador, and they said, “Your country had
                    just intervened in the Dominican Republic.” I said, “Of course, it hasn't.” I
                    didn't want to believe it, but again the heavy hand of the United States was
                    still felt.</p>
                <p>Q: You were in the graduate school. I would think it was almost the normal
                    separation between the graduate student and the academic world and the
                    government, the government getting in there and messing around and the academics
                    usually take a somewhat anti-American government line.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>DODD: There was not an “us and them” attitude principally because fellow
                    classmates and professors came from academia and the government. We may have
                    differed on many subjects, but constant contact and association limited, even
                    ended, early hostility.</p>
                <p>Q: One of the things, of course, on all our missions, not just there but
                    everywhere else in the world, one of our concerns was the Communist menace. Did
                    you see that as being a valid problem?</p>
                <p>DODD: No, from my perspective as a historian of Latin America, it was not a
                    problem because I saw basically - at least I always like to assume I did -
                    political agitation, Socialist Party or Communist Party, as manifestations of
                    gross injustice within Latin American states. People can argue, “Yes, but they
                    were tied with the Cubans,” or “they were tied with the Russians.” Some were.
                    But I saw it really, in Central America especially in the '70s, beginning in the
                    '60s, as movements that were determined really to correct a grossly unjust
                    political and social economic system. I think history may justifthis comment.
                    But now we look at Central America and we find all FMLN people now in congress,
                    the mayor of San Salvador, Sandinistas in congress. Once they were given
                    basically the opening for political participation, insurgencies ended. And that
                    was my argument from the beginning.</p>
                <p>Q: When you were working in Central America but elsewhere too, did you find
                    yourself having to resist being coopted by the 10 big families or the 20 big
                    families? Each country seemed to have these.</p>
                <p>DODD: There was no question about it. As I mentioned earlier, I went to high
                    school and college with members of the old families. When I went back there, I
                    looked them up. Sometimes I stayed with them, had dinner with them, lunch,
                    whatever. But I had a very good, healthy perspective on it. I knew it was a
                    minority, because I worked in the archives and went to the universities and saw
                    where there were people from a far different circle of friends. Did they know I
                    was with the opposition? I don't know. It certainly didn't seem to make any
                    difference. But I was a foreigner, I was studying their history, and intended to
                    be eclectic in my choice of friends and so on who showed interest in my work. I
                    had terrible experiences teaching Latin American history in the '70s. I had
                    classes, for example, where sons and daughters from the same family were either
                    Sandinistas or old Somoza allies, in the same classroom.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Speaking of families, did your father take much of an
                        interest iLatin America, or was he elsewhere?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>DODD: He had a tremendous interest in it, although he never spoke a word of the
                    Spanish language. He was on the Foreign Relations Community. Interestingly, the
                    father of Carlos Salinas, the former president of Mexico, was in the senate. My
                    dad got to know him and they established what then became or has become the
                    Mexican-American Parliamentary something. They meet every two years. My dad had
                    long encouraged us to study Spanish. He used to say that probably there would be
                    more people speaking Spanish in the United States than English. It was motivated
                    in part because my dad had two sisters who were linguists and they taught
                    Spanish and French and German. Language was always important, and my dad spotted
                    the Hispanic world and encouraged all of us to learn about it. In fact, all of
                    us really took a interest in Latin America ultimately in some way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you sort of hitchhiked around, were you able to sample
                        thAmerican embassies or consulates?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I rarely never went to them simply because my work was focused on research,
                    toiling in archives and libraries. For a student, the U.S. embassy was a remote,
                    distant institution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You got your Ph.D. in...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: 1966.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you know what you were going to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Absolutely. I wanted to teach - there was no question about it - I taught a
                    course in European history at George Washington University. It was in the
                    evening. At the end of the course a woman walked up to me and said, “You know,
                    my husband and his department at Georgetown Foreign Service School are looking
                    for a historian. His name is Carroll Quigley.” I had taught Mrs. Quigley for a
                    whole semester and I didn't know it. She said, “I think you'd better call him
                    up. I think he might like to have you.” So I went right over to Georgetown and
                    started to teach. I knew exactly what I wanted to do when I worked for the
                    Ph.D.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you started at Georgetown in 1966?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: In 1966. Q: And that was it.</p>
                <p>DODD: And that was it. However, during the course of your career you teach
                    elsewhere. I taught in Mexico, for example, in Guadalajara, Mexico.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During the late '60s what was Georgetown like at that
                        time? We'rtalking about the protest movements.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: It was slow coming to Georgetown, but by '68/'69 Georgetown exploded with
                    student unrest, demonstrations, closing down classes, classrooms, and so on.
                    Yes, like its contemporaries elsewhere, the University was engulfed in the
                    Vietnam War. But generally the student body was conservative, supporting the war
                    longer than most universities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you deal with this, and how did you feel that
                        thUniversity dealt with this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I dealt with it in this context. I remember having classes, setting aside a
                    class to discuss the Vietnam War. But I held to a syllabus of a course. I felt
                    it was important for those of us on the faculty to maintain some integrity to
                    the academic environment, not simply just throw your hand up and say we're going
                    to have an off-street liberal arts program. So I worked through the system but
                    allowed the flexibility for students to deal with it. I took, for example,
                    Vietnam, the intervention in Guatemala in '54, the Bolivian revolution of 1952,
                    the Cuban revolution of '59- revolutions and nationalism. A group of us then in
                    the department of history ultimately taught courses in Regional Histories. We
                    taught freshmen a course on the Middle East, Africa, Asia, and Latin America
                    called Empire and Independence in the Modern World, which studied nationalism
                    and revolutions like Vietnam. It explained basically the ethnic, cultural, and
                    political upheaval of the '60s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get hit with the grade inflation and all
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Sure did, absolutely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think we're still suffering from this now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Absolutely. We were hit with grade inflation largely because, at least
                    initially, a failure in a course could send a young person to Vietnam. That's
                    when I began to see grade inflation become a real problem. Most of us on the
                    faculty had some difficult times with it. We really did, very difficult
                    times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would imagine it would be very hard.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>DODD: A 'B' for me going through school was a good grade. But it was a
                    catastrophe in the late '60s. The pressure, I always say, begins at home. I
                    think these kids got through high school with A+s; we were looking at those on
                    transcripts for admission to Georgetown, and then they expected to be perfect
                    when they got there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And now, I'm told, it's reached almost a business thing.
                        “We pafor the school, so we deserve...”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: A ticket to graduate school or law school or whatever it was. I talk to
                    colleagues at Georgetown now, many colleagues, around the country. Teaching is
                    very difficult today. That's one issue. Another one is just getting their
                    attention in a classroom when they're sitting there with laptops. I don't know
                    whether I'll go back into teaching. I'm weighing it very carefully. I'm not so
                    sure I could do it. It's not easy, and I talk to colleagues who are very tired
                    and very frustrated and discouraged.</p>
                <p>Q: During this time - we're really talking now a period between '68 until you
                    became an ambassador - did you see a change? You said you had several
                    Fulbrights.</p>
                <p>DODD: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you use these?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: There were two types. One Fulbright was given to several academicians
                    around the United States in the field of Latin America, history, anthropology,
                    sociology, literature, and political science. We went as a group to Latin
                    America and visited countries for a few months. When arriving in a country we
                    had joint seminars with colleges in universities. Then we pursued our particular
                    fields of interest, like meeting with historians and so on. It was a wonderful
                    experience. I received a Fulbright later on for research on a Honduran political
                    leader, the life of Tiborshio Cariesa, Honduran president in the 1930s who'd
                    been active in politics in Honduras from the turn of the century to 1969..</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your particular area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: My area was Latin American History, Diplomacy, the foreign policy of Latin
                    American countries, which I had started to teach at Georgetown. It was a new
                    field undertaken by Harold Eugene Davis at American University, a great scholar,
                    great Latin American historian. I began to teach that course: the diplomacy and
                    foreign policy of Latin American states.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of how well Latin American
                        history wataught in Latin America?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Basically Latin American history for sometime was taught as official
                    history. They didn't have the rigorous independence on the part of academicians.
                    Today as before, most academicians in Latin America have full-time jobs in
                    administrations, so they bring with them, I always say, the baggage of their
                    party and ideology. It's changing. Maybe the Internet and computers are doing a
                    lot of that. They now work with their U.S. and European counterparts learning
                    more about their disciplines. They are becoming more independent today, not
                    because of jobs or better pay but, I think, because of more contact with other
                    parts of the world.</p>
                <p>Q: Also, one hears about the tradition of independence of students during the
                    time they're students. They sound like a rather unruly crew as far as getting to
                    sit down and listen to lectures and that sort of thing.</p>
                <p>DODD: It's true today - or, I should say, less so today. But generally students
                    find more interest in organizing political parties and planning an agenda for
                    when they take power. Oddly and paradoxically, if you meet ministers or vice
                    ministers today in Costa Rica or Uruguay, where I spent the last eight years,
                    you will find they were student activists in their day. So part of university
                    training in Latin America experience is really training for the time when you
                    take appointive related office. It's a training ground. It was the same, for
                    example, in the law school at the University of Havana when Fidel was there. You
                    study but you also do a lot of politicking and making friends and alliances.</p>
                <p>Q: Were there different teaching techniques? I think our teaching has moved much
                    more into the dialogue and away from the lecturing. At Georgetown did you find
                    that you were moving into a different style of teaching?</p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, no question about it. I could sense it. Students were coming into the
                    Foreign Service School from good high schools where there was more collegial
                    work done. Yes, I could see signs of that, and then sometimes when I went to
                    Latin America and tried to teach a seminar, students there still sit behind
                    desks with pen and pencil waiting to hear what you say. I found that rather
                    difficult because I used to give lectures when I was chief of mission....</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dry up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Absolutely dry up. But a lot of my colleagues at Georgetown, more senior
                    colleagues, found it very difficult with that change. Teaching case studies in
                    InterAmerican diplomacy - using simulation exercises - prevented me from drying
                    up. It was a new way of teaching.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came in at...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>DODD: I came in with a straight lecture form, follow the script, and you did it
                    right from the podium. But by the time I was finishing at Georgetown, it was a
                    vastly different experience.</p>
                <p>Q: Speaking of Georgetown, Georgetown moved from being a Jesuit school to being
                    an Ivy League school essentially. There was a very deliberate effort to cut
                    loose. Who was the...?</p>
                <p>DODD: Tim Healey.</p>
                <p>Q: Father Healey very deliberately said, “The best of the Catholic schools is
                    going to be competitive with the best of the liberal arts schools.” Did that
                    start while you were there?</p>
                <p>DODD: It did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This must have caused some strain.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: It caused a great deal of strain. There were those on the faculty, I
                    remember, who felt strongly that teaching should be the center of the
                    pedagogical experience or at least of what a faculty should do. Then there were
                    those who said, no, research should be the soul. During my period then
                    Georgetown wanted both scholarly pursuits within publication and excellence in
                    the classroom. I think many of us found that difficult. It was not easy. It was
                    very hard to research, write and publish and teach all at the same time. I
                    remember my colleagues at Harvard and Yale were given offices in a library. A
                    library, that's where your office was, because you were supposed to write. Then
                    you give your graduate seminars or, if you give undergraduate courses, you give
                    the lectures but your teaching assistants did the spade work. We didn't have
                    that. It was very difficult and very stressful. Time Healy helped to establish
                    blocs of time with fellowships and grants to research and/or to teach, to
                    write.</p>
                <p>Q: On this, I would think that you would have a good number of people who were in
                    the academic world, particularly with so much emphasis on 'publish or perish',
                    who aren't very good teachers. They don't empathize.</p>
                <p>DODD: No, they don't, many of them don't. Yet in my case, I found when I was
                    researching something and writing something, my courses were better, much
                    better. I felt good about giving a lecture because, while some of it was out of
                    a textbook they were reading, some of it may have been out of what I was finding
                    or culling from an archives. And students like that. At least I found that good
                    students like to have someone in there who can say, “Well, that's not what I've
                    been finding in the archives. I really enjoyed that stage, when there was some
                    research and writing going on and there was some teaching going on - not easy
                    but it was fun.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>Q: Also the history field. I got a master's in history but I was a Foreign
                    Service officer. I've always been interested in history, and there was what I
                    thought was a horrible period of time when the computer first came in and all
                    the historians were running around getting voting data, trying to find sort of
                    the philosopher's stone from the damn computer. Everything was quantified. Did
                    that hit you?</p>
                <p>DODD: No. I think this must have hit after I left for Uruguay, although it may
                    have just started. But a lot of it was graphs and quantifying things for
                    political scientists and economists, yes. I'm aware of this. I was just
                    beginning to see signs of it when I left eight years ago. There has been an
                    interesting article about that in one of the leading journals in my field. The
                    historians now become so bogged down in data that they're losing sight of some
                    of the big picture and the reading public.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Most of the history that I enjoy reading has been written
                        bnewspapers.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: A couple of colleagues and I were talking about this the other day. I was
                    saying some of the good histories: David McCullough's biography of Truman -
                    Doris Kearns Goodwin, an academician. But she's one of the popular historians -
                    there really are some serious scholars writing good narratives, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And McPherson on the Civil War was knocked down because he
                        wrotpopular books.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Exactly. I always say, if you want to attract students and you want to
                    attract people's interest in history - and I think it goes for anyone regardless
                    of your field or discipline - you have to make it engaging, readable, and
                    somehow, some way, connected to their experience.</p>
                <p>Q: Something has always disturbed me: the idea that there was a difference
                    between a political scientist and a historian. Looking at it, I guess, with
                    prejudice, if I open a book and I see too many graphs and things like this, I
                    just shut it and go somewhere else. Did you find yourself caught in this? How
                    did you view political science, scientists?</p>
                <p>DODD: I always found political scientists interesting, because my colleagues in
                    that field or discipline were usually very good at creating what they call a
                    paradigm, a model. Then when teaching jointly with them, the historian can fill
                    in the story, embellish the cause with results of events.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you tell me: I think I know, but what is a
                        paradigm?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>DODD: It's a system. It's a certain kind of social system or political system or
                    an economic system. We historians work on precedent; we look on antecedents; we
                    cull from the past and see if there are any lessons that can be learned in the
                    present. And that's where I found history for me valuable and instructive.</p>
                <p>Q: When you were teaching at Georgetown, you must have become involved in a
                    symbiotic relationship between Georgetown and the State Department's Foreign
                    Service.</p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, very much so. We used to have Foreign Service officers in the School
                    of Foreign Service. They called it in the “diplomat in residence.” I found them
                    interesting and helpful. I say 'helpful' because it was wonderful to have them
                    around in a seminar when you're teaching diplomatic history of Latin America.
                    Maybe one of them had been in an embassy. They brought a great deal of practical
                    information to a course and to the faculty. Many of them were very helpful in
                    linking together my history courses with what you would need in taking a history
                    of Latin America in how you practice diplomacy. And they were good critics. They
                    found that there was a lot of material we were doing that was repetitive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were many of your students looking towards...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Sure. I ran into students every week in both posts. On several occasions
                    I'd go in to see a foreign minister with my colleagues in the embassy and we'd
                    sit at these long tables. It would be a difficult, contentious problem, and I'd
                    look over in the corner of the table and there would be a student waving at me,
                    and I'd say, “I hope you did well on the course.” I ran into Foreign Service
                    officers from home and professional diplomats in Latin America all the time -
                    journalists, lawyers, doctors, all former students.</p>
                <p>Q: You were there during a period of time when there would been sort of an earth
                    change in Latin America, which before had been sending its elite to Europe. In
                    Argentina, Britain was called home.</p>
                <p>DODD: Absolutely, England or France.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By the time you'd gotten there, this had really
                        changed.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>DODD: This had changed, no question about it. The bulk of applicants and interest
                    in Fulbrights increased significantly, although unfortunately the awards have
                    not been as plentiful for economic reasons. But now students flock to the United
                    States for their undergraduate, graduate, and postgraduate work. In Costa Rica,
                    just about anywhere I'd go, I'd run into former Fulbrighters. There are over
                    1,000 Fulbrighters in Costa Rica, and that's a country of only three and a half
                    million people. And the focus, of course, is on their professional experience in
                    the United States. There are many other reasons, of course, but our universities
                    have just boomed financially and Europe's have suffered. Many cabinet officers
                    in Latin American administrations, the “teamocrats,” are graduates of our
                    business schools.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, and mostly universities really depend now on the
                        foreigstudents.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: They do, even though, I'm sorry to say, less than eight percent of our
                    American high school students study a foreign language, which is disturbing. But
                    certainly the interest from Latin America is growing for the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Separating the time when you were the chief of missions in
                        two countries but prior to that - you were talking about Latin American
                        diplomacy and all of this - what were you seeing, as you studied this and
                        getting feed back, about the diplomatic corps of various countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I saw the professionalization of their foreign ministries; that is, they're
                    beginning now to train, to educate people to become professional diplomats.
                    Costa Rica now is moving dramatically in the direction of recruiting people to
                    study in the foreign service academy and to reduce the number of political
                    appointees. This has been true in Washington and elsewhere. Brazil has had a
                    first rate career service since the early 20th century.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It used to be this was where you sent the erring second
                        son.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Exactly, and as your political fortunes declined, too, you were sent
                    abroad. This was true in the United States in the mid-19th century. But they are
                    clearly becoming more professional. None of them had reached or was approaching
                    the Brazilian foreign ministry which is, of course, first class.</p>
                <p>Q: You know, I heard something, and it was a particularly good comment. Everyone
                    talks about the professionalism of the Brazilians, but I've had a couple people
                    say, “Yes, but you take a look at it and essentially it's the Brazilians using
                    all the tricks in the trade and great knowledge to say no.” In other words, it
                    really doesn't advance anything, and they all come from one class, and they're
                    very good at what they do, which is really to keep Brazil Brazil.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>DODD: In many ways it's true. It certainly still remains today an elite - I
                    should say the profession draws from the Brazilian elite. There's no question
                    about it. If you put on a roster the names of Brazilian diplomats abroad, it's a
                    Who's Who of the descendants of late 19th century, the golden age of Brazilian
                    diplomacy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your father left the senate, but when did your brother
                        come in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Christopher ran for the House of Representatives in 1974. Bill St. Onge,
                    who was the Congressman from what was called 'a shoestring district' - that's
                    the area running along the East Coast - died suddenly. I'll always remember
                    Christy and I were driving along in my Volkswagen and he said, “Which one of us
                    will jump in?” I said, “Well, you live up here. Go ahead. I'm back in
                    Washington.” So he did and ran in '74 and has been in Congress ever since.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You obviously come from a political family. Did that bug
                        ever geto you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: It never really did in the sense that I wanted to jump into elective
                    politics. I love politics, I love to talk about it, I read about it, but I
                    really loved what I was doing. I love teaching. If I had gone home to teach,
                    yes, I might have gone into it possibly. But then I was here in Washington
                    teaching a subject I loved very much, and I didn't want to break that, go back
                    home and change careers.</p>
                <p>Q: Teaching at Georgetown, living in Georgetown, did you find yourself using your
                    knowledge about Latin America? Did this suck you into the power world, people,
                    Congress and other people, who were looking for information as well as...?</p>
                <p>DODD: Many times I would meet with my brother Christopher during the 1980s when
                    Central America was in such upheaval. Once in a while, he might bring another
                    member of the Senate along with him - Mathias from Maryland, and Sarbanes - and
                    we'd talk about Latin America. But our conversations were always based around
                    this framework. I gave them what my brother said, “Latin America from the bottom
                    up.” They knew some assumptions from the top down, policy issues. Sometimes I
                    would suggest history books for members of the Foreign Relations Committee and
                    my brother would get them xeroxed and pass them around. So I approached my
                    contacts as an education experience - I liked that. But I never wavered from
                    offering what I thought as a historian to be helpful to practitioners whether
                    they were Foreign Service officers or members of Congress.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ____________ if you watch people who kind of lose their
                        rootand....</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>DODD: I didn't do that. I was a happier person as a result of it, because I knew
                    what I liked to do and I felt I could bring something to the table. In 1981 I
                    taught at the Foreign Service Institute teaching Central American history. I
                    remember my first introductory lecture was on geography and pre-Colombian or
                    pre-modern Central America, and the course ended about noon. I remember the dean
                    called me in and said, “You know, these people are going down in the next few
                    weeks. They need a more contemporary approach.” I said, “Okay, I'll revise the
                    syllabus.” I decided I didn't want them to think they were bringing a current
                    events instructor in, they read the newspapers as much as I did, I'd give them
                    something a little more in depth. But anyway, I always used to tell that
                    story.</p>
                <p>Q: How did you come out at the university during the '80s - talking about El
                    Salvador, Nicaragua, and the Reagan administration? All of a sudden, the whole
                    focus was on the Communist menace that was going to hit Brownsville, Texas. How
                    did that hit you as your own thought, and the students and contemporaries?</p>
                <p>DODD: For me it was a golden opportunity, and I seized on it too. I got invited
                    all over the United States to speak at colleges, universities, Chambers of
                    Commerce, and the rest of it, on what the roots of the Central American crisis
                    were historically. I found that this was probably the most useful period of my
                    life in terms of not the academician but really being a spokesperson for my
                    profession, trying to help people understand. People were eager to read books on
                    Central American history - and there weren't many good ones on the subject. But
                    it was an invigorating time. I was not overwhelmed and disappointed, because I
                    saw it as a window to explain the roots and the causes of these events, civil
                    wars, insurrections and rebellions as being symptomatic basically of flawed
                    economic and political systems. Interesting, if you looked at Central American
                    in the 1980s, which countries experienced civil wars? Of course Nicaragua and El
                    Salvador, the two countries where probably political participation, broadening
                    of the political spectrum, was constricted and narrowed in the late '70s, where
                    countries like Honduras with poverty, the political system functioned because it
                    was open, or relatively speaking it was more open than its neighbors, even
                    though poverty was more endemic and severe. I explained, “El Salvador with a
                    middle class? Nicaragua, a booming modern economy.” But I said, “The failure was
                    that in those two states, even while the economic situation improved, political
                    rights were obliterated. That sometimes produces revolution and violence.” So to
                    answer your question, it was not a wonderful era in terms of the struggle that
                    these people experienced. But from a professional historian's perspective, it
                    was our chance (Central Americanists) to explain the roots of civil war and
                    politics in that region.</p>
                <p>Q: I find the interesting thing is somehow during this period, what you call the
                    glitterati, Hollywood and all, picked up the side of the Sandinistas and all...
                    You had this sort of the Who's Who of the entertainment world and the academic
                    world and the sisters, the Merino sisters, and everyone else getting involved on
                    the side of the Sandinistas.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>DODD: Because that was the popular way to propagandize social revolution and
                    revolution, especially the opponents to the Somoza regime. What I tried to
                    explain was that the structure of the old Augustus Cesar Sandino regime (as
                    proposed in the 1920s) was similar to the party organization of the FSLN in the
                    1980s. It was disciplined, well organized, thinking of changing a whole system,
                    political and economic. But I said then that there were within that huge
                    organization (FSLN) people who were greatly anxious to improve basically the
                    political process in Nicaragua. Of course, many of them left disillusioned, but
                    there were many others. But yes, the Nicaraguan Revolution became popular,
                    perhaps because it was a second Vietnam. That's why the burden here on
                    historians was particularly severe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find people who wanted you to come up with a thing
                        showinthat this was a great positive movement and all that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, many were disappointed. I wasn't explaining basically that these were
                    all good people. Trying to replace a politically corrupt system was something
                    better. I was trying to point out as a historian it was symptomatic there of
                    economic and political problems that both Nicaragua and El Salvador had
                    experienced and needed changing. When the Asians' peace plan emerged, when you
                    were tying in all of these political groups to the same process, internal
                    reconciliation, I said, “If we left it to Central Americans, as we did
                    previously many times, and working with Mexicans, you could reach an amicable
                    solution.” This happened. So to people who thought it was the moment of reaching
                    paradise, I said no. Nor was it here a time to retract and to push back
                    things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find the student body was taking much of a stand
                        on this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, they were. They were taking a stand opposed to the Somoza regime. I
                    think in most cases, or in the case of El Salvador the FLMN as it was called,
                    yes. But I think in the case of El Salvador there were more instances where
                    presidents and political leaders were showing a strong tendency to be more
                    cooperative. Duarte, for example, comes to mind. Students, graduate students,
                    others liked him. He was liked in Congress. He went to Notre Dame with many
                    members of the House and built on these relationships. These were examples where
                    there was a great deal of connectedness with Central America on the part of U.S.
                    citizens and institutions. Georgetown's Jesuit community had close ties to the
                    Catholic University in El Salvador. That further deepened my students'
                    involvement in these, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You also missed the period which came later of political
                        correctness, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, I did, I missed that. That was just beginning to emerge.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was not one of the great moments. It represents
                        control.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Basically, I did keep up with journals in my field, Latin American history,
                    while I wrote. But I could see it permeate the article and treatises into the
                    field of Latin American history that it became almost impossible for a historian
                    to reach a kind of consensus cause and effect in history. Unless you used the
                    right language and the right reference racially, sexually to this or that
                    gender, you could be criticized and condemned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think we can stop at this point... We'll pick this up
                        withy hoyou got into foreign affairs as a practical thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Today is August 2, 2001. Tom, were you, prior to your appointment, sort of
                    keeping up with people, bring them in, who have been involved particularly in
                    Latin American affairs in the Foreign Service, not only our Foreign Service but
                    other people's foreign services and all? Were you bringing them into your class
                    work?</p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, that was part of the structure on the course on Latin American
                    diplomatic history that I was teaching at Georgetown. There were case studies in
                    inter-American relations, crises of one kind or another, and so that course,
                    taught over the years, involved professionals, skilled Foreign Service officers,
                    from the U.S. as well as from Latin America. This is a great resource here in
                    the city. We brought them over to the School of Foreign Service, both the
                    undergraduate course I taught in Latin American diplomatic history and the
                    graduate program, master's of science and foreign service. So I brought in the
                    practitioners and worked along with them in those case studies.</p>
                <p>Q: I've never served in Latin America but I've heard many people say,
                    particularly dealing with Mexico but some of the other places, that the foreign
                    affairs side usually is sort of the reserved playground of the left within the
                    political spectrum in a country, particularly Mexico and all, because in a way
                    it doesn't make that much different to the powers that be, so they can kind of
                    beat up on the Yankees there.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>DODD: I think that it true to some extent. Foreign affairs and foreign affairs
                    ministries in the last few years, during my tenure, since 1992 and '93, have
                    become more professionalized. In Costa Rica an effort has been made to create a
                    cadre of career professionals. Many new Foreign Service officers going into the
                    ministries, foreign ministries - in Uruguay and Costa Rica - had studied in the
                    United States, so they had a more measured and, I think, a better understanding
                    of what we're about up here. So the era of simply bashing the Yankee to gain
                    some political stature doesn't really hold anymore, at least certainly in the
                    two countries I was accredited to.</p>
                <p>Q: It's a natural extension, but had you had any experience, either as an expert
                    of consultant or anything like that, in the foreign affairs field other than
                    being a teacher prior to your appointment as ambassador?</p>
                <p>DODD: It did. Back in the '70s, Stu, I worked on a contract basis with the Policy
                    and Coordinating staff in the Department of State reviewing, reading and
                    sometimes writing papers dealing with Latin America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What does that mean? What were they looking at?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Actually, as I recall, these were like position papers dealing with Latin
                    America. They were looking for accuracy; were there enough themes that were in
                    these position papers on how to begin to implement some foreign policy; that
                    reflected basically a reality in dealing with Latin American countries. My
                    recollection was dealing with Central American and the Spanish Caribbean. I also
                    gave lectures out at the National Defense University. I chaired the Central
                    American Seminar at the Department of State Foreign Service Institute and at the
                    InterAmerican Defense College. So I applied some of the tenets of Latin American
                    diplomatic history to those courses. At Georgetown University, there were many
                    people from the U.S. Foreign Service and from the foreign ministries of other
                    countries. I worked closely with these people like team teaching courses from
                    time to time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then, let's talk about when you got actually
                        employed, toothe queen's shilling. How did that develop?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: You know, it's always been a tradition in the School of Foreign Service at
                    Georgetown that you should put some time into public service. Of course, most of
                    the attention was focused on the Department of Defense and the Department of
                    State. So when Madeleine Albright was named to the U.N., I kept encouraging her
                    over the years to get involved, and she did, in political campaigns....</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She had been a faculty member or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: She was a faculty member. Madeleine was there probably 18 years or more. So
                    I always encouraged her and she did me, and so in 1992 when the governor of
                    Arkansas was elected President, she, of course, went to the U.N., and then there
                    was the opening or the possibility of going to Latin America. But I wanted to
                    pick a country that was a democracy where you could really work on strengthening
                    democracy in a small country, and Uruguay opened up. In the spring of '93 I had
                    a syllabus all ready for fall '93. As much as I was, of course, interested in
                    Latin American diplomatic history, I wasn't absolutely certain that going to a
                    post as a chief of mission would be the easiest or maybe the best thing to do.
                    But I thought about it and went to class one day and was mulling about it in
                    class. At the end of a class, and in the back of the room, I heard a voice say,
                    “Oh, for heaven's sake, why don't you put your money where your mouth is? You've
                    been talking about public service and work for time. Apply some of your
                    theories.” It was a rather shocking and a rather abrupt thing. It was too late
                    to say, “Who said it?” so I went back to the office and I decided I'd do it. But
                    again, it was a quantum leap. Even though I had been in and around diplomats and
                    been to Latin America often, worked in the archives of foreign ministries, it
                    was a leap across a stream into the unknown.</p>
                <p>Q: Unlike so many other people who've had this appointment who were not coming
                    from within the Foreign Service, you were probably far better acquainted with
                    the terrain and all this.</p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, I think that's correct. I certainly felt comfortable after I decided,
                    yes, I would go ahead with this, because I made the rounds of the Department of
                    State and met former students, former colleagues that I had known, former chiefs
                    of mission to Uruguay specifically. There were several of them retired here in
                    the Washington area. A couple of them lived elsewhere, but there were several of
                    them, three or four. I remember Woodward, Robert Woodward - by the way, who just
                    died. I had wonderful visits with him. He was living in Washington back in the
                    '90s, and I had long visits and conversation with him. I took notes from these
                    former chiefs of mission. And there were others: Malcolm Wilke, who actually was
                    living in Uruguay and Chile; Richard Brown, my predecessor, of course, was
                    there, and I saw him after he came up; but there were a couple of others that I
                    had seen and talked to about the country. Dean Andrew Steidman at Georgetown was
                    very helpful. He relayed the do's and don't's of running an embassy. I kept
                    copious notes. I still have them. They've been invaluable because they not only
                    assisted me on the details in the big picture of running an embassy but they've
                    also been helpful to people I have subsequently assisted as COMS.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Without going through the whole list, what are some of the
                        bido's and don't's?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>DODD: One of the big do's that I learned about from some experience at Georgetown
                    when I headed up a program in the graduate school for Latin American studies. Be
                    visible, be seen, and make a point of visiting colleagues who are working with
                    you. That was something that interested me, because going to an embassy there is
                    the temptation of getting in the elevator in the basement and going directly up
                    to your office. I never did that, or at least I didn't do it often. I stopped on
                    a floor each week and visited offices. I always visited the consular section in
                    the mornings before they got started or at the end of a day. A big don't is do
                    not micromanage an embassy. Let people do their jobs.</p>
                <p>Q: It took me almost a year to get George Kennan to come to the counselor section
                    when I was in Yugoslavia, honest to God. He was on the fourth floor, I think,
                    and I was in the basement.</p>
                <p>DODD: Mary Ryan, the Assistant Secretary for Consular Affairs, was very helpful.
                    I went to see her, and the big 'do' was to visit the counselor section. Don't do
                    it every day obviously; don't do it mid-morning: the window's open and they're
                    busy; but check in there at the end of a day. So what I did in both countries
                    was have a coffee hour with them once a month at the end of a day. I did it with
                    the other sections. So again, you asked me the big 'do': Be visible; visit; let
                    them know when you're coming, don't pop up at busy hours - that's just
                    interference. See the Marines; always stop and say hello to them. I had
                    breakfast with them twice a month at their house early in the morning. Those are
                    the big 'do's'. A big 'don't': There are always issues coming to the table;
                    don't make a decision on any key issue, whether it's bilateral with the
                    government or something the Department of State is asking about, until you bring
                    everybody into the picture. There were many times I ultimately had to make
                    decisions and, of course, people were unhappy. But they were unhappy that their
                    position or their views were not taken. Yet they were heard, and that was key. I
                    learned that really from academic life. A dean or a chair of a department in a
                    university will “sink” if they don't bring in people at the ground level. So
                    that was something not to do, that is, to disregard their interest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the ambassador's training seminar,
                        ambassadoriaseminar? Did you find that very useful?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I did find it very useful, and I found it more useful in the details, the
                    'do's' and 'don't's.' What I learned most from that seminar was the role of
                    different agencies and departments in an embassy. I really learned for the first
                    time that it's just not all foreign service. On the contrary, it includes a wide
                    range of agencies and departments. I learned basically how to coordinate and
                    consult and to pay attention to what they're doing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also, wasn't there, at that time and, I think, still,
                        quite a loof emphasis on what are your legal responsibilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>DODD: That's right; that's all part of it, with the different agencies and the
                    military. That was key, very important, what authority, for example, you had
                    over the armed forces.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How big was your seminar at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I believe it was somewhere between 15 and 20.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was right at the beginning...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: That's right, in '93. It was the beginning of a neadministration.</p>
                <p>Q: There was a problem that often occurs and that is the political appointees -
                    this wouldn't apply to you because you'd been around the block - the political
                    appointees, many of them, are coming out and they're told, “Watch out for those
                    Foreign Service people; they're going to stick it to you,” and a lot of
                    suspicion, which usually wears down but it's an inhibitor.</p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, I agree, I did hear, and I've heard it even after my years began, that
                    is, after I arrived in Uruguay and would go to conferences of one kind of
                    another. What I think may have been the turning point or help at least in my era
                    were the meetings of chiefs of mission from Latin America. I understand that was
                    a first. I remember - I forget his name at the moment, a wonderful guy, the
                    Assistant Secretary for Inter-American Affairs; I'll think of it in a
                    minute...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Alec Watson.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Alec Watson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm interviewing Alec.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: He's wonderful. I have enormous respect for him. He brought together the
                    chiefs of mission for Latin America. That was helpful, to answer your question.
                    I think it helped to smooth out some of the tension or maybe suspicions. I
                    noticed with many colleagues who were political appointees, there were no longer
                    feelings without regard. They were more comfortable, more confident on calling
                    on them, the career people, the professionals.</p>
                <p>Q: You'd already studied Uruguay as part of your parish anyway. From the desk
                    before you went out there, what were you getting about Uruguay? Where did it
                    stand, its importance, and how things were going there?</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>DODD: The picture that I got initially was that it was a democracy but really one
                    that was fragile, that had a military regime with some very difficult times in
                    the '70s and '60s. The urban insurgence movements challenged institutions. The
                    judiciary was not strong. The congress, yes, exercised considerable authority,
                    but most of the incumbent officers, ministers, were people that had been tested
                    during that time of the late '60s/early '70s during the insurgency. So it was a
                    country that I had to tread carefully in terms of resurrecting old wounds but
                    had to spend a lot of time fostering, encouraging, really building deeper and
                    stronger democratic institutions. Last, Uruguay was always a key player
                    resolving regional conflicts. I began to think of ways to initiate this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any major outstanding issues between Uruguay
                        and thUnited States that you felt you'd better get in and settle?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: No, really not. In fact, my sense from the Department was that things have
                    stabilized, it's quiet, and I remember saying to Alec Watson, “Well, basically
                    then maybe what you want me to do is stay off your screen.” I said, “How about
                    being creative?” He said, “Yes, let me know what you've got on your mind,”
                    before I got too creative. Basically to get right to the point so I don't leave
                    this hanging: I then subsequently suggested to him and another Deputy Assistant
                    Secretary that maybe being creative would be two things: one, begin to do some
                    reporting on Uruguay's role in MERCOSUR and look more carefully at the interior
                    of the country and its MERCOSUR border ties to Argentina and Brazil in trade
                    matters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain what that is?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, basically to look at the Southern Cone's efforts to create a common
                    market. Uruguay, being highly literate, politically stable, it would be
                    interesting to see how and what role it was going to play in MERCOSUR. And in
                    that context I pursued that. We did a lot of economic reporting on MERCOSUR from
                    the perspective of Uruguay, that is, looking at Uruguay's border, ties, and
                    economies with Brazil, Paraguay, and Argentina.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now, M, how do you spell the last name?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: MERCOSUR.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Merco means market.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>DODD: Market, exactly, of the South. So that was a major objective and it meant,
                    of course, that I had to do a lot of traveling in the interior to get to know
                    the intendentes or governors. What I was interested to see basically was just
                    what kind of role Uruguay would play in this southern market. It turned out
                    ultimately, before I left, that Uruguay would become the administrative capital
                    of MERCOSUR.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What countries considered themselves MERCOSUR?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Brazil, Uruguay as I just mentioned, Argentina and Paraguay. Chile has
                    since become an associate member of MERCOSUR, so it covers an enormous amount of
                    territory.</p>
                <p>Q: I would assume Uruguay could put itself in the middle because Argentina and
                    Brazil are sort of rivals, and Uruguay being smaller but with a very literate
                    population fit in between literally and figuratively.</p>
                <p>DODD: There was a change during my tenure that I think was very significant in
                    Uruguay's role here. Yes, historically Uruguay always played its neighbors one
                    off the other. This was axiomatic. It was fundamental in order to survive,
                    survive invasions. What happened in the post-Cold War era was that Uruguay then
                    became more engaged with its neighbors. It would try to get Brazil, Argentina,
                    and Paraguay to deal with economic issues not political matters, and to use
                    Montevideo or Punta del Este, the famous resort, as a conference center. There
                    were several meetings, in fact ongoing meetings, between presidents, foreign
                    ministers, ministers of economy who would meet in Uruguay. It was more engaged
                    with the neighbors to bring them together in Uruguay, not create or exacerbate
                    tensions and frictions between those major powers like Argentina and Brazil.</p>
                <p>Q: I would imagine they would be in a way taking heart but maybe be apprehensive
                    of the North American Trade Association, NAFTA, that was going on between
                    Mexico, Canada, and the United States.</p>
                <p>DODD: Yes. Brazil has been in the last few years highly suspicious of NAFTA and
                    the United States' effort to promote a Western Hemisphere trade agreement. But
                    during my tenure there as chief of mission, MERCOSUR really decided not to go it
                    alone permanently but to build a South American common market and then at some
                    future date hook up with NAFTA and create a Western Hemisphere free trade
                    association. MERCOSUR then actively looked to Europe and the European Union as
                    helpful first and obviously becoming a new market for MERCOSUR and its exports.
                    So when I was there, MERCOSUR looked very closely to Europe, away from
                    NAFTA.</p>
                <p>Q: Chile was high on our list that President Clinton was trying to get fast-track
                    agreement to basically put Chile into the NAFTA association. Was that considered
                    to be we were playing in the MERCOSUR's back yard? Was that a little bit
                    dirty?</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>DODD: Chile became an associate member of MERCOSUR, because the fast track
                    failed. But now (2002), the United States and Chile are negotiating a free trade
                    agreement. The United States is reaching out to Chile, having moved along very
                    rapidly and very effectively in its fiscal and economic reforms, privatization,
                    making it, of course, a very, very, very likely and good candidate for
                    NAFTA.</p>
                <p>Q: Well now, how about Uruguay? Were we taking a look at Uruguay, because Brazil
                    is so huge that's always unique no matter what you think about Latin America?
                    Argentina has had almost terminal problems. But were we thinking of Uruguay next
                    after Chile?</p>
                <p>DODD: No, that never became an issue. We were looking at Uruguay as a politically
                    stable, predictable country that would be helpful in creating regional stability
                    in that area and being a key diplomatic agent in terms of getting the
                    Argentineans and the Brazilians, and the always volatile Paraguayans into the
                    pattern of creating an orderly Southern Cone market system that ultimately might
                    reach what is called ACLA, or the Western Hemisphere free-trade association.
                    Uruguay was not going to be plucked out for a free-trade agreement with the
                    United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk a bit about the government. When you arrived,
                        whaessentially was the government and how did you deal with it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: The government was headed by Luis Alberto Localle, a member of the
                    Nationalist Party, a center right party, extremely friendly to the United
                    States. One of his interests was to privatize the state-owned, state-managed
                    industry, and the government was anxious to privatize the telecommunications
                    industry, too. So they were especially solicitous of me and the embassy to help
                    and to encourage this and to bring the United States' Small Business
                    Administration down to show them how this could be done. Our relations were very
                    good with the Localle administration, very friendly. He had traveled and studied
                    in the United States, so he knew Washington. He was succeeded by a man named
                    Sanguinetti, who was a member of the Colorado Party, the center left. It was not
                    necessarily unhappy with the state-owned, stated-managed industry. Sanguinetti -
                    I've described him - and, by the way, I even mentioned this to him when I saw
                    him frequently - I said, “You're really a Europeanist.” I said, “You're more
                    comfortable with French than you are with English,” and he said that was true.
                    So Sanguinetti was a more distant...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you say Europeanist, you're really talking about the
                        labosocialist....</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>DODD: Absolutely, Italy - he was of Italian extraction, very fond of his country
                    of origin, and was very supportive of the labor movement in Uruguay, which, of
                    course, is very powerful. So there I had a challenge. For example, when I would
                    ask to see him on a matter, he would say, “By all means,” but met him at his
                    home later in the day. I suspect or always felt that he did not want a highly
                    visible contact or association with the U.S. ambassador. So I saw him always at
                    his home in his library in the late afternoon. And I must say, they were always
                    very productive sessions. He was always very frank with me, very honest, and
                    also very interesting. I think he's truly one of the best informed Latin
                    American leaders today. He knows the history of that part of the world. He
                    always had something that was helpful to say about how I might look at another
                    country in Latin American, how Washington might deal with it, and they were
                    always very incisive and helpful.</p>
                <p>Q: Let's say the president of Uruguay asked the American ambassador, “You know,
                    if you're dealing with Paraguay, you ought to do this.” Well, you can pass this
                    on, but this will end up to the American ambassador to Paraguay as being a bit
                    gratuitous.</p>
                <p>DODD: I didn't pass it along. But I must say, there were problems with Peru, I
                    remember, and Sanguinetti said to me something that was very interesting. He
                    said, “You know, Peru has never won a war.” And you know he's right, “You must
                    understand it's a country that constantly chafes under that sense of defeat.” He
                    never really said, “This is how you deal with President So-and-so,” but he had
                    more themes, historical themes that I thought were very helpful in terms of
                    dealing with the country's contemporary policy that appeared contentious,
                    fractious, or overly sensitive. I found those kinds of observations very
                    helpful, very helpful. He was well read, extremely well read, not so much on
                    U.S. history and literature unfortunately; again, Europe was his focus of
                    attention.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find, say, that the French ambassador or others
                        werwooing Uruguay?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, there's no question about it. I got to know the French ambassador
                    fairly well. I could tell that he was very comfortable there, as were most
                    European ambassadors. My closest colleague was the British ambassador. He always
                    said, like me, the record of Great Britain in the 18th or 19th century was not
                    all that commendable. We were not necessarily the outsiders - I don't mean to
                    say that - but my colleagues, other European colleagues and continental
                    colleagues, were very comfortable there, very comfortable. The Sanguinetti
                    government was very solicitous of their interests. I'm referring specifically to
                    meetings that the European Union ambassadors had. There were always Uruguayan
                    representatives there. So there was a lot of ongoing dialogue and discussion
                    with the Europeans in Montevideo. But when Localle was president, I don't think
                    the European ambassadors were anywhere near as close to the government. Localle
                    was much more solicitous of me and the United States with respect to trade
                    missions if he could get them. I saw a distinct change when Sanguinetti came
                    in.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this translate itself into any action or inhibiting
                        things.let's say, when Sanguinetti came in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: There were a couple of votes that the Uruguayan representative at the
                    Organization of American States and at the U.N. cast - with respect to Cuba, for
                    example - that were not in tandem with what the Department of State. So, yes,
                    but this was not the case again under the Localle administration. They were much
                    more helpful and solicitous of our interests.</p>
                <p>Q: Tell me: on the subject of Cuba - by this time Cuba was kind of on its own -
                    from Uruguay with a leftish government, a socialist government, was there
                    sympathy for Cuba, or was this a place to sort of show their independence? How
                    was Cuba viewed?</p>
                <p>DODD: Well, it was a combination of both. Uruguay under Localle simply was not
                    sympathetic to Fidel Castro and made no pretense of being neutral on it. But
                    Sanguinetti was clearly sympathy towards the Castro regime. In fact, there was
                    discussion that Castro might even visit Montevideo during my period there. There
                    was no question but that Sanguinetti was sympathetic to Castro. That is that he
                    should be recognized and brought into the family of Western Hemisphere. This
                    might have been - I'm not certain - an effort to be more independent. But I
                    think Sanguinetti worked closely with the Europeans on European states that were
                    equally sympathetic towards Castro.</p>
                <p>Q: Because the subject of Cuba has come up, when you were teaching and all,
                    obviously Cuba was always there, and there's much more of a debate now than
                    there used to be about whether we've done ourselves more harm than good in
                    trying to isolate Cuba rather than to overwhelm them by allowing visits and
                    getting in and all that. What was your personal feeling on that?</p>
                <p>DODD: My personal feeling, Stu, was I thought, and still do, that the time had
                    long since passed when we should recognize Cuba and engage it, that is, bring it
                    into the Western Hemisphere councils, the OAS, and there we could be much more
                    maybe effective with colleagues in pressuring Cuba to be far more humane on
                    human rights and other issues, the distance at arm's length always created
                    problems. As chief of mission in Uruguay, I always was the outsider. In Costa
                    Rica, the Costa Ricans would always say, “What are you really going to do about
                    Cuba?” They were watching carefully, of course, at their neighbors change views
                    like Honduras. So I was constantly under a lot of pressure to be candid about
                    something that I knew was not going to change or didn't expect to change. That
                    got to be very tiring, because it also closed other possibilities of engagement
                    with Cuba.</p>
                <p>Q: In a way it sounds like people I've dealt with - and I had little to do with
                    this - with our policy towards Israel dealing with Arab countries and all that.
                    You knew what the political realities were, and there was no point in arguing
                    it, but it was awkward.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>DODD: It did impact on several occasions on other things I was trying to do but
                    I'd always kind ran into this issue of sanctions, economic sanctions, against
                    Cuba. That always clouded or crowded out other things that I wanted to get done
                    with these two small countries. And, again, I was also pressed and asked, “What
                    do you really think? What is really going to happen in Washington? Will they
                    change?” and so forth, and I had to stick to the party line obviously.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But those that really had to deal with it understood the
                        politicof the thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes and no. I don't think the Uruguayans really grasped the politics of
                    pressure groups here in the States. The Costa Ricans, on the contrary, yes -
                    geographically closer to the United States, the contacts, of course, are so
                    numerous and diverse. The Costa Ricans caught the picture in terms of Congress,
                    its position obviously on the Cuban question and the embargo, those who were for
                    it and against it. Members of the Cuban-American community and Costa Ricans knew
                    each other well. But the Uruguayans were infinitely more - again, maybe
                    geography had something to do with it - simply did not get the full spectrum of
                    different opinions and views in the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did upper middle class, bright Uruguayans go to
                        college?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Europe - France, England, Spain and Italy. This is changing and I could see
                    some movement in the direction towards coming to the United States. Costa Rica
                    is completely the opposite. The upper middle class of Costa Rica comes to the
                    United States. In fact, without exception - maybe I'll have to check this some
                    day - every minister in the Figueres (Jose Maria Figueres, administration that
                    was in power when I arrived) and the Miguel Angel Rodriguez Echeverria
                    government all had attended United States universities earning degrees from U.S.
                    universities. So, again, to go back to my point, there was clearly a better
                    understanding of the United States and its diversity in Costa Rica, more so than
                    in Uruguay.</p>
                <p>Q: Was it part of your portfolio to try to get more Uruguayans up to the United
                    States for a significant period of time - I'm talking about maybe either being
                    educated or getting a good, solid visit - and sort of woo them away from this
                    European connection?</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>DODD: Yes, and let me be precise. This was not done by any directive from the
                    Department of State, but surely with the declining amount of money and funds,
                    the Fulbright program, for example, we had to turn to other resources to do
                    this. I relied heavily on Partners of the Americas. It was established in the
                    1960s with the Alliance For Progress. The sister state with Uruguay was then and
                    still is Minnesota. So we encouraged academic exchanges, farmer-to-farmer
                    programs. In other words, we made a special effort to do just that, to do it
                    through the state partnerships. I didn't give up on Congress and trying to get
                    money, but certainly I had to be more resourceful in doing this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would think that our business programs in universities
                        would bparticularly interesting to the Uruguayans.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: No, I have to tell you there was very little activity in that area. The
                    National University in Uruguay is an antiquated institution. It needs some
                    fundamental reform. They simply have not been offering those kinds of courses to
                    attract the attention of undergraduates, nor had there been much interest on the
                    part of the American Chamber of Commerce then in this area. The state Chambers
                    of Commerce, for example, Florida, Texas and California, had not shown much
                    interest in Uruguay. This may have, of course, changed since I've been there,
                    but certainly not during my tenure.</p>
                <p>Q: Was there any way that you could call upon the academic mafia, of which you
                    were a bona fide member, through whatever contacts you had with the University
                    of Florida or Minnesota or something, and say here's a good hunting ground,
                    particularly for masters' degrees in business and things like this?</p>
                <p>DODD: I went to the Library of Congress in the Hispanic Division. I got help from
                    them, yes, in tapping some university representatives to come down, from the
                    business schools, humanities and social sciences departments for research
                    projects, and for librarians, too*-. That, of course, would have been the
                    interest of the Library of Congress. We did a lot of work in that area to
                    develop programs and library exchanges through the Hispanic Division of the
                    Library. The Hispanic Division put us in touch with other universities who in
                    turn then developed contacts with the libraries in Uruguay.</p>
                <p>Q: This was a period - it continues but was really picking up speed - that was
                    the rise of the electronic communications. I'm thinking of programs, computer
                    programs, computerization, and it was really revolutionizing things. Was this
                    impacting much in Uruguay?</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>DODD: I worked very closely with the binational centers all around Uruguay and
                    was able to get computers into all of the binational centers in Uruguay, about
                    28 of them. It was just beginning, the importance of rural schools as well as
                    schools in Montevideo to get linked up with the high tech and the computer age.
                    Again, we put in the computers and then hooked up the binational centers amongst
                    themselves and with the major center in Montevideo. We were starting this and it
                    was in its early stages, but we got at least the infrastructure, the computers
                    in place. This was my major achievement as COM in Uruguay.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the government leadership plugged into this revolution
                        thawas coming? We could see it in the States.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Barely. The Minister of Culture showed some interest, but we were mostly -
                    we, I say the U.S. embassy and then the United States Information Service, an
                    agency then - we were really cutting new ground and turf and we were on our own.
                    There was really no noticeable or significant assist from the government. Costa
                    Rica was something entirely different.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll go to Costa Rica, but let's talk about the Ministry
                        oForeign Affairs there, this was your principal contact?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: It was my principal contact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the Ministry and, say, the
                        UruguayaForeign Service and its apparatus?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: The Foreign Ministry was small. It was a competent and skilled career
                    foreign ministry. But the bulk of its activity, you could tell, the busy work of
                    the Foreign Ministry was with European powers, European states, and with some
                    growing interest in Asia and Japan, Taiwan, Korea, commercial relations during
                    my tenure with growing interest for the Uruguayan Foreign Ministry. I'm not sure
                    there was even a ministry of foreign commerce in Uruguay. So economic and
                    commercial interests were surfacing. The foreign ministers, with whom I was in
                    close touch and very friendly - obviously their native language was Spanish, but
                    if you couldn't speak Spanish, you then had to speak French or maybe German.
                    They could not speak English. I warned my successors: you've got to learn
                    Spanish or French in the Foreign Ministry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression, and you were getting also from
                        youcolleagues, about the professionalization of the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>DODD: Very slow. It was mostly political appointees, but Sergio Abreru, who was
                    Foreign Minister when I first arrived in the Localle administration, was
                    interested and very anxious to create more career service and had established,
                    if my memory serves me correctly, actually a commission to do it, to study it,
                    to begin to look at it. But when I arrived there, there were a few career
                    people, mostly the political appointees.</p>
                <p>Q: It's been sort of an accepted thing that the Brazilian Foreign Service is
                    particularly good, although I've heard some criticism of it saying it's all very
                    nice but these are all mainly the kids of diplomats. They speak a couple
                    languages but they don't know their country. They know Rio and Sa� Paulo, and
                    they're good lawyers, but that doesn't really-</p>
                <p>DODD: It may be one of Latin America's oldest foreign ministries, but certainly
                    it does not draw from a very wide or broad spectrum of universities and colleges
                    in Brazil. It's still the sons of Rio Branco, the old Brazilian diplomats,
                    yes.</p>
                <p>Q: What about the universities there? Correct me if I'm wrong, but didn't the
                    Tupamaro guerilla movement really come out of the universities?</p>
                <p>DODD: Correct, exactly.</p>
                <p>Q: You know, one always thinks of Latin American universities as being full of
                    red-hot leftists who become red-hot rightists after they graduated, but could
                    you describe the universities?</p>
                <p>DODD: The National University in Uruguay is today, sadly and, I think,
                    tragically, still center for a lot of rhetoric from the left. It's too bad,
                    because the university was politicized back in the 1960s, and at least when I
                    left in 1997, it had not recovered. The National University in Uruguay was, in
                    curriculum matters, that is, programming, in terrible shape. Many, many, many
                    Uruguayan academicians left during the late '60s and into the '70s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they driven out really...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, driven out, and they found good jobs in the United States and Western
                    Europe and did not come back. It was a very sad thing. The Catholic university
                    in Montevideo is a good one. It's solid academically. It's private, of course,
                    and independent, so there were far more interesting and exciting programs being
                    introduced, one of which you've asked me, about business M.A.'s. Business
                    administration was introduced in the Catholic university during my period there.
                    There was, as I say, a far more rigorous academic program in the Catholic
                    university. The National University students would take an average of something
                    like seven to eight years to finish. It became essentially a podium for
                    political rhetoric. When I was there, it continued to do so. I have to say sadly
                    it was not regaining its once very prominent stature.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we making an effort to - 'penetrate' is the wrong
                        term - topen up the university to the American view of things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Many times I suggested and offered as an academician to go to the National
                    University to just visit the students or faculty members, maybe even try a
                    lecture or two. But I was asked not to. If I had gone to the campus, I might
                    have just provoked or created here an outburst of not so much anti-Yankeeism but
                    maybe anti-government. They were fearful of that. I did go to the Catholic
                    university, gave papers there, to read papers on U.S. diplomat relations with
                    Uruguay. Academicians from the States appeared at those conferences and from
                    elsewhere in Latin America. But I was told not to do it at the National
                    University - not that the subject of my lectures would become a point of
                    discussion, but my presence there would. I felt very unhappy. I was very
                    disappointed about that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's really very sad.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: That was very sad, because I felt comfortable in universities and I don't
                    mind criticism, I like it, but they - they, my colleagues in the embassy - felt
                    it would be perhaps more damaging than helpful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were sort of the resources of Uruguay at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Really basically farming. The rural part of the country has had at its base
                    the cotton export that remained very important, meat industry, too. Those are
                    the basic exports and had been traditionally. When I say meat and cotton, you
                    could talk about 19th century Uruguay. Efforts were being made to diversify that
                    economy, moving into different types of meat products. They were getting into
                    the fruit export and some industry. But it was slow moving. Uruguay was then in
                    the early 1990s still struggling to find markets for cotton and meat. Again,
                    that was something they were doing 100 years ago.</p>
                <p>Q: It strikes me that Chile has learned to play the seasonal thing in fruits; in
                    other words, when it's summer in the United States, it's winter in Chile, and
                    vice versa. So when you want grapes, you get nice grapes in January. It would
                    seem that Uruguay could play that both in the United States and Europe.</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>DODD: It could do that, yes, but it was basically the planting. The Ministry of
                    Industries was essentially looking at what was traditional and how to diversify
                    that. Again, as I mentioned, in the fruit sector, that certainly was being
                    examined and there was some movement in that area, canned fruits, not just plain
                    apples and oranges but canned orange juice and so forth. But, again, Uruguay is
                    still, was then in the '90s, a managed economy, a state-managed economy, so that
                    there were not many incentives for private manufacturers or people in the
                    agricultural sector to do much that was creative or innovative.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it does sound like it was a very conservative
                        economy whicdidn't give much room for the entrepreneur.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: No. In fact, I used to have meetings once a month with the business
                    community of Montevideo, which included some U.S. citizens, heads of companies
                    there, and Uruguayans, of course. I spent four years with them trying to find
                    ways to get these businesspeople involved in the politics of foreign trade and
                    so forth, and had a very difficult time of it because they were not politicians.
                    Since they hadn't gotten into that profession, they were also very, very, very
                    cautious about even pressing their cases with governments, particularly the
                    Sanguinetti administration.</p>
                <p>Q: Around there were there examples of other countries that were beginning to
                    move, what we call globalization, but where things are moving very rapidly,
                    particularly electronic communications, computerization, world trade, and all
                    this, which requires very precise management. And it sounds like Uruguay was
                    very poorly situated in terms of government, education, and everything else.</p>
                <p>DODD: Exactly, in that context. This was in the early 1990s. It is a literate
                    population, politically stable, socially stable. In other words, it had all of
                    the basic elements to enter the global economy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It didn't have sort of an Indian underclass.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: No, it didn't, nor a black underclass - but a large middle class. In other
                    words, these were all elements and factors that would attract high-tech
                    industries. But, as I mentioned, there was no planning, no strategy. Now, I may
                    be dated since 1997.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What we're doing is we're capturing the time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>DODD: The time, and that's what's important, and from 1993 to '97 there was no
                    planning in that area and in that direction. As I say, there was no ministry of
                    foreign commerce. The Ministry of Transportation was thinking in terms of
                    rebuilding the old railroad system.</p>
                <p>Q: Were there any shocks? You know, the United States, when it turns around,
                    changes policy, or increases tariff - did you run across any problems?</p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, I did, in a couple of cases in Uruguay's meat exports. The Agriculture
                    Department on several occasions stopped the entry of Uruguayan meat into the
                    United States. This caused a major and abrupt crisis. The Department of
                    Agriculture did not have a representative in the embassy in Uruguay, so there
                    was not a close monitoring of the country's exports to the United States.
                    Processed meat, for example, from McDonald's became a major issue. Ultimately
                    McDonald's and several meatpackers in Uruguay worked out an arrangement so that
                    things quieted down. But up to about 1994/'95 Uruguay simply exported to the
                    United States and hoped for the best. They weren't carefully watching the
                    sanitary needs obviously of our importers. So from time to time their exports
                    would hit, shall we say, the meat ax without carefully watching.</p>
                <p>Q: Were there any issues that the United States was concerned with that may have
                    caused concern or demonstrations or something in Uruguay? Maybe it's so far away
                    - the Balkans...</p>
                <p>DODD: Overall our bilateral relations were good on most fronts except the ones
                    that I mentioned, the Cuban question, the embargo. That was always not
                    contentious - that would be an exaggeration - but it was sensitive. There were
                    no great issues. As I say, we in the embassy worked more in a positive vein
                    promoting the integration of Uruguay into MERCOSUR. I spent a lot of time on
                    economic reporting from the borders of Uruguay with its neighbors looking at
                    education and trade between and amongst its neighbors, which was moving along
                    very rapidly, as a matter of fact, faster than what official Montevideo was
                    prescribing. The school teachers from Brazil were teaching Portuguese in
                    Uruguayan schools in the northern part of the country. In other words,
                    integration, education... Uruguayan students, we noticed and encouraged, were
                    studying in Brazil, southern Brazil. It was much easier to get there and cheaper
                    than to go to Montevideo to go to school. So, again, on those issues we were
                    working in a very positive vein. There were not contentious issues, to answer
                    your question, with Washington that brought people into the streets.</p>
                <p>Q: What were relations, say, with Argentina? Argentina is certainly economically
                    almost a basket case. It looks like it should be doing very well.</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>DODD: At the turn of the century and in the early 1900s Argentina was somewhere
                    like maybe the second or third developed country certainly in the Western
                    Hemisphere, in the Western world. But that was Buenos Aires, not Argentina -
                    that's a vast difference, the province of Buenos Aires. But relations with
                    Uruguay were always - not always; I have to be careful here - were problematic.
                    Specifically when Argentina would devalue or maybe stop the export of Uruguayan
                    cotton or meat to Argentina. It would provoke a crisis. Relations were
                    problematic always with Argentina. With Paraguay relations were rather good, as
                    a matter of fact. Historically there's a large number of Uruguayans of
                    Paraguayan descent. Families are closely linked and tied with Paraguayans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a river tie, isn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Oh, sure. The Rio de la Plata and the Uruguay River. And in Brazil
                    relations are good with Uruguay. As I mentioned, the borders there or schools
                    and different joint business ventures with Brazil. Frontiers are poorly marked
                    and there is an entirely different language and culture in the
                    Uruguayan-Brazilian borderlands.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So Brazil's not conceived as the colossus to the
                        north?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: No, not today. Although historically Brazil and earlier Portugal occupied
                    the Banda Oriental (today Uruguay). Now Uruguayans in the northern part of the
                    country work very closely with Brazilians. In fact, you can cross those borders
                    and not realize you're even in Brazil or back into Uruguay. But with Argentina
                    trade relations are very, very contentious. The Argentinians historically have
                    been generally perceived by Uruguayans as arrogant, feeling much more culturally
                    superior, better educated, and bigger and better in every way. They vacation in
                    Punta del Este on the Uruguayan Atlantic coast, and they're simply not perceived
                    as happy visitors - they're happy but the Uruguayans aren't. In other words,
                    Montevideo has always been treated or perceived by Argentineans as kind of
                    Buenos Aires many years ago, and this, of course, has been an irritant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So for businesspeople would Sa� Paulo be more in Uruguay
                        the placto wheel and deal?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Certainly for Uruguayans who live in the central and northern part of the
                    country, but Buenos Aires is still important. You'll have flights now between
                    Montevideo and Sa� Paulo, yes, regular commercial flights, but the heavy-duty
                    traffic is still across the river by plane or boat to Buenos Aires.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is Buenos Aires the place you go to have fun?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>DODD: You go to have fun. You have really especially good meals, good
                    restaurants, theaters especially good, symphonies. Culturally Buenos Aires is a
                    great city - there's no question about it - and this is an irritant for its
                    neighbors, Paraguayans and Uruguayans.</p>
                <p>Q: What about the problem of smuggling and all that? I'm told that Paraguay
                    is...</p>
                <p>DODD: It's open.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is its main industry.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: It's its main industry. The amount of smuggling, drug trafficking clearly
                    became a problem across the Paraguayan borders and from Brazil into Uruguay.
                    Uruguay became a transit point to Montevideo and out to the Atlantic for
                    shipment to Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On drugs, this has always been a focus of our policy.
                        Hoinvolved did you get?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I was deeply involved. DEA, of course, had representatives ithe
                    embassy...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Drug Enforcement Agency.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Drug Enforcement Agency. We were considered primarily wittransit issues,
                    overland issues and by river.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was transiting from where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: From the Andes through Bolivia and through Paraguay, mostly through
                    Paraguay, and the Uruguay River down to Montevideo and out to Europe and the
                    United States. Drug consumption in Uruguay was not necessarily a serious problem
                    when I was there. We did not work on preventive issues and rehabilitation; it
                    was transit.</p>
                <p>Q: The pattern usually is that for a certain period of time they say, “The drug
                    problem is your problem” - talking to the United States - “and not ours. We're
                    just transiting through.” But pretty soon this begins to seep through, and the
                    money and the addiction.</p>
                <p>DODD: The addiction begins to work its way. But when I was there from '93 to '97,
                    it was transit; transit issues was my paramount interest.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>Q: You mentioned their close ties to Europe, and, of course, Europe is also a
                    consumer, Western Europe, of drugs. Did they have the equivalent of a DEA, or
                    were we left to carry that?</p>
                <p>DODD: We were left to carry out a lot of the work. The Ministry of Interior was
                    not well equipped to deal with this, so our DEA, our Drug Enforcement Agency,
                    was basically trying to set up an infrastructure, a drug enforcement office, in
                    the Ministry of the Interior. When I was there, we were working on the basics of
                    it - finding computers to put into an office. It was rudimentary and not in any
                    way, shape or form sophisticated to deal with it alone. I think they were moving
                    along and developing a cadre of good people in the Ministry of Interior, but it
                    was in the early stages.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about our military? Did we have ship visits? Were
                        winvolved there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: In the early stages, yes, our military in the embassy was working with
                    their counterparts, the Air Force, the Army and their Navy, on drug issues,
                    primarily drug issues. There were a few ship visits but not really that many.
                    The paramount interest for the Air Force and the Army and the Navy was to
                    develop basically training and get some equipment for interdiction, drug
                    interdiction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very early in the Clinton administration they had a major
                        LatiAmerican meeting in Miami.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: The Miami Summit of '94.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Those things sometimes create more anticipation than the successes. But it
                    certainly set into motion the pattern of subsequent summits, again, going from
                    Miami and then to Chile ('98), and then recently to Quebec ('01). So these
                    summits have been moving along and setting agendas, so in '94 the Miami Summit
                    set the agenda for a free-trade agreement - and then the time was set for 2005 -
                    but an agenda was set on other issues, not just free trade. It created the
                    structure for more exchanges between our departments, Department of Justice, our
                    DEA people, for example, working with their counterparts. So in that period '94
                    to '97 I was in the stage of just setting up the framework for more dialogue
                    between our departments and their ministries. The Ministry of Interior, I should
                    add that, too.</p>
                <p>Q: Did Uruguay see itself as a leader or more of a follower in international,
                    particularly OAS or whatever you want to call it, in that area?</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>DODD: The focus of its attention during my tenure there was basically working
                    with MERCOSUR; as I mentioned before, playing a key role, the administrative
                    center, the coordinator of MERCOSUR. But in many ways too a small country with a
                    big international reputation more for its stability, its democratic tradition.
                    It spoke out under Sanguinetti on human rights issues - with the contradiction
                    that it recognized the Castro regime. But it felt by recognizing Castro it was
                    important to engage him, too. But on those issues of human rights, yes, it
                    perceived its role as being high profile in the international organizations. But
                    for practical purposes, on commercial issues it was focused on MERCOSUR and much
                    of its attention was directed in that area.</p>
                <p>Q: What about Puerto Rico? Sometimes this is an issue of Latin Americans who say,
                    “Oh, you should free Puerto Rico, or whatever you're doing.” We keep holding
                    referendums. The Puerto Ricans don't want to leave, but you get beaten up on
                    it.</p>
                <p>DODD: I was asked frequently about Puerto Rico. My response was, what has
                    happened in Puerto Rico is that through several plebiscites, referendums, Puerto
                    Ricans chose the commonwealth status, or a free associated state. I said that
                    throughout its history - or I should say really since the 1940s under Munos
                    Marin - they've had elections and in some cases plebiscites and referendums. “Do
                    you want independence, do you want statehood? Do you want to continue the
                    commonwealth status?” They have chosen that direction. So I said, “We've always
                    been basically open in the sense choose what you want. We have not dictated the
                    commonwealth status. If they want to be independent, that's their business.”
                    Stu, maybe I wasn't all that persuasive with student groups and faculty members,
                    but I never got much criticism back, because when I threw it back in a sense in
                    their laps by saying, “The Puerto Ricans choose the form of government they
                    want. They have a representative in Congress that cannot vote in the House but
                    they can vote in committees,” and I said, “That was a step forward, and because
                    they wanted it and we accepted it, so they can move to a voting representative
                    in the Congress if they make that choice of statehood.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find your embassy as an operating unit?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Sometime ago, I guess when I was talking to you earlier in the interview,
                    one of the great joys I had working in the embassy in Montevideo was I had so
                    many former students who were career Foreign Service Officers but also from the
                    Department of Commerce, DEA, and so on. It was a superbly well organized
                    embassy. I was especially fond of and appreciative of the work of the Foreign
                    Service nationals. These were the Uruguayans in the embassy. I think any
                    knowledgeable U.S. citizen in the embassy would tell you that, that they were
                    really the backbone of an embassy. They had the historical memory of the place,
                    they were well educated. I found a splendid embassy and people that I grew to
                    like. I've always been grateful for their patience and tolerance of this
                    political appointee.</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>Q: How was your DCM or DCMs?</p>
                <p>DODD: Wonderful, Jerry Whitman, and Nancy Mason succeeded him, career Foreign
                    Service Officers. They were first class. They knew their jobs. Basically I set
                    out initially by saying the buck stops at my desk. I used the word or I
                    described, I said, “You work on the plumbing of the embassy, and let's look at
                    the mission statement, and my job is to get out of the embassy and sell this
                    mission statement, and we support all of the different agencies in it,” and
                    that's how it worked. They were happy managing the day-to-day operations of that
                    embassy. I was happy giving speeches, visiting governors of the states, working
                    on the mission plan's agenda, and working closely with what is now called the
                    Public Diplomacy Section. It used to be the United States Information Service
                    and, of course, that was press, radio, cultural affairs. That's where I focused
                    my attention.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the press? How did you find the Uruguayan
                        media?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: The media, professionally it was wanting in some areas. But overall our
                    relations with the press were excellent. But we were proactive in that. Again,
                    the USIA, Public Diplomacy now, made a special practice, I did, of having a
                    luncheon every month with editors and working members of the press of the major
                    newspapers, both from Montevideo and in the interior. I would package a trip to
                    the interior which would include meeting with the regional press, radio, some
                    television. That was the bulk of my work. Again, implementing the mission plan
                    meant a lot of leg work and a lot of traveling, which I liked, and they were
                    happy to have me out of there, out of the embassy. Your DCM was looking at the
                    administrative side. If something came up, of course, that was intractable or
                    couldn't be resolved, obviously I had to deal with it. But aside from what I
                    mentioned about being visible and working the floors and paying attention to
                    what people were doing, my job was to get that mission plan working.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then in '97 you left there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I left in September of '97. I was there exactly four years. Q: So how did
                    your next assignment come about?</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>DODD: How did that come about? I got word from the Department saying that the
                    career person was leaving Costa Rica and there was a big battle over who would
                    be that person's successor. Apparently they decided to not select either one of
                    those career people. So I was in Montevideo and they said, “Well, get ready for
                    another round of it.” Then my brother Christopher, who was in the Senate on the
                    Foreign Relations Committee, said, “Yes, Costa Rica's been a battleground. It's
                    a lovely country. It's a nice place to be assigned to. Would you want it?” And I
                    said, “Yes.” I had to be careful about my tenured position at Georgetown,
                    although they were very liberal in granting me leave for four years. At Harvard,
                    you know, you only get about 18 months. So to get to my point, yes, there was an
                    opening available, and I said, “All right, I'll make a career choice. I'll go
                    for four more years, but I'll have to give up my tenured position at
                    Georgetown,” and I did that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I forgot to ask. Are you married?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about the wife. Would you talk a bit about the
                        mosimportant part of a mission, and that is the distaff side, your
                        wife.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I was married in 1970 and then divorced and remarried, so I waa bachelor in
                    Uruguay, but I was married in Costa Rica.</p>
                <p>Q: I thought we would stop at this point, because I would rather have a good,
                    solid session on Costa Rica, so we'll obviously pick up about your wife and also
                    the whole thing about Costa Rica.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>This is August 13th, 2001. Tom, I can't remember. Did we cover how you got to
                    Costa Rica? Yes, we did. Okay, so you arrived in Costa Rica when?</p>
                <p>DODD: I arrived in the late fall of 1997.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were there until when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Until this year, 2001.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Costa Rica and also in Central
                        Americin 1997 when you appeared?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>DODD: Basically I would describe it simply, that it was a region at peace,
                    politically stable, and for anyone who worked or traveled in Central America a
                    decade earlier in the 1980s during civil wars, intraregional conflicts, social
                    upheaval, it was an entirely new stage, a new panorama, peace, tranquility,
                    political stability. It was a remarkable change from one decade earlier when I
                    was there on a Fulbright. That was the first and the most dramatic, but not
                    surprising for me since teaching and traveling there periodically, I could see
                    the evolution of change in that region from Contra wars and Sandinistas,
                    revolution, civil war in El Salvador. It was extraordinary. You asked me
                    precisely Central America but Costa Rica in general. When I returned to Costa
                    Rica in '97 as chief of mission, of course, things had changed in the decade.
                    But it was still, as it was in the 1980s, the bastion of political stability and
                    social tranquility. That was the one constant in Central America among its
                    nations.</p>
                <p>Q: Prior to that had any of the powers, including the Sandinistas tried to mess
                    around in Costa Rica or Ollie North and our NSC, an awful lot of people were
                    playing games and they really didn't pay much attention to boundaries.</p>
                <p>DODD: There was great migration in Costa Rica from all over Central America,
                    mostly political refugees in the 1980s. In fact, one of the biggest problems I
                    had soon after I arrived was the demining process along the Costa Rican and
                    Nicaraguan border where hundreds of land mines had been placed by Contras and
                    Sandinistas. So, no, there were no boundaries, and Costa Rica was the haven of
                    U.S. Contra military operations up in the northwestern part of the country. In
                    fact, property there was expropriated - a man named Hall - that was used as an
                    airstrip by Ollie North. When I got to Costa Rica, I had to deal with a lot of
                    the legacies of what I call the land and air use of Costa Rica by combatants of
                    Central America.</p>
                <p>Q: We'll come back to that, but when you arrived there, did you have any sort of
                    instructions in your attache case or in your mental attache case?</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>DODD: Yes, I did, at least in my mental attache case. This was a - I've always
                    described, and I think it's correct - Costa Rica, a small developing country
                    with a huge, enormous international reputation on several fronts, a country
                    whose representative were very active in international organizations like the
                    OAS, the Human Rights Commission, the InterAmerican Commission on Human Rights.
                    When I arrived, Costa Rica also had a seat on the UN Security Council. So when I
                    arrived, I was dealing with a small country, small in population and size, but
                    with a very, very prominent role in the world stage. So in my attache case
                    basically were several objectives. First was to deepen and strengthen Costa
                    Rica's democratic institutions, because they in turn would have an impact on its
                    neighbors: that is, a court system which was transparent or become stronger,
                    decentralized government in Costa Rica, which it was trying to do to get more
                    local authority to cities and towns. This too would have an impact on its
                    neighbors. So my agenda basically was to begin to work on those two major
                    issues, how to strengthen Costa Rica's democracy but make it significant for its
                    neighbors. Again, for me to say or even suggest or imply to Costa Ricans that
                    they needed help in maintaining a democratic institution would have been
                    ludicrous and out of order. But to help them strengthen their institutions to
                    help their neighbors was, I think, not only a legitimate objective, but I think
                    it really was serving our interests at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find your embassy when you arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: It was a fine team of people really. It was a large embassy, by the way.
                    There were several other departments represented at the embassy along with the
                    Drug Enforcement Agency, Commerce for example, the Central Intelligence Agency.
                    In other words, it was a large embassy for its regional role. In other words,
                    just as important as working with Costa Rica, we had to work with its neighbors
                    on drug enforcement, on interdiction, for example. So I would describe it as a
                    fine team of seasoned and experienced people with a considerable amount of
                    service in other parts of Latin America. These were not people who had been
                    earlier assigned to China or Afghanistan, or who were brought in from way
                    outside. There were good linguists helpful to me over the four years. There was
                    a very fine and maybe, according to State Department assessments, the finest
                    Foreign Service nationals. These were really first-class professionals with
                    considerable service. We're talking about 30 years, 40 years service. They were
                    called FSNs, Foreign Service Nationals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They're so important.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Their work was fundamental to me. In many ways, I said to my U.S.
                    colleagues often, they're really the backbone of an embassy. These people have
                    great historical knowledge and memory, and they can bring to the table lots of
                    things that are helpful.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your DCM?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I had two DCMs. Linda Jewel was my last DCM. She was from the United States
                    Information Agency. It was an interesting appointment in the selection because
                    it was at the point that the Agency was then going to be merged with the
                    Department State, and I'm a strong advocate of public diplomacy. I think it's a
                    fundamental aspect in the conduct of our relations with our Latin American
                    neighbors. And she knew the press and cultural affairs. So coming from the
                    Agency was, I think, a special and a unique talent to get that experience, and I
                    thought that was important and very significant.</p>
                <p>Q: Let's talk a bit about, before we get to the issues, the government of Costa
                    Rica. How close were our ties to them, and had the decade of turmoil before sort
                    of wounded our relationship?</p>
                <p>DODD: Our relations with the Costa Rican government were simply excellent when I
                    arrived. I did not have to repair any fissures or great damage in any way, shape
                    or form. There were sticky problems, land expropriation cases, squatters
                    appearing on U.S. property in Costa Rica. The legacy though that I should be
                    very candid and up front about was that in the decade of the 1980s the United
                    States was probably spending as much as $350,000,000 a year in Costa Rica
                    through AID, and then it was stopped. Maybe less than five years before I
                    arrived there, AID left Costa Rica. So on that point there was, I think a very
                    difficult legacy. We didn't have the money to spend and to hand over to Costa
                    Rica on every project that they proposed. In fact, I had little or no money. I
                    basically had to wrestle with the problem, “We don't have the money but we may
                    have ways and means to help you get help.” I really became a facilitator to show
                    them basically how and where to get help from non-governmental organizations in
                    the United States, maybe other agencies at here that might help them on
                    projects. I spent four years doing that. I didn't have money to hand out
                    directly. I developed the expertise with colleagues in the embassy in how to be
                    good agents essentially for providing assistance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tom, could you explain why we'd been spending all that
                        money anthen we weren't spending any money?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>DODD: Basically we were spending that money because this was back in the '80s,
                    this was Cold War diplomacy. We would spend as much as needed to fend off either
                    dictatorships, insurgencies that Washington felt were alien or inimical to the
                    interests of the United States in the area. The Cold War abruptly ended that
                    policy of propping up neighbors because we wanted stability at all costs to
                    basically an era where we perceived no challenges to our security which meant,
                    of course, that Congress was not about to underwrite essentially checks for a
                    U.S. mission abroad unless it was obviously of great significance. The emphasis
                    changed then - or the term 'security' - from essentially external threats to
                    basically regional threats like drugs. Drug interdiction became defined as a new
                    type of security threat to the United States, so that monies then flowed fairly
                    frequently and in substantial sums in that direction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of a government? Who were some of the
                        personalities yowere dealing with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I was dealing first with the son of the founder of modern Costa Rican
                    democracy, Jose Maria Figueres. His father, Don Pepe Figueres, led the famous
                    and very significant 1948 revolution and civil war in Costa Rica, abolished the
                    military in 1949, wrote a new constitution, became president, in fact two or
                    three times. I was dealing with the son of the founder essentially of modern
                    democratic Costa Rica. The founding father of modern Costa Rica, President
                    Figueres' father, created basically a welfare state, a patrimonial state, and
                    the son, with whom I was dealing, was trying to modify it dealing with the new
                    global economy of privatization of state-owned industries and attracting foreign
                    technology. So I was dealing with a member of the same family but a president in
                    another generation, a younger generation, who was coping more with the global
                    economy, something that his father did not have to deal with in 1948. It was a
                    friendly government and, of course, the President, Figueres, pressed me over and
                    over again, and I saw the significant of it, of trying to attract foreign
                    companies, U.S. companies and specifically high-tech industry. He attracted the
                    Intel Corporation to Costa Rica. He did so in a manner that has helped to
                    transform and change the Costa Rican economy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a Georgetown connection in Costa Rica?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>DODD: Huge, it was huge. You know, I'll say to colleagues now, and it's becoming
                    more apparent to me, “The legacy of your teaching as an academician generally
                    takes a while.” The benefits, if you want to call them, and the rewards of
                    teaching who reappear as they become mature and enter professions. Every day I
                    ran into Georgetown graduates, ministers, vice ministers, members of the
                    National Assembly, businesspeople, lawyers, doctors; and, second, I also ran
                    into Fulbrighters. I was awarded two Fulbrights in Latin America. There are over
                    1,000 Fulbrighters, former Fulbrighters, in Costa Rica. Imagine that, in a
                    country of just under 4,000,000 people. So there, of course, we did lots of work
                    with the Fulbrighters and Georgetown graduates and former students. I had a huge
                    network of friends and associates. To go back to your earlier question, the
                    change in U.S. policy there, I didn't have the resources of the U.S. government
                    to spend, but I had a huge resource of support from the private sector. We
                    organized the first Fulbright association in Costa Rica to raise money creating
                    more Fulbright scholarships. I had a huge network of former students, graduates
                    and, as I say, from the Fulbright association, which may be per capita one of
                    the largest in the world.</p>
                <p>Q: Well now, how about employment for these people who just be membership in this
                    group you were mentioning and other groups? It seems like you must have had a
                    rather highly educated cadre.</p>
                <p>DODD: Highly educated. As a matter of fact, you may know, general knowledge,
                    Costa Rica's about 99 percent literate. You will find it in the professional
                    classes of people both in the public and private sectors. Many - in fact, in the
                    government, well over half of them, have studied in the United States. They have
                    advanced degrees here, as President Figueres did, the President whom I had to
                    deal with initially, and the next President, Miguel Angel Rodriguez Echeverria
                    holds a Ph.D. from the University of California. So, again, these people studied
                    in the United States at a very high and sophisticated level of education.
                    Therefore, working with them was very easy and mutually beneficial, because they
                    understood us so well; with our faults and great attributes.</p>
                <p>Q: Was their sort of the ten families running the place or something like that,
                    that you hear about in other Latin American places? You didn't have the
                    military, but I was wondering if they had that family...</p>
                <p>DODD: No, you don't have that family network, although there are families that go
                    back to the late 19th century, the great coffee families, yes, but generally you
                    find Costa Rica has one of the strongest two-party system in the world that go
                    back to the 1940s. So, no, to answer your question, you deal with political
                    parties and their ideology.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really disparative income, is there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>DODD: No, there isn't, not by comparison with other countries in Latin America.
                    There's a substantial middle class in Costa Rica, well educated. By no stretch
                    of the imagination do you talk about a few families dominating the political
                    process. They don't, although they play a role in it, but parties are not
                    identified by the names of families who are in them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Indian population?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Very small, probably 10,000 if that, located in the southeastern part of
                    the country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you don't have that...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: These is not a problem of how to integrate or how to givautonomy and self
                    government to an Indo-American population.</p>
                <p>Q: Well then, let's take some of these things that you were talking about. One is
                    the deconstruction of the Cold War, the mines, the facility. What had happened
                    and what were you trying to do?</p>
                <p>DODD: Basically what had happened is that Costa Rica was the only country in the
                    area without any significant - in fact, no significant - civil wars or conflict
                    within its border. As a democracy, it became the haven of political exiles from
                    other Central American countries like the Sandinistas who actually formed their
                    government in Costa Rica before going back to Nicaragua in the summer of 1979.
                    It was also a base for our operations, the United States' operations and
                    assistance to the Contras. So Costa Rica then became essentially the locale for
                    political groups vying for power in their respective countries. A free press
                    there allowed them considerable liberty and independence to propagandize their
                    positions. Second, Costa Rica, along its northern border specifically, was
                    heavily mined by both Contras and Sandinistas, an armed border, not two
                    countries poised to go to war but basically two countries whose competing forces
                    in Nicaragua were using Costa Rican territory.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't have a Costa Rican military?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>DODD: Didn't have a military, so landing strips and roads were built along the
                    northern portion of Costa Rica with easy access to Nicaragua. So, again, it was
                    essentially a haven basically for contending and competing forces, the
                    Sandinistas and Contras, in Nicaragua and in El Salvador to some extent between
                    the FMLN and the competing government forces. So the demining process became one
                    of the most important jobs I had to undertake, to demine those areas along Costa
                    Rica's and Nicaragua's borders, with the Organization of American States and
                    Costa Rica's security forces. It was a very difficult job, because, of course,
                    it takes a great deal of expertise. I finally resorted to the strategy of
                    publishing funny books, comic books, in Spanish about the dangers of walking
                    through mines for high school and grammar school kids in villages along the
                    Costa Rica border. We distributed them up there. I can't tell you honestly
                    whether it had any significant effect, but it certainly raised essentially the
                    dangers on much of the land around the Rio San Juan river which divides those
                    two countries, Nicaragua and Costa Rica. We still have more to do up there. I
                    got something done, but there's still more to do. I can't give you percentages
                    and I'm not certain exactly what the estimates are off the top of my head, but
                    there may be as many as 1,200 mines still to be identified, but that's an
                    educated guess.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you have any residue - this would be true, I guess, of all of Central
                    America - of kind of free-booters, guys with AK47s or American automatic rifles
                    or something? This has been a way of life for some time, and we're still sort of
                    wandering around the jungles. Was that a problem?</p>
                <p>DODD: Not really, not during my tenure there, but certainly it's a good way to
                    describe it historically. Central America's always been a land of free-booters,
                    from William Walker in the mid-19th century on. Yes, there were conscripts, of
                    course, but there were also volunteers from all over joining up with wars for
                    liberation as well as becoming participants in paramilitary forces to contend
                    with those new insurgent and revolutionary forces. But I didn't have that
                    problem. Things had calmed down by then. I was doing the cleaning up
                    essentially, demining.</p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>Q: Of course, you were up against an even more insidious force than anything
                    else, and that is the drug business. You're not that far from Colombia and
                    you're on the route. Tell me about what the situation was.DODD: When I arrived
                    in 1997, all the estimates that I had been briefed on was that the drug
                    trafficking by land, sea and air had passed the danger point in Central America
                    and could easily transit by land, by sea, along both coasts of Costa Rica and
                    its neighbors. At that point in 1997 there had been preliminary discussions
                    about negotiating a bilateral ship rider agreement which would allow United
                    States Coast Guard and naval vessels to enter Costa Rica's territorial waters to
                    pursue fast boats from Colombia coming up both the Atlantic and the Pacific
                    coasts and getting into the rivers and estuaries of Costa Rica, unloading their
                    drug supplies to local drug dealers. I didn't fare very well initially. In fact,
                    when I first looked at polls that we had issued to be done, well over 75 or 76
                    percent of the Costa Rican population opposed any kind of ship rider agreement
                    that gave the United States the right to jointly pursue fast boats from Colombia
                    within their territorial waters. Lawyers, judges, members of the National
                    Assembly were all opposed to it. Then something very interesting happened. The
                    Minister of Public Security, a man name- I had enormous respect for him - and I
                    became good friends. I liked him. He was a nice person. He liked history, and we
                    used to trade stories together. But to get to my point, I give him really great
                    credit because he realized that the drug trafficking using Costa Rica as a
                    transit site was having a profound and significant impact on drug consumption by
                    Costa Rican college, high school, and grammar school kids. He did his own poll
                    and discovered it was more alarming. It had reached an epidemic stage. What
                    Lizano did - and our strategy was basically that I would not as U.S. ambassador
                    try to turn around public opinion in Costa Rica by saying they needed a treaty.
                    On our urging, he went to the National Assembly, briefed members of that body on
                    drug consumption in Costa Rica. He turned the issue around. We were able to
                    negotiate a ship rider agreement. We got the full and unqualified support of
                    members of the National Assembly and press. His ministry signed an agreement
                    allowing U.S. Coast Guard and Naval ships to come into those waters. What I had
                    to do was every time a U.S. Coast Guard ship approached the territorial waters
                    of Costa Rica following or pursuing a fast boat, I had to get on the phone, call
                    the Minister of Public Security and the President of the National Assembly to
                    get their approval. Now we were given four months to six months without
                    permission to go ahead approval to one of those vessels to pursue a joint
                    operation after a United States vessel entered territorial waters. I can tell
                    you, sadly, fighting drug interdiction was not my favorite subject by any means,
                    but I have to tell you we were able to reduce drastically the shipment by sea,
                    by fast boats from Colombia to Costa Rica's coastal waters. What was happening
                    was El Salvador, Nicaragua and Honduras were, when I left this year,
                    negotiating, in a process negotiating with those countries to sign ship rider
                    agreements, too. My hope is that all of these Central American countries will
                    combine these bilateral agreements with the United States into a regional
                    compact of some kind and have joint action, so once a fast boat, if it did
                    escape, left Costa Rica on either one of its coasts and went to Nicaragua's
                    coast, the Nicaraguans could pick up the operation and do so based on a
                    bilateral ship rider agreement or a joint drug interdiction operation. So,
                    again, not a very nice subject, but obviously we had to deal with it and
                    confront it. It was not easy for me because Costa Rica without armed forces,
                    without military services, any agreements, contracts or whatever with our Navy
                    or Coast Guard conjured up there the worry that it's territorial sovereignty
                    would be in jeopardy. In fact, today Costa Rica has a small academy at work
                    creating a professional coast guard prevent not only drug trafficking, but to
                    protect marine resources of Costa Rica. The tuna and the other resources of
                    Costa Rica's coast now have been taken or seized by this small but growing coast
                    guard force that can capture poachers and seize ships and sell them and make
                    money on it. So it's more than simply drug interdiction, although that was the
                    principal objective; it was also to help the country capture and control its
                    vast marine resources and protect them.</p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>Q: Since Costa Rica has become sort of a haven and has more potential and doesn't
                    have as much sort of underclass as some of these other places, was Costa Rica at
                    all a place of immigration, too, from other countries? Was that a problem?</p>
                <p>DODD: A tremendous issue and problem. The population of Costa Rica is about 3.5
                    million; it's under 4 million. There were estimated - I'll give you the high
                    number - 800,000 Nicaraguans who have fled to Costa Rica since the Sandinista
                    revolution, originally political refugees, now more economic refugees. The low
                    figure may be 200,000, but even that's substantial. They moved into Costa Rica
                    and basically have taken on what we would call for lack of a better word, the
                    menial jobs, housekeepers, construction workers. They have found work. But of
                    course it has put a heavy strain on the Costa Rican state-owned, state-managed
                    agencies such as the pension system, the welfare system, the hospitals, schools.
                    We built several hundred classrooms in communities where Nicaraguans have moved
                    and settled. That's, by the way, through the regional AID project. It was one of
                    the most successful programs I've seen in the post-Cold War era. We put up
                    literally hundreds of classrooms in these schools in areas where Nicaraguans
                    have moved most recently. The great drought now in Central America has posed the
                    possibility of another wave of immigrants from El Salvador and Nicaragua. Costa
                    Rica and, of course, become politically viable and contentious should they
                    accept more Nicaraguans and, of course, Costa Ricans have tried to get help from
                    the United States on dealing with this migration issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the other way? Were Costa Ricans going to the
                        UniteStates to immigrate or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: No. There are maybe two communities in the United States of Costa Ricans,
                    one in New Jersey and one in my state of Connecticut. But they are mostly
                    (Connecticut) professionals, doctors, lawyers and so forth, and in New Jersey
                    they are people who migrated for work and send remittances back home. Costa
                    Ricans who travel to the United States do so for education, learning English,
                    and simply vacation. And they come up in great numbers. So we don't have that
                    issue that other Central American countries have with the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the media there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>DODD: The media was tough, very tough. La Nacion was the major newspaper. My
                    relationships were always good, but they never covered as much as I thought they
                    should about the U.S. But the media was difficult, and I'll tell you why and
                    where. There were substantial numbers of expropriations of U.S. property during
                    the Contra period and in the post-Contra period, so I had to adjudicate those
                    and clean them up. But equally important was the great problem of squatters.
                    It's a problem for Costa Ricans, dealing with squatters. If you don't occupy and
                    effectively control your property and develop the land, squatters can come on,
                    and in different departments in Costa Rica, maybe in 30 days if you don't remove
                    them or if they move on your property and settle there in 30 days it becomes
                    their land for use and in some cases ownership. In other words, the laws are
                    simply a patchwork and a quilt of different regulations and statutes. When I
                    first arrived, an American, a man named Dalton, who owned property in southern
                    Costa Rica was killed, allegedly by squatters who came on his property when he
                    tried to remove them. So this was a contentious issue. Of course, I had to look
                    out for that family's interest to find out exactly what the causes were and to
                    get that case adjudicated. But the press was tough saying. I was wrong and the
                    squatters were right in several instances. So I had a lot of work to do. I had a
                    lot of explaining to do. It was not a friendly press to the United States, but
                    being a historian, Stu, at least I could understand why. It didn't take me very
                    long to figure out that the U.S. ambassador who had been a proconsul for so many
                    years was not really trying to meddle in their politics but was simply trying to
                    represent American citizens whose property had been taken over. So I had a
                    tactic. I developed a strategy for dealing with the press in the capitol city. I
                    made trips all over the country and deliberately tried to explain my position,
                    Washington's position, to local and regional press and radio and television
                    stations in the interior. I certainly got our story out a lot better. I just did
                    an “end run” on their national newspapers located in San Jose, went out to
                    explain really what I was going to do. I'm not saying it worked, but certainly
                    we did finally settle many of these cases, these squatters and one or two
                    cases.</p>
                <p>Q: You were there during a very embarrassing time for the United States, and that
                    was when your Georgetown colleague, President Clinton, got himself involved with
                    a nice little intern and there was impeachment. In the first place, this must
                    have been just bloody embarrassing, wasn't it?</p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>DODD: I always describe it as both difficult and embarrassing, but then again, in
                    Latin American countries historically they're culturally macho. Culture says,
                    well, men are about those kind of activities all the time. I think what puzzled
                    them the most was how the press in the United States could get so interested in
                    the private life of a person, and they treated it at that level: what's going on
                    up there and why is it creating so much interest and attention when a matter of
                    that kind is not in Costa Rica. Then on another level, yes, when you talked to
                    people, they, of course, wanted to know how and why the President of the United
                    States would get involved in this kind of activity. It obviously affected and
                    had a great impact on his moral suasion here as the chief executive. So I had to
                    deal with those on two levels. The government was not interested or concerned
                    about it. They simply said that's usually the business of most men anyway
                    worldwide, so why are you so worried about it in your press and public? But on
                    another level, if you talked to people, yes, they were concerned about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But even beyond that there's the impeachment. Looking back
                        on it,it's really amazing that the damn thing even got going.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Then, again, two levels on that I had to deal with. The impeachment process
                    for most Costa Ricans, government and public and private sectors, was, “Why
                    would you get into an impeachment process over the moral or personal conduct of
                    an individual, President of the United States or otherwise.” But second, they
                    did discuss editorially in the press, radio and television that our Constitution
                    can work and function; that is, there is a process of both Congress' inquiry and
                    the President's right to defend himself if he has to with his partisans, lawyers
                    and members of Congress. So they saw institutionally a process that was set into
                    motion without violence, not coup d'�tats and the like.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about with communications? You know, much has been
                        made about how people in Washington can pick up the phone and the Internet
                        and all that. Did you find as the ambassador this became a problem to be
                        either bypassed or to people beating down your shoulder?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>DODD: I describe it basically during my four years there, the opening and the
                    burgeoning of diplomacy. Non-governmental organizations, environmentalists for
                    example - there are so many - business sectors all conduct their mutual
                    interests outside of the operations of the United States embassy. In other
                    words, for a U.S. ambassador today in Costa Rica the conduct of diplomacy is
                    multifaceted. It's commercial diplomacy, it's environmental diplomacy, and it is
                    something that simply broadens, widens and deepens, of course, the issues that
                    you have to contend with as a chief of mission. It's no longer your despatches
                    or maybe e-mail alone to the Department of State reporting politically on what's
                    going on. But now you have to keep your eye on the new channels of communication
                    between government agencies and non-governmental groups. So the job has become
                    not impossible, it's just become more complex, and you have to be infinitely
                    more attuned to and careful and aware of what the trends are in the relations
                    growing out of the communications revolution.</p>
                <p>Q: One of the things that happens with other governmental agencies is they tend
                    to go towards regional places, and one always discovers that the most pleasant
                    capitals in an area seem to attract them. They don't go to where maybe their
                    problems are but where the living's easy. I would think that San Jose would have
                    meant that you ended up with quite a few centers of American governmental
                    activity.</p>
                <p>DODD: I did, but I also have to add another element: the schools are good, your
                    children are safer, your spouses, husbands or wives, can walk the streets and
                    feel more secure. Yes, the quality of your life is good. But in no way did the
                    attraction of San Jose to U.S. citizens and other departments or agencies of the
                    United States detract from their constant travel to other countries from the
                    base of a true democracy and stable South. For example, my agricultural attaches
                    were some of the most outstanding people I ever met. They not only educated me
                    on the importance of products and protecting them for the United States but also
                    here on the trends in Central American economic integration and problems. If my
                    agricultural attache, he called me on the phone and said, “Mr. Ambassador, I've
                    got a rice problem,” I usually had him upstairs to my office faster than sound
                    could travel, because a rice issue or potato crop problem in the United States,
                    that is, exporters from our country who couldn't get into Costa Rica while
                    potatoes rotted at the port, it could hurt other bilateral relations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the major exports and imports of Costa
                        Rica?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>DODD: Basically, as I mentioned here, there are two sectors: the high tech from
                    Intel, Abbott Laboratories, gave but bananas and coffee still remain a major
                    export. Coffee reaches selected markets in the United States, so do
                    non-traditional agricultural products, canned foods, for example. So the Costa
                    Ricans were always looking for that niche in the United States market. Our
                    exports to that area ran from onions, rice, potatoes, so we also exported
                    agricultural products, not simply high-tech industry. I had to deal basically in
                    several areas with high tariffs and an interesting cap that Costa Ricans placed
                    on the importation of many of our agricultural products, allowing Costa Rican
                    producers to have preferential treatment in the domestic market. So I was always
                    waiting for the cap to hit Costa Rican production and consumption to allow
                    United States exports in. But the biggest issue that I faced in dealing with
                    imports/exports basically was the Caribbean Basin Initiative of the Caribbean
                    countries and Central America to allow Costa Rican textiles into the United
                    States in December of last year. Finally the Caribbean Basin Initiative in
                    Congress was approved so that in several areas, specifically textiles, Costa
                    Rica could export to the United States using U.S. woolen products but allowing,
                    as I say, the production of textiles in Costa Rica to be exported to the U.S.
                    market.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved at all in the banana war that was
                        going on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, I did. The banana war basically was to allow U.S. companies like Dole
                    and Chiquita in Costa Rica to get into the European Community market. The
                    European Community, European Union, gave preferential treatment to former
                    British, French colonies, states, in the Caribbean to the European market over
                    Latin American exporters, like Costa Rica and Ecuador obviously banana exporters
                    in Costa Rica were excluded from the European market. It was a constant issue
                    and battle, and we, of course, pressed changes. Ultimately the World Trade
                    Organization was going to review that; they were going to review it this year,
                    2001. Some opening had finally been provided to allow a quota system to begin at
                    some time, I think, 2002, if I'm not mistaken.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about Cuba? How did our policy with Cuba play?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>DODD: Basically the Costa Ricans were, as I would describe it, watchful waiting.
                    I was constantly queried by the Foreign Minister and other cabinet officers as
                    to when United States policy would change with respect to the embargo. Of
                    course, I didn't know. Costa Rica is one of the few countries in Latin American
                    that does not have diplomatic relations with Cuba. They have a commercial
                    representative in Havana now, a consul there to handle commercial affairs. So
                    what Costa Ricans are doing basically is watching the United States carefully to
                    see for any changes. They don't want to be left alone in the Western Hemisphere
                    as the only country that does not have diplomatic relations with Cuba. There
                    were some cases, yes, of Cuban refugees coming to Costa Rica, seeking exile. On
                    several occasions we helped the Costa Ricans get them settled in. In fact,
                    there's a network of Cuban exiles in Costa Rica that generally have made their
                    settlement easy and comfortable, so that there aren't major waves difficulties
                    like the Mariel exodus, for example. Nothing approaches that in Costa Rica. So
                    I've described it as watchful waiting. They along with the United States are the
                    only countries in the Hemisphere that do not have relations - I'm not sure about
                    Argentina, but in any case the only one in Central America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't one of these things that people would twit you
                        on althe time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: All the time. Basically, how long will the embargo endure? When are you
                    going to change this policy? I had to do a lot of education explaining basically
                    that foreign policy is the projection of domestic interests, that essentially
                    the Cuban-American community, with Senator Helms and the Republicans in control
                    of the Congress, there could be no change. Yet Republicans from Iowa and Kansas,
                    concerned about their agricultural exports, wanted an opening. But during my
                    tenure basically Costa Ricans were essentially asking me, “When will this
                    change? Give us the inside track when it happens.” I said, “It's an open,
                    contentious domestic debate.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Catholic Church the predominant church there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: The Catholic Church is the predominant church although there are large and
                    substantial and growing evangelical Christian groups - it's substantial, Stu -
                    not only in Costa Rica but throughout Central America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And actually in Latin America.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>DODD: In Latin America in general, absolutely, in South America. The Catholic
                    Church in Costa Rica is strong. It's not just in its educational system and
                    parochial schools but even in the public school area. For example, in most of
                    your public schools you'll see crucifixes on the wall. Catholic religious
                    holidays are celebrated by the public school. The papal representative, the
                    representative of the Pope, is the dean of the diplomatic corps, but I
                    understand in most Latin American countries the dean of the diplomatic corps is
                    always the apostolic delegate. There may be exceptions; I'm certain Cuba would
                    be one, and there may be others. But the Catholic Church has a very, very
                    significant role in Costa Rica; there's not question about it. It's a voice on
                    social issues, economic issues. The Archbishop, Arieta, speaks out all the time
                    and will criticize the government on social issues. The Catholic Church has had
                    a good record in Costa Rica. It's always been essentially a pioneer in the areas
                    of focusing attention on the need for social justice and economic reform. This
                    goes back to the 1930s, and there are several very significant prelates who were
                    right in the forefront of the Christian Democratic Party, all coming out of
                    Rarem Novarum of the 1930s. Some of the significant labor legislation in Costa
                    Rica began in the 1940s under Rafael Calderon, who was a Christian Democrat. So,
                    again, the Church has had a good record on those issues. It has not been
                    identified as an ally of the rich, the landed coffee barons.</p>
                <p>Q: How about with all these missionaries, particularly the evangelical ones and
                    Bible society groups and all that? Were they kind of doing their thing, or did
                    you have problems?</p>
                <p>DODD: No, we did not have problems. They all functioned very well and actively
                    all over the country. What these evangelical groups do - and I think it made
                    them attractive - is that they deal basically with community needs, economic
                    needs. These evangelical groups will open up a hospital or a clinic or build a
                    school, and this is precisely what these communities need. The evangelicals
                    have. The evangelicals have given structure to communities that have not
                    received help and assistance from the government or directly from the Catholic
                    Church. There's another element. I always used to point out to colleagues.
                    Evangelicals give great emphasis on the Bible and reading the Bible and making
                    it germane and pertinent to what they have to do. In the more extreme cases, of
                    course, in Nicaragua and El Salvador the evangelical groups were associated with
                    people who were politically active in defending their barrios against Somozas
                    and others. In Costa Rica they deal more with community work, and this obviously
                    makes it very appealing.</p>
                <p>Q: How about Americans coming down, being this sort of island of tranquility?
                    Were you having Americans coming down and taking a modest pension and turning it
                    into living nicely there?</p>
                <p>DODD: Yes. Again, my estimates are risky. We don't have any figures on the number
                    of U.S. citizens there, but it may run to 35,000 Americans.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's significant.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: That is significant. Many of them, a substantial number of them, have
                    retired here, come down with pensions, started up businesses, small businesses,
                    and have been very successful at it. The American Chamber of Commerce - it's
                    called the American-Costa Rican Chamber of Commerce - that our pensioneers, cum
                    business people, have brought in Costa Rican counterparts in joint ventures. I
                    would say that the American community retired there, works there, lives there,
                    retired there are very, very active in local government. I used to travel around
                    and bring my consular officers with me to see them, an American association in
                    different parts of the country, because they know a lot of what's going on in
                    the community. They are involved in the development of several communities in
                    Costa Rica.</p>
                <p>Q: A question I forgot to ask: With the drug traffic, was drug corruption, which
                    is the real poison of this whole thing - with people getting addicted to drugs,
                    it's a tragedy, but almost greater is the power of money that corrupts things -
                    was this showing its head?</p>
                <p>DODD: No, it did not. We simply did not have a problem of drug barons appearing
                    in Costa Rica. The problem in Costa Rica was transit, getting it to the bigger
                    and more lucrative markets north, Guatemala, Mexico and, of course, the United
                    States; and second, it was the growing domestic consumption in Costa Rica. Now
                    you're looking down a road. I don't know, we don't know, the answer to that,
                    whether it will create a culture of drug barons, but certainly not in Costa
                    Rica. Corruption in Costa Rica was minimal and low, low level but not in any
                    case alarming. Although through our public diplomacy, public affairs section, we
                    worked hard with the judiciary in anti-corruption efforts, at least creating
                    safeguards to prevent this kind of thing, such as money laundering. While I
                    suspect it was going on, it was an area that the embassy was just beginning to
                    look at with the Treasury Department, for example.</p>
                <p>Q: You mentioned when you arrived that Costa Rica was on the Security Council.
                    I'm told this is the equivalent to an earthquake, and what you want to do if
                    you're in a small country, for God's sake, keep them off the Security Council -
                    talking about for the ambassadors.</p>
                <p>DODD: Oh, there's no question: I was a very busy person the first year I was
                    there. As you can well imagine, every issue that came up on the U.N., whatever
                    it was, sanctions against Iraq, yes. I lost count of the number of demarches I
                    had to get down to the Foreign Ministry. Frankly, I was delighted when they got
                    off and got back down to local business. Then I could obviously deal more
                    comfortably with our bilateral issues.</p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>But your question points something out that's really very significant, Stu, and
                    that is that a country like Costa Rica, a small country, today in the world of
                    multipower-centered interest, small countries can turn us down and turn us aside
                    and say, “We'll go elsewhere.” In other words, if Costa Rica turned me down or
                    said they were not going to support us on a vote, in the Security Council, for
                    example, I couldn't threaten reprisals. Because a country like Costa Rica has
                    access to many different resources today for financial help and support. But the
                    point is you can't take even the smallest country in the world today for
                    granted. The Cold War is over. They don't need us as much as they did
                    before.</p>
                <p>Q: One of the great movements going on today is - I don't know what you want to
                    call it - multinationalism. We're having protests in the streets about
                    international market and all that. From the point of view of the Costa Ricans,
                    what was their feeling towards this?</p>
                <p>DODD: Well, I'll tell you: a mix, and I should say at different levels. An effort
                    on the part of the present government, Miguel Angel Rodriguez Echeverria, to
                    create concessions, another word for privatization of the telecommunications
                    industry, was approved by the National Assembly. But as soon as the provisions
                    of that privatization of the telecommunications was proposed and made public,
                    street demonstrations occurred, not riots but demonstrations, and the bill was
                    withdrawn. My point is that efforts to privatize the state-owned, state-managed
                    entities and make them competitive worldwide has created immediate negative
                    reactions in Costa Rica. But at the same time for the educated of Costa Rica, if
                    you talk to most people, they see the need for updating, modernizing their
                    telecommunications industry. The whole gamut of government operations have to
                    become competitive, and to do so they've got to be placed in the arena of
                    competitive free markets. But again, like all good politicians, the leaders of
                    the National Liberation Party, the center left party, have been a bit cautious
                    because their constituency, a working class, are more critical of privatization
                    and more cautious in their approach to opening their markets to a global free
                    market system. So, interesting, a small country, politically stable, socially
                    stable, has tried to deal with the fissures that have emerged in their society
                    as the country edges into a global market. It's small; it can't compete in most
                    of its exports, bananas, coffee, and so forth, so it's got to move cautiously
                    and very carefully. It's not easy to simply say, “Come in and buy whatever you
                    want or sell whatever you want,” because obviously it's affected deeply and very
                    quickly by world price changes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is it a member of the World Trade Organization?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But does that make a difference...?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>DODD: Not really, because simply the WTO, the World Trade Organization, is only
                    just beginning to function. What Costa Rica has really preferred to do is to
                    deal with the United States directly on these issues of finding a niche in the
                    United States market - put very directly, to try to get into NAFTA or to become
                    really the beneficiary of Mexico's membership in NAFTA. So Costa Rica is doing
                    this: it's negotiating and concluding free trade agreements, bilateral free
                    trade agreements, with Mexico, Chile, the Dominican Republic. It is trying to
                    get into the world market by selecting countries they can be reasonably assured
                    of, that their exports will sell and sell competitively but at a good price.</p>
                <p>Q: We mentioned at the end of the last interview about your spouse. You said,
                    “Let's talk about that in Costa Rica.” We're interested here in how people in
                    American foreign affairs work as a team, and they often do.</p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, and we did. Molly basically had been teaching school, high school,
                    students for several years here in the District of Columbia in an area called
                    social justice and had a regular program for bringing her students into the
                    District of Columbia, into the soup kitchens, homeless shelters, dealt with
                    street children. I said to her before we got down there, “Is this something that
                    you would be interested in doing, working with charitable organizations, state
                    or private, in Costa Rica?” and she did, working very closely with many
                    different organizations, both state and private, in Costa Rica dealing with
                    intercity youngsters, specifically youngsters. That was her major project. In so
                    doing, she organized, was able to organize successfully, programs for several
                    orphanages for young girls, mostly abused children. This was her major work, and
                    on a volunteer basis she got a great deal of help from people in the U.S.
                    embassy, but also Costa Rican people helped her in this area. She worked on
                    social justice issues as she did at home, and I think she was immensely
                    successful. Molly arrived speaking no Spanish. She had a working knowledge of
                    the language and worked at it. I think, like so many experiences you have, the
                    very fact that she showed an interest and took classes and tried to use the
                    language, that was flattering and I think it conveyed the impression that, if
                    you're learning a language, you must be interested in the culture you're living
                    in at the time. She was immensely successful, I think for that reason.</p>
                <p>Q: In the Latin American context, what about voluntary organizations? These are
                    the guts of the American system. We all use volunteers, including in our program
                    right here; we have a volunteer corps and all this. What about what you were
                    seeing in Latin America, obviously in Costa Rica but other places?</p>
                <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                <p>DODD: Volunteerism is simply not a popular way in which communities, local and
                    national, play a role in these countries. Traditionally it has never been that
                    way. The state welfare system really dominated the area of dealing with problems
                    laid outside basically what would be called the private sector initiative. It is
                    changing somewhat, but my wife found it particularly difficult to organize Costa
                    Ricans in the area of providing time, money, whatever assistance unless these
                    Costa Ricans had lived or worked or studied in the United States. So what she
                    did basically was shift in the direction of getting help from Costa Rican
                    citizens who had not necessarily been volunteers in the United States but at
                    least were familiar with it. But overall, to answer your question, no, volunteer
                    organizations are not prevalent, and I don't see any sign of it changing except
                    maybe what influence we may have on Costa Ricans who come here to live and work
                    and do go back home and say, “Yes, this is important. In lieu of government
                    assistance, we have to do something.” But I can't say honestly that I saw any
                    significant change in this area in Costa Rica other than basically the
                    initiative of private individuals like my wife.</p>
                <p>Q: What was your impression of the Costa Rican diplomatic service, particularly
                    their representation in Washington? Do you feel there was a good communications
                    channel between the foreign ministry and the embassy? What was going on?</p>
                <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                <p>DODD: I would describe it unqualifyingly: the Costa Rican foreign ministry deals
                    with Washington and the embassy there in a very open and effective way. I
                    preferred working with the Costa Rican foreign service professionals. During the
                    President Rodriguez administration his foreign minister, Roberto Rojas, who was
                    a businessman, has made a special effort in recruiting, training, and creating
                    really a professional foreign service there, and only during my time did this
                    happen, or at least any noticeable development in that area. Number two, I also
                    learned - and I noticed that this was a major change - that the Costa Rican
                    embassy here in Washington, whether represented by a professional ambassador or
                    a political appointee, certainly knows how to operate in Washington, and maybe a
                    little better than its neighbors - I can't make a judgment there. For example,
                    the Costa Rican embassy during my four years always worked very closely with the
                    U.S. Congress, sometimes to our annoyance. Because the Costa Rican embassy would
                    invite members of the U.S. House of Representative to Costa Rica and we didn't
                    know about it. The Department of State didn't know about it. And it was very
                    annoying, I can assure you, to run into a Congressman walking around Costa Rica
                    in a souvenir shop. He was down there not just to play golf but on business, to
                    learn more about the drug war, interdiction, or to look at a land expropriation
                    case. Those were matters that were my responsibility. I should have known about
                    it. So I'm revealing here a complaint that they were very good at it. But
                    sometimes I think they stepped over the line. Of course, I had to know, the
                    embassy had to know, if a member of Congress went to Costa Rica on a matter that
                    we were dealing with - if it was to go down to play golf, that was their
                    business, which they did do. The Costa Rican embassy is very good at that. They
                    get their message out, and they didn't wait for the U.S. embassy down there to
                    help them, and sometimes our messages were at cross-purposes. In so doing, as I
                    say, there were sticky times, but I guess you might say they're just getting
                    better at what they do. You can't blame them. That's what the ambassador's job
                    is up here, just to get his message out, but it sometimes gave me
                    heartaches.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask this. You had leader grants and all that. Did
                        yoinform the Costa Rican embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, as a matter of fact, we did. I know it works both ways. We worked very
                    carefully with them. But I must say too that the staff here, the DCM, whose name
                    I forget now at the moment, were very good people and I worked very well with
                    them. They were first class, as a matter of fact.</p>
                <p>Q: Both at the university and often in the foreign ministries in Latin America -
                    we've talked about this before - if you're going to be an anti-American, be a
                    Marxist. You get it at the university, and those that don't become captives
                    immediately on graduation end up in the foreign ministry; and it's carrying out
                    a sort of residual anti-Americanism. Did you find any of that?</p>
                <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                <p>DODD: I honestly didn't. Most of the anti-Americanism I found - as you say,
                    residual - I always described as more historic. I was always reminded that
                    William Walker invaded Nicaragua and Costa Rica. Well, I can live with that. In
                    other words, as an ambassador there I didn't run into any opposition to United
                    States' policies except maybe the privatization, the competitive global market,
                    but I said that's not a product of our doing. This is what's happened in the
                    world. So very honestly I felt going out to the universities - and I did a lot -
                    I said, “What are your complaints?” I sometimes had to go look for them. That
                    was one of them, as I say, the competitive world market, but I said, “I can't
                    control that.” The U.S. government can't control that. It's the world today. But
                    I was, of course, reminded of U.S. intervention in the Dominican Republic and
                    Panama, and I said it was Cold War diplomacy. I said, “Yes, we made mistakes. We
                    intervened and then we forgot about you. It was a mistake. We should have had a
                    more consistent kind of relationship with you.” I said, “I think that was a
                    fault,” and I was very open about it and willing to discuss it. But I also said
                    that much of our foreign policy over the years was a product of domestic
                    pressure groups. We weren't always of one mind in things that we did in Latin
                    America or didn't do, but I also sometimes was pointed in my references to the
                    fact that Latin Americans have got to do more too to give direction and purposes
                    to what it wants and it's got to make sacrifices and not wait for what we do all
                    the time and then react to it. But honestly, Stu, I think in retrospect being an
                    academician really gave me a distinct advantage in these two posts, because
                    academicians in Latin America “go to the head of the line.” They just do,
                    whether you're a Foreign Service representative or a business person, whatever.
                    If you have academic credentials and you've been a teacher, you have some
                    credibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did find though in Uruguay, if I recall, you had
                        problems witthe university...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I didn't get into the national public university. I was tolsimply not to
                    go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But in Costa Rica...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: I went to the University of Costa Rica, the Universite Nacionale, maybe two
                    or three times a month. I gave a lecture, or there was always something out
                    there to do or go to, or maybe I had the president of the university at the
                    residence for lunch and we had different projects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it was a completely different atmosphere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Entirely different.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I take it then there wasn't this residual Marxist...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                <p>DODD: There was some but...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You hope for that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0077" n="Page0077"/>
                <p>DODD: Sure, you want some criticism, of course, you do, debate, discussion - it's
                    fun - but not this contentious, confrontational thing. I didn't want to go out
                    to the university in Uruguay and create a riot for something that we had done 25
                    years ago. It just was not necessary. I didn't need that; the embassy didn't
                    need that. There's one area - if I may just take the initiative - I haven't
                    discussed with you, and that's environmental diplomacy in Costa Rica. It's a
                    major subject, and I'd hate to let it go by. When I became chief of mission in
                    Costa Rica in '97, the Department of State created what we called environmental
                    hubs. There were, I think six or seven worldwide. The U.S. embassy in Costa Rica
                    was the hub for Latin America. I think subsequently now another one has been
                    created in Brazil - I'm not certain. But it was a major, major opening dealing
                    with environmental issues in Costa Rica, which is of paramount interest to them.
                    I've described it here as environmental diplomacy. We had to work at the
                    international level with Costa Ricans on environmental issues, global warming,
                    carbon dioxide emissions and so on. I just want to reflect on several of these
                    things. We dealt with environmental issues in Costa Rica and the hub - dealt
                    with Central American and the Caribbean - as much for self-interest, enlightened
                    self-interest. For example, fires in Guatemala and Belize affect the crop
                    growers in Florida, Louisiana and Mississippi. My point is to protect U.S.
                    industry through better environmental conditions abroad. Pollution over fishing
                    in the Caribbean off the Central American coast in Central American waters
                    affected U.S. fishing interests in coastal states like Florida and Louisiana. In
                    other words, I looked at environmental issues as much for U.S. interests as I
                    did for Costa Rican interests. We helped them mostly working with
                    non-governmental organizations. So infertile fields, polluted areas, river
                    streams create pressures for Central Americans to come to the United States. In
                    other words, if working conditions or economic conditions aren't good, they're
                    going to leave and create pressures here. It's enlightened self interest
                    basically, what we touched on on a very important issue with Costa Ricans,
                    because we dealt with environmental issues globally, regionally - in other
                    words, Central America and the Caribbean - and directly with Costa Rica. The
                    embassy set up seminars every month at the residence. We invited representatives
                    of environmental organizations in Costa Rica, sometimes the rest of Central
                    America, to simply discuss amongst themselves some of the key environmental
                    issues. I didn't go in with a blueprint to tell Costa Ricans how to deal with
                    environmental issues, but when the opportunity came, of course, we explained
                    what our position was on an issue or maybe how we could be helpful on an issue.
                    But it was basically to create a forum to get environmental groups within Costa
                    Rica, Central America and the Caribbean to meet and talk and to discuss these
                    issues. It was truly one of the most interesting parts of my assignment there. I
                    spent a quarter to half my time on it, along with drug issues. The Biodiversity
                    Institute dealt with the environment. The pharmaceutical companies in the United
                    States like Abbott Laboratories looked at plant life for future work on
                    medicines, drugs for health purposes. It was a fascinating part of my job. Larry
                    Gumbiner was the hub environmental officer there, the first one there, a
                    splendid human being. He did a first-rate job and had a great staff. Thinking
                    back now, it was one of the most interesting parts of my assignment.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0078" n="Page0078"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's look at Costa Rica. What were they doing in this
                        regard?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Basically in this area they created essentially one of the most developed,
                    highly sophisticated national park systems in the Western Hemisphere (maybe the
                    world). They claim - and I think the percentage is fairly accurate - about 26
                    percent of their land mass, which is about the size of West Virginia, is in
                    national parks. They were especially interested in preserving those parks and
                    extending the number of national parks by working with neighbors in creating
                    what is called a meso-American corridor, that runs through Central America, to
                    create not just park lands but to protect the flora and fauna that can be so
                    valuable, absorbing carbon dioxide emissions. So the country was really at the
                    forefront, I would say, in Central America and the Caribbean.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about industries they already had? Were they pretty
                        gooabout pollution controls?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes, fairly good, certainly not vehicular emissions in Costa Rica. they
                    were working on that when I left. But with certain U.S. companies like Intel,
                    Abbott Laboratories, Proctor &amp; Gamble, any one of the U.S. corporations who
                    come to Costa Rica, environmental issues are uppermost in their planning. Then
                    taking it on a regional but a global level, the Under Secretary of State for
                    Global Affairs, Timothy Wirth, played a very important role in helping me get
                    these issues here right on the forefront, taking Costa Rica as a model on
                    environmental and global affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did Costa Rica deal with the Nicaraguan government and
                        thPanamanian government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Let me take each one. The Costa Rican-Nicaraguan relations were contentious
                    on several levels. I mentioned one just a while ago, the Nicaraguan refugee
                    issue. Costa Rican-Nicaraguan relations deteriorated, not to the point where
                    ambassadors were recalled. The San Juan River, which is the boundary between the
                    northern boundary for Costa Rica and the southern boundary for Nicaragua, became
                    a major bone of contention. The San Juan River is under the sovereignty of
                    Nicaragua. It is not a river at a certain point which divides the boundaries of
                    these two countries. Costa Rica wants to allow its security forces to patrol the
                    rivers. Nicaragua has respected this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's sort of like the Potomac, which the District has up
                        to thVirginia shoreline...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: And this is correct in the sense with Nicaragua.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a pain in the ass.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0079" n="Page0079"/>
                <p>DODD: It's just a nuisance, because what happened was during my time [was that]
                    Costa Rican national security forces needed to use the river to visit Costa
                    Rican towns along the estuary and, in so doing, on several occasions the
                    Nicaraguan security forces stopped the Costa Ricans from using the river. Under
                    the Treaty of 1888, Nicaragua was recognized as having sovereignty over the
                    river but subsequently had given Costa Rica the right to use the river for
                    security purposes. So it became very, very, very contentious. And a debt issue
                    also was on the agenda here, the Nicaraguan debt to Costa Rica ran somewhere
                    about 300 to 400 million dollars. The Costa Ricans wanted that paid off. But the
                    Nicaraguans wanted debt forgiveness and so forth. Relations were not good, but
                    not to the breaking point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it sort of a personality thing, too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: As a matter of fact, the Foreign Minister of Costa Rica, Roberto Rojas, was
                    a very good friend of the Nicaraguan Foreign Minister. On the contrary, Lino
                    Gutierrez, who is now a deputy assistant secretary of state, knows that area
                    better than I do. When I was brooding over this conflict, said, “Tom, stop
                    worrying about it. Central Americans know each better than you or I will ever
                    understand them,” and I think he was right. So they knew each other. They may
                    not have gotten along all the time, but they could talk to each other a lot
                    better and more effectively that I could. But relations were not good. They were
                    testy but not at the breaking point. Then looking south, relations with Panama
                    were good. But I always explained that there were really no issues, border
                    issues, that were irritants. Panama's relations usually run east and west, of
                    course, with Washington but not contentious with Nicaragua, except the drug
                    issue, but not contentious. We always were trying to find ways to cooperate with
                    the Panamanians on drug issues in the overland transit route.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Costa Rica get any benefit by being on both coasts,
                        thPacific-Caribbean thing, or not? Does it make much of a difference?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0080" n="Page0080"/>
                <p>DODD: There are several things, I suppose, you could raise. The east coast of
                    Costa Rica is black; it's African Costa Rica, and these people are of West
                    Indian origin. They came there to build the Panama railroad and settled there,
                    but also they helped build Costa Rican railroad too, in the late 19th century.
                    Their connection is to the Caribbean, black Caribbean, and to some extent the
                    United States. But that area of the east coast needs economic development. Lim�n
                    is the major port for imports and exports to Costa Rica, but only on the
                    planning stage have efforts been made to build a port. It's a major tourist
                    attraction. At least that's where the tourist boats go to. On the west coast,
                    the Marriott Corporation, for example has a resort on the west coast. There are
                    several new hotels opening up along there for U.S. tourists, moved from Mexico,
                    high crime, costs, have moved now to the Costa Rican west coast. So in that
                    sense, yes, you might talk about the east and west coast with advantages but
                    more with different characteristics and looking in different directions. To talk
                    about the west coast and Asian trade, no, that would be pushing the issue,
                    that's not a factor; or east coast trade, the Afro Costa Rican with the West
                    Indies, no, that's pushing the issue, because tourism and commercial interests
                    are tied to the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Does Mexico play any role in this area, the colossus to
                        the neanorth?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Mexico plays a major role in Central America, it has historically. But very
                    specifically during my tenure, Mexico played a major role: Taking the cultural
                    assumptions that, of course, Mexico has with the area, language and the
                    Indo-American culture, but Mexico being a member of NAFTA is Central America's
                    hope for getting into free trade agreements or maybe getting into NAFTA so
                    countries like Costa Rica and what is called the northern tier of Central
                    America, Guatemala, Honduras, and El Salvador, have signed free trade agreements
                    with Mexico. Mexico is sometimes referred to as the colossus of the north but
                    more now in the context of being really the friendly neighbor that may open the
                    possibility of getting access to the North American Free Trade Agreement. But
                    Mexico matters. The Mexican ambassador in Costa Rica is a major player in
                    diplomatic circles, much more so, for example, than the Brazilian or the
                    Argentinean or Chilean diplomats.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is there anything we haven't covered?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0081" n="Page0081"/>
                <p>DODD: I mentioned the environmental issues because I wanted to get that up-front
                    for you, because not to talk about 25 percent of my work there would be a gross
                    omission on my part. But I would say really the area of foreign policy that was
                    of great interest to us was the issue of human rights. Costa Rica was always the
                    mediator, the arbiter of international disputes. With no armed forces it's posed
                    some problems, as I mentioned, in the ship rider agreement. But the biggest
                    challenge really for me and the embassy was to help Costa Rica redefine the word
                    'security' and to help Costa Rica modernize its security forces. Sixty percent
                    of the police consisted of political appointees. You have to professionalize
                    this institution with better pay and training. We were trying to work with them
                    in modernizing their state structure. I'm not saying we're pushing them to
                    overturn policies dealing with the role of the state in the society but trying
                    to help bring them up to the 21st century on security issues, redefining
                    security issues. It's not the Soviet Union anymore; it's drug consumption and
                    it's street crime. These are the things that are of concern to them and to us.
                    Domestic issues in Costa Rica and the U.S., like so much in the Western
                    Hemisphere, are converging. We all have the same problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you left, as ambassadors do, after four years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A good four years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DODD: They were truly, I think, the best years of my life. As I mentioned several
                    weeks ago in my interview with you, when one of my students said, “Why doesn't
                    he put his money where his mouth is?” I felt that I had done something that I
                    was somewhat hesitant to do eight years ago, but I found that I could do it. I
                    worked with some wonderful career people, and we got some things done. I put
                    teaching Latin American history to the test!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Great. Well, I think we'll stop at this point.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
