<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000146">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Donald S. Brown </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Foreign Assistance Series</p>
                <p>DONALD S. BROWN</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: W. Haven North </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: December 4, 1996</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>(Note: This Oral History combines the text written by Don Brown in advance of the
                    interview. The text from the interview provides a supplement to the written text
                    and is incorporated in various sections of the overall text.)</p>
                <p>Early years and education</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You served with AID for how many years, Don?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I was with AID for a little over thirty years. I retired from AID in 1983
                    and went on from there to the United Nations and IFAD (International Fund for
                    Agricultural Development).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's start off with a description of where you grew up
                        and your early education with the emphasis how you got interested in
                        international affairs and international development.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I was brought up in Garden City on Long Island, New York. I had two older
                    brothers. The oldest, Dean Brown, later being involved in the diplomatic
                    services and the middle brother, Bob, having had a lot of interest in foreign
                    affairs although his work in that area was largely in social research and the
                    like.</p>
                <p>I graduated from Garden City High School as did both of my brothers. Somebody had
                    suggested that I should be an engineer as my father had been so I went to
                    Cornell for a year. But I must say I didn't do very well because my math was
                    lousy. I ended up on probation and I decided that I had better go off and think
                    about what I wanted to do with myself. I joined the army for two years. I was
                    lucky enough to get into Officer Candidate School and spent the last year of my
                    time in the military as a Second Lieutenant in the infantry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you overseas?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>BROWN: Always in the United States. I was fortunate to be in that period in
                    between wars in which the United States was involved so there was no real need
                    to be overseas. It was clear to me as I thought about things that I liked the
                    concept of doing something with social benefits, whatever that might mean. I
                    also needed to look for a school that thought in those terms and I ended up
                    choosing Antioch College because it has a very open system and liberal concepts,
                    as well as its work-study program. I studied economics and labor relations with
                    the thought of going into some form of work in labor relations. And my work
                    periods at Antioch were related to that.</p>
                <p>However, at the end of school, Mark Gordon, who was then the executive director
                    of the Technical Cooperation Administration-Point 4, and who had been recruiting
                    Antioch students for part time work activities in Point 4, met me and after some
                    long conversations asked if I would join him when he was going out to become the
                    first Director of the Point 4 program in Ethiopia. That sounded interesting
                    although I didn't know too much about it, but I had felt very positive about
                    Truman and his policies including his concepts of aid programs and particularly
                    the Point 4 program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you had any work-study programs at TCA before that or
                        was this the first time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: No. I had never had a work-study program at TCA, although I did a
                    work-study program with MSA for a period of time where I worked with Joe
                    Mintzes, with whom I worked many years later in Zaire.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of work were you doing then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I was just doing some very simple research work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get connected with the Foreign Aid Program
                        from Antioch? Why that as opposed to something else?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>BROWN: Well, as I say, Mark was interviewing people for work-study programs in
                    TCA for 2-3 month periods. In that process, the fellow that runs the study
                    program from the college, knowing I was graduating, made it a point to bring
                    Mark and I together. We hit it off very well. And Mark needed a junior officer
                    to go with him. That was all very well and we thought we would welcome such an
                    assignment. But then we discovered that because my wife was not yet an American
                    citizen I was not allowed to take a Foreign Service assignment. Instead, I took
                    the junior management test, passed it and managed to come in as an intern into
                    the Washington offices of Point 4, working in part on back-stopping to the
                    Ethiopia program. So, why did I do this? Because, as I say, I had an interest in
                    humanitarian issues without having very much direction and I realized that my
                    studies in economics and labor relations were useful in some respects and my
                    Antioch studies gave me a broad enough background. And Antioch was the kind of
                    school that gave you a broad background. So, that is how I got started.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your brother in Foreign Service then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes. He was a Foreign Service Officer. He had returned from the Second
                    World War and finished up his college and went directly into Foreign Service at
                    that point. He was on his first major assignment in the Congo...Zaire today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did talking with him stimulate your interest,?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Oh yes. Of course. There was some interest that flowed from that. I think
                    it was a range of forces and to be perfectly frank when Mark Gordon talked to me
                    and told me about Ethiopia, I looked it up on the map to make sure where it
                    was... I thought I knew. And I saw it was on the other side of France and I
                    thought if I could go there then Micheline could come with me and see her
                    family. It was incidental, but a nice thought.</p>
                <p>Introductory assignment with TCA 1952-1954</p>
                <p>I joined TCA in 1952 for an initial Washington assignment. I worked with Cedric
                    Seager, Ed Felder and Adele Boke largely in support of this new Ethiopia
                    program. While much of what I did was relatively routine operational work, I did
                    become directly involved in negotiations with Oklahoma State University in what
                    would become an important agricultural education project in Ethiopia, one which
                    proved over time to have a major impact on agricultural training there. I was
                    also pleased that part of my functions indirectly involved the recruitment of
                    Haven North, one of the stars of US economic development programs.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>During this period I deeply appreciated the action of my supervisors when they
                    fought to get me my first promotion well ahead of normal time and then when they
                    sponsored me to take part in a summer-long State Department seminar involving
                    about 20 officers from State, Defense, CIA and myself at the American University
                    of Beirut (AUB) followed by brief visits to several Near Eastern countries.
                    Micheline was able to join me during the time in Beirut. This was our first real
                    exposure to the Middle East and we began a life-long interest in the region and
                    appreciation of Arab culture. At AUB we were thoroughly exposed to the deep
                    concern felt in the Arab world by the establishment of the state of Israel and
                    the strong concern about the future of Palestinian refugees. This same concern
                    was repeated in each of the Arab countries which we visited thereafter - and, of
                    course, in Tel Aviv we heard equally strong Israeli views on the legitimacy of
                    this new State. It became clear to us that the region was facing deeply
                    antagonistic cultures and states and that establishing enduring peace would not
                    be easily achieved - and those antagonisms have in fact led to continuing
                    conflicts which have not yet been overcome.</p>
                <p>After two years in Washington, Cedric Seager arranged for me to have an
                    assignment in Iran.</p>
                <p>First overseas assignment in USOM/Iran 1954-1956</p>
                <p>We found Iran to be a fascinating first field assignment. We arrived shortly
                    after Shah Reza Pahlavi had been restored to power following a CIA organized
                    coup d'etat which overthrew the Mossadegh government - a regime then considered
                    dangerous to Western petroleum interests. It was considered an important part of
                    American policy to support Iranian development efforts to demonstrate the
                    validity of the Pahlavi regime. As a result, the Point 4 (TCA) Mission was
                    enormous, over 200 Americans, 10 field posts, a relatively large budget, and
                    strong influence on governmental developmental (and, indirectly, political)
                    policy.</p>
                <p>In the first year I worked as Special Assistant to Director Bill Warne, a
                    wonderful, thoughtful, very politically attuned activist, a former Director of
                    the Bureau of Reclamation. A close colleague and friend, also a Special
                    Assistant to Warne, was Reza Ansari, who much later became Prime Minister of
                    Iran. We lived an often contradictory and fascinating life - as the youngest and
                    most junior staff member, my wife and I were relatively free to wander around
                    Tehran and to meet a wide variety of working and middle class Iranians. At the
                    same time, because of my close working relation to Warne, we were often invited
                    to dinners and receptions given by high level Iranian officials. It was not
                    unusual to spend a day poking around nooks and crannies of Tehran and then that
                    night go to a gala dinner at the home of the Minister of Planning or the
                    Minister of Court. It was a heady mixture.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>We also had freedom to travel extensively-privately and on USOM business, often
                    accompanying Bill Warne. When he first asked me to go on a trip, he recalled his
                    own first trip with a senior, one-armed Bureau of Reclamation official. When
                    Warne asked that official what should be his functions, the official pointed to
                    his missing arm and said “carry my bags”. In a sense, that was my role working
                    with Warne-seldom directly involved in decision making, I was working so closely
                    with him and his immediate associates that I had a wonderful chance to see how
                    that process was carried out. I would note that Micheline and I had the great
                    pleasure of seeing the Warnes again many years later when he was in Egypt on an
                    assignment with the International Executive Service Corps.</p>
                <p>When I first arrived in Iran, Lucy Adams was head of the Isfahan field office.
                    Her idea of a vacation was to accompany Isfahan tribal groups on their annual
                    trek from the mountains to the plains. After my first year, Lucy became Program
                    Officer and asked me to join her there. This gave me good experience in watching
                    the program formulation process. Again my work was essentially routine as such,
                    although I did have an important role in better organizing and chronicling what
                    was done as part of the historical record. However, I was engaged in all the key
                    meetings which Lucy chaired or attended. It was a wonderful working with someone
                    like Lucy with her dynamism, charm and gracious manners.</p>
                <p>Still, some of the senior staff were rather fuddy-duddy. A sign of this was the
                    comment by one senior mission official who objected to the lack of clarity in
                    dinner invitations calling for informal dress - he noted that things were
                    clearer when he was young, when informal meant black tie.</p>
                <p>It was clear from our range of contacts with Iranians that Islam-Shiite
                    Islam-played an important part in the lives of many. It was also obvious that
                    poverty and misery were wide spread. At the same time, however, the Shah and his
                    government initiated extensive land reform measures which were bringing
                    significant improvements to at least some small farmers and these efforts were
                    firmly supported by the Point 4 Program. However, they raised strong antipathy
                    among the clergy and the landholding class-the clergy, since some religious
                    lands were affected. I must admit, however, that, despite what had already
                    happened in the Mossadegh period, we did not foresee the kind of changes which
                    took place in Iran several years later-though on reflection they were not
                    totally surprising.</p>
                <p>Certainly, in the short run, the TCA program achieved many of its prime
                    objectives-a certain amount of political stability, the beginning of important
                    agricultural changes, a vast program of education and training, including
                    sending thousands of Iranians to the US for training. But perhaps it laid some
                    of the seeds of destruction of the Pahlavi regime by supporting change which was
                    imposed and sudden, by the exposure of thousands of Iranian students to
                    democratic regimes which contrasted sharply with that of the Shah, and by an
                    overly close association between the US and Iran-an association which became
                    even closer in the decades which followed.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>A great event during our stay in Tehran was the birth of our first son- Alain
                    Bahram Brown-whose middle name derived from a close friend who later became
                    Minister of Health, Bahram Farmanfarmayan.</p>
                <p>While life in Tehran was fascinating in many ways for the reasons already
                    mentioned, it was not always easy. Water was a major problem. There was no
                    central water supply and the bulk of our water was delivered by “jube”-the open
                    gutter through which water poured down from the mountains and then was
                    distributed throughout the city. While we were better off than many, living at a
                    higher point than much of the city, we carried the smell of Iranian jube water
                    in our linen and clothes for a long time thereafter. It is maddening when you
                    have to boil all water, even the baby's bath water. But the fascination of
                    Tehran outweighed the difficulties for both Micheline and I.</p>
                <p>Transfer to USOM/Libya program office - 1956-1958</p>
                <p>Four years after he had brought me into the organization as a Junior Management
                    Intern, I finally got to work with Marc Gordon who had moved on to be Director
                    in Libya. At that time, Libya was the quiet kingdom of Idris, years before the
                    Qadhafi revolution and turmoil.</p>
                <p>While the USOM program was an active and interesting one, Libya was in many ways
                    a disappointment after the excitement of Iran. The Government was largely
                    without resources (this was the pre-oil period when the largest export was scrap
                    metal left over from World War II) and trained staff. Most people we dealt with
                    lacked the worldliness of many of the Iranians we had known. Women in particular
                    had few educational opportunities and possibilities of meaningful exchange with
                    them (even by Micheline and other caring wives) was difficult. Tripoli was a
                    pleasant but unexciting and plain city and Cyrenaica was little different.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, there were exceptionally well preserved Roman, Phoenician and
                    Greek ruins scattered along the coastal areas and these made for interesting
                    outings. Housing was certainly adequate if simple and the beaches were a
                    pleasure.</p>
                <p>There were really two US aid programs going on. One, the USOM, ran a modest range
                    of rather useful programs, with heavy emphasis on training and on water
                    resources. I have been pleased over the years to meet many very able Libyans who
                    participated in USOM educational programs, both in Libya itself and in the US
                    Major contributions to the agricultural education system endure to this day.
                    Heavy emphasis on water conservation techniques still mark Libyan agricultural
                    programs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In your discussion of the program in Libya, you made a
                        comment about major contributions in agricultural education and so on. Could
                        you elaborate a little more on what were the contributions you were talking
                        about?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>BROWN: We helped in the establishment of a structure of agricultural secondary
                    schools. And while there was no agricultural university at that particular point
                    in time, we did a lot of participant training of people intended to develop
                    future capacity for university level teaching.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any agricultural schools before?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: There were no true agricultural schools. There were a couple of schools
                    that professed to have some responsibilities for agriculture but they had no
                    farms. They had very little in the way of practical agriculture. We were
                    interested in introducing the concept of practical agriculture training for
                    agricultural leadership. And I think we did something. I have met Libyans since
                    then who have gone out of their way to talk about the fact that they had been to
                    those agricultural schools and really benefitted enormously from the system that
                    we helped to establish. So I think that was important.</p>
                <p>The second American aid program was organized as a form of compensation for the
                    installation of a major US defense facility, Wheelus Air Force Base, which
                    continued to exist until closed by the Qadhafi regime. This program was run by
                    the Libyan American Commission and concentrated on building a wide range of
                    infrastructure facilities-highways, urban improvements and the like. Nominally
                    headed by a Libyan official, the program's Executive Director was Erv Hannum, a
                    US official on secondment to the Libyan Government. Erv was a dynamic and able
                    man, but many of us in the USOM were concerned at the heavy emphasis on
                    infrastructure of a nature and capacity of questionable viability (although some
                    of the Commission programs proved very useful once petroleum deposits were
                    exploited).</p>
                <p>The Commission programs certainly met their political objective, to assure
                    continued access for Wheelus Air Base, at least up until the Qadhafi coup. While
                    it can perhaps be argued that the coup was engendered in part as a reaction to
                    the existence of the base, it is likely the base would have disappeared in time
                    under even favorable circumstances as defense needs varied. As for USOM
                    programs, their most important impact was that of exposure through training and
                    education. Even in today's circumstances, one remains able to deal reasonably
                    effectively with many senior Libyan officials because of that earlier
                    exposure.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>Marc Gordon was normally an active and concerned leader but was weighed down in
                    this period by two problems -certain family concerns plus the “support” of a
                    very nice but extremely weak political appointee as Deputy. Dick Cashin provided
                    very strong leadership as Program Officer and Lloyd (Doc) Jonnes' economic
                    analyses were exceedingly thoughtful-he more than anyone else saw the potential
                    role that petroleum might play. For my own part, I had far more opportunity to
                    work directly with senior technical advisers than had been true in Iran. For
                    someone like myself, with no technical training or background outside of
                    economics, it was good to begin to work with education, agricultural, health
                    technicians and the like and to understand better the kinds of issues with which
                    one needed to be concerned. But I cannot deny I still approached these issues
                    far too much as an outsider with too little appreciation for how our ideas
                    should fit into local circumstances.</p>
                <p>One thing I certainly learned was the ability of Roman builders. A large Bureau
                    of Reclamation staff was doing useful work on water conservation. They located a
                    large wadi where 2,000 years earlier the Romans had built a series of water
                    retention dikes for several kilometers down the wadi which had obviously been
                    successful in their time. The Reclamation team rebuilt the system using all the
                    Roman foundations and following the overall Roman plan. The result was
                    wonderful-the valley flourished once more and the project became an outstanding
                    success. The Reclamation people decided to do the same on their own, so they
                    went through a similar process in a nearby wadi - but using their own designs.
                    It looked like the other-and cost even more. But when the first floods hit the
                    valley, the entire reclamation effort ended as a huge pile of stones at the
                    bottom of the system. After that it was back to basics! But the US was not
                    alone. The British built a huge damming structure in the plains between the
                    Jebel and Tripoli intended to control flooding in the city. The first real storm
                    created rubble surpassed only by Libya's Roman ruins.</p>
                <p>Libya produced another Brown, when our second son, Dean, was born at the hospital
                    at Wheelus Air Base. While this was certainly a good hospital with some capable
                    staff, there was a strong tendency among male doctors to look down on and act
                    poorly with women patients, including unfortunately Micheline. In the end we
                    regretted having relied upon it.</p>
                <p>On the whole, I would rate Libya as having been at the low end of our
                    assignments, overtaken only by many of the hardships encountered in our next
                    assignment-Somalia.</p>
                <p>Program Officer in the USOM in Somalia-1959-1961</p>
                <p>We arrived in Mogadishu, where I was assigned as Program Officer, about 18 months
                    before the 30 June 1960 Somali Independence Day and stayed about one year after
                    that date. Since Italian and British Somaliland joined together only at
                    independence, our first 18 months were in the Italian area and we worked largely
                    (though not entirely) with Italian officials - most of whom stayed on as
                    important advisers in the post-independence period.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>The rationale for a program in Somalia at that time was not abundantly clear,
                    although it was considered that the Horn of Africa was a geographically
                    important area where stability should be preserved. In effect, it appears to
                    have been undertaken largely as a result of Italian interest in assuring some
                    economic improvement in a country where they had important stakes. The mission
                    itself, up to independence, was in fact an off-shoot of the USOM mission to
                    Italy. While the US presence had been promoted primarily by the Italian
                    Government, there were substantial differences between what the US sought to
                    achieve and Italian interests. As in many other Point 4 type technical
                    assistance programs of this period, the United States sought to build capacity
                    for the future -in agriculture, in educational and training programs and the
                    like (but also in a strengthened national police force). The Italians, on the
                    other hand, were far more political in their efforts, aimed primarily at
                    assuring a continued major presence and role after independence.</p>
                <p>Will Muller was a capable and active Mission Director. We had some excellent
                    senior technical staff, but also some with really strange ideas-our senior
                    engineer wanted to create a new port at Chisimaio by using nuclear explosions!
                    Although the diplomatic mission was only a Consulate in the initial period, it
                    had highly able young officers, especially Dick Post as Political Officer and
                    Mike Ely as Economic Officer and they were a constant help to us in the aid
                    mission.</p>
                <p>Although I was then only an FSS-5, I was named as Program Officer in an FSS-3
                    position - and my deputy was Clark George, who was himself an FSS-3. This could
                    have been a terribly embarrassing and difficult situation for both of us, but
                    especially for him. I give him great credit for taking it well, making it
                    possible for us to work productively together. Will Muller's understanding was
                    also critical in making this relationship work.</p>
                <p>Life was certainly not easy in Mogadishu-with water again a major problem. The
                    household system used saline water delivered by truck while drinking water was
                    limited to that in jerry cans and large glass demijohns delivered every two
                    weeks (but the demijohns at least serve as lamp bases in our household today).
                    The first house to which we were assigned by the administrative section had
                    shutters but no windows-but lots of bugs. While we sprayed the interior once
                    every two weeks, the lack of windows made this a rather useless process. The
                    geckos were useful for some bug control although rather annoying when they fell
                    on us in bed. One had to close all water passages (sinks, bathtubs etc.) tightly
                    or the cockroaches invaded in force. We gave our dog to friends because of the
                    heavy tick infestation in the yard. Constant illness hit family members, all
                    exacerbated by an absolute lack of decent medical facilities. Our son Dean
                    became so sick and so weak Micheline had to take him to Nairobi for over a month
                    of care and recovery. We thank to this day the thoughtfulness and consideration
                    at what was then Gertrude Gardens Hospital in Muthaiga.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>Soon after that, the senior State Department Medical Adviser visited Mogadishu
                    and immediately condemned the house and ordered us out of it. Amazingly enough,
                    several years later a State regional medical adviser was assigned to that same
                    house and ended up being evacuated with gangrene infections. One does wonder
                    whether our systems couldn't have better memory banks.</p>
                <p>The USOM mission was located in a compound of several buildings which had earlier
                    been used, we were told, as a brothel for Italian military officers. It had gone
                    downhill by the time we occupied it. I was fascinated when several years later I
                    visited Mogadishu (as IFAD Vice President) and found myself calling on the
                    Permanent Secretary of Interior who was located in the same office which I had
                    occupied when assigned to Somalia.</p>
                <p>At the time of independence Somalis proclaimed their singleness, whether coming
                    from Italian, British, or French Somaliland, the Ogaden region of Ethiopia or
                    the Northeast province of Kenya-thus the five pointed Somali flag-because of
                    common heritage, language (spoken but not then written), religion etc. Little
                    was then said, particularly at the political level, of the importance of clan
                    relationships although some clan based songs were forbidden. At one point the
                    Somali-American Women's Club, of which Micheline was President, organized a sort
                    of dancing lesson for those Somali women whose husbands had studied abroad and
                    enjoyed Western dances. Some of the Somali women then demonstrated their songs,
                    several of them being forbidden. The police finally came and closed down the
                    affair - and the next day Russian diplomats were quoted as saying this was
                    another example of Western cultural imperialism. In any event, I must recognize
                    my own lack of foresight in failing to understand just how deep these currents
                    were running and what they would mean in terms of total breakdown of any kind of
                    organized state 30 years later.</p>
                <p>At independence there were virtually no Somalis with university training. To the
                    degree we could, the USOM program put heavy emphasis on educational activities,
                    and these were pursued by others who followed us. It was good to see, during my
                    visit many years later, the much larger number of trained and able Somali
                    technicians, many of whom had studied in the United States. It is regrettable
                    that political wisdom did not match that growth in technical ability.</p>
                <p>We were blessed during this period with the birth of our third son, Christopher,
                    although that event had to take place in Nairobi because of the lack of proper
                    facilities in Mogadishu. On the whole, while we had many Somali friends and
                    found them an attractive and agreeable people, for a variety of reasons this was
                    our hardest and least well remembered post.</p>
                <p>A new assignment as Program Officer in USAID/Sudan 1961-1963</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>Having passed through Khartoum airport on many occasions, when the temperature
                    was in the high '90s at 2 am, we had some reservations about going to the Sudan
                    after Somalia. However, these were soon overcome by the pleasure we had in
                    gaining many Sudanese friends, in finding so many sophisticated men and women
                    who were well educated and well trained and real experts in their field and who
                    gave us a warm welcome wherever we went.</p>
                <p>Bill Wild was the USAID Director. A wonderful, colorful figure who looked
                    remarkably like Yul Brynner (and loved signing Brynner's autograph when asked by
                    people in the street), Bill was well liked throughout the international and
                    Sudanese communities and that made the work of all his team easier. More an
                    activist than intellectual, Bill gave his senior staff lots of room to make
                    their own contributions. That in turn gave me broad scope to work again with
                    technical leadership on a range of programs in health, education, agriculture,
                    geological services and the like, programs which seemed to make reasonable and
                    enduring contributions to these particular activities.</p>
                <p>Important funding was also provided in the form of budget support through food
                    aid and commodity import programs. When I arrived we were seeking to reduce this
                    dependence on budget support but Sudan's huge and unending financial problems
                    remain in an even more grave state today than was true at that time. But the
                    circumstances did give me my first opportunity to work closely with the Central
                    Bank Governor and senior Ministry of Finance officials on broad development and
                    financial policy issues. Many of these senior economic officials were
                    exceedingly able and went on to important functions in international
                    organizations, banks and the like. Yet their ability to bring real change to
                    Sudan was limited, largely I think because there is something in Sudanese
                    culture which resists decision making and problem resolution. It is discouraging
                    to see how the Sudan, whether under dictatorial or democratic regimes, seems to
                    be incapable of real movement and improvement despite these many able people.
                    When I read about Sudan today, virtually all the problems we were dealing with
                    in the early '60s remain largely unsolved, causing continued poverty and
                    misery.</p>
                <p>An important Sudanese personage has been Sadiq el Mahdi. Even when we first met
                    him as a young man he was well known due to his father's and grandfather's
                    religious and political roles but he was still only at the edge of the political
                    scene during our period when a military government reigned. I was deeply
                    impressed by his wisdom and his views on how to deal with Sudan's difficulties.
                    I thought it was good when he became Prime Minister many years later. I then had
                    the pleasure of a long conversation with him in Rome when he took part in one of
                    IFAD's Governing Councils. I was once again struck by his understanding and
                    thoughtfulness. His comments on failures of the previous Nimeiri dictatorship
                    and his very sound analysis of Nimeiri's errors in dealing with the problems of
                    dissidence in Southern Sudan seemed very accurate. Unfortunately he became
                    another example of the disappointments one can face in Sudan when some months
                    later he carried out many of the same kind of negative actions towards the South
                    which had been part of Nimeiri's downfall - and also became a part of Sadiq's
                    own downfall.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>I have always tried to work in close harmony with State colleagues. However,
                    Ambassador Moose, a fine Arabist but strongly conservative about the usefulness
                    of assistance programs, was difficult. At one point we were called upon to
                    prepare a multi-year major program document (I believe it was Jim Grant who, at
                    the time, designed the format to be used), which was to be submitted to
                    Washington through the Ambassador. I worked very hard on that presentation which
                    projected the need for continued technical assistance in many fields and also
                    called for continuing but diminishing budget support. It was reviewed carefully
                    within the aid mission as well as with senior Embassy staff. It was fully
                    supported by DCM Tom McElhiney and Political Counselor Peter Chase. We presented
                    it at a two hour long Country Team session. Again there was essentially
                    unanimous support among the USOM and Embassy staffs.</p>
                <p>At the end, however, Ambassador Moose expressed his view that any aid to the
                    Sudan was a waste of money. He stated we could submit the program but he would
                    prepare and submit his own commentary, which he did in a two page State
                    Department condemnatory message. The result was that our proposals became a Best
                    Seller within the Department -and in the end were fully endorsed by both State
                    and ICA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the character of that program that you were
                        putting forward that seemed to cause some controversy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I don't think it caused any trouble with anybody else but Ambassador
                    Moose. Simply put, Ambassador Moose was basically opposed to aid in any form.
                    Ours was a fairly straight forward presentation. We had put a lot of work and
                    effort into the justification and so forth. It was justification for certain
                    types of technical assistance, a small amount of capital aid particularly in the
                    transport sector which we felt was an important one and a certain amount of
                    financial assistance including PL 480 because of the extreme financial
                    circumstances which were facing Sudan at the time. And I must say have been
                    facing Sudan ever since then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember any particular technical assistance
                        projects that were unique at that time or special?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Again, we were doing a lot of work in the field of education. I must say I
                    found that interesting since I had not dealt very much with educational programs
                    before that time. On reflection I realize that it wasn't a very focused program.
                    To be perfectly frank, I'm not sure just what was the longer term impact.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>We worked very hard with the Geological Survey which was important for the Sudan,
                    being such a vast country and so badly charted. It was important for them to
                    have better geological survey information and we did a lot of work with them.
                    There I think we were particularly successful because they had a small cadre of
                    very good people. We also provided a lot of training, along with equipment and
                    new ideas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were they surveying?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: They were developing essentially better mapping and geographical
                    understanding. How the country was structured and where there might be various
                    minerals and so forth. Where good agricultural land was located and what this
                    meant for transport systems and the like. It was just basic information which
                    really was a part...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it part of an institution?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes. There was in existence a small geographic or geologic service but it
                    was mal-equipped. And while it had some good people in it there was no depth.
                    But it gave us a good structure with which to be able to work and I think we did
                    a lot to bring it along to become really become quite a first class geologic
                    service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any other projects you want to mention at this point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Well, there were some specific road projects. Again, Sudan was a country
                    with vast distances and vast difficulties. And we provided some help in this
                    area. Particularly connections into the Gezira where the Gezira cotton
                    development scheme was taking place. We did some work in industry and helped to
                    bring about some industrial investments by helping to make connections to the
                    right people and that sort of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the program country wide or mostly south or mostly
                        north?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: It was mostly north. Later AID moved the program much further afield and
                    particularly out into the desert areas of the west. It was a relatively new
                    program and really concentrated largely on needs as seen from Khartoum. Before,
                    for several years before I got there, it had essentially been a financial
                    program and not a technical assistance program. So the technical assistance
                    program was really just beginning. We concentrated heavily on the north and not
                    even the northwestern desert area.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you didn't have much exposure to the problems of the
                        south?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: No. No. Very little. We were well aware of them of course, because of the
                    conflict that existed even at that time. But, no, I never traveled in the south.
                    Our people did not travel in the south. We knew very little about the real
                    circumstances there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say here that you were involved for the first time in
                        broader policy issues. Do you want to elaborate on what those issues
                        were?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: As I say, the Sudan was facing then, as it has ever since, major financial
                    problems-shortages of resources, poor allocation of resources, great gaps in
                    social services and the like. And part of our assistance was in the form of
                    financial aid, direct financial aid, as well as PL 480, and it was a question of
                    trying to assist in developing reasonable policies for budget management and for
                    proper allocation of those resources. It was essentially that. It was not a
                    deep, broad program. But for me who had never dealt in that area, it was a
                    strikingly interesting thing to think about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of reception did you get from the Sudanese?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I think certainly from the financial crowd we got a good reception. We
                    worked closely with them and they recognized full well the importance of our
                    resources. They were not disturbed by our taking an interest and a role and
                    working with them on the utilization of those resources. The Sudanese
                    economists, while they tried valiantly frankly had much less success in getting
                    the Sudanese government to keep the kind of discipline that was necessary. And
                    that again, has been a perpetual problem of the Sudan ever since then.</p>
                <p>Life in Khartoum was far more agreeable than we had anticipated. While there was
                    much hot weather, the winters were cool and refreshing, a real delight.
                    Year-round dryness made Khartoum far more comfortable than the muggy climate of
                    Mogadishu. We had a modest but pleasant house - with no bugs. We traveled less
                    than usual, partly due to difficulties of transport to many regions. Khartoum
                    was well equipped with wonderful tennis clubs and Micheline and I played more
                    actively than before. A group of us enjoyed night time picnics on the edge of
                    the Nile, hoping we had found locations where there were no crocodiles. Another
                    group enjoyed music and we had a series of musical suppers going on. Downtown
                    movie houses were open air but equipped with boxes and several of us would go
                    together, sharing a form of picnic supper while watching the show. In almost all
                    of these events we were a mixed group of Americans, Sudanese and other
                    nationalities.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>One distressing element of the weather, however, were the haboobs or dust storms
                    - storms which would suddenly gust up bringing absolute clouds of dust which
                    filtered into everything and left one blind if outdoors. You could always tell
                    when a haboob was coming, even on a clear day, by a smell in the air and then
                    the first traces of dust. During one of our nighttime Nile picnics, a dozen of
                    us smelled such a storm coming. We rushed back into our cars and headed for the
                    city - but within a few minutes we were absolutely lost in the sand - barely
                    able to follow each other. We circled around and around, getting even further
                    lost. Finally, someone spotted a well lit “road” and we all started rolling down
                    it, waiting to see where it led. Only when this “road” came to an end did we
                    discover we had been driving down the main runway of Khartoum airport.</p>
                <p>We have always had a wide range of pets around the house - a gazelle in Tripoli,
                    a cheetah in Mogadishu, dogs and cats in every post. In Khartoum we adopted for
                    a while a young white mehari (racing) camel who was great fun. We nursed him
                    with milk in a beer bottle with an ingenious kind of nipple. He would wait at
                    the gate when we went out for the evening and then nuzzle his neck around ours
                    when we returned. He later became very famous as an actor on television
                    advertisements for Camel Beer, and drinking his milk from a beer bottle made him
                    a real success.</p>
                <p>As a whole we enjoyed our time in Khartoum. We had a good mission and I was
                    involved for the first time in broader policy issues. We thoroughly enjoyed our
                    Sudanese and international friends- Micheline in particular had a much more
                    active interchange with Sudanese than had been possible in Libya and even in
                    Somalia and she particularly enjoyed her time teaching French to young students
                    at the American school. This time we regretted leaving the post.</p>
                <p>Deputy Executive Secretary and then Executive Secretary in Washington:
                    1963-1965</p>
                <p>I started off this assignment in Washington as Tunisia Desk Officer for a short
                    while. My Assistant Administrator was Ed Hutchinson. Hutch was a tough task
                    master but open and fair and I came to admire him greatly. Many years later Owen
                    Cylke and I asked Hutch to come to Egypt to chair a mission staff retreat, which
                    he did in his usual admirable way. One Saturday I met with him to make a
                    presentation on some program ideas for Tunisia on which we had been working very
                    hard. Hutch listened carefully, asked probing questions and seemed close to
                    agreement. However, at the end he said he simply could not buy the idea - but “I
                    admire your manner and the way you put the case so strongly”. That made up for
                    the disappointment in having our ideas turned down (Hutch, by the way, was
                    probably quite right in the decision he took).</p>
                <p>After a short while, Fred Simmons, who was then the AID Executive Secretary,
                    invited me to join the Administrator's office as Deputy Executive Secretary. I
                    leaped at the chance, even though Fred warned me the hours would be long and
                    difficult. I later welcomed the chance to take Fred's place when he moved on to
                    other activities.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>Following a decade in the field, it was fascinating to work at the center of AID
                    decision making. This was the time when most economic development activities had
                    been brought together in one organization, AID, and Dave Bell was its first
                    Administrator. He remains my ideal of what an AID Administrator should be all
                    about. Highly intelligent, well grounded in finance and budgeting, deeply
                    concerned about what assistance programs ought to aim at, idealistic at the same
                    time as pragmatic and realistic, concerned with the problems of the poor but
                    knowing the need to respond to political necessities, highly able as a
                    bureaucrat and in his relations with the political world, and obviously well
                    thought of in the White House, he was a great leader and a wonderful person with
                    whom to work. While he sometimes seemed somewhat cool and reserved, I will never
                    forget his thoughtfulness at one particular time. I was called to an emergency
                    when one of our sons was rushed to the hospital. I did not get back to the
                    office for two days. In that period, Dave called us at home at least three times
                    to inquire how our son was faring.</p>
                <p>Obviously Bell had some major issues to face in bringing this single AID agency
                    into reality. He was wonderfully partnered by his Deputy, Bill Gaud. Bright,
                    energetic, strong in his manner of expression (which often approached that of a
                    master sergeant), Bill proved an excellent foil to Dave Bell and different as
                    were their personalities they worked in excellent harmony.</p>
                <p>The strong leadership of Bell and Gaud led to selection of a group of very able
                    Assistant Administrators and Mission Directors. One important lesson I learned
                    from them was the necessity to devote substantial time to personnel issues -
                    selection, indoctrination, leadership, discipline, recognition. I had never
                    realized that senior managers would spend up to a third of their time on various
                    aspects of personnel issues, but that was certainly the case with Bell and
                    Gaud.</p>
                <p>While “growth” was still very much the central theoretical focus of development
                    programs (Rostow's take-off concepts), Dave Bell showed great insight in his
                    recognition of the problems of poverty and particularly of the need to build
                    strong institutions to support development efforts. While faced by a President
                    -Johnson-who traveled widely and often wanted to leave expensive development
                    gifts behind him, many of which proved to be non-viable white elephants, Bell
                    sought to insist that the vast bulk of resources go into meaningful longer term
                    institutional and financial actions. I give him great credit for taking
                    leadership in showing that neither gifts nor growth alone were the solution. As
                    former Director of the Office of the Budget, Bell was extremely conscious of
                    costs and demanded the highest possible level of performance per administrative
                    dollar.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>As the managers of the Executive Secretary's office, Fred Simmons and I were
                    expected to remain neutral and avoid taking positions on issues which were being
                    debated between the Administrator's Office and the rest of the agency. Thus, in
                    theory our jobs had little to do with real decision making. However, we saw that
                    process in its most intimate manner. Further, by deciding what matters needed
                    more consideration before going to Bell and Gaud for action, Fred and I carried
                    a substantial substantive role. Bell and Gaud would often ask our views on
                    particular issues which they were considering. Though some senior staff
                    occasionally felt we carried our interventions too far, I think the majority
                    appreciated what we were doing and were especially responsive when we
                    demonstrated the manner in which the Administrator might react to an unsupported
                    or inadequately vetted proposal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the development policy or strategy of AID at that
                        time? I've gotten mixed views of what it was trying to encompass. This was
                        in the early days. But, what was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Well, really, I can't answer all of that. Although while I was around that
                    office, a lot of this decision making was taking place far beyond my camp. But
                    it was the first effort to try to bring various strings of American assistance
                    together. There had previously been one agency essentially dealing with capital
                    assistance, another one dealing with technical assistance and all that. This was
                    an attempt to bring it together. It failed in one sense to do that
                    adequately-which has been, frankly, a bane of AID ever since, that is, the
                    relationships with the international banks and international organizations which
                    stayed with Treasury. But in that period, Dave Bell was a strong enough person
                    that he had substantial influence on US policy with respect to the World Bank
                    and the regional banks.</p>
                <p>So, one major effort was clearly to bring some order into programs which had been
                    managed and carried out by a variety of different organizations. It was also of
                    course, a period when despite the interest of people like Bell in development
                    issues, the agency was being at least partially torn apart by Vietnam and
                    increasing involvement of AID in Vietnam. And that was hard.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You saw the effect of that while you were in this
                        position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Only the beginnings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In what ways?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>BROWN: A lot of time spent on the issue. Some people shifting their interest from
                    development towards interest in combating guerilla warfare and the like. It was
                    an era with Kennedy and then Johnson were interested in these kinds of things,
                    that you could contain Communism by containing insurgence. Those ideas were
                    always around.</p>
                <p>I don't honestly know what Bell felt on those issues but certainly my exposure
                    was to a man who wanted to deal with development. Bell's concern, I must say, as
                    far as I could see, was primarily and largely with the broad set of policy
                    issues in a particular country. He was therefore especially taken by problems in
                    India, Pakistan and the like where there was a capacity to deal at the policy
                    level. That was true also to some degree to some of the programs that were of
                    most interest to him in Latin America. At the same time, I felt certainly that
                    he had a deep recognition that pure development growth without concern for
                    equity was not enough.</p>
                <p>I don't say that he did much in that direction-he did not impose new ideas. There
                    was no basic human needs that was built into the program. But it was there in
                    his psyche and it did seem to me that it had some impact on the direction in
                    which certain programs went without being that carefully articulated. So, it was
                    a policy of development with a sense that the world is a better place if there
                    is less poverty but seen in terms of poor nations more than in terms of poor
                    people. It was a period of seeking to look holistically at what we were doing in
                    countries and trying to develop meaningful strategies for how you dealt with
                    major recipients. But all that was beginning to be affected by the elements of
                    what was going on in Indochina.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There wasn't any particular limit on what activities we
                        could be engaged in when you have the basic human needs, and so on and
                        certain things were ruled out as well as things ruled in and so on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I don't think so. I don't think there was any particular limitation. Bell
                    was very attracted by policy frameworks and he was a starter of what were
                    essentially policy type lending in a few cases. I recall, in a couple of
                    countries in Latin America there were major education sector programs for
                    example where the flow of resources had depended on the evolution of the
                    education system. In India and Pakistan there were broad financial packages
                    aimed at underpinning the development budget.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find AID as an organization at that time from
                        looking at it from that top-level perspective?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>BROWN: I must admit it was difficult for me to have very strong views on that. I
                    had been in the field. I had not experienced working in Washington except in
                    those very early days as an intern. It did not seem to me to be an unreasonable
                    structure. Regions were given “relative preeminence” if I can put it that way.
                    Obviously the technical people were listened to but it was largely a question of
                    regional concentration and that was in part Bell's concern with national
                    strategies. And the fact that those strategies had to flow from the country
                    though the regional offices rather than too much emphasis on technicians. That
                    is an organizational structure that I personally prefer. I think that the
                    emphasis must be on the country level and on the regional level. And while your
                    technical people are absolutely essential in making sure you are doing the right
                    things, they should not be up front in organizing programs as such.</p>
                <p>While my job satisfied me very much, life in Washington was less appealing for
                    Micheline. We had a pleasant small house in a nice suburban area. But we were
                    far from the center of Washington. The children were young and needed lots of
                    care. Salaries were small and the cost of theater prices and baby sitters meant
                    we got little enjoyment from the best parts of Washington life. She was only too
                    happy to move on to our next assignment, a year at Princeton. Before leaving
                    Washington, we had to pack our personal things - some to go to Princeton, some
                    to go into continuing storage and some in preparation to go overseas a year
                    later - but without knowing where we would be going. What proved amazing is that
                    we made largely the right choices. After our several moves we had become more
                    expert in this part of foreign service life.</p>
                <p>A year's sabbatical at Princeton University-1965-1966</p>
                <p>I deeply appreciated Bell and Gaud's support for my application for mid-career
                    training at the Princeton Woodrow Wilson program. One reason for my choice of
                    this program was precisely because the Woodrow Wilson School refused to give any
                    academic credit for courses we might take, urging us to follow those activities
                    which could be valuable to us rather than better filling a formal academic
                    record.</p>
                <p>Arthur Lewis' course on economic development best responded to specific economic
                    aid program issues. I enjoyed it although I found his theories on rural-urban
                    labor exchanges to be too theoretical and too general in nature. By far my most
                    stimulating professor was Jim Billington, who ran a fascinating program on
                    Soviet history. He introduced me to a wide range of Russian and Soviet
                    literature. He had a way of making intricate matters clear and was deeply
                    responsive to the specific interests of individual students. I loved that course
                    not just for its content but for the wonderful way in which it was conducted.
                    Jim Billington is now the Librarian of Congress and I gather he is doing a great
                    job in that complex function.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>Princeton was a good place to be. I was challenged by young graduate students who
                    had what were often for me new and different views and debate with them was
                    refreshing and fun. Course work was enjoyable and evenings were filled with
                    exciting guest lecturers, artistic and cultural events and the like. Our house
                    was 100 meters from the football stadium and it was great fun for the family to
                    become involved as Princeton fans. The same applied to basketball, especially
                    since this was the time of Bill Bradley's domination of the court. We liked
                    living in a relatively small although very sophisticated town while being only
                    an hour away from the excitement of New York City. Our sons loved their
                    schooling and the openness of life in general-and even enjoyed it when they fell
                    through the ice while learning to skate. The university invited Micheline to
                    take part in classes of her choice which she did with great pleasure. She became
                    the star of her Russian class and added Russian to her (then) collection of
                    English, French, Persian, mid-level German and some Italian (she later added
                    fluency in Italian and in Cairene Arabic). She also ran, as usual, a wonderful
                    household full of friends and family - and did some tutoring to Princeton
                    undergraduate students as well.</p>
                <p>Back overseas as the USAID Representative in Algeria-1966-1967</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>Our first assignment after Princeton was to Algeria where I was to replace Phil
                    Birnbaum as AID Representative (some years later I again succeeded Phil as
                    Deputy Assistant Administrator for Africa and then again as Vice President of
                    IFAD). We arrived at an inauspicious time-Algeria was adamantly opposed to US
                    activity in Vietnam, leading to very cool diplomatic relations and the
                    occurrence of a series of carefully controlled “demonstrations” in front of US
                    offices to show the anger of “the people”. Consequently, the AID program was
                    necessarily small and limited in impact-a little PL 480 food aid, some
                    participant training programs, support to various Algerian voluntary agencies,
                    management of what was then called the Ambassador's Special Fund (for small but
                    possibly politically interesting activities or those having useful small
                    institution impact). Getting to know Algerian officials was hard because the
                    Government sought to build a fence between Americans and socializing with
                    Algerians. However, I did have some dealings with a young, bright Algerian
                    official, Idriss Jazairy, who later became President of IFAD and with whom I
                    worked for eight years at IFAD. We also managed to build a friendship with
                    Mohamed Shaker, who later became Ambassador to the United States and then
                    Executive Secretary of the Economic Commission for Africa. Through our neighbors
                    (Mme. Claude Radievski, who as a lawyer had defended Ben Bella against the
                    French), we also enjoyed a strong friendship with an Algerian Surete official
                    who later proved very helpful. But mostly our Algerian friends were private
                    citizens in no way associated with government. We were fortunate to be quickly
                    accepted into a group of very nice Algerians and international types who shared
                    the costs of running an old beach house to which we all retreated when the
                    weather allowed. We did manage to travel a moderate amount, despite the need for
                    official permission for every sortie outside of Algiers, and came to love the
                    varied beauty of Algeria. Life was made pleasant because we had a wonderful
                    place to live at the top of the hills above Algiers which we inherited when AID
                    Agricultural Adviser Leroy Rasmussen left Algeria. The house was small but the
                    grounds included a small pool and a tennis court and this was one place we could
                    bring many friends in an enjoyable but discrete setting.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>Our stay was short, however. In April of 1967, as US-Algerian relations
                    deteriorated further, it was agreed there was little prospect for a useful aid
                    program. I was therefore asked to move on and become Deputy Mission Director in
                    the Congo (now Zaire). Micheline stayed in Algiers to permit the children to
                    finish the school year. But her stay ended with a bang with the Middle East
                    Six-Day war in June, 1967, which led to a break in relations between the US and
                    Algeria and then an evacuation of the Embassy staff. Micheline had a difficult
                    but, in a sense, fascinating time at this period. When the war broke out she
                    happened to be spending a weekend in Paris visiting family, with the children
                    remaining with friends in Algiers (one of them with a prominent Jewish family,
                    the other two with the US military attach�!). It took a lot of dealing to get
                    back into Algiers but she succeeded, only to find our house had been sequestered
                    and she had to spend more time getting to the right people in order to get back
                    in and bring the family together. As soon as she got in, the evacuation order
                    came. While she and friends tried to get some of our belongings packed, in the
                    end she had to leave most just where they were. However, the Surete official
                    with whom we had become friends, assured her that he would take personal
                    responsibility to get our belongings safely and properly to us in Congo/Zaire- a
                    promise he kept (except for Micheline's Russian-English dictionary and some of
                    my Princeton books on Soviet history). He also came to the airport to make a
                    public showing of seeing Micheline safely off on the evacuation flight. For
                    reasons I will soon explain, Micheline then ended up in Paris with the children
                    for the rest of the year. I had one chance to come up to Paris from Leopoldville
                    (now Kinshasa) for a short visit - and when I was there the same Algerian
                    official was in town and made it a point to invite us out to lunch to be sure
                    all was well. How he found out where we were I do not know, but the Surete seems
                    to know all and there he was bidding us a final farewell.</p>
                <p>Despite all these limitations, we enjoyed our time in Algiers. Algiers itself is
                    a beautiful city, and there were a number of other places, on the coast as well
                    as in the desert oases, which were a delight to visit. Those Algerians we got to
                    know were unfailingly pleasant although the tough side of Algerian personalities
                    was certainly apparent. While the program was very small, its emphasis on small
                    self-help projects gave me my first real opportunity to work with a range of
                    PVOs (NGOs) and I certainly appreciated the fine work they were doing.</p>
                <p>An amusing (but somewhat costly ) experience in Algiers is that we got two
                    telephone bills at home- one for our own regular use, the other for the
                    Government's tap on our phone.</p>
                <p>First assignment as a Mission Director in Zaire-1967-1970</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>As noted, I went to Leopoldville (Kinshasa) in April, 1967, leaving the family to
                    follow me at the end of the school year. The Director at the time was Joe
                    Mintzes, for whom I had once worked on an Antioch College job assignment with
                    ECA (the Economic Cooperation Administration). Joe and I had gotten on well in
                    ECA and had the same good relationship in the Congo these many years later.
                    However, our time together was relatively short since Joe was getting ready to
                    end his Congo tour. Joe amused me by one of his habits-he had the New York Times
                    Sunday edition delivered to him, but it always arrived several weeks late. No
                    matter what day of the week it arrived, he and his wife put it aside and then
                    read it in leisurely fashion over Sunday breakfast-just like back in
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>Micheline was to join me during the summer. But just as she was traveling from
                    Paris to Rome to catch a flight, another mercenary rebellion broke out in the
                    Congo and no dependents were allowed to arrive. She was informed of this just as
                    she was about to board her plane from Rome to Leopoldville. She had first to
                    return to Rome itself (with hardly a penny or lira in her pocket) where she
                    waited several weeks to be told the suspension of travel would be indefinite.
                    She then had to scurry back to Paris, get the children installed in school, find
                    housing and all the rest. It was amazing how well she survived all of that.
                    Finally the travel suspension was lifted and the family joined me for Christmas,
                    1967. I was fortunate during this period that my brother, Dean Brown, was in
                    charge of Central African affairs at State - one of only two times our career
                    paths crossed-and he was able to add substantially to the sometimes difficult
                    communications between Micheline and I through this uncomfortable period.</p>
                <p>Those first months in the Congo were very difficult. The country was still
                    reeling from a series of mercenary rebellions and from the efforts of secession
                    by the copper rich Shaba region. Foreign exchange was virtually unavailable and
                    shops were bare (I lived next to what had been a very impressive supermarket
                    which had aisles and aisles of shelves - all filled with nothing but plastic
                    buckets and sandals). Foreigners were leaving, and since few Congolese had
                    benefitted from adequate education or managerial level experience, the kingpins
                    of the economy were in peril.</p>
                <p>But in 1967-1968 there was the beginning of limited political stability in the
                    form of Colonel, then General, Mobutu, who emerged from the chaos of the Congo
                    to become its Prime Minister and then President. While the effects of this last
                    gasp (at that time) of mercenary activity were still being felt, over the next
                    few years insecurity decreased and some form of central government control took
                    place. Even Lubumbashi and the copper region seemed gradually to become secure.
                    While Mobutu proved himself over time to be a scandalous dictator who stole vast
                    amounts from the Zairois treasury and people, in this 1967-1968 period the
                    growing stability that he represented was well recognized (and rewarded).</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>And while the Congolese Government suffered from a severe lack of trained
                    officials at all levels, it was blessed by an outstanding Central Bank Governor
                    and by a small group of very able officials at the top levels of the Ministry of
                    Finance. Some thoughtful IMF officials as well as two or three excellent Belgian
                    Government officials worked closely with these key officials as did we in the
                    AID mission, seeking to build new strength in the overall economy. Together we
                    developed a package of reforms, including a major devaluation, which the
                    Congolese officials then had to sell to Mobutu. He finally accepted it when
                    together they concocted a clever political approach. They replaced the Congolese
                    franc with a new currency, the Zaire. Although the exchange rate between the
                    Congolese franc and the new Zaire actually represented a major devaluation, it
                    was given a new and positive twist by making the Zaire equivalent to two US
                    dollars, or 100 times as much as the Belgian franc and announced proudly as such
                    by Mobutu. This reform movement did work for several years, and launched a
                    period of important growth in the Zaire economy - destroyed later, of course, by
                    the thievery and peripatetic changes introduced by Mobutu over time (when also
                    those outstanding Congolese officials had left the country). From then on it has
                    been largely a case of chaos.</p>
                <p>This was a very exciting time for me. While I had dealt with some economic policy
                    issues in the Sudan, I was here deeply immersed in these extremely complicated
                    deliberations, which had to be conducted in deepest secrecy because of the
                    impact that such a steep devaluation was expected to have. With the growing
                    effectiveness of the reform program and as political and financial stability
                    increased, the need for a strengthened assistance program also meant a large
                    growth in our activities. Increases in Commodity Import and PL 480 programs
                    provided Zaire needed financial backing during this period of transition.
                    Important new resources were devoted to educational programs at all levels.
                    Efforts were made to strengthen agricultural education and research; while there
                    were several reasonably well trained and well motivated Zairois
                    agriculturalists, the very limited ordinary budget resources devoted to
                    agriculture along with the great distances and transport problems meant our
                    programs had only limited impact. In a country as vast as Zaire, improved
                    transport was a major necessity. Starting in this period and for many years
                    afterwards AID (and later the World Bank) devoted substantial resources to
                    maintenance and upgrading of roads and to better river traffic; as far as I can
                    determine, the long term impact of these efforts was very limited, again due to
                    the lack of consistent support, and financing, provided by the central
                    government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In your discussion of the program in Zaire, you did make a
                        few comments about the activities that you were supporting: like educational
                        programs and so on. Could you elaborate any more about what you were trying
                        to do in those programs? Were there any new institutions being created or
                        any new...?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>BROWN: No. The institutions with which we worked were in existence if in often a
                    moribund state of existence. There was an agricultural service and there were
                    regional agricultural centers and offices but they were very weak and our
                    concern therefore was not to try to introduce any new organizational structures
                    but to first get more resources into the agricultural system and to work with
                    people to try to plan better the way they use the relatively small resources
                    they had available.</p>
                <p>In the general field of public administration there was a nascent new public
                    administration institution which had been organized primarily by a combination
                    of Ford Foundation and United Nations assistance. And we certainly supplied a
                    lot of support to that because we considered it particularly important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it effective? How did it do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: It seemed to me at the time that it was the beginning of a very good
                    institution. I was there through three graduating classes and I was impressed by
                    the kinds of people who were coming out of the school. And having looked over
                    its relatively short history-it was in existence perhaps five or six years when
                    I got there-it seemed to me that it was coming along pretty well. And the people
                    it was turning out were pretty good.</p>
                <p>You have to remember this is a country which had a terrible shortage of able and
                    trained people. And this was an institution which was beginning to do something
                    about that. We did work, as I mentioned, in the financial field. Which was
                    largely technical assistance worked out in very close conjunction with the
                    International Monetary Fund as well as representatives of the Belgian
                    government. Certainly I felt during the period of time we were there that was
                    extremely helpful and...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We were able to have effective policy exchanges and policy
                        reform efforts?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: We participated along with those others. I must say we were not the lead
                    but we participated with the IMF and the Belgians and the Zairians in a major
                    economic reform. An economic reform which involved a major devaluation and
                    cleaning up of the financial and fiscal system. And yes, we played an important
                    part in that.</p>
                <p>It was difficult because in these types of circumstances, you had to be very,
                    very cautious-very secret-frankly when you are going to introduce a major
                    devaluation it is not something that you talk about in the newspapers. But it
                    was very successful. The country's financial situation quickly stabilized.
                    Investments began to flow in again. And that was also associated with the fact
                    that Mobutu, in his early days, represented political stability and political
                    dynamism of a positive nature.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>So that there was this combination of political and financial stability in a
                    country which has enormous resources. It helped bring new investment in. It
                    helped open up and legalize a range of exports which had been taking place but
                    had all been going through illegal channels and so forth to increase the foreign
                    exchange earnings. And therefore permit greater liberalization on the import of
                    goods and vastly broadened the access and availability of resources of all kinds
                    to all levels of the society. I would say, in its time, it was extremely
                    successful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was corruption still prominent at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: The corruption issue became prominent later. I mean it was growing. It was
                    nascent. We certainly saw examples of it. We had a team, I can't remember from
                    what company, but one of the major consulting firms that was trying to negotiate
                    with the government to provide broad services in a number of different sectors.
                    It fell apart at the end when the Zaire minister made a huge demand for payment
                    by the company to him personally. So corruption was there and it became much
                    worse in the years following.</p>
                <p>There wasn't much to be corrupt about frankly when we were there-until after the
                    financial reform. It was only after a little while that people really got into
                    this and of course, President Mobutu led it from the very beginning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you meet President Mobutu?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Two or three times but on a limited basis I must say. I did not...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any impression of him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: An interesting person. Strong personality. Intelligent and quick witted
                    but certainly not intellectual. And with relatively little real understanding of
                    how the world as a whole works. It was understandable given his background. But
                    there were some real limitations...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he have any interest in the development of his country
                        as such, as opposed to...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: False interest. False interest in the sense that it was the promotion of
                    some silly programs which did not really have any impact-in the name of the
                    people-but did not really have any impact.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He wasn't really concerned about their welfare?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Let me give an example. There was an American doctor there who was doctor
                    to Mobutu and had a lot of influence. And together they dreamt up this scheme of
                    river hospitals which sounded nice. And they put some boats on the river and ran
                    them up and down as hospitals. But they never dealt with the problems of
                    preventive medicine at all. And so to me this was a farce. This was a showboat
                    of development.</p>
                <p>Mobutu was interested in the big schemes. The Shaba Power Program and things like
                    that. Frankly there were also the activities where you could rake off the
                    largest amount whereas programs for people didn't matter much. Those are
                    impressions and they are certainly partly impressions from that period and
                    partly impressions that came from later on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything more on the Zaire experience or programs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: No. I think that between them things are covered.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ok. But you were economic counselor as well as AID
                        director.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes. I was economic counselor which is in part why, a part of my
                    involvement in all these financial discussions was in that function and part of
                    it was in the AID director function.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well that is quite unusual, isn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes it is. Very unusual. And I had insisted under the circumstances that
                    my formal deputy be the person who would otherwise have been the senior economic
                    officer in the Embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did it work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: He was a deputy on both sides. I think it worked very well because of the
                    number of the personalities that were involved in it. The Ambassadors in
                    particular were supportive of this and willing to give it a good, hard try.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>People from State in the Economic Section were open to it and willing. Obviously
                    the most senior person would prefer to be counselor himself. But we worked well
                    together. A lot of the day to day economic section work that was involved, I
                    just turned to that deputy to do. And in many of those areas, the economic
                    section was working as an economic section without any relationship with AID as
                    such. But when it got down to major policy considerations, we worked together.
                    And we had joint staff meetings of senior staff from the economic section and
                    AID. We talked these issues out together. We made joint presentations to the
                    Ambassador and back to Washington and so forth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This apparently worked reasonably well from your
                        observation of the relationship between AID and the Embassy. Is that a
                        pattern that you thought was generally applicable or unique to this
                        situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: It is partly unique because of the particular circumstances of Zaire. It
                    is also workable it seems to me only if you have an important AID program.
                    People in the State Department are not about to be subordinate to an AID
                    director if the program with which he is working is not a particularly important
                    one.</p>
                <p>But I think that in a number of countries it is a workable thing. Now would it
                    have been workable in Egypt when I went there? I don't think so. Only in the
                    sense that the management of the Egypt program was such an enormous affair in
                    itself. Also to worry about commercial affairs and other issues in the economic
                    field would have been impossible. In any event, it is essential that the
                    Ambassador assure that the senior economic officer or the senior economic
                    counselor and the AID director work very closely on the economic policy issues.
                    But it is not necessary to bring them together in a single institutional unit.
                    For that to work in Egypt took some very able senior State officials and I was
                    glad I had the right people to work with.</p>
                <p>Going back to Zaire, it can be said that AID programs of the period certainly
                    contributed sharply to the initial financial reform efforts and provided the
                    basis for modest stability, greater investment and political consolidation for a
                    period of time. They also contributed to training of a range of officials who
                    have worked mightily to try to improve the economic well-being of the country
                    against heavy odds. But over time Mobutu's economic mal-leadership, the
                    squandering and waste of resources, the exceptionally high levels of corruption
                    and the breakdown in meaningful political development have led to a Zaire today
                    which is a chaotic morass. Throwing resources at development problems may have
                    favorable political impact (and that was true in those first critical years in
                    Zaire), but there is little chance of having a real effect on bettering the
                    lives of poor people if the leadership and the will are lacking.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>Charley Mann was Mintzes replacement. Charley's background had been mainly in
                    Asia, but he relished this new assignment. He was smart and generally quick
                    thinking, although somewhat stolid and Germanic in his personal relations. We
                    got along well enough but I must admit that I was not unhappy when, after a
                    while, he was asked to take over the Laos Mission and I was named as his
                    successor as Mission Director, but also as Economic Counselor of Embassy.</p>
                <p>We had a good if small mission with some excellent staff members. I deeply
                    admired the way Ambassador Bob McBride presided over the American community in a
                    difficult and sometime dangerous period. In my combined role, I worked even more
                    closely with my Embassy colleagues. I traveled a good bit of the country, often
                    to visit agricultural programs with Leroy Rasmussen whom I had known in Algeria.
                    Travel was always difficult due to unmaintained roads, limited and poor railroad
                    connections and a substantial breakdown in river and air transport,
                    circumstances we sought without much success to overcome.</p>
                <p>During this period Dave Shear was head of the Central Africa section of the AID
                    Africa Bureau and we worked closely together. I quickly recognized his admirable
                    abilities and his strong and consistent support to our work in the field. We
                    built a relationship then that flowered even further when later we worked
                    together on overall Africa development issues.</p>
                <p>We were fortunate to find a somewhat odd but pleasant house right on a bend of
                    the Congo (Zaire) River which had good entertaining space and which again became
                    a center for lunches and dinners with our Congolese and international community
                    friends. The children had good schools and thoroughly enjoyed some of their
                    outings into the countryside. We had a parrot who adored women and children but
                    hated men. The rest of the family loved that beast, but he made a special effort
                    to come pecking after me whenever I would settle down in comfort at the end of
                    the day. Our youngest, Christopher (then about seven) adopted (or was adopted
                    by) a chimpanzee who belonged to neighbors and they took happy walks down our
                    street, hand in hand.</p>
                <p>While we had several Zairois friends, there is no question that many Zairois had
                    been deeply affected by the often cruel and highly racist Belgian regime and
                    settlers. As a result, it was often difficult to know how individual Zairois
                    might react to situations which were fairly normal in other societies. This was
                    particularly upsetting to mission wives, who were too often faced with confusing
                    and sometimes unpleasant situations related to the households.</p>
                <p>As a whole, we all enjoyed our stay in Zaire. Certainly I had an exciting job and
                    learned a lot during our time there. But the sense of tension made us feel it
                    was time to move on.</p>
                <p>A second Mission Director's assignment in USAID/Morocco-1970-1972</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>We went to Morocco in February, 1970 and stayed about 30 months. Morocco was
                    considered an important country for US defense concerns, both because of its
                    physical location at the opening of the Mediterranean but particularly for the
                    wide range of defense facilities (mostly Air Force) which were provided to the
                    United States by the Moroccan Government. The United States had maintained a
                    sometime prickly but basically close relationship with King Hassan over many
                    years. The AID program was justified, therefore, largely in terms of its support
                    to these mutual security interests. This had a double impact- it did mean that
                    reasonably important resources were devoted to the program without many
                    questions being asked - but it also meant that the program must be carried out
                    without causing any grief in US-Moroccan relations, i.e. without putting any
                    large demands on Moroccan leadership for the manner in which they supported the
                    program.</p>
                <p>There were good and reasonably well organized activities underway there when we
                    arrived and it was easy to move into the Director's position. Before long I was
                    joined by Harvey Gutman as Deputy, who consistently played an upbeat and helpful
                    role.</p>
                <p>We put heavy emphasis on social programs which would have some impact on poverty,
                    including important Food for Work activities designed to stimulate self-help
                    programs. Despite affecting an interest in and support to these programs, few
                    Moroccan officials really seemed to have real involvement in them and there is
                    real question as to their longer term utility. When Assistant Secretary of State
                    Dave Newsom made a visit, he was at first impressed by the appearance of some of
                    these small projects until it became clear Moroccan staff had been out painting
                    them the night before to make them “attractive” solely for his visit.</p>
                <p>In the field of agriculture and water resources, however, AID played an active
                    and useful role and its programs were well supported and welcomed. There was a
                    good team of agricultural specialists, including some fine consultants from the
                    Universities of Minnesota and Michigan State. They made particularly useful
                    contributions to agricultural education and to agricultural planning through
                    university to university relations with both the university agricultural faculty
                    and with the Ministry's research staff. Eliot Berg played a special role in
                    managing these technical relationships and also brought economic analysis into
                    agricultural planning for the first time. Moroccan officials comment to this day
                    on the lasting value of what was achieved. AID also financed several irrigation
                    projects which were generally very successful in physical terms but we had much
                    less impact in assuring who would be the proper beneficiaries of these
                    investments. However, I was interested to see, when I joined IFAD many years
                    later, that several IFAD irrigation programs were in fact based on extending
                    activities initiated by AID during this period, and that IFAD did have greater
                    influence on the question of participation by the poor.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>Living in Morocco was very pleasant. It is a beautiful country, with great
                    variety evolving from its site between two seas, Atlantic and Mediterranean, its
                    impressive mountain chains, its beautiful deserts, and its marvelous ancient
                    urban areas such as Fez and Marrakech. The road system is excellent as is rail
                    travel. Accommodations from simple to luxurious were available almost
                    everywhere. Moroccan cuisine is outstanding, outpaced in my view only by French
                    and Chinese cooking. As a consequence, we thoroughly enjoyed all our chances to
                    travel widely throughout the country. We lived in the same house occupied by AID
                    Directors for two decades and it was comfortable and a good place for
                    representational activities. For the only time in our whole career, we had a
                    Moroccan cook who really knew how to cook-on his own with minimal
                    direction-giving Micheline greater freedom from the kitchen than at any other
                    time.</p>
                <p>Moroccans with whom we dealt were invariably pleasant, seemingly open and
                    generally hospitable. But most non-Berber Moroccans seem to have two
                    personalities - that within their own culture and the other when faced by
                    foreigners. And foreigners are seldom allowed into more than a very superficial
                    relationship with them. There is almost a sense that certain Moroccans are
                    chosen by the system to deal with outsiders. My brother Dean, who had been DCM
                    in Rabat several years before we arrived, gave Micheline the names of ten
                    Moroccan ladies who, as part of this system, would surround her and treat her as
                    a friend. He was right in nine of the ten cases.</p>
                <p>While there certainly are Moroccans who care about the problems of poverty, they
                    seem fairly rare. It was my impression that even the opposition, while
                    proclaiming concern about the poor, was primarily concerned with bringing about
                    change in the political system rather than seeking a real change in the
                    situation of the poor. In a country with such deep contrasts between the
                    ultra-wealthy and the poor, these attitudes are distressing. More than that, the
                    obsession with wealth leads to corruption, cruelty and mismanagement.</p>
                <p>It was these attitudes, as well as the major effort to assassinate King Hassan in
                    the Skhirat attacks of 1971 followed a short while after by the attack on
                    Hassan's aircraft led clearly by General Oufkir, one of Hassan's closest
                    associates, which made me question whether the United States was not too
                    dependent on its relation with Morocco. I provoked an extensive debate within
                    the country team on this issue. While there were one or two others who agreed
                    with my concern, the majority felt strongly that US-Moroccan bonds were too
                    important to be put to any test over equity issues. But I admired Ambassador
                    Stuart Rockwell for the impassioned and thoughtful way in which he allowed that
                    debate to take place. We remained close friends despite his strong disagreement
                    with me on these issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You have made a number of comments about contributions to
                        Moroccan agriculture and the Hassan II Institute of Agriculture and
                        Veterinary Medicine project with the Universities of Minnesota and Michigan.
                        Could you elaborate on the institutions that were created by this work?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>BROWN: Well, I think the major and lasting institutions were in the field of
                    agriculture and particularly in the field of agricultural research. Both within
                    the structure of the agricultural faculties and within the structure of the
                    resources.</p>
                <p>I think an awful lot was learned together on how to deal with issues of Moroccan
                    agriculture. A lot of people were well trained. A number of concepts from
                    American educational and research systems were built into that. And I think
                    there was really some lasting impact.</p>
                <p>In our efforts in dealing with programs impacting on the people broadly, I think
                    of the Food for Work activities that we had for example. As far as I am aware,
                    they have had little lasting impact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why is that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Frankly Moroccan officials don't care. They make passes at being
                    interested in humanitarian affairs and problems of poverty but they are not very
                    serious about it. And while we had institutions that functioned fully well
                    during that period and after I left and there is no question that they were not
                    institutions which could rally meaningful support at the policy level within the
                    government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You made a comment IFAD had picked up on some projects
                        initiated by AID. Can you be more specific about what those projects
                        were?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Part of the AID program involved some major irrigation schemes,
                    particularly a pair of dams in a new irrigation area in the north of the
                    country. We put a lot of money into that. Basically into the infrastructure and
                    so forth. We tried to assure that there was a broader concept of participation
                    by poor farmers in the utilization of those resources. It was the nature of the
                    geography and so forth of that particular area which made it difficult to carry
                    that out even if one was willed to do so. And since the Moroccans weren't
                    particularly willed to do so, it didn't get very far.</p>
                <p>But a lot of the ideas that we were talking about at that time were then picked
                    up by IFAD in other irrigation schemes where IFAD itself was primarily concerned
                    not with the up-stream infrastructure but the down-stream infrastructure at the
                    farm level. And as I say, a lot of ideas that we in AID had put in place now
                    were carried out by IFAD and the Moroccan government. It is true that the
                    geographical and social circumstances of the IFAD projects were of a nature
                    where it was easier to get agreement to insure reasonable equity in the
                    allocation of those resources.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else on Morocco you would like to mention at this
                        point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: No. As a whole, was a very pleasant interlude in our lives, especially
                    after the tense and busy lives we led in Zaire.</p>
                <p>Return to USAID/Washington as Deputy Assistant Administrator for the Africa
                    Bureau-1972-1976</p>
                <p>In 1972 we returned to Washington for our second long assignment there, when I
                    was appointed as Deputy Assistant Administrator for Africa. I worked then for
                    the Assistant Administrator Sam Adams, a wonderful, thoughtful and generous man
                    whom I love to this day. He gave me broad scope to undertake a range of
                    different activities and did it in a manner which was constantly supportive
                    without being interfering. I give him special credit for his insistence, too
                    often over extensive opposition, on a special intern program for minorities - a
                    program which over the years led to some outstanding senior minority officers in
                    AID. I was deeply unhappy when later he was essentially forced into retirement
                    to permit a White House appointee to take over the AA position. While Stan Scott
                    was a decent person, he had no experience whatsoever in development issues and
                    little understanding of Africa. However, Stan and I got along well enough and I
                    gave him my loyalty, which he repaid by giving me wide freedom and support.</p>
                <p>Africa has always received short shrift by the United States and one could see
                    this in the way the Africa Bureau was given the least possible resources but
                    constantly put under active scrutiny. I remember presenting a $3 Million project
                    to the agency's senior review committee in an intensive discussion which lasted
                    an hour and a half - followed by Committee approval of a $100 million loan to
                    Pakistan after ten minutes of desultory discussion.</p>
                <p>Sam Adams was deeply distressed by this inadequate attention and a major part of
                    our work together was an effort to induce greater interest and support to
                    African development needs. Sam was especially concerned that the Sahelian area
                    (a term with which I, along with many others, discovered only at this time) was
                    largely ignored in American policy. He saw a gradual decimation taking place in
                    the region and its rather special culture due to a lack of resources and lack of
                    interest. He was one of the first to point to the gravity of the awful Sahelian
                    drought of the early '70s-really the first of a series of African natural
                    disasters which have since received support from the United States-and Sam
                    recognized that this awful event could also bring about greater public interest
                    and concern.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the Bureau as an operation at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>BROWN: The Bureau was not strong. It had some good people in it but it was not
                    strong. The leadership in various offices was moderate but not great. There was
                    also a heavy tendency for people with predominately AID/Washington backgrounds
                    to be in the more senior positions rather than people with field experience.</p>
                <p>With all my great admiration for Sam Adams, and I trust that comes across clearly
                    in what I've said, Sam was not that interested in organization and was not
                    pushing that hard on “who” did “what”. I think...I was concerned about and I
                    think we made some organizational changes, particularly with the structure and
                    direction of Washington subregional offices and field regional offices. We also
                    made a very serious effort to get more and better senior staff and particularly
                    people with field experience. Those are the changes, if any, that I would have
                    made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the African Bureau rank in relation to the rest of
                        the Bureaus in the agency? How was it treated?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: As I think has been almost universally the case, the weakest. The weakest
                    in terms of impact, the weakest in terms of resources available, and that was
                    part of the reasons that it tended to be weak in staff in Washington. Now that
                    is not the same as staff in the field because I think the issues of Africa
                    attracted a lot of very good people in the field. But as soon as they got very
                    good, they got stolen off by the other Bureaus which were stronger and had
                    better capacity to get at the administrator or whatever.</p>
                <p>The Sahel Development Program</p>
                <p>Over time I became more and more involved in the Sahel disaster, especially as
                    public criticism, particularly in the black community, grew over the inadequacy
                    of American response. The Administration, already buffeted by the public over
                    other issues, recognized the need to take stronger action. Among other things,
                    Maury Williams, then AID Deputy Administrator, was named overall Sahel disaster
                    coordinator and I spent a lot of time working directly with him. Maury was
                    demanding and sometimes harsh in that period, but he got things done and drove
                    the rest of the agency to give the Africa Bureau the support it needed. While
                    the disaster still caused thousands of deaths, in the end United States relief
                    efforts were essential in keeping the toll as low as was the case. A lot of
                    lessons were learned-preparation against potential disasters, pre-stocking,
                    transport and logistical needs, building disaster prevention capacity etc.
                    Fortunately the AID Disaster Relief Office paid considerable attention to these
                    lessons and this helped AID be more active and effective in subsequent disaster
                    situations.</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>While the drought response was first priority, several of us felt that there was
                    real need to look past it and into how resources could be used better to build
                    an economically stronger and more disaster resistant region. Encouraged
                    especially by Sam Adams and Maury Williams, I worked closely towards that end
                    with many able Africa Bureau hands concerned with the Sahel, but especially with
                    Dave Shear and Princeton Lyman. We were interested in two levels - what could
                    AID itself do aimed at more fundamental and longer term support to the region;
                    and how could the Sahelian nations and many interested donors work more
                    effectively together using shared understandings and goals.</p>
                <p>For the first purpose, we sought direct legislative support for strengthened aid
                    programs while at the same time putting major resources into defining the most
                    effective kinds of responses for AID to undertake. We used every trick we knew.
                    The Administration being under considerable stress related to other issues, we
                    tried to show the political benefits it could achieve by a positive response not
                    only to the disaster but also to longer term Sahelian needs. Fairly quickly we
                    got the broad support, in State, in AID and in the White House, needed for this
                    programmatic approach. At the same time, we worked closely with Hubert Humphrey,
                    who had returned to the Senate and the Foreign Relations Committee, on
                    legislative tactics. Davy McCall of the Committee's staff, was exceptionally
                    helpful in his support. In the end we did get legislation which established the
                    Sahel Fund. Years later this initial Fund evolved into the broader African
                    Development Fund which provided the kind of recognition and program basis for US
                    support to Africa which Sam Adams had so strongly advocated.</p>
                <p>I remember one amusing conversation we had with Senator Humphrey during this
                    period when I asked him why his views on a particular issue seemed different
                    from those he expressed when Vice President. His response was that “where you
                    stand depends on where you sit!”</p>
                <p>With funding more secure, major efforts were underway to provide meaningful
                    program content. I must admit I was probably overly concerned with showing early
                    results while many of my colleagues in the African Bureau argued that we knew
                    too little and needed to build a stronger research base. We managed to achieve a
                    reasonable consensus on these points and did devote considerable effort to
                    building for the longer term while putting reasonable resources into
                    agricultural projects which did have some more immediate productive impact.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>On the Sahelian and international fronts, there was a growing recognition of the
                    need for a large scale international effort-accompanied by a mad scramble as to
                    who was going to be in charge— each party recognizing the need for coordination
                    while fighting to become the ultimate coordinator. On the African side, the
                    states did come together to establish a regional Sahel planning office. While
                    this was welcomed by donors, they also wanted a mechanism by which their views
                    would be taken fully into account. The World Bank organized its own Sahelian
                    section. Brad Morse built a Sahel Affairs Section into UNDP. The French and
                    Belgian Governments each sought a leadership role. Edouard Saouma, the then new
                    Director General of FAO, was convinced FAO should be in the lead. In AID we
                    convinced our colleagues that it would be a mistake for any single donor,
                    including the United States, to be the lead organization since no single
                    external coordinating donor would be acceptable to Sahelian leadership. We urged
                    a new form of relationship which would bring the Sahel planning group into close
                    liaison with a combined organization of donors. From this was born, with great
                    difficulty, much debate, innumerable visits to other donors, and several
                    international conferences, the Club des Amis du Sahel. The idea of the Club was
                    that it was a gathering place for donors and Sahelian states to work out ideas
                    and develop planning models for investment purposes, but to do this in a
                    collegial manner. While no one organization or nation was in charge, it was
                    recognized that different groups had special abilities and sectoral and
                    sub-sectoral committees were established under the leadership of different
                    national groups. It is very much my impression that this approach has worked
                    generally well and it has served as something of a model for AID's current
                    approach to meeting the needs in the Greater Horn of Africa. Equally there are
                    some similarities between the approach of the Club and the way in which donors
                    have worked within SADEC on southern African development needs.</p>
                <p>I remember vividly the international conference in Dakar where the concept of the
                    Club was finally given unanimous consent. Up to the last vote we were unsure if
                    it would be accepted and in fact several hours were spent the night before
                    convincing Saouma of the rightness of this approach. After that final vote Dave
                    Shear and I went off to have one royal celebratory dinner.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the Sahel program itself, would you elaborate on what
                        the strategy was for bringing Sahel from this famine-drought period into a
                        more development mode.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN:: First, one has to recognize these things are all overlapping.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sure.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: And that you were putting your concentration, more concentration on
                    certain stages and elements of a process than in others. And in the first years,
                    there was nothing. There was hardly a program in the Sahelian states until the
                    drought came. So you were dealing with the weakest probably the weakest program
                    in AID in existence anywhere in the world.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>Sam Adams was insistent that more attention needed to be given to that part of
                    the world. But it was hard to find the justification. There was little in the
                    way of economic resources, mineral resources, etc. These were countries that did
                    not have any for the most part any major influence on US interests. And one
                    could talk about humanitarian concerns and one could talk about economic
                    potentials for the future and what that could mean for trade and so forth but it
                    didn't have much of an echo. So you are starting from a very weak situation.</p>
                <p>You had a terrible drought. A terrible problem with the need for massive amounts
                    of food. Coming at the same time that the United States was selling off enormous
                    amounts of food to Russia because of the weak harvest in Russia at that
                    immediate time. The prices were going up and the availability was going down. It
                    was a huge struggle just to get people to accept that they had to devote
                    resources to provide food aid to the region. And that took a lot of effort.</p>
                <p>Then you had to spend a lot of time worrying about the infrastructure. Some kind
                    of infrastructure through PVO's; through AID itself. Through the nascent
                    missions that we had in place. To get that food where it needed to go. We
                    certainly did not succeed in that process nearly as well as AID was able to
                    respond to subsequent disasters but I think we did as well as one might hope in
                    retrospect. We also helped the agency learn a lot about pre-stocking,
                    organizing, planning, communications, transport and logistics and the like.</p>
                <p>I don't know how much I would have thought about the need to move to development
                    in Sahel if it hadn't been for Sam Adams saying, “By God, we will”. And it was
                    he who really said this was an area of neglect and these are cultures that are
                    going to die without some help and we need to do something. And he whipped us up
                    in the gentle and mild way that Sam whips anybody up to begin thinking in those
                    terms. And as I've said, some of our concerns were could we not get a stronger
                    legislative base? And we spent a lot of time on that.</p>
                <p>As noted, there was also the question of how the international organizations, the
                    international system, was going to respond and we spent a lot of time trying to
                    deal with the institutional basis for that. We worked a lot with the media and
                    the public about the need for movement in this direction, while at the same time
                    being heavily criticized by the black community for not doing nearly enough.
                    There was a combination of those two things. And both sides, the black community
                    was absolutely right. We weren't doing enough but the other side had to be
                    whipped up to do something. So, then the question is, “What?”</p>
                <p>The paucity of information was horrendous. At the local level there wasn't much.
                    Given the weakness of our programs, there was little historical knowledge. But
                    it was obvious to us that what was needed was longer term solutions.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it also true that the French were not very interested
                        in having us get interested in that area or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Well, they were not eager, I will say that. But I will also say that I
                    think we worked in good cooperation with the French technical assistance
                    agencies and we were not stopped. But clearly the French feared that if we
                    became too active that there might be a shift in attention by leadership in
                    those countries away from France to the United States and they didn't want that.
                    But I don't think that kept us from things and in fact, to the degree that there
                    was any kind of meaningful background and knowledge about the region it came
                    from the French government.</p>
                <p>As I say, it was obvious to us is that what was needed were long development
                    program strategies that would take into account the degradation of soil, the
                    limitations due to soil, water and climactical conditions. And I knew an awful
                    lot of people who kept saying, “We need to study, we need to study.” And, of
                    course, they were right that we needed to study things if we were going to have
                    meaningful programs over a period of time. At the same time, we needed to
                    produce something. We couldn't just study and call on the time of officials to
                    learn about livestock or sorghum production and we had to get in there and do
                    something.</p>
                <p>And I suppose I probably put more attention than I should have on trying to get
                    people to turn out working projects. Working projects which could be urban or
                    rural but primarily rural obviously. Primarily agricultural of one kind or
                    another. They were usually such things as small irrigation schemes or improved
                    seed or improved marketing systems and the like. And some of that was useful and
                    some of that worked and stayed. But some of it obviously, the institutional
                    backup structures were so weak that at any time we backed off a step, they would
                    collapse.</p>
                <p>But still, I accepted the fact that those longer term strategies were needed and
                    the kind of studies that were involved were undertaken. And one of my interests
                    in the concept of club of “Les Amies du Sahel” that I've talked about was that
                    bringing together the knowledge of the French and the Americans and FAO into
                    some kind of cohesive structure was likely to bring about the kind of knowledge
                    and development of institutions that was necessary faster than doing things
                    solely by ourselves.</p>
                <p>Now, I understand later evaluations have said we didn't do enough in institution
                    building in that period and I certainly understand that. And it is both a valid
                    and invalid conclusion in my opinion. I think it would have been extremely
                    difficult to do very much more in institution building at that period. Now, did
                    we do enough over a longer period in trying to develop the right help and the
                    right institution doing the training programs etc. I can't say because I was by
                    then off in Egypt and not following the program that closely. But certainly
                    people like Princeton Lyman, Dave Shear and others were making every effort to
                    try and have a balanced, reasonable and rational approach to the region
                    including longer term strategies.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The concept was really to talk about or deal with the
                        region as a whole and so there was an effort to mount a major regional
                        projects as such. That was part of the strategy, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: It was part of the strategy. I don't think it was a major part of the
                    strategy. I think we recognized that there were sufficiently important national
                    differences and even local differences that you had to put the concentration of
                    your interest at the local level. At the province level. At the national level.
                    There were certainly some things that could be done regionally. There were some
                    transport things that could be done. There was the whole question of the Niger
                    River and its utilization which had regional implications. There were the
                    interconnections between the in-land states and Senegal and the Ivory Coast as
                    coastal states which were important. And we looked at and worked on some
                    regional activity. But I personally, while I tried to do what we could on the
                    regional level, I thought it was far more important to work at the national
                    level. Always seeking to take experiences learned in one country and see to the
                    degree to which they were applicable to another.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To what extent did you find the African leaders in the
                        Sahel interested in a common program approach to their development?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: The African leaders were interested in a “Marshall Plan”, as they
                    constantly called it. A massive resource transfer program. And since it seemed
                    to appeal to a lot of people if that could be done in regional terms, they
                    talked largely about the need for regional programs. But, that was essentially
                    simply to get more resources at the national level. And of course, that didn't
                    work. There was an important increase in flow of resources into the region but
                    never anything approaching the dimensions of a Marshall Plan or anything that
                    you could even conceive of as being that. And of course for good reasons.
                    Circumstances were totally different.</p>
                <p>But there was an increase in resources. And there were increasing thoughtful and
                    able people at the national level and within the framework of some regional
                    institutions which over time better and better utilized those resources.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a time of a great debate...I don't hear it so
                        much now...of whether the desertification process was expanding .We had a
                        big MIT study on that subject, I believe , at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did that work come out?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>BROWN: I don't think it came out anywhere exactly. Like the number of dead as a
                    result of the drought. You never knew what the result was and I've heard numbers
                    that were different by 1000%.My assumption is, from my limited reading on the
                    subject, that there is a major cyclical problem for the region but it is not a
                    continuous decline. We are seeing this year good rains in most of the Sahelian
                    states. In fact flooding in some areas. But there is a cyclical problem there.
                    It was interesting in IFAD as we built into our programming a greater
                    recognition, not of average circumstances, but of cyclical circumstances — an
                    attempt to recognize perfectly well that one year out of four or five you were
                    going to have a disaster and you had to build your programs around that concept.
                    I don't think any of us were doing that back in the '70s. I assume AID is
                    probably doing more of that sort of thing at the present time as well. But I
                    still think that is what it is. It is a cyclic problem-a serious one. And one
                    which will never end in the Sahel. I mean you are not going to reach a point
                    where there are no more droughts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, finishing up on the Sahel. What do you suggest from
                        your experience are the lasting results of the effort of the “Club du
                        Sahel?” What do you see as continuing benefits and effects in these
                        countries? Are they better off because of it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I would certainly hope that the people of the Sahel are better off now
                    than those who lived there twenty years ago and that there has been a flow of
                    resources. There has been a flow of knowledge and there are better trained
                    people. There are programs going on in every one of the Sahelian states in the
                    field of agriculture which give promise for broader agricultural production; for
                    more safe agricultural production. There are capacities to deal with disasters
                    which didn't exist before, so that when they occur, the impact on people's lives
                    is still terribly important but not so deadly. So yes, I think a lot has been
                    done. But I am constantly fearful of the decline and ebbing of US interest in
                    Africa, in general. And I think we are certainly seeing it in terms of AID flows
                    at the present time. Which is one of the reasons that I was so interested in
                    getting a legislative base at least for the Sahel at that time. And I was very
                    pleased to see that in subsequent years others managed to broaden that to the
                    African Development Fund.</p>
                <p>It is hard to give all the hard-headed justifications for doing a lot in that
                    region except perhaps in very selected countries. But to me there is no question
                    that Africa is going to continue to be an element which cannot be forgotten by
                    the world, whether you like it or not. That there are opportunities for broader
                    understandings, broader trade, broader opportunities back and forth between the
                    United States in particular in Africa. And I think it is important for this
                    country to continue to participate with others-not alone-but participate with
                    others in reasonable levels of support to African development.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any other major initiatives while you were in
                        that position?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>BROWN: The Sahel was dominant. There was no question. We had obviously other
                    programs of importance in other countries-Kenya, Tanzania and so forth. It was a
                    period for the beginning of programs in the BLS countries: Botswana, Lesotho and
                    Swaziland and we gave a lot of attention to trying to get those programs
                    underway in a meaningful way. There was certainly recognition at that time of
                    the strong and deleterious impact of the relationships with South Africa on the
                    rest of the countries of Southern Africa. But I would say there were no major
                    new initiatives of any kind. We did get AID levels up as a whole, not just in
                    the Sahel but AID levels in Africa. And that was because of increased interest
                    in Congress, by the administration and by the people in African problems as a
                    whole. And that, in itself, was something of an accomplishment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You spent a lot of time on the Hill, I guess, during this
                        time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes, I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would you characterize your experience with
                        testifying?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Very diverse.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very diverse I'm sure.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I have had some very hard experiences in the face of people who simply did
                    not believe from two different perspectives: those who simply did not believe
                    that we should be doing what we were doing; and those who simply did not believe
                    that we were doing as much as we should be doing. And I had some very
                    sympathetic hearings where people still may have felt we should have been doing
                    more but understood the limitations within which we were working and trying to
                    find ways to be helpful.</p>
                <p>As I have also mentioned in my other comments, the big thing one learns is the
                    importance of Congressional staff. You can't convince a member of Congress very
                    readily on a one-on-one basis. You must work with the staff, both the committee
                    staff and appropriate individual members. And we did an enormous amount of that.
                    Both in terms of meeting with them and bringing them into regional meetings.
                    Making sure they got to travel to programs in the region and the like. It is
                    something I have done a lot of now between that period and later in Egypt.</p>
                <p>It is not something I revel in. I would not want to be a Congressional Liaison
                    Officer, I can assure you that. I have great admiration for IFAD's
                    representative here in Washington who has done a marvelous job in working with
                    the Congress but I would not trade positions with her for anything.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>Summing up on work in the USAID Africa Bureau:</p>
                <p>It was a great honor for me to share the Rockefeller Public Service Award with
                    Dave Shear for our work in the Sahel. This was a recognition I had long aspired
                    to but never felt I would achieve. I thank AID Administrator Dan Parker and
                    others who took the time to prepare a thoughtful and effective
                    recommendation.</p>
                <p>While Sahelian affairs were certainly the center point of my four years as DAA,
                    there was much to do in the rest of the program. As noted earlier, despite
                    considerable public interest in Africa, the United States has consistently
                    devoted little attention to the continent except during emergencies. Some
                    progress had been registered in Anglophone Africa but Francophone Africa
                    remained very much at the margin, except for our efforts in the Sahel. In order
                    to understand better the needs of the continent, I traveled extensively,
                    visiting all but a handful of African countries during that period. We tried, as
                    a result, to bring some greater order into regional planning, with greater
                    emphasis on a narrower range of objectives and with more insistence on attention
                    to the problems of the poor and less on politically inspired physical monuments
                    of dubious value.</p>
                <p>We worked hard to keep the Washington African diplomatic community informed. We
                    spent much time seeking cooperation with State Africa Bureau officials. Much
                    effort went into working closely with PVOs (Private Voluntary Agencies) and to
                    keep the media properly informed.</p>
                <p>I have already stressed the importance of Congressional contacts. This was my
                    first real exposure to the legislative process and it was very revealing. One
                    learned quickly how intricate it could be. As I have said, important as are
                    close ties with members, working with Congressional staff - both Committee and
                    members' staff-is equally critical. While some members of Congress, especially
                    on the Democratic side, were highly dubious as to whether we were doing enough
                    in Africa, especially in response to the Sahel drought, I do feel that I was
                    received with reasonable grace and decency during those presentations I made to
                    Congressional committees and in smaller private meetings. In one hearing Senator
                    Kennedy raised a number of very direct and hard questions to which I responded
                    as best I could - and at the end of the hearing Kennedy made a point of
                    recognizing the limitations which faced us in the Bureau and the efforts we were
                    making to overcome those limitations. I learned a lot about how to work with the
                    Congress during this period that proved highly useful not only then but also
                    later in my Egypt and IFAD experiences.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>My deep preoccupation with these problems left me with less time to think about
                    family issues than should have been the case. While the children had adapted
                    well to life in the United States when they were younger, all three had some
                    re-entry problems now that they were in their teens. Micheline was left too much
                    alone to deal with those problems. Living again in the Maryland suburbs we took
                    little opportunity to enjoy the nicer aspects of Washington life. It seems I
                    managed to get Micheline into the city more by dragging her to endless
                    diplomatic receptions than by taking her to the theater and the like.</p>
                <p>After a few years of this life, both Micheline and I were ready to return
                    overseas. A few opportunities came up, but none seemed particularly promising.
                    However, in early 1976 Johnny Murphy, then AID Deputy Administrator, called me
                    to his office. He told me how important the aid program in Egypt was going to be
                    due to significant political changes and Egypt's potential role in the Near East
                    peace process. He said that a big expansion of the program called for
                    experienced leadership. He noted how much I cared about the development aspects
                    of AID work. Despite the fact that the Egypt program would be highly political,
                    he nevertheless urged that I take on that position. I did not immediately
                    respond but as soon as I got out of his office I called Micheline and we both
                    reveled over what was for us wonderful news - and the next morning I went
                    straight to Johnny to say yes.</p>
                <p>A major new assignment as Mission Director in Egypt-USAID's largest
                    program-1976-1982</p>
                <p>Egyptian-American relations had been cool and distant for many years,
                    particularly during the latter years of the Presidency of Abdel Nasser. Such
                    assistance programs as had existed earlier had all been terminated. Even at the
                    beginning of the Sadat Presidency there remained coolness in those relationships
                    until two events-the “October War” of 1973 in which Egypt for the first time had
                    some decisive military victories over Israel (even if the final outcome of the
                    war was initially a return to the pre-existing situation); and Sadat's
                    termination of a range of relationships with the Soviet Union. From that point
                    forward, Secretary of State Kissinger and President Nixon saw new opportunities
                    to work with the Egyptians, particularly with regard to regional peace. A first
                    major step in that direction was negotiation of the first Sinai accords, which
                    provided Egypt with at least partial recovery of lands lost in the 1967 war.</p>
                <p>It was at this point that the United States announced its intention to provide
                    major economic assistance to Egypt-assistance which almost from the beginning
                    reached $1,000,000,00 a year in combined PL 480 and AID Supporting Assistance
                    funds. It was at this point, facing the high political stakes of this new aid
                    level, and having to move aid levels up sharply in response to the Kissinger
                    announcements, that we arrived in Cairo. (It should be recalled that the initial
                    steps towards seeking regional peace taken by Egypt at that time were then
                    followed up on a relatively consistent basis over following years by the Second
                    Sinai accord, by Sadat's visit to Jerusalem, by the Camp David negotiations and
                    finally by the establishment of diplomatic relations between Egypt and
                    Israel.)</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>As far as I am concerned, being able to manage the Egypt program was the absolute
                    pinnacle of any AID manager's career. Certainly for me, and my family, it was a
                    wonderful experience. While running the biggest aid program since the Marshall
                    Plan was exceptionally demanding, it gave the opportunity to use all the skills
                    which had been acquired over more than twenty years. And while it was true that
                    there were highly political and public elements to what we were doing, we were
                    able to convince both Egyptian and American leadership that an important part of
                    these vast resources must go towards development which could strengthen local
                    democratic institutions and ensure greater equity.</p>
                <p>My first years in Cairo were devoted to the task of making this point with
                    American and Egyptian leadership and then finding the programmatic means by
                    which it could be achieved. The efforts of the AID Mission in that direction
                    were helped by Congressional concern that money should not be an answer in
                    itself but that the program should concern itself with issues of Basic Human
                    Needs (then a central concern of AID's regular Development Assistance Program)
                    and this was built into appropriation legislation. While the USAID Mission
                    certainly did not succeed in meeting all our aspirations in this regard, I am
                    convinced that the program has had a significant impact on the lives of many
                    Egyptians, that it laid the groundwork for increasing decentralization of
                    development decision making and that as a result there was better use over time
                    by Egypt of its own resources.</p>
                <p>But moving the program in that direction took time and effort. In order to commit
                    these high resource levels, substantial amounts were initially devoted to large
                    infrastructure projects-cement plants, power generation and distribution,
                    telecommunications and the like. Food imports under PL 480 also played an
                    important part in easing the Egyptian financial situation and represented about
                    25% of the total aid effort in these years. Although many of these major capital
                    projects contributed substantially to overall Egyptian growth by providing the
                    underpinnings which were critical to expansion of the productive sector, I was
                    not alone in believing that there was need to broaden the impact of the program
                    in order to have a greater direct effect on as wide a range of ordinary
                    Egyptians as possible. As noted, language was inserted in appropriation
                    legislation calling on greater attention to Basic Human Needs. Roy Prosterman, a
                    college professor now with the Hunger Project, was then running a rating of the
                    Basic Human Needs contents of selected AID programs-and the Egyptian program
                    initially achieved an almost zero score. While we had lots of reservations about
                    the way Roy concocted his scores, it meant a lot to all of the staff to see the
                    program receive higher and higher ratings as we moved more actively into
                    agricultural programs; health and family planning activities (it was during
                    these six years that the Egyptian family planning efforts turned population
                    growth from a constantly growing figure to one in major decline); basic
                    education activities with special emphasis on girls' education; low cost housing
                    including AID's largest family centered, do-it-yourself tenement upgrading
                    program; and most particularly for a wide variety of urban and rural based
                    programs of decentralized development activities which brought decision making
                    far closer to those concerned than had ever been true in earlier Egyptian
                    development efforts.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>I am particularly proud of this variety of decentralized development programs.
                    Given Egypt's long history of highly centralized government decision making, I
                    initially had questions as to whether it was in fact feasible to work with and
                    strengthen local government and popular mechanisms. Much credit goes to a number
                    of key USAID staff members who traveled widely and developed strong relations at
                    central, governorate (state) and local level, which in the end convinced me (and
                    others) that there was a real will and capacity to undertake this new approach.
                    Equally, it was helpful for some key Egyptian leaders to find that the United
                    States had a strong interest in the same things which they had been advocating
                    and which could help bring their own ideas into focus and force.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's add bit more on Egypt. Particularly on your interest
                        in decentralization programs. That is of some interest in AID now. How
                        effective was that effort in a highly centralized bureaucratic situation?
                        Was there willingness to really decentralize? Or what was being
                        decentralized?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Egypt of course, is absolutely dominated by the Nile. Everything in Egypt
                    is dominated by the Nile. And for 5000 years the government has promulgated from
                    the center all the rules. And people have not participated. Under Nasser there
                    was some opening up of that.</p>
                <p>There were some efforts at democratization. There were some efforts at getting
                    views from the public on issues of development and issues of interest to them.
                    Although that began to fade in the last few years of the Nasser administration.
                    Sadat was too involved in the broad issues of the Middle East, Egypt-Israel,
                    Egypt and the United States, Egypt's financial situation to really care very
                    much about that sort of thing. I think he was a great man but that was not his
                    strength.</p>
                <p>At the same time, I felt two things. One: while the AID program was having an
                    important impact on certain urban areas and on certain infrastructures of one
                    kind or another, it was important for the people of Egypt to see the results of
                    the Egyptian-American relationship. And that wasn't going to happen by just
                    doing things in Cairo. That there was need to get out in rural areas.</p>
                <p>It was also clearly my feeling that while the Nile would always dominate
                    thinking, more and more people needed to be involved in the decision making
                    process. They had to be there. They had to be represented. They had to be
                    listened to. Decisions could not just be promulgated. You could see some of the
                    failures in the functioning of the Egyptian irrigation system because too much
                    of it was imposed and too little of it was farmer motivated. So, I certainly
                    felt it was important to try and find ways to work with local communities. I
                    wasn't sure at the beginning whether this was possible, because I was afraid of
                    corruption. I mean we knew that there was a lot of corruption in Egypt and were
                    very fearful of it. We were fearful of misuse of resources even if it wasn't in
                    terms of corruption.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>And, as I said, our staff did an enormous amount of traveling at that time
                    talking to people...at all levels, all over the country. And they came back
                    convinced that those with influence at the local levels were more interested in
                    influencing the decisions of the central government than local government. At
                    the same time, they shared some of the things that we were feeling. That is,
                    that it was important at the local levels that there be greater participation.
                    And we came to the conclusion that it was safe to try and find ways.</p>
                <p>There were a couple of institutions in the government that were concerned with
                    local government and local development. They were weak. We worked very hard in
                    trying to improve their capacity. None of this took us very far until a
                    particular person became Minister of Planning. He and I had talked before he
                    became minister — he had been a special assistant to Sadat — several times on
                    this question of decentralization. And he had indicated and had a strong
                    interest in it.</p>
                <p>When he became minister, we pushed and he accepted and he took the lead in
                    working with other elements of government in saying that this was something that
                    was necessary. We couldn't have done anything without him. And from that
                    relationship we sought to devise a series of programs of one kind or another
                    which put resources into the hands of local governments and local citizens -
                    local programs for the development of simple infrastructure based on decision
                    making-organized through the governor of the province in open sessions with the
                    people to decide what they were interested in and where they were willing to put
                    in some of their labor to get these things done.</p>
                <p>Programs of resources, going again through the governors and the governorate
                    system for financing of small scale enterprise of one kind or another. A range
                    of things of this sort. I think they were evidently successful in themselves. We
                    saw a lot of things happen. We certainly had, I thought, the political impact
                    that had been of particular consideration at the beginning. We were beginning to
                    open things up. I think we were getting a lot more people both in central
                    government and locally interested in the concerns.</p>
                <p>What had not happened in my time was any significant enlargement in the
                    governments own resources going out to local government. And obviously during my
                    time we all felt that was absolutely critical. No such program was sustainable
                    only with US government resources. We talked a lot about that. Unfortunately the
                    minister with whom I had been working went and got himself into some
                    difficulties and he was out of power and his successors did not have the same
                    strength of interest as people in the Ministry of Finance who had gone along
                    with this but were still not prepared to see allocation of the resources up
                    until the time I left. Now, I understand that more has taken place since then.
                    I'd love to see an evaluation of that whole process now to see to what degree it
                    has in fact had any significant substantive continuity within Egypt.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But your impression is that there was fairly wide-spread
                        participation in the decision making about the use of resources within the
                        local areas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes. And then I've seen this more particularly in some IFAD projects that
                    picked up on what AID started during that period in which I could see very
                    clearly. We were working in IFAD projects specifically on agriculture at the
                    governorate level. Agriculture which had always been dominated by Cairo. And
                    still is in many respects. But in the IFAD projects some important levels of
                    decision making were in fact shifted to local government officials. Those local
                    government officials were making significant efforts to try and group farmers in
                    one form or another in order to hear them...to talk with them and to respond to
                    them and to get them involved. So, yes...I do think...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this process being institutionalized for as long as
                        AID had money to provide?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Well, as I say, it was being institutionalized but those institutions were
                    not being funded adequately up until the time I left. And I don't know the
                    degree to which they may have been properly funded since then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was any of the financial operation decentralized or was
                        that still very central?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: That is exactly what I am talking about here. The bulk of resources
                    received at the governorate level were received under programs already decided
                    by the central government. There was very little local tax authority. Very
                    little local income generating, very little local influence on what programs
                    would be undertaken. This is what we were trying to change. And that, as I say,
                    required certain block grants or whatever you want to call it. Something to go
                    to the governorate which they would control and which they would decide on. I
                    just don't know the degree to which that...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You found the other ministries were...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Agriculture at first was very resistant. But then Yusuf Wali was named as
                    Minister - he still is the Minister of Agriculture as well as Deputy Prime
                    Minister. In AID we had only a limited period to talk decentralization issues
                    with him, but again, IFAD was picking that up. And IFAD has worked exceptionally
                    well with him and he has been fine in this area. The Minister of Education at
                    the time was very good in accepting proposals on our part first to look at
                    educational mapping to try to get a better idea of where schools were in
                    relationship to kinds of populations and then how schools could be built which
                    were responsive, both to centrally seen deficiencies and to local initiatives.
                    And he was very involved in that.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>While strong support existed in the US Congress for what we were doing, it was
                    somewhat startling when a Reagan appointed Assistant Administrator criticized
                    these efforts as “simply building new levels of government”. Given the thousands
                    of years when Egyptian leadership focused its attention around central control
                    of the Nile, one must recognize that little can be accomplished in Egypt by
                    ignoring government. But much was possible aimed at broadening public
                    involvement and support and that, it seemed to us, was more important than
                    simply seeking to eliminate layers of government.</p>
                <p>Over the years, then, we introduced a range of different programs and projects
                    which supported efforts at decentralized decision making. First was a program to
                    provide governorates (states) with resources for small scale, local rural
                    infrastructure in which public participation could be readily assured. While
                    there is no question that some Governors failed to understand the importance of
                    participation, others responded wonderfully and did excellent work. Second was a
                    program of small loans for investment in small scale rural enterprises - either
                    private or public but which had been agreed upon at local levels and accepted by
                    governorate administrations. A somewhat similar program aimed at supporting
                    small scale urban enterprises was rather less successful since it became far too
                    immersed in local politics.</p>
                <p>Finally came a program of support to locally initiated small-scale urban
                    infrastructure projects, initiated at the community level-local roads, school
                    improvements and the like. In addition to placing substantial resources into
                    programs specifically designated as supporting decentralization, other technical
                    programs emphasized the same theme. Thus a nation wide program for strengthening
                    basic education, especially for young girls, worked through decentralized
                    planning mechanisms. Much of AID's family planning programs had a similar basis
                    and initial efforts in greater emphasis on decentralized agricultural
                    undertakings were also part of our efforts. Initially little in the way of
                    Egyptian resources (other than leadership at the local level) was devoted to
                    support of these programs, but by the time I left Egypt there was a clear
                    increase in Egyptian financing -and I hope that is something that has continued
                    since that time.</p>
                <p>While proud of what we achieved in supporting equitable development, I achieved
                    far less in an area of concern to both Republican and Democratic
                    Administrations, that of strengthening the private sector. While I certainly
                    shared that objective, I felt that we were being asked to put too much emphasis
                    on direct support to the private sector rather than seeking better to reform the
                    policy environment in which the Egyptian public sector functioned-and the
                    positive impact that public sector reform could have on incentives for the
                    private sector. I felt strongly that without a more level playing ground between
                    public and private investments, the private sector was unlikely to undertake
                    useful productive investments no matter what other incentives might be
                    provided.</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>Public sector industry in Egypt is to be found everywhere. From the time of
                    Nasser it has been heavily subsidized. It depended on resources from the
                    Treasury rather than from the banking system, meaning that there were no
                    effective means for rationing resources into the most productive activities.
                    This is why the USAID argued strongly that we should put much more emphasis on
                    seeking to bring about reforms which would make public sector companies act on a
                    par and equal footing with the private sector. I felt this was a more effective
                    way to strengthen private investment than by providing direct financial and
                    other support to private investors while castigating the public sector. I did
                    not get too far in this direction and I think we achieved far less in the
                    productive industrial sector than should have been possible with the overall
                    resources we had. (However, it is my understanding that we must have made some
                    of these points with Egyptian officials since there has been a certain movement
                    in these directions in more recent years).</p>
                <p>There were two outstanding US Ambassadors in Egypt during this time-first Hermann
                    Eilts, then Leroy (Roy) Atherton. Hermann was a highly able Arabist, an
                    intellectual, a distinguished diplomat, and an activist. He wanted everything
                    done right - and quickly. At first he was hesitant about me, questioning whether
                    I would be sufficiently politically responsive. We developed a close and highly
                    effective relationship after I showed him that the USAID could respond rapidly
                    and with considerable political acumen in ticklish periods. One example was a
                    package we put together out of existing resources but which we could sell as an
                    important response to Egyptian needs following the food riots of 1976. With this
                    stronger working basis I could then get Hermann's recognition of the importance
                    of equitable development-of assuring that a reasonable part of AID resources
                    were devoted to programs that could have a broad effect on the lives of ordinary
                    Egyptians - and what we could do to nurse it along. He became, over time, a
                    strong advocate of what we aimed at - and gave me personally his full support
                    while avoiding being overly directive. Roy was also an accomplished diplomat
                    with substantial experience in the Middle East. He was a lower key manager than
                    Hermann, but that did not diminish his effectiveness. He came with greater
                    appreciation for what aid programs could do and was consistently supportive of
                    the USAID programs.</p>
                <p>It was not easy working for different masters - AID and its leadership, State and
                    its leadership, and Ambassadors in the field. Both Ambassador Eilts and
                    Ambassador Atherton made all these problems far easier than might otherwise have
                    been the case -and they did this at a time when changes of an enormous character
                    were taking place in Egypt and in the region as a whole which called on all of
                    their diplomatic skills. I am deeply appreciative to both of them for that
                    period.</p>
                <p>The entire USAID team was outstanding. We were able to draw on the highest levels
                    of skill throughout the agency and many people made real sacrifices in order to
                    join the staff. Of major help to me was my Deputy Mission Director, Owen Cylke.
                    Owen was a constant source of ideas, new approaches, enthusiasm, and spirit. We
                    simply could not have done as much as we did without his major
                    contributions.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>John Hannah was AID Administrator when I was appointed to Egypt, but the election
                    of 1976 brought in Jimmy Carter and a new AID Administrator, John Gilligan. I
                    had little opportunity to get to know him except for one very brief visit he
                    made to Cairo. Being so occupied by changes he was seeking to bring about in
                    AID/Washington, and beset by considerable bureaucratic infighting taking place
                    within AID and between AID and other agencies at the time, support out of AID/W
                    was weak and contradictory. I had a couple of run-ins with some of the new
                    senior AID/W staff who, I felt, were undercutting me personally and, in some
                    cases, taking broad swipes against Mission Directors as a class (the “pots and
                    pans” campaign was an example of the latter). We survived that and continued to
                    build the program effectively. But it was a great relief when Doug Bennet was
                    named Administrator. Doug not only took on a deep personal interest in the
                    program but he provided me and the whole USAID staff with an enormous sense of
                    support and understanding. I have thought of him as a real friend ever since and
                    have called on his help on several occasions in more recent years. When a new
                    Republican Administration was elected, Peter McPherson became Administrator.
                    Peter also took a deep personal interest in the Egypt program. He visited us a
                    few times (once at the airport between 2 and 4 am on New Year's Eve!) and was in
                    regular touch. While I felt that Peter's emphasis on the private sector was
                    perhaps partly ill-placed for the reasons I have already mentioned, I did
                    welcome his close and constant attention.</p>
                <p>Another person who was always thoughtful and helped overcome many roadblocks was
                    Joe Wheeler, serving first as AA/Near East, then as Deputy Administrator, then
                    as AID Counselor. He had a clear understanding of the many incongruities in the
                    Egyptian economy and what this meant in terms of our program content. He worked
                    hard at seeking to assure agency wide support for our efforts. He worked well
                    with Egyptian officials who were well impressed by his sharp mind and his broad
                    understanding. While we had occasional differences (one always had differences
                    over a program as vast as that in Egypt) Joe and I worked well together.</p>
                <p>We had one amusing incident with Joe -he, his wife, Micheline and I were making a
                    trip into southern Egypt. Without prior notice we dropped in on a small village
                    to see how social services were functioning. Among other things, the four of us
                    walked into a primary school. The moment Joe entered the room, children started
                    screaming and leaping out the windows. It was only afterwards that we learned
                    that an inoculation team had been there the week before and the kids assumed
                    Joe, in his suit, was going to stick nasty needles into them once more.</p>
                <p>The Egyptian economy was a series of major contradictions. Many policies were put
                    in place during the Nasser period which were intended to help the poor,
                    especially the rural poor, but which had become so distorted or corrupted that
                    they were serving largely the elite and an urban middle class. Subsidies on
                    bread certainly were important to the poor but were provided to the whole
                    populace, to the point where bread became the cheapest available poultry
                    feed-but at an enormous budget cost which drained resources from programs that
                    might really have been more helpful to the poor. Subsidies on fertilizer, again
                    intended to help poor farmers, seldom reached them and were siphoned off by
                    large holders - but the prices paid to small farmers for their crops remained
                    low on the assumption they got the fertilizer subsidy. Enormous subsidies on
                    energy - electricity, gasoline, etc.-were far more beneficial to the rich than
                    the poor and diverted use of energy away from petroleum exports and foreign
                    exchange earning exports. Subsidies to public sector industry became so high
                    that several Egyptian economists estimated that it would be cheaper to import
                    fertilizer and to continue to pay the salaries of one particular fertilizer
                    factory than to keep it open if one calculated the real costs involved. It was
                    the business of the international community - the World Bank, IMF and AID in
                    particular-to try to convince Egyptian leadership of the need for change. This
                    was certainly not an easy task and in the end only the beginnings of reform took
                    place during my period. However, our continued insistence on the need for
                    reform, especially of such items as energy subsidies and narrowing eligibility
                    for food subsidies, did appear in following years to have more meaningful
                    effects on Egyptian economic policy-or at least that is what my former Egyptian
                    colleagues tell me now. But this demand for reform did place USAID leadership in
                    a difficult position- on the one hand, we needed to respond to AID/W
                    expectations for reform (expectations often expressed in the form of possible
                    quid pro quos) at the same time that the political forces of the Embassy and
                    State wanted maximum levels of stability in our relations with the Government
                    since the search for peace in the region was to have priority. I give credit
                    both to Hermann Eilts and to Roy Atherton for their help in defending what we
                    were trying to do and the way in which they assisted in the negotiation process
                    with the Egyptians ( while still telling me to keep it as cool as I could). I
                    did feel that AID/W (and IBRD/IMF) held some wrong priorities as to which
                    subsidies to fight. Particular pressure was applied to adjust bread prices.
                    Although those prices were obviously out of line, and the subsidies were
                    universally rather than selectively applied, there is no question the poor did
                    benefit - far more, for example, than from energy subsidies. The argument that
                    adjusting bread prices to give a greater incentive to grow wheat was also
                    probably wrong, since Egypt's agricultural comparative advantage did not lie
                    with wheat but with other products which could better bear the heavy cost of
                    irrigation water-and 95% of Egypt's agriculture depends on Nile water. When the
                    Government, in a badly organized maneuver, did seek abruptly to adjust bread
                    prices, major riots with many deaths took place. Not only were the adjustments
                    then withdrawn, but the political repercussions of that ill-thought-out venture
                    remained in the forefront of thinking of Egyptian and American political
                    leadership. It is true that the donor community also emphasized the need for
                    reform of the energy sector and I am informed that much more has taken place in
                    that regard in recent years. One issue on which I simply could not give support
                    to Egyptian leadership concerned land reclamation, i.e. expanding the irrigated
                    area into the sandy desert regions on the edge of the Nile Delta. I argued that
                    standard cost/benefit analysis could not support such investments. My Egyptian
                    colleagues responded in rhetorical terms that population increases, etc.
                    required provision of more agricultural land and they also argued that there
                    were hidden costs (urban infrastructure, etc.) that were being borne because of
                    this limited land availability. I urged my Egyptian colleagues to establish a
                    hard and satisfactory economic analysis going beyond standard cost/benefits
                    which could take their concerns into account and which could show a real
                    economic betterment to be achieved through land reclamation. That simply was not
                    forthcoming and the justification was almost always simply in nationalistic and
                    political terms. On one visit of Doug Bennet and Joe Wheeler we went to see
                    President Sadat at his home in Suez. On the way Doug and Joe spelled out all the
                    arguments they would use with Sadat against Egyptian reclamation policy. When we
                    arrived, Sadat was sitting on a lawn by the Suez Canal. He arose, walked to us,
                    escorted us back to where the chairs were gathered and immediately went into a
                    long defense of reclamation - to the extent it seemed to sweep Doug and Joe off
                    their feet since none of their well planned counter-arguments ever got
                    expressed. I did my best to find ways to satisfy in part the lust for
                    reclamation work through some limited research programs aimed at testing out
                    best agricultural practices for different reclamation activities, but my best
                    Egyptian friends still call me that anti-reclamation type.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>One thing we all learned quickly was the need to deal with the media (Egyptian
                    and international) and also to back up high level US Government officials and
                    Congressional delegations (CODELS) during their visits. Working with the
                    Egyptian press and radio/TV was not particularly difficult, but American media,
                    especially TV, made a real effort to trip us up over difficult issues. I am
                    thankful that I had had some exposure to the media over Sahelian matters during
                    my time as DAA/Africa and managed to minimize problems which might have
                    resulted. In some cases I managed to reach an understanding with a TV or radio
                    interviewer over the major issues to be discussed so I could be reasonably
                    prepared. In other cases, however, questions were raised which were really
                    rather out of bounds and responding was difficult and since the interviewer had
                    the power over what was included and what was excluded from the final broadcast
                    product, one could always find oneself appearing to say things which were not
                    what was meant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else on the Egypt experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Well, a big concern I felt was that Egyptians tended to assume that things
                    would never change. I feared that there could be a sudden or a rapid decrease in
                    US economic assistance without preparation on the part of the Egyptians as to
                    what would be the impact and implications on their own operations. That decrease
                    hasn't taken place. But you never know in this world now. Certainly there has
                    been a decrease in IDA support. The World Bank provides no IDA support to Egypt
                    at this time. And while our work seems legislatively sacrosanct at the moment,
                    that could change at any time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is this sort of an almost artificial support effort for
                        Egypt that leaves them at high risk?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: In a sense. Not in my view as nearly as high a risk in terms of its
                    intrinsic role in the economy as that with Israel. But in the Israeli case they
                    are probably better protected from change than is true for Egypt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: There are a lot of people who broadly support AID to Egypt that are sort
                    of uneasy. They don't quite understand why. They understand why AID to Israel.
                    They don't understand why such high levels to Egypt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved in the issue of why not make the
                        Egyptian program simply a cash transfer like we do for Israel?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>BROWN: This is where I had a lot of difficulties with both some of my closest
                    colleagues in the Congress and with a number of them in Egypt itself. I was
                    certainly prepared to see certain areas made into block grants. However, I felt
                    it was important, for political as well as development purposes, that the United
                    States continue to have a role, a function, in the decision as to how resources
                    would be used. And I felt that until the Egyptians were better prepared to
                    support the institutions and the funding arrangements to support programs for
                    the people, that if there were a shift to block grants of any kind it would not
                    work. Now, can we do better in sectoral or perhaps geographic grants of some
                    kind where we reach broad agreements on how resources should be used and then
                    move ourselves out of the center? I think that is very possible. And I don't
                    think it has been pursued very much. I was not encouraged to pursue it when I
                    was there. Either people wanted to have full control or there were these others:
                    Jim Bond was one with whom I argued for years on this one...who wanted to just
                    turn it over: you know, it is a political gift and it is a political sale let's
                    take care of it that way. So, I wasn't given much encouragement on sectoral
                    lending or sectoral grants.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What have you perceived as the change or increase in
                        capacity of the Egyptians to manage a major program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Oh, I think they have been substantial.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are they in a better position now to do that sort of thing
                        than before?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Substantial. Much deeper understanding of the need to deal with the
                    reality of economics. There are institutional improvements: the structure of the
                    Ministry of Agriculture has shifted to be much more responsive to the needs of
                    farmers. A variety of things of that sort where I think, yes, there is the
                    capacity, and importantly to me and this is why I would have even liked to try
                    regional block grants was the growing strength of capacity at the governorate
                    level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But some people describe the bureaucracy as very rigid and
                        impossible to deal with and function in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: It is very difficult. It is very difficult. And certainly that is true for
                    ordinary daily issues-daily problems-getting your permit, getting your
                    this...getting something else. It is almost impossible to find the right people
                    in the bureaucracy and when you do it is almost impossible to get what you need
                    without some kind of baksheesh. In that sense the rigidity is there.</p>
                <p>But at the leadership level I think there is much greater creativity and
                    thoughtfulness. I think they can do all right on their own without much
                    difficulty. I would like to see them give greater attention to what it would be
                    like if they didn't have that American aid supporting them.</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else on Egypt at this point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: High level visits were an enormous demand on staff. It seemed that CODELs
                    in particular did not want to visit Israel on the Sabbath and therefore made it
                    a point to use the weekends for their Cairo stops - meaning an even longer week
                    for the staff than usual. Some delegations were thoughtful and well briefed.
                    Others simply expected the staff to be their purchasing agents in the bazaar.
                    Others were very demanding but clearly deeply interested and we welcomed seeking
                    to respond to them. I remember one Congressman from New York who required that
                    he be supported by two Embassy/AID Control Officers because of the wide range of
                    his interests - and he was right.</p>
                <p>Visits by Secretaries of State, Agriculture and the like were a huge burden,
                    although tending to affect the Embassy rather more than the USAID. Presidential
                    visits, of which there were several, were even more demanding for the whole
                    staff. One particularly charged period was for the funeral of assassinated
                    President Anwar Sadat. For this three Presidents (Ford, Nixon and Carter)
                    attended, along with previous Secretary of State Kissinger and then Secretary
                    Haig. I was assigned as Control Officer for President Carter and Micheline
                    provided support to Ms. Carter. I must say I found it a delight to serve Carter
                    who acted in an extremely pleasant and gentlemanly manner and Micheline has the
                    same reactions to her work with Ms. Carter. Micheline was also envied by all the
                    other women members of the American delegation since Ms. Atherton arranged for
                    her to sit with her, Ms. Sadat, Ms. Nimeiri of the Sudan, the wife of the
                    deceased Shah of Iran, Ms. Carter and herself during the funeral
                    proceedings.</p>
                <p>At a dinner among the American party, the three Presidents each made short
                    speeches. President Nixon lauded (perhaps for the first time in his life) how
                    American diplomats were so good in their treatment of Presidents - but forgot to
                    say anything about Sadat. President Ford made a rather maudlin and unfocussed
                    statement. Jimmy Carter made a moving and thoughtful speech which was just right
                    in its assessment of Sadat.</p>
                <p>The whole family loved our time in Egypt. Our oldest, Alain, was then at the
                    University of Colorado, but spent one semester at the American University of
                    Cairo (AUC) and made several vacation period visits. Dean did a year at AUC
                    before going back to the States for university studies and Christopher finished
                    his high school studies in Cairo and then spent two years at AUC. Christopher in
                    particular has a wide range of Egyptian and other classmates who remain his
                    close friends to this day.</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>Micheline loved it. She learned to speak Egyptian Arabic because she could not
                    stand being in such a wonderful city without understanding everything possible.
                    She explored Cairo from end to end-one of our Thanksgiving days was spent with
                    her taking me on a walk of the old city from the Western Gate to the Eastern
                    one, stopping at innumerable different shops, museums, mosques and the like
                    where she was known. We traveled extensively - both on official activities and
                    on private trips. We visited all of the Nile Valley from end to end. We had a
                    series of visits to the Sinai once this was back in Egyptian hands and had one
                    particularly spectacular visit to Mount Sinai and to Ras Mohamed. Petroleum
                    company friends arranged a one week visit to “the New Valley”, the series of
                    oases west of the Nile with half a dozen fascinating but seldom visited towns.
                    Our last major trip was to Siwa, the western most oasis and one that we could
                    visit only in our last year because of earlier security considerations.
                    Alexander the Great visited Siwa and there are some who claim he is buried
                    there.</p>
                <p>Throughout our stay we were overwhelmed by the friendliness and openness of our
                    Egyptian friends. They welcomed us into their families and homes and made us an
                    integral part of their lives.</p>
                <p>At one point Micheline criticized me harshly (and rightly). We had gone to an
                    official dinner. Our Egyptian hosts took me off to the head table and I simply
                    left Micheline to fend for herself. She did so, but then told me in no uncertain
                    terms that I was becoming too self-centered in the glory of my functions as AID
                    Director. I tried from then on to be less obsessed with my self-importance.</p>
                <p>As already noted, Egypt was a wonderful experience for all of us. While I knew
                    that after six years change was due, it was hard for us to accept that our time
                    there had come to an end. Certainly I did not foresee any future assignment in
                    AID which could be as stimulating, as exciting and as much pure fun as our six
                    years there. Still, it was time to move on.</p>
                <p>A brief period in USAID/Washington and service as the Executive Director of the
                    Commission on Peace and Security-1982-1983</p>
                <p>Peter McPherson, USAID Administrator, understood that I hoped to be able to find
                    a function outside of AID and he was very helpful in that regard. It took a year
                    to settle on such an assignment, as Vice President of IFAD. In the meantime,
                    while trying to find the right opportunity for me, Peter asked me to serve as a
                    Special Assistant to take on various tasks he wanted done.</p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>During the last several months of my Washington stay, Peter also asked me to
                    serve as Executive Director of the Commission on Peace and Security, the
                    “Carlucci Commission”. This was an interesting period since it gave me a chance
                    to get to know the members of the Commission, including Frank Carlucci himself,
                    Cliff Wharton (then President of the University of the State of New York),
                    several members of the Congress and so on. My brother, Dean, was a member of the
                    Commission and this was the first time since Zaire that we worked on a task
                    together. It is my impression that what Peter McPherson was seeking out of the
                    Commission was a reinforcement of the interrelationships of economic and
                    security assistance ( a view to which I have never fully subscribed myself,
                    although I understand the political usefulness for development aid which this
                    connection once held). He was particularly concerned at weak interest in both
                    the Administration and in Congress for the World Bank soft window - IDA-and I
                    think he saw the Commission as a means for reinforcing that interest. Certainly
                    the final report of the Commission backed up these views-but given the
                    continuing Administration reservations about IDA at that time, the Commission
                    Report was basically buried and little concrete happened as a direct result of
                    it (the Mexican financial crisis of a few years later was far more emphatic in
                    making the Administration recognize the importance of these international
                    financial institutions).</p>
                <p>Appointment as Vice-President of the International Fund for Agricultural
                    Development (IFAD)-1983-1995</p>
                <p>For thirteen years I served as the second Vice President of the International
                    Fund for Agricultural Development (IFAD), following in the footsteps of Phil
                    Birnbaum. I worked with the first three Presidents of the Fund - Abdulmuhsin
                    El-Sudairi of Saudi Arabia, Idriss Jazairy of Algeria and the current President,
                    Fawzi Al Sultan of Kuwait. I think earlier my years working with Arab officials
                    were helpful since I was able to perform effectively with each of these three
                    rather different individuals in circumstances of mutual respect. Working with
                    IFAD was a welcome culmination to a long career devoted to development
                    activities since it centered its programs on concerns which had become
                    increasingly important, in my view, as to what should be the central concern of
                    economic assistance - fighting hunger and poverty.</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>When I joined IFAD it was still a new organization-only five years old-and it was
                    still struggling to establish its own place in the international organization
                    system. IFAD was initially organized as a follow up to the World Food Conference
                    of 1974 with an emphasis on improving food production, and was seen as a
                    particularly attractive instrument for increasing OPEC country participation in
                    the financing of development programs. (In the first rounds of IFAD funding,
                    OECD countries provided about 60% overall funding and OPEC countries came up
                    with about 40%, with other developing countries initially providing only
                    marginal amounts to the Fund's overall resources). IFAD found it necessary to
                    carve out a workable niche in the development field and gradually this came
                    about through a concentration of efforts aimed at overcoming rural poverty. At
                    first IFAD had little new to contribute in programmatic terms and organized
                    poverty programs much as had other donors. But over time, the Fund experimented
                    with a wide range of new approaches (while always seeking to safeguard the
                    financial benefits of its projects, since they were being financed by developing
                    governments with borrowed funds). By the time I left at the end of 1995 IFAD had
                    become an acknowledged leader in dealing with participant oriented and
                    beneficiary planned development efforts which sought to help poor rural people
                    make their own lives better.</p>
                <p>As Vice President, I had a variety of different functions, depending in part on
                    the particular abilities and interests of the three different Presidents that I
                    served. From the beginning I had a strong interest in program content and how it
                    should evolve in a manner which could be most beneficial to poor rural people.
                    My long experience with AID provided me with a rich background which was fully
                    recognized and acknowledged by my colleagues and gave me considerable weight in
                    these program deliberations. For example, I was insistent from the beginning
                    that IFAD should give greater attention to the specific needs of women and must
                    organize its projects and programs accordingly. After some considerable
                    resistance (in that sense IFAD was little different from other development
                    organizations at that time), we got the whole team on board and brought women's
                    concerns directly into the mainstream of all our programming. I participated
                    actively with others in a programmatic evolution which gave increasing emphasis
                    on participatory development, assuring that the beneficiaries themselves played
                    an important role not only in implementation but also in planning of projects
                    which would affect them. At a time when other development agencies were
                    emphasizing market forces, we pursued vigorously the need for targeting - for
                    establishing means which could assure that the impact of projects really flowed
                    to the persons intended.</p>
                <p>All of these programmatic concerns were of deep interest to me and I welcomed
                    opportunities to have my views taken into account. But we also had to
                    demonstrate to the world at large - both donors and recipients-that what we were
                    doing was useful and that it worked. I therefore spent an enormous amount of my
                    time on various aspects of what could be broadly called public affairs.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>Before I even joined the Fund I met with some key Congressional members and their
                    staffers to be sure they found me acceptable in this new role and would be
                    prepared to work with me. I must say that in those first days I found only a
                    small handful of persons in the Congress who knew anything at all about IFAD. We
                    worked very hard to change that and by 1995 we had built very solid
                    Congressional backing on both sides of the aisle. The time I had spent on
                    legislative matters in the Africa Bureau and with respect to Egypt aided me
                    greatly in this period - but so did the strong and consistent support we
                    received from certain members and especially from some key staff
                    representatives. While I concentrated heavily on US support, I was also very
                    much involved with a range of other donors and spent a good bit of time
                    traveling to capitals of actual and potential donors in reaching out for further
                    funding. While occasionally we claimed more than reality, I think that basically
                    we became known for being forthright and honest in our various presentations of
                    IFAD's usefulness and its funding needs and that certainly boosted the Fund's
                    reputation as well.</p>
                <p>As Vice President I also had overall responsibility for overall financial
                    management, including both Treasury and Controller functions. While I had long
                    been familiar with Controller and audit activities, I had never previously dealt
                    with organizational investment programs and I had a lot to learn in this area.
                    For a variety of reasons (generosity of certain donors paying in cash, long lead
                    times between receipt of contribution and disbursements against long term
                    projects, etc.) IFAD gradually built up an important investment portfolio - over
                    a billion dollars-the income on which paid for all the Fund's administrative
                    expenses as well as adding to its committable resources. I can not deny that
                    having responsibility for such important financial resources was scary at
                    times-for example when the Iraq invasion of Kuwait took place and we had been
                    holding important Kuwaiti and much smaller Iraqi investments. Fortunately the
                    three Presidents I worked with were skilled in this area, we had excellent staff
                    work and we developed solid relations with external advisers-and as a result our
                    investment portfolio grew and our income became an important part of our overall
                    operations. I also had responsibility for personnel matters and as I have noted
                    before this took an enormous part of my time as well as that of the President
                    and other senior managers.</p>
                <p>Those thirteen years with IFAD were very satisfying. We were a small organization
                    (about the same number of professionals for a world wide program as had been on
                    the USAID/Cairo staff) with a wide range of nationalities involved. The staff
                    was highly dedicated and motivated, caring deeply about the Fund's narrowly
                    focused attention on rural poverty. We experimented a lot, but did so always
                    recognizing that we needed to keep our borrowers interest foremost. We did
                    become, I believe firmly, what Idriss Jazairy liked to call the Lighthouse of
                    Knowledge on rural poverty issues - a lighthouse whose rays affected the
                    thinking of many other donors and contributed importantly to the way they have
                    now approached the problems of rural poverty.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It would be useful to elaborate a bit more on what you saw
                        as the unique role of IFAD in relation to all other development assistance
                        programs. There was some controversy as to why we needed IFAD, wasn't
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Well, IFAD was born on the basis of bifurcated political interest. There
                    was a world food conference. There was great concern about world food
                    production. There was a sense that something needed to be done. But there was a
                    resistance certainly among several Western countries including the United States
                    to the establishment of any new institution until the OPEC countries indicated a
                    strong interest in being supportive of some kind of new institution which would
                    be deeply concerned with agricultural production.</p>
                <p>While the language of the agreement establishing IFAD makes reference to poverty,
                    that was not initially a predominant consideration. It was agricultural
                    production that was the priority, flowing largely from the World Food Conference
                    concern. But IFAD came into existence more because of the OPEC interest in an
                    institution in which they would have influence and the West's interest in
                    bringing more OPEC money into the development process than for its
                    functions.</p>
                <p>Once it was established, it became important for the Fund to find its own place.
                    The word that was constantly being used within IFAD was its “niche”. What was it
                    that IFAD could do which would over time justify its continued existence,
                    whatever might happen to the OPEC role. This was important since there was
                    growing weakening in OPEC support. Iran had been a major factor in the
                    establishment of IFAD and of course after the revolution, that changed
                    totally.</p>
                <p>Long before my time, senior staff, particularly Assistant President Sartaj Aziz
                    from Pakistan, argued for greater concentration on the poor. For understandable
                    reasons, the first President Al-Sudairi was interested in getting something
                    happening...getting some programs in place so he could demonstrate impact was
                    more important to him than poverty issues. But Artaj-Aziz kept pushing on the
                    need to address poverty.</p>
                <p>When Jazairy became President, after Sudairi's term ended in the seventh year of
                    IFAD's existence, he was deeply interested in both the problems of poverty and
                    finding that niche. And from that point on the Fund devoted the vast majority of
                    its resources to programs that could be demonstrated to have an impact on poor
                    farmers. Now there was always a big argument within the organization between the
                    poorest and poor. You know, some people love to say, “We were serving the
                    poorest of the poor,” without even being even able to define who the poorest of
                    the poor were. I always preferred talking about the poor as a whole because in
                    cultures of this sort, you can't deal with the poorest of the poor by
                    themselves. You have got to deal with larger issues. That is a side issue, but
                    it was one which continues to haunt the Fund.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you give some examples of the kinds of things you were
                        trying to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>BROWN: Everybody talks about the Grameen Bank in Bangladesh. There is no question
                    that Grameen is essentially the work of a brilliant man, Mohammed Yunif. But it
                    was IFAD that was the first international organization to provide support to the
                    Grameen Bank. This to us was an exciting and interesting new approach to how you
                    could get resources into the hands of poor people and especially women. It was a
                    nascent little organization. It was lending to a couple of thousand people when
                    we moved in. I think we helped put it on the map. The World Bank wouldn't touch
                    it when we did. We asked them to appraise the project. They wouldn't do an
                    appraisal much less put any money in it. Now we are out of the bank. We have no
                    need to continue to finance the Grameen Bank because others came along and gave
                    it all necessary resources. But that was an institution that was very much in
                    the heart of the sort of things that we were concerned about.</p>
                <p>We were highly interested in programs with indigenous people. The special castes
                    and groups in India, and particularly in Latin America the indigenous people. I
                    think we devised some programs which sought to be structured within the culture
                    of the indigenous people and sought to respond to how they perceived things
                    should happen, but were also sellable to government to get government
                    support.</p>
                <p>I think that was interesting. Again, we were the first international institution
                    to be able to work with indigenous groups in India. And we, after our first
                    program, we were asked repeatedly to do much the same sort of thing. And I don't
                    think that anybody else from the outside, except some small NGOs, are doing that
                    sort of thing.</p>
                <p>We gave much more attention to traditional crops because these are the crops of
                    poor people. We gave much priority to small scale irrigation, simple irrigation,
                    things of this nature. We were saying look at the issue from the point of view
                    of these people who are poor and what is it that is most needed by them and how
                    can one build it. I think IFAD has helped establish institutions in a number of
                    countries and programs of continuity, whether public or private, which are
                    having a strong impact. The Fund is now looked upon within the United Nations
                    system as the leader in dealing with poverty issues and it is believed that the
                    Fund has more useful things to say about poverty issues than any other agency.
                    One great advantage of all this is we have one issue that we deal with-rural
                    poverty. We have a staff who cares, who are absolutely dedicated to that. They
                    are not thinking about broad economics. They are not thinking about broad
                    financial issues. Obviously they think about those as they impact on poverty
                    issues. But it is poverty that they are concerned about. They are a wonderful
                    staff. They really got it. By the way, excuse my repeated use of “we,” since I
                    have now left the Fund, but you can see from that how much it meant to me.</p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>Now, one major problem for us right from the beginning was Edward Saouma, the
                    Director General of the FAO. Saouma opposed the establishment of IFAD from day
                    one. If it was going to be established, he wanted it to be a part of FAO. He
                    equally opposed, as you know, the establishment of the World Food Council which
                    was also established as a result of the World Food Conference. And as a result,
                    the relations between IFAD and FAO, which should have been enormously fruitful,
                    were weak. It is true there were good relations on working issues of one kind or
                    another. But there was a constant constraint in this because as soon as Saouma
                    learned that things were getting too warm he would cut them off. And it has
                    really been very, very, very sad. Really both institutions would have been much
                    richer. IFAD was trying to repair that. And I think...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jacques Diouf, the present Director General of FAO.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I think Jacques is working on his side to try and repair that. But
                    Jacques, of course, has had his own problems in making sure he got control of
                    that organization. And it had not gotten very far up until the time I left,
                    although the trend is clearly to be closer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Didn't you rely a lot on FAO technical people for
                        technical services?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: We did. The World Bank supported the technical center in FAO which
                    designed projects for the World Bank and to which was added a section to design
                    projects for IFAD. We obviously worked very closely with them. But there was
                    never a meaningful discussion between the heads of the two agencies on “whither
                    go agriculture”. On how can we work better together in the Ivory Coast or some
                    such thing. Never such a discussion. And I just think that was a great, great,
                    great diminishment of what each of us could have done. But that is past and I
                    trust with Jacques things will be better.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else on IFAD you want to say?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: My years with IFAD provided a highly satisfying end to my development
                    career because of its concentration on equitable growth. I am convinced we
                    learned lessons there which need to be applied more broadly by all donor
                    programs - and I am happy to see that this has been increasingly recognized by
                    some of the key players in supporting economic development.That is about it.</p>
                <p>Concluding observations on international development and foreign assistance
                    programs</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's turn now to general observations on your experience
                        in international development. This is a difficult question to answer in a
                        general way, but what aspects did you find work well ? What was important
                        and what do you think had lasting effect that was worthwhile?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Well, I simply believe that the lives of millions-hundreds of millions-of
                    people around the world are better today as a result of the combined efforts of
                    world community working together with respect to development needs in poor
                    countries. Whether that comes from the World Bank or us or from European
                    community members or from Japan or whatever.</p>
                <p>I see the changes that have taken place in life expectancy and the spread of
                    disease, in the availability of education, in the number of university
                    graduates-this sort of thing in Africa for example. It is an enormous change.
                    Not all of it comes from assistance activities. A lot of it comes from domestic
                    efforts in those directions. No assistance is useful without that domestic
                    interest. But there is no question in my mind that a lot of that could not have
                    been achieved without outside help. Outside help financially and outside help
                    technically.</p>
                <p>Now the world has changed a lot. We still view technical assistance too much in
                    traditional terms of sending a technician to do something to help somebody
                    somewhere at salaries which are fifty times higher than those they are supposed
                    to be helping. We all need to rethink that sort of thing. And this is one place,
                    again, where IFAD was very much in a leadership role of trying much more to draw
                    on local capacities for project design and project management and the like.</p>
                <p>But still there have been improvements in people's lives. Now that progress has
                    been affected obviously by corruption in many countries. And I look at a place
                    like Zaire and whatever efforts were put in there, however many millions or
                    billions of dollars were provided to Zaire, people's lives have not improved one
                    whit. And that is because of a leadership that didn't care. There is clearly a
                    critical issue. You are not going to do much unless leadership cares. Unless
                    leadership is prepared to say that equity is an elemental part of development
                    strategy.</p>
                <p>Now that leadership need not necessarily always be the President or the head of
                    state. It can often be institutions and people with influence and whose
                    influence can be enhanced by the relationship with an AID agency over a set of
                    programs which are important. I think that happened with respect to what we were
                    able to do in agriculture in Egypt for example, because we had in the end, two
                    ministers in a row who really cared. And we were never able to do much with
                    irrigation in Egypt because we didn't have a minister there who had the same
                    kind of care.</p>
                <p>So, there is no point in doing anything unless you've got leadership which is
                    supportive of and certainly not taking actions which are detrimental to the
                    development process. But if you can do that, I think it is important to
                    continue.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But doesn't our foreign policy interests-our political
                        interests or security interests compel us to go ahead and do things to
                        support a Mobutu or support a government that doesn't seem to care so
                        much-like Morocco and so on. How did that compromise the AID program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Of course, it does.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It shouldn't be there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Of course, it compromises it. Why did we not meet our security interests
                    in Morocco, for example, which was essentially in the establishment of air
                    bases, through the defense budget. I mean, after all, that is what it was. It
                    was in defense interest. Why didn't we do it? We could make cash grants to
                    Morocco. Whether we made cash grants to them or had programs in the end they
                    were going to use the resources the way they wanted. Why not just give it to
                    them through the defense budget rather than corrupt what was meant to be a
                    developmental effort.</p>
                <p>Zaire is another case clearly where our so-called “security interests” were so
                    predominate that we were willing to put up with anything. I don't know what you
                    do under those circumstances because at a particular time there certainly were
                    security interests.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is your interpretation of our security
                        interests?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: This is where I often have great trouble, frankly, with the analysis of
                    what our security interests are. And how important they are. I stopped arguing
                    the importance of Morocco as a security concern. The entry into the
                    Mediterranean; its access to the Atlantic and the Mediterranean. The
                    availability of facilities for VOA-a whole range of things. But I have always
                    had real questions about how meaningful were those security interests in Zaire
                    and many other countries as well. I think if one cares about development, one
                    would have to make a better effort to separate it from the security
                    interests.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, that poses some real problems in funding. For years and years
                    and years people argued as to whether economic and security aid should be in the
                    same bill or not. Those that wanted them on the same bill ended up winning
                    because it was always felt that you could get enough votes from each side to get
                    a bill through. The problem is that once the major issues — that is, the
                    relationships with the Soviet Union — are no longer a security issue of the same
                    nature, there is no longer a meaningful security development nexus and
                    development needs to stand on its own without having developed a sufficient
                    rationale itself. That should have been done over the last 40 years and never
                    has been done. That leaves the field open for all of those to simply say, like
                    Ambassador Moose did in Sudan, “It is a waste of money.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't have as you said, much of that kind of a
                        political security rationale for the Sahel and that program went
                        forward.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: That went forward.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On a developmental rationale?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: It went forward clearly on a development rationale but to be perfectly
                    frank because the Nixon Administration was facing so many issues in Vietnam and
                    elsewhere that it needed something that would act as a lightning rod to those
                    who could see something positive coming out of that Administration. That's how
                    we got the support.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: And we did get it. At the time we had a Democratic majority in the Houses
                    of the Congress and it was easier to bring them along to support something of
                    that nature. But it worries me that today we may simply abandon the development
                    effort and I think it may be premature to do that. It is certainly premature in
                    Africa to give up that effort. This is particularly true at a time when at our
                    urging — by “our”I mean the United States and the Western communities as a whole
                    — Africans in the direction of democracy and economic reform; just as they are
                    struggling to bring those two almost incompatible policies along, we start
                    withdrawing. And what are they stuck with? Programs which are killing their
                    people without the financial support which could mitigate that problem. And they
                    are facing elections because we insisted upon that as well.</p>
                <p>I believe firmly that close economic ties between developed and developing
                    countries are important - for humanitarian reasons, because of a belief in the
                    need for a more egalitarian world, because our own society can be threatened in
                    the face of inequity-one sees the latter problem increasingly sharply in terms
                    of the difficulties being faced both in the United States and in Europe over
                    migration from poor countries.</p>
                <p>For too long we depended heavily on security considerations as a rationale for
                    financing economic development. The Carlucci Commission was an example of how we
                    sought to relate development and security issues. I certainly played on this
                    theme myself on occasions when I was seeking to assure adequate funding for
                    development purposes. This worked well while the Cold War existed. Without that
                    rationale we suddenly find ourselves floundering for a justification of
                    continued economic aid.</p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>Certainly throughout that period we accomplished a lot, even if we failed to do
                    all that might have been possible. Education and health facilities improved,
                    diseases were overcome, longevity increased, and while the numbers of the poor
                    increased their percentage of overall populations went down.</p>
                <p>The American people face a quandary at this point about what role the United
                    States should play. Sympathetic to the plight of those facing disaster
                    situations, Americans have insisted consistently that the United States respond
                    in proper fashion. But Americans have far less understanding of the need for
                    development as such - and how development can arrest or at least lessen the
                    potential impact of disaster. India is certainly a case where development,
                    particularly of agriculture, has virtually eliminated the potential for a
                    national food disaster. That is an example we need to share with those who
                    question economic cooperation. If others share my concern about the continuing
                    need for the United States and other nations to play a role in helping the less
                    fortunate of this world, we need to find new ways to express that need.</p>
                <p>Over the years I have concluded that while the United States has a responsibility
                    for supporting the development efforts of poor countries it is not enough simply
                    to foster higher growth rates. Too often accelerated growth has been detrimental
                    to large parts of developing country populations and has led to greater
                    mal-distribution of national wealth. I have become convinced that growth and
                    development are often meaningless unless they are accompanied by a major effort
                    to help the poor make their own lives better-to increase rather than to lessen
                    equity. That does not diminish the importance of growth since it is clear no
                    society is willing to make the sacrifices to share existing wealth more
                    equitably and that equity can be achieved only through a fairer distribution of
                    higher income levels.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's narrow our focus to USAID. Where do you see
                        AID over the years and the foreign assistance program in relation to the
                        international development effort? Was it particularly unique or was it just
                        one of the crowd?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Well, one thing is clear, and that is that over the years AID became a
                    major center of knowledge. There is no question in my mind of that. I mean, the
                    depth of our field staffs, the depth of our strategy analysis, the depth of our
                    technical analysis means that we know an awful lot about the development
                    process, globally, regionally and nationally. Somehow or another that has to be
                    maintained.</p>
                <p>I certainly accept some of the themes that AID is promoting at the moment and it
                    needs to have... it needs itself to have a niche now. It needs to have a role
                    within the development function which is complementary to but separate from that
                    of the World Bank, the IMF and the regional banks.</p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>The whole concept of development however, needs greater understanding and greater
                    support because it is not just AID that is under attack-it is the World Bank, it
                    is the regional banks, it is everybody and it is not just the United States. It
                    is increasingly happening even in those European countries which have been at
                    the forefront of development support. And there simply has to be a greater sense
                    of unanimity about what the development process is about. I have been arguing
                    for the last several years in various speeches here and there that poverty, the
                    alleviation of poverty, must be a major focal point.</p>
                <p>Now maybe that is just because I was working for an agency whose primary concern
                    was poverty but I continue firmly to believe that the public in wealthy
                    countries can react to and be supportive of something which deals with poor
                    people. Maybe not in their own country very well, which is what is happening in
                    the United States at the present time. But they can with people who are much
                    poorer in poorer countries. But they need to know that any effort is not just a
                    palliative but is effective. And we need, as agencies, to stop fighting each
                    other and to find more effective ways together to deal with problems of poverty.
                    And unless we do that, I do feel that the development effort will be finished
                    before the 21st century.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the topic of poverty has been on the agenda off and
                        on. The World Bank says they are committed to poverty and people are asking
                        what is inhibiting everybody to really address this issue.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Oh, yes. All you have to do is look at World Bank projects and you know
                    they are not really dealing with poverty. They are dealing with development
                    which they say will then reach poor people. They disapprove of targeting. How
                    the hell do you deal with poor people unless you make some effort to say, “These
                    are the people we want to reach. These are what they need and therefore we have
                    to have the structures and the institutions etc. which will get those resources
                    to them.” And if you simply say, “Well, here's a wonderful piece of land and
                    some poor people on it and therefore we will develop this land”, it isn't
                    necessarily going to get to the poor. There is not a cohesive sense of what this
                    is all about. Targeting is as critical to poverty alleviation as getting the
                    policies right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A lot of people say at first you have got to get the
                        policies right, you have got to get the prices right before you can help the
                        poor. Or otherwise it won't work.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>BROWN: I think those are important issues. But if you start by talking in terms
                    of helping the poor, you must be sure the policies you are “getting right” are
                    not going to have a more detrimental effect on the poor than on anybody else.
                    But that's not what's happened. The poor are the ones who have suffered the most
                    by every economic reform. I expect that they will suffer. It is inevitable when
                    you've got the kind of massive change that some of these reform programs call
                    for, that there will be harm. But unless there is a conscious effort to build
                    into those reform programs themselves activities which help the poor, then there
                    is going to be damage. There is going to be deep damage. So, no, you cannot
                    convince me that the World Bank, despite all of the statements that it makes is
                    fighting the problem of poverty or at least in the right way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the other agencies generally within the development
                        community?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Regional banks are even worse than the World Bank. The World Bank at least
                    says the right things and tries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the bilateral donors?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: They vary. Unfortunately some who care about poverty often go to the other
                    extreme of not worrying about broad policies at all. Some donors have been
                    prepared to put money into institutions no matter how badly or stupidly the
                    government is allocating and using its own overall resources. That is an extreme
                    statement, I accept.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you said one of the keys is that you had to have
                        leadership who cared and how do you deal with that issue?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Well, leadership in poor countries has become much more conscious of the
                    need to deal with poor people. They are much more conscious of dealing with
                    women for example. Much more conscious of dealing with the environment. When the
                    West first started talking environment to poor countries they all said, “No!” or
                    if you are going to do anything about environment you are going to pay for it on
                    top of everything else. Now I hear major officials in many developing countries
                    taking full cognizance of the need to deal with environment and to use whatever
                    resources are available to do that as part of their development effort.</p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>Certainly I've seen much more attention to the problems of women. Because these
                    are two issues in which, truly, the United States and Western countries have put
                    a lot of attention in their aid programs. But I still don't think either donors
                    or developing country leaders really — despite the rhetoric — put very much
                    attention to poverty. This is why IFAD to me is so important. It is the
                    institution which is doing it and which is showing others what is possible and
                    the way they ought to go about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's wrap it up with one last question here. What
                        would your advice be to someone who said, “Mr. Brown, you have been overseas
                        in many missions, you have been mission director and so on...what advice-I'm
                        going out to be mission director in some developing country. What advice
                        would you give me on this assignment? How can I do my job well?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Be smart and think out your problems. But being smart means making sure
                    you are able to deal with all the others who are dealing with those
                    problems-whether that be national government officials, your own mission, your
                    ambassador, your assistant administrator back in Washington, your Assistant
                    Secretary in State, whatever it may be. You have got to build a sense of
                    teamwork towards the objectives you are aiming at. Without that you are not
                    going to get anywhere.</p>
                <p>I was very concerned when I first went to Egypt — that Hermann Eilts was really
                    very leery of having me around. It was through a number of things that we were
                    able to do together that we became a team. And then I could count of his
                    political support and he could count on my responsiveness to his political
                    issues while also dealing with development. I think that is terribly
                    important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But in terms of development strategy or policy-anything
                        particular in that? Obviously that depends upon the situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Obviously your development strategy depends upon the situation. Don't
                    think that you come as a mission director with wonderful new ideas that have
                    never been thought about before. People have probably thought about all of the
                    ideas you have and may have designed many programs some of which were successes
                    and some of which were failures. Take that into account. Don't think that you
                    are going to come and bust up programs and change programs and change directions
                    because you are smarter than the past. Maybe you are...but you've got to keep
                    that past in mind.</p>
                <p>And then you've got to build some kind of a broad, coherent strategy as to where
                    you want to go. You may not have all of the pieces of that strategy but you have
                    to have at least a broad sense of where it is you want to go. But that strategy
                    has to sufficiently flexible that with changing circumstances you can change the
                    pieces that have to go into it.</p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>I seldom said openly that my strategy for Egypt was, in fact, to try and do the
                    best I could to help poor people. Because if I had put that up front, those
                    concerned with politics would never have trusted me an inch because they would
                    assume I would not have been responsive to what they wanted to achieve with the
                    Egyptians.</p>
                <p>So the underlying interest in the poor was always there. We concocted
                    decentralization programs because they had a real development meaning but also
                    political impact. When we had to do larger infrastructure things, we tried to
                    find ways to insure that the needs of the poor would be least damaged by taking
                    over of land or whatever it might be. And perhaps benefitted. But my views were
                    never articulated, although my close associates certainly understood and shared
                    my view.</p>
                <p>Who Made it Possible</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I think this is it. Is there anything else you want
                        to add at this point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Let me make one last point. An enormous number of people contributed to my
                    ability to make some contributions to the development process. I have mentioned
                    a few of them in these presentations.</p>
                <p>But the most important person throughout has been Micheline Charbonnel Brown. She
                    has been my inspiration, my driving force, my constant supporter. She has been a
                    wonderful mother while also being very much a part of the professional life we
                    led through these many years. Certainly she complained about some of the harder
                    aspects - but then buckled down to what had to be done. She has friends around
                    the world who admire her for her charm, her graciousness, her intelligence, her
                    frankness about all matters and the helping hand she has extended to all who
                    sought it. We have spent a great 46 years together.</p>
                <p>Annex: 1. Brief Biographic Information:</p>
                <p>Born 2 April 1928 in Queens Village, New York. Moved in 1929 to Garden City, New
                    York, and resided there until university.</p>
                <p>Parents and Brothers:</p>
                <p>Father: Lewis P. Brown, Engineer in charge of bridge maintenance, Brooklyn and
                    Manhattan Bridges, New York City Mother: Elizabeth Amy Brown, Secretary
                    Brothers:</p>
                <p>Robert Walter Crossley Brown, lawyer, economist and social scientist.
                    deceased</p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>L. Dean BROWN: Foreign Service Officer Retired, Career Ambassador,Ambassador to
                    Senegal and Jordan</p>
                <p>Marriage and Family:</p>
                <p>After over a year of “pen pal” correspondence (that is another story), married
                    Micheline Charbonnel in Chartres Cathedral, Chartres, France, December,
                    1950.</p>
                <p>Sons are: Alain Bahram Brown, born in Iran, 1955 Dean Michel Brown, born at
                    Wheelus Air Base, Tripoli, Libya, 1958 Christopher Laurent Brown, born in
                    Nairobi, Kenya (when family was stationed in Mogadishu, Somalia) 1960</p>
                <p>Education:</p>
                <p>Garden City schools, high school graduation in 1945.</p>
                <p>Studied Engineering at Cornell University, 1945-1946. Ended the year on probation
                    and decided clearly not an engineering type.</p>
                <p>Antioch College, Yellow Springs, Ohio, 1948-1952. Decided on Antioch because of
                    work-study program (half time on campus, half on the job each year), the liberal
                    spirit, the smaller size. Studied towards working in the field of
                    labor-management relations (and “work” assignments were related to that
                    field).</p>
                <p>American University of Beirut, Summer 1953, part of State Department organized
                    summer program of studies and visits to the Middle East.</p>
                <p>Johns Hopkins Center for International Studies, Washington DC-1956. AID sponsored
                    Program Officer's Training Program.</p>
                <p>Princeton University, Woodrow Wilson School, 1965-1966, AID mid-career
                    training.</p>
                <p>Work History</p>
                <p>Spent 1952 to 1983 with TCA (Technical Cooperation Administration, called Point 4
                    after a fourth point in President Truman's State of the Union speech) and its
                    successor agencies, i.e. ICA (International Cooperation Administration) and AID
                    (Agency for International Development). Since I also had an Antioch Work
                    Assignment with ECA (Economic Cooperation Administration (ECA) which became MSA
                    (Mutual Security Administration) while I was assigned there, I have managed to
                    take part in essentially all the agencies dealing directly and solely with US
                    foreign assistance policy and programs.</p>
                <p>1952-1954-Junior Management Intern, TCA/Washington 1954-1956-Various assignments
                    with USOM/Iran-Special Assistant to the Director, Program Assistant, etc.
                    1956-1958-Assistant Program Officer, Libya. <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                    1958-1961-Program Officer, Somalia 1961-1963-Program Officer, Sudan.
                    1963-1965-Deputy Executive Secretary then Executive Secretary, Administrator's
                    Office, AID/Washington. 1965-1966-Mid Career Training-Princeton University
                    1966-1967-AID Representative, Algiers. 1967-1970-Deputy Director, then Director
                    and Economic Counselor, Zaire. 1971-1972-Director, Morocco. 1972-1976-Deputy
                    Assistant Administrator for Africa, AID/Washington. 1976-1982-Director, Egypt.
                    1982 - With Joe Wheeler, named as AID's first two Career Counselors for
                    Development. 1982-1983-Special Assistant to AID Administrator Retired from AID
                    in 1983. 1983-1995-Vice President, International Fund for Agricultural
                    Development, Rome, Italy</p>
                <p>Awards and Other Functions: AID Meritorious Honor Award AID Superior Honor Award,
                    1973 Rockefeller Public Service Award (shared with David Shear) 1977 AID
                    Distinguished Honor Award 1975 and 1982 AID Distinguished Career Award 1983
                    President's Distinguished Foreign Affairs Award 1983 Order of the Republic of
                    Egypt, 1982 Citation for performance with IFAD placed in Congressional Record by
                    Senator Inouye, 1995 President, Rome International Chapter, Society for
                    International Development, 1989-1994</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
