<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000560">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Dorothy Jester </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Foreign Affairs Series</p>
                <p>CONSUL GENERAL DOROTHY JESTER</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Laurin Askew</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: July 21, 1998</p>
                <p>Copyright 2000 ADST</p>
                <p>JESTER: My first post was Munich, Germany, where I arrived in February, 1946. You
                    can imagine what it looked like. Just rubble covered with snow. But the
                    occupying Third Army took care of people who had arrived to reopen the American
                    consulate general. We were housed in apartments taken over from the Germans and
                    we ate three meals a day in the Army Mess, which formerly was the Haus der
                    Kunst, the art museum. Whatever became of the art we never knew.</p>
                <p>I was the only woman in a group of men, not only from the consulate but from the
                    Army, who took the written exam for the Career Foreign Service in September of
                    1946. In December I was delighted to learn I had passed, but I then had to wait
                    until June of 1947 to take the oral. This was administered by a panel of five
                    men, headed by the legendary Joe Green, who later gave me the happy news that I
                    had passed. But because of budgetary restraints, I could not become an officer
                    and move from my annual salary of $1,800 to a princely $4,300 until June of
                    1948.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened next?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: I was assigned to Mexico City as a junior Foreign Service officer on loan
                    to the United Stated Information Agency. It was because State was still short of
                    funds, or so I understood, that a about 100 FSOs were lent out to other
                    agencies.But I really enjoyed the work of scholarship exchange, essentially
                    screening young Mexican candidates for in-service assignments in some of our
                    government agencies, such as the Bureau of Labor Statistics, the Public Health
                    Service or the Department of Agriculture. I helped other students get
                    undergraduate or graduate education in the United States with the help of the
                    Institute for International Education in New York.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did you stay in Mexico City?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>JESTER: Until 1951, when I was transferred to the American consulate in Mexicali,
                    up on the California border. There I issued visas and passports until 1954, when
                    I was glad to be sent to Managua, Nicaragua, as an economic officer. I was the
                    second in a two-officer economic section, reporting to the Department mostly on
                    agriculture, trade, and labor matters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long were you there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Just a year and half, and then I was transferred back tGermany, this time
                    to Bonn.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And when would that have been?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: In 1956. I stayed in Bonn, as assistant commercial attache, until 1958,
                    when I was transferred to the Department of State for a four-year tour. In 1962,
                    I went to Santiago, Chile, to do economic reporting. On the way to Santiago, by
                    ship, I learned I had been promoted to FSO-2, which was the reason I was only
                    there for a year and a half. The inspectors recommended that I be transferred to
                    a smaller post where I would be head of an economic section. This meant the
                    embassy in Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And how did it work out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: It was fine for about a year and a half. Then, you may recall, there was
                    a rebellion on the island, resulting in American troops being sent in by
                    President Johnson in 1965. All economic work stopped, and the ambassador put me
                    in charge of evacuating American civilians. I remember being on duty at the
                    embassy for 36 hours straight to get the evacuation underway. As things were
                    brought under control, the decision was made to expand the contingent of the
                    Agency for Economic Development, whose local director would also head the
                    embassy's economic section. Ergo, I was surplus. But I was delighted to learn
                    that I was transferred back to Mexico City.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From Mexico City, you retired. In what year was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: I retired officially on November 30, 1971.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: November 30, 1971. Fine. Now let's go back to the more
                        personaaspects of your beginnings.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>JESTER: I was born in Mesa, Arizona, in 1914, but lived in E1 Paso, Texas, until
                    I was about 10, when my family moved to Los Angeles, California. I attended
                    Stanford University, majoring in Spanish. Then I taught it for three years at
                    Anaheim Union High School. At the end of that time I was offered tenure, but
                    somehow it did not appeal to me to stay in that small town the rest of my life.
                    This was well before Disneyland.</p>
                <p>So I turned the tenure down, and just by great fortunate coincidence, almost the
                    same day, I received a letter from a friend in the Education Department at
                    Stanford telling me that some Stanford people who were running the American
                    School in Quito, Ecuador, were looking for teachers. Was I interested? I was,
                    and I went to Quito and taught fourth grade for a year. If I had stayed a second
                    year I could have had my way paid back to the States, but I found the 10,000
                    feet of altitude pretty hard to take. Luckily, at the end of the year I met an
                    engineer from the Pan American Sanitary Bureau. He told me the Bureau was
                    opening an office in Lima, Peru, asked me a few questions about my background
                    and whether I could take shorthand. When I said I could but didn't claim to be
                    fast, he said I could have a job if I wanted it. It was the answer to my
                    prayers!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you said you taught Spanish. Did you start
                        learninSpanish in E1 Paso?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: I learned a lot of Spanish listening to my bi-lingual mother, who had
                    been raised in Mexico. When I got to high school and took Spanish my teachers
                    seemed pleased with my accent. So I decided to major in Spanish and teach it in
                    high school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So already by the time you hit Quito, you were perfectly
                        at homwith Spanish.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: I was fluent, and it helped too with the job in Lima. There I lived with
                    girls who worked in the American embassy. Through them I met other embassy
                    personnel, even attended some embassy parties. I decided early on that when I
                    got back to the United States I would apply for an embassy job. It was January
                    1945 before I returned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: 1945?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Yes, the war was still on. As I had promised myself, the first thing I
                    did was apply to the Department of State. While I waited for an answer, I took a
                    job with an export company in Los Angeles. Sometime in late summer a college
                    friend called and invited me to ride with her across the United States to Fort
                    Bragg, North Carolina, to pick up her husband, now back from overseas.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>From Fort Bragg, I took the train up to Washington. Checking in at the State
                    Department, I was told that there was no money for new hirings. However, I was
                    encouraged to stick around because the situation could change. So I got myself a
                    job in the press section of the Pan American Union. Four months later, in
                    January, I was called by State with the news that there was a new appropriation
                    from Congress to reopen the consulates in West Germany. In February 1946, I left
                    for Munich.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you tell me what year you started in Quito?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: It was 1941. I was there when Pearl Harbor was attacked. I remember
                    breaking into tears over the news. I was away from my country when it was in
                    trouble, and I could do nothing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then Lima.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Yes, I was in Lima from 1942 until January, 1945.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Was it your experience in Quito and Lima that
                        directioyour attention toward the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Oh, yes. Definitely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's then continue on with Munich. Tell us a little
                        biabout Munich.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: I was one of the first three women secretarial staff to arrive.
                    Incidentally, we were in a military plane that had to land in a snowstorm. They
                    actually talked us down by radar, believe it or not. After getting settled in
                    some temporary military housing, we went to call on the consul general, a real
                    character named Parker Berman. Did you ever hear of him?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>JESTER: As he looked us over, he asked if anyone could take shorthand. I spoke up
                    and said I could a little. I'd been doing it in Lima after more or less teaching
                    myself. So I was his secretary for the two years I was in Munich. I had really
                    hoped to be one of his vice consuls. But when I had mentioned this to a
                    personnel officer in the State Department, he had said that unfortunately
                    because I was a woman even my two college degrees were not enough. But he
                    encouraged me to apply to be designated to take the Foreign Service exam. If I
                    passed, I would be on a par with the men.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You passed it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Yes, I took the written in September 1946 and learned in December that I
                    had passed. But I had to wait until June of 1947 to take the oral from a panel
                    that had been around the world, with Munich its last stop. Then, once I had
                    passed the oral, I had to wait until March of 1948, another nine months, to be
                    sworn in as a junior officer. Again, the Department was short of money for
                    officer positions. Isn't that something?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. I wasn't in the Department in those days. Anything
                        more oyour experiences in South America?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: I'll never forget one experience in Lima. One Sunday in 1944, when the
                    war was still very much on, I got caught in a sudden build up of surf at the
                    beach at Herradura (which means horseshoe) and found myself tiring terribly as I
                    struggled in the huge breakers. Suddenly, an arm appeared to get me through the
                    swollen surf to the beach, where I sank in exhaustion.</p>
                <p>It was George Munro, an embassy officer, who had been swimming out beyond the
                    surf and happened to see me silhouetted in the breakers. George had been kidded
                    as giving aid to the enemy for saving a couple of Japanese girls the week
                    before. Now he was fully forgiven for having rescued an American.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go down to Callao?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Yes, a street car went to Callao, the port, and I had friends there. I
                    was too poor to see very much of Peru. I did not get to Iquitos, for example.
                    But I did get to a small town in the mountains. By mountains, I mean it was by
                    road up to, and way beyond, 16,000 feet. I remember once getting out of the car
                    at that altitude and having my knees literally buckle under me. There just was
                    not enough oxygen to stand up on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you going to La Oroya?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>JESTER: Yes. How did you know?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I spent six years in La Oroya.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: You did, really?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's go on to Munich. That must have been a very
                        interestintime there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: It was. As I said, I became the consul general's secretary, and so I
                    didn't have to work on visas. In the front office, of course, I got in on
                    special cases. I can't think of any particular one right now, but they nearly
                    always involved “displaced persons,” as refugees from the war were called. All
                    were trying to get to the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was before the Marshall Plan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: That was definitely before the Marshall Plan, which was announced, I
                    think, in the summer of 1947. Almost overnight you could see a change. Suddenly,
                    goods appeared in store windows that had not been there before. Apparently,
                    there had been some hoarding. But it really sparked the Germans. You know, they
                    are hard working to begin with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you know German or learn German?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: I studied it with a little German professor, and I got up to the “useful”
                    level. You know, the Department had ascending grades of one through five. I was
                    about five in Spanish but only three in German.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then you got to use it again when you got to
                        Bonn.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Right. But in Bonn, as assistant commercial attache, my work was mainly
                    with American businessmen seeking information or contacts. I didn't need German
                    so much at work. It was useful socially, however.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then from Munich did you go back to Mexico City?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: No, it would be the first time in Mexico City.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: 1948 to 1951. What was your responsibility there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: As I mentioned earlier, I was assigned on loan to the U.S. Information
                    Agency, and I worked on student exchange programs. When I was assigned to Mexico
                    City later in my career, I was to see examples of the impact of such programs. I
                    remember once at a cocktail party being introduced to a doctor who was head of
                    the national mental health hospital. He said, “Oh, Miss Jester, you sent me to
                    Johns Hopkins!” I think I was diplomatic enough to say, “No, doctor, you sent
                    yourself. I only took care of the paper work.” I met others who had become bank
                    presidents or were being sent out as ambassadors to Japan and other important
                    countries. It really was a program with impact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right. I think you already mentioned what satisfaction you
                        got from your job there. Now to Mexicali.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Yes. There I had a consular assignment issuing visas and passports.
                    Incidentally, I also got a letter from the personnel office of the State
                    Department saying, “Miss Jester, I hope you understand that when you are in
                    Mexicali you will not be in charge when the principal officer is away, even
                    though you have the rank of consul (as FSO-5), because the Mexicans would not
                    understand. Taking charge will be the vice consul, Mr. Williams.” Some years
                    later, I learned that a copy of the letter was sent to the supervising consul
                    general, Carl Strom, who responded with a blistering letter to the Department.
                    But the old meanie didn't send me a copy.</p>
                <p>Q: Do you think that was motivated by the attitude in the Department toward women
                    generally in the Foreign Service, or was it really a concern of the
                    Mexicans?</p>
                <p>JESTER: That's the way it was expressed, that the Mexicans would
                    nounderstand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is there anything more about Mexicali. Did you have any
                        particulaexperiences that you want to talk about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: No, not that I recall. It was rather nice being in Mexicali for almost
                    three years, because from there it was only a relatively short drive up to South
                    Pasadena, where my mother lived. Then the Personnel Department of State asked if
                    I would like an economic assignment for my next post. I said it sounded great,
                    and so I went as a junior economic officer to Managua.</p>
                <p>It was a two-man economic section. About nine months after my arrival, number one
                    was transferred and I moved up. A vice consul named Donald Easum soon arrived to
                    help. Did you ever hear of him?</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Easum with an S? I ran into him in Madrid.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER. Right. Well, Don Easum was brand new to the Service but was smart as a
                    whip. He had delayed his entry into the Foreign Service until he could finish
                    his Ph.D. in economics. He was immediately an effective officer, and really
                    personable. He has remained a good friend.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any educational preparation? Did you major
                        ieconomics at school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: I never even had a course in economics. But in the Foreign Service you
                    learn on the job. When I was assigned to the Department in 1958 I took night
                    classes in economics at George Washington University, and I soon learned that I
                    could hold my own with graduate students because of my practical experience in
                    the field.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the state of our relations with Managua at that
                        time, ithe 1950s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: It was fine. You may remember a story of Roosevelt talking about Somoza,
                    the dictator, saying, “Yes, he's an SOB but he's OUR SOB.” Actually, he was a
                    very nice person face to face. I'll tell you my first experience with him.</p>
                <p>The day I got to Managua, the ambassador invited me to a party he was giving that
                    evening for the president and his wife and just the embassy staff. I arrived to
                    find chairs and tables around the swimming pool, with a sheltered area at one
                    side for the honored guests and the ambassador and his wife. At one corner of
                    the pool, there was a small band of musicians. The president always took music
                    with him.</p>
                <p>As we happily dined in the lovely tropical evening, the band launched into
                    Mexican music, specifically “Jalisco!” (That is the name of the state of which
                    Guadalajara is the capital.) I had just come from Mexico where I had learned the
                    guitar and many Mexican songs, so I could not resist joining in. Suddenly, I
                    noticed the ambassador summoning me over. He said the president wanted to talk
                    to me. He asked me how I happened to know the song, and I repeated what I have
                    just told you. Then he asked me to go up and sing it with the orchestra. I still
                    have a picture of myself singing into the mic.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>About three weeks later, the Foreign Service inspectors were in town. My
                    housemate, Florence Finne, who was the administrative officer, were at a table
                    with the inspectors at a big party given by the president at the Casino Militar.
                    There was a large orchestra playing. Suddenly, we were aware that President
                    Somoza was walking across the dance floor to our table. He reached for me and
                    took me up to the orchestra, where he and I together sang “Jalisco!” He would
                    break lustily into the chorus but would have me sing the verses. I'll bet you
                    have never met anyone else who sang a duet with a president.</p>
                <p>He was personally very nice. When I was transferred from Managua, the ambassador,
                    Tom Whelan, who was a potato farmer from North Dakota, a man so informal he
                    would not ride in the back seat of his limousine but always up front with the
                    chauffeur, told me we had to go say goodbye to the president, who was again very
                    gracious.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Bonn is next.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Bonn, of course, was much more formal. I was surprised to hear our German
                    employees, who had known each other for years, still address each other as Herr
                    and Fraulein. Our informality as Americans must have been hard for them to
                    understand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the embassy like, or was it an embassy? Wasn't it
                        mission?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: No, it was an embassy by then. The ambassador was James Conant from
                    Harvard, a very able person, who was succeeded by David Bruce, another wonderful
                    man. Both were political appointees.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you had four years in the Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Yes, in the Department I was assigned to the Bureau of Economic Affairs,
                    where I worked on the PL 480 program. That was the program under which we sold
                    U.S. surplus agricultural products to third world countries and took payment in
                    their currencies, which in turn we would use in their countries for our embassy
                    and other expenses. It was a good program, very good. I don't know if it is
                    still in existence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you like the Department, I mean as contrast to the
                        field?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>JESTER: I liked it, but I was always interested in getting to the field again. I
                    bought a home. The dumbest thing I ever did was to sell it when I left after
                    four years, instead of letting it be rented and appreciate in value. That house,
                    which I paid $25,000 for, I sold for $32,000. I think it would be worth around
                    $300,000 now. But I guess I'm not the only one with that kind of story.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I'm another one, but you selected a good
                        location.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Oh, yes. It was just off Reno Road between Connecticut anWisconsin
                    Avenues, a three-bedroom red-brick colonial two-story house.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else about the Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: I remember Ed Martin was head of the Bureau of Economic Affairs. He was
                    friendly and approachable. I also remember Douglas Dillon, who was also in State
                    at that time. I recall once having to get something cleared by him. I went in
                    with some fear and trembling, but he was very nice. The work also involved some
                    contact with other embassies. For example, if we were selling wheat to a third
                    world country, we had to be sure it would not...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Step on Canada's toes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Right. Canada or Australia or whatever. We made sure tclear with anyone
                    that might be affected.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Chile.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: In the embassy in Santiago, I was number two in the Economic Section
                    under a nice fellow named Tom Favel. The work generally involved reporting on
                    local business conditions, trade, the mining industry and agriculture. About a
                    year after my arrival, we had a visit from the Foreign Service inspectors. As I
                    may have mentioned, I had recently been promoted to Class Two. The inspectors
                    decided I was too high ranking for the position in Santiago, and so they
                    recommended a transfer to a post where I would have my own economic section.
                    This turned out to be Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Until they landed the paratroops?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, the Dominican Republic, you say, was in
                        Johnson'administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Yes, this was shortly after the Trujillo regime, and there was an interim
                    government headed by a triumvirate, the chief of which was Donaldo Reed (or
                    Donny Reed, as everyone called him). He was quite a nice person, but he was
                    unable to hold things together, and the place blew apart.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was the man who later was ambassador in Saigon,
                        Bunker?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Ellsworth Bunker, yes. He was sent down to the Dominican Republic to help
                    straighten things out. An impressive man. I was so happy that I got to know him.
                    I remember that he later married a Foreign Service officer named Carol Laise. I
                    never met her. Did you?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I did.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>So it was Santo Domingo till the end of 19657</p>
                <p>JESTER: Not quite. I think I left there about late September, but was headed for
                    Washington to serve on the Selection Boards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then to Mexico City, in January 1966, back to your old
                        stompinground.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Right, January 1966. I was number two in the very large economic section,
                    but four years later I moved up to be head of the section, assuming the title of
                    Counselor of Embassy for Economic Affairs. That's the title I had when I
                    retired.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me a little bit about the business relationships with
                        Mexicat that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: They were fine. I felt we had really good relations with the Mexican
                    government through the various ministries we routinely had contact with. I
                    remember a conversation I had with an officer in the Ministry of Finance, who
                    got on the subject of relative military budgets. I reminded him that Mexico did
                    not need a big military because it had the well-armed United States right above
                    it. He was happy to agree with me.</p>
                <p>At times, my job involved helping businessmen, but only if it was something that
                    the commercial attache felt had a potential problem of a broader economic
                    nature.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>For a while, I was the only woman on the ambassador's country team, but later
                    another female officer named Margaret Hussmann arrived to be the supervising
                    consul general, responsible for the work of the embassy's consular section as
                    well as that of six or seven consulates in other Mexican cities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: He was Robert McBride, a career officer. Yes, I really enjoyed Mexico. I
                    liked it so much that I was not ready to return to the United States when I
                    retired. So I moved to the second largest city, Guadalajara.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Yes. I lived there for 10 years and got to be very active in the American
                    Society and in a group organized to raise money for the symphony. I had many
                    friends among both Mexicans and Americans. We also had a good bridge club. All
                    in all, it was very pleasant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What, if any, one experience stands out in your
                        recollection?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: I can't think of any one experience, but the totality of experiences in
                    Mexico was, for me, the best. I loved Mexico. I still do. However, I don't want
                    to go back to Mexico City, because the beauty of the city is gone. It is so
                    contaminated. When I was there for the first time in 1948, you could see
                    snowcapped volcanoes on any day that it wasn't raining. Now it is a rare sight.
                    It is a shame, but that enormous growth had to bring its problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wonder if we could get back to the subject that we have
                        talkeabout a bit, the position of women in the Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Perhaps you could...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>JESTER: Well, when I went in I understood that there were maybe half a dozen
                    women Foreign Service officers. In fact, when I passed the oral exam in Munich,
                    I later was told that each of the five men on the panel was polled separately,
                    each voting in my favor, until the last man was reached, a former Civil Service
                    commissioner. He stood up and shouted, “Whoopee, I'm vindicated! Apparently, he
                    had been teased for voting in favor of other women candidates who had not
                    passed. They had teased him about being charmed by a nice smile or good
                    legs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was in 1947?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you see a change in the corporate view of women as
                        yearpassed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: I must say that women were never, in my recollection, openldeprecated or
                    insulted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No sexual harassment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: No, no. There was never anything such as we hear of now ithe work place.
                    I certainly never encountered any.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And did you, particularly in the earlier years, feel you
                        were ahome in the embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>JESTER: Oh, yes. The embassy became a very close unit, as you know. You'd be
                    transferred to another post and always find someone there who knew someone where
                    you had been, and you were old friends immediately.</p>
                <p>Q: I found that, too. As a matter of fact, I also found very good quality among
                    officers and staff. Some of the secretaries to ambassadors deserved a lot of
                    credit.</p>
                <p>JESTER: Thank you for letting me participate in the Oral HistorProgram.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
