<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000709">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Peter P. Lord </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>PETER P. LORD</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Lambert Heyniger</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: April 13, 1998</p>
                <p>Copyright 2000 ADST</p>
                <p>Q: Good afternoon. My name is Lambert (Nick) Heyniger and today is Monday, April
                    13, 1998. I am interviewing Peter P. Lord. Peter and I were colleagues in the
                    Foreign Service and I'm looking forward to an interesting and enjoyable
                    interview. So, Peter, to get started, I note from your biography that you were
                    born abroad in Italy. Why was that?</p>
                <p>LORD: I was born of American parents so I have no Italian blood in me although my
                    wife insists that anyone born in a Roman hospital would immediately be baptized
                    in the Catholic faith, of which she is a member and I am not. My father was
                    working as the librarian at the American Academy in Rome. By the time I was two
                    years old, we returned to the U.S. so I didn't learn any Italian.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And don't have any particular memories of it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you can't be president.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: The Constitution says natural born Americans and there is a question as to
                    how that is defined. I assume I could have been president if the occasion had
                    arisen.</p>
                <p>Q: Okay, you returned to where?</p>
                <p>LORD: We lived briefly in Iowa but that was just for two or three years, after
                    which my father became director of the Boston Public Library. So, I grew up in
                    the Boston area, living in Jamaica Plain until 11. We moved outside of Boston to
                    the town of Boxford and occupied a house which had been in my mother's family
                    built on property which the Indians sold to her family in the 17th century. That
                    property is still in the family.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go to school?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>LORD: I went to grade school in Jamaica Plain and Brookline until the fifth grade
                    and then when we moved to Boxford I completed the sixth through eighth grades of
                    primary school there. It was a small country town at that time (in the 1940s),
                    during the war years. There was a two room school house and I was in the
                    classroom which had fifth, sixth, seventh, and eighth grades. So, I was always
                    in that one classroom. There was no high school in Boxford, so I went to one
                    year of junior high school in the neighboring town of Andover before going off
                    to Phillips Exeter Academy in New Hampshire, where I spent four years. This put
                    me a year behind, but my father thought with my rural upbringing that I might
                    not be competitive enough in a place like Exeter. As a result, I duplicated the
                    courses my first year there that I had in junior high school and found them very
                    easy. I spent four years at Exeter and enjoyed them very much.</p>
                <p>Then I went on to college at Harvard, the only college I applied for (It was
                    easier to get into such places in those days.), and spent four years there. I
                    was interested in the field of international studies, but in those days (This
                    was just after the war, the class of 1952.), such a field had not yet been
                    developed. Then, if you were interested in that area, you had to study either
                    history or government courses at Harvard. I did some of both. The most current
                    course in European history that you could take then ended with Europe before the
                    war. So, if you were a young person in 1950 and you wanted to understand postwar
                    Europe, there was not very much offered there that gave you an insight into that
                    period. From an historical point of view, I guess it was too early to interpret
                    history that recent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you majored in history?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I majored in modern European history. I was not distinguished student at
                    Harvard, but I enjoyed it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you interested in the Foreign Service at that
                        point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, at that point I didn't have any specific interest to guide me. I was in
                    the naval ROTC and I knew that I had an obligation after college to serve three
                    years of active duty in the U.S. Navy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you probably didn't take the courses that you
                        otherwise mighhave taken in economics or sociology?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I did have to take a course each year in naval science, whiccut out some
                    other subjects that I might have taken.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But, you had a good time at Harvard and enjoyed
                        yourself?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I did, but like a lot of undergraduates I was sort of finding my way in
                    terms of academic interest. I was active in the Harvard Crimson which gave me
                    some experience of a more practical nature.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were a reporter?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, I was not a reporter. I was on the business board side, which had to do
                    mainly with the advertising operations - selling advertising, making the layout
                    of the newspaper before news and other articles went into it. It was a highly
                    competitive process, difficult and challenging and a nice social experience
                    because of the people you were involved with there on a different basis from the
                    academic side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you do sports at all, or were you an actor, etc.?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I did no varsity sports but I was always athletically inclined, and the one
                    sport that I could develop there was rowing of single sculls. I became a member
                    of the 30 Minute Club, which is based on a certain distance that you row in 30
                    minutes, which meant you were one of the better rowers. I have maintained an
                    interest in rowing to the present day, and I now compete in various races.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you row on the Potomac now?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I am a member of the Potomac Boat Club and row out of there and compete in
                    a series of head races that take place in the fall - three mile races at the
                    head of rivers. I go up to the Head of the Charles and compete there in October.
                    So, this is an interest that I developed way back then.</p>
                <p>Q: Anything else that you did in college that you think served you well or not so
                    well in the Foreign Service? Anything in retrospect that you would suggest that
                    young people who were interested in diplomacy as a career should think about
                    while they are undergraduates?</p>
                <p>LORD: If they know they are interested in the Foreign Service then, of course,
                    they can shape their academic program even more specifically now to that
                    end.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any experiences that you had as an undergraduate which
                        yothought would serve you well later on in your working life?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: A part from the general maturing process that you go througas an
                    undergraduate, I don't think of anything.</p>
                <p>Q: All right. So, now we are at 1952 and you have graduated from Harvard and gone
                    off into the Navy. You were in the Navy for three years. What did you do?</p>
                <p>LORD: I spent three years on a heavy cruiser, the USS Baltimore, in a gunnery
                    division. That experience did have a bearing on my developing an interest in the
                    Foreign Service, or perhaps more generally, in living abroad because my ship
                    deployed to the Mediterranean every summer the three years I was on it to join
                    the Sixth Fleet and train there. In that process we visited just about every
                    country that is located on the Mediterranean, particularly the northern
                    coast.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You enjoyed this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: That was fascinating. It interested me greatly and my one thought was:
                    wouldn't it be nice, instead of having to go back to the ship at midnight when
                    liberty ended every night, to stay on shore and live there and see what it was
                    really like.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever have a chance while you were either at
                        college owith the Navy, to spend any time abroad, perhaps on leave with the
                        Navy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: NROTC obligated you to summer cruises so I didn't have an opportunity for
                    other travel during those formative years, which I regret because those years at
                    that age are special, particularly during the summer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you learn any foreign language at college or the
                        Navy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I had been a good student of French at Exeter. In fact, I passed my initial
                    foreign language requirement for the Foreign Service in French, having refreshed
                    it the summer I got out of the Navy at the Middlebury College summer French
                    school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you spent most of your navy career with one ship and
                        it wain U.S. waters except during the summertime?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>LORD: Yes. Among the more memorable experiences aboard ship when we were overseas
                    was a cruise to the Scandinavian countries. We were the first U.S. Navy ship to
                    visit Stockholm since before the war. We also represented the U.S. Navy at the
                    Coronation Naval Review at Spithead, England. That was probably 1953. There were
                    ships from navies all around the world - three, four, or five long lines of
                    ships at anchor. There was a gala ball with all the different colors and kinds
                    of uniforms you could imagine. The Queen on the royal yacht Britannia reviewed
                    the ships while we were all standing at attention and saluting her as she went
                    by.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That gave you a little chance to meet naval officers from
                        othecountries and exchange experiences.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, it exposed me to some of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your interest of getting into the Foreign Service
                        obviously grewhile you were in the Navy. When did you take the exam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Before I got out of the Navy, I had to decide on what to do next, and the
                    Foreign Service was one of my interests. I took the Foreign Service Exam in San
                    Francisco in July, 1955 within days after I was released from the Navy after
                    three years of inactivity intellectually because that is not what you get in the
                    Navy. So, I was pretty rusty and did not past my first written exam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the exam still three and a half days at that time
                        1955?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, at that point it was just one day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you didn't do as well as you had hoped the first time
                        around,what did you do then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I had already applied to the Middlebury College summer French school and
                    went there for the summer program. I thought it was excellent and it really
                    revived and improved my French greatly. Meanwhile, I had applied for the next
                    Foreign Service Exam which was given in early December. To prepare myself better
                    this time, I took advantage of a course that Georgetown University had at the
                    time, which was a special preparatory course for the Foreign Service Exam. It
                    was two months long, from the end of September to the end of November and I
                    found it a very helpful review. In fact, it covered some areas I hadn't been
                    exposed to before.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was two months at Georgetown?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have other career interests at the same time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Somewhere in the process, probably not until the new year, I also looked
                    into American business involvement overseas. In the springtime I interviewed a
                    number of companies that had overseas operations because my basic interest was
                    in working abroad in some way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were going to be an IBM man or General Electric man in
                        Paris?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: That could have happened. One company that I might have gone with, if I
                    hadn't come into the Foreign Service was the Vick Company. They had marketing
                    operations around the world and offered me a job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The second time, you took the exam what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I fortunately passed it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would be in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: That was in December, 1955. The next step, of course, was thoral exam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything in particular that you remember they asked you
                        about ithe oral?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: That came up in the spring. I don't recall any specific questions. I took
                    it in Boston. There was a three person board, one of whom was a difficult member
                    and the other two, I guess, were less so. Of course, you are feeling pretty
                    serious about an important exam like that and not in a mood of levity. The one
                    criticism they levied on me afterwards was that I needed to develop a better
                    sense of humor!</p>
                <p>Q: I know, in my own experience with the oral examination, that the examiners
                    sometimes try to find an area that you are not particularly familiar with or
                    don't have much of a background on and then sort of probe you on that just to
                    see how you handle yourself. That didn't take place during your exam?</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>LORD: I really don't recall now. I had spent some time during the spring
                    continuing my personal review of current events and various fields that I
                    thought I might be asked about, so I think I was much more prepared for this
                    exam than I had been when I first started the whole process.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came in when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: In September, 1956.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were assigned to the A-100 course at FSI in
                        September?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. Then my first assignment was in the Department in thINR bureau in the
                    old office of biographic information.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What area did you work in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I worked in the office that dealt with Algeria, Morocco,Tunisia, and
                    Overseas France (the French areas of sub-Saharan Africa).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your boss?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: My boss was Roland Jacobs, who had served in France.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did a young intelligence analyst in INR do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: This was biographic information. The main task was to collect information
                    on world leaders and potential leaders. We received most of the reporting from
                    the posts in our geographic area and reviewed it for information that was
                    particularly relevant to a person of interest. Posts, of course, had a
                    biographic reporting responsibility and sometimes they would send in nice
                    finished biographic reports, but much of the information that was in our files
                    at that time was what the analyst culled from various reports, either by putting
                    articles or sections of reports in the file. Or we went through the reports with
                    enough of a fine tooth comb so that we would type on 3x5 cards information that
                    was briefer but relevant. In that process, I taught myself how to touch type,
                    which was an invaluable tool later on. But, I'm afraid those files are full of
                    some terrible typing glitches. It was an educational experience for a new FSO in
                    that you became familiar with Foreign Service reporting and with a geographic
                    area of the world.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>Q: Peter, if I recall correctly at that time the French were having an extremely
                    difficult time in Algeria. This was the time when part of the French army,
                    particularly the paratroopers and the Foreign Legion were thinking about going
                    back and taking over Paris and the country. It must have been quite a dicey
                    period. Were you called upon to try to produce intelligence forecasts?</p>
                <p>LORD: I'm trying to think back. I was in BI from 1956-58 and I think what you
                    just described occurred a little bit after that. The FLN was certainly active as
                    an insurgent group in Algeria at the time and we did biographic reports on all
                    of the leaders that were involved. So, it was an area of transition which led to
                    what you just described.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were your contacts with the desk officers? Were they
                        good odifficult?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: The north African countries would have been in the EUR bureau at the time.
                    The desk officers that I dealt with for Morocco and Tunisia were particularly
                    helpful. I can't remember now who was desk officer for Algeria. The desk
                    officers played an important role in grooming a young FSO.</p>
                <p>Q: In terms of bureaucracy, were you as a young INR officer invited to staff
                    meetings in EUR, asked to provide intelligence input to policy discussions in
                    the bureau?</p>
                <p>LORD: No, the office director would have handled such requirements. We were the
                    lower level people who did the work, collected the information and put it
                    together in some kind of useable form. Our most frequent product was a report on
                    new government personalities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have contact with other intelligence agencies like
                        thCIA, DIA, NSA, etc.?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I think the contact with other agencies at that time was minimal. If we
                    were doing a report on a military figure in a government I am sure we would call
                    somewhere in the Pentagon (DIA didn't exist at that time) to get whatever input
                    they could add. We would get, of course, reports from attach� offices at
                    embassies abroad, so we probably had a lot of the military input already.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have anything to do with NSA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Nothing to do with NSA that I recall, or really with CIA.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>Q: That is rather ironic because not much longer after that biographic
                    information was transferred from the State Department to CIA and the State
                    Department lost its biographic capability.</p>
                <p>LORD: The Department can still request that information.</p>
                <p>Q: I remember that a number of older hands in INR were more and more distressed
                    that responsibilities and functions that they used to exercise and enjoy were
                    transferred to CIA and sometimes not with the best of feelings.</p>
                <p>LORD: I think the job in biographic information was a good introduction for a new
                    FSO so it was too bad to lose it in that sense. But there are so many more
                    responsibilities the State Department has now that the bio function probably is
                    of less importance than some others, so maybe the present arrangement makes
                    sense.</p>
                <p>Q: Anything else that people should know about how INR worked in the mid-'50s? Do
                    you remember any particular colorful people who worked with you in that
                    bureau?</p>
                <p>LORD: Well, I met people whom I have known ever sense, but I don'think anything
                    in particular stands out.</p>
                <p>I should add, however, that at that time office space was at a premium perhaps
                    because of the expanded responsibilities of the State Department. We started out
                    in the old State Annex 1 which was on 23rd street, occupying some of the space
                    now where the northwest corner of Main State is. We were moved to temporary
                    quarters down on the Mall in temporary naval buildings still being used down
                    near the reflecting pool, as I recall. Then we occupied a second office space
                    area in the temporary buildings on the Mall almost across from the Museum of
                    Natural History. That was the old post-World War II Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now we are at 1958. Anything important happening in
                        youpersonal life?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No. I remained single until 1966.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, in 1958 you went overseas?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>LORD: My first assignment overseas was to Khorramshahr, Iran, which, of course, I
                    had never heard of. This was somewhat of a disappointment for someone who had
                    studied modern European history and had been working on Overseas France. With
                    the help of my office, a request went out to personnel saying that I was needed
                    urgently in the office and they couldn't afford to release me right then. But, I
                    ended up in Khorramshahr and found it to be an interesting and enjoyable place
                    after all. It was a small consulate which has been closed now for a number of
                    years. It was located at the confluence of the Karun river and the Shatt al Arab
                    (the Tigris and Euphrates), which forms the boundary between Iran and Iraq and
                    flows down into the Persian Gulf, which is maybe 20 miles to the south past
                    Abadan Island. Khorramshahr was then the major port of Iran. It is also across
                    the Karun river from Abadan Island, which is not so much an island, really, as
                    part of the mainland but separated by some small waterways. Abadan is where at
                    that time the oil refinery belonging to the international consortium was -
                    American, British, Dutch and French oil companies. It was the major refinery for
                    Iran and an important source of petroleum for Europe and the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it a two or three person office?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We had a consul, Jack Bowie, two American vice consuls, aAmerican admin
                    assistant and a USIS office with one American in it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your responsibilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: My responsibilities the first year were somewhat unique in the Foreign
                    Service. This was a period when we had a very large AID program in Iran, which
                    was then modernizing under the Shah, and the volume of imports through the port
                    of Khorramshahr for the AID program and the huge American mission in Tehran and
                    elsewhere around the country warranted special attention because the port was
                    antiquated, overloaded, and a lot of these official shipments were stuck there,
                    disappearing or just piling up when they were needed elsewhere. So, the embassy
                    decided they needed to have an FSO in charge of official imports. I became in a
                    sense a port officer with that general responsibility. The embassy did have a
                    contract with a Lebanese freight forwarder, which was a new contract. My job was
                    to work closely with this freight forwarder, supervise the contract, ride herd
                    on them, coordinate priorities with them, making sure they found this cargo and
                    getting it promptly cleared through customs and on to trucks to make the long
                    trip up to Tehran.</p>
                <p>I did that for a year. It was kind of fun, actually. The freight forwarding
                    office was run by a young Lebanese fellow. He and I were about the same age, and
                    we got along very well. He had a staff of local Armenians, primarily, and it was
                    a very congenial group.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>Q: It is always useful in the Foreign Service to have a real chance to get out of
                    the office and into the field and deal with local people and observe situations
                    first hand and this was a good way of doing that.</p>
                <p>LORD: This wasn't so much in the political sense, which perhaps is what you
                    meant, but it was an opportunity for contact with a certain function, mainly the
                    port and the people that were associated with it.</p>
                <p>The reason we had a consulate in Khorramshahr was because the area had been one
                    of significant unrest during the Mossadegh period. Mossadegh had been moved out
                    about 1954, if I remember correctly, and the Shah picked up from there. So, it
                    had been an area where the embassy felt we should have a listening post, which
                    is why the consulate was there. The unrest had threatened the oil refinery, the
                    main American interest there and the American citizens working there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was sort of the oil center of Iran and a very
                        sensitive area.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. It was a very important European and U.S. interest. I only mention
                    this because I was there the two years from 1958-60 when there was no political
                    unrest. Things were politically very quiet. The Shah was firmly in control,
                    riding high. The degree of discontent with the Shah's regime which developed
                    later on in the '70s didn't exist back then in the late '50s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do your second year at Khorramshahr?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: The second year I rotated into the job of the senior vice consul who was
                    responsible for consular affairs and also for the limited general political and
                    economic reporting.</p>
                <p>Q: Were there any particular characteristics in doing consular work in coastal
                    Iran? Did you do a lot of crew list visas? Did you have a lot of problems with
                    American seamen?</p>
                <p>LORD: It was an easy consular job in that there was not a great volume of any
                    aspect of consular work there. There were some crew list visas, some services to
                    American citizens working at the refinery in Abadan, and there was a certain
                    amount of visitors. I handled just IVs; I think all NIVs were issued by Tehran.
                    So, it was a relatively simple consular function there which left some time for
                    general political and economic reporting - a quarterly report, as I recall,
                    about developments that were taking place. A good part of that was monitoring
                    the development effort with AID support in Khuzestan Province.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you at all function as a field officer for the USAID
                        missioin Tehran?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>LORD: Not really. They had people who would come down and work on some of the
                    projects. One of the large projects that had American financing was the major
                    dam that was being built outside of Ahvaz. American contractors were involved
                    and I would go up there on a regular basis to keep abreast of whatever problems
                    they were facing, and I did some reporting in that respect.</p>
                <p>During the time I was in Khorramshahr, the border between Iran and Iraq was
                    closed because they were arguing over where the boundary line actually went
                    along the Shatt al Arab River. That is where I learned the word “tallweg,” which
                    I think is the word that is suppose to describe where the deepest part of the
                    river runs. It may not necessarily be in the center or on either side, but it is
                    where the current runs deepest.</p>
                <p>Because of this border dispute, you could not drive or fly to Basrah, which was
                    too bad because I understood just before I got to Khorramshahr that Basrah was a
                    nice change of pace for a visit. It was a little more developed than
                    Khorramshahr.</p>
                <p>Q: About the same time you were in Khorramshahr I was in Jordan and one of the
                    most enjoyable things to do was to go out in a landrover and see what you could
                    see in the desert. Was there any opportunities to do this?</p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, I can remember a nice trip up into the interior of Khuzestan province,
                    the southwestern province which is part of the Tigris/Euphrates plain. It is
                    flat and the population is ethnically more Arab than Persian. The upper reaches
                    of the Karun river are quite pretty and the British consul, who was quite a
                    character in the sense of old British tradition would go up there hunting. One
                    time he invited two of us from the consulate along. We had gun bearers to carry
                    our rifles - a nice little safari to a lovely area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That sounds like a lot of fun. How long was the trip?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: That was probably just a weekend. Another time an up country trip was
                    organized by the Italian honorary consul, a shipping agent and, again, a
                    colorful person. He also liked to hunt. On that trip was the Lebanese freight
                    forwarder, a very attractive young French woman who was visiting a friend of the
                    Italian consul, and I don't remember who else. We camped in a very appealing
                    area.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>I also visited Bushehr, an old, virtually abandoned port south along the east
                    coast of the Persian Gulf. I just read recently that Bushehr is the location of
                    a nuclear reactor that Iran is developing and is a source of controversy between
                    the United States and Iran at the moment. So, Bushehr has obviously modernized
                    since I was last there. On that same trip to Bushehr, a colleague came down from
                    the embassy at Tehran. We flew to Bushehr from Khorramshahr and the embassy sent
                    a vehicle down to Bushehr to pick us up there. The idea was to drive back to
                    Tehran using the road from Bushehr up to Shiraz and through Isfahan to Tehran to
                    see what that would be like for accommodating freight shipments. I remember not
                    so much about the road, which was not paved, but the visit to Persepolis, which
                    is just outside Shiraz, which, of course, is one of the great historic ruins in
                    the world, an ancient Persian site and home of Darius the Great. In those days,
                    you could just walk into the ruins and pick up pieces of fluted columns. I have
                    some as bookends at home now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had Alexander been through that area at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Alexander the Great had been through, I'm sure, at some point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you didn't see any Macedonian coins?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No.</p>
                <p>Q: With the benefit of hindsight I want to ask you a couple of questions. In view
                    of the whole Mossadegh business, was there a great deal of concern in Iran at
                    that time? Did you have contacts with security people or secret police or
                    anything like that with regard to concern about a communist takeover?</p>
                <p>LORD: Not down in Khorramshahr. Any of that would have been
                    morTehran-oriented.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there labor unions in the refineries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: There were, but their contract and conditions were not a source of trouble
                    during the time I was there. If there were labor negotiations and contract
                    renewals going on they were handled without strikes and upsets.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you at that time notice any particular Islamic unhappiness with the Shah?
                    Were there mullahs and ayatollahs who were muttering and making speeches in the
                    mosques about how Iran was straying from the Islamic path?</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>LORD: As I mentioned earlier, I think, back in the late '50s none of this
                    opposition to the Shah or the American influence had developed to a serious
                    degree. It was there in a latent sense, I'm sure, but there were no restrictions
                    on traveling around the country, no hostility. On that same trip from Shiraz on
                    up to Tehran, we stopped at Isfahan, which is where some lovely mosques are,
                    perhaps the loveliest in Iran, and there were no problems going around to look
                    at them. So, as I say, it was a relatively benign period, ideal for traveling
                    around and exploring the country.</p>
                <p>One other memorable adventure was the climbing of Mt. Damavand, the highest
                    mountain in Iran, which is, I think, a little over 18,000 feet. It is not far
                    north of Tehran and some people from the embassy were planning an ascent of
                    Damavand. Since I was interested in mountain climbing, they asked me to go
                    along. My problem was to adjust to the altitude. In Tehran one was living at
                    5,000 feet, whereas I was living at sea level at Khorramshahr. I did go up for
                    one practice climb, which helped, but adjusting to the altitude at higher levels
                    on Damavand was very difficult for me, more so than for them, but we all did
                    make it to the top, and it was a memorable experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The climb must have taken several days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, we drove to the site, climbed part way, rested at night in a sleeping
                    bag in a camping area and then the next day made the ascent and came back down,
                    sliding down snow fields on our butts!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They didn't have camps or hostels?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, there was nothing there to help you. It wasn't a tourispilgrimage the
                    way Mt. Fuji is in Japan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. We wrap of this tour in the Middle East and you are
                        theassigned back to Washington. Why?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Well, my next assignment was to Caracas, Venezuela, which was not on my
                    preference list, but certainly sounded better than Khorramshahr did when I was
                    first told about that assignment. I was assigned to Washington for language
                    training before going to Caracas. As I mentioned earlier, I had satisfied the
                    French language requirement, but rather than send me to a French speaking area,
                    the Department assigned me to Caracas. I had a 16 week course. I started in
                    January and ended sometime in May, I think.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>This was back in the days when personnel assignments permitted more time between
                    assignments than they do these days. You didn't have to rush from one place to
                    the other so that a post didn't have to suffer a vacancy in the meanwhile. I
                    lefKhorramshahr in October and didn't have to start Spanish until January, which
                    gave me about two and a half months for leave along the way. I had a delightful
                    trip from Khorramshahr back via Cairo, a Yugoslav ship from Athens along the
                    Yugoslav coast, to Dubrovnik and Belgrade, visiting friends both in the
                    consulate in Sarajevo and the embassy in Belgrade. I then flew on to Austria and
                    to Madrid, where I visited my sister and her husband, who was also Foreign
                    Service. I flew up to London and boarded the SS United States and sailed back to
                    New York first class!I took the Spanish course in the old FSI in the basement of
                    Arlington Towers. It was, I think, a good course. Spanish, of course, is a
                    pretty easy language if you have a good aptitude. So, I got a 3/3 out of that
                    with no problem. I arrived in Caracas in July, 1961.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What position were you assigned to there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I was assigned to the political section as the third persothere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember who some of your colleagues were?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. It was an interesting period to be there because Kennedy had just been
                    elected president, took office in January that same year, and appointed as
                    ambassador to Venezuela, Teodoro Moscoso, from Puerto Rico. He was a native
                    Spanish speaker and someone who had been involved in the development of Puerto
                    Rico and was very much a gung-ho, hands on, activist ambassador in Caracas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he a career or political appointee?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: He was involved in the development of Puerto Rico and was a political
                    appointee. He was able to relate well with the president of Venezuela, Romulo
                    Betancourt, as they were both social democrats and on the same political
                    wavelength.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the political counselor when you arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>LORD: When I arrived the political counselor was Jack Cates, again one of the
                    more colorful people of the old Foreign Service, and a good mentor. He knew his
                    way around Caracas very well. He left not too long after I arrived and was
                    replaced by Ted Long, another good mentor. Moscoso didn't stay that long either
                    because he was invited back to Washington to head up the Alliance for Progress.
                    When he left the deputy chief of mission, of course, became charg�. That was C.
                    Allan Stewart, who was an old pro in the Foreign Service and someone who had
                    very close ties with Betancourt before he was even elected president.</p>
                <p>At that time, probably the fall of 1961, President Kennedy and wife Jackie came
                    for a state visit to Venezuela to show U.S. support for Betancourt and his
                    attempt to reestablish democracy after the dictatorship of Perez Jimenez and to
                    give the Alliance for Progress a boost. That was a very successful visit. I had
                    a role in it being responsible for Jackie Kennedy's part of the visit, its
                    planning and execution and rode in the cavalcade in the car behind her car and
                    was able to see the faces of people lining the street as she drove past. Most
                    were excited, some hostile, but she captivated the populace quite well.</p>
                <p>It was a very successful visit after some misgivings over security. It was almost
                    canceled at one point because the U.S. security types were not convinced that
                    the government of Venezuela could guarantee Kennedy's safety because it was a
                    period of some opposition to the U.S., particularly by the several leftist
                    parties which were receiving support from Cuba. That is what made the whole
                    two-year assignment in Venezuela so interesting, that Venezuela was one of the
                    prime targets of Cuban subversion during this period. U.S. support of Betancourt
                    was the key to making democracy work there. Alan Stewart, after the successful
                    Kennedy visit, was appointed ambassador. This was an unusual case of a charg�
                    being elevated to ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1962.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes.</p>
                <p>Q: Peter, there is a three man political section and then probably a bunch of CIA
                    types masquerading as political officers as well, but what were your particular
                    responsibilities in the section?</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>LORD: I was responsible for maintaining contacts with COPEI, the Social Christian
                    Party, that was in the coalition government with the Democratic Action Party of
                    Betancourt. I was responsible for political input to the WEEKA, the weekly
                    report submitted by the embassy. One of the more enjoyable responsibilities was
                    doing quite a thorough report on the agrarian reform program in Venezuela
                    together with a junior agricultural attach� and another young political officer
                    who joined the office as the fourth person, when we developed into a four person
                    office. The three of us took a trip all around the country visiting agrarian
                    reform sites, which was a great way to see the country and get an understanding
                    of that program. We wrote a lengthy comprehensive report. Agrarian reform was
                    one of the key programs of the Betancourt government and was politically
                    important because the AD party relied to an important extent on the vote of the
                    campesino, the farmer. As in many developing countries, the campesino hasn't
                    always been enfranchised, but can provide important electoral support for
                    democracy, as in not only Venezuela but also Bolivia and Mexico.</p>
                <p>Q: This is your second assignment in a developing country. Particularly in
                    Venezuela, it is giving you an opportunity to gain some familiarity with
                    agriculture in developing countries, rural development, etc.</p>
                <p>LORD: Particularly the political aspects of that. That was my focus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the United States engaged in trying to foster
                        ruradevelopment in Venezuela at this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Oh, sure. There was an AID mission there and we were givinassistance to the
                    agrarian reform program and other programs, too.</p>
                <p>Q: Agrarian reform because much of the arable land had been owned by a small
                    number of well-to-do families?</p>
                <p>LORD: Some of the land was being redistributed. I can't remember how it worked
                    but, of course, the controversial aspect of land redistribution is whether the
                    original owners were adequately compensated or not. Venezuela being a relatively
                    rich country because of its oil industry was able to fund programs like that
                    better than some other countries. In any case, there were a variety of
                    settlements which were prototypes for agricultural reform and development where
                    farmers were being given land and needed financing and technological
                    assistance.</p>
                <p>Q: Was the Betancourt government, for example, actually seizing land which was
                    owned by well-to-do landowners but wasn't being used, and distributed...?</p>
                <p>LORD: I can't remember the details of that. It seems to me it wanot a huge
                    controversy.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There wasn't violent rural unrest?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No. As, I say, I think it was because the government was ablto afford to
                    compensate the landowners.</p>
                <p>Q: The Castro and Cuban attempts to subvert the government of Venezuela were not
                    focusing on the poor people in the countryside but rather in cities?</p>
                <p>LORD: This was one of their first, early attempts at subversion and they were
                    experimenting. A Cuban arms cache was discovered on a peninsular on the coast in
                    western Venezuela, which was a rural area. There was another period when there
                    was some aggressive insurgency along the coast of eastern Venezuela. So, they
                    were trying to develop an insurgency in those rural areas, but as time
                    progressed their real focus was in Caracas, itself, and maybe Maracay. They used
                    the university students wherever they could. Q: How about the labor unions?</p>
                <p>LORD: The labor unions were pretty much controlled by Betancourt's party. Both AD
                    and COPEI had strong labor unions. There was a communist dominated federation,
                    but it was not as strong as AD/COPEI.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the embassy have a labor attach�?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, the embassy had a labor attach�. When I got there, he was Irving
                    Tragen, who later became well known for a variety of positions that he filled
                    later on - AID director in Bolivia and country director for parts of South
                    America later on.</p>
                <p>Q: So, the embassy had a pretty good feel for what was going on in the labor
                    field. Is there anything else that you would like to talk about with regards to
                    your tour in Caracas?</p>
                <p>LORD: The Cuban supported insurgency grew more and more serious while I was
                    there. One of the highlights was a bomb that actually exploded in the embassy.
                    We had received advance intelligence that a bomb might be exploded in one of the
                    restrooms in the embassy, so all the restrooms were closed except for two on the
                    top floor, and where a Marine guard was placed. Well, somebody, a visitor,
                    somehow was directed to the open restrooms on the top floor. The visitor had no
                    briefcase or anything else in which he could be carrying a bomb. Apparently, he
                    had plastic explosives strapped around his body under his clothes and he
                    apparently wasn't frisked by the Marine. He installed the explosives and left
                    and shortly thereafter a bomb went off in the men's restroom on the top floor
                    and blew a hole in a part of the embassy's external wall there. Fortunately,
                    nobody was in the restroom at the time. The Marine outside felt the blast and
                    was stunned but not hurt.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>One of the military group's members was temporarily kidnaped - I don't recall his
                    name. He was held briefly before he was released. I don't remember the terms of
                    his release. That happened just about the time I was leaving.</p>
                <p>Q: It seems to me from my research that there were several incidents like this in
                    Venezuela at that time and usually people were held for just two or three days
                    and then released. It wasn't as happened later when Ambassador Asencio was held
                    for two months and other people like that. Anything else that you would like to
                    add about colleagues of yours in the embassy or...?</p>
                <p>LORD: I should mention that the other person in the political section, the number
                    two, whose name I hadn't mentioned before was Nat Davis, who became a
                    prestigious member of the Foreign Service, ambassador to Chile among other
                    places and the director general of the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was he doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Well, he was the number two in the Political Section. I remember one
                    project that he was working on was high priority because it was Attorney General
                    Bobbie Kennedy's pet project, that every embassy should develop a youth program.
                    This was particularly important in Venezuela where the left was trying to
                    subvert the youth and we needed to reach out to them. University students were
                    considered as potential agents of Cuban insurgency, so every university was a
                    trouble spot with students acting up. Central University in Caracas was closed
                    much of the time I was there. In fact, one of the early harbingers of this early
                    leftist insurgency was at Central University when Ambassador Moscoso made a
                    visit there not long after his arrival. Although he wasn't in his car at the
                    time, it was attacked and his briefcase, which had classified papers in it, was
                    stolen out of the trunk. So, it was a bit embarrassing at the time.</p>
                <p>Q: When we take up this interview next time it will be 1963 and you are being
                    reassigned from Venezuela to the States for Latin American area studies at
                    Columbia University.</p>
                <p>LORD: Before we leave Caracas let me mention two of my more interesting side
                    trips there. One was a trip that two of us from the embassy and a young German
                    fellow made to AngeFalls, which is the highest waterfall in the world. It has a
                    straight drop of about 3,000 feet. It is located in southern central Venezuela.
                    We flew down to what is now a national park at Canaima, but in those days it was
                    just a little outpost and there was a Dutch fellow named Jungle Rudy who put
                    together an expedition for the three of us, and including himself and an Indian
                    guide all in one canoe together with camping equipment and food. It was an
                    aluminum canoe with an outboard motor on it. We took about a week's trip up two
                    rivers to get to Angel Falls itself.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why isn't that better known?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Oh, it is. If you do any tourism these days...</p>
                <p>Q: The ones that most of us have heard about in Latin America are the Iguacu
                    Falls on the border between Brazil and Paraguay or the Victoria Falls in Africa.
                    Three thousand foot vertical drop?</p>
                <p>LORD: The volume of water is quite small. It is a ribbon falls. This is down in
                    the area that author Conan Doyle made famous with his novel The Lost World. The
                    falls are on top of a mesa that is sort of isolated. You could dream about
                    unusual wildlife existing up there isolated from the rest of the continent. It
                    is named Angel Falls after Jimmy Angel, who flew in there and crashed on the
                    mesa from which the waterfall descends. I think he survived; I can't remember.
                    Today this is part of a national park and there are organized tours to take you
                    down there.</p>
                <p>Another trip that some of us made was to southwestern Venezuela on one of the
                    tributaries to the Amazon river where we visited the native Indian people who
                    live there in primitive habitat. I did an airgram on that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How far, just to give us an idea, in miles was it from
                        Caracadown to the Amazon river?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Well, it is a tributary to the Amazon, so it is down close tthe Colombia
                    border where the border goes north and south.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It must be at least 500 miles.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: At least, and maybe more. I remember doing an airgram on that visit because
                    it was so fascinating. I prepared it and my boss said something like “That was a
                    real labor of love; I wish all your reports reflected the same degree of love.”
                    Ironically, it was a report that received a favorable comment from the Bureau of
                    Indian Affairs in the Department of Interior!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was an Indian tribe living on the banks of a
                        tributary othe Amazon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there pirana there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I guess so, I can't remember.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, let's break it off here and we will start in 1963
                        with arestudies at Columbia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: All right, good. ***</p>
                <p>Q: This is Lambert (Nick) Heyniger and today is April 30, 1998 and this is the
                    second session with Peter Lord who has been telling us about his Foreign Service
                    experiences. Last time we ended with his tour in Caracas and now we are going to
                    hear about Peter being reassigned for universities studies. This is 1963 and
                    what happened?</p>
                <p>LORD: The Department was looking for people to do area studies on Latin America
                    and I was accepted into the program. They offered several places where these
                    studies could be taken, none of which particularly appealed to me geographically
                    or otherwise. So, I made a case for pursuing these studies at Columbia
                    University in New York at the Institute of Latin American Studies there.
                    Coincidently it turned out that so did some other candidates who were selected
                    for the program. I think there were three of us there doing Latin American
                    studies. We all arrived there more or less by our own choice.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why hadn't the Department previously used Columbia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I don't know. There are lots of different centers for international
                    studies, including Latin American studies. I guess the one at Columbia was
                    relatively new and they just wanted to perhaps send people to the more
                    traditional places. This was a period when interest in Latin American studies
                    and the Alliance for Progress was burgeoning.</p>
                <p>It was a good choice. It was a good program and I think we all benefitted from
                    it. I viewed New York City like a foreign country, a place that I wanted to
                    visit and get to know, but not necessarily spend the rest of my life there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember some of your professors?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. The director of the institute was Charles Wagley, who was a well known
                    anthropologist, as I recall. I did not have a course under him but I did under
                    Ronald Schneider. He was teaching the political science course which were my
                    particular interest. He had worked previously in INR for awhile so he understood
                    the State Department, understood us students. He was the advisor for all three
                    of us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were your fellow officers?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>LORD: The two other students who were doing political science, werAshley Hewitt,
                    now deceased, and Wayne Smith, who became a Cuban expert.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, he is going to be the officer in charge of the
                        interessection in Havana.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. Two other people were there, both studying economics.One was Jerry
                    Lamberty and one was Al Zucca.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is during the Kennedy administration. Did your
                        professorget you involved in studying developmental problems in Latin
                        America?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We were given a good solid grounding first of all. We took a Latin America
                    history course. I don't think I took a course in Latin American geography, but I
                    did some reading on that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Economics?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I took an economics course given by Albert Hirshman. I also studied
                    political parties with Robert Alexander. I'm a little vague on the courses I
                    took now. There was only a fall and spring semester.</p>
                <p>Q: One question I'm dying to ask you is I think during this period many countries
                    in Latin America still had military regimes and with a strong American military
                    interest in Latin America was there any discussion with your professors about
                    the political military aspects of U.S. relations with Latin America?</p>
                <p>LORD: I'm sure there was but I don't recall specifically now. I drecall a book on
                    the subject of the military regimes in Latin America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get exposed to Latin American culture, literature,
                        music,etc.?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: As I recall we did not get into that too much. It may have been covered
                    tangentially in some of the courses I took, but there were no specific courses
                    in those subjects that I recall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you think this idea of area studies was a good
                        one?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>LORD: I did. I had been assigned to Venezuela without any prior experience in
                    Latin America whatsoever. I was taught Spanish, and I suppose I was given the
                    area studies course of two weeks before I went, but that didn't provide that
                    solid a background, especially when you are brand new to the area. But, while I
                    was there the two years, I became aware of my ignorance of the rest of the
                    hemisphere and how developments in Venezuela might relate with those elsewhere.
                    So, I felt the need for a good solid grounding in the area and that is what this
                    program provided. It was very useful and gave me a lot more confidence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel that you were at that time making a
                        commitment tthe rest of your career being in Latin America?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I was interested in the area and I wasn't worried too much about the rest
                    of my career, but I was interested in going back. I must say I approached
                    Columbia University at the graduate level with some trepidation, wondering what
                    it would be like competing with the younger, smarter students, but discovered
                    that if you are motivated and disciplined, you do well.</p>
                <p>The course requirements for a masters degree at Columbia could be met in one year
                    and I did that in the two semesters that I was there from 1963 to 1964. In
                    addition a masters dissertation was required and I managed to accomplish that in
                    the next year so in 1965 I got a masters degree from Columbia in political
                    science as a result of the State Department-sponsored year there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember what you wrote your paper on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: As my advisor said, it wouldn't be too difficult to make a dissertation by
                    expanding on a paper that I had written in the spring semester for his class. I
                    had written a paper on the political dynamics of the political system in
                    Venezuela and to that I added two more sections making the focus of the paper
                    the peasantry as a political factor not only in Venezuela but also Bolivia and
                    Mexico. This was a political factor that deserved attention in developing
                    democracies in Latin America because obviously the peasantry, which had been
                    largely excluded as an electoral influence in many countries, if given the vote
                    because of their numbers could make the difference in whether a party gets
                    elected or not. In those three countries, the democratic reform governments
                    could rely on a franchised peasantry to support them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And support the government that's elected.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>LORD: So, it was a study of comparative politics in those three countries and the
                    subject was of enough interest so that the Land Tenure Center at the University
                    of Wisconsin, which focused on anything to do with agricultural subjects, picked
                    it up and republished it as one of their series. That was pleasing.</p>
                <p>Q: I just might interject here that a few years ago I got a masters in history
                    and there is now a school of history called the people's history, which looks at
                    countries not from the point of view of who were the prime ministers or
                    generals, the business leaders or significant events, but rather what were the
                    common people doing. What were carpenters and masons and farmers doing. It is a
                    relatively new school approach to studying history by studying common peoples
                    lives and interests. This is exactly what you were doing thirty five years
                    ago.</p>
                <p>Your next assignment was to the Department?</p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. I was assigned to the Bureau of Inter-American Affairs, to the
                    Colombia desk. Colombia and Venezuela were covered by the same Office of North
                    Coast Affairs. It might have made more sense to assign me to the Venezuela desk
                    because that is where my experience had been, but the office had two new desk
                    officers assigned and the most urgent need was Colombia, which was a little
                    busier at the time, so I went to the Colombia desk. In terms of expanding my
                    horizons, this was a good move because I learned a lot about Colombia. One of
                    the unique features of the bureau at that time was the combination of State and
                    AID offices, two separate organizations but with AID falling under the direction
                    of the Department of State. The idea in Latin America was to integrate the State
                    and AID desk officers dealing with the same country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the AID people feel about this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: The AID people were less than enthusiastic because State was given the
                    supervisory role. I had an AID desk officer who was subordinate to me. I knew
                    next to nothing about AID matters so I had a lot to learn and had to develop the
                    relationship. But, I think it made sense and worked reasonably well. As a
                    result, in addition to getting educated on Colombia, I got educated about AID
                    and how State and AID can both work together.</p>
                <p>In sum, the two years on the Colombia desk were probably the mosformative years
                    for me in the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>At the end of those two years, I moved over to the Venezuela desk for my final
                    year in ARA/NC to work on a country where I had served for two years and knew
                    well. Because of the very small AID program there that was being phased out, it
                    was a less demanding job.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>During that last year, I married Suzanne Kelleher, a program officer in AID's
                    Latin America Bureau, whom I had met two years earlier when I was working on the
                    Colombia desk. We were married in August, 1966.</p>
                <p>In July, 1967, I was assigned as principal officer at the American consulate in
                    Arequipa, Peru, the country's second largest city and the major center for the
                    southern third of Peru. Arequipa has always been politically active. President
                    Belaunde, then president of Peru, originally came from Arequipa. Our consular
                    district included all of southern Peru, from the borders with Chile and Bolivia
                    as far north as Cuzco. It included both the Altiplano, the high tableland at
                    11,000-12,000 feet, where Cuzco, Puno, and Lake Titicaca are located, to the
                    coastal area. The main American private investment there was the Southern Peru
                    Copper Company, a subsidiary of American Smelting and Refining Company in the
                    U.S. Its main site was the large open pit copper mine located at Toquepala. It
                    also had a large smelter at Ilo. The consulate was responsible for providing
                    American citizen services to mine employees and following relevant political
                    developments. Another American-owned company in Arequipa was Leche Gloria, a
                    dairy company owned by the Carnation Milk Company in the U.S. They had several
                    Americans living in Arequipa, adding to our very small American community.</p>
                <p>The consulate had a small American staff of only three officers - myself, a vice
                    consul, and an administrative officer. The vice consul and I would alternate
                    taking trips each month through our consular district - a loop by train or
                    vehicle up to Puno and along the Altiplano through Sichahi to Cuzco, whence we
                    flew to Lima for consultation at the embassy before flying back to Arequipa.</p>
                <p>The U.S. presence in Arequipa was quite limited. We had a one-person USIS office
                    plus a binational center run by an American USIA employee. USAID had two
                    American contractors stationed in Arequipa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you were the desk officer for Colombia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, during some difficult years for Colombia. The main problems were
                    economic and at that time AID was providing large sums of lending to program
                    loans...</p>
                <p>—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Peter Lord is talking about his tour of duty as principal
                        officein Arequipa, Peru.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>So, there was an AID contractor there but no AID mission?</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>LORD: There was no AID mission or military mission there. We did have a Peace
                    Corps office there with a deputy director who administered the Peace Corps
                    programs and personnel in southern Peru. I suppose there were 60 or 70 of them.
                    That was a relatively successful program, I would say. We would occasionally
                    visit Peace Corps volunteers and they always drew my admiration for the
                    conditions they were living in and the relationships they had with the local
                    populace. I have always thought the Peace Corps complements very well the U.S.
                    diplomatic presence in a country. The embassy's and the consulate's main job is
                    to relate to the government and to look out for U.S. interests in the country
                    and to try to meet as wide a variety of people as possible, but, by the nature
                    of the job you are spending most of your time in the capital city or wherever
                    the office is and you don't have a chance to get out and relate to the common
                    people of the country. The Peace Corps does and they develop that part of the
                    bilateral relationship which we, Foreign Service people, can't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else that you would like to tell us about life
                        and lovin Arequipa? What did you do for fun? What did you do on
                        weekends?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Frequently we would take a trip outside of town. The Cailloma valley was a
                    lovely valley with good fishing and small towns and some Peace Corps volunteers.
                    Now I believe the valley is a fishing destination on some of the tourist
                    routes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fishing for something like trout?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is it possible to go hiking in the mountains?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Well, I did climb to the top of El Misti, a 19,000 foovolcanic cone
                    overlooking Arequipa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By your self?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, there were two Peace Corps volunteers, myself and a guide. He showed us
                    the way to go and we got to the top. One of the volunteers didn't make it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did it take you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>LORD: We drove from Arequipa at 7600 feet to a point on the mountain flank
                    at12,000 feet, so we only had to climb from 12,000 feet to 19,000 feet. We
                    climbed to 15,000 feet by the end of the day and slept there for several hours
                    to rest and adjust to the altitude.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is there a hut or hostel there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, there is nothing there at all. We started climbing around midnight or
                    shortly after; we had timed this with a full moon, so visibility was pretty
                    good. We reached the summit about dawn. It was tough going at that altitude, but
                    it was just a question of putting one foot in front of the other and stopping
                    for a rest every few feet. Coming down, of course, was much easier. So, we took
                    about 24 hours.</p>
                <p>Q: I have a particular interest because while I was in Dar, I climbed
                    Kilimanjaro, which is about the same altitude, but that is a five day trip and
                    you are staying in huts. Sure, the last day we got started in the middle of the
                    night and started out by lantern light for the top climbing over this sort of
                    volcanic scree and we all had sticks to hang on to. It was one step and then one
                    breath and then one step and one breath.</p>
                <p>LORD: We experienced the same kind of scree.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But what a feeling of exhilaration when you get to the top
                        ansee the sun rise.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you play golf or tennis or go swimming?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: You could play tennis. There was a lovely club with a swimming pool. In the
                    summertime, you could go down to the beach near Mollendo where the upper class
                    of Arequipa had summer cottages. There was always somebody who invited you down
                    if you wanted to go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did it take to get from Arequipa to the
                        ocean?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: An hour and a half.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. There was a good road.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good restaurants in Arequipa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: There were some. Arequipa is a delightful town. It is an old colonial
                    Spanish town from the 16th century. There are some marvelous old stone churches
                    built out of a volcanic stone called sillar. It is a white volcanic stone which
                    is quite soft so it can be cut into blocks easily and then the blocks on the
                    facade of the church can be easily sculptured into elaborate baroque designs.
                    Some of the 16th and 17th century churches are still standing, although some of
                    them had to be repaired because this area of the world is along the fault line
                    and there have been some damaging earthquakes there. The whole time we were
                    there we would feel light tremors.</p>
                <p>One of the more historic building there was the Convento Santa Catalina, a
                    convent for nuns. According to an old Spanish tradition, if you chose that way
                    of life for your daughter, she would go in there and live a cloistered life for
                    the rest of her life and not know anything of the outside world. This convent
                    carried on that tradition right up until the time we were there. By the time we
                    arrived, most of the nuns had either died or been moved elsewhere. Just as we
                    left, the convent was opened to the public. We were given a tour before it was
                    opened to the public. We felt very privileged to go in there and see the spartan
                    life lived by the nuns and read some of the accounts of daughters of prominent
                    Arequipan families who were sent there never to see the outside again.</p>
                <p>The convent, the churches, most all of the buildings in the city, are built out
                    of this white sillar, so it is called la ciudad blanca, the white city, and it
                    is really a lovely place. It is now much more on the tourist route than it used
                    to be. You can fly now from Cuzco to Arequipa and back to Lima.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would suppose in a provincial city, your socializing was
                        abou75 percent in Spanish?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Oh, yes, almost entirely in Spanish except for the Anglo-Peruvian community
                    in Arequipa and the American Mining Company, which is not part of the social
                    life in Arequipa because it was located some distance away. We found the
                    Arequipe�os to be very friendly and Arequipa an easy place to get to know
                    people. We still keep up with friends there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, now it is 1968...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>LORD: Let me go back and mention the Kennedy brothers. John Kennedy was
                    assassinated in the fall of 1963 when I was at Columbia University. I remember
                    that quite vividly. Today I am glad that I was back in the States and could
                    watch this whole ceremony on television. Bobbie Kennedy was assassinated while
                    we were still in Arequipa. Both Kennedys were very popular in Latin America and
                    in Peru. After Bobbie Kennedy's assassination an interdenominational service was
                    held at the local Jesuit church which is right on the main plaza of Arequipa, a
                    lovely historical church built of sillar with a splendidly carved facade
                    outside; the inside had that wonderful combination of white sillar, old dark
                    woodwork, and gold leaf-covered religious decorations. The senior Jesuit priest,
                    a Protestant and a Jewish representative participated in that service. It was
                    remarkable to think that this little outpost in southern Peru would honor an
                    American political figure who was not a prime minister or president in that
                    sense. After all, Lima was the same country where only a few years earlier Vice
                    President Nixon was pelted with stones and spit upon. The Alliance for Progress
                    and the Kennedys evoked quite different attitudes there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That must have been a very moving experience for you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. That came towards the end of our time there, I think iwas in June. It
                    was one of our last memories there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the post closed while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Well, we closed it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a cost cutting measure?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, it was one of those periodic exercises where the Department decides to
                    close a certain number of consulates to save money.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you have had your principal officer's job pulled out
                        frounder you, where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We were reassigned to the embassy in Lima in July 1968. I went from
                    principal officer in Arequipa to second secretary of embassy in Lima as second
                    person in the political section. It was a fascinating time to be there because
                    Peru was going through some political turmoil that we witnessed firsthand. We
                    got to Lima in July and in October a military coup overthrew the Belaunde
                    government and ended that democratic interlude in Peruvian history. Peru then
                    embarked on a military dictatorship which took on statist attributes with a
                    strong anti-American bias.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The military overthrew Belaunde because they thought he
                        was toliberal?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: They thought that democracy was not working in Peru. One problem was the
                    IPC case (International Petroleum Company) which was a subsidiary of Standard
                    Oil, I believe. The government had nationalized IPC holdings several years
                    earlier and negotiations had been going on for some time over compensation. The
                    Hickenlooper amendment was very much involved. The Belaunde government finally
                    reach an agreement on IPC compensation and Belaunde's opponents used it to
                    discredit the government, much as it seems to me the Republicans of today seize
                    on issues to discredit Clinton for political reasons. The IPC settlement was
                    perfectly legitimate and valid but one can make it look as though the government
                    sold out to American interests if presented that way. But the Belaunde
                    government had been under siege by its traditional rivals, the APRA party and
                    the Social Christian Party as well as the left. Belaunde spent most of his time
                    trying to survive rather than dealing with the economic and social problems of
                    the country effectively. So, the military got impatient and decided they would
                    step in and do things better. Of course they didn't. They went in exactly the
                    opposite direction that governments are going today in Latin America. They
                    nationalized more foreign and private interests, particularly the fishing
                    industry. Peru, at the time I was there in the late '60s, was the world's
                    foremost exporter of fish products, largely fish meal. That didn't last
                    long.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The number one exporter?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: The ocean off the west coast of South America is an unusual phenomenon in
                    that the Humboldt current coming up from the south, which is a deep and cold
                    current, rises along the coast and brings up nutrients from the depths. This is
                    fertile feeding ground for fish, particularly for anchovy, which is turned into
                    fish meal. With the effect of el Ni�o and changes in ocean environment since
                    then, the fishing industry now is very small. But, when the military government
                    nationalized it and started off on its own the industry was reduced
                    significantly and what had been an important aspect of the economy went rapidly
                    downhill. In addition, the nationalization of the sugar industry and some mining
                    and oil companies had a very chilling effect on the whole private sector and
                    foreign investment.</p>
                <p>Q: You would think just the opposite, that a conservative military government
                    coming in would try to foster conditions that were favorable towards
                    business.</p>
                <p>LORD: To the extent that they did try to attract foreign investments I think they
                    looked elsewhere than to the United States. They certainly did in the field of
                    military assistance by working closely with the Russians. The Russian military
                    assistance replaced American. So, Peru tried to join the neutralist camp in
                    world politics at that time and it was a difficult time for U.S. policy
                    makers.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your job in the embassy in the political section was
                        what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I was number two in the political section which meant that did a lot of the
                    drafting of the political reporting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any particular political party that you
                        werfollowing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: After the military coup, the political parties were dormant sthat normal
                    kind of division of responsibility fell by the way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you covering labor unions, for example? LORD: No, we
                        had a labor attach� who did that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you were drafting straight political reporting
                        odevelopments in Peru.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. Largely whatever mischief the military government was uto.</p>
                <p>Q: Was the switch from American arms purchases to Russian arms purchases an
                    important feature of U.S.-Peruvian relations during this period? Did you make a
                    lot of representations about arms sales and purchases?</p>
                <p>LORD: I don't recall. There were serious bilateral disagreements over military
                    assistance, over the IPC case, over nationalization policies in general.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Peruvian military indicate to you that they were
                        thinkinabout taking over the IPC assets?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: It moved in that direction. While I was there the chief negotiator for the
                    United States on the IPC case was John Irwin, who had come down from Washington,
                    and I was designated his aide. So, I went to all of those meetings and took
                    notes. He must have come down at least three times to meet with representatives
                    of the military government to discuss the IPC case and what to do next. As I
                    recall, no agreement was reached with the military government and they finally
                    seized the IPC assets and aid was suspended.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No compensation?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>LORD: Talks went on about the subject of compensation and I thineventually there
                    was a settlement after President Velasco bowed out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that an important factor U.S. aid to Peru? Did we have
                        substantial AID program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We did. We had a good size AID program there as well as military
                    program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, when that was suspended, was that a significant event
                        iU.S.-Peruvian relations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: The suspension was probably gradual but it really was a significant
                    development. At the time it was probably claimed by the military as a great
                    triumph, but for the long term well-being of the country, it was a step
                    backwards.</p>
                <p>Another bilateral problem we had was Peru's extension of its territorial sea and
                    economic sovereignty to 200 miles. This resulted in their seizing U.S. tuna
                    fishing boats out of San Diego frequently. That was always a subject of
                    negotiation. I remember going with the naval attach� one time up to Piura, which
                    is in northern Peru in the area where the fishing boats were seized. That is
                    where they fished for tuna off northern Peru and off Ecuador. That continued to
                    be a problem after I left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The U.S. did not recognize the 200 mile limit?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: This was all caught up in negotiations related to the law of the sea, which
                    was a global negotiation on our part. I can't remember the details now but we
                    weren't going to accept the unilateral assertion of economic sovereignty over
                    200 miles, as I recall.</p>
                <p>Q: And probably the U.S. fishermen didn't either. So, you must have had a lot of
                    activity with the Peruvian navy going out and nabbing American fishing
                    boats.</p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, it happens quite a bit and maybe a bit more often ofEcuador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador there then?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>LORD: The ambassador was J. Wesley Jones when I arrived. He came down to Arequipa
                    while we were there. I remember taking him to visit a Peace Corps site in the
                    outskirts of Arequipa. They were probably building a school or community
                    building. I remember him being offered a big tall glass of chicha, which is a
                    fermented corn drink that they use as a kind of beer and it tastes sort of like
                    hard cider. It is not heavy and not too strong. I had not anticipated that and
                    was surprised, too, but he was a real professional and took the glass of chicha
                    proffered and drank the whole thing in one or two gulps. I apologized afterwards
                    to him for being faced with that situation, but it didn't seem to bother
                    him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good for him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: He was the ambassador to the Belaunde government and he bore some of the
                    responsibility for the IPC negotiations and the agreement not working out, at
                    least in the eyes of the Peruvians, so when the military came in he left shortly
                    after that. Eventually Toby Belcher came down as ambassador. He was the one who
                    had to work with the military.</p>
                <p>Q: One thing that puzzles me Peter, my notes show that the Peruvian military
                    government ousted the U.S. military representatives. I suppose there was a MAAG
                    mission or something like that. Why would a Latin American military government
                    want to push out the American military representatives?</p>
                <p>LORD: I think they viewed U.S. military assistance and the role of U.S. military
                    advisers as being too intrusive. They were suspicious of U.S. motives and didn't
                    like the relationship that existed, feeling it was too close to U.S. officials
                    who were trying to undermine Peruvian sovereignty in some way. They just wanted
                    to adopt a more neutralist stance and started cozing up to the Russians to show
                    their independence.</p>
                <p>Q: They felt that with the American military arms sales and advisers that this
                    was sort of leading to some American military domination of Peru, or at least
                    the presence was too large there, too intrusive?</p>
                <p>LORD: They were just very paranoid about the role of the U.S. and suspicious of
                    the military, CIA and U.S. presence in general. They wanted to limit the ability
                    of the U.S. to influence events in Peru.</p>
                <p>Q: We talked a little bit about your life as a consul in Arequipa and what you
                    were doing and the kind of life that you led. How did that change when you got
                    to Lima? Did you have a different kind of lifestyle?</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>LORD: Well, you made a whole new set of friends. Of course, you had the embassy
                    staff as a nucleus and met other American and Peruvian friends through them and
                    through your own contacts. We had quite an active social life in Lima with an
                    entirely different group of people. There was a much larger diplomatic corps,
                    more Americans and a different variety of Peruvians. A successful
                    representational gathering that was held at the residence while I was there was
                    one for the moon landing in 1969. We had all kinds of people (Peruvians,
                    government, media, etc.) there with multiple TV screens positioned inside the
                    residence so everybody could watch the landing on the moon. It was a spectacular
                    event.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think USIA did a terrific job of making it possible
                        foembassies and foreign capitals to view the event.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: After that, three of the astronauts came through with pieceof the moon rock
                    as a public relations sequel to the event.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember who they were?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Not right offhand.</p>
                <p>Q: It was a great thrill for me when I was in Dar es Salaam a little later on and
                    a group of astronauts came through and one of them was Pete Conrad who had been
                    a classmate of mine both in school and at college. It was great fun to see him
                    again.</p>
                <p>Anything else that you would like to add? Did you think it was better for your
                    career being at an embassy rather than a consulate? What rank were you by this
                    time?</p>
                <p>LORD: I was an FSO-4, I guess. Working at an embassy you certainlbecame well
                    known among a group of senior officers.</p>
                <p>A couple of other things worth mentioning. It was a great time to be in Peru
                    because it was before any of the insurgency that came on later which made it
                    difficult to travel around the country. Even under the military we were free to
                    travel around pretty much, so frequently on weekends we would get out of Lima
                    because the climate of Lima is unique in that this cold Humboldt current that I
                    mentioned cools off the air there which is quite moist, giving Lima a very humid
                    atmosphere. In the wintertime, it is under a continual cloud cover and in the
                    morning the humidity is 100 percent. You would think it had rained the night
                    before, but it hadn't. The west coast of Latin America from northern Chile on up
                    to Ecuador is arid; it never rains. In the summertime, the sun is warm enough to
                    burn off some of the overcast so you have some sunlight. It can get quite hot in
                    the summer as a result, but in the wintertime it is cold, grey, and
                    depressing.</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It sounds like Lima is a little depressing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: This is a circumstance that exists only along the coast. When you get up a
                    little higher, a half hour out of Lima, you can get above this continual cloud
                    cover along the coast and into the sun. There are lots of interesting valleys,
                    towns, mining sites, etc. to visit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, the whole embassy on weekends takes off to the
                        east?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Some people more than others. We certainly enjoyed traveling. The Callejon
                    de Huaylas is one of the more picturesque valleys in the mountains to the north,
                    and the small town of Huaraz was central to it. This was all destroyed in May,
                    1970 by one of the worse earthquakes that Peru has experienced in this century.
                    The town of Huaraz was completely wiped out by a mud flow from a 20,000 foot
                    mountain at one end of that valley. As a result something like 30,000 people
                    were killed just in that one town. When you add the other towns where similar
                    things occurred there were at least 50,000 deaths as a result of the earthquake.
                    The U.S. played a remarkable role in supplying emergency relief. I can remember
                    the air force adviser, and who was very much an activist, take charge sort of
                    fellow, coordinating a lot of the relief that came in by air from the U.S. for
                    the Peruvians. We had an operation going around the clock. That was one of the
                    memorable events while I was there. In Lima we felt the earthquake. I remember
                    running up the stairs to get one of my daughters out of her crib and running
                    down the stairs again (The whole time the house was trembling.) and running out
                    into the street. Fortunately, no real damage or loss of life occurred in Lima;
                    most of it was up to the north.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's end for this session. It is 1970 and your tour in
                        Lima iending and where are you going next?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: That's an interesting story of chance in the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's save that until the next time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: All right.</p>
                <p>Q: Today is May 7 and I am Lambert (Nick) Heyniger and I'm continuing our
                    interview with Peter P. Lord. In terms of chronology Peter has just wound up his
                    tour as political officer in Lima and has been reassigned to Bridgetown,
                    Barbados as DCM. So, Peter, let me ask you first, how did you get to be a DCM at
                    your early young age?</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>LORD: That was a result of coincidence, fortuity and good luck. We were assigned
                    from Lima to the political section in the embassy in Madrid. The day the packers
                    came I received a call from Washington saying sorry but your assignment has been
                    canceled but go ahead with your packing anyway we will find some place else for
                    you to go. The reason the assignment was canceled was because the principal
                    officer in Porto Alegre, Brazil, Curt Cutter, had been stopped at a roadblock by
                    terrorists. Being a good Californian he didn't stop but put his foot on the gas
                    pedal and ran the blockade and survived, but with a bullet wound in his back.
                    So, he was promptly removed from harm's way, in case there should be another
                    attempt. Well, where to put him? Why not a nice safe spot like the political
                    section in Madrid? So, off he went to my job in Madrid.</p>
                <p>When we got to Washington they asked how would I like to be DCM in Barbados
                    because the DCM there, John Dreyfuss, now deceased, had been suddenly moved, I
                    think, to Guatemala City, requested by whoever was ambassador there at the time.
                    Not knowing much about Barbados but being attracted by the title of DCM I said,
                    “Why not?” So, off we went to Bridgetown and found it busy, interesting, a great
                    place to be, a very enjoyable assignment, one of our favorites.</p>
                <p>Q: Before we get there, I believe often in the Foreign Service, the ambassador or
                    principal officer is quite interested in who is being assigned to his or her
                    post. In this case you are going down there to be the ambassador's deputy, did
                    you know the ambassador?</p>
                <p>LORD: The ambassador was Eileen Donovan, a career Foreign Service officer, who
                    had previously been consul general in Barbados during an earlier time before
                    independence. She was suddenly being faced with having to replace her DCM and
                    there not being much choice. She asked me if I would be interested. I think she
                    was really quite worried that the Department would assign someone to Bridgetown
                    who didn't want to go. In fact, my predecessor there, I think, who was much more
                    of a Latino oriented political officer much preferred to go off to Guatemala
                    City.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were a Latino type yourself by this time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Well, I didn't know what it would be like, but I assured hethat the job
                    appealed to me. She said, “Okay,” and down I went.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Bridgetown like?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>LORD: Bridgetown in those days was a more pleasant and manageable embassy and
                    place to live in than it has become since. This was before the U.S. intervention
                    in Grenada, before we had an AID mission in Barbados. We had a small USIA office
                    which was closed when I was there. I seem to bring closings wherever I go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: USIA was cutting back. We had a large Peace Corps for the eastern Carribean
                    program which was headquartered in Barbados. The mission was not too big, it was
                    quite small as a matter of fact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think we should also mention, should we not, that you
                        were nojust an envoy to Barbados but also to a number of other islands.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: There were six other islands which were “associated states” in association
                    with Great Britain. These included from south to north, Grenada, St. Vincent,
                    St. Lucia, Dominica, Antigua and St. Kitts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which meant you had to do a great deal of traveling.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Well, somebody did and usually that was not I, unfortunately, although I
                    did get to all the islands at least once. The leaders of all these states were
                    usually strong personalities who had been in office for some time and the
                    ambassador knew them from her previous tour as consul general, so she would go
                    around whenever anything important had to be done. Otherwise, our one political
                    officer was responsible for liaison with these island governments, so he
                    traveled quite a bit. In addition, we also had in our consular jurisdiction two
                    British crown colonies, Montserrat and the British Virgin Islands. So, that
                    added up to Barbados plus eight other islands, which was quite a long title for
                    the ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have an economic officer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We had an economic officer and an administrative officer. The busiest part
                    of the embassy was the consular section because traditionally immigration to the
                    U.S. from Barbados was high. The “Bajans” live on an overpopulated island. It is
                    an island which is only 20 miles long and 16 miles wide, which makes it smaller
                    than Rhode Island or Delaware. Barbadians are well educated and tend to
                    emigrate. Money sent home by them has come to be an important source of national
                    income. So, the consular section was quite busy. There was a consul, and two or
                    three vice consuls.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>Q: This is a new job for you and more of a supervisory and management position
                    than what we would call a substantive position, what were your chief
                    responsibilities?</p>
                <p>LORD: They were the same as in any embassy. I was an alter ego to the ambassador
                    and had to fill in when she was not there. As time went on, she spent more time
                    away from the office, if not traveling or on home leave, just at home on the
                    island because of health problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you found yourself to some extent running the
                        post?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. It wasn't a difficult job and I enjoyed that. It was a busy job
                    contrary to what many people might think, but it wasn't too busy, we had time to
                    enjoy the island, the water sports and do some traveling.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember because I visited you there, you had small
                        children.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. While in Lima our first two daughters were born and a third daughter
                    was born in Bridgetown. This was a very easy place to bring up young
                    children.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your residence on the water? Could you go swimming all
                        thtime?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We were not right on the water but close to it and for young kids all you
                    had to do was put them in a bathing suit and take them down to the beach every
                    day. We had servants who made life easier for my wife. But, she also got quite
                    involved with the local community, which is English speaking. People are very
                    friendly there and don't have some of the hang ups and attitudes towards
                    Americans that you find on some of the other islands where the racial
                    composition of the population makes for much more friction both in their local
                    politics and towards the American presence.</p>
                <p>Q: I would like to pursue that a little further with you. For one reason or
                    another I have visited a number of Carribean islands myself, including Barbados
                    and Jamaica. I see a rather significant difference between life and culture and
                    people in Jamaica on the one hand and in Barbados on the other. Barbados struck
                    me as a place where everyone seemed to be nicely dressed. The elderly Barbadian
                    women when they went into town had crocheted gloves on and hats and everybody
                    was nicely turned out. I got the impression that Barbados was a well established
                    society. Is that true?</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>LORD: It's true that it is a civilized place and that it has taken its English
                    inheritance seriously and adopted British ways up to the point that it is
                    frequently called “Little England” just because it has some of the same
                    conservative, well behaved attitudes towards getting along with each other. I
                    suppose that has been breaking down gradually over time, particularly as lack of
                    employment and economic problems assert themselves. But, at least when we were
                    there it was a very friendly, easy place to get along and the people were nice
                    in the sense you described.</p>
                <p>Q: I wanted to ask you if Barbados, while you were there, got involved in any
                    efforts towards Caribbean union, Caribbean federation. Was the local government
                    trying actively and hard to promote closer relations with other islands? Was
                    that a priority?</p>
                <p>LORD: Not really. That had been tried and played out pretty much. The Federation
                    of the West Indies involving Jamaica, Trinidad, and Barbados and the larger
                    islands didn't get anywhere because of differences in size and costs and who
                    should bear them. Barbados was under the leadership of Errol Barrow, who was the
                    first prime minister after independence in 1966 and who had a second term. He
                    won reelection while we were there. He was very much a strong, independently
                    minded person who had been trained as a lawyer and economist and tended to see
                    things in realistic and practical terms and always weighed decisions and
                    policies in terms of what made sense for Barbados. Costs were always an
                    important factor because Barbados is not a rich country.</p>
                <p>Q: Was part of the problem that he and the Barbadian government were concerned
                    that possibly federation would actually bring a lowering of the standard of
                    living, a lowering of the economy in Barbados as other islands got more
                    attention?</p>
                <p>LORD: Not necessarily. Barbados is so small that it stands to benefit from
                    becoming a part of a larger economic unit. But, it doesn't have much money to
                    contribute.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Barrow didn't see any particular benefits for
                        Barbados?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No. He also didn't want to be upstaged or overwhelmed by thlarger countries
                    of Trinidad or Jamaica so he tended to go it alone.</p>
                <p>Q: Let's shift focus a little bit. You mentioned that one of the other islands
                    that you were responsible for was Grenada. Can you tell us anything about
                    communist penetration of labor unions, particularly on the docks and in the
                    harbor of Barbados? Any show of Cuban interest in getting involved in
                    Barbados?</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>LORD: No, that wasn't a real threat or danger when I was there. The labor
                    movement in Barbados was dominated by the Barbados Labor Union and was led by
                    Mr. Frank Walcott, who was a member of the same party as Barrow. So, he was a
                    senior member in the labor movement and in the parliament. Labor didn't get out
                    of hand. Most of the private economic interests in Barbados were controlled by
                    the traditional white elite.</p>
                <p>Q: There is bauxite, for example, in Jamaica and therefore there is more labor
                    unrest, more chances of the government having trouble with unions than would
                    likely be the case in Barbados?</p>
                <p>LORD: I don't know that you can blame it on bauxite. Usually mining industries
                    like that pay a pretty good wage. The problem in Jamaica is you have two very
                    competitive parties there and probably two competitive labor groupings and that
                    may account for the labor unrest in Jamaica in part. Barbados has just one
                    government-related union. The economy in Barbados had traditionally been based
                    on sugar - harvesting sugarcane and refining it.</p>
                <p>Q: I'm getting the idea that Barbados and Barbadians are possibly somewhat more
                    conservative than might be the case with other islanders. Were there problems
                    with regard to crime and American citizens being molested or attacked?</p>
                <p>LORD: Very seldom. That has become more frequent, as I understand it, lately, but
                    at the time we were there the economy was in fairly good shape, although I think
                    it has gotten worse since then because sugar has continued to decline. Tourism
                    has become bigger and bigger and provides the main source of income. But, that
                    means there are a lot of tourists around and Barbados looks at tourism
                    ambivalently because while they appreciate the money the tourists bring in, they
                    don't like being overrun by largely white tourists who are taking precedence
                    before anybody else while they are there. So, with the worsening of the economy
                    and the increase in tourism, that means there will be more crime and resentment
                    of whites.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there for four years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We were assigned for three and we liked it so much we stayefor four.</p>
                <p>Q: Do you remember during that period any particular times when you had to make
                    demarches to the Barbadian government on U.S.-Barbados issues or international
                    OAS or UN issues?</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>LORD: Certainly there were a lot of UN issues taken up because Barbados was
                    essentially a pro-western, pro-American government that thought the same way we
                    did on many things, so Barbados' support was sought in the UN. I remember
                    particularly the debate over whether the China seat should go to Red China or
                    stay with the Nationalist Chinese. Barbados had established formal diplomatic
                    ties with Taiwan and had a resident Chinese ambassador there who did a very good
                    job. The Department called me in the evening one year when the vote was just
                    about to come up. The country director back in Washington said that they really
                    needed Barbados' vote this time around and could I find out what Barbados was
                    going to do. This was after I had been there for a while and my contacts were
                    well developed, so I was able to obtain assurance that evening from the foreign
                    ministry that Barbados was expected to vote in favor of Nationalist China. I
                    passed this along. And it did.</p>
                <p>One of the bilateral questions that took a lot of our time while we were there
                    was negotiating a new air transport agreement between the U.S. and Barbados.
                    Errol Barrow was a pilot and had a strong interest in establishing a national
                    airline. He wanted to get a route to the U.S. It was complicated by the fact
                    that the tourist industry brought a lot of tourists on flights from the U.S. to
                    Barbados and many of them on U.S. carriers. Barbados wanted to restrict U.S.
                    carriers as leverage for getting its own route to the U.S. Formal negotiations
                    were held in Bridgetown with U.S. government representatives who came down from
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They applied pressure in the sense that they said you
                        can't havany more flights to Bridgetown unless we get a gateway in JFK?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: That is what the arguments would be carried to an extreme but they were
                    wise enough to know that they didn't want to deny U.S. flights and therefore
                    U.S. tourists. They never did get agreement for their airline, which they
                    finally established. It wasn't really a Barbados airline although it had the
                    title and so forth. It was a plane leased from Freddy Laker's enterprise in
                    Britain, as I recall, and the question revolved around what constituted an
                    airline and whether this was just a temporary lease which didn't make it an
                    airline. But, it did fly to Luxembourg via Iceland. I took it one time.</p>
                <p>Q: Anything else that you would like to tell us about your tour in Bridgetown?
                    You were there for four years. You must have practically developed webbed
                    feet.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>LORD: You asked about the communist influence. There wasn't any that amounted to
                    anything anywhere in many of the islands. Antigua and Dominica had some
                    pro-communist activists but they were kept pretty much boxed up and under close
                    surveillance and didn't generate a large following. The New Jewel Movement,
                    which developed in Grenada while I was still there under the leadership of
                    Maurice Bishop, was more nationalist and leftist in some aspects than the
                    existing government. Most of the time I was there, it was led by Eric Gairy, one
                    of those old time leaders who was an autocrat and aristocrat. When Maurice
                    Bishop did gain political power and was then executed by the movement backed by
                    Cuba that led to the U.S. intervention, that did become a serious threat by
                    Cuban backed forces. But that happened after I left. It happened fairly quickly.
                    When I left in 1974, that was not a danger. I can't remember exactly when our
                    intervention in Grenada occurred and Bishop was killed, but it was several years
                    afterward.</p>
                <p>Q: Yes. Also, it seems to me that in the context of the Caribbean that actually
                    executing a government leader seems a very unusual thing to have happen.</p>
                <p>LORD: It was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Barbados established diplomatic relations with Cuba in
                        1972. Did we make a substantial effort to try to persuade the Barbadian
                        government not to do so?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, we did. I don't remember now the circumstances of that recognition. I
                    think it was probably an effort by Errol Barrow to show his independence of the
                    U.S. and to assert his own Barbadian nationalism. A resident Cuban mission was
                    not established in Barbados while I was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ambassador Donovan stepped down while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, she was there when I arrived and still there when I left. She finished
                    her tour shortly after I left and the new ambassador came later that same year,
                    1974.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With a new DCM.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, but he arrived after I left so we did not overlap.</p>
                <p>Q: It is always unfortunate, isn't it, when both of the top two people leave and
                    arrive at the same time. You enjoyed being a DCM in the Caribbean?</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>LORD: Yes, that was good fun. It was a good career move and a nice place to live
                    because Barbados was such a pleasant place, both in climate and friendliness of
                    the Barbadians. I might add that the one memory I have of one non political
                    event was the erupting of the volcano in St. Vincent, which is a 100 miles due
                    west of Barbados. St. Vincent is a charming little island with a 3,000 foot
                    volcano called Mount Soufriere. It was a favorite place to take people who came
                    to visit who liked this kind of adventure. The first time I climbed to the top
                    of Soufriere was from the windward side with an old school friend who visited.
                    There was a lovely cone in the top with a clear green lake in the crater.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go down in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. It seems to me we did go down and felt the water and even went for a
                    swim. The next time I went over I took my wife along and two other visitors. We
                    had an arduous climb up from the leeward side on a much hotter day. We got to
                    the top to find that the clear green lake had turned to a light grey. Steam was
                    rising from the crater lake with a strong sulfurous smell. We concluded that the
                    volcano was becoming active and we shouldn't stick around very long, so we
                    didn't. We went back to the hotel we were staying at which was run by an
                    American who had been there a number of years and who had an interest in nature
                    and its forces. We reported this to him and asked him to report it to the
                    authorities. I don't know what happened but it never got reported and the fact
                    that the volcano was becoming active was relayed by a pilot of a small plane who
                    happened to fly over and noticed it. So, I didn't get credit for this discovery;
                    somebody else did.</p>
                <p>It didn't erupt violently. What happened was that an island of molten lava
                    appeared in the center of the lake and, fortunately, the plug was never blown at
                    that time. I went back later a third time and saw this island of volcanic
                    material in the center of the crater. But Soufriere has been a problem ever
                    since. There have been periods when it has threatened to erupt and when they
                    have actually evacuated the population from the northern end of the island where
                    the volcano is, but I don't think it has erupted violently with a lot of ash the
                    way the volcano in Montserrat did just recently or the way Mont Pelee did in
                    Martinique in 1906, or thereabouts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you think is going to happen with Montserrat? I
                        thinthey have wanted to evacuate all of the inhabitants for a while.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: The southern part of the island where the capital, Plymouth, is located has
                    been almost completely destroyed by the ash which is many feet deep. I think all
                    the buildings, the capitol and docks, etc. from what I read have been abandoned,
                    and they are hoping to rebuild in the northern end of the island, which is less
                    likely to be affected by future volcanic activity.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather you didn't go swimming on your second and third
                        trips uthe Soufriere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are now at 1974 and you have been in Barbados for four
                        years.What happens next?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Next I was assigned to senior training at the National War College (NWC),
                    so we went back to Washington and spent a very interesting year there, at least
                    for me since I was at the college. My wife found it less rewarding to be stuck
                    at home with three young children and no help.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the National War College at Ft. McNair?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go on your trip?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: To Africa, but I went on only half of the trip because by the time that
                    came up I knew that I would be assigned to Lusaka, Zambia, so I was able to
                    break off from the National War College trip and visit Lusaka briefly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me a little more about your time at the War
                        College?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We had a good class. Stape Roy and I were in the same home room to begin
                    with. He later went on to be ambassador to a number of places. Jim Rosenthal was
                    also in the same home room; he went on to become an ambassador. Mike Kennedy was
                    one of the hostages in Tehran in 1979. Terry Healy went out to be DCM in New
                    Zealand and then ambassador to Sierra Leone. So, we had a number of excellent
                    people in the class.</p>
                <p>Q: What is your estimation of the value of this course? I know a number of people
                    are somewhat concerned that State Department officers when they are selected for
                    senior training go off to a military institution for their training. Is this
                    really a worthwhile experience? Some officers have looked upon it as a year
                    off.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>LORD: I think it is a very valuable year and I think most people who go through
                    it feel that way, too. It certainly is not a year off, they make you work very
                    hard. It is a very broadening experience. It is meant to broaden the military
                    members and also to broaden the civilian students. So, you get a broad exposure
                    to national security in its widest concept, whether you are talking nuclear
                    deterrent strategy, which was an important issue back in 1975 when I was there,
                    or whether you are dealing with the international oil crisis, which was another
                    serious issue at the time. You get a broad review of all the geographic areas,
                    which lets you catch up on the rest of the world.</p>
                <p>Q: Beyond these substantive aspects where you are learning about other parts of
                    the world or political/military concerns, does the War College also prepare
                    students in terms of management training, supervisory training skills?</p>
                <p>LORD: No, it did not and I can understand why because you have such a mix of
                    military and different civilian students there that their management
                    requirements would be so different.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Managing a submarine is different from managing an
                        embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. The NWC tended to concentrate on more substantive subjects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said you had learned while you were at the War College
                        that you were going to be assigned to Lusaka in Zambia. How did that come
                        about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I liked being DCM in Barbados so I looked to see what elswould be
                    available. The job in Lusaka was the one that fell my way.</p>
                <p>Q: The assignment to Barbados in a certain sense represented a moving away for
                    you from Latin America. You never went back. Most FSOs who get into Latin
                    American affairs never escape.</p>
                <p>LORD: Well, there are certain advantages to that. Once you become well known in a
                    bureau and all your experience is there you are likely to find a home and jobs
                    there. Some say that a bureau after a while has an obligation to use you, take
                    care of you. If you don't have a parent bureau in that sense, you are an
                    outsider. There probably is some truth to that. But, at the time there were no
                    jobs coming up at my grade level in Latin America...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were by this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I was a class 3 I believe.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would think that most DCM jobs in Latin America would be
                        reallsenior officer, FSO-2 and up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: That's right. The Bridgetown job was classified at a level and I as a 4 was
                    put in there because of the need at the time.</p>
                <p>Q: So, you were offered Lusaka, said, “Fine” and off you went arriving in Lusaka
                    in 1975.</p>
                <p>LORD: We got there in August, 1975.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: The ambassador was Jean Wilkowski. That assignment was made fairly early in
                    the year. When I was still at the War College, she came to Washington on
                    consultation with an agenda that she felt I could help her with. The War College
                    is pretty much a full-time job and you don't have a telephone in easy reach. You
                    are at Fort McNair.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did she want?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I can't remember the project now but it was something that would be normal
                    for the desk officer to do, but the desk officer was busy, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was Ambassador Wilkowski different from Ambassador
                        Donovan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: She was much more dynamic, much higher key in terms of operating style. She
                    had a lot of good ideas, all of them requiring a certain amount of staff time to
                    work out. The embassy in Lusaka was a small embassy: one political officer, one
                    economic officer, one consular officer, DCM, a one-man USIS operation, and no
                    Peace Corps. Her ideas and projects really stretched that embassy to its limit.
                    A person with as much momentum as she had really deserved a larger embassy and
                    staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm getting the impression that people felt they were
                        workinpretty hard.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>LORD: Yes, she kept everybody very busy. I came in in the middle of this as DCM
                    and became the liaison between her and the staff. She was really pretty much a
                    hands on ambassador and used to get involved in everything. At times one felt
                    she really didn't need a DCM because she liked to deal directly with the
                    operative officers themselves. Anyway, I found it a difficult situation and
                    found her difficult to work with. She would change her mind, which everybody has
                    a right to do, but wouldn't always keep you informed.</p>
                <p>Q: The job of a DCM is often to be the alter ego for the ambassador with the
                    assumption that the ambassador is out of the embassy a great deal attending
                    diplomatic functions or meeting with host country people and that the DCM runs
                    the embassy somewhat like the head of chancery in the British service. But, if
                    your ambassador is a very hands on person who wants to know is some detail what
                    is going on in the consular section, that gets in the way of you or any other
                    DCM who is trying to be the supervisor of the various embassy sections.</p>
                <p>LORD: Unlike in Bridgetown where I had been the ambassador's alter ego and could
                    step into her role vis-a-vis the host government, etc., that was not the case in
                    Lusaka because she handled herself all of the relationship with the president of
                    the country, Kenneth Kaunda, who ran pretty much a one-man show himself and was
                    the key government person. My period in Zambia coincided with the proxy cold war
                    going on in Angola where we were supporting one side in the civil war there and
                    the Russians were supporting the other side. Part of our support involved Zambia
                    as a transient country. I was never brought into any of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the United States government on a semi-covert
                        basisupporting Jonas Sivimbi and UNITA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, I would say so, but it wasn't part of my job description or the
                    embassy's really. Understandably, if it was going to be of a covert nature it
                    would be held closely. But, this was true in general of relations with the
                    people at the ministerial level, etc.</p>
                <p>Q: Was Ambassador Wilkowski dealing with that as well as the normal diplomatic
                    considerations? Was she also the one who supervised the assistance to the
                    Angolans?</p>
                <p>LORD: I think much of it was coordinated between her and Kaunda. can't get into
                    that because it was not an area that I was privy to.</p>
                <p>Q: It could be that Zambia was an unusual situation but I thought that in most
                    embassies whatever clearances and activities the ambassador was privy to, the
                    DCM was privy to as well.</p>
                <p>LORD: That frequently is the case but that was not the case there.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>Q: Some of the main things that concern the United States in Zambia are copper
                    mining, the railway that had been built by the Chinese from Tanzania to Lusaka,
                    the whole question of Zambia's isolation from the rest of the world because so
                    many of the supply routes went through South Africa and on the other hand
                    Zambia's involvement in the liberation of Southern Rhodesia.</p>
                <p>LORD: Southern Rhodesia was another big issue at the time. Kaunda was leading the
                    African effort to bring majority rule to Southern Rhodesia. At that time the
                    border was closed and we had no relations with Southern Rhodesia. Most of these
                    issues were Zambian issues rather than bilateral issues. We had a position and
                    would make that known from time to time and consult, but Kaunda was his own man,
                    and very much a leader of the third world and kept the U.S. at arms length.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Mugabe in Lusaka?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I don't recall. He might have been in and out but he was noa player at the
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who handled embassy relations with the liberation
                        forces?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I think that Mugabe and the other nationalists were located iTanzania.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Along with the South Africans.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. Zambia was for one reason or another not a locatiowhere the
                    nationalists were active.</p>
                <p>Q: It also might be somewhat dangerous because the South African security and
                    secret police could reach out to some extent through Southern Rhodesia and cause
                    trouble for the insurgents if in Zambia much more easily than they could in Dar
                    es Salaam.</p>
                <p>LORD: Zambia was feeling very much its geographic landlockesituation which
                    affected its ability to export its copper.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Benguela railroad open at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: It was not open; it had been sabotaged. That was very serious and Zambia
                    was trying to develop alternative railroad transport through Mozambique and
                    through Tanzania.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was that working?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: After a point it was working all right but they were having trouble getting
                    the same volume of exports out as they had before the sabotage.</p>
                <p>Q: I had been in Dar es Salaam a bit earlier and it is one thing to build a
                    railroad from the coast to Zambia, but you also need to improve the port if you
                    are really going to accelerate imports and exports. When I left Tanzania not
                    much had been done to really transform the port in Dar es Salaam.</p>
                <p>LORD: I think the port of Dar and the port of Beira in Mozambique were both
                    bottlenecks for Zambian exports and imports. Zambia at this time was just
                    beginning a long downturn in its copper earnings. Not only were they having
                    trouble with transportation but the copper prices were also on a continual
                    decline. So, Zambia has been in serious economic trouble ever since I was
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you tell us a little more about President
                        Kaunda'dissatisfaction with American policy towards Southern Africa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: He was a great advocate of majority rule in Southern Rhodesia and in South
                    Africa. He was always dissatisfied with the perceived lack of support. But, he
                    and Ambassador Wilkowski seemed to have a good relationship. She spent a lot of
                    time in his office. Bilateral relations between the two countries were really
                    carried on between her and him. Everything else was secondary. Otherwise, it was
                    not a particular interesting time to be in Zambia because Zambia took a
                    neutralist position. The Chinese and Russian embassies there were big. The
                    government was not receptive to us really. It was a very formal relationship and
                    the atmosphere was not one where you could easily develop Zambian contacts of a
                    political nature or even of the cultural nature. The Zambians took their lead
                    from Kaunda. While Zambia had been subject to British influence in the past, it
                    didn't seem to have sunk in very much in terms of friendly pro-Western
                    attitudes.</p>
                <p>Q: This is very much the case when I was in Dar. We had a great deal of
                    difficulty persuading Tanzanian officials to come for dinner or to a reception.
                    When USIS brought people and attractions to Tanzania, people didn't really turn
                    out very much for them. Did you, yourself, have the chance to travel around the
                    country much? LORD: It was an appealing place to be in terms of the wildlife and
                    the climate. We did get down to Victoria Falls on the Zambezi river, and to the
                    game park at Kafue in the West. We did not get to the game park in eastern
                    Zambia or the game park just across the border in Botswana. So, there was plenty
                    we didn't get to because our tour was curtailed.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any interesting American visitors that you had a chance to
                        takto some of the tourist areas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Not really. Zambia was pretty much off the beaten path.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were your kids by this time going to grade school? Was
                        there ainternational school in Lusaka?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: There was an international school and our two oldest daughters were there.
                    This was their first time in school, so they were feeling their way. I think
                    they enjoyed it. Our tour was curtailed and we left in March. My wife's mother
                    was dying of cancer and she left to go back to take care of her. The ambassador
                    kindly consented to arranging a compassionate transfer for us. We would have
                    been separated and the children would have been affected at that age.
                    Furthermore, it gave her the chance to find another DCM.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who replaced you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I can't remember who came in as DCM, but Goody Cooke was sent out to fill
                    in and to help prepare for the upcoming visit of Secretary Kissinger some time
                    later that spring.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever compare notes with him and battle scars?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: He said he was left alone pretty much to work on the Kissingevisit and
                    there didn't seem to be any problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. So, this is 1976 and you are reassigned to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I was reassigned to the Department in PER/FCA as chief of thLatin America
                    personnel assignment division.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a great job.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I enjoyed the job. I had not seen personnel in operation before. My
                    assistant and I were responsible for staffing all the diplomatic and consular
                    posts in the ARA area. We coordinated closely with the ARA bureau in doing that,
                    although we were part of the Personnel Bureau under the director general. The
                    regional bureaus were no longer in a position to make assignment decisions to
                    the extent that the personnel officers in the geographic bureaus used to. But,
                    their recommendations and preferences were taken into consideration.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Everybody is interested in personnel. That is one thing
                        learned during my tour there. Who was the director general?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: The director general, I think, when I came in was Carol Laise. She wasn't
                    there the whole time but I can't remember who succeeded her. Dick Fox was the
                    director of CDA (career development and assignments). Art Wortzel was Dick's
                    boss.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were working for Fox?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were in charge of assignments to Latin
                        America?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes.</p>
                <p>Q: So, it is a constant daily interplay between the interests of the officers and
                    the interests of the bureau. The internal diplomacy and negotiating within the
                    Department was almost as extensive sometimes as with foreign countries.
                    Right?</p>
                <p>LORD: It took a lot of coordinating and researching and convincinsometimes.</p>
                <p>Q: Because either the bureau does want or does not want certain people in certain
                    positions and that is one side of the equation. The other side of the equation
                    is what is good for the officers in their development and also where does the
                    best interests of the service lie.</p>
                <p>LORD: I think by and large the system worked pretty well while I was there. There
                    was a good collegial group of officers who approached personnel assignments in a
                    responsible, professional manner. The difficult thing was when you had several
                    candidates who were equally qualified, somebody had to lose out. Generally it
                    came down to sensible, easy decisions, I would say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your job had more to do with dealing with positions rather
                        thadeveloping careers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. The career advising function was in a separate office. We worked with
                    the career development advisers who recommended to us officers who would be well
                    suited for the jobs we were trying to fill.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>Q: I recall there were either weekly or biweekly meetings where you and all the
                    other officers who were handling assignments to the bureaus and all the officers
                    who were handling people's careers got together and sat down and assignments
                    were proposed and discussed.</p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, the so-called panel meetings. There was a series everweek depending on
                    the cone, economic, political, admin and consular.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In your opinion the system was working rather well when
                        you werthere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I think it was working pretty well.</p>
                <p>Q: Some time during this period, Secretary Kissinger got perturbed, particularly
                    with the Latin American bureau, by cables that were coming in which were written
                    in such language that people outside the Latin American bureau couldn't
                    understand them. It was a very specialized knowledge, somewhat like AID cables.
                    This is when he came up with changing geographic areas after each
                    assignment.</p>
                <p>LORD: I believe it was called GLOP.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell us about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Global Overseas Program, or something like that. I don't remember it too
                    well except that it was one factor determining a person's assignment. It had to
                    be out of area if the person had been in one area for a certain length of
                    time.</p>
                <p>Q: This must have been kind of tough for the bureau because the bureau wants
                    officers who have experience in the area and you were constantly being more or
                    less compelled to accept officers whose previous career had been in Europe, or
                    some other area. How did that work out?</p>
                <p>LORD: Well, the geographic bureaus had to live with it and sometimes when they
                    felt strongly they might have that factor over ridden somehow. By and large, a
                    lot of people had served in more than one bureau so in many cases they already
                    met the requirement. Sometimes, if there was a good job somewhere else, they
                    didn't mind escaping from a bureau.</p>
                <p>Q: When I was in personnel working for Ambassador Laise as the director general,
                    it was early in her tour as director general and she deputized my boss,
                    Barrington King, and about half a dozen other officers in personnel to do a
                    study and make recommendations as to how the entire personnel system and the
                    functioning of assignments and the advancement of officers could be improved.
                    Did anything like that take place while you were there?</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>LORD: It seems to me that there were always studies going on of one sort or
                    another, but nothing comes to mind and I didn't become involved in any such
                    studies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Washington for two years. By that time, your
                        wiffelt able to go overseas again?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: She, of course, found Washington a hardship because she had three children
                    to take care of. Her mother had passed away later that spring or summer.</p>
                <p>Q: In principle, an assignment back in Washington at that time was for four
                    years, but you left after only two. Any particular reason for that?</p>
                <p>LORD: There must have been some flexibility there because I was eligible for an
                    assignment overseas. Again I was interested in a DCM job and the one that came
                    up this time was Yaounde, Cameroon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is your second assignment as DCM in Africa and you
                        arrived there in 1978.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell us first about the American embassy in Yaounde. Who
                        was thambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: The ambassador was another woman, my third woman ambassador,Mabel
                    Smythe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A career officer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: A political appointee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A political appointee in Cameroon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. Her husband had been a political appointee as ambassador years before
                    in the Middle East and he died shortly before she went out to Yaounde.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any relation to Henry Smythe of the atomic bomb, the
                        famouprofessor?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I don't think so. She was a delightful personality.Everybody liked her.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did she like Cameroon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: She did. She was a black American who had previous experiencin African
                    affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had she been teaching about Africa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: She had been in New York with a foundation which promoted American/African
                    relations. So, she took the job with relish and made friends everywhere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had she been there long when you arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: She got there in the summer and wanted the DCM who was there to stay until
                    she got her feet on the ground and until an inspection scheduled for November
                    took place. That was arranged and we arrived middle or late November and spent
                    the next three years there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was the embassy in Yaounde different than the embassy
                        iLusaka?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: The entire U.S. mission in Yaounde was a bigger more complemission than
                    either of my two earlier ones.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We had a big AID program, a big Peace Corps program, a larger USIA
                    operation with three or four Americans in it, but it was still a small U.S.
                    mission. We had an ambassador, DCM, no political officer, an economic officer,
                    consular officer, admin, GSO and regional security officer. So, the embassy side
                    was pretty small. The AID side was the biggest there. So, it was a big country
                    team to coordinate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, this was in that sense a more interesting job for
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: It was a very interesting and challenging job in that sense. Cameroon is
                    complicated, too, in that part of it is Francophone and part of it is
                    Anglophone. The western part of Cameroon had been part of Nigeria and at the
                    time of independence a referendum was taken to see whether that part wanted to
                    join Nigeria or Cameroon. They voted to join Cameroon. The Anglophone part is
                    definitely in the minority. They feel disadvantaged by the Francophone majority
                    in the south and north.</p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Most of the government including the prime minister and
                        thministers are more apt to be Francophone than Anglophone?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, the majority are, but the president at the time, Ahmadou Ahidjo, was a
                    very skillful balancer of ethnic and regional groups. He had not only the
                    Anglophones in the west, but also other tribal areas which are perhaps more
                    important in the north, south, and east. The northern part of the country is
                    Muslim. Central Cameroon is dominated by one tribal group. Southern Cameroon,
                    where Douala is, the commercial center and the larger of the two cities...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Douala is larger than Yaounde?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, it is the commercial city.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why is the capital in Yaounde?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: That is a good question. I can't remember the answer to that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do a lot of people in Cameroon speak both English and
                        French?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. If you are an Anglophone and have any national ambitions you have to
                    learn French. It is more that way than the French learning English.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't think you had had previously a French speaking
                        post.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I had not although I had satisfied my Foreign Service languagrequirement
                    when I entered with my school French.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they give you a refresher?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I did have an FSI refresher before I went out and that watremendously
                    helpful.</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>While Cameroon was made up of this marvelous mosaic of regions and ethnic groups
                    and language groups, it was a difficult place to make your way in some ways
                    because it was pretty much an autocratic state run by Ahidjo. He didn't want his
                    government being too friendly with any outside power, particularly the United
                    States. The Ahidjo government was friendly but kept us at arms length. The
                    French, of course, had the inside position there since it was a former French
                    colony.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also the British as well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Well, no. Some of the people in the Anglophone part of western Cameroon
                    probably had ties with the British embassy, but the government was a Francophone
                    government by and large.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So this is a second assignment where cultivating relations
                        witthe host government is kind of a challenge.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Certainly Zambia was that way, and Peru under the military wasomewhat that
                    way, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have for example a hard time making appointments
                        tdeliver demarches or talk about bilateral relations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, you could always get your hearing at the foreign ministrbut you weren't
                    always sure if they understood or were sympathetic.</p>
                <p>Q: One thing that we certainly found in the embassy in Dar es Salaam was that
                    USIS was very helpful in terms of having functions where there either was an
                    American basketball team or American film festival or something like this that
                    people in the host government wanted to come and see and then you might have a
                    chance to at least get to know them a little bit.</p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, that would help break the ice. The AID program was a good bridge, too.
                    It had a large staff with good contacts with the ministries. It all added up to
                    a sizeable relationship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The fact that we had a large AID mission did not
                        improvrelations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Basically, the relationship was friendly, but they just didn't want to get
                    too close. There was an active social life, and you ran into government and
                    private sector people, but it wasn't as easy as some other places.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get a chance to travel around?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. We got all around the country. I climbed Mount Cameroon, as a matter
                    of fact, which is near the coast in Anglophone Cameroon. It is 13,000 feet high
                    and rises right from the coast, so you are climbing most of that distance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That must have been an overnight trip.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: It was an overnight trip. We went over to Buea and up halfway the night
                    before, starting in the early morning for the summit. Unfortunately, the clouds
                    came in so we did not reach the actual summit. It was windy and rainy.
                    Fortunately, there was a hut fairly near the summit where we could take refuge
                    and warm ourselves. Then we started down.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Peter, I know that you are a rower, did you have a chance
                        to dany rowing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No. There was no water there. There is nothing to recommenthe location of
                    Yaounde. There is no river- (end of tape)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying that Douala is high so that the
                        climate...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, Yaounde was high enough (over 2,000 feet) to have a comfortable
                    climate. Douala is right on the coast and has a very humid and uncomfortable
                    climate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's why the capital is Yaounde.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Maybe. While Yaounde is tropical, it is quite comfortable,although
                    humid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any wawa (West Africa wins again)
                        stories?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>LORD: I have plenty of those stories since things don't always work as well in
                    Cameroon as they do elsewhere. I should add that another facet of the job in
                    Yaounde made it interesting and that is that embassy Yaounde had in the past
                    been accredited to the government of Equatorial Guinea. Equatorial Guinea is
                    adjacent to Cameroon's southern border on the continent, but its capital,
                    Malabo, is on the island of Fernando Po. Diplomatic relations between the U.S.
                    and Equatorial Guinea had been suspended several years earlier when the previous
                    ambassador and DCM had been declared persona non grata by one of the worst
                    tyrants of Africa at the time, Macias. He, together with Idi Amin of Uganda and
                    Bokassa in Central Africa, probably were three of the worst African autocrats.
                    In any case, I had been in Yaounde a year when in August, 1979, I think, Macias
                    was overthrown by one of his own lieutenants largely because things had gotten
                    so bad there that the economy had ceased to function, and no one had been paid
                    for six months, including the army. So, the senior military leadership took
                    action and deposed him.</p>
                <p>Soccer was a big sport in Cameroon. Every once in a while, there would be a big
                    match and everybody would turn out from the president on down. So, the
                    diplomatic corps had its own seating. It was a colorful event and sometimes of
                    political significance depending on the political situation. The French still
                    had a resident embassy in Malabo, and the French ambassador told me during the
                    soccer game about the coup there. We reported that very promptly.</p>
                <p>One of the reasons that I was assigned to Yaounde was because I spoke both French
                    and Spanish. Equatorial Guinea, being a former Spanish colony, spoke Spanish
                    pretty much. After the coup, the Department sent the deputy director of Central
                    African Affairs at the time, Len Shurtleff, and myself to Malabo to establish
                    contact with the new government. I was the first to arrive. The new government
                    wanted to make a good impression on the U.S. because it needed help. So, I was
                    met at the airport with a driver and limousine. Later the same day or the next
                    day, I can't remember which, Len Shurtleff arrived via Madrid on a Spanish
                    flight. We made contact with the new government.</p>
                <p>Malabo was a remarkable place to visit at that time. It was virtually a city that
                    had ceased to function, where nothing worked. There was no electricity; water
                    was in very short supply; nobody on the streets because the people had been
                    terrorized. It was a ghost town which I saw gradually come to life during
                    frequent visits thereafter. We made initial contact with the government on that
                    visit. I was the main liaison and reporting officer thereafter. So, I would make
                    periodic visits there. I also found the frequency for the government radio
                    station and was able to listen to their broadcasts from Yaounde and record, much
                    as we are doing right now, all the decrees that the new government issued, new
                    appointment of personnel, enunciation of policies, etc. So, my job took on a
                    major new component, that of tracking developments in Equatorial Guinea and
                    reporting them. Each trip to Equatorial Guinea was an experience because...</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I can't remember the first time I went, but we subsequently chartered a
                    small aircraft to get there. Air Cameroon started service at one point. If there
                    were more than one of us going from the U.S. embassy, or if I was the only one
                    and there were others from another embassy or from the World Bank or Cameroon
                    government, enough people to fill up a small plane, we would go that way.
                    Sometimes there would be transport to meet us at Malabo and sometimes there
                    wouldn't be. In the beginning, the government took good care of me. They always
                    found a place for me to stay and I was put in the VIP house the first few times
                    - a place that actually had electricity, although not all the time. And if the
                    water wasn't running, they would bring big jugs of it. Another time, I stayed in
                    the only hotel that was functioning. Gradually more and more visitors were
                    coming in from the World Bank, UN, IMF, Spanish aid, etc. and the place was
                    swarming with foreigners to the extent it was taxing the infrastructure and the
                    support services.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You began then to take your own tent.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Well, eventually, the Spanish brought a cruise ship down and tied it up to
                    the dock and it was used as a floating hotel. Malabo has a delightful round
                    harbor with high sides and entrance from the sea that is very protected, a
                    former volcanic cone, which is why it is so round. At one point was the hotel
                    where we stayed sometimes and right along one side of the harbor were diplomatic
                    residences, including that of the French ambassador, who had been there through
                    it all. So, that was a real experience living with Equatorial Guinea as it
                    evolved. The Department wanted the embassy to find a consular agent to represent
                    us there. We had had a prior embassy there, a two person embassy, and you may
                    recall that one of them killed the other.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was the desk officer who was in the next office to me,
                        AErdos. He absolutely lost his mind.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: It is the kind of place where you could lose your mind.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He shot his communicator.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>LORD: I think so. Anyway, the Department was reluctant to establish another
                    embassy in a country that was so small and inconsequential at the time. I
                    checked around and came up with various possible agents and went in to see the
                    foreign ministry with a proposal. I found a Spanish diplomatic representative in
                    there as an advisor to the foreign minister. This particular person I had met on
                    my way to post when I stopped in Madrid for consultation. The Spanish felt
                    strongly that the consular agency was not what the situation required. They
                    didn't want to have to bear the whole load of bringing Equatorial Guinea back
                    into the modern world by themselves. They wanted other western embassies in
                    there, especially the U.S., to help shoulder that load. So, the idea of a
                    consular agent was knocked down at that meeting by the foreign minister, who
                    obviously got his advise from the Spanish. Despite the Department's preference
                    that we not open an embassy there, we felt that the American embassy Yaounde
                    should recommend that one be opened because here was a small country that was
                    casting off its ties with the Russians and Chinese who had established
                    themselves there in a big way under Macias. The economy when I arrived really
                    existed on a barter basis with the Chinese. The “scotch” whiskey was Chinese;
                    the beer was Chinese; everything was Chinese. So, eventually the Department did
                    agree to establish a small embassy and by the time I left, a resident
                    administrative officer had arrived to help establish a U.S. embassy office under
                    Ambassador Smythe, who remained resident in Yaounde but was accredited to
                    Equatorial Guinea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's leave it there and resume next time with
                        furtheinformation about Equatorial Guinea.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Good.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Q: This is Lambert (Nick) Heyniger and it is May 20. We are continuing the
                    interview with Peter Lord. We stopped last time when he was telling us some
                    vignettes about Equatorial Guinea. So Peter, over to you.</p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>LORD: I mentioned the accreditation of Ambassador Smythe. Initially, I was
                    designated as charg� d'affaires after the coup and the return to normalcy.
                    Later, we had to get Mabel Smythe, the ambassador in Yaounde, accredited as
                    ambassador to Equatorial Guinea. When Lannon Walker, deputy assistant secretary
                    in the Africa Bureau, was visiting Yaounde, the idea was to go over to Malabo
                    while he was there so he could talk with the Equatorial Guinea President. The
                    other part of the idea was more or less decided at the spur of the moment, that
                    Ambassador Smythe should go along and present her credentials at the same time.
                    This was difficult to arrange on short notice because communications with Malabo
                    were virtually non-existent. Getting through via a direct telephone call was not
                    always possible, but a surer way was to communicate via Madrid. So, I called the
                    U.S. embassy in Madrid and asked them to communicate via the Spanish foreign
                    ministry to the Spanish embassy in Malabo to ask them to advise the government
                    that we wanted to do this. Of course, when we arrived by chartered plane the
                    following day, nobody in Malabo knew anything about it. But, the government
                    wanting to please, because they were still looking to us for assistance and
                    support, managed to schedule a presentation of credentials to the president,
                    with refreshments and some officials present, on extremely short notice.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Smythe sometime after that was reassigned back to the Department to
                    the African bureau as deputy assistant secretary and the new ambassador who came
                    out to Yaounde was Hume Horan. He was also to be accredited to Equatorial
                    Guinea, presented his credentials with more advanced notice. As another Spanish
                    speaker, it was good to have him involved. He took a lot of the load off my back
                    reporting on developments in Equatorial Guinea and getting to know the
                    officials. Each time he went over in the past, it was difficult to know exactly
                    what was going to happen in terms of expected arrangements for accommodations,
                    etc. As I mentioned, we were helped at some point along the way by having a
                    resident administrative representative there who greatly improved our ability to
                    do business there.</p>
                <p>Q: Incidentally, with Ambassador Smythe, not every ambassador has her or her
                    credentials lying around ready to be picked up at a moment's notice and present
                    them. What did she have?</p>
                <p>LORD: That's true. I can't remember now, but I think probably Lannon Walker must
                    have brought some with him or else they were pouched out in advance. What we
                    hadn't done was to arrange the time yet. So, you are right, that could have been
                    a problem, but I don't recall it as having been one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hume Horan, as I recall, would say he was primarily an
                        Arabist.What was he doing in Yaounde?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>LORD: His career had been as an Arabist. He was ready for his first
                    ambassadorship and Yaounde was available. He also spoke French and Spanish. He
                    is quite a linguist. He impressed the local Arabic members of the diplomatic
                    corps in Yaounde with his fluent Arabic. He had ample chance to practice it in
                    Cameroon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did you serve with Hume?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: As I recall, it was about a year. I think he came out therfor the last year
                    of my three years there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything you can tell us about working for him as an
                        ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: He was a first rate ambassador, a good person to work for, and I had a good
                    relationship with him, as I did with Ambassador Smythe. They were both excellent
                    ambassadors to work for. Hume was, of course, a career officer, so he was
                    perfectly able to find his own way around in a very effective manner. It was a
                    good team we had there under him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any particular problems that you two, or more pertinently
                        you,were working on during this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I don't recall any particular problems. Oil was being explored for and
                    being found off the coast, an extension northward of the oil deposits that had
                    already been tapped in Gabon. The same thing was happening in Equatorial Guinean
                    waters, too. The new government was talking with American oil companies about
                    concessions and exploration. Oil was discovered either while I was there or
                    shortly thereafter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the oil companies do their own negotiating or did they
                        wanyou or someone else to go along?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, they pretty much handled it themselves. They did not require a lot of
                    help.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else you would like us to know about your time
                        there in Cameroon?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>LORD: I don't think so. As I said, we had a very effective team. A new AID
                    director, Ron Levin, came out at some point. We had a history of good AID
                    directors there, but Levin, who was there my last year or maybe longer, was
                    bilingual in French, and that made a big difference. We had a big AID program
                    going with some new loans. So, the relationship with the Cameroonian government,
                    I would say, got quite a bit closer during that period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I assumed you were talking to the Cameroonians about UN
                        votes annon-aligned topics.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, the usual diplomatic business and they tended to be fairly
                    cooperative, although they liked to preserve their independent, third world
                    stance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To go back for a second, when you were there was there a
                        fairlsubstantial AID program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: About how much?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I don't remember the figures, probably in the neighborhood of a $30 million
                    program, large for a country of that size in Africa at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there many people in the AID mission?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: It was a good size AID mission. I would say the AID mission, itself,
                    roughly equaled in numbers of U.S. personnel the rest of the American official
                    presence there. I am thinking 30 people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything particular that happened with USIS?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We had a good record of cultural presentations that were well received by
                    the Cameroonian public. I think of the “Red Clay Ramblers” as one group who came
                    through and there were others, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I think that is about it. I think I mentioned earlier it was a fascinating
                    country to travel around because of the geographic and ethnic variety.</p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Most people speak French?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: French in the Francophone part and English in the Anglophonpart.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They didn't just speak African languages, they spoke a
                        Europealanguage as well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. Certainly the officials did and anyone who was educatedid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of accommodations would you find on your
                        travels? Werthere guest houses, hotels, or railroad hotels?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Usually you would go to one of the cities or larger towns, thcapitals of
                    the various provinces, and they would always have a hotel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Food you could eat?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: And food you could eat. I don't remember any problem with thfood there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you take your family on any of these trips?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Oh, yes. Their favorite trip was to go to the northwest province and the
                    western province, the first was Anglophone and the second was Francophone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: The Anglophone area, the Northwest Province, is a particularly scenic area
                    with enough elevation to be pleasantly cool. Because of the language tie and
                    because they felt like second class citizens they were very receptive to anyone
                    who wanted to pay attention, especially fellow Anglophones.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there game parks in that part of Africa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: In the north there was a game park with quite gooaccommodations.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Elephants and giraffes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: There were elephants, but I don't think any giraffes. Therwere also plenty
                    of larger birds, like storks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But, your kids enjoyed that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes.</p>
                <p>Q: Let's move along. Now we are in 1981 and you finished three years out in
                    Yaounde and you come back to the Department. Where did you go?</p>
                <p>LORD: I came back to the Department without an assignment and spent the first
                    year there working on an interim basis on the staff of the Presidential
                    Commission for Broadcasting to Cuba. This was the commission that was studying
                    the possibility of establishing a radio station to broadcast to Cuba, similar to
                    Radio Free Europe or Radio Liberty. The station did eventually come into being
                    and was called Radio Marti.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What does “Marti” mean?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Marti was a Cuban patriot, one of the forefathers that Cubans in general,
                    like to point back to as one of the authors of Cuba's independence from the
                    Spanish.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were working in the State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: In the State Department supporting the presidential commission, whose
                    members were, of course, presidential appointees. They were involved in a great
                    deal of coordination with the Congress and with the Cuban American Foundation
                    leader, Jorge Mas, who strongly supported Radio Marti.</p>
                <p>Q: Can you tell me Peter a little more about why, if the U.S. government wants to
                    step up a radio station to broadcast to Cuba, is the commission located in the
                    Department of State, for example, rather than in USIA?</p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>LORD: That is a legitimate question. This was a foreign policy issue and an
                    important one in our bilateral relations, and I think that is why State, with
                    its clout, was involved. Once the decision was made and legislation passed, then
                    it became more the responsibility of USIA. In fact, I think Radio Marti came
                    under the board of international broadcasting, which is an independent group,
                    but I think USIA was involved, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the presidential commission do any negotiating at all
                        witthe Cuban government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, it was mostly negotiating with the Congress. The Cubagovernment, of
                    course, was adamantly opposed to Radio Marti.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you negotiating with Congress about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Legislation to provide the funding and to establish thorganization.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would presume that the Congress would be very much in
                        favowith all of this.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes, but it was controversial in the sense that it wouldn't make relations
                    with Cuba any better and some people who felt it would have been provocative
                    would have opposed it. Others might have opposed it on grounds of funding. It is
                    a nice idea but would it be cost effective because the Cubans would very likely
                    jam it and it might not get through at all. But, this was in the early years of
                    the Reagan administration and fit in very well with the stance they wanted to
                    adopt towards Cuba.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Peter, can you recall any particular allies that you all
                        had ithe Congress or any particular opponents?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I don't recall offhand what the attitudes were, but by anlarge it was not
                    controversial and received bipartisan support.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What can you tell us about Mas Canosa, a very well known
                        Cubaexile leader in Florida? Did you get to know him at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Only through the meetings of the commission, not on a personal basis. You
                    saw him and others interacting which was interesting. I should say that the
                    office of Cuban affairs in the bureau of Inter-American affairs was the office
                    that played a role in this, too, supporting and guiding us.</p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did you come back from Cameroon without an assignment?
                        Dianyone have a health problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, no onward assignment had worked out that I was interestein at that
                    point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So now we are up to 1982 or 1983?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We came back in the summer of 1981 and I worked on Radio Marti until mid
                    1982. In the fall, I might mention, I got promoted to the O-2 rank and that
                    helped in the assignment process. I was assigned the following summer as officer
                    director in the Bureau of International Narcotics Matters, then called INM, in
                    charge of the INM program office, which provides assistance to source countries
                    where illegal narcotic crops are grown - Mexico, where the opium poppy and
                    cannabis are grown, and Colombia, which produced at that time a lot of cannabis
                    and was and still the major refiner of cocaine which is refined from the coca
                    leaf. The two largest growers of coca leaf are Peru and Bolivia. Those were the
                    main big countries in Latin America where we provided large assistance
                    programs.</p>
                <p>Q: Okay, Peter, you have the Department of State responsible for foreign
                    relations, you have DEA, which handles narcotic matters on the enforcement side.
                    Now this is called the office of programs in the Bureau of International
                    Narcotic Matters. So, it is not ARA?</p>
                <p>LORD: INM is an independent, separate bureau with its own fundinapproved by the
                    Congress for anti-narcotics programs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But with global responsibility?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. It really functions a lot like AID, with its own appropriations an
                    administration of these funds. In addition to the Latin American countries which
                    I mentioned, the other source countries are in the “golden triangle,” Burma
                    particularly, in Southeast Asia, as well as Pakistan in South Asia. Those were
                    all big source countries where we had big programs. Of course we also had other
                    programs providing assistance to all the transit countries in between to help
                    those countries take enforcement action against the transit of these products on
                    their way from the source countries to the consuming countries.</p>
                <p>Q: So, you say in a number of these drug producing countries we had fairly
                    substantial programs. Would these be State Department people or DEA people?</p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>LORD: We had State Department people who were paid by the INM budget in each
                    country where we had a major program. It was their job to administer the
                    program, and to be in touch with the host government and the officials
                    responsible for narcotics control. Some of the programs were quite substantial.
                    In Mexico, we supported a fleet of helicopters and some fixed wing planes to
                    spray the cannabis crop. It was the most effective way of covering a large area.
                    In Burma, we supported aerial spraying, too, because you can spray effectively
                    against both the poppy and the cannabis plant. We were just building up in Burma
                    when the change of government towards the end of my period there cut that
                    program way back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What your people were doing was government-to-government
                        work. They were not out in the field riding around in helicopters looking
                        for poppy fields?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No. The local government organizations are supposed to do that. The DEA is
                    also there to assist. So, the two organizations represented abroad would be INM
                    and DEA. INM on the programming side of crop control and DEA on the enforcement
                    and interdiction side. In the countries where there are bigger enforcement
                    programs, there can be a large number of DEA agents who work with host
                    government organizations in trying to collect intelligence and apprehend both
                    traffickers and product.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, you are an office director. Who was your boss? Who
                        waAssistant Secretary for INM.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: This was a relatively new bureau that had been established two or three
                    years earlier. I think there had just been one assistant secretary in charge
                    before. The current assistant secretary was a political appointee, a New Yorker
                    with a prosecutorial background. He was new to Washington and foreign
                    operations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it interesting to work for him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: He was able to provide the clout when we needed it, and he learned a lot on
                    the job and was quite effective. The two DASs that brought the professionalism
                    and the continuity to the bureau were Clyde Taylor and Jon Thomas, who was also
                    a political appointee. They were both very operational-minded people who spread
                    the INM word and did an excellent job coordinating with DEA, Department of
                    Justice, Customs, Coast Guard, all the players.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get to travel much? Did you get to go to
                        conferences?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>LORD: The bureau in its entirety does a lot of traveling. There is one part of
                    the office which liaises with the United Nations. The UN system has a number of
                    international agreements in effect to elicit the cooperation of the various
                    countries around the world and to set standards for trying to control illicit
                    narcotics. So, the people who dealt with that part of the effort would go to the
                    related meetings that were usually UN-sponsored. I, myself, got to Colombia,
                    Peru, Bolivia, Ecuador, Burma, Thailand, Pakistan, and Vienna, where the seat of
                    the UN agency that deals with narcotics is located.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get back to your old post at Arequipa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: I took a side trip there on one of my visits to Peru.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There wasn't a consulate there any more.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, there wasn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you look up some of the Foreign Service
                        nationals?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We really only had one local that worked in the office on a regular basis.
                    I saw her and also looked up some of the other friends we had there.</p>
                <p>Q: Let me ask you something else and reveal my own prejudice about this. I kind
                    of had the feeling that we in the United States have spent a lot of time, money
                    and effort on trying to either reduce the production of narcotics or to
                    interdict their entry into the States. Personally, I believe that things being
                    what they are, if there is a market, the market is going to be supplied. I kind
                    of think that if you are trying to combat drugs, I would like to see us spend
                    more time either trying to persuade people not to take drugs or going after the
                    pushers and the sellers and distributors and make it much, much more difficult
                    and dangerous for American citizens to buy and to use narcotics, thereby trying
                    to decrease the market. Now, you know more about this than I do. What is the
                    problem?</p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                <p>LORD: Those things you just described need to be done. Part of that is the
                    enforcement side, and DEA and all the various police jurisdictions around the
                    United States are dealing with that constantly. Another component of the program
                    that was funded by INM was a program of demand reduction, aimed at trying to
                    publicize the problem and to educate people and get them to recognize the
                    dangers of drug addiction and change their habits. This was a joint program with
                    some of the other departments in the government and with local jurisdictions.
                    Nancy Reagan, the First Lady, was behind a program o“Just Say No,” and hosted a
                    visit by the first ladies of drug producing and major transit countries at the
                    White House there that was quite successful. But, by and large, the profits from
                    the illicit drug trade are so great that one of the biggest problems is
                    corruption. The traffickers have enough money so that they can buy people in
                    their own country and any highly sophisticated equipment that they need like
                    aircraft and boats to smuggle the narcotics.</p>
                <p>Q: Being in the State Department, the State Department is not supposed to play
                    any role in educating or propagandizing the American people, but did you ever
                    get a chance to talk to your boss, for example, the Assistant Secretary who had
                    been a prosecutor, or other legal people in the United States about making it a
                    capital punishment to possess or sell drugs? Is the American legal establishment
                    opposed to this somehow?</p>
                <p>LORD: No, I think if you look at the penalties that people have to pay who are
                    caught with narcotics you will find that they have become more severe over time.
                    In fact, some of the penalties for possessing small amounts of marijuana are
                    considered too severe since that is one of the more minor narcotic offenses.
                    Critics addressing the general drug problem all see some emphasis that they
                    think needs to be changed or something that needs to be done differently, and
                    the emphases have changed as you go along. But, it is such a big problem that
                    everything that is being done is valid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But we are not having much success.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: You have to do everything and you have to do it better and do more of it.
                    The reason that it hasn't been successful is because, as we said, the
                    traffickers have so many resources at their disposal that there is a very
                    elusive and tough criminal to deal with.</p>
                <p>Q: You could send an unmarked car down to southeast Washington to a known drug
                    area and take a movie film of drug buys being made and just say, “Okay, all of
                    you people, particularly the buyers, are going to jail for twenty years,” but
                    that doesn't happen.</p>
                <p>LORD: It happens up to a point. The jails are full of drug offenders right now.
                    They are overloading the jails. You need more police, more jails, more people to
                    deal with this because it is such a huge problem.</p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>Q: Either that or do what really happened, for example in Holland where I served
                    earlier. The Dutch have a different attitude. They say, “Well, we will make
                    drugs available to you at a reasonable cost.” That way you eliminate all the
                    profits and let people who want to have drugs have them. Is that any better?</p>
                <p>LORD: The other argument is, of course, if the present system of controls is not
                    working effectively, then maybe you take a lesson from Prohibition and legalize
                    drugs. That is more along the lines of what the Dutch do. The reason nobody is
                    willing to consider that seriously in this country, I think, is that you are
                    taking such a huge risk by legalizing narcotics and making it available to
                    everybody that the problem could get much worse. You don't know for sure, but
                    drugs are so much more destructive and addictive than whiskey and cigarettes. It
                    is an entirely different kind of problem and nobody wants to take that risk.
                    Furthermore, you would be completely upsetting the whole international
                    apparatus, starting with the UN and with all the various cooperative
                    arrangements with other countries, if you did this.</p>
                <p>One factor that we haven't mentioned is the various drug and transit countries
                    themselves. If they were more effective in their own countries, they might be
                    able to reduce drastically the drug crop. Usually we are dealing with countries
                    that are not politically strong enough to...</p>
                <p>Q: They are not politically that strong or that economically developed. They are
                    huge in area and if you are a drug grower there is just so many areas you could
                    use.</p>
                <p>LORD: In general, when countries have an effective government and are cooperative
                    you can make real headway. When I first came into the job at INM, Mexico was
                    regarded as the model country. But, that was before corruption got to be so
                    great. The Mexicans had made major progress in spraying and eliminating the
                    production of both poppy and cannabis. Peru and particularly Bolivia did not
                    have the political control or will to effectively implement drug control
                    programs. Bolivia is now doing better and I guess Peru is coming along. But,
                    they have had their ups and downs. As I said earlier, we were making progress
                    with Burma but then the government changed. A military government came in which
                    was not cooperative. So, that is the way it goes.</p>
                <p>Q: Narcotics and drug trafficking is now one of the major foreign problems that
                    the United States of America faces. Are we winning, or losing, are things going
                    to get any better? What do we need to do?</p>
                <p>LORD: I hope we are keeping a lid on the problem. It could be a lot worse. We are
                    probably staying even as far as statistics go. At least we have in operation all
                    of these different programs that we mentioned, many of them funded by the State
                    Department in the producing and transit countries. We are just trying to make
                    those programs work more effectively.</p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>Q: Peter, would you be in favor of actually deploying special United States
                    military forces, troops on the ground and air and naval units to go out and
                    attack these fields? Would you be in favor of sending down 5,000 American
                    Marines to Colombia to...</p>
                <p>LORD: No, that doesn't work. That has to be done by indigenous forces in the
                    countries. You don't solve problems that other countries have by massive
                    deployment of U.S. manpower. That generates an opposite reaction that would be
                    over the long run ineffective. So, you have to provide incentives and training
                    and the technical knowhow to countries to do this themselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Use the military and policy forces in the country
                        itself.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: You work with whatever organizations are involved and usuallit is police
                    and probably military, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Except the headlines that I see in the paper recently are
                        thathe Colombia military is really not doing very well.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: They are not doing well now and I'm not quite sure how that has come about.
                    It is partly do to poor leadership, increased corruption and less assistance
                    from the U.S. We had a model program going in Colombia when I was at INM. That
                    needs to be regenerated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is that pretty much it for international narcotics
                        matters?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, now it is 1985.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. My tour in INM was up and I was in the process of looking toward a
                    foreign assignment again. As you know, the more senior you get the fewer
                    satisfying jobs there are and the greater is the competition for them. There
                    didn't seem to be anything coming up that really suited us. About that time, I
                    was offered a job with a company that had a contract with the State Department
                    to do a crisis management training program. So, I decided to accept that offer.
                    I retired from the Foreign Service in January 1986 and spent the next eight
                    years in this crisis management training program which took me to many places I
                    hadn't been before. Basically it involved going to embassies abroad and
                    implementing the program there. It was very successful and very interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There are lots of embassies that need help managing
                        crises?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: It is very much a part of the Foreign Service, but it is a program that
                    doesn't fit into the active Foreign Service, itself, so it is a service that is
                    contracted for. This program had its genesis in the increase in the terrorist
                    threat abroad, particularly the hijacking of aircraft in the Middle East and the
                    bombing of the Marine house in Beirut in the early 1980s. So, the Congress
                    appropriated money to deal with this increased terrorist threat. A lot of new
                    money was spent to increase the number of regional security officers and to
                    improve the physical security of embassies. Funds were also made available on
                    the training side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were a trainer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: At this point in time, the State Department's guidance to embassies on what
                    to do in crisis situations became much more comprehensive than it had ever been.
                    We are all familiar with the old E&amp;E plan which was the guidance of what to
                    do if things really break down and you have to get out of a country, an
                    emergency evacuation. But, there are so many more kinds and various degrees of
                    crises along the way before you reach the need to evacuate, for which we are
                    better prepared to deal with now than we used to be. The Emergency Action
                    Handbook was prepared about this time to replace the old E&amp;E manual. These
                    training programs I talked about were intended to acquaint embassies with all
                    the procedures that are available for dealing with different kinds of crises
                    covered in this big, thick handbook. Normally handbooks go on a shelf and get
                    dusty. But, if you are forced in a simulated exercise, which is what we put
                    together, to deal with these crises and use what is in that handbook by actually
                    walking through the steps, then you are more likely to remember what is there
                    and to be able to use it if necessary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You would go out, for example, to the embassy in Bogota,
                        Colombiand would be there a couple of weeks conducting an exercise?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We would prepare an elaborate exercise which was modeled on a military
                    exercise format. We would then go to an embassy, get the whole country team for
                    two days, which is a major challenge in itself with any busy embassy. Embassies
                    usually don't want to take time out for an exercise, but with the proper push
                    from Washington and from the ambassador, they can make that time available. For
                    countries prone to these kind of threats, whether terrorist threats or even
                    natural disasters, which we also work into our exercise, we prepare an elaborate
                    scenario, basically setting a scene in the near future with everything going
                    wrong. Then we introduced prescripted messages, reports, telegrams, telephone
                    calls setting in motion increasing political instability, threats to public
                    order, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: People had to stay up all night?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: We didn't run these through the night, although the military does that
                    sometimes. We would take a set of closed circuit telephones with us and the
                    country team would be in one room and we, the control team, in another room. We
                    would communicate with them and the rest of the world by these closed circuit
                    telephones, all simulated. It was quite realistic. Even though I worked for a
                    contractor, we had office space in the Bureau of Diplomatic Security and had
                    access to the classified reporting from the country where we were going,
                    enabling us to present a realistic exercise based on developments in that
                    country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You must have really enjoyed it, you did this for eight
                        years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: When we went to a country to do this we would take along frequently someone
                    from the Consular Bureau because consular folks play a big role when things are
                    going wrong. We would take somebody frequently from the AID's Disaster Relief
                    Office. We would take somebody from the area's regional military command, like
                    USSOUTHCOM in Panama, and somebody from the Pentagon, because DOD can provide
                    assistance in time of need. If the simulated situation gets worse and an
                    emergency evacuation is planned, again, the military can play a key supporting
                    role.</p>
                <p>It was a lot of fun. I started off on my first trip observing and learning how
                    the program was done. On that trip, we went to Baghdad, where we still had an
                    embassy at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Two garden spots of the world.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: Yes. I spent more time in Latin America, however, because that was where my
                    expertise was and I became the Latin American team leader conducting these
                    exercises in virtually all of the Latin American countries. This was during a
                    period when you had the Sendero Luminoso in Peru, insurgency in Colombia, civil
                    war in El Salvador, Sandinistas and Contras fighting in Nicaragua. There were so
                    many countries where there was a real potential threat that the embassies really
                    paid attention to what should be done if some of these threats get worse, so it
                    was quite an effective program that was generally well received.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you think of the way the Peruvian government
                        handled thtakeover of the Japanese embassy a year ago or so?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: By and large, they did the right things. You stress the need in a hostage
                    situation like that to buy time and keep the people talking until they get too
                    tired and their defenses wear down.</p>
                <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                <p>Q: I want to take you back, if I may Peter. You actually had a career in the
                    Foreign Service of 30 years and became a senior officer. What sort of
                    reflections do you have about the Foreign Service and the diplomatic life that
                    you might want researchers or historical people to be aware of based on your
                    career? If you had it to do all over again, would you do the same thing?</p>
                <p>LORD: I think most of us agree that the diplomatic life is quite adventurous and
                    quite exciting and one that offers a great deal of variety. Everybody has
                    entirely different experiences. My experiences were in the smaller embassies in
                    the developing areas of the world where one deals, perhaps, with different
                    problems than one does if one is in the European capitals. To my way of
                    thinking, life in the developing world sometimes has a greater degree of
                    excitement and adventure to it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Have any of your children expressed interest in going into
                        thForeign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, I don't think any of them are inclined that way. I don't know if I
                    would recommend that everybody go into the Foreign Service these days. It is a
                    different world out there and a different service than when we were in it, and I
                    tend to think that life was more pleasant in many of the places where I have
                    served in the old days than it is now because life had a more gracious quality
                    to it then when some of the problems of insurgency and economic crisis that
                    prevail today didn't seem to be in the forefront. Diplomacy, of course, is
                    changing and communication is part of the big difference.</p>
                <p>Q: Right. Since our Foreign Service careers ended, the Cold War has ended and we
                    are much more confronted with global problems, population, terrorism, economic
                    development and things like that. The usual way the Foreign Service is organized
                    is by cones, political, economic, consular and administrative. There are a
                    number of people now who are advocating at least one more cone for global
                    matters such as population, environment, narcotics, terrorism, etc. Do you think
                    it is possible given the nature of the State Department to have a really
                    successful career of 30 years in global issues?</p>
                <p>LORD: I think some people probably could do that. There are not enough global
                    issues to keep everybody busy. A really well qualified person is going to be
                    dealing with a lot of those issues anyway whether he is an economic or political
                    officer, let's say.</p>
                <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                <p>Q: I'm also thinking though that the people who seem to get promoted the most and
                    to have the most luck in terms of becoming ambassadors are those in the
                    political and economic cones. It is hard for a consular officer to get much
                    above the O-3 ranking. Sure, there are administrative officers who become
                    counselors of embassy and even ambassadors. But, there would be the question of
                    competing. Let's say you spend 20 years in global issues and now you are ready
                    to be a DCM somewhere. Are your chances as good as someone who has been in the
                    political or economic cone?</p>
                <p>LORD: That is hard to say and why I think officers with a well rounded background
                    of experiences are perhaps more the ideal. It seems to me there is room for
                    people to serve in the political, economic and global functional areas and that
                    needs to be done so that the really able people have that rounded experience and
                    therefore will move on to the more senior levels. There are advantages and
                    disadvantages of increased specialization which the global issues perhaps
                    imply.</p>
                <p>Q: Any other thoughts? Now is the time to sit back and talk about the Foreign
                    Service as a career and anything you would like to say about your 30 years.</p>
                <p>LORD: It was a very interesting 30 years and most of it was very enjoyable. But,
                    it is a changing world not only with communications but with the requirements
                    and resources. We are going through the process of having to do more with less,
                    and that is what is difficult and which tends to overload everybody. You have to
                    avoid too much of an overload, which means you have to delegate more
                    responsibility. Advances in communications will perhaps make things simpler.
                    Those are the issues that I see that have to be dealt with.</p>
                <p>Q: I have been away from the Foreign Service directly for quite some time now,
                    but it is my understanding that morale, particularly in the middle and upper
                    levels of the Foreign Service is not good. One of the reasons, that you referred
                    to in your remarks, is that there are more good officers than there are good
                    jobs. It is very, very tough to be a DCM or ambassador at a grade one or grade
                    two post when there are 20 or 30 people competing for it. Is that good? Is that
                    the way things should be?</p>
                <p>LORD: You have to have a personnel system which doesn't get overloaded at the
                    top. It has to have some kind of attrition along the way, and that is the way
                    the present system is designed with the senior threshold and so forth. I don't
                    know how well it is working. One of the negative aspects of our system is that
                    you do have a lot of people who are very able and for whom there are not
                    rewarding jobs at the senior level just because there aren't enough to go
                    around, so very good people are losing out along the way, whether at the senior
                    threshold or afterwards.</p>
                <pb facs="0077" n="Page0077"/>
                <p>Q: Ambassador Quainton, Tony Quainton, a year ago when he gave his swan song as
                    director general, talked about how difficult it is to get people to retire.
                    Let's say you have been in the foreign service for 25 years and you are an O-3
                    and your chances of becoming an ambassador are pretty slim, but it is awfully
                    difficult to get people to retire. They just don't want to go. For comparative
                    purposes I had the chance to serve in the military, in the pentagon, for two
                    years as an exchange officer, with some very, very capable army officers who
                    were in their late thirties or early forties and most of them expected that they
                    were going to serve 20 years, that they were not going to make flag rank and
                    that they were going to retire and go on to a second career. This approach has
                    not really sunk in with the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>LORD: Except you do have the senior threshold as a hurdle and indicator. Since
                    promotion opportunities seem more limited than they used to be, there is going
                    to be a certain amount of attrition around the senior threshold. That is what is
                    supposed to equate with the same point in a military career. I don't know how
                    well this threshold is working, how many people it does force to retire at
                    perhaps an early age. One problem with the Foreign Service is that the Foreign
                    Service experience translates less easily into second careers outside the
                    Foreign Service than does the military experience.</p>
                <p>Q: That is why I think the diplomat in residence plan is so helpful because it
                    gives officers who are thinking about retiring two years to be in an academic
                    setting and perhaps make the transition to being a professor. Maybe we need to
                    think about expanding that program.</p>
                <p>LORD: However, to be an effective academician you need advanced degrees and two
                    years isn't enough to get that in. You have to really prepare ahead of time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think I have pushed you and poked you enough. Any
                        finathoughts?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LORD: No, I think that takes care of it. Thank you.</p>
                <p>Q: Peter, I want to thank you very kindly for submitting to this exercise and I'm
                    sure our successors will benefit by it very much and in due course you will be
                    getting a rough draft of the interview which you are totally at liberty to edit,
                    change, delete, add, whatever you like. Thank you very much.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
