<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000885">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Joseph P. O'Neill </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>JOSEPH P. O'NEILL</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Thomas Dunnigan</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 19, 1998</p>
                <p>Copyright 2000 ADST</p>
                <p>Q: This is Thomas Dunnigan speaking and the date is May 19, 1998. Today I will be
                    talking with Joseph P. O'Neill, who spent many years in the field of foreign
                    affairs and served in some of the more difficult posts in modern times. Joe, why
                    don't we start off by you filling me in a bit on your background and your
                    education, your military service and your work experience?</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I was born in New York City on March 16, 1935. My father was a laborer
                    for Consolidated Ditchdigger and my mother was a domestic in a (and she was very
                    proud of this) very high class Protestant household. She remembers that the
                    first time she rode in a limousine was when she went to get married and the
                    “master” gave her his limousine to get to the church. I graduated, after leaving
                    Power Memorial High School, from George Washington, joined the Army, as all the
                    poor Irish did at that time, where I spent three profitable years. I learned one
                    thing in the Army. I learned I didn't know very much and I learned I had a lot
                    to learn. After that, I went to work on Wall Street. I worked on Wall Street
                    until I was about 24.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of work did you do on Wall Street?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I took care of all the administrative or “back room facilities” for two
                    brokerage houses. One was up on Oppenheimer Avenue. The other was Eastman
                    Dillion Union Security. I would ride on the A train from uptown Manhattan to
                    downtown</p>
                <p>Broadway and read the whole first section of The New York Times cover to cover,
                    minus the editorials. One day, sitting in the subway, I said, “I'm so interested
                    in what's going on overseas, why don't I go and join the Department of State?”
                    This was 1960. It was at this time that the United States was expanding
                    overseas. They were hiring.</p>
                <p>So, I joined the Foreign Service in January of 1961. For a few months, I worked
                    in the New York Passport Agency. I was sent to Vientiane, Laos, where I spent
                    from 1961 to 1963 in a staff position as a communications officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you asked for Southeast Asia, any particular
                        area?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: I had asked for only three assignments: Vietnam, Laos, anCambodia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, that was an interest of yours.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: That was my great interest. So, I went there in '61. We had Winthrop
                    (Win) Brown, a great ambassador, stiff and upright, pure as the driven snow, a
                    man who was not very happy with this new young President from not a terribly
                    good family out of Massachusetts. Went back to see the President and came back
                    and was his devoted servant from that moment forward. Could not believe what a
                    fantastic gentleman Mr. Kennedy was. It was a great time. At that time, we had
                    the former Governor of New York, Averell Harriman, coming through Laos to do all
                    the negotiations for the Geneva Accords. He came out to see to the Geneva
                    Accords implementation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Laos was a principal point of interest to the
                        Kennedadministration, much more than Vietnam at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Well, it was the battleground. When Kennedy came in, he had a problem.
                    The Lao communists, for want of a better term, were primarily nationalists, but
                    the whole complication of people, plus pressure from the Vietnamese, who always
                    considered Laos and Cambodia within their sphere, kept the pot boiling. In fact,
                    if the French had not come in in the late 1800s, all of that area would have
                    been Vietnamese. People forget that Laos asked the French to become their
                    protectors. The French had defeated the Cambodians and the Thais balanced the
                    French and the British off against each other. But at that time, Laos was the
                    focus. Being in the “back room” in the communications, I recall at one time
                    either reading or hearing a senior officer at that time saying that Kennedy was
                    absolutely mortified that he couldn't find a couple of divisions to put in
                    Thailand to threaten the Lao and the Vietnamese about coming in and taking over
                    that country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the Lao themselves afraid of the Vietnamese?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Always. They always considered their neighbors aadversaries or as
                    predatory animals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did that include the Chinese, too?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Chinese, Thais, the Vietnamese, everybody. Somebody described Laos as a
                    zoo for, people, mostly foreign, who were different. Vientiane was a really
                    sophisticated culture city, not for operas, but for the people who were there.
                    There were Corsicans, of course, involved in the narcotic trade. There were
                    Legionnaires who did not want to go home. There were Italians, Americans, French
                    priests and “ladies” from all over the world - Korean, Italian, Burmese, and
                    many others engaged in the oldest profession. Chinese engaged in normal trade
                    along with Thais and Vietnamese in a certain amount of harmony. So, you had all
                    these people living close together, many educated by the French. Even the senior
                    communists were educated by the French. Many had gone to the Sorbonne.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was your French? Did you have to use it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: At that time, the Department did not train any of its [clerical] staff
                    in French. But knowing I was going, I had gone over to Berlitz and invested the
                    magnificent sum of $300 and learned French. So, when I went out there, I was the
                    only clerk who could speak French. Because I was a clerk, I could go to all
                    those disreputable places where officers could not go and where you could be
                    drinking beer and Colonel Kong Lee would be sitting next to you or Premier
                    Nastaban and his ministers at the Vien La Tre or to The White Rose to pick up
                    the enjoyment for the night. So, I saw these people. I was in my most
                    unsophisticated way, as Bill Hamilton and Phil Cadman (Bill Hamilton was chief
                    of the Political Section. Cadman was the DCM.), [you might say, “useful”]
                    because I could tell people who was in town and who was doing what at a very
                    low, corrupt level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your communicator assignment involve code work or
                        mainlpouch work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I was responsible for all the pouches, moving all the classified
                    materials throughout town. Plus, I did some of what we called at that time “poke
                    and tape” because all the communications were done by one-time tape.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you were it in many ways.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: It was a fairly big code section. Arlene Monette was in charge and we
                    had four of us on the State side of the communications office. The CIA had its
                    side, so there were another four. We put out a lot of telegraphic traffic.
                    Everything that happened in Laos, as you said a few moments ago, was important.
                    Laos was considered by Kennedy at that time a place where he was going to put a
                    line down. He just did not know how weak we were militarily. All he was able to
                    bring in was, I believe, about two battalions of Marines, which he then sent up
                    into the northeast of Thailand and they remained in Udorn. I can't remember the
                    other place, but it was along the border. He moved the Marines because the Thais
                    were very, very upset. When the Marines came in, they were put in trucks and
                    rolled through Bangkok.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So people could see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, they were put in trains and shipped up north. I went over to visit
                    them because I knew one or two of the Marines who were from my old neighborhood.
                    They were well-trained, able to do what they were going to do. But as one of the
                    sergeants said to me, “If we have to go across the river, we'll inflict
                    casualties because we're not coming back across.” A sober assessment of the
                    situation probably, very sober and very accurate. All they had at that time were
                    M-16s. No, they didn't. They had M-1s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Still those World War II M-1s is all they had?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They were carrying M-1s. They had 50 calibers [machinguns]. All the
                    wreckage of the Korean War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember them well. Were you able to travel about Laos
                        at alor were you confined in Vientiane?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I got around a bit. One, because I was a bachelor and, two, I don't like
                    to use the word “expendable,” but I was useful. So, I got up to the “boondocks.”
                    I got up to the Plain de Jars and Luang Prabang. But I didn't get to any of the
                    CIA bases. They were still “secret, off limits.” They were being supplied out of
                    northeastern Thailand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were living conditions like in Vientiane at the
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Great. I know people will say, “Oh, they were terrible.” But at some
                    time (I can't remember when), all the dependents were moved out of Vientiane. It
                    was sometime in '61 and they came back in '62. The wives stayed primarily in
                    Bangkok, most of them. A few of them went back to the States. So, a two family
                    household evolved. The gentlemen had their families in Vientiane and they had
                    their families in Bangkok. There was plenty of food. There was plenty of booze.
                    There were nightclubs, whorehouses, and of course, very, very interesting work
                    because everybody came through there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the morale like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Winthrop Brown kept morale very, very high. He knew what was going on
                    and, except in one case where one of the officers tried to have a relationship
                    with one of the Marines, he had a laissez faire attitude. He himself was
                    straight as an arrow and he knew that some of his officer weren't. One of his
                    officers who later went on to be Consul General in Marseille was notorious for
                    his liking for the ladies. There was nothing vicious about it. He just loved
                    them, all colors, all sizes, all shapes. He enjoyed Marseille for years
                    afterwards.</p>
                <p>Q: Given the situation at that time in Laos, Joe, was there fear among the staff
                    as to their own personal security? Where there any terrorist incidents?</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Once the ladies and the children had left, I think, the question of fear
                    sort of evaporated. Of course, during one of the coups, they had blown the whole
                    front part of the embassy away. There were shootings in town, occasionally. But
                    most of the fighting was upcountry. Of course, officers who went upcountry
                    understood that the danger was there. But there was no terrorism factor like
                    there had been in other posts where I would serve in the future.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there an anti-American feeling? How did the Lao feel
                        abouour staff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: The Laotians were great. They really didn't care one way or another as
                    long as they were left alone. They were sort of bystanders in a fight in their
                    own country. So, they really didn't care. Nothing seemed to bother them at
                    all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was your first time in Vientiane. In 1963, you went
                        tVietnam. You went to Hue, in fact, which is halfway up Vietnam.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Hue was important for a number of reasons. One, it was the family home
                    of the Diem family or the Ngo family (I don't know how you want to call it
                    during this interview). Let's call it “Ngo Diem Nhu's family.” His brother was
                    the Archbishop of Hue. Another brother was the governor of Hue. His other
                    brother was his political advisor. Of course, then there was Madame Ngo Diem
                    Nhu, who was probably the only man in the family. So, it was all...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, they were well-connected in Hue.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Well-connected. They were a Mandarin family with one terrible cross.
                    That was, they were Catholic. They were always considered outsiders. People
                    forget that the Ngo Diem Nhu family had his older brother killed by the
                    communists previous to his coming to power. Ho Chi Minh had offered both an
                    apology, retribution, or recompense, and a position in his government but Diem
                    would not take it. He had his own idea of who he was. He was a Mandarin. He came
                    from a family. Ho Chi Minh was nothing in his eyes. This was the classic... He
                    was more Mandarin Chinese in mentality than Mao Zedong. He was born, I think,
                    about 300 years too late. I remember, when I asked to go to Hue-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, you asked? I wanted to get into that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, I asked George Roberts, who had been the political officer in
                    Vientiane, Laos, and then had returned to the Department to become a personnel
                    officer. He knew me and I wrote him. I said I wanted to go there because I felt
                    that there were going to be an exciting place. Old George, who later made
                    ambassador, wrote back that I was really going to sort of an isolated, not
                    terribly important post, and it was just going to be very quiet.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had a consulate there at the time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. John Helble was the consul there, who was very, very unhappy with
                    what was going on and who reported back to Washington about how things were. So,
                    when I got there. Jerry Greiner was the chief of station. It was just the three
                    of us. We covered everything from Quang Tri to Quang Ngai and what eventually
                    became ICorps. I spent two years in Hue and then two years with AID working on
                    Da Nang.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went there for State though?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: I've always been with State. I was given what was considered a
                    tremendous promotion with this assignment. I joined the Foreign Service as a
                    Foreign Service staff 13, (GS-4). I had made GS-5 the same year. I was going to
                    take over a GS-7 position. Man, my career was just starting on an upswing. I
                    went to Hue and became the budget officer, the administrative officer,
                    communicator, and the officer who prepared certain political work, even though I
                    was not an officer. I was still staff. I didn't become an officer until years
                    later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a military threat there at the time that you
                        arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: There was a MAAG [Military Assistance Advisory Group] mission there. I
                    remember, there was not a great threat there at that time. In fact, all the
                    military officers would hang on and hang on in order to get a combat
                    infantryman's badge. The only way that you can do that is to get involved in a
                    firefight. So, they were always out on patrol. This was '63. In '64, it got a
                    little more heavy. Then, of course, the Marines came in later. What happened was
                    that the period of time, only the Viet Cong were involved there in that area.
                    The NVA, the North Vietnamese Army, did not come down yet. They were not
                    terribly involved.</p>
                <p>I have two stories that I'll tell you about this. One, after John Helble left,
                    there were a number of people who came in there. John Negroponte, who had come
                    up from Saigon. He was out of Hue visiting the other provinces and I was left
                    there, and the CIA guy was there, a new fellow. He came charging in. I did their
                    traffic also. He said, “The NVA has come across the border.” I said, “No way.
                    Everybody says they're not coming. They're going to stay in Laos. They're going
                    to use the Ho Chi Minh trail.” “They're coming in. I got to report it. I'm in a
                    terrible bind here. Negroponte is not here.” So, I said, “Okay, I'll send it
                    out. I'll send it out immediately. I'll send it only to Saigon.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then, Saigon will decide whether they want to send it
                        tWashington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. I sent it out and I slugged it from CIA for CIA. It was the first
                    time I had ever done that. I sent it out “NIACT Immediate.” By the way, I would
                    code it up and then we had a Vietnamese fellow who sent it out by CW [commercial
                    wire]. The incoming messages would be handled the same way. The cable was
                    “headed” so that all would know what was coming was important. Don't delay
                    processing. So, down it comes. Then the panic sets in. Some types of phone calls
                    could never get through between Hue and Saigon. This time, all the calls got
                    through. The messages consisted of “What the hell is going on up there?” “I sent
                    a cable. That is all I know.” “I can't talk anymore.” Mendenhall (chief of the
                    Political Section in Saigon) called; he was upset. I told Negroponte what had
                    happened when he returned from the field. He said, “There goes my career.” I
                    said, “Oh, no, I headed the cable from CIA for CIA.” He said, “Are you sure?” I
                    opened up the safe and I showed him the outgoing tape. He never forgot it. The
                    report was accurate. The NVA was coming across the border from Laos.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [Negroponte's] career wasn't harmed by that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No. He's the only ambassador who has been vice consul, consul general,
                    and ambassador (pro consul) in Honduras and later Manila.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever get any visits up there from the ambassador
                        oothers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, we had all the ambassadors up. Ambassador Henry CaboLodge and Max
                    Taylor came up. Kissinger came through also.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So no congressmen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No congressmen. They never came up. After John Helble left on
                    assignment, he was replaced by Sam Thomsen. Tony Lake, later NSC advisor to
                    President Clinton, was assigned to Hue for some months. He, by the way, was a
                    real political force, as was Halpern when they were in Saigon. People forget
                    that “Rolling Thunder,” the big bombing missions into North Vietnam was in part
                    run by Halpern, he of the Pentagon Papers fame. You see the conflicts that later
                    occurred as both Halpern and Lake left the government over Viet Nam though they
                    were “hawks” when they were in Vietnam. When we were in Hue, the leader of the
                    opposition was Trich Tri Quang, who was the senior Buddhist monk in the country
                    and who was running the opposition against, first against Ngo Dinh Ngo, and then
                    against us while we were there. Trich Tri Quang used the consulate in Hue as a
                    conduit to the United States government, first through Sam Thomsen and finally
                    Tom Cochran. Tom Cochran was our last consul in Hanoi in the 1950s and later our
                    last consul in Hue. I worked for Cochran again when he brought me back after
                    Tet.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He died about a year or two ago.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: He was our consul general in Da Nang. The problem in that area was the
                    conflict between the Diem family, that was conservative Catholic, a minority
                    family in a majority Buddhist country. Diem had no sensitivity toward the people
                    with whom he had to live and work. The Diem family had a very bad idea of how to
                    rule people. They ruled Vietnam as if they were in the 1600s in China. Other
                    problems included Madam Ngo Dinh Nhu, the sister in law of the president, who
                    was the de facto ruler of the country. She was tough and opinionated. I am
                    reminded of [Russian Queen] Alexandra of Nicholas and Alexandra - narrow minded.
                    The same character - women, which is not going to sound politically correct -
                    who were only interested in protecting their husbands, keeping them in power
                    without regard to the long term interests of the husband or the country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In her case, her brother-in-law.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Her brother-in-law. The Buddhists wanted to take back their country and
                    I can understand this. Most of the Catholics in North Vietnam or a significant
                    portion did not come from South Vietnam. They were refugees after '54 from the
                    North. It just did not work. Nobody should also in any way think that Ho Chi
                    Minh was an agrarian reformist. He was a nationalist communist dictator cruel to
                    his own people in the north. One only has to look at what he did for North
                    Vietnam vis a vis what Diem did for South Vietnam. North Vietnam was always,
                    under the French and under the Chinese, the richest part of the country with all
                    the natural wealth. The South had the food. The question later developed of how
                    these two parts of the country could survive economically. I think, until about
                    1964, the State Department was the body that moved the foreign policy in Vietnam
                    and then came General Westmoreland. Westmoreland was as narrow minded as any
                    general I've ever read about. He makes McClelland, the Civil War general, look
                    like a brilliant, opportunistic Stonewall Jackson. There was a great, great
                    general there at that time by the name of General Walt, a United States Marine
                    Corps general. He had started two programs. One was called “Kit Carson.” This
                    was a program whereby a Marine squad or a Marine platoon (but no bigger) was
                    integrated with a Vietnamese squad or platoon. They would each feed a meal to
                    the other every other day. Lunch would either be Vietnamese or American. Then
                    the next day the opposite. They would live in the villages and they would stay
                    there for six to nine months. It was good. It worked for about seven, eight,
                    nine months until NVA finally crossed the DMZ. When the NVA came across, they
                    were too big to handle [by the smaller] units. [Such small unit tactics were]
                    good if they were going to fight guerillas. When the NVA came, Walt said, “Look,
                    we can't defend the whole damned ICorps with what I've got, which is about two
                    and a half Marine divisions. Let's do this. We will protect the DMZ down along
                    Route 1 and from the coast in about 30-40 miles, 50 maximum, all the way down.
                    We will then have a major road, the railroad, the sea, and the major cities, and
                    the most fertile land and at least 75-80% of the population. We will hold this.
                    We will protect this. We will fight in the other parts. We will then build
                    Adrian's wall. When we see them sort of getting up together, we hit them with
                    everything: the planes, the task force, etc.” Our friend Westmoreland's idea was
                    that we would have a war of attrition. We would kill them. The Viet Cong/NVA
                    would not be able to take the pain, he thought. As we saw them, we would go out
                    and kill them. They would not be able to run and hide.</p>
                <p>I see two things wrong with this. One, we could not afford the casualties. You
                    can see the results of this in the Powell Doctrine today, which is, you arrive
                    on time, you don't cause any trouble, and then you leave on time. If something
                    is accomplished, okay. If nothing is accomplished, so what. That is the result.
                    Now, here you have this long fight. There is no way we could win because Ho Chi
                    Minh and his army were willing to fight to the last Vietnamese in North Vietnam
                    and South Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were not going to fight to the last American.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: We lost this war politically in part. There were many other reasons,
                    when Robert Kennedy ran for the Senate in New York and said, “John would never,
                    never fight in Vietnam the way we are doing now... We should not be there
                    anymore, etc.” Again, another misconception. Remember the reason that our
                    friend, President Kennedy, was in Texas was that he had to carry Texas in the
                    coming election. The last political remark he made before he was shot was,
                    “Lyndon, at least we'll have two states: Massachusetts and Texas.” He was going
                    to be accused in the next election of losing another Catholic country afer
                    “losing” Catholic Cuba. It was thus necessary for him not to lose Vietnam.
                    Recall that the Catholic hierarchy never supported Kennedy; they knew the family
                    and his father. He could not have carried the Catholic clergy if he “lost” or
                    abandoned “Catholic” Vietnam, even though Vietnam was not Catholic, but
                    Buddhist.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That would make '64 a very difficult fight for him. When
                        thMarines landed near Da Nang there, did that-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They landed at Phu Bai just south of Hue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did that increase your work or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Believe it or not, Tony Lake was one of the officers who went out to
                    meet the Marines as they came flying in. At Phu Bai at that time we had a big
                    listening station. We were listening to everything the Viet Cong [did]. We also
                    had a big VOA station out there which was broadcasting all over Vietnam. So, the
                    NVA were coming down. The Army people who were there couldn't hold it. We just
                    had the Tonkin Gulf [incident]. Even if we had not gotten involved in the Tonkin
                    Gulf, the Marines would have come in to protect these stations. So, they came
                    in. The only problem we had was local problems with fights between the Army
                    troops and the Marines in the bars in town. We got that settled out by giving
                    them every other night in town. On Sunday, they couldn't go into town and they
                    each had one day to themselves.</p>
                <p>Q: Real diplomacy, Joseph!O'NEILL: Yes. The other thing was, the Marines were
                    very good. I went out to stay with them off and on. Negroponte and Sam Thomsen
                    were busy with other things. There were only three of us. We had to take care of
                    these people out there. I would go out. I speak New Yorkese and the Marines and
                    the Army quite understood that. They never knew what my rank was, thank God. By
                    that time, I think I had made FSS-8 (GS-6).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were a diplomat to them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I was the diplomat. I was the fellow they should pass verpolitely at the
                    restaurant.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was morale at the post when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: We were so busy. By that time, by the way, they had a really excellent
                    USIS [United States Information Service] guy in there, Bill Stubbs, who spoke
                    Cambodian and French. We also had some German doctors up there. They were all
                    killed during Tet. Bill is retired now. There was a police advisor who wasn't
                    terribly good. He felt that the way to stop this whole thing was to give all the
                    police officers shotguns and let them kill every NVA they saw, which didn't last
                    very long. Morale was fine. All of us were bachelors or “temporary
                    bachelors.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was going to ask whether or not there were dependents
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No dependents. So, not all of them, but I would say a significant
                    majority of the officers had household arrangements. We had a daily telegram.
                    You had the consulate and my house next to it. So, everyone would write their
                    portion of the cable for whoever was the officer in charge, whether it was Sam
                    Thomsen, Negroponte, or Lake. They would type it out and put it together. They
                    would go over and sit in my house, which was in the consulate compound. I would
                    sit down and would “poke it out.” It was on an old fashioned, old, manual
                    typewriter with a “crypto tape” I typed pretty close to 50 words a minute. The
                    rest of it would take about an hour. Then we'd wake up the Vietnamese CW
                    operator, who lived in the compound with his six or eight children (He now has a
                    restaurant here in Arlington.) and was in the French colonial army for a number
                    of years. He would “pound it out.” Then we would all get up at eight or nine
                    o'clock the next morning and start all the many things that had to be done.
                    There would be the administrative things or maybe seeing the demonstrations out
                    around town. Some of us would be going out to make trips out to Quang Nai or
                    down to Da Nang or whatever. Remember, we did everything by road. There were no
                    helicopters. There were no short trips. So, you would leave and it would be four
                    days, maybe five, depending on convoys and the rest. We would go to Da Nang
                    through the Hai Van Pass, a long, dangerous, and torturous ride. We would stay
                    in Da Nang and operate from there. It was time consuming and there were many
                    days, weeks, months if I think about the whole two years, when the senior
                    officer in charge of the consulate in Hue was a Foreign Service staff 8
                    (GS-6).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you travel in jeeps?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Jeeps. No armored jeep, but we carried sidearms. I carried a Swedish K
                    and a 357 Magnum, which I would lay on the seat beside me. Very often we
                    traveled with interpreters. John Helble, one of the great officers in the
                    Foreign Service, would take a driver with him. I generally drove myself. I don't
                    recall taking a driver with me. Sometimes I would go with another American. In
                    fact, I think I was the last American to drive from Hue up to Lao Bao. Lao Bao
                    was right on the border with Laos. That was in '64.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Q: In 1965, you were moved to the CORDS [Civil Operations and Revolutionary
                    Development Support] program at Da Nang. Tell us a little bit about the CORDS
                    program. What was that intended to do?</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: There was an Army colonel in charge, Sam Wilson. CORDS was the hope that
                    we would help the Vietnamese administer their government in an efficient and
                    democratic way. From the State side, we got, I think, in general, some excellent
                    officers. [From] AID, we had a mishmash of ex-Army officers, contractors, and I
                    do not know what. We had fishery advisors, education advisors, sanitation
                    advisors on everything and many of the advisors did not know their jobs.
                    Sometime in this period, I got to know the French consul general in Da Nang,
                    Monsieur LeBouef. He said something which I have never forgotten. He said, “You
                    have more administrators in my consular district (which was the equivalent of
                    ICorps) than we had in all of Indochina prior to 1954.” He was correct; we would
                    have an American sitting with almost every Vietnamese official above the rank of
                    deputy district officer. It was foolish. I ascribe this primarily to
                    Westmoreland, who had by that time taken over both the military and the
                    political side of the war. He did not understand either the U.S. military on the
                    ground or the Vietnamese. It was badly done in every way. During this time,
                    1965-1967, I was the advisor [to] the mayor of Da Nang, but I did other things.
                    It was difficult to control all the advisors who reported to Saigon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you asked for this assignment or was this just-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I'm not quite sure exactly how that happened. I know that a number of
                    senior officers knew me and they had offered to bring me on to AID as an
                    officer. I said, “No.” But then they had started to ask State people to be
                    detailed [to AID]. So, they asked me to stay on detailed to AID. I think there
                    was a mistake made there. I think the AID people thought I was an officer
                    because I was the only staff who ever was an AID advisor. There were refugees
                    coming into Da Nang. I helped with some of this. But again, there was rampant
                    corruption. Some of it, we should just have left alone, but we focused on it. We
                    let a Buddhist group come in. We would give them cement and roofing. We couldn't
                    account for all of it in an audit, but we would see a beautiful pagoda going up.
                    Catholics would come in and they would do the same thing. There would be
                    churches built. There might not be a water well built, but there would be a
                    rectory for the priest, a room for the monk, or there would even be a whorehouse
                    built. We would worry about that stuff, but at the same time at the port, tons
                    of material was disappearing. Somebody said (and I'm sure it's accurate) that if
                    we had used all the cement that had been purchased and sent to Vietnam, we could
                    have paved the whole country. There were ships sitting out there at Da Nang
                    waiting to offload for three or four weeks, some for months. They were short
                    loaded. They were selling cement from off the ship. It was awful.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>We did, I think, a couple of things wrong. One, we sent out a conscript army to
                    Vietnam. You cannot fight a guerilla war with a conscript army. Two, most of the
                    Army (There were exceptions, were ticket punchers. They knew exactly to the
                    minute when they arrived and when they were going home. Most of the Army never
                    saw combat, never heard a shot fired in anger, and were very pleased not to.
                    Counter that with units like the Airborne divisions or the Marines. The Marines
                    spent 13 months there. There were terrible casualties among the Marines; they
                    kept most of their people in the field.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's their tradition.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: That's their tradition.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They're all fighters.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Even those who were in the back, who were in the rear, always wanted to
                    get some front line time. You have to again note that toward the end of this,
                    many of the Marines were not volunteers. They were drafted. Still, they were
                    able to imbue in them this difference. That war did not have to come out the way
                    it was. Much of the problems, of course, were in the States over Watergate and
                    the rest and politics within the political parties. There were ways to mitigate
                    the sufferings out there. The important thing about this whole Vietnamese war,
                    whether we should have been there or not, people did vote with their feet.
                    Whenever there was a fight coming up, I had never, ever seen people flee away
                    from us to [the Viet Cong] before a fight. I never saw them running the other
                    way from us. We would be coming up (and I spent a lot of time with the Marines
                    and others) and I never saw them heading out toward Viet Cong country.</p>
                <p>Q: That's a good indication of where their sentiments were. Were you there when
                    the Marines' air base was attacked and so forth at Da Nang? There were some very
                    vicious Viet Cong attacks I gather.</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: That was the Tet offensive. Is that the one you're talkinabout?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, this was in '65 when they shot up a lot of helicopters
                        andestroyed...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They snuck in, yes. But again, that was overconfidence by the Marines
                    and sloppiness. It happens all the time. It happened in Beirut. They sometimes
                    forget to do the necessary like Roman Centurions. They were all going out to
                    fight some stupid bunch of slaves (Spartacus) and they forget to put up night
                    defenses. They get sloppy. It happens all the time. It's very difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's human but it happens in the military, too, doesn't
                        it? Waour consulate in Hue attacked while you were there or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No. Again, the USIS building was burned down. I was there when it
                    happened. I remember alerting people by CW what was happening. I think we sent
                    that one in the clear. I can't recall. Bill Stubbs was over at the USIS building
                    getting his people out. The burning was done by university students who wanted
                    the Americans out. Many of them wound up being murdered in the Tet offensive.
                    They saw their saviors coming and didn't know that they were going to wind up in
                    the grave. Anyway, he was over there getting his people out. Tony Lake ran from
                    the consulate about 600 yards up to the USIS building to make sure that Bill
                    Stubbs and his staff got out. Then, finally, they came in one by one to the
                    consulate. We sat there in the consulate listening for this tremendous (by our
                    standards; it was only a few thousand) mob move down to the consulate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there no police, no military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: The Vietnamese authorities did not interfere at all. So, we sent home
                    our staff, one of them Tuy Cam, a beautiful young lady who later married Jim
                    Bullington (later ambassador), who came after me; Joe Nguyen, one of our great
                    Foreign Service nationals, whom we found out a few years ago was a member of the
                    Vietnamese intelligence organization. We sent them all home. We sat there. The
                    question was, what were we going to do if they came into the building? We had
                    all our weapons sort of sitting around. We hadn't decided what we were going to
                    do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had no Marine guards?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No Marine guards. There was us. That's another thing, I think, that
                    people forget about the Foreign Service, especially at that time. All of us,
                    Frank Wisner, John Negroponte, Tony Lake, John Helble, all of us traveled
                    throughout southern Vietnam without guards. Some of us were captured. All of us
                    were shot at. Steve Ledogar was under mortar attack a number of times. Gil
                    Sheinbaum, who was down in Hoi An, was shot at a number of times. I was shot at.
                    We were very lucky not to have been killed. I now think abouNegroponte,
                    Sheinbaum, Wisner, and Lake. They're all my age or a few years younger. One
                    would not even imagine these guys driving through guerilla held areas. If I had
                    to count up how many times I've driven through areas which were considered
                    hostile, I would need more than my fingers and my toes. But we did. Foreign
                    Service officers did. They did it then. Regrettably, we don't do it as much as
                    we used to.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, [the mob] never came to the consulate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They came and they streamed in front of the consulate. But they did not
                    come in. I still don't know why they didn't come in, but they didn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were communicating out of Hue, were you able
                        tcommunicate with Washington or only with Saigon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: The instructions were that we sent everything to Saigon. Saigon would
                    pass it on. I think, in a way, it was this way so that Saigon would have control
                    over what went out. We had really tremendous officers in Hue. We first had John
                    Helble, who told us in '62 and '63 how deep and difficult going into Vietnam
                    would be. At that time, we were able to go straight into Washington. But at a
                    certain time he was told not to communicate with Washington directly. After that
                    when the other officers came to Hue, we sent everything down to Saigon. I think
                    some of the cables were not passed in whole to Washington. I think they were
                    excised or they were made parts of other cables. At least, I think, the flavor
                    and the passion of the officers' writing was best.</p>
                <p>Q: There was fighting in Da Nang in those years between the South Vietnamese and
                    anti-government forces. Could you say a little about that?</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: In ICorps, we had a very good general, Nguyen Chanh Thi. He had been a
                    sergeant in the French colonial army and had risen through the ranks. He was not
                    well educated and not from a “good family.” Very honest, decent - he made a fine
                    Vietnamese first division, the best in the army. Then he was moved down to Da
                    Nang to take charge of ICorps. Everybody was very, very pleased with this. I
                    think he was moved down to ICorps at our insistence because he was so good.
                    Other generals were fighting for power in Saigon. They were not terribly
                    interested in who won the war. It reminds me of Chiang Kai-shek, “I'd rather
                    kill Mao Zedong than Japanese.” This is what was happening. He cut most of the
                    corruption in Da Nang. We had the port at Da Nang, which was always corrupt, but
                    he cut the corruption. He started to become very popular among the people. So,
                    there was a big fight over this. Richard Holbrooke, later assistant secretary
                    for East Asia and Pacific and ambassador to Germany, was one of the officers in
                    Saigon at that time. I remember having a conversation with him. In Saigon, the
                    politics was that General Thi had to go because we had bigger fish to fry. We
                    would replace him with a better general. Highly unlikely. Highly unlikely. We
                    did, by the way, replace him with a good general who eventually died in a
                    helicopter. I said, “You know the reason that this general has got to go. One,
                    he's not married. He doesn't have a family. He has no future in this country.”
                    Holbrooke said, “You don't understand.” Maybe I didn't understand. We were
                    caught by the people who were our allies and did not, as the French or the
                    British would have done, send them away. The French would have sent them off to
                    some whorehouse in Paris. The British would have sent them off to Asmara or the
                    Seychelles for a pleasant exile. But we did things stupidly. It goes on. We want
                    people to behave in our image. People in the rest of the world act for their own
                    interests. It just doesn't work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was any of the fighting between the South Vietnamese based
                        oreligious considerations, Christian versus Buddhist, or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Not at that time. I must admit that (again, politically incorrect) many
                    of the more competent officers were Catholic. Was this for a historical reason,
                    i.e. that the French had trained them and then that Diem promoted them? No, it
                    was strictly over power. There were, of course, the tinges of religion, but that
                    was only as a mask for the people. Only power.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had an exciting time in Vietnam. Then in 1968, you
                        went bacfor language training in the Thai language. Did you ask for
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I was still staff. As one of my officers wrote in my efficiency report,
                    I was really much too big for my britches. They owed me because by that time the
                    President had personally presented me with the Department's Superior Honor Award
                    at a White House ceremony with the band playing and all the rest.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's very interesting. Was that President
                        Johnson?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Lyndon Baines Johnson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Congratulations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Thank you. Brought the whole family down. It took placin the White House
                    Rose Room, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was that for in particular?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: That was for four years of not getting myself killed. At that time, the
                    Superior Honor Award was the highest award given by the Department of State. I
                    was still willing to serve in Vietnam; I did not want to leave the area. The
                    Department felt that I had spent too long in Vietnam, almost four years, and had
                    too many personal reasons to remain there. I said that I would be happy to do
                    something else and suggested that I learn Thai. This threw the Department into a
                    tizzy because they knew that I was not an officer and a staff had not to that
                    time taken a hard language.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They put you in language training as a staff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Right. I did about five months. I was sent up to ChianMai.</p>
                <p>Q: Where did you get your training, in Washington?</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, at the Foreign Service Institute over in the old FSI building in
                    Rosslyn. Then, I went up to Chiang Mai, spent two years there, did a lot of
                    political reporting for the consulate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you still staff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I was still staff. I did all the consular, all the administrative, plus
                    some of the political reporting. We had a political officer up there, but I
                    would do some of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your consul general?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Wever Gim. A guy named Don Elson was the number two, and me, and then
                    there was a big CIA station there. They were supporting the Thai border guards,
                    which was under the patronage of the King's mother. They were involved in all
                    sorts of things: trying to keep an eye on the opium traffic and the communist
                    insurgency. Again, speaking Thai and being a bachelor still, I did a lot of
                    traveling. So, I would go and see all the American citizens around, and
                    [otherwise] became useful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: American citizens in north Thailand were mainly
                        missionaries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Missionaries. Very few businesspeople. There was a university up there.
                    Then there were Thai communists in our consular area. At the end of the two
                    years, Ambassador Unger, who knew me from Laos because he replaced Win Brown in
                    Laos, after being DCM in Bangkok, [as] ambassador, had now returned to Bangkok
                    as ambassador.</p>
                <p>As my tour was finishing up, they couldn't find anyone to be public affairs
                    officer in Phitsanolok [Province]. The guerilla war was starting to blow up
                    there. They had a CIA base stuck away in the hills. The ambassador was not
                    overly pleased with the lack of control he had over that area. I was looking for
                    a job. I spoke Thai. I think I got another promotion as a staff officer. I think
                    I was an FSS-7 by that time (GS-8). So, again, fortuitous circumstance, I went
                    down to Phitsanolok as the branch public affairs officer responsible for six
                    provinces, but did primarily political reporting. I did a lot of USIS reporting
                    and USIS work, but the main thing was to be a liaison with the Thai Army Third
                    Division. They had a MAAG. The officers were there for a year or a year and a
                    half. They had their families. They were not efficient, motivated, or good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were American forces you're talking about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. That there was a small team. Then they had a Air Force station
                    there that did refueling. That was right in the center of the county. So, there
                    were probably 150 military floating around the area in various states of
                    undiscipline. An occasional CIA guy would come through. The ambassador, I think,
                    was uneasy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Leonard Unger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was in Bangkok?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: By that time, yes. So, I think that was one of the reasons he wanted
                    somebody down there to replace Dick Usher, who was leaving. So, I came in. I did
                    a lot of reporting. Then again, it was very fortunate, nobody knew I was staff
                    except the ambassador. I was just a State officer who was sent down there. The
                    people didn't know whether I was a State officer, CIA, or the ambassador's
                    hatchet man, whatever, but I spoke Thai and got around.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who wrote our efficiency report? O'NEILL: Ben Courtney
                        wrote the efficiency report.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And he was...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: A USIS officer. But Ben knew what I was doing up there. I was very, very
                    good for them. So, I traveled those six provinces. I liaisoned with the Third
                    Army.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the Thai army?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: The Thai army had not fought in 20 or 30 years. It was involved in
                    politics. It really wasn't a terribly good army. But it was also not a brutal
                    army. It did not “bang on” its own people. Thailand has been blessed these many,
                    many years with a great king whose idea of putting down insurgency, was to build
                    roads and water wells in the area. He would bring water and schools. He himself
                    would go. Nobody touches the King, nobody. So, when these people had roads to
                    bring out their food, water in which to grow their food, and a possibility of
                    school for their children, what could the communists offer? The army offered
                    some type of security. Once a person gets a small little truck where he can put
                    his family up front and his goods in the back, the communists can't beat it. I
                    think, over a period of time, the Thai army became better. It will never be a
                    great army because it doesn't have anyone to fight. When it has to fight, it
                    does so reluctantly. The common soldier is a peasant soldier. He's in for a
                    short period of time and he's out. That's the end. Most of the generals are more
                    interested in their portion of whatever it is that they get out as corruption,
                    etc.</p>
                <p>Q: Unless you have time for me to something further to add about that tour in
                    Thailand, let's move on to 1971 when you moved to the Philippines.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: What happened was, I got sick toward the end of my tour in Thailand. I
                    had a mild case of something exotic. I also had trouble with my eyes, all for
                    the first time. So, I had a rather long time at home. I really never wanted to
                    go to the Philippines. I thought the Philippines was a sideshow. Also, I was
                    being sent out as a consular officer. Again, one of those hybrids, as a consular
                    officer first and not yet an officer. So, when I went out to Manila for a short
                    period of time. When the position in Cebu could not be filled immediately, I was
                    asked if I would go down to do the consular work. Again, my reputation of having
                    had done political reporting, etc. was still fairly well known. So, I was sent
                    down to work for Dan Sullivan. Dan really was more an inside man. His wife,
                    Margaret, was there and the children. He knew a lot of people in Leyte, which
                    was further north. My predecessor had done some reporting, but was not overly
                    industrious or interested. So, I put together the consular section, which was in
                    some sort of disarray. It wasn't a terribly difficult thing to do. I had to
                    learn the situation very quickly. Then Dan asked me to go out and see some
                    American citizens who were in jail in the south on criminal charges. When I went
                    down there, as a matter of course, I went-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the south, you mean down in Mindanao?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Mindanao and down into Davao and the other areas. When I went visiting,
                    I normally, as in any other post, went and did my business: I saw the Governor,
                    I saw this man and that official. I came back and I wrote up my consular work
                    and separately I wrote my political [observations]. Cebu was so outside the
                    mainstream of the regular Foreign Service that we had no classified
                    communications. We had a one time pad. So, we would have a once a week courier.
                    All our reporting was done by memcons or airgrams. I preferred the memcon
                    because it gave me a lot more ability to say what I wanted to and it got [to]
                    people who made policy. After about four or five months, we start getting notes
                    back from Washington saying, “Hey, these are good things, but why does it take
                    so long?” Bill Hamilton was DCM in Manila, the same Bill Hamilton from Laos. He
                    said, “I want to see everything that comes out of there because I want to make
                    sure it goes with what we say.” We then, with the acquiescence of Washington,
                    sent Washington a copy of our reporting direct to the desk. Then the desk
                    started to complain to Manila about the delay in receiving Cebu's reports. So,
                    Manila was caught in the middle. After that, they just simply ignored us and let
                    us do our work.</p>
                <p>Hank Byroade was the ambassador in Manila. He and Imelda Marcos had a platonic
                    love affair. It was platonic and it was a love affair. It was very difficult for
                    anyone to get anything through to him about how bad Marcos was running the
                    country. Dan Sullivan was an FSO-2 and was close to being selected out. I think
                    I was an FSS-6. We were really in bad position with the people in Manila.</p>
                <p>While this was all going on, I had started to build up a tremendounumber of
                    contacts.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the people in Manila come to visit you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Seldom if ever. [When they did], they would come down on the Air attach�
                    plane. They would spend a couple of hours and go right back. I don't think they
                    ever spent more than two days in the whole south.</p>
                <p>[Nevertheless, we were getting a goood picture] of what's going on. Our sources
                    start telling us all sorts of things. We start finding out details of what was
                    going on. Who is doing what to whom, where the money is, what sort of corruption
                    there was. We were in really, really deep trouble [with the embassy until] the
                    Foreign Service inspectors come through. This was especially true when we
                    started to secure really excellent information on the Marcos family. [Our
                    reporting saved Sullivan]. The inspectors said everything we were doing was
                    wonderful. Dan finally made [FSO grade]one.</p>
                <p>Let me add just one other thing that I sort of forgot. I think one of the reasons
                    that I was such a viable candidate for Cebu was that I had met a lovely
                    Filipina. The embassy and the Department at that time, for a variety of reasons,
                    were not all in favor of (Mind you, this was 25 years ago) interracial or even
                    international marriages. The fact, I think, that I was 36 or 37 at that time
                    made no difference. I was still staff. They gave us a very bad time. I guess
                    they thought that if I was down south, that would be fine. At that point, I did
                    apply and asked for permission to marry. Remember the old deal where you had to
                    send them your resignation and then you had to wait for 120 days? Well, we
                    arranged to be married on about the 125th day. It gets close to, I think, about
                    the 100th day. Dan Sullivan signed off on a cable which said, “The vice consul
                    would like to know whether he is going to be allowed to marry because if he's
                    not, he has to tell the cardinal who is going to marry him that he will not be
                    marrying the vice consul of the United States, but just a United States citizen
                    if he does not have permission to marry.” Seventy-two hours later, the
                    permission arrives.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Congratulations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: You saw one of the results of that marriage. (TiffanHope, age 12, was
                    introduced upon the arrival of Mr. Dunnigan.)</p>
                <p>Q: Yes, I did. Tell us a little bit about the fighting in the south between the
                    Muslims and Christians. That was going on at this time, as I recall.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Oh, yes. I got down to Zamboanga and the Basilian Islands. I was
                    [reporting on] everything. It is well to recall that the south had always been
                    Muslim, had been even in Spanish times. In recent times, after the Americans
                    came and especially after WWII when the land in the north, especially in the
                    Ilocos area, had become so poor there was a general migration of Filipinos into
                    the Mindanao area and further south. That caused all sorts of problems. The
                    immigrants were Catholic. They began to take away land that belonged to Muslims,
                    which brings me to another story.</p>
                <p>I had gone down to see the [province] of Illano del Sul, which had a Muslim lady
                    governor. She was governor only because her husband could not run for
                    reelection; his wife ran in his place. He told me the same story that others had
                    reported that the Catholics were bad. He explained how little money he and the
                    other Muslims had had. But, he had recently received money from his friend
                    Muammar Qadhafi in Libya and also some arms. If the Christians (and he knew I
                    was a Catholic) were going to steal, rape, and murder, he wanted the Americans
                    to know that they weren't going to lay down and die. This is 1972 and Muammar
                    was already supporting all sorts of Muslim factions in the south, not terribly
                    generously, but when you have nothing and someone sends $20,000 and 200
                    rifles... When I heard this, I knew that this would raise alarm signals in
                    Manila with Ambassador Byroade and Bill Hamilton. I spoke with some very
                    knowledgeable sources in the area to confirm the information. I also spoke with
                    the governor of Bukidnan, who I knew very well and [who] was to be my best man
                    at my wedding. [He] provided further information. The embassy and the Agency
                    [Central Intelligence Agency] were unaware of these events. When I returned, I
                    wrote the report and showed it to Dan Sullivan. We sent it along with some fear
                    since it demonstrated Marcos' lack of control in the south and the way things
                    were more quickly going out of control.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have an Agency representative in Cebu?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No. I wrote it all up and sent it up on the next poucwith a copy to
                    Washington. They were really pissed in Manila.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It hit the fan, in other words.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: It hit the fan. They wanted to know how I was so involved. The inspector
                    saved us. If the inspectors had not come down and seen how careful we were about
                    this, we would have been in deep trouble.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>[We had another reporting coup] when Marcos took over, pulled his internal coup,
                    and destroyed democracy for years. At that time, we fortunately had an American
                    naval vessel sitting in the harbor which was there on R&amp;R [rest and
                    relaxation]. The communicator, boy, did he work for the next three or four days.
                    We asked CINCPAC [Commander-in-Chief, Pacific] if they could [let] the ships
                    stay in port for additional hours so we could report reaction in the consular
                    district [to Marcos' coup]. Manila would not allow the ship to remain because it
                    would appear that we were involved in [Philippine] internal affairs, or
                    whatever. Dan Sullivan did some tremendous cables because he knew all the
                    military in Cebu. They just opened up to him. Dan Sullivan had the best
                    information about what was going on in the coup and how the military in Cebu
                    were reacting, as well as in Manila, notwithstanding at the time the close
                    relation between Byroade and the Marcos family. The embassy was caught with
                    their pants down there, absolutely caught.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the feeling in your area about the Marcoses?
                        Hdeclared martial law during this period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: That's right. First of all, everybody in that area knew Imelda. They
                    knew she was poor. The first pair of shoes she ever got she got from the
                    Redemptorist Fathers. She didn't wear underclothes because she didn't have them
                    until she was close to her teens. They knew she was the mistress of the former
                    Speaker of the House before she was Marcos' mistress and then married him. In
                    character, she was not much different than Madame Ngo Dinh Nhu or Lady Thatcher,
                    except both come from a better class family. But Imelda's people were living on
                    the generosity of others. She never forgot that. She didn't forget it in her
                    clothes or shoes, in the way she acted. She never forgot anybody who ever
                    brought it up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. It was something you didn't bring up.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: You didn't bring it up. They knew Marcos. Marcos was always a
                    lightweight. The medals he got were political medals. Imelda, like Madame Ngo
                    Dinh Nhu, ran that country. She had no guidance on the way up, nobody who said,
                    “You don't have to dress like a whore for everybody to look at you; a little bit
                    of restraint is best.” I'll give you one great story about her. She called in
                    some very wealthy businessmen and said that she wanted to build a cultural
                    center. She said, “Let me have some money.” So, they gave her a blank check and
                    said, “Do what you want with it.” So, she had her people call up to find out
                    what was in their account and wrote it to the penny. They were very, very upset.
                    She would take scheduled Philippine Airlines planes and take the plane someplace
                    else. Again, in a way, she reminds me of Alexandra of Nicholas and Alexandra,
                    narrow minded, kept her husband in power because when the husband goes, she's
                    gone. The children weren't terribly good, as one can imagine. The people in the
                    south did not like her. They despised her. They looked down their nose at her,
                    but they couldn't do anything. The Muslims were on the outskirts. They were just
                    protecting themselves. The Muslims, regardless of all the propaganda, never were
                    that serious a threat to the government in Manila because, even though they were
                    Muslims, they were still Filipinos.</p>
                <p>They have the same vices and the same internal family flaws. There is a Tagalog
                    phrase called “Utang na lob.” It means “A debt of obligation.” If somebody is
                    your godfather, he is as responsible for you as if he was your father and maybe
                    more. The corruption was endemic. It is regrettable, but the major export of the
                    Philippines has always been human beings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How well I remember from my days there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I went through all the Middle East as an inspector and the Filipinos are
                    the nurses, maidservants, and the mistresses; the men are chauffeurs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any anti-American feeling in Cebu at the time?
                        Was thconsulate ever demonstrated against, attacked, or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No. Cebu belonged to the Toledo family. When I came down from Manila,
                    they didn't know what to make of me. They thought, one, I was a CIA agent; two,
                    I had been sent down “special.” But I wasn't sent down special, but rather to
                    replace somebody who was leaving, who was not well liked or well respected. I
                    was older. That made a difference. I guess I acted a bit more conservatively. I
                    didn't go around without a coat and tie. I had calling cards. The small things
                    that make the difference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the Filipinos notice immediately.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Notice immediately, yes. The Filipinos are culturally and religiously
                    influenced by the Spanish with a superficial American facade. If you recall, the
                    Miranda Plaza bombing, when a number of politicians were killed, was reportedly
                    done (and this was probably true) by the Marcos family. The Osmanias opponents
                    felt that they had no one that they could speak with at the embassy, so they
                    came south to Cebu, their home base. They spoke with Dan Sullivan, the consul,
                    but more to me because they thought I was CIA. Sullivan knew all this and we
                    reported it to Manila. Manila was unhappy with the reports because of the close
                    Marcos-embassy relations. They sent down the consul general, Larry Lawrence, to
                    speak with us and tell us the view from Embassy Manila. He carried back a
                    diplomatic pouch with our reports, which told the embassy exactly what was going
                    on. Lawrence was outraged because he was supposed to see that our reports
                    mirrored the embassy's reports. Lawrence as the consul general also had close
                    political/personal relations with the Marcos family as only the consul general
                    in Manila can. The people in the south were initially in favor of the coup, but
                    the continuation of the draft, but on a grander scale, [was something] they
                    didn't want.</p>
                <p>Q: That was quite an interesting two years in Manila. Then in 1973, you went back
                    to the Department and stayed there for a year. What did you do during that
                    period?</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I came back to the Department. It wasn't quite a year. It was less than
                    a year. I came back because I married Josephine. I had asked if I could stay on
                    in Cebu for the birth of our first child, as Josephine was pregnant just as we
                    were leaving. They said, of course, “No.” I married in April. We left in
                    August/September. I worked in the visa office. I was there for a two year tour
                    until somebody came by and said, “We're looking for somebody to go out to
                    Calcutta.” They looked at me and I said, “Hey, you guys forget, I'm married now.
                    I have an adopted girl, my wife's half sister. I have a new baby not yet three
                    months old. This was June. You're going to send me out to that cesspool?” I came
                    back home and I talked to Josephine. Josephine said, “What's going to happen?” I
                    had just made officer. I forgot that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me about that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: I had just made officer. She said, “You go out there and you'll be
                    consul in Calcutta. It can't be too bad.” There was a Mustang Program they had
                    opened up. Perkins, who was later director general and is now ambassador in
                    Australia (He's on his way home if he's not home already) was head of the panel.
                    They looked at my file and I said, “I want to be an officer.” They said, “You
                    don't have a university degree. All you have is your work experience.” By that
                    time, I guess I had 11 years in the Service. I said, “Look, you've got a Mustang
                    Program.” They said, “We really want people who can speak a language.” I said,
                    “I speak Thai and I speak French.” “But you don't have any college.” They banged
                    on me about the lack of a university degree, which, by the way, I would like to
                    say for anybody who reads this thing, I think that I would have been an awful
                    lot more useful to the Department and useful to my family if I had a degree. I
                    would have made ambassador if I had a university degree. I don't have it; I'm
                    not going to do it. There are other reasons I didn't make ambassador. [Anyway],
                    they let me come in, I think, as a Foreign Service officer six. When I married
                    Josephine, it was '73. I made officer in '72.</p>
                <p>So, we decided to go out to Calcutta. When we said, “Josephine and I are going to
                    Calcutta, 99% of the Department was happy for us. One percent (most of the
                    people I was working for in the Visa Section) wasn't because I didn't finish the
                    full two year tour.” I was almost 40 years old. I knew how to do things. I
                    didn't have to go and bother people. I went out to Calcutta.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you go out as?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I went out as a consular officer. At that time, we had a terrible
                    problem in Calcutta. It was called the “Harcos-Fletcher” matter. Two guys trying
                    to smuggle narcotics in Calcutta had been caught on the King George naval dock.
                    They had not been arrested for smuggling, but had been arrested for trespassing
                    on military property, spying, and held under the Official Secrets Act. The case
                    received so much domestic political pressure that Henry Kissinger had to take it
                    up personally with Indira Gandhi.</p>
                <p>This case, I'd like to say, went on for almost two years. I had to visit them in
                    the jail every day. While they were in jail, they went on a hunger strike. They
                    had to be force fed, which I had to watch. The jails in Calcutta were terrible.
                    Finally, we arranged for them to be under house arrest, which they had to pay
                    for. My wife had to go out and buy all their food and bring it in. I had to
                    attend High Court hearings and actually answer questions before My Lord, Justice
                    Talukdar. I forget all the paraphernalia that I had to say, that I was only here
                    to provide comfort to two American citizens, not in any way to observe the
                    proceedings, which I was absolutely positive were being conducted as if it were
                    before the Supreme Court in Washington. Boy, I really put the grease on that
                    one. I spent two years at Court and three years in Calcutta.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>The consul general who was just leaving was a nice guy. The deputy consul general
                    in Calcutta was not terribly industrious. I became the de facto number two. I
                    was taking care of the Consular Section and the Harcos-Fletcher matter, which
                    had Secretary of State's interest and Embassy Delhi's interest because everybody
                    was afraid they would die in Indian custody. There was a time when they were
                    really possibly going to die. We finally had them put under house arrest. That
                    was what lead to Josephine being the purveyor of all their foods and other
                    necessities.</p>
                <p>Then I started to travel on normal consular business. I went to Bihar, to Orissa,
                    all over our consular district. Each place I went, I would sit down as I did in
                    Cebu and I would write long bios on everybody I met. There was a bio form at
                    that time. As time went on, down toward the end of our two years, they asked us
                    to extend, and we did for a third year. So, we did three years in Calcutta. I
                    received a Meritorious Honor Award out of that. But I found the Indians, if you
                    approached them on an intellectual basis, and told them you weren't interested
                    in propaganda, and you talked to them about what was going on that affected them
                    and their relationship with us, you could get a decent dialogue - not a dialogue
                    where you would [have a meeting of the minds] because we still had the Vietnam
                    War. The Vietnam War was going on. And they were very proud that the Vietnamese
                    were beating us. Occasionally, when they would annoy me, I would say, “And I
                    know how well you did against the Chinese.” The Chinese had recently beaten them
                    in a border fight. That would really get them. Sometimes I would say, “You know,
                    Calcutta was very important in this fight against the Chinese because the
                    Chinese had sent down scouts who got as far as Calcutta and went back and said,
                    'If we take Calcutta, we'll lose.'" After a while, they left me alone as it
                    regards Vietnam.</p>
                <p>I just want to go back for one thing: Vietnam and the Tet offensive. When the Tet
                    offensive happened, I was in Chiang Mai, but they called me back because we had
                    a number of officers in Hue. Some of our officers in Quang Tri had been under
                    the gun for weeks and weeks, been shelled and the rest. That was Steve Ledogar
                    and Dick Brown. They had to leave. There were others. So, I went back. They were
                    still bringing Marines into Hue when I went in with them. A number of people,
                    German doctors, innocent civilians, had been killed for no reason. I'm not
                    talking about priests. I'm just talking about normal people who had been
                    killed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They ran amuck.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I don't know what they were doing. They seemed to have lost discipline.
                    Of course, to retake the old city of Hue, which the Marines went in and took
                    terrible casualties, but the other point is that the Vietnamese marines who went
                    in with our Marines (not immediately, but following up) took great casualties.
                    Of course, I think, psychologically, the United States lost the war when Robert
                    Kennedy started saying that “Our boys are dying and no Vietnamese are dying” and
                    then Cronkite went out and said, “There's a possibility we can't win this.” We
                    lost it.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>But then they were back to Calcutta, the consul general and I did all the
                    reporting. I did a lot more than he did. He did the analytical stuff. I did the
                    grunt work primarily because as a consular officer, you get around to see
                    everybody and nobody says to the American consul, “You can't come in.” They'll
                    say that to the economic officer or the political officer, maybe even say that
                    to the consul general, but somebody in that family is going to need a visa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How well do we understand that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I understand it and used it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the ambassador visit Calcutta very often?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. Fortunately, by that time, Galbraith (His son is now ambassador in
                    the Balkans) used to come up on a regular basis, primarily to go to Orissa to go
                    swimming. The other ambassadors came up to see us occasionally and the DCM came
                    up to see us, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had a huge consular district.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. We couldn't visit most of it because the Indians wouldn't let us.
                    The Department for some ungodly reason was very interested in knowing what was
                    happening among the tribes up on the Burmese border.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the northeast there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, up around Assam and Nagoland. I have no idea why. There were human
                    rights violations out there. I had met a number of Italian priests who were up
                    that way, and Irish Christian Brothers. My uncle was an Irish Christian Brother.
                    So, I had a good entree to that level. The archbishop of Calcutta was made a
                    cardinal while I was there and was a friend of the family and had been to the
                    house, and had Josephine's cooking, as everybody else did in that town. It was
                    just intellectually a very stimulating post. For the first time, we had a
                    democratic communist takeover.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think Bengal was communist controlled.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. Well, it became communist controlled and never has left communist
                    control. Jyoti Basu. But he was a communist who played golf. He was a communist
                    who liked his Scotch and water. He was a man who loved the finer things in
                    life.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any personal security problems there in
                        Calcutta?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: The Naxalites were still wandering around the area. Thconsul general had
                    a bodyguard.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Explain them a bit.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Naxalites were really anarchists, very, very outside the realm of the
                    communist, Marxist party. They were really beyond the pale. They really believed
                    in killing their enemies. They had killed a lot of people. They were being
                    fought by the West Bengal armed police, which were paramilitary. The fight was
                    really run from the rank of sergeant to about captain by Anglo-Indians. They
                    were “mean mothers.” I mean, they were really bad. They had no compunction.
                    Naxalites never went to trial. They were always killed in fights. It was
                    difficult for me to understand some of it because they were in a corner with
                    their hands behind their back and they were still “allegedly fighting.” It was
                    very, very difficult fighting. Most of these officers eventually immigrated to
                    England or to Australia or Canada. They had no future in India because they were
                    “Anglo.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any effect of our Pakistan tilt in those
                        days?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They never could understand why we were pro-Pakistani. I said, “You mean
                    because they support us in the United Nations, they buy our weapons, they engage
                    in trade with us, etc. and you holler at us, you're against us every time,
                    against us over this and that?” “We have a right to be like that. We're Indians,
                    we're Bengalis.” I said, “We have a right to make our own friends.” “Oh, you
                    only want people who like you?” “That's what friends are for.” The Indian
                    general in charge (interestingly, Jewish) of that area was another friend of
                    mine who had been in charge of an armored division going across into Bangladesh.
                    He now was in charge of all Indian troops in that area. We had some very
                    interesting conversations. He only got annoyed at me once because I got to know
                    many of his middle rank officers. He felt that I was pumping them for
                    information, which I was. But we had a good professional relationship. It was
                    not a personal relationship. But he understood exactly what I was doing. He had
                    a very low opinion of politicians and especially Indian politicians. He knew
                    they were all bribable. This was, by the way, during the time when Mrs. Gandhi
                    took over the whole government. She and her son ran it: forced sterilization,
                    etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She declared a state of emergency.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: That's right. It again shows you the value of consulates. [At times],
                    had better information [from Calcutta] about what was going on in Delhi than the
                    people in Delhi. They had very fine officers there, but Indian politicians would
                    return home to Calcutta. It was easier for us to see them and they to see us in
                    my house. I remember having a man by the name of Kamal Nath, who I think has
                    finally been caught by his own government for misappropriation of funds. He came
                    and gave us great information on Thanksgiving Day about Indian atomic energy
                    research. He didn't know he was giving it. We had talked about a number of
                    things. Afterwards, I remember saying to David Korn, who was probably the best
                    writer in the whole Foreign Service, absolutely without par, “Well, I'm not
                    going to write this, am I? You're going to write it, aren't you?” He said,
                    “Well, if you write it, I have to rewrite it, so let me do it.” So, he did it.
                    He left out this piece. He had sent it out without showing it to me. I forget
                    what I was doing the next day. I came up and I said to him, “We're got to report
                    this.” He said, “Yes, I guess we have to.” I said, “Why don't we just to report
                    it EXDIS [exclusive distribution] since it's sensitive?” The result was a
                    beautiful cable from the ambassador in New Delhi (a professor from Ohio or
                    someplace), or I guess it was written by the DCM, saying how much they
                    appreciated the first cable and how much they appreciate our sensitivity in
                    sending this other cable separately and restricted. David Korn said, “You know,
                    luck to the goddam Irish.” The Agency was upset that we beat them on this. The
                    chief of station tried to take some of my sources. He eventually did after I
                    left.</p>
                <p>But it was for me a very stimulating thing. The poverty waatrocious. We met
                    Mother Theresa before she came in November.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was going to ask you whether you had met Mother
                        Theresa.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: We did. We met her and her nuns. Again, the previous consular officer
                    was just a real asshole, a jerk, and was making these poor nuns go through all
                    the things that had to be done to get into the States. So, I gave them all B-1
                    visas and said, “Now, make sure you enter through New York.” I put a little
                    note: “Under the patronage of Francis Cardinal Spellman.” Never had another bit
                    of trouble, not legal, but correct</p>
                <p>The Bengali is really a terribly interesting person. He loves poetry, politics,
                    and is not terribly interested in a great deal of profitable or economic work.
                    But in all this, he is a ferment for India. The old saying “What Bengal thinks
                    today India thinks tomorrow” is or was at the time I was there very, very
                    accurate. You could see the swings in mood, the beginning of Indira Gandhi and
                    her son pushing too far, pushing the Bengali to do something which they hate to
                    do: work. It was just that sort of ferment in the society which caught on. In
                    that period under martial law, Mrs. Gandhi was able to do so many economic
                    things. It has been forgotten, but there were useful things done. The Indian
                    bureaucracy was and continues to be inefficient, ineffective, and corrupt. I
                    think that will be an inhibiting factor in anything that happens for the
                    foreseeable future.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>Q: What was the religious situation like in the Calcutta region when you were
                    there? Was it Hindu dominant? Was there much antipathy toward the Muslims? Were
                    there any Muslims or others there?</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: The Muslims were not a problem in Calcutta at the time I was there
                    because they were so few. Their presence was barely noted. There was an
                    Anglo-Indian community which was primarily Protestant-Catholic, but of no
                    political influence, nor [were there Muslims] into Mizoland or into Assam or
                    Nagoland. There were animists and Christians and they were a problem which was
                    beginning at that time. I think David Korn pointed out to Delhi and Washington
                    that the movement of Bengalis out of Bangladesh into that area was going to
                    cause friction, which we see by today's paper does cause friction. I don't see
                    religion in that area being a problem. I would not say the same for places like
                    Bombay or in that particular area because they were adjacent to Pakistan. There
                    is still a significant Muslim-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, the Bengalis moving out of Bangladesh would be
                        Muslim?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Absolutely, but they were not moving into Bengali Hindu areas. They were
                    moving into tribal areas to the north, where the land is rich and where there is
                    work and, more importantly, where there is water.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the position of the Soviets when you were there
                        iCalcutta?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: It's amazing. It will always amaze me both in Calcutta and in Ethiopia
                    how they have such a good intelligent system, many contacts with the people, and
                    still don't know what the hell is going on. In every case when I was there, any
                    time there was a political controversy, they were always wrong. I knew the
                    Soviet officer who was head of intelligence. He was a guest at my house. He was
                    sent back to Moscow because he had so misreported the situation. I had a very
                    excellent relationship with the number two at the Russian consulate general,
                    which was big. [Calcutta] had Polish, Bulgarian, everybody was there. There was
                    a big Eastern presence, plus an Iranian presence. Everybody was in Calcutta
                    because at one time it was a stopover for all the planes going to and from
                    Europe. Everybody refueled there. The next refueling place was in Bombay. I
                    don't think the East Bloc was terribly effective. In fact, I think they were
                    bad. They did not associate with the people. Anything they did was in a very
                    formal or within a narrow parameter, but there was no personal interplay
                    between-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Even though Bengal was ruled by communists at the
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: West Bengal at that time was not ruled by the communists, but was
                    eventually ruled by the communists alone. Very, very bad relations. The other
                    thing is, they had one token mixed marriage in their community. A Russian girl
                    married somebody from Mongolia. In our community, which was much smaller, there
                    were a number of mixed marriages: mine, a fellow who was married to an Indian
                    girl. Somebody would come up and say, “Isn't it great that you have more mixed
                    marriages in your community than the Russians?” We would say, “We really don't
                    give a damn. We don't sleep for politics. We sleep for passion.” Always shook
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the Chinese communist influence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They had a very difficult time. In fact, if I recall correctly, they had
                    no representation in Calcutta. It was something that the Indians did not like to
                    talk about. They knew that they were beaten by the Chinese. They felt aggrieved
                    that after all the political support that they had given the Chinese during the
                    Vietnam War, the Indians only sent a medical unit during the Korean War, they
                    had always been a friend of China, voted for their entry into the United
                    Nations, had tried to do all sorts of things for them, but when it came to a
                    border dispute, they wouldn't acquiesce to India's point of view and then had
                    beaten them badly. What hurt was that those units that did well against the
                    Chinese were the Gurkhas, tribal units, not Hindu regiments. The Sikhs did well
                    against them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a Vietnamese presence in Calcutta?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, there wasn't a Vietnamese presence in Calcutta. There was one in
                    Delhi, but it was a Saigon presence. I was going to be called back to go to Laos
                    (1975) to help them evacuate in those final days, but I was involved in this
                    Harcos-Fletcher matter. I was the only one who was accredited by the courts to
                    attend these official secret trials. Delhi and Washington considered that more
                    important than me going back to Laos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we have a Peace Corps presence there in that
                        area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: There was no Peace Corps.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because the Indians didn't want it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They didn't want it. They had left at some time. I can'remember when
                    they had left, but we did not have a Peace Corps presence.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your tour in Calcutta ended in 1977, I believe?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were next transferred to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I came home for Portugese language.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You took Portugese language and went on to Lisbon.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. There was a question about where I should go next. I thought it
                    would be best to go back to East Asia, where I knew the place, etc. But my
                    career counselor and Josephine said that I needed a different outlook on life.
                    So, I was sent out to Lisbon as the consul, later the consul general. I did
                    primarily consular work. I was responsible for the Azores. I did political
                    reporting out there because the consul out there didn't want to, didn't feel she
                    should do it, she was a consular officer. I visited Oporto, had some consular
                    cases in Funchal. But of that whole assignment, we had one baby while we were
                    there. That was Kevin, the fellow you just met who is going into the Marines. I
                    was also sent out to Teheran on TDY. It doesn't show up on the records.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Those were the bad days in Teheran.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. I went out in January of '79. The Shah was still in power. In
                    February, the Shah left and Khomeini arrived. February 14, the mobs took over
                    the embassy for the first time. That was interesting; Ambassador Sullivan was
                    out there. Sullivan knew me because he had come in and replaced Byroade in the
                    Philippines. He was very kind when I was out there. He said, “You know, after
                    you left, the political reporting from that area just deteriorated.” I was so
                    pleased that he noticed my reporting. So, I was out there. What was interesting
                    was the interplay between the embassy, Brzezinski, and Carter just before the
                    takeover, during the takeover, and after the takeover. The absolute stupidity,
                    ignorance of the senior American military officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned the embassy, Brzezinski, and Carter. Where
                        was thState Department in all of this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: I consider Sullivan the State Department. Sullivan did all his work with
                    Brzezinski. He did not go back through whoever was head of NEA. The first day
                    when I got there, and I regret to say this, there were political officers of the
                    junior and middle grades who were on the phone back to Washington undercutting
                    Ambassador Sullivan, saying that “We shouldn't be here, we should all be
                    evacuated, we should all be sent home, not just the wives and the children. We
                    all should get out of here. Stop issuing visas, the whole thing.” A number of
                    things happened here. One, we had probably the most incompetent consul general
                    in the world, Lou Goelz, as the consul general in Teheran. He was issuing visas
                    as fast as we could stamp visas without regard to who we were letting in. We
                    were bringing in Pan Am planes to take out Americans and we found out that
                    everybody on the Pan Am plane were Iranians. They weren't Americans. We were
                    bringing in extra planes to take out third country nationals and Americans and
                    found out the Iranians were leaving. We had a rough time taking out the Israeli
                    embassy. Brzezinski personally called Sullivan to make sure that the Israeli
                    embassy was taken out, on a priority basis, regardless.</p>
                <p>First of all, let's talk about the military.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, and what were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: My job was to help get the Americans out of the area and to help
                    adjudicate some of the visas that were being processed there. First thing, the
                    senior American military officer, three stars, was from Germany. Sullivan asked
                    each officer “Will the Iranian troops stand with the Shah? Can we count on
                    them?” The American officer said, “Absolutely, sure, they will stand.” Sullivan
                    asked, “How do we know this?” “Because the officers had given their word as
                    gentlemen.” We're talking about Iranians. We're not talking about British
                    officers. They just flopped. The other thing was that Brzezinski and Sullivan
                    were talking to each other but were not listening to each other. Brzezinski
                    could not, and neither could Carter (I think it's impossible for people to
                    understand) understand that this thing was falling apart. This was the Shah.
                    This was a man who had been courted by every President since President Truman.
                    This is a man we put on the throne.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was thrown out once before.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Right, and we had brought him back. Kermit Roosevelt, who was a CIA guy,
                    brought him back. So, here we have all these things. Then we have another
                    problem: there was low morale in the embassy. There was low morale in the
                    Consular Section, which was the biggest consular section we had in the world.
                    There was low morale there because Goelz would not stand up and [refuse to]
                    issue visas. He had some very incompetent consular officers there, just awful.
                    One who later goes at another post, doesn't follow up on an American who dies
                    under mysterious circumstances. Really bad. It was Goelz himself. He just lets
                    them go through. Somebody refused a student visa goes over and gets a tourist
                    visa. Just nothing. Just awful. That was the problem.</p>
                <p>Then you had the problem of whether the President, Mr. Carter, will be tough. In
                    other words, will he say the necessary things. We had no relations with
                    Khomeini. Nobody knew him. Sullivan now knows shortly after Khomeini arrived
                    that things had gone bad and wants people out. The Agency does not want to go
                    out. Many of the officers don't want to go out. Their families are there.
                    They're making 25%. You've got “listeners” who don't want to go out. Sullivan
                    can't get a hold on it because to get this thing done, he has to get permission
                    from Washington to send them home. He can't get it done. He just can't get it
                    done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Washington would not give that permission?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Washington would not give that permission. Then comes February 14th.
                    Mobs start to come across the wall. The Marines are armed and ready to fight.
                    Everybody is battened down. Sullivan is trying to get some word out of
                    Washington, but can't. He has two choices: a) he can fight and hope that
                    everybody will not be killed; or b) he can give up. So, he decides to give up
                    and he moves everybody, myself included, into the vault. By this time, smart guy
                    that Sullivan is, there is hardly any secret papers around. There is just hardly
                    any. He's only got one last channel, one crypto channel left. Then he hollers in
                    to Eugene O'Neill, not me, the CIA communicator, and he says, “Is it destroyed?”
                    O'Neill throws it in the barrel and says, “It's destroyed now” and then we
                    surrender. Then they march us all out: Marines, secretaries, a couple of
                    correspondents, into a courtyard. He has Skip Boyce, who is Sullivan's
                    interpreter, who is now, I think, DCM in Bangkok. So, we're all marched out
                    there and we're all lined up against the wall. We all know what the hell is
                    going to happen. We're going to get shot. So, the Marines and the others start
                    to put the women to the back. We say, “When they shoot, you fall under the
                    bodies.” Then Sullivan, God bless his heart, starts to move off to the side,
                    with Boyce, his interpreter, hoping that if there is going to be shooting, they
                    will shoot him and not us. So, he and Boyce keep talking. As this happens,
                    another faction starts to come into the courtyard.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were all civilians, not uniformed people, on the
                        Iraniaside?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: All civilians. Every single one were civilians. All of them. They come
                    in and then there is a big argument. Then the radicals start to move out. I
                    would suggest that five minutes, give or take, we were all dead.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very close shave.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Very close shave, closer than anything I had experienced in Vietnam.
                    Really close. The thing that got me after this as we all sort of sat around in
                    the American community who were there on February 14th, every one of us knew
                    that if we had been killed, we would not have been avenged. Ronald Reagan... We
                    just would not. So, February 14th until I left sometime in March, we never had
                    complete control of that embassy. Their people were in the embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, they were still there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Still there. We moved in and moved out. One of them forced me to give a
                    visa under threat of a gun. I gave the visa and then I wrote under the page
                    FORINSEED. When he got to New York, the immigration people picked him up, beat
                    the living hell out of him, threw him on a plane, and sent him back. Barbara
                    Watson, who was at that time assistant secretary for Consular Affairs, was asked
                    by INS, “O'Neill is one of your officers?” Then they asked about the visa. “Yes,
                    that's exactly what he would have done.” When he came back, he had the “gall” to
                    come to the embassy and complain to the Iranian guards, who then beat the living
                    shit out of him also!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A pretty brave act.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Well, I knew the guy wasn't going to figure out if I put “INS” in among
                    all these letters. It didn't make any sense to him. But when the INS people saw
                    it, it kind of stuck out at them. We had no control. The bad thing about that
                    whole thing was, one, lack of communication between the White House and
                    Sullivan; two, the undercutting of the ambassador by members of his own
                    staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This I had never heard of.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: I told Sullivan personally to his face about this and his DCM, Nes. I
                    told them they were calling back and he shouldn't let them. I told them, “They
                    were calling back, saying everybody should be evacuated.” I can't remember what
                    Sullivan said. I said, “I'm not going anyplace.” But that was it. As a result of
                    that, when Reagan came to power, he sent out instructions: No embassy should be
                    given up without a fight. That thing has never been taken off the boards. I
                    remember, when I was in Khartoum, telling the security officer and the regional
                    security officer that those were the instructions of the President of the United
                    States and they hadn't been taken back. “We're not operating on them,” they
                    said. “Fine, give me something in writing about it.” I did. But again, it's the
                    question (I still feel this very strongly) of, if we had been killed, there
                    would not have been the other portion, the 444 days. There would not have been
                    the terrible damage done to our foreign relations. People say the Mayaguez
                    incident after the Vietnam War was a waste of people. For the people's family
                    who died, I can see their point of view. But the people in Hanoi did not see it
                    that way and the people in Phnom Penh did not see it that way. That's why it's
                    so important...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's why it happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Probably, I don't know. Back to Portugal, beyond that incident, this was
                    again Carter's time, we could not speak officially to the South Africans except
                    in Washington and in Johannesburg, but the consular officer could talk to [a
                    South African]. We could not speak to the Angolans, because we didn't have
                    diplomatic relations, but still people needed visas to go to the States and I
                    issued them. So, I did that sort of stuff. That was two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You couldn't have left Teheran with a very optimistic
                        attitude ato the future.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No. Khomeini lived in the 11th or 12th century, not unlike a lot of
                    people that we'll talk about in the future in Khartoum. They're happy back there
                    intellectually. This was a time of power for Islam; it's clean, it's clear,
                    everybody knows what is right and wrong, not much different than
                    fundamentalists.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Two years in Lisbon and then you went back to
                        Thailand.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, I went back on a direct transfer. This was the time when there were
                    the “boat people” coming out of South Vietnam. They needed somebody who could
                    speak Thai, somebody who had done consular work, and Lisbon bored me. So, I went
                    back. I did refugee work for two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Bangkok?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, I traveled all along the Cambodian border down to Songkhla, it's on
                    the sea. Anyplace the boat people came in, we tried to go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These refugees were mainly Vietnamese coming in, or
                        Cambodian?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: There were two groups. The ones who came across the Thai southern land
                    border were all Cambodian. The others were Vietnamese boat people who were
                    coming out. Again, there was a tremendous difference of opinion about these
                    people who were coming out. Lionel Rosenblatt and Shep Lowman and a number of
                    others felt that anybody leaving Vietnam was entitled to go to the United States
                    because we had lost the war, we should never have been there, we should never
                    have destroyed their society. For people like Shep Lowman, who was married to a
                    Vietnamese girl, and Lionel Rosenblatt, who had worked there, they should have
                    known better. But they all felt a moral obligation which they felt the United
                    States government should feel to help these refugees. We started to interview
                    them [for refugee asylum]. We found they were fisherman who never had been on
                    any side. We found that there were people who were merchants and had never been
                    on any side, never had fought with us, never had fought with the Viet Cong.
                    There were Chinese. There were a whole bunch of them. “Why are you coming out?
                    Did the Viet Cong or the communists burn down your house?” “No.” But after a
                    while, they got the answers right, but then you'd ask them a little bit
                    different and you found out that they were economic migrants. Then that caused a
                    whole problem within the Refugee Bureau. For me, another problem was abortion.
                    There were some people who were in the Refugee Bureau and in a number of
                    organizations who were assisting in abortions. I went and saw Bert Levin, who
                    was DCM, and I said, “Look, you know me. I'm not a great Catholic. You knew me
                    before I got married. I had an interesting bachelorhood. But I can't do this.”
                    So, he said, “Look, don't. Just stay away from it. Do something else and don't
                    let anybody bother you about it.” I said, “I just don't want to cause the people
                    up front a problem.” So, I did a lot of interviewing, political reporting, and
                    the rest.</p>
                <p>The refugees started to become big business. Catholic Relief Service, Lutheran
                    World Federation, everybody wanted to get in because they were charging
                    significantly high administrative support costs and they were supporting a lot
                    of other worthwhile interests. They would move these people into the United
                    States with, at the beginning, little or no training, and they gave them some
                    training, help them speak English. Still, I believe we had no obligation. They
                    would get them in and say, “We are going to be responsible for getting them
                    housing and a job.” They would get them in and assist with housing and then they
                    would put them on welfare.</p>
                <p>Some of the people we really owed, liked the Hmong, and Jerry Daniels, who spoke
                    of Mao, a former CIA guy, he got a lot of the people sent to Montana, around
                    Missoula, and places like that. He did a good job.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>But for the rest, it was a business. Regrettably, some of these people, again,
                    like Lowman and Rosenblatt, were involved in this. They were not honest about
                    how they obeyed the Immigration Nationality Act. Then we had an immigration
                    officer who was trying to do their job. We had people who were actually on the
                    other side and who were murderers. We had all sorts of problems of trying to get
                    these people sorted out. But there was a press to move these people.</p>
                <p>On the Cambodian side, we had real refugees. Some we could tell really needed
                    assistance. I remember writing to Bert Levin. I said, “You know what we're doing
                    here. In many cases, we are taking the best and the brightest out of these
                    communities and we're leaving behind a shell.” We are. We left behind shells on
                    both sides. The Vietnamese didn't care if these people left. As far as they were
                    concerned, they were making money by selling space. I cannot believe that the
                    Vietnamese government would have allowed it if they did not want over 400,000 of
                    their own people to leave Vietnam. My God!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Many of them were trained, educated.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: We did well on this. There are two points. One, we did not have a moral
                    obligation to take them in; second, we did not press for those people who we
                    should have pressed. We could have made some sort of a deal to get those people
                    who were in the education camps, those officers, the rangers, the Marines, the
                    Airbornes who fought so bravely, the district officers who were good people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There would be no objection to bringing them in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Absolutely not, but we couldn't get them out. We got thespeople.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there much fighting among the refugees
                        themselves?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, we wouldn't permit it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about incursions by the Vietnamese?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: The incursions by the Vietnamese took place only in Cambodia. They came
                    across the border for a variety of reasons. One, I think, initially because they
                    were thinking back to their ancient history and they were going to take over
                    Cambodia as a part of it. Cambodia was going to be like Laos, a territory. That
                    was the initial part. The second part, I think, was (end of tape)-</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>Pol Pot was an absolute madman according to every Cambodian I ever spoke to. We
                    were talking about why the Vietnamese made incursions into Cambodia. Even they
                    must have been horrified at what this person was doing to his own people. I
                    think there was a mixture in there. The Vietnamese wanted to increase their
                    empire. They were going to take over Laos. It was not going to be a big problem.
                    They wanted Phnom Penh and they wanted perhaps even to move a little further.
                    The Vietnamese are imperialists no different than the Chinese. We will see this
                    in the years coming. But the question of the Vietnamese has always been ethnic.
                    It always will be. The Cambodians don't like the Vietnamese and the Vietnamese
                    don't like the Cambodians, even in French times. You could never have had a
                    Vietnamese-Cambodian mixed unit. They had to be separate.</p>
                <p>There were people in the Refugee Bureau who were leaking to the press, who were
                    managing the press, who had a list of telephone numbers if something wasn't done
                    the way they wanted. They would have a story planted in Washington, Paris, and
                    Bangkok, all over. It was a terribly bad way to do business. I'm sure the best
                    people involved in the Refugee Bureau were supporting U.S. government
                    policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In your work, to whom did you report?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I reported to Lionel Rosenblatt. He was head of the Refugee section.
                    Bert Levin was the DCM. Bert wrote my review. He was a good officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was consul general in Hong Kong.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: He was consul general in Hong Kong and ambassador in Burma. There was
                    also a disagreement between Abramowitz, who was the ambassador, who was
                    definitely in favor of helping the refugees and whom the people who worked in
                    the Refugee Section continued to tell Abramowitz what the Vietnamese were doing
                    in Vietnam was similar to the Holocaust. To Abramowitz and his wife, Sheppie, it
                    pulled their heartstrings. On the Cambodians, there was no doubt that they were
                    entitled to protection. Whether they were entitled all to be brought to the
                    United States was another question, but that's something I just don't have any
                    more thoughts on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any drug problem in the camps or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Drugs were a problem, but they were an export problem, exports from the
                    Golden Triangle thru Bangkok out to Europe and the United States. But that was
                    entirely done by different groups and had nothing to do with the camps.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the end of this, you were given an assignment to the
                        NationaWar College, which was a nice thank you for some of the work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, it wasn't. I got the National War College because of my writing to
                    Bert and others within the Refugee Bureau telling them how badly the situation
                    was being managed and that the people we were bringing out were not refugees,
                    they were economic migrants. This is how it all happened. Lionel Rosenblatt had
                    Shep Lowman downsize the Refugee Bureau. He was under pressure to do it anyway.
                    So, they decided to downsize by one position, by one position number, and by one
                    position name: mine. So, I went over and I saw the administrative officer. I
                    said, “Jesus, I've got four small children and just got here. Now I've got to go
                    back. I don't have an assignment in Washington. I don't know what's going to
                    happen me. Thank God, I just got promoted. I just made 01. What am I going to
                    do?” He said, “We need you.” I said, “Well, they just cut my position.” He said,
                    “They can't cut your position until you finish your assignment. They can't do it
                    ahead of time.” So, I go skipping lightheartedly to see Lionel and Colonel Mike
                    Edlund, who were in charge at that time and said, “That's what's the deal. You'd
                    better call Washington. Unless you get me an assignment that I want or a decent
                    assignment someplace, I'm not willing to go.” Some year or two ahead of time, I
                    had asked to go to the Naval War College, but since I didn't have a university
                    degree, I couldn't go to the Naval War College. So, in comes a cable: “Would you
                    be willing to go to the National War College (which is more prestigious) in
                    September? If so, reply to us promptly.” So, I go back and I tell Josephine
                    about this. We were dancing, we were happy. I sent a cable back. I go back and I
                    spend one of the nicest, most pleasant years I spent in the Foreign Service. I
                    learned a lot. It was good for me. I downsized, I relaxed, spent a lot of time
                    with the family. We had some great speakers. We had Vernon Walters and President
                    Ford.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were any of the military college or people you had known
                        iVietnam there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No. My closest friend at that time was a lieutenant colonel in the
                    Marine Corps by the name of Butch Neal, who is now a two star Marine general,
                    who was a Marine spokesman during the Gulf War, really a first class officer, a
                    nice guy. It was useful (later deputy commandant of the U.S. Marine Corps).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I agree. That year at the War College, I think we all find
                        that about the best year in the Foreign Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: I've got one story to tell you about that. Of course, the military
                    always thought we were champagne drinking, cookie pushing idiots. We all had to
                    jog. So, I used to jog in the morning at 7:30 or 8:00 o'clock. One day, I've put
                    on my jacket and shorts and I'm doing my jog in the snow. All these guys would
                    come by and give me the finger and everything else. I continue my jog. They were
                    all kidding me. Then just before we break for lunch when the others did their
                    job, the commanding general stands up and he says (I forget why he was there.),
                    “There is no necessity for jogging today because of inclimate weather.” I stand
                    up in a loud voice and say, “The State Department has already jogged in
                    inclimate weather” and sit down. Every single one of the military had to go out
                    and jog. I never felt so good!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a wonderful story and it's so typical of the
                        workout.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, but they were great guys. I learned a lot from them. The lectures
                    are superb. The only lady we had in our class was Barbara (Bam Bam) MacNamara,
                    who is now number two in Operations at NSA.</p>
                <p>Q: We had no women in my time. Those were the benighted days. At the end of that
                    year, you went to a different part of the world, Addis Ababa, as DCM. Was that
                    an assignment you looked forward to? How did that come about?</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: When I had left Bangkok and went to the National War College, for some
                    reason, David Korn, who was my consul general in Calcutta, wanted me to come out
                    and be his DCM. David was going to be ambassador to Mauritania, but there was
                    another Korn in the Department at that time, a political appointee, Korn. He was
                    a very Zionist Jew. Mauritania wouldn't take him. They confused the Zionist Jew
                    with my David Korn. So, that finished him. But when he was going out to
                    Mauritania, he called me up o the phone and said, “Come out and be my DCM.” I
                    said to him, “Ambassador, my function is not political.” “It will be all right.”
                    I said, “I have to worry about the children's school.” “It will all be all
                    right.” I went to the National War College. He gets Addis Ababa. I get Addis
                    Ababa. I knew that he wanted me and I wanted him. So, I went out.</p>
                <p>I'm very fortunate in that I always follow people who are not terribly
                    industrious. So, I again follow a very unindustrious number two, who goes on and
                    becomes consul general in Salzburg. So, I went out and it's Mengistu's time of
                    bloody murder, 20,000 Cubans in the country, thousands and thousands of Russian
                    advisors, Yemeni air force people up in Asmara, just littered with all types of
                    Bulgarians, Hungarians, Poles, the rest. We had a very small embassy. We had
                    three or four station people who eventually got PNGed out. We had four or five
                    State officers. We had a big communications staff. We had “listeners” and
                    others. There were about 12. There were a couple of secretaries. We had a six or
                    seven man Marine guard detail. All told, we had, I think, 28 people.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were dependents there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: With dependents. It was a great dependent post. I came in to see David.
                    He says, “I want you to report. We aren't doing enough. I can't do it all. I'm
                    glad to get rid of this idiot. I want you to really start focusing on the
                    African embassies because my predecessor did not focus, didn't do anything. He
                    did the British, the French, the Italians, and the Germans.” So, I do that and I
                    start to pick up contacts. The British had a really excellent embassy there.
                    Ambassador Barber. The second man's name was David Bowman, later chief of
                    Protocol at the FCO [Foreign and Commonwealth Office]. The Germans had a good
                    embassy. For some reason, David did not get along with the French. I think it
                    was because the French did not like the fact that David spoke French so well (He
                    was a graduate of the Sorbonne), and because he was not terribly good with the
                    charg� or ambassador. They weren't entirely open with David. David was cold. He
                    can turn into ice. So, I had that. So, I did just a whopping amount of
                    reporting. It was so much reporting that Josephine was very upset with me at
                    times because I spent hours and hours at the embassy. We all lived on the
                    compound. I was about 30 yards from the house. It was just terrible amount of
                    time that was required for political reporting.</p>
                <p>Mengistu had also East Germans there, with whom I became very close. I became
                    close with three groups: the East Germans, the Chinese, and the Russians on that
                    side, which the security people even now bitterly ask me about. Here we had the
                    problem. We have a station which was good, has some good contacts, and we don't
                    have any overt reporting. So, I go on and start doing all this. To be honest,
                    you could be out every night in the week there. I was out five nights a week and
                    one night we'd entertain. Josephine's cooking and friendliness were a real
                    asset. So, we start to get this reporting. I do the writing of it. David does
                    the rewriting, writing, rewriting. But we turned into a fabulous team. Pretty
                    soon, David and I know as much about what's going on in that town than all the
                    other embassies combined.</p>
                <p>We find out a number of things. One, the Russians did not get along well with
                    Mengistu. Mengistu loves the East Germans. But the East Germans [look down on
                    him]. Mengistu hates the Americans because when he was in training in the United
                    States, people treated him [condescendingly like a black American]. He's not a
                    nigger. He's not a Negro. He's not an African. He is an Ethiopian. It's a
                    mindset. It's terrible for our relations, but we understand it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Mengistu ever receive David Korn?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Oh, yes, he received me, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, good.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: He had a good foreign minister, a good deputy, Ato Bekele. He had good
                    people. When we were there, he was okay. He had a nice wife. She was very, very
                    religious. She could sort of break on his more erratic and murderous moods.</p>
                <p>Let me tell you a story about Mengistu. Mengistu is the son of an imperial lord.
                    The father took extremely good care of him, saw that he went to a good military
                    academy, arranged for his training in the United States, took care of his
                    mother. This kid (Mengistu) had it going for him, not withstanding the fact
                    that, by our standards he was illegitimate. When he comes to power, he is the
                    chairman. His father dies. (After Haile Selassie was killed, Mengistu buried his
                    bones under his office and has killed hundreds of thousands of others more,
                    including one of his ministers in a cabinet meeting. This was a bad boy.) His
                    father dies. A man of honor, a man who was loyal to his emperor, etc. So, they
                    have a great funeral for his father. His wife goes to the funeral. He doesn't.
                    He sits off in a car nearby. The funeral goes on for hours as the people praise
                    the honor, the nobility of his father, everybody knowing that the son is sitting
                    out there and he's hearing this, knowing that in praising the father, they
                    condemn him. He couldn't do anything because Mengistu knew as the people were
                    praising his father, they were never going to say anything like that about him.
                    They never did.</p>
                <p>Another story: Josephine goes out to do the shopping. This tells you about
                    Russian- Ethiopian relations. She goes around to all the stores and she
                    complains to me that she's always being followed. So, I say, “Are they bothering
                    you?” “No, they're following me.” So, I go and I see Lev Mironov, who was the
                    deputy at the Russian embassy and later the ambassador there. I said, “Look,
                    we've done business together. When my Marines caused a problem, we settled it
                    out. When one of your people caused a problem, we settled it out. We've
                    exchanged information. I've never lied to you. Now I have a real problem. People
                    are following my wife. You know my wife. She's been here in your embassy. You've
                    been to my house. She is not involved in this business.” He says, “I know.” “So,
                    why are you doing this?” “Because I've been told to.” So, I said, “It upsets
                    her.” He said, “Why don't you tell your wife that these people are only for her
                    protection and that's it. Then Lev said, “When my wife goes down to shop, she
                    doesn't have any bodyguards and they spit at her and the other ladies of this
                    embassy.” [The Ethiopians] hated [the Russians]. They called them “poor
                    Americans, poor white trash.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is in Ethiopia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: This is in Ethiopia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Run by Mengistu.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Run by Mengistu.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And supported by the Russians.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: And supported by the Russians. It again shows the relations. The East
                    German Stasi, absolutely first class. The deputy head of their mission was
                    Stasi. I knew him very well. While we were there, around Christmas, David Korn
                    is not in the country. He's gone back to see the family.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in charge.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I was in charge. The Stasi catch one of our CIA agents with his hand in
                    the pocket book. I mean, catch him with people. Regrettably, this agent without
                    any physical coercion but to save his own ass, this American rolls up the rest
                    of the organization, gives it away. We don't know that he's been captured. All
                    we know is he's disappeared. I hear but I don't know that he's been picked up.
                    This is when the Agency and State worked really the best I've ever seen in my
                    life, not because I'm involved, but we really worked correctly. I went over and
                    saw the two CIA guys. I'd give you their names, except they're still active. I
                    say, “What are we going to do?” So, we sit down. I said, “I will go down to the
                    Foreign Office and say that's he's missing, that he's been on the booze, and
                    he's having trouble with his wife and that he's sleeping with somebody else. We
                    can't find him.” We don't want to turn the guy in. We'd like to have him back
                    before David comes back and maybe save his career. The Foreign Office says,
                    “Don't know a damn thing about it.” They really didn't know a damn thing about
                    it. So, we start making all sorts of inquiries. I start some messages back to
                    the Department. Every message I send back to the Department I immediately tell
                    the Agency the State number. When they send their message back, they tell me the
                    number so we are able to keep each of our own sides informed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you're coordinating.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Coordinating. We had a disagreement about how to handle it. I can't
                    remember what the disagreement was. I think it was modalities. We both reported
                    exactly the differences we had in both our channels. Finally, I'm out at some
                    party and I see the Minister of Justice. I say to him, “Look, we are having some
                    really terrible problems about this. We know you've got him.” I don't know that.
                    He might be dead in a ditch. He minister says, “Yes.” I say, “It's time that we
                    get this thing settled out. You have to pass this to Mengistu.” So, I go back
                    and tell the charg�, David Korn. The Ethiopians because they won't talk to us
                    tell the Israelis in Nairobi that they have the CIA agent. President Reagan
                    sends General Vernon Walters, who was in Africa at that time, to go to Ethiopia
                    and get the agent. This is the first time that I met General Walters.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The famous general.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: By this time, David is back. So, we go out to the airport to see our
                    friend, General Walters. The first time I've seen him. This great hulk of a man,
                    obviously with gout, comes lumbering off the plane, flops in a car, and we go up
                    to the embassy, and we say, “What are you going to say to Mengistu?” “The
                    President of the United States wishes to have back Mr. Timothy Wells,” who was
                    the officer who they picked up. His name is no longer classified [Goshu Wolde].
                    We said, “What else?” “Nothing more.” We go down and see the Foreign Minister.
                    Walters says the same thing. Our friend Mengistu is up in Asmara because he's
                    having military problems up there, [needs] to put some spine in some of his
                    soldiers. So, we have to fly our friend, General Walters, up there. David goes
                    up. I stay in Addis Ababa. Mengistu wants to negotiate. Walters has no
                    instructions to negotiate. His instructions are to bring him back, nothing more.
                    That's all he has to say. “My instructions from the President of the United
                    States are to bring back Mr. Wells.” Mengistu gives him a three hour lecture on
                    Ethiopian history. Walters goes back to Addis, decides he will not sleep in
                    Addis, but he'll go back to Nairobi and sleep in Nairobi. He sleeps in Nairobi.
                    We get a message saying that General Walters should come back the next day and
                    get Wells. So, we get Wells. But then they PNG the whole station. The whole
                    station is gone. I remember how this all happened because I was at dinner with
                    the Finnish charg� and I get a call. I've got to go to the embassy. So, I leave
                    the dinner and go to the embassy. I'm told to put our staff aboard a Lufthansa
                    flight. I go to Lufthansa and I (You understand how much I had to pay for this)
                    ask Lufthansa to delay a flight. For Lufthansa to delay a flight is sort of like
                    asking God to put the world on hold.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Germans are very punctual.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Raised to let the sun set in the west and rise in east or something. I
                    have no idea. So, I get them to hold the plane for about 45 minutes. We get them
                    out. It was just miserable. The whole station was wiped out - every single
                    person.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How had they captured this fellow?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: The Stasi was very good and they had obviously been following him or
                    following somebody involved in his cell and they raided the house and they
                    caught him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they turned him over to the Ethiopians.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: The Stasi were never visible. We never, to the best of my knowledge, saw
                    a white face. But they did it. I know because the East German who was-</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They trained Mengistu's bodyguards, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, they did. Before this, there was another man at the East German
                    embassy who, just after I had come in, started to spread a lot of very bad news
                    about [me], specifically that I was chief of station, and that I was involved in
                    all sorts of shenanigans. I went and saw David. The next day was going to be an
                    East German national day. We would go. If he would go, I would go. David who
                    hated these things with a purple passion said to me, “You go and you tell the
                    East Germans that you're coming, you're going to stay for a few minutes, and
                    leave, and why.” So, I did this. I embellished on it. I said that “I personally
                    will have nothing to do with any member of your embassy as long as he's here.”
                    Within months, he was gone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did they hold our man? Was it a matter of
                        weeks?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Weeks, probably as much as a month. It was a mess because he
                    disappeared, his wife was around. She's still in the Agency, by the way, under
                    her maiden name. His girlfriend was around, I believe, pregnant, though I can't
                    recall. When he comes back, he's with his wife and he gets her pregnant. It was
                    “Peyton Place,” a real repugnate situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Talk a little bit about the famine in Ethiopia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: In '83, we had no AID mission in Ethiopia for political reasons and for
                    aid reasons, aid reasons being that AID did not believe there was any need for
                    it. There were a number of NGOs and they were doing some work: mother healthcare
                    primarily. We were providing some small stuff. Since there was no AID officer
                    there, I was the AID officer. I would sign all the necessary papers to get stuff
                    in. But it also gave me an excuse to travel because I wouldn't let the food in
                    unless I could see it. I used that reason through my whole more than three years
                    in the country. So, that all went along. There was a deep dispute in Washington.
                    On the AID side, was a man by the name of Francis Xavier Ready, who said we
                    should not give any food at all to Ethiopia regardless of the famine because all
                    we would be doing is to support Mengistu and his people because even if they
                    didn't use the food, other food would be used by him. So, all we were doing in
                    one way or another was feeding the Ethiopian army, which was not [in our] best
                    interests.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was not a State position, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: There was no common position across AID, State, and CIA. There was no
                    one group being for it and one group being against it. I, who had served in
                    Calcutta and was in Vietnam - was used to seeing dead bodies and famine and all
                    the rest, was upset by what I was seeing. I knew what was going to happen
                    because they were starting to eat their seed grain. David had me write an
                    “O'Neillgram,” which in effect was very stark. “We can tell how bad things are
                    because the children are dying. The children have red hair. The women are
                    self-aborting and many women have decided not to have children. The water is
                    dirty. Communications are bad. Humanity deserves-”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are we talking about one region?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, it all began up north in what is now Eritrea. It was a disaster.
                    Then, if anything was grown, one side or the other would steal it. So, we had
                    this very difficult problem. David for moral reasons because he was a very moral
                    person, and I because of maybe a mixture of morality and politics, or because I
                    couldn't see any utility of letting people die... Ronald Reagan, the great
                    conservative, said, “We do not make foreign policy on the bodies of women and
                    children.” So, that broke it out. But they eventually had to get rid of Francis
                    Xavier Ready, who was a political appointee, he was made the ambassador to
                    Equatorial Guinea.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>You'll appreciate the humor of this because that was the last TDY post I ever
                    had. I closed down Equatorial Guinea. I'll give you a story about this. Senator
                    Kennedy comes out with his children, a man whose politics I don't like, but who
                    I like as a human being. He takes his boy who has lost his leg and his daughter,
                    who is a very smart, tough, intelligent young lady, up to Mekele. We arrived in
                    Mekele a little late, but on time for the Kennedys. We stand out there with a
                    Jesuit, who was at that time head of the Catholic Charities, the only decent
                    person I ever saw running Catholic Charities. You heard this horrible moan and
                    the wind comes sweeping down the mountain. The temperature had to have been 10
                    degrees Fahrenheit. It was about 6:00 pm. The weather was so cold that refugees
                    were huddled and the Kennedy boy started to cry. A tear falls down his face. The
                    tear froze on his face. God bless him, Kennedy; he came back and helped to move
                    more food in that area. Mickey Leland came out later, but was all show. He had
                    with him a black congressman from the first district of Philadelphia (Gray), who
                    had a mind like a computer. He was a brilliant man. He left the Congress, I'm
                    sorry. He went to take over the United Negro Fund. He did a tremendous job in
                    getting more food out. It was terrible. But there were, again, because of
                    personal relations, things that could be done then without regard to politics.
                    We were trying to get food into an area. We had the food, the Russians had the
                    plane, and the Poles had the helicopters. We also got a couple of DC-3s. There
                    were the four of us. We went around. David did not do it. He sent me to do it. I
                    say, “What can you do” and Fracher from AID and Machmaer from AID. We did do
                    this. The Poles would spot the area with helicopters. We supplied the gasoline
                    for the Russian aircraft and all of us delivered food. A small thing, I told Lev
                    Mironov at that time the reason why Lev and I should be friends was that
                    sometime in the future there was going to be some really bad problem and there
                    would have to be a bridge and we would solve it. I said, “The chances of our
                    countries ever being friends in our lifetime is nil.” Of course, look at us
                    today. We're friends. The politics were horrible because Mengistu killed people.
                    He killed some of his best generals.</p>
                <p>The papal nuncio there, Monsignor Thomas White, always cheated at tennis. It was
                    his great flaw in life. He cheated at tennis. Anyway, he had great information
                    and managerial experience in refugee matters there.</p>
                <p>The other thing was that even the Poles and the rest wanted to talk and they
                    wanted to talk in a manner in which they wouldn't get their ass in trouble. So,
                    at these big cocktail parties, I did as much work as I did in the office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What you're telling me is that we have to combat this
                        iconjunction with people who we considered our enemies at the time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Absolutely. We did more because we had all the food. Let me also say
                    that Mengistu and some of his crew stole millions of tons and made lots of money
                    out of it. Francis Xavier Ready was right: we did help the government. It was
                    our own choice. We wanted to feed them. It's just awful.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it during this period that Congressman Leland was
                        killed ithat crash?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, that was five or six years later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we give any assistance to getting the Jews (Falashas)
                        out oEthiopia into Israel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. That was again that horrible person, Lou Goelz, who was now deputy
                    assistant secretary of State. There was a Jewish organization whose name I won't
                    mention because they still do work like this (and I'm not talking about Mossad)
                    who also had people in Ethiopia, in Addis, who I knew well. They wanted to get
                    people out, but to get people out through the airport, they had to have a visa
                    to go someplace. My feeling was “Let's give them a visa, but let's give them a
                    real visa with a fraudulent number on it.” We've got A visas and B visas and L
                    visas and all. “Let's give them (because we didn't have that type of visa) an X,
                    Y, Z visa. So, if they have this visa, then they can leave. They can get their
                    exit permit.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did this to show Ethiopian authorities.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Right. They had no intentions of going to the United States. They were
                    not getting a visa which they would use to enter the United States legally. They
                    were getting a “visa” to nowhere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That would get them out of the country.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Right. I sent this information back to Washington and Lou Goelz goes
                    through the goddam roof. I never got another job in the consular cone after
                    that. He wrote that such an issuance would violate the integrity of the visa.
                    What we had to do eventually was to give a visa to go out with the assurance
                    that these people would fly to the United States and then go back to Israel. It
                    shows you how-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean from Ethiopia to the U.S. and back to
                        Israel?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. It goes to show the weird stupidity of this. Lou had served on the
                    border in Mexico. He had served in Iran and given thousands of visas to Iranians
                    who were not eligible to enter the United States. He goes and gives us this
                    trouble. We help with the Falashas by going up into Gondar, where they were. I
                    made half a dozen trips up into Gondar. One time, the governor of the province
                    beat up one of my local employees. Fortunately, I was traveling with Senator
                    DeConcini and Senator Trible. I immediately met with these two senators and
                    protested immediately to the governor. I told her, “We're going to protest.
                    We're going to see Mengistu.” But they had a nut up there as head of security, a
                    man who was sent out on a regular basis to East Germany to get his head screwed
                    on right. It was bad. We would go up into the villages. I will say about the
                    Falashas that I did make one mistake, an egregious one. I didn't know they were
                    so many. I thought they were in the many thousands. I didn't think they were in
                    the tens of thousands. I was off by a significant number.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Israelis know how many there were?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, they did not know how many they were because they were constantly on
                    me to find out how many there were. I don't think it became obvious how many
                    there were until we got up into the late 1980s.</p>
                <p>Q: You often wonder, if they knew how many they were, whether they would have
                    been so eager to take them all in, where they were having a tough time
                    assimilating.</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: You know, believe it or not, they had an easier time assimilating the
                    Ethiopian Jews, the Ethiopian Falashas, than assimilating some of the ones from
                    Morocco and some of them who have just recently come out from the Soviet Union.
                    The Ethiopian Falashas have turned out to be excellent soldiers and border
                    guards and things like that. They are still discriminated against because of
                    their color. We have a friend who is an Ethiopian-Amharic who recently visited
                    Israel. She said that many of the children cannot speak Amharic anymore. They
                    only speak Hebrew. She said some of the older people are starting to lose it.
                    She said that sometimes it's difficult for them, but she noted, “My son has
                    trouble when he goes down to Georgetown because he's half Amhara, half
                    American.”Q: Well, it will work out. I remember, when I was in Israel, we had
                    only a few of them there and they were having a tough time then.</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Now there are more.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then they brought in thousands.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: And now they're a voting block. There's nothing like thballot to make
                    people sit up and take notice.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any more comments about your time there? Tell us about
                        this TDyou had in Djibouti.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: That was after I finished Ethiopia. Let me say this about the Cubans
                    down in Ogaden. When I was there towards '86, they had been turned into beer
                    soldiers. They were selling their weapons, shoes, and clothes for beer, the
                    Cubans. They had really deteriorated. One, they weren't being paid much. The
                    other thing is that in looking at the time that we were in Ethiopia, the Amharas
                    as a tribe were the dominant tribe. They were the ones who provided the kings or
                    the emperors. This is no more. We can go back and talk about when I was in
                    Eritrea. There were any number of times when the Emperor, Haile Selassie, or
                    Mengistu could have made some equitable solution with the Eritreans for a united
                    country. But Mengistu was not a rational man. I think, by the time we got there,
                    he was slipping slowly but surely into a state of mental imbalance. He was only
                    interested in people who didn't have the guts to tell him the truth. I only met
                    him once one on one. I used special English when I have to talk to certain
                    people because while he spoke English, he didn't particularly like it. He didn't
                    like to speak English. He understood all the sayings. He also thought I was CIA
                    and wondered why I wasn't thrown out. I said, “Maybe because you wanted to have
                    an embassy in Washington.” Of course, that was not the reason. That was pure
                    bragging on my part.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It had its effect.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: It had its effect. The question of Mengistu's mental competenc- (He's
                    alive, by the way, still in exile in Zimbabwe) he killed without feeling.</p>
                <p>As for Djibouti, I'd come back to Washington and I went up to see Jim Bishop. We
                    were very lucky at that time. We had the greatest front office in the Africa
                    Bureau. We had Crocker, Wisner, and Jim Bishop, fabulously great guys. So, I had
                    gone up to see Jim Bishop to say “Mea culpa” because I had gone to Frank Wisner
                    and told him after Addis I wanted to go to Khartoum and be the DCM not knowing
                    that Frank did not do personnel work, never has, never will, not terribly
                    interested in it even for his own people. Even with our Vietnam association. So,
                    I went and said, “I really should come and see you. I'm sorry I didn't do it.
                    What can you do for me?” He said, “Tough, baby, I don't have anything for you.
                    But I need somebody to go out TDY to Djibouti.” I said, “My French is rusty. I
                    haven't used it since Vietnam, but I'll be very happy to go out.” He said,
                    “Alright, you go on out because the ambassador is being called back to the
                    United Nations for three or four months.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Djibouti was now independent?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. So, I went out for three months. They had a big problem down at the
                    port over AID food. Things weren't being moved. The AID guy there, his mind was
                    not really between his ears. It was resting someplace else. We had one fellow at
                    the station. They were trying to build a new embassy, etc. So, I went out. I
                    cleaned up the AID portion of the thing and then started to do some small
                    reporting on Somalia, helped with the administrative stuff, did some reporting
                    on Ethiopia from that side of the border, and made myself somewhat useful. The
                    Ethiopians were kind enough seeing that I returned from Washington to increase
                    staff in their embassy. It was just very nice. I told them how much I enjoyed my
                    time in Addis and told them what I was going to do only three or four months. It
                    was useful for the future. Later on, I was involved in Somalia. I was involved
                    in Eritrea. It's not a big place. I went out and saw the Legionnaires, who were
                    very, very, very well disciplined, but I saw them play among themselves: mean
                    mothers. Of course, Djibouti is really sort of like Shanghai in the '30s. There
                    is nothing that's not for sale there. It's great working. I'd get up about 5:30,
                    have breakfast, work until 1:00 or 2:00, go home and have lunch, and sleep until
                    six or seven in the evening. It was so unbearably hot during [the rest of the]
                    time. At 7:00 pm, I would go out to eat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The sun was down and you could begin operating again.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Right. I improved my French and the rest. There was one very bad problem
                    there, which I solved. We had a Marine general who was in charge of CENTCOM. He
                    had come in to Djibouti, had met the French general, told him he was the senior
                    military officer in the whole area. He was not noted for his diplomatic tact. He
                    said he wanted to use Djibouti a sort of staging base and was going to take this
                    up with the president of Djibouti, Goulet, who is still, by the way, in power.
                    He must be 90 if he's a day. He went off and he saw Goulet. He made all these
                    promises. He didn't clear it with DOD. He didn't clear it with State. He didn't
                    clear it back with anyone. The Djiboutians don't know what's going on. The
                    French believe that we are going to come in and take their back door, which
                    Djibouti is for them. They need Djibouti because they don't have “long legs.”
                    They have “short legs” and they need to refuel in Djibouti for Tahiti, Reunion,
                    for all the other places they have along East Africa and in the Pacific. So, I
                    come in. The first thing I do after seeing the foreign minister is go running
                    over to see the French ambassador, Ambassador Thomas. I tell him how pleased I
                    am to be here. I tell him how my son, Kevin, speaks French with a French accent
                    because he went to lyc�e in Addis Ababa and he's now at the Lyc�e Rochambeau in
                    Washington because I don't want him to lose his French, which, thank God, he
                    never has. Then I say things like “You know, when I'm here, I will do nothing
                    with this government without talking to you first. I'm going to see the foreign
                    minister. I'll be seeing the president when he returns. I don't intend to see
                    very many of the local politicians because I'm waiting just for our ambassador
                    to return. I ask the ambassador, “Do you and your army ever have generals who
                    talk before they think?” He said, “Occasionally.” I said, “You know, we have
                    them in the Marine Corps.” That was the end of that. Then I found out from our
                    people in Paris that he had sent back saying, “They've got a new officer here.
                    He speaks French and he seems to know the area. He's been very helpful and has
                    told me all about Ethiopia and what Washington is thinking.” Ambassador Thomas,
                    a very fine guy, very nice.</p>
                <p>What was luck of the draw was his political officer, who was married to a
                    Thai/Vietnamese girl. So, she was a little lonely there. She spoke excellent
                    French, of course. She had nobody to speak Thai with. So, we went to a dinner
                    one night and we started to speak Thai. We spoke for a few minutes. Then we
                    spoke French. She also spoke English. Then I would say to her, “What's the exact
                    phrase in French for this?” I would ask in Thai and she would say it. We had a
                    wonderful time. By the time the ambassador returned, the question over us
                    storing things in Djibouti had gone. We had started the first (not in my time,
                    but about six months later) agreement in which we kept the French informed, that
                    we would bring in our observation planes to refuel in Djibouti so they could
                    watch Russian submarines coming down the Red Sea after they had been refueled at
                    Dalak Island.</p>
                <p>Q: I think that's one of the most astute things you did in your service was to
                    call on that French ambassador first thing because he would have found out
                    immediately what you were going to do and he would have resented it.</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Absolutely. I did the same thing when I was in Equatorial Guinea. The
                    Spanish prefer that you always tell them what's going on. They always know more
                    than you do about certain things. After they trust you, they'll tell you
                    everything.</p>
                <p>Q: Did we get involved at all in refugees from Yemen when you were there in
                    Djibouti?</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No. By that time, the civil war in Yemen had quieted down. All the
                    people who had been picked up by the Britannia and the rest had been moved on.
                    The British had an honorary consul there who was in charge of one of the British
                    banks there, who I had met on a previous trip down there, who was very nice. It
                    was good. I didn't do a lot of in-depth reporting out of there, but nothing fell
                    apart while I was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After your tour in Djibouti, you came back to Washington
                        anbecame an inspector?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the chief of the Inspection Corps at the
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: It was a civilian. He had just come in and he just retireabout a year
                    ago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not Bill Harrop?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, he was the first outsider. Good guy. I really worked for Ambassador
                    Ed DeJarnette and Ambassador Walker. So, I worked for those two.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you a program or administrative inspector?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Consular.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where? Did you travel overseas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, I did all the Scandinavian countries, Spain, Portugal,Jordan,
                    Cyprus, Greece, Kuwait, Bahrain, and maybe one other.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, you got to see some places where you hadn't been.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. But most of it was sort of cut and dry though. At one time, I was
                    pulled off inspection and went to a country which is not named here to tell an
                    ambassador that it was time to go home, time to leave the service. He had
                    started to become an imperial ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he a career man?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. He had enough years in. It was regrettable. When I came out and
                    talked to him, he fairly well knew what was going on. I said, “Your assignment
                    is coming up soon. Why don't you just pack it in? It's better for everybody.” He
                    agreed. He said, “Well, anyway, I have an onward job. I think I'll take that.” I
                    said, “Alright. In that case, why don't we assume that this conversation, for
                    all practical purposes, never took place? You don't sign any papers. I don't
                    sign any papers. I just came up to ask you about morale in the embassy.” He
                    said, “Does any of my staff know about this?” I said, “The only one who knows is
                    your private secretary and I'm sure she will say nothing; and the regional
                    security officer who I have not told completely the truth.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Inspection Corps effective in your point of
                        view?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: The Inspection Corps today are headhunters. Let me caveat this. I
                    recently had problems with the Inspector General's Corps. I'll mention it in
                    brief. I went down to Bermuda. I took my son with me at my own expense because I
                    was on TDY. I couldn't bring a car, couldn't bring anything. My son came down
                    with me because he was having some personal problems. Everybody knew about it.
                    He came down. He lived with me. I sent him to school. I paid the fees. But he
                    went to school in an embassy vehicle, which was on the way to pick up mail and
                    would pick him up when it went down to deliver the rest when school was
                    over.</p>
                <p>Q: It would have gone whether he went to school or not.</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. [But the IG became] all upset about it. I pointed out that when I
                    used the embassy car for other business, private business, I always paid my own
                    and always paid the people. They wanted 45 days without pay and $1,000. I fought
                    them and won on all counts. But it was two years that interfered with ongoing
                    assignments and caused a number of other problems. Officers who are currently in
                    the Foreign Service Inspector Corps who are career officers say that they have
                    some pressure to catch officers. The old Foreign Service inspectors was
                    regrettably not good either. You put a guy in there for a couple of years either
                    to reward him, punish him, or to wait for a new assignment. They didn't do the
                    things they were supposed to. So, there has to be a balance. I think it's right
                    that we have an outsider running the Inspector General's Corps, I really do. But
                    I think it's got to be focused; I think that we should stop looking for nickels
                    and dimes. Everybody knows to be careful about them. I wish it would start using
                    a little bit of common sense. Otherwise, it will mean all sorts of problems.</p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've been wondering for some time if it was worth the
                        money angreater manpower.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: You have to do it because the Senate wants it done. I think it should be
                    done because there are still idiots out there who take advantage of their TDY,
                    their education allowances. Regrettably, with the pressure on visas, there are
                    going to be problems with the visa issuing process. Just imagine that we had
                    somebody in Buenos Aires that was issuing visas to Koreans to come to the United
                    States when the Korean population in all of Argentina is less than the number of
                    visas issued. We had an officer who was out on one of the islands doing the same
                    thing for Chinese. These things can be done, but we should never leave anyone in
                    Manila issuing visas on the line for more than a year. Then do six months and
                    break them up. If we have lines out there 10 miles long, that's their problem,
                    not ours.</p>
                <p>Q: That's right. Jamaica, Manila, Mexico City, Dominican Republic, many places
                    like this. Do you have any comments that you'd like to make about your time in
                    the Inspection Corps?</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: One, I learned a lot. I learned how not to do things. I think the reason
                    that the three posts I had after that, each one of them got superior marks for
                    administrative work and internal controls, because I had done that. The other
                    thing is, I was able to sit in and watch how ambassadors didn't take care of
                    their people and to watch how important it is to have a good DCM. If you don't
                    walk to the embassy, if you don't walk into the kitchens, and you don't walk
                    into the communications sections, don't pick up your own traffic, you know
                    garbage. You don't know a thing. You're operating in the blind. People were very
                    annoyed with me when I was in Khartoum and again in Addis Ababa. I would walk in
                    and inspect the kitchens, look at the stoves, complain and bitch about it, and
                    make the medical officers go in and inspect them, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Speaking of Khartoum, that's where you went next after
                        your timin the Inspection Corps. Did you go as DCM?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I went as DCM. I worked for Jim Cheek. Jim Cheek replaceKorn in Addis
                    Ababa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did this eventuate? Did you ask for this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I had always wanted to go to Khartoum. So, I lobbiefairly strenuously
                    for it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It seems to me that you had nothing but hot posts and you
                        wantethe hottest, I guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: If you're going to try to be good at something, you have to stay there.
                    So, I had three years in Addis. I had a few months in Djibouti. I had been
                    following Khartoum, Sudan, had always wanted to go there. So, now it came up. I
                    arrived, again fortuitously, at a really interesting time. There was a whole
                    change of government. Saddiq el-Mahdi had just been overthrown by General
                    Bashier, who nobody knew.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Our embassy didn't know him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Didn't know him. We had a terrible ambassador there before Ambassador
                    Cheek. He went to every party. He spoke beautiful Arabic. He didn't know what
                    the hell was going on. He was caught entirely by surprise. I remember coming in
                    and being there a week. I went through the embassy and went through the
                    commissary and went through the rest. I went in and saw a USAID officer in the
                    consular section, saw her near tears. I said, “What's wrong?” She said, “You
                    know, we're $85,000 in debt.” I said, “Did the DCM know about this?” “I sent him
                    the figures.” “Has anybody talked to him?” “No.” I'm talking about the previous
                    DCM. “Did anybody talk to the ambassador?” “No.” So, I do a sweep through the
                    embassy. I find fire hazards, things not in order. I pull out index cards and
                    say, “It says you're supposed to have 85 widgets here. I only counted 20
                    widgets. A literal mess.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Run by an American supervisor?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, who was very lucky because he got promoted just as I arrived on
                    board and who left shortly after I arrived. He wanted to extend. Wouldn't let
                    him. So, I went up and saw the ambassador. I wrote this all out. I said, “Look,
                    this is what I'm sending down to the administrative officer. I want you to see
                    it. I'm not going to give you a copy because I think, eventually, they'll come
                    and complain, but I don't want you to be blindsided.” He read it and said, “What
                    am I going to do?” I said, “I don't know, but we've got inspectors coming out
                    here. I don't know what you want to do.” He said, “Do you think I should stay on
                    for the inspectors?” I said, “Sir, you don't have a DCM here who is responsible.
                    Your old DCM is gone. So, he can't be blamed for it because he's gone. You will
                    be blamed for it. I suggest you leave a little bit earlier than planned, as
                    you've done your three years. I'll hang on to the post for three or four weeks
                    when the new ambassador comes in. I know he's ready to come.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had we named one already?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, Jim Cheek. We had named one already. This guy was ohis way out. I
                    said, “Leave on time or early.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before the inspectors get here?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Before the inspectors. So, what happens? I try to get this thing in
                    order and we find out a whole pile of things. One, there has been a revaluation
                    of the local currency. The administrative officer had “forgotten” to mention it
                    to the allowance division. [Furthermore], people had gone on home leave while
                    still getting their 25% in the States, had gone on annual R&amp;R leave in the
                    States and still gotten their 25%. I again tell the former ambassador. He says,
                    “What am I supposed to do?” I said, “Well, if you're involved in this, if you
                    have gone on leave to the States and still taken the 25%, then I suggest you
                    give it back immediately.” He said, “Well, I'm too high grade to get 25%
                    anyway.” I forget how it all worked. Eventually, the inspectors came in and
                    fortunately for Jim Creek and myself, I've got all this documented: letters down
                    to saying “You can't do this.” The administrative officer went home and never
                    served overseas again. The DCM and other officers had to give money back. It's
                    funny: the DCM went on to be ambassador, and has gone on to be ambassador a
                    second time. It shows you, unless the inspectors catch you while you're on
                    post... It's regrettable. Eventually, like I say, Jim Cheek and I came out of
                    that smelling like a rose.</p>
                <p>But then again, as we come along, I start to meet the Islamic fundamentalists by
                    happenstance. I still haven't got any idea how it all happened, though I give a
                    lot of credit to Bob Downey, who was, regrettably, for only a short period of
                    time my chief of the Political Section. He then went on to Lagos, an absolutely
                    fantastic officer. I start to meet them and then I start to meet the more high
                    ranking ones. I start going out to the mosques on Friday night after prayers to
                    eat “fritur” and drink warm goat's milk. We had a deal. If I went to the mosque,
                    we did not talk politics regarding Sudan and the United States. You'd talk about
                    politics involving Russia, England, literature, anything. So, I got to know them
                    very, very well. I got to know Hassan el-Turabi very, very well. I wrote
                    countless cables on him. I wrote what is, I think, the definitive bio on him
                    that's still in the Department. I got down south to-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get into troubled regions?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Oh, yes. In fact, toward the end of my assignment (I don't want this to
                    sound like a braggart) I had become very influential within Islamic fundamental
                    society. They knew that whatever I told them was the truth. When Hassan El
                    Turabi was beaten up in Canada by some Sudanese, I found out because the chief
                    of intelligence, Nafi Ali Nafi, called me over to his office and asked if this
                    had happened. I said I hadn't heard about it. He said, “How much information can
                    you find out?” So, I went back and I sent a NIACT to Washington and to Ottawa,
                    saying, “Could you please advise?” Then they advised. I went back and I told
                    Nafi. Then they finally got their communications going. All they had was one
                    officer in Ottawa, who was not at the office that day, that week, that month.
                    They were very grateful for all the help. I cannot tell you how happy I was to
                    get the news that it did not take place in the United States, though now there
                    is a conspiracy theory that the CIA arranged to have Turabi beaten in Canada
                    rather than the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Our friends are always willing to help us with those
                        theories.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Right. The other part of this thing was that Turabi wanted to go to the
                    States. Our embassy in Cairo did not want him to get a visa. I fought
                    strenuously that he get the visa, both on consular grounds and political
                    grounds. Frank Wisner was the ambassador in Cairo when this was going on.
                    Finally, we got the visa. But then there was another visa issue to the Sheikh
                    Abdel Rachman, the fellow who was involved in the blowing up of the World Trade
                    Center. That was issued by a member of the Central Intelligence Agency in
                    Khartoum by mistake. We've been suffering from it ever since. The Agency [and
                    maybe others] knew that he was traveling in the area looking for a visa and
                    never told us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: His name should have been in lookout books and everything
                        else.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Anybody who knows that area knew who Sheikh Rachman was. He had been
                    acquitted of complicity in the murder of Sadat. That name should have shown up
                    like a shot. But we had, in the consular section an FSN, a Christian from the
                    south who didn't recognize the name, didn't go to the lookout book, whatever. I
                    can't tell you what a terrible thing it is that that had happened. It was
                    atrocious. It happened when I was the charg�.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember reading in the paper that he got his visa in
                        thAmerican embassy in Khartoum.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: There was another one. Then, of course, the most difficultime was when
                    we had to evacuate the embassy during the Iraq-Kuwait war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was going to ask you about the effects of the Gulf War.
                        Sudawas on the other side there.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Sudan verbally was on the other side. Of course, our Egyptian friends
                    were doing us no help because they wanted our relations with the Sudanese to be
                    as bad as possible. Irv Hicks was the deputy assistant secretary for Africa.
                    Everybody panicked over this whole damn thing. It was, again, the Powell
                    Doctrine in place. We were having troubles in Somalia. We were just evacuating
                    Somalia over internal events. Jim Bishop was the ambassador there. Schwarzkopf
                    did not want any Marines anyplace, except near Kuwait. He didn't want to let
                    anybody there and he didn't want to let any of his troops away from the Gulf. He
                    wanted the whole bloody place evacuated so it wouldn't be necessary for him to
                    protect it. He saw as his primary duty to defeat Saddam Hussein. First of all,
                    we evacuated all the civilians, all the dependents, and some of the staff. Jim
                    Cheek decided to do this. Then he had put me in charge of making sure the place
                    was absolutely letter perfect to get out in a hurry. At the end, we could have
                    burned everything in about 10 minutes. Everything else, like EXDIS, extra
                    passports had been shipped off to Nairobi. All the bio files were shipped off to
                    Nairobi. Anything that we could. We were down to the Marines, the RSO, the U.S.
                    bodyguards, one political officer, a refugee officer, the embassy doctor, the
                    communcations section, administrative officers, and a consular officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And a station chief.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: And the station chief and his smaller crew. We were ordered to evacuate.
                    Then the question is, “Will they leave anybody behind?” So, it's decided that I
                    will stay behind, live in the ambassador's residence, and work out of the
                    British embassy. So, they bring in a New Jersey National Guard C-147 and we
                    bring out all the Americans that are left who want to go with us, all the Brits
                    and everybody else who want to go. They were all brought down to Nairobi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Leaving Joe O'Neill in Khartoum.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Leaving Joe O'Neill in Khartoum with some automatic weapons, his
                    Sudanese bodyguards, the local staff, and one administrative officer, Mike
                    Margereaux.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Living in the ambassador's residence and working out of
                        thBritish embassy.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: The residence was right across from the British embassy. It was a very
                    interesting time. I couldn't fly flags. I couldn't go around town. Allen Ramsey
                    was the British ambassador there and he took his job - of making sure nothing
                    happened to me - very, very seriously. But I was still under pressure from
                    Washington to tell them what the hell was going on around. I was really
                    constrained. Once, the British ambassador really got pissed at me for being too
                    active. In fact, he got so mad that he told me that he was thinking of having me
                    withdrawn back to Washington because he wouldn't be responsible for me
                    anymore.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to send cables using his circuits?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Only his circuits.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Through London and into Washington or directly?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, London into Washington. It was not an easy time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did this period last?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: About a month. Then the Egyptians come and tell me that the Palestinians
                    have a “contract” on me. I tell them, “Absolutely, this is not true.” Then the
                    Germans come by and say, “The Egyptians are telling me that the Palestinians
                    have a contract on you.” The Russians come by and they tell me the same
                    thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Everybody is putting a “contract” on Joe!</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: That the Palestinians have a “contract” on me. But the Russians do
                    something. I really understand why they did it. They tell Washington from Moscow
                    that they have information on a “contract” on O'Neill. So, the deputy foreign
                    minister calls in the ambassador and the DCM in Moscow late at night to the
                    foreign office. They don't know what the hell is coming off. They come in and
                    they say, “We want to tell you, we're your friend. We want to warn you that your
                    man (They give the name and the name is spelled correctly) who is working out of
                    the British embassy, even though he's got Sudanese bodyguards, is going to be
                    murdered by the Palestinians on orders of Saddam Hussein. Even though we are
                    trying to help you with Saddam Hussein by being intermediaries, we want to tell
                    you about this issue just to show you that we're your friends.” These guys went
                    charging back. NIACTS go flying all over. A call goes out to London: Tell
                    O'Neill to come back now, no ifs, ands, or buts. Get him back! So, I have time
                    only to send one cable, which I make sure I put a number of addressees on,
                    saying how bad this is. The Egyptians just did not want anybody there. We have
                    now, again, in 1998, withdrawn our embassy out of Khartoum for security reasons.
                    The French have increased the personnel at their embassy. The Egyptians are
                    there in force. The Germans are there. Everybody's there except us. We are
                    trying to lead a plot against the Sudanese. Let me make a comment about Hassan
                    El Turabi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excuse me. Did you leave then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, I had to leave. I came out and the British ambassador has
                    bodyguards, too. He doesn't use local bodyguards; he uses his own. Eight Royal
                    Military Police. They all accompany us. Again, thank God for Lufthansa. They put
                    me aboard a Lufthansa flight to Frankfurt. I never felt so protected. They
                    almost want to put me in a bullet proof vest, but I wouldn't wear one. So, that
                    went along. Allen Ramsey later becomes ambassador to Morocco, and is Sir Allen.
                    He is now retired, a great officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the Egyptians got their wish, didn't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, because they kept saying to Washington. It delayed a carrier
                    because we kept a carrier in the Red Sea longer than we should have. They kept
                    saying that the Sudanese had large numbers of surface to surface missiles, that
                    they were going to let Saddam Hussein use air bases in Sudan to bomb our ships
                    coming through. One, Saddam could not have gotten his planes down to the Sudan.
                    They don't have surface to air missiles. They didn't have surface to surface
                    missiles. [The Egyptians] kept pouring out piles of garbage. We sat there and we
                    listened to it. On the other hand, Downy replaced me. So we never officially
                    shut the embassy. And, of course, we got the full embassy up and running in late
                    April 1991</p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>Let me say one more thing showing how our friends, the Egyptians, tried to do
                    things. Just before the Iraqi-Kuwait war, a cable comes out of our embassy in
                    Cairo suggesting that there be some sort of an alliance in the Red Sea with
                    Egypt, Saudi Arabia, Yemen, and maybe Ethiopia to all work together, have like a
                    small NATO, in which the Americans would put up the money, the Egyptians would
                    put up the army and air force, and the Saudis would put up money. They would
                    then have an entity. I knew what was happening. The Egyptians wanted to suck us
                    in. But then I said, “Who are we going to fight? Israel?” If we use this, what
                    will the Egyptians suggest, that they take back control over the Sudan and the
                    waters of the Nile? I did a really terrible thing on it. I torpedoed that one.
                    You could see what President Mubarak was trying to do. He was trying to be the
                    leader with everybody else's money. He would supply some soldiers and he would
                    get the maximum political gain.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It doesn't seem to make much geopolitical sense or
                        anything else.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No. I'm surprised it ever got by Frank Wisner.</p>
                <p>Q: Any more comments about your time in Sudan? How did the people feel about
                    Americans? Were they hostile?</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, they were very friendly the further I went from Khartoum. Under
                    Nimeiri and again under the Mahdi, especially under Mahdi. President Reagan had
                    given bulgur when there was a great famine out in the west. It was called
                    “Reagan bulgur.” Everybody knew where it came from. We built a road out there.
                    We did a lot of things. Our reputation with the Sudanese is excellent. A lot of
                    their people have been educated in the United States. The other thing is, when
                    people think about Sudanese fundamentalists, they think of people on camels with
                    bloody swords charging down on Christians. Most of the senior people in the
                    government had been educated in the U.S. Turabi has a degree from the Sorbonne
                    in law and the University of London in law. His chief of intelligence, Nafi El
                    Nafi has his doctorate in microbiology from the University of California. Others
                    had been to Kansas, Tennessee, Yale, Harvard, and various universities in the
                    U.K. and Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They had been around.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They had been around. They had seen the corruption in the west and, like
                    fundamentalist Christians, want to return to the past. With them, they would
                    like to go back to the ninth, 10th, and 11th century, to the bloom and the glory
                    of Islam. They can't do it and they can't move forward.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's frustrating.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: It's frustrating for them and then it's again frustrating for us in
                    trying to put together some sort of an entity that will balance off these
                    people. The southerners are Christians, but they are divided by language, tribe,
                    and interests. They have been fighting each other long before the Muslims ever
                    got there. They are as corrupt as anyone you'll ever see.</p>
                <p>Q: The southerners.</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: The southerners. Garang, who is the “great leader of the south” was a
                    great ally of Mengistu and used his troops to kill Ethiopians on the border
                    between Sudan and Ethiopia. That's why Meles Zenawi, who is currently the
                    President of Ethiopia, and Isaias Aferke, who is currently the President of
                    Eritrea, they would do business with Turabi and some others, but not with
                    Garang. Remember, Africans are like Irish: they never forget. They remember who
                    did the murdering, the raping, the looting, and, with that, the destroying of
                    the water wells.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It doesn't bode well for other parts of Africa I can think
                        otoday either.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No. For Zaire. Anybody who thinks Kabila is a democrat forgets that one
                    of his great teachers was Che Guevara. Che Guevara worked closely with Kabila 30
                    years ago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, we forget Che Guevara and days in Africa.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After leaving Khartoum, you came back to Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, I was direct transfer to open up the embassy in Eritrea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you became the charg� in Asmara.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: That's right. One of the reasons I was made the charg� there was that
                    when Jim Cheek and I first entered Khartoum, we had other interests beyond
                    bilateral relations. Washington had finally decided that Mengistu was going to
                    lose and that Meles and Issayas were going to be the new leaders. We knew
                    nothing about them. So, Jim Cheek assigned me to start having contacts with
                    these people. So, I did. I started to have contact with all of them. In fact,
                    Isaiah was sitting in Jim Cheek's home when I walked in and told the ambassador
                    that Asmara had fallen without a shot. Issayas could not believe it, because the
                    Amharas said they would destroy it and burn it to the ground like Berlin before
                    they would give it up. Issayas said, “I don't believe it.” I went back out and
                    reconfirmed with BBC and then with the Agency. I went back there and I said,
                    “Mr. President, the Ethiopians have surrendered Asmara.” He still remembers, I
                    was the first one to call him “Mr. President.” So, one of the reasons I was sent
                    over was I didn't have an assignment and the other was that I knew the
                    President.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, you had, of course, the requisite background in the area, which was very
                    important. You were there for the independence in '93 then.</p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Again, this is where my arrogance becomes my b�te noire. There was a
                    referendum to see whether the people of Eritrea wanted to be independent or not.
                    In May, when there was an independence vote and celebration, who would recognize
                    the country? The referendum went off flawlessly. I was involved, the United
                    Nations, everybody was involved. Flawless. No cheating, no nothing. It just went
                    well. Some weeks after this, not very far after, the United Nations answers
                    itself “Completely clean. We believe the referendum was free and fair.” The
                    Italian Minister comes down from Rome and says, “We're going to recognize the
                    country today.” The president and the foreign minister say, “We're not prepared
                    to be recognized. We were going to be recognized on independence day. Everybody
                    wants to recognize us on that date.” The Italians say, “We can't give you any
                    money. If we return saying you don't want to be recognized by us, what can we
                    say in Rome?” So, the foreign minister goes hustling around and his deputy goes
                    hustling around. They say to the Sudanese, “This is what's going to happen.” The
                    Sudanese ambassador says, “I intend to recognize you. I am an ambassador with
                    plenipotentiary [powers].” The Egyptians say the same. They come to see me. They
                    say, “What are we going to do?” I said, “First of all, I'm going to have to
                    think about this. I can't do it immediately.” They said, “Alright.” So, I go
                    running back to the embassy. They came to see me at lunch in the house. I put a
                    NIACT on the wires to Washington and through Addis Ababa because I'm still de
                    jur� working for Mark Baas, but not de facto. Though I'm separated, I still
                    technically report to him. So, I send out this thing: “I know we're supposed to
                    do this. This is what I intend to do unless if pressed to the wall.” Then I
                    write out a letter which I cannot recall. It says, in effect, “The government of
                    the United States has every intention to recognize you, etc.” I send this off.
                    Then I don't get any response. I wait hours for a call. I finally get a call.
                    They said, “We just got the cable.” I said, “It's a NIACT.” They said, “Don't
                    you know the Department?” I said, “What am I supposed to do?” They said, “Well,
                    we're going to the White House.” So, I then sent out another cable saying, “The
                    Italians, the Sudanese, and the Egyptians are going to recognize. I think it's
                    incumbent upon me not to wait until we get all the papers done or we will be
                    something like the 85th country to recognize. It will cause us terrible
                    problems.” I don't have any answer. I get no answer back, no cable back. So, I
                    type up the letter and I stick it in my pocket because there is going to be a
                    ceremony at the hall to officially announce that the referendum is approved. So,
                    as we get up and start to leave, I notice the Italian ambassador has taken his
                    minister in. I start to move toward the door, trying to take with me the
                    Sudanese ambassador, who is a good friend. The Sudanese ambassador doesn't
                    really care one way or the other, but the Egyptians hang. Then we look together
                    and we decide that we can't just let the Italians and the Egyptians do this. So,
                    we wait and then the deputy foreign minister comes and says, “You'll have to
                    make your mind up.” I said, “Well, I have a letter.” I had the embassy seal on
                    it.</p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>I tell Washington what I have done. Washington was not pleased. They said that
                    they knew why I did it, they said I should not have done it; they weren't happy.
                    I would like to make a point here. Some year or two later, when my efficiency
                    reports were being reviewed, I am low ranked for exceeding instructions, though
                    Mark Baas, who is the officer who wrote the efficiency report, said I showed
                    courage, etc., as did the inspectors. It was just awful. To this day, it's a day
                    on which I recognize the government, that it stands. We're the fourth in the
                    line. Four countries recognize that day. That's why we're number four. It upsets
                    me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course. It was the delay in Washington that probably
                        causeit.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: We finally brought all the papers out. All the papers came out on May
                    15th. By that time, when we handed in the formal papers, 87 countries had
                    recognized Eritrea by that date.</p>
                <p>Q: This was, of course, in the first months of the Clinton administration. The
                    probably weren't well organized for this sort of speedy action.</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They weren't all there. They weren't organized and nobodwas willing to
                    take them on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, even though your old friend, Tony Lake, was back as
                        NSadvisor.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: He had not put his stamp on it. He hadn't gotten set up. The other thing
                    was, when I came over to Eritrea, there was more than just me coming over.
                    Hassan El Turabi started to get worried. I state this with some care. He sent a
                    message to his ambassador in Khartoum that I was to be watched very carefully
                    while I was in Eritrea because I knew them very well, I knew the Koran, the
                    politics, and that I should be considered dangerous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not friendly, but dangerous.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Dangerous. But even at that time, as long as I was in Eritrea, senior
                    Sudanese officers would come over from Khartoum by private plane to talk to me
                    and ask me to report to Washington this or that. We had a fine ambassador there,
                    Peterson, but they still kept coming to me. I had Somalis start to visit
                    also.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there for the independence day? Did we send out
                        special delegation or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, we didn't get that done. We sent out one officer, who later became
                    our ambassador, Houdek. Everybody else sent deputy heads of state, ministers,
                    the rest. We sent out one officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Ethiopians send anybody?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They sent their president, who made a great speech in Tigrean, which
                    then comes back to what we talked about before. It's now the Tigreans who are
                    the major influence in the Horn of Africa. They hold most of the influential
                    positions in Ethiopia. There are a number of tribes there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any other comments about your days as charg� there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. It was not easy. Eritreans are not easy people. We had a consulate
                    general there in the old days, a great big compound which was still there. I
                    wanted it back. It was my property. It was diplomatic property. We had bought
                    it. They said they couldn't find the papers on it. I spent $100 and somebody
                    found the papers and then put the new stamp of the new government on the papers.
                    The Minister of Defense wanted it. He's now Minister of Foreign Affairs. The
                    Eritreans wanted me there because they knew me from Sudan. They knew I was a
                    friend. They knew I had contacts. I said that I would not fly my flag, I would
                    not issue visas, and I would let no other officer be assigned me until I got my
                    consulate back. They stonewalled me. Finally, Hank Cohen came up. Hank is not
                    the most effusive character you'll ever meet. So, I briefed him on what I wanted
                    done. He had done all the things and he had talked with President Issayas. There
                    we were at lunch. I said to Cohen, “Mr. Assistant Secretary, I really would like
                    to take you around to the old consulate building, which I expect to get back,
                    but I can't get it back. If I can't get it back, that's why I didn't fly any
                    flags on the car to come and receive and why I can't ask you to stay overnight.”
                    Cohen wasn't going to stay overnight.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you couldn't ask him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: It didn't matter. Cohen wasn't staying there. The President turns to his
                    minister of defense and is very coarse. He said, “I thought we had agreed to
                    give the consulate general back.” Petros Solomon didn't say anything. Issayas
                    looked at me and said to me something. I said, “I couldn't think of a more
                    appropriate time to bring this matter up.” He said, “You'll get the consulate
                    general back.” I said, “When?” He said, “This week.” I said, “Thank you.” So, I
                    got the consulate back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was a real feather in your cap, I think, and Hank
                        must nohave forgotten that one.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Oh, he did. He forgot. But the point is, it saved the United States
                    Government in excess of $10 million. All the buildings and grounds, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever have military attach�s with you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, when I got there, I had one car and one typewriter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: That was it. I found my old chauffeur, a driver from Addis Ababa, had
                    retired in Asmara. I rehired him. Because we knew nothing about the country
                    (Nobody had been through that country in 15 years), I started to travel. This
                    was before Josephine and the children came out and even later when she was
                    there. They went home from Khartoum and then they were going to come out again.
                    I traveled all over the country. I was the first American officer in 30 years to
                    drive from Misawa to Asab through the Donakel Desert. It's called the Donakel
                    Desert. No roads, no nothing, absolutely barren.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For four wheel drive vehicles.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, we did it. It was from Misawa to Asab througDonakel. The first
                    officer to have done it in 30-odd years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Whatever happened to Kagnew Station?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: It was taken over by the Ministry of Defense, is still used by them.
                    They, I think, now have moved all the soldiers out further along to a new area.
                    But in the process of giving it up, it was a relay station, but then as
                    technology got better, we didn't need it. In addition, the Eritreans, who were
                    later my friends, were kidnaping our soldiers and shooting at us. One of the
                    things in dealing with the Eritreans is that they knew that I was traveling
                    through their areas when I was DCM in Addis Ababa, 1983-1986, with the Ethiopian
                    Army when I was moving food and doing the rest and trying to find them. They
                    knew about that. They said to me in '89 or '90, “How come your policy has
                    changed towards us? We haven't changed intrinsically.” I said to them, “Because
                    you're going to be winners and we don't back losers.” They appreciated that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I'm sure they did. Well, that came to an end;
                        youcharg�ship there. A new ambassador came out?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Houdek came out. It also was the end of my career. I became involved in
                    Somali affairs. Somalis came up to see me. The President was involved in
                    Somalia. I made TDY trips into Somalia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Out of Djibouti?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Out of Asmara. I told the Department it should never get involved in
                    this area. When we got involved, I said we should withdraw and let others take
                    over. I compared Somalia to a “poison chalice.” In fact, I wrote a cable on it:
                    “Somalia: the Poison Chalice.” I suggested we pass the poison chalice to those
                    who thought they had an antidote for it who were willing to drink it. We had
                    neither an antidote nor were willing to bear the pain. I also, which was the
                    crowning blow, wrote to the Secretary in a NODIS cable. He liked the cable. He
                    gave it the 6th floor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That did it then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: That did it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me about your TDYs to Bermuda and Equatorial Guinea,
                        twquite different places.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: And also to Bosnia. When I came back, they put me on the Somali Desk,
                    but I wasn't fit for it. I had never served in Washington. I didn't know how to
                    do these things. So, the director general had an EEO and OIG complaint in
                    Bermuda. She asked me if I would settle it out. The people in Bermuda thought I
                    was coming down for a day or two. I came down for a week, went back and said,
                    “These people are never going to get together. They have no concept of how to
                    get along. It's too small. There is one tandem couple and one secretary. It just
                    isn't going to work this way.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say it's an EEO problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes, there was an EEO problem. There was also an OIG problem. So, it was
                    the DG, Genta Hawkins, who sent me to Bermuda. It was good for personal reasons.
                    I took down my son, Kevin, with me. I found out that nobody had been doing any
                    reporting. Bermuda was in the process of voting for independence. The Governor
                    General down there, Lord Waddington, former Home Secretary for Margaret Thatcher
                    and later her leader in Lords. It was a general opinion of both of us, talking
                    about history, that in 1776, the Bermudians shipped all types of arms and
                    munitions to George Washington. In the '30s, they shipped booze to the United
                    States. We thought that two out of three was enough. We didn't want Bermuda to
                    start shipping anything else. You can sort of guess what they were going to
                    start shipping.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had a consulate general there at that time.
                        Career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, always non-career. They were in the process of holding it for a
                    non-career. So, they sent me down. I worked closely with Lord Waddington and
                    others, especially black females, in Bermuda. My comment to them was, “In
                    Bermuda, black females stand up and hold office. In Jamaica, they lie down in
                    office. Take your choice.” They knew exactly what I was talking about. Sir John
                    Swan was not happy with me. He knew I was only there for a short period of time.
                    He was the Premier. When the referendum came along, he put his own political
                    life on the line. The referendum was voted down heavily. He left. A new premier
                    came in. Then one of my friends, on whom I had written a bio (I'm terrible about
                    bios) is now the Premier. She is really a fine lady and is probably the only
                    premier or head of state who has had a bio written on her years before she got
                    there saying she was going to be it.</p>
                <p>The EEO complaint, it was quiet while I was there. To save money, they brought me
                    out six weeks before the new man got on board. In that six weeks, the whole
                    thing rose up again. So, it's now in the courts. The IG complaint I just took
                    care of. I went back to the IG and said it was “de minimus,” a non-starter.</p>
                <p>Q: Wouldn't that be something that we would have sent out a special inspector
                    for?</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They thought it could be handled and it could be as long as they were
                    not left together alone. When I was there, the gentleman did excellent work on
                    base negotiations (We were closing down a base) and on economics. His wife, who
                    was the administrative officer, kept us out of all sorts of trouble. Absolutely
                    wonderful person. I had horrible problems with my per diem from a previous post
                    or something. It was all messed up. I said to the secretary, “I don't know what
                    to do with it.” The secretary said, “Would you like me to take care of it?” I
                    said, “Yes. Here are the papers?” I asked, “What should I do with it?” She said,
                    “Do you know how to do this?” She said, “Yes.” I said, “Bring it back when it's
                    ready for my signature.” Everything worked out nicely. They just couldn't get
                    along together. They just didn't get along together.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned a military base. Do we still have our base
                        iBermuda?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: We closed it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I landed there once.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Sam Donaldson went down there for “Prime Time” or “60 Minutes” or
                    something and did an atrocious piece on it, showed an admiral playing golf,
                    giving the impression that the golf course was on the base, which it wasn't. It
                    was off base. He was showing people on beaches, saying in effect that the
                    beaches were on the base, but they weren't. It should have been turned into a
                    Coast Guard base for interception of narcotics. That's what it should have been
                    turned into. But we couldn't do it. Once it got in the papers, it was gone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, those years between '93 and '96, you were in and out,
                        guess, on these TDYs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. When I came back after Bermuda, the DAS in the African Bureau asked
                    if I would go out and take care of Equatorial Guinea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the problem or the situation there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: The situation there was, we had an ambassador in there who came into
                    Equatorial Guinea, as a first time ambassador. He made “his bones” doing human
                    rights in Uganda. He came in and he was going to be the human rights man in
                    Equatorial Guinea. He was going to get rid of the head of state and have a
                    democratic government there. He was going to lead the Spaniards and all the rest
                    in this tremendous march toward democracy and human rights. In the meantime, he
                    had the Peace Corps withdrawn. He had the AID withdrawn. He ruined relations
                    with the Spaniards when he complained to the Spanish Foreign Minister that their
                    personnel were not pushing on human rights enough. He complained to the French
                    Foreign Office saying the same thing about the French embassy. He complained to
                    the United Nations about it. He wrote 16 and 17 page cables out of Malabo. I've
                    never written a 16 or 17 pager even after talking to Hassan el-Turabi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And this is out of Equatorial Guinea? A 16 page
                        cable?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: That's right. He had Ambassador Render, who was chief of AF/C, crazy
                    over this thing. He almost got PNGed, except somebody advised the President, “If
                    you PNG him, you make him a great hero and that's not what you want to do, so
                    you wait.” There was terrible morale in the embassy because nobody knew what was
                    happening. We couldn't get pouches-</p>
                <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the ambassador still there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No, he had been moved. I told the Department I didn't speak Spanish. I
                    spoke French. Again, I said my French was awful. They said, “Go down and do
                    anything.” So, I went down. The first thing I did after seeing the foreign
                    minister, saying, “Look, I'm not here to interfere in internal affairs of the
                    government. We're the same color, but that's all.” He speaks good Spanish; I
                    don't speak Spanish. I said to him in French, “I'll make you a solemn promise: I
                    will never send anything to the Department of State on any information I receive
                    unless I first check with you. Count on me. I intend to see some people, but you
                    will see them and I will see them.” He said, “I want to assure you that nobody
                    tried to threaten your ambassador.” I said, “I believe you.” I said this in
                    front of all his officers. “I believe that nobody in your government or anybody
                    in your employ tried to threaten the ambassador.” They were not exactly
                    sure.</p>
                <p>After seeing the foreign minister, I went over and saw the Spanish charg�, Jos�
                    Marie Ridau, a young officer. He had recently returned from Moscow, was
                    definitely going to be a Spanish ambassador. This was the officer who the
                    American ambassador told that he, because of his age and experience, was going
                    to be in charge of the diplomatic community and was going to lead them in this
                    foray into human rights. I came over, apologized for not speaking Spanish. He
                    spoke excellent English. I said, “You know, you are the senior here because you
                    were charg� longer than I and I surely intend to coordinate with you. I'm not
                    Bennett. I don't look like Bennett. I don't act like Bennett. Furthermore, to
                    you, Equatorial Guinea is important. To us, Cuba is important. Cuba is a pain
                    for us. Equatorial Guinea is a pain for you. I intend to work with you.</p>
                <p>“I understand that elections are going to be held and that the international
                    community will be involved and that the Spanish government will be leading.” The
                    charg� says, “Well, we can modify it if you have any objections.” He said, “They
                    won't be free and fair. They will be somewhat free and somewhat fair.” I said,
                    “Something like Chicago. I will go to the meeting with and stand by you and
                    listen to the translations by my local personnel and learn Spanish as quickly as
                    I can. But I will know at one of the first meetings to say in Spanish 'The
                    Spanish charg�' speaks for the American charg� in this matter.” After that, no
                    problem with any of the diplomatic missions or with the United Nations.</p>
                <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                <p>Then there were people in prison. The American charg� would not go out and bang
                    walls or make a march down to the jail like the former ambassador. The Spanish
                    charg� and myself would go and we would meet these people. I would see people
                    and he would say, “Now, you have a choice. You can let them out of jail and we
                    will report that they were in jail and released, both of us, or we will report
                    that they are in jail and being tortured. We have to assume they're being
                    tortured because they are in jail.” They would say, “Well, it's going to take us
                    a day or two.” We would say, “Five days. Get them out.” They were all out. By
                    the time he left and was replaced by an ambassador, there were no political
                    prisoners in jail. Something like 40-odd prisoners were released.</p>
                <p>In Washington, Ambassador Render felt I was too close to the President and too
                    close to the people and, in a way, not pushy enough about getting the human
                    rights thing on the front burner.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were no Americans in jail.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No. These were all Guineans.</p>
                <pb facs="0077" n="Page0077"/>
                <p>Complicating this matter because I get along very well with oil riggers and other
                    people, I knew that Mobil and United Meridian were the only ones able to find
                    the oil. They did on my watch. I didn't see any reason why our relationship
                    deteriorated so badly that we couldn't do business with these Guineans.
                    Washington, the desk officer and Render, both felt that the oil companies could
                    take care of themselves. I knew better because there was a border dispute
                    between Nigeria, with Elf on their side, and Equatorial Guinea with Mobile and
                    United Meridian Corporation, and America on their side. Elf wants to get closer
                    to the president of Equatorial Guinea against the U.S. oil companies. Render
                    felt I was much, much too close with the President, much too close with his
                    chief of security, who was, is, and probably will be a murderer. I said to
                    Render when I came back for Christmas, “I can't play it both ways. If I scream
                    at these people, they're in jail and they get beaten up. I get these people out
                    and I have to do business with them.” She was not pleased and mentioned in my
                    efficiency report that I was much too close and much too far ahead of the
                    Department on that matter. But we do have our oil and there was nobody in jail
                    when I left and the elections were going to be held. I feel that there's got to
                    be a balance. You can either be all oil and forget the human rights or you
                    cannot. I think it can be managed. We did improve relations. When I left, I got
                    an honor: They gave me the Order of Independence, which they didn't give the
                    previous ambassador, and didn't give to any of the ambassadors, as I can recall.
                    They offered to give me land in Equatorial Guinea, which I could not accept. But
                    I told Washington this. I see a sort of narrow-mindedness by people about human
                    rights, which we will go on to, but you have to get these things done. One of
                    the desk officers, I think, said, “You know, so what if somebody stays in jail
                    an extra month?” I said to her, “What's the difference between getting one slap
                    every day and the slapping stops after seven days or stops after 37 days?” But
                    we got all our pouches through. After that, we had no trouble with anybody.
                    People came in and out. When somebody got sick, we were able to get them out in
                    a hurry. The French, whom I always admire, took care of the gard� publique,
                    their people. When the French officer responsible for them (and I traveled with
                    him twice) went out into the “boondocks” to these stations where his Guinea
                    officers were, these officers reported to him as if they were French officers
                    standing in the center of Paris. They found out he was coming. Their shoes and
                    everything sparkled. They came and they saluted properly. They spoke in French.
                    They told him anything he wanted to know about everything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They respected him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They respected him and the French were smart. They're increasing the
                    number of officers they have out there training the police. They're going to put
                    one officer up in President Obiang's home province and they're going to build a
                    school for training police up there. They're going to leave an officer up there.
                    Do you think that officer isn't going to know everything that happens in that
                    area? They're training their military. They're not sending out some officer. The
                    officer they sent out was a captain who was a graduate of St. Cyr. This officer
                    was a Russian language officer. He was learning English. He will eventually be a
                    general in the French army.</p>
                <pb facs="0078" n="Page0078"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How large a staff did we have in Equatorial Guinea? It
                        must havbeen very small.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Small. Before I arrived, when the ambassador was there, you had the
                    ambassador, a secretary, a political officer, a consular officer, and a
                    communicator: five people. When I came out, there was the communicator and a
                    secretary. We eventually got an administrative officer. They wanted to send a
                    consular officer. I said, “Don't send a consular. I don't need it. We'll just
                    train the secretary,” who was very, very good. She was Spanish speaking. I got
                    her an honor award, which she richly deserved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were other agencies there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: No. The previous ambassador had done such a job. First of all, let me
                    say something about the government of Equatorial Guinea. It is murderous. Under
                    the old regime, they killed everybody and they still do an occasional killing.
                    But there is a significant difference in the murderousness. It's not completely
                    bad. It's not completely good. But if you want to measure it, I'd say it was a
                    hell of a lot better than Bosnia or Rwanda.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's go on to Bosnia. You did a TDY there. In what
                        capacitwas that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: I'd come back from Equatorial Guinea. By that time, my ability to secure
                    a job in Africa or the Africa Bureau was finished. It was dead. The letter to
                    the Secretary, comments on Somalia, the reporting out of Asmara, they just
                    didn't want me around anymore. I was just not their officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A prophet is not welcome in his own country.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0079" n="Page0079"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: They'll forgive you if you're wrong, but they won't forgive you if
                    you're right. I haven't been wrong. I just had not been wrong. So, I came back
                    and they put me in declassification. I sat there. Then Bill Pope, who had been
                    the African officer in Paris, while I was in Khartoum, remembered me and I
                    remembered him. He said, “What are you doing?” I said, “God, that must be
                    interesting.” Some weeks later, he asked me, “Are you interested in going out to
                    Bosnia?” I said, “I don't know the area, but, God, yes, I would be interested.”
                    He said, “We need a deputy head of mission for border watching between
                    Serbia-Montenegro and Bosnia Herzegovina.” I said, “Great. That's fine for me.”
                    So, I went out until we closed down. I traveled extensively to Serbia Montenegro
                    and got into Tuzla and Sarajevo and the rest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Names that have become famous in recent years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Yes. Then I came back and stayed on the Serbian Task Force until
                    September of this year. Then I went to Jennifer Ward, who was the director
                    general for Personneland asked her if there was going to be any change. She
                    said, “If you're willing to hang around, there may be something in June of this
                    year (1997), but I can't guarantee anything.” I saw Dick Shinnick (S/S-EX) and
                    he said the same thing. I was becoming embarrassed to be doing nothing.
                    Washington was not my cup of tea and they weren't going to give me anything of
                    any utility. Again, some of it was my own fault. There were jobs that were
                    around, but I didn't hear about them. If my personnel officer knew, she wasn't
                    telling me. I hadn't really an infrastructure or a group of friends in
                    Washington who would be my rabbi. So, I thought about it and I said, “No, I'm
                    going to pull the plug and set up for retirement in declassification.” By the
                    way, people say there is a life after the Foreign Service. I told Jennifer,
                    “Yes, there is, but to be honest, it's not as sweet.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any final reflections on your career? Would you do it over
                        again?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Oh, yes, I'd do it over again. I think I might have done one other
                    thing. Instead of going to Lisbon, if I had gone to an Arab country, I think
                    that would have been... I really have a great affection for the Koran and for
                    the Muslims. I'm sorry that I had not done that. But I did not know anything
                    about Muslims at the time that I chose Portugal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you recommend to a young person today a career in
                        thForeign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0080" n="Page0080"/>
                <p>O'NEILL: Not unless he's got friends in the Service already. I can't see it.
                    First of all, the whole lifestyle has changed. When we went into the Foreign
                    Service, it was an occupation, not a vocation. When we went in, we went in for a
                    lifetime. Now, the management people say you do 20 and you get out. You're no
                    different than a trainer in the Army. We learn our profession over years. It's
                    not like running a platoon or a company. It takes us time to learn some of these
                    things. I think one of the reasons I was effective in the Foreign Service is, I
                    wasn't all over the place. I spent 12 years in Southeast Asia and 14 years in
                    East Africa. These things are like osmosis. When you're in the area and people
                    know you're there, they also have friends on the other side, on the same side.
                    If you know X, they may know Y and both of you may know A. You may next be in
                    there someplace and they know you. They don't care what you do. I could be a
                    drunkard as long as they know me. They know I'm a Catholic. They know I go to
                    church on Sunday. They also know I drink a little. They also know other
                    things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they know you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: They know me. They know I never told them a lie. If a guy or a gal is
                    going into the Foreign Service, I definitely suggest they go to small posts to
                    start. Female officers are extremely good in the Middle East. I know, everybody
                    says, “Oh, ladies can't get along in the Middle East.” Absolutely not true.
                    Robbie Newell, who was my consular officer in Addis Ababa, now a senior officer,
                    can go into any office in a foreign office in Saudi Arabia and be able to do
                    business because she is not considered a lady as Saudis consider a lady. She is
                    an American.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You're talking to the man who sent April Glaspie to Jordan
                        i1966. I know well of what you speak and I agree entirely with you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Not only that, they can go places we couldn't go. They can go and see
                    the people who hold the money: wives. Everybody says the wives don't have any
                    influence. I know Hassan El Turabi's wife. She can make Hassan El Turabi's aides
                    jump and I mean jump. When he's getting tired and she wants them out, she comes
                    in and sends them away. She decides who they will marry. Her daughter married
                    the son of Saddiq el Mahdi. The two fathers are political enemies, have been
                    enemies for years. The wives who are sisters arranged this. Wives arrange
                    marriages, they arrange finances, and the rest. The men, they do the outside:
                    the foreign affairs and the hullabaloo. The “Minister of Interior” in the house
                    is the wife. My friend, Robbie, knew as much of what was going on [as anyone].
                    She knew who was the favorite wife, what influence, where money was spent, where
                    the children would go, should I send my daughter to such and such a school? They
                    asked Robbie. You don't think that makes a difference when Robbie goes and sees
                    the old man and says, “Oh, I saw your wife and how nice your daughters are.” She
                    can say that. I couldn't say to the minister “What a beautiful daughter you
                    have.” He'd cut my goddam throat in a second!</p>
                <pb facs="0081" n="Page0081"/>
                <p>But if you're going to go in, first of all, you've got to have the necessary
                    paper, the necessary degrees. It would be useful to have languages. But the best
                    thing is some street smarts. You can't learn them. I know plenty of officers who
                    speak any number of languages. I think about the former U.S. ambassador in
                    Khartoum. He speaks Russian, Arabic, all these. He can't communicate and find
                    out what was going on.</p>
                <p>Q: You're absolutely right, Joe. In the final analysis, the main point is to get
                    your point across to another person and put it in a way that he'll
                    understand.</p>
                <p>O'NEILL: Right. You can't learn that from “Skies and Spy” and all this. Ladies
                    still, whether in front or in back, in most of the nations that we do business
                    with (That's everything, that's not just Eastern and Western Europe.) - it's run
                    by ladies. Ladies have tremendous power. If they're not taken into context and
                    not taken into the way it's supposed to be done, you lose an asset. Hassan El
                    Turabi's wife liked me because I arranged things for the family. When her
                    daughter came to get a visa, she stood on line and I heard about it. I put on my
                    coat and my tie. I walked outside. I asked if she was the daughter of Hassan El
                    Turabi and she said, “Yes.” I said, “You will please come with me.” I took her
                    into an office. I sat her down. I brought a female clerk in to sit with her
                    while I took care of her papers. When I came to talk with her, I let the female
                    sit with us. I then said, “How are you going to get home?” She said, “I will get
                    a taxi.” I said, “I will give you a car.” She said, “No, I can't take a car
                    home.” I said, “Please, I insist.” She wouldn't take it, but she told her father
                    and mother.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that's a good note in which to end this
                        extremelinteresting interview.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
