<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000782">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Charles W. McCaskill </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>CONSUL GENERAL CHARLES W. McCASKILL</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: July 7, 1993</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>This is an interview with Charles W. McCaskill. This is being done on behalf of
                    the Association for Diplomatic Studies, and I'm Charles Stuart Kennedy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could we start where you come from? A bit about your
                        background, where were you born, when, and a bit about your family and
                        education?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I was born in Camden, South Carolina, on February 21, 1923. Camden had
                    a population of about 5,000 then. Everybody knew everybody else, doors were
                    never locked, people never worried about their kids because they knew somebody
                    was looking out for them. But times were very hard; I was a Depression child. My
                    father was an elected county official for 29 years until he was defeated
                    unexpectedly in 1929. He lost everything when the banks closed. My mother was a
                    school teacher. I remember when she supported the family on $45.00 a month or
                    something like that. My father died in 1935. It was am article of faith with my
                    mother that my brother and I would attend college.I was a fairly good high
                    school football player and had a number of football scholarships, including one
                    to Auburn, Alabama, which had a very good team in those days. But since, by the
                    time I graduated in 1941, the war was looming, I chose an academic scholarship
                    to The Citadel, the military college in South Carolina. I completed two full
                    years there before I went into the Army on June 12, 1943. I served 34 months, 17
                    of them in the European Theater. I was discharged on April 14, 1946.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do in the military?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: My military service was relatively unremarkable: infantry basic
                    training at Fort Riley, Kansas; the Army Specialized Training Program (ASTP) at
                    the University of Nebraska for six months; shipment to the 66th Infantry
                    Division at Camp Robinson, Arkansas in March, 1944; and finally, overseas with
                    that division in November, 1944. After a month in England, we sailed for France
                    on Christmas Eve Day, 1944, heading, we thought at the time, to the Battle of
                    the Bulge which was then raging. One of the two transports on which about half
                    of the division was sailing was sunk in the Channel with the loss of 750-800
                    people, a very rude introduction to the war for young soldiers. I was not on the
                    vessel which was sunk, but I lost a number of friends. My company's losses were
                    18-20 as I recall. We learned later that we were in fact not headed to the
                    Battle of the Bulge, but went instead to the defensive perimeters around St.
                    Nazaire and Lorient, two of the big sub-pens cut off by General Patton in his
                    dash across France. The 94th Division, which we relieved, went to the Bulge and
                    suffered very heavy losses.A rather good little book entitled A Night Before
                    Christmas has been written on the sinking.After the war, I went to the 42nd
                    Rainbow Division in Austria where I remained until March 1946 when I began
                    heading home for discharge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Austria then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes, for about six months. I was discharged on April 14, 1946, and
                    returned to The Citadel as a civilian student in July, like most veterans
                    anxious to finish school and get on with my life. At the time, I anticipated
                    going into South Carolina politics, and planned to go to the University of South
                    Carolina Law School since a law degree from the University was a prerequisite
                    for getting into politics.Somewhere along the line — I really can't say where —
                    I lost the desire to go to law school or to get into politics. I think, first,
                    that the Army showed me that there was a world beyond the borders of South
                    Carolina, and secondly, going overseas showed me there was a world beyond the
                    shores of the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: World War II, as I do these interviews, was the greatest
                        recruiter for the Foreign Service. For me, it was the Korean War. I mean,
                        this broke us out of our convention to the womb.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: It really did. I don't know just where, but somewhere along the line I
                    decided that I wanted to get into the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you heard about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: I first heard about it from my brother who took the exam in 1946. He
                    was a rather good student of languages and scored well when he took the exam,
                    just failing to pass. I am not sure when his interest in the Service waned. I
                    think my first interest in the Service as a career came from him. Anyway, I
                    abandoned the idea of going to law school and took a graduate degree in history
                    and political science, looking toward the Foreign Service.I graduated from The
                    Citadel in September, 1947 and took the exam then in Atlanta, flunking it by two
                    points. That was in the time of the three-and-a-half day exam, a very long and
                    tough undertaking. I went to the University of South Carolina, where, as I
                    noted, I took a graduate degree in history and political science.I was offered a
                    slot in the Displaced Persons Program issuing visas to displaced persons in
                    Germany. I was sworn in as an FSS-11, Vice Consul, in March of 1950, and shortly
                    thereafter sailed for Germany. Our government had determined that it was easier
                    to take the consulates to the displaced persons than it was to take the
                    displaced persons to the consulates. I was in Schweinfurt, a sub-office of our
                    Consulate General in Frankfurt. Our office consisted of three officers and two
                    American clerks. In each camp, there were a Displaced Persons Commission (DPC),
                    which helped with assembling necessary documents, etc. for the applicants, and
                    an INS representative.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Immigration and Naturalization Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes. In our case, the INS rep was on the same floor we were on. The
                    applicants were in a real pipeline: applicants would come from the Displaced
                    Persons Commission up to us, they would be interviewed, and, in most cases,
                    visas were issued. Then they would go down the hall to the INS Inspector who
                    would check them out and in effect admit them to the US. If there was any
                    difficulty between the INS and the Consulate on a particular case, we worked it
                    out on the spot. When the DPs arrived at a US port, they had already been found
                    to be admissible and could be processed out to their sponsors. The system worked
                    rather well, since any questions were worked out on the spot by the DPC, the
                    Consulate and the INS.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were some of the people? What types of people were you
                        seeing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: We were in a rather large, former German Army camp, the Schweinfurt
                    Panzer Caserne. All of the several thousand people living in the camp had been
                    uprooted by the war. There were Poles, Hungarians, Balts, some Czechs, people
                    from all walks of life waiting to start a new life. In the camp, the DPs were
                    taken care of by various welfare organizations: the National Catholic Welfare
                    Service, I think HIAS had a representative. . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was the Jewish agency, and then there was the Tolstoy
                        Foundation. There was a Protestant one whose name I can't think of.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: The Church World Service. All of these organizations were doing a
                    great deal toward clothing the DPs, feeding them, etc. And of course, our
                    government was very much involved in the program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the main causes on the political side keeping
                        people from coming into the United States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Anyone who had had anything to do with the Nazi organizations, or
                    Germany itself, was ineligible to receive a visa: an application for Nazi Party
                    membership, for example, membership in any Nazi Organization. One of our
                    interpreters. a Latvian who spoke Latvian, Lithuanian, Russian, Ukrainian,
                    German and English, was himself ineligible because he had applied for membership
                    in the Nazi Party when Latvia was occupied. The old Berlin Document Center
                    records, which we apparently captured before they could be destroyed, were
                    really quite reliable and did some of the DPs in by revealing their past
                    political activities. There was an occasional moral turpitude case, but most of
                    the refusals were based on political grounds. And there was little attention on,
                    or attention to, the Communist menace.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I might say for the record when I was in Frankfurt with
                        the Refugee Relief Program five years later, where this sort of cleaned up
                        the situation. If you had one crime of moral turpitude, and it wasn't too
                        bad, we could excuse it. Membership in the Nazi Party was not ipso facto
                        ground for refusal. It had to have been significant activity. Many of these
                        things were just a cleaning up process.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: By then some different interpretations had come in, involuntary
                    membership, membership in youth organizations under 16 years of age, for
                    example.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was sort of cleaning up although the Communist side was
                        emphasized much more. You were there about a year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes. We had some family problems and I came home and went to work in
                    the Visa Office, at that time experiencing a flood of work. Two well known visa
                    circulars had gone out — remember that this was the beginning of the Cold War —
                    establishing new criteria for refusing visas or at least for referring cases to
                    the Department for advisory opinion. It was a rather long list of categories of
                    cases, including the cases of those who had relatives in Eastern Europe, those
                    who had ever lived in Eastern Europe, those who had visited Eastern Europe, and
                    on and on. This was in the McCarthy era, when Senator Pat McCarran and
                    Congressman Francis Walter were the driving force behind terribly restrictive
                    security visa regulations</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Francis Walter of Pennsylvania. Pat McCarran was a Senator
                        from Nevada.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: These two were the Visa Office's special patrons on the Hill. They
                    were already drawing up the Immigration and Nationality Act of 1952, the
                    codification of much of this. It was known as the McCarran-Walter Act.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And basically the core document for 20 or more years. It
                        kept being amended. I think they came up with really new legislation in the
                        1980s. You were in the Visa Office from 1951 to 1956?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes. While I was there I became interested in the Greek cases being
                    referred to the Department from all over the world because the Greek resistance
                    organizations and the Greek seamen's union were on our proscribed list. This is
                    an oversimplification of a complicated question, but basically describes the
                    situation. Athens was complaining that many applicants were not really
                    excludable, and my boss in the Visa Office asked me to make a study of the
                    situation and draw up some guidelines. Through this study I became involved in
                    and very interested in Modern Greece, stimulated to a very great degree by
                    Charlie Lagoudakis, a man who knew more about Modern Greece than any other
                    single person I have known and the Greek specialist in INR. Anyway, as a result
                    of this interest, I applied for Greek Language and Area Training — as it was
                    known in those days — and began training in January, 1956. I was the first
                    Foreign Service Greek language trainee. This was during the time of the Wriston
                    Program in the Department, and soon after language training started, I was sworn
                    in as an FSR and later lateraled in as an FSO. The language school of FSI was in
                    an old barracks on C Street about where the Diplomatic Entrance is now. My tutor
                    and I were in a very small room — about 8' by 12' — for six hours a day. Alone
                    in the class I had no gauge by which to judge my progress. I argued
                    unsuccessfully for more grammar, more stress on reading, etc. But the “system”
                    was much less sophisticated than it has become and I was confined to six hours a
                    day of repetition and about an hour a day on the tapes. I had to admit, after I
                    finished, that I had learned a good bit of grammar without realizing it and that
                    when I wanted to say “the son of my sister's friend” I did not have to figure
                    out how to say it. While I did not learn to read Greek as well as most of those
                    who followed me learned, I did come out of FSI with an excellent accent.The
                    program then was a two-part program: if you did well in the language, you then
                    had an academic year of area studies. Finding a program in Modern Greek studies
                    was not easy in 1956. We contacted the Dean of the Department of Oriental
                    Studies at Princeton, who had been a classmate of the Dean of the FSI Language
                    School, and he suggested that I might study in his Department. Actually, the
                    Turkish and Persian area students had been studying in the Department of
                    Oriental Studies for some years.I went to Princeton thinking I would be working
                    with Dr. Lewis Thomas, the Ottoman History man, not knowing until I got there
                    that he was on sabbatical that year. I sort of bounced around the first
                    semester; I did take a course under a marvelous professor from Columbia, Tibor
                    Halasi Kun, who was brought in to give the Ottoman History course the first
                    semester. The second semester I found my way over to the Woodrow Wilson School
                    and Dr. Cyril Black, a well-known eastern and southern European man who agreed
                    to do a reading course on Modern Greece for me. That reading course, and a
                    graduate seminar of Black's which I took, constituted the meat of the year for
                    me. Professor Black was really very helpful and motivated me a great deal. I
                    kept in touch with him for some years after I left Princeton.I went directly
                    from Princeton to Thessaloniki. I was disappointed that I was not assigned to
                    Athens, a wonderful and interesting post. But I loved the three years we were in
                    Thessaloniki.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were married?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes, I was married and had two small sons, five and just over two at
                    the time. As I noted we were there three full years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: 1957 to 1960?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes. The consulate was relatively small in those days — although not
                    as small as it has become since then. We lived in the suburb of Aretsou, and it
                    was not long before my boys were in communication with the Greek kids. By the
                    time we left Thessaloniki in 1960, they were bilingual in Greek, completely at
                    home in Greek and in the Greek environment. When they spoke Greek in Cyprus,
                    Cypriots mistook them for mainland Greek kids.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in Thessaloniki?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: The first year-and-a-half I was doing consular and economic work. When
                    we got a new boss in 1958, I, as the only language man on the staff, began doing
                    more political work, following the minority question in Thrace, for example, and
                    traveling more. The new Consul General felt, and I agreed, that the language
                    officer should get around more.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the Consul General?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Robert S. Folsom, a fine CG and a good friend. My first Consul General
                    was Philip W. Ireland, who was sometimes quite difficult to work for. Under
                    Folsom, I saw a lot of Northern Greece and learned a lot about the area. There
                    were some interesting problems there, such as the Muslim minority in Thrace,
                    which I have mentioned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the political situation in this period in
                        northern Greece as you saw it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: When I first arrived in Greece, Karamanlis had just been elected Prime
                    Minister. When the Prime Minister, General Papagos, died in October, 1955, he
                    was succeeded by Constantine Karamanlis, who had been the Minister of Public
                    Works in the Papagos Government. Karamanlis was “chosen out of turn”, so to
                    speak, and there were those who saw “the foreign hand” in his selection.
                    Karamanlis was elected in his own right in February, 1956, and was governing
                    when I arrived in Greece. For reasons I do not remember, a group of Deputies of
                    Karamanlis's party broke with him in the spring of 1958, he lost his majority in
                    Parliament, and he was forced to call elections, I believe in May, 1958. The
                    Greek Communist Party, known in Greece by the acronym KKE, had been outlawed in
                    Greece since just after World War II. There was an organization, however, the
                    Union of the Democratic Left, known by its acronym EDA, which became the
                    umbrella for all sorts of fellow-travelers, leftists, some old-line communists,
                    etc. Meanwhile, the old Liberal Party, was led jointly by George Papandreou and
                    Sophocles Venizelos, the former the father of Andreas Papandreou, the latter the
                    son of the great Eleftherios Venizelos. The party was known to be weak, but it
                    nonetheless offered a slate throughout the country.</p>
                <p>In those elections, Greece and its allies received a tremendous shock when EDA
                    received almost 25% of the popular vote, 24.6 or 24.8%. EDA became the largest
                    opposition party and the principal opposition in the Parliament, the leader of
                    the opposition, though I have forgotten the number of deputies it elected. The
                    Liberal Party, the old historic party, was practically wiped out, with only
                    three deputies in all of Northern Greece.</p>
                <p>Karamanlis formed a government because he had a majority of the 300 deputies in
                    Parliament, but it was a shock to everybody that EDA, a leftist-front
                    organization, could take almost 25% of the popular vote. To give you an idea,
                    the famous composer Mikis Theodorakis was elected on the EDA ticket.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, the man who wrote the music for the move “Z” and
                        other things.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: That's right. A man who has been all over the political spectrum, most
                    recently in the conservative party of Constantine Mitsotakis. There were
                    elections again but I have forgotten just when since I had left for Cyprus.
                    Karamanlis governed until 1963, when he had his big argument with the Palace and
                    left in a huff for Paris.</p>
                <p>I went on home leave in 1959, and learned from Personnel, when I was passing
                    through Washington on my way back to Thessaloniki, that I had been assigned to
                    the new Embassy in Cyprus as Economic/Commercial Officer. The Department was
                    busily engaged in staffing the Embassy in Nicosia, and I was being assigned as
                    the Greek language officer. We left Thessaloniki in July of 1960 on direct
                    transfer to Cyprus.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To go back to Thessaloniki at that time: How were
                        relations between the Consulate General and the Embassy? What was the
                        feeling towards Ambassadors Riddleberger and Briggs would you say?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Actually we had three Ambassadors while I was in Greece. Ambassador
                    Allen. . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: George Allen.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Ambassador George Allen was there just a short time. I consider him,
                    Ambassador Riddleberger, and Ambassador Briggs three of the finest career
                    ambassadors I had the honor, the privilege, of working for. They were all
                    different, of course.Ambassador Riddleberger was very senior at the time but was
                    a very warm human being. In those days, when we were in the Embassy, we would
                    drop cards on the Ambassador as a courtesy. Once when I was there and stopped to
                    drop a card in Ambassador Riddleberger's office, his secretary suggested that he
                    might want to see me. She told him on his intercom that I was there, and he
                    asked me to come in. In response to my protestations that I knew he was busy and
                    did not want to interrupt him, he insisted that I come in and “sit down and
                    smoke a cigarette.” We talked for 10-15 minutes when he was in fact very busy. I
                    was tremendously impressed that he would give me so much of his time and I have
                    never forgotten it.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Briggs was an entirely different type, a very colorful Ambassador. He
                    used to visit Thessaloniki frequently because he was a big duck hunter and there
                    were lots of duck in Northern Greece. As I noted previously, I considered
                    Ambassador Riddleberger and Ambassador Briggs among the best career senior
                    Foreign Service Officers I knew during my career. I seem to have stronger
                    memories of the two of them than I do of Ambassador Allen who left Greece
                    shortly after I arrived.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were in Thessaloniki, how did you and the people
                        around you view George Papandreou? What was the feeling towards him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: In Thessaloniki, we did not know much about Papandreou and we depended
                    on the Embassy for guidance on such matters. As I indicated earlier,
                    Papandreou's party was in shambles. After the election debacle of 1958, word got
                    around that the Embassy was looking for promising young Liberal Party members to
                    cultivate. Two sons of prominent Liberal Party politicians returned to Greece
                    about that time, i. e. 1959: Andreas Papandreou, George's son, and John
                    Tsouderos, the son of previous Prime Minister Emmanuel Tsouderos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Andreas Papandreou had been an American citizen?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes, teaching economics at the University of California, a very highly
                    regarded economist, married to an American woman. He returned to Greece in, I
                    believe, 1959. One had to wonder if there was more to his return than met the
                    eye.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you talked to people in Thessaloniki, were you getting
                        a feeling for the view of the royal family at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I have no recollection of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It shows it was not a major topic.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: It was not. I have absolutely no recollection of ever discussing it
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the local politicians? How did they impress
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I knew several of them and they impressed me fairly favorably.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again going back to this time. Were efforts made by the
                        military, the politicians, etc., to mute the differences with Turkey, to
                        avoid being constantly hit with headlines about the things Turks were doing
                        to Greece etc.?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: No, there was nothing in the media, or almost nothing in the media.
                    There was a conscious effort by the Greek Government to keep the lid on the
                    minorities question. I always felt that the Greek Government went out of the way
                    to conform to the Treaty of Lausanne, which provided for the Muslim minority in
                    Thrace and the Christian minority in Istanbul. I thought, and continue to think,
                    that Turkish claims of harassment of Turks in Thrace are terribly overdrawn. I
                    don't for a minute say there is no discrimination. There is discrimination there
                    as there is everywhere in such situations. But I have never thought there was
                    any real harassment of the Turks in Thrace. Greece has, over the years, gotten
                    the short end of the stick on this one, and the Turks have continued to
                    exaggerate their claims. You have only to look at what happened in Istanbul in
                    September, 1955, when mobs ran rampant against the Greek community in that city
                    to see that the Greeks have been taken on this one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were monitoring it too.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: We followed it rather closely, though very discreetly since the
                    Government was very sensitive on this issue. A member of the Ministry of
                    Northern Greece made it quite clear to me that his Ministry was under standing
                    instructions not to do anything to complicate the problem for Athens, to give
                    the Turks no grounds for complaint. The Muslims, or Turks, lived very much to
                    themselves in those days. I went into a Turkish village in Thrace on one
                    occasion to pay a claim against the Consulate resulting from an accident and
                    found that the Turk whom I needed to deal with spoke no Greek. The gendarme, who
                    was helping me, spoke a bit of Turkish and interpreted for me.</p>
                <p>To repeat what I said a minute ago, I have always thought that Greece has never
                    made its case very well on the minorities question. The Greek community of
                    Istanbul, over 100,000 in 1955, is down to 5-10,000 today. The Muslim or Turkish
                    community in Thrace was about 100,000 in 1955 and is 120-140,000 today. Those
                    figures speak for themselves. Ankara, under the leadership of the Turkish
                    Ministry of Foreign Affairs, has very skillfully stirred up the minorities
                    question against the Greeks from time to time, using it as a diplomatic weapon
                    against Greece. The Turks would take some minor, isolated incident and blow it
                    all out of proportion. The Turks have bullied the Greeks on this one, as they
                    have on other subjects, and Greece has been relatively free from real criticism
                    on this one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Cyprus from 1960 to 1964. In the first place,
                        what was your job when you went out to Cyprus?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I arrived in Cyprus almost exactly one month before independence,
                    which occurred on August 16, 1960. I went as Economic/Commercial Officer but
                    found after I got there that I would also be doing the consular work because the
                    Department had taken a budget cut, and we had lost the consular officer
                    position. The position was restored in about a year, but until then I did the
                    consular work in addition to my duties as Economic/Commercial Officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you describe Cyprus at the time you arrived, what the
                        political/economic situation was?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: The London-Zurich Agreements establishing the new Republic of Cyprus
                    had been signed in February, 1960, and there was some relief (obviously
                    premature) among all parties concerned (except the Greek Cypriots) that the
                    Cyprus Problem was “settled”. Athens was truly anxious to put the Cyprus Problem
                    to rest, to get on with solving some of Greece's problems. It should be kept in
                    mind that Greece was at war longer than any other single European country — from
                    October 28, 1940 to the end of the Bandit War in 1949 — and the Greek Government
                    wanted to get on with rebuilding the country. The Greeks had been completely
                    preoccupied with Cyprus from the early 1950s and time and energy that should
                    have gone into reconstruction of Greece were devoted to Cyprus. The
                    international community was fed up with Cyprus, which had been at the center of
                    the world stage for some years. So the feeling in Greece, at least in
                    Thessaloniki, was one of relief that the problem was settled. It was our
                    perception that the Greeks were relieved.</p>
                <p>When I arrived in Cyprus I was surprised to find a general feeling among the
                    Greek Cypriot community — which was 80% of the population — that the
                    London-Zurich Agreements would not work, that the safeguards written into the
                    agreements for the Turkish Cypriots were extreme, that the agreements were “not
                    fair”, and on and on.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>In truth, the agreements were an extremely complicated set of agreements which
                    did, in my opinion, give the Turkish Cypriots too many safeguards. Former Under
                    Secretary of State George Ball described the Agreements as an “impressive
                    diplomatic tour de force” which were “too complex to be workable”. Most
                    objectionable to the Greek Cypriots, Turkey could, under the Treaty of
                    Guarantee, intervene in Cyprus. The Turkish Cypriot community's vetoes,
                    legislative and executive, could bring the government to a standstill; the
                    Turkish Cypriots, 20% of the population, were given 30% of the civil service and
                    the legislature. The Greek Cypriots vigorously opposed the concept that the two
                    communities on the island were equal partners, that there was no majority
                    community and no minority community, that they were both equal participants in
                    the government. The Greek Cypriots, including Makarios, felt that the agreements
                    had been imposed on Cyprus by circumstances, that Makarios had been “forced” to
                    sign ; no Greek Cypriot was present when the Greeks and the Turks reached
                    agreement. Makarios stated later that he signed because the British threatened
                    to partition the island if he did not agree to the agreements, and he feared
                    that intercommunal fighting like that of 1958 would begin again. Moreover, Greek
                    Prime Minister Karamanlis rebuked Makarios rather strenuously at the first
                    meeting in London and threatened to withdraw Greek support if Makarios refused
                    to sign the agreements. Makarios had indicated in 1958 that he could accept a
                    solution of an independent Cyprus rather than insisting on union with Greek.
                    Great Britain by 1958 had reviewed its security position and had decided that
                    bases on the island would satisfy its security requirements and that it did not
                    need to hold the entire island. All of this led to the conference in Zurich and
                    later in London.I've gone beyond the political/economic situation on the island
                    when I got there but this does give a little flavor of what we were hearing when
                    I arrived. I might add that I have thought about the London-Zurich Agreements
                    over the years, and I have concluded that it was probably impossible for a small
                    group of Greek and Turkish diplomats to work out, even in outline, such
                    complicated agreements, and I have wondered if the agreements were drafted in
                    London and slipped to the Turks who then put them on the table in Zurich. You
                    may recall that they met in Zurich for less than a week and drew up an outline
                    of the agreement; they then met in London a few days later to sign them. Many of
                    the provisions had been contained in previous British proposals — most recently
                    the MacMillan Plan — but one still has to wonder if the Greeks and Turks had the
                    diplomatic expertise for such an undertaking.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>Speaking of the pressures on Makarios, Ambassador Nikos Kranidiotis, the Cyprus
                    Ambassador in Athens for many years, in his book entitled Difficult Years says
                    that Makarios anguished all night over whether or not to sign. He received calls
                    from Queen Frederika in Athens, from former Governor of Cyprus Hugh Foot, and
                    from the leader of the British Labor Party, all urging him to sign. As a
                    footnote, I asked Frederika, whom I came to know fairly well when I was Consul
                    General in Madras, if the story were true and she said her husband spoke to
                    Makarios. The King only called, she said, because they were afraid that the
                    Karamanlis government would fall if Makarios refused to sign. She indicated that
                    fear that the government would fall justified what otherwise could have been
                    termed “intervention” in Greek internal affairs. I believe Kranidiotis' version,
                    and have always felt, that for whatever reason, Frederika was dissembling with
                    me.Cyprus was dubbed by some over the years as “The Reluctant Republic”, since
                    it was felt that the solution really desired by the majority Greek Cypriots was
                    union with Greece rather than independence, and that independence was “forced”
                    on Makarios. Those very early days were very interesting and exciting and even
                    humorous as we approached independence. There was a story on the island that
                    Makarios, by then the President-elect, and Turkish Cypriot Vice President-elect
                    Fazil Kucuk realized rather late that they had not even thought of a flag. After
                    all, every country had to have a flag on independence day, and they agreed on a
                    temporary flag which was a sort of yellowish-clayish outline of the island on a
                    white background with olive branches underneath. That was to be temporary, and
                    they were to design a more appropriate flag later with their help of time.
                    Nobody has yet designed another flag of Cyprus and that one is still used as the
                    official flag.</p>
                <p>I rode around Nicosia, the capital, a good bit on independence day, and I saw
                    Greek flags in the Greek quarter and Turkish flags in the Turkish quarter. This
                    is what a former governor referred to as “the flag nuisance” in Cyprus. Under
                    the British occupation, the Greek Cypriots traditionally brought out the Greek
                    flag on holidays, rather than the Union Jack. This tended to grate on British
                    nerves but they never found a way to counter it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the feeling when you arrived in Cyprus, from your
                        colleagues at the Embassy and in Washington, about where Cyprus was going.
                        What was the feeling at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: There was actually widespread interest in Cyprus when it became
                    independent. It was one of the first newly-independent small republics. With a
                    population of 600,000 it was considered a very small country in those days, and
                    there was considerable interest in seeing that it worked. Because of the long
                    fight against the British and the fact that the problem was debated at such
                    length in the UN, everybody knew where and what Cyprus was.Our own interests
                    were several: (1) to deny the Soviets access to the Mediterranean through
                    Cyprus. There was a well organized Communist Party of 10,000 members on Cyprus
                    and in 1960, this was of considerable concern to us. (2) to insure the continued
                    function of US facilities — our Federal Broadcasting Information Service (FBIS)
                    facility, our relay facility, etc. — on the island; (3) to insure the continued
                    functioning of the British Sovereign Bases (SBAs) on the island; (4) to work to
                    prevent Cyprus from disrupting the southeastern flank of NATO by becoming an
                    issue between our NATO allies Greece and Turkey.</p>
                <p>These are given in no particular order, though there was some preoccupation with
                    the “communist threat” in Cyprus, and even President Kennedy was said to be
                    taken with the island and the problem in the early days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: FBIS is not a covert intelligence operation. We would
                        monitor broadcasts, translate them, and then pass them out to anyone.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: It is an overt monitoring service, and that particular location was
                    highly effective for monitoring internal domestic broadcasts in the Soviet
                    Union. It was said to be one of our most effective FBIS stations. Secondly, we
                    had a tremendous radio relay station, only a relay point. Communication
                    facilities were not as sophisticated as they are today. The relay station had
                    direct lines to Washington. Messages would go, for example, from Beirut to
                    Cyprus, off of one wire onto another for direct transmission to Washington. And
                    then there was another facility referred to just as a station. I suppose it was
                    an NSA facility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: National Security Agency.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: It was staffed when I was there by US Navy personnel because during
                    the Greek Cypriot terrorist campaign against the British life became so tense
                    that the Department had problems getting civilians to go there. We had a rather
                    large complex of facilities and a very real interest in the island. We wanted to
                    protect our interests and keep Cyprus from falling under Soviet influence.
                    Remember that the Soviet fleet was active in the Mediterranean at the time, and
                    our interests in Cyprus were real.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>To show our interest we wanted to get off to a quick start. One possibility we
                    had was a PL 480 program which we were able to justify on the basis of a drought
                    of several years. It took some doing — we did not even have a copy of PL 480 in
                    the Embassy when we started talking about it with the Cypriots. A couple of AID
                    types came over from Amman to help us out, and we drew up a program for 50,000
                    tons of wheat and barley. We gave it to Cyprus under Title II of PL 480. It was
                    worth several million dollars and the Cypriots appreciated the gesture. The
                    British had given Cyprus a golden handshake, really in return for the sovereign
                    bases, and ours was the first assistance of any kind outside the British. We
                    also began an Exchange Program and other USIS activities. And significantly,
                    Makarios paid an official visit to Washington, and Vice President Johnson paid a
                    return visit to Cyprus. Two visits in the first couple of years of Cyprus's
                    independence were proof of out interest in the island.</p>
                <p>The Soviets had a tremendous diplomatic establishment in Nicosia, and we
                    concluded that it was a regional Soviet base. They had an excellent Turkish
                    language officer in their Embassy, and one or more Greek speakers.</p>
                <p>Our Embassy was relatively small. The Ambassador, the DCM, a Political Officer,
                    an Economic/Commercial Officer, and a rather large administrative section
                    because we gave administrative support to FBIS, the relay base, etc. The station
                    was composed of three officers and two clerical staff. But, as I said, the
                    Embassy proper was very small.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Ambassador the whole time you were there was Fraser
                        Wilkins, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: All but about six months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One, how did he operate; and two, what was your impression
                        about how he felt about Cyprus?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Ambassador Wilkins arrived in Nicosia in September, 1960. I do not
                    know for sure, but looking back I believe his only instructions were to
                    encourage the Cypriots to make London-Zurich work. I have recently read some
                    declassified materials that would seem to indicate that Wilkins did not believe
                    the Agency's reporting and did not seem convinced that trouble was on the
                    horizon. I had heard this from some of the Agency people some time ago, but only
                    recently have seen a few things indicating that it was indeed the case.As I
                    mentioned previously, it was suggested that we might use PL 480 as one of our
                    instruments, but I am relatively sure nobody was looking at the possibility that
                    London-Zurich would not work, nobody was doing any contingency thinking, let
                    alone contingency planning. I think those were the Ambassador's instructions and
                    I think he hewed to that line.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were on your economic/commercial side, what were
                        your main tasks?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Interestingly there was a fair amount of commercial work, inquiries,
                    etc. Even in a population of 600,000, merchants were looking for new products to
                    sell. And American firms were looking for business in Cyprus, which let it be
                    known that it needed a new power plant and a small refinery. Remember that
                    Cyprus was oriented toward the UK; on independence, people began to look
                    elsewhere. The economy of Cyprus was not doing badly at independence. The income
                    from the British bases was a significant factor in the economy; the “Golden
                    Handshake” was a boost. I have forgotten the figures but the per capita income
                    of Cyprus was much higher than that of Greece or Turkey. And there was great
                    interest in the economy. Just before independence, it was announced that the UN
                    would send a team out, under an eminent American economist, Dr. Willard Thorp,
                    to draw up a five-year plan for Cyprus. The UN delegation consisted of several
                    good economists so I drew on their expertise to some degree.</p>
                <p>But there was not all that much pure economic work in a post that small,
                    especially with the UN team and our own AID mission, when they came in about a
                    year, so I sort of gradually slipped over into political-type work, talking to
                    people, getting out around the island, etc. Cyprus was a wonderful place to
                    work, and access was easy. I still remember those days very warmly as among my
                    best in the Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about your contacts with the Turkish side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I had fairly good contacts on the Turkish side, but in truth the Greek
                    Cypriots were the dominant business/commercial/banking forces in the island. To
                    give you an example: I gave a party in the port city of Limassol, a sort of
                    get-acquainted party. Limassol was the business capital of Cyprus, and instead
                    of asking 50 or 60 people to drive to Nicosia, I gave the party in Limassol.
                    Even in the business capital of the island it was difficult to find Turkish
                    Cypriot businessmen of any significance. One of my best friends in Nicosia was a
                    Turkish Cypriot who ran a well-known bookshop, but he was relative small scale
                    then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying there was a ten thousand-strong dedicated
                        Communist Party which is really a very potent weapon. Ten thousand
                        disciplined Communists in any place can be a problem. Did we have much
                        contact, or feeling for what they were doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes, we had contact with them. The Political Officer had contact with
                    them, and we would see them at parties occasionally. Makarios never considered
                    them a danger. He was in many ways relatively naive politically. He considered
                    them members of his Greek Cypriot flock, no danger to him. He actually made a
                    deal with them in the first election. Makarios was not unopposed in the first
                    election held just before independence, and he gave the Communists five seats in
                    the first Parliament in return for their pledge not to oppose him. He felt in
                    the final analysis that he could control them, that he really did not have to
                    worry about them. I guess you could say that he actually was proven right. He
                    seemed to think we overplayed “the threat”. We were very conscious of them and
                    their very strong labor union. To counter the communist union, we worked closely
                    with the non-communist union and did what we could to strengthen them through
                    grants, exchanges, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As the new republic began to take shape, what was CIA up
                        to, what were they doing? Or was that beyond your camp?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: You may remember that Agency reporting was distributed on a
                    need-to-know basis, and since most of their reporting was political, I was not
                    on distribution for their material. However, I knew the Agency people very well
                    — we were good friends in fact — and while I did not see their reporting, I knew
                    what they were talking about. The Chief of Station was also a good friend of
                    mine. So while I was out of the loop officially, I was nonetheless privy to the
                    substance of what they were sending to Washington.</p>
                <p>One of the things that has haunted me about Cyprus, and continues to haunt me to
                    this day, is that the Agency apparently was reporting that the island was going
                    to blow up, that the two communities were arming themselves to the teeth, and
                    that a blow-up was inevitable. In fact, in early 1963, the Chief of Station
                    indicated his strong belief that the situation would blow before the end of the
                    year. What haunts me is that if they were reporting this back to Washington,
                    wasn't anybody reading it? And why did we not do something to head off the
                    crisis? In their book entitled Facing the Brink, reportedly based on Mr. Ball's
                    papers, Edward Weintal and Charles Bartlett said something to the effect that it
                    was “inconceivable” but true that no advance planning was done for the
                    “predictable” Cyprus crisis. Mr. Ball says in his own book that the effort to
                    maintain a balance between the two communities “was bound to fail”.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>So, based on all of this — recognition that the Cyprus “experiment” was bound to
                    fail, good CIA reporting, etc — why did we do nothing to head it off? We
                    admitted in retrospect that Cyprus was a very strategic piece of real estate
                    between two NATO allies which alone should have pushed us to try to head off the
                    “predictable” crisis. And of course this was on top of the fact that we had
                    failed to recognize the problem for what it was in the 1950s, that is, simply
                    another problem of a colonial people wanting self-determination. It was
                    complicated by the fact that self-determination for the Greek Cypriots meant
                    union with Greece. And the fact that 20% of the population was Turkish Cypriot
                    made it even more difficult. However, we handled it poorly all along, and that
                    is something else which has haunted me all these years. It is of more than
                    passing interest to me, in looking at the problems in the area overall, that the
                    Turkish Kurds constitute 20% of the population of Turkey, as the Turkish
                    Cypriots were 20% of the population of Cyprus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any feeling about what the CIA — I'm not
                        trying to drag out dirty secrets — but any feeling how the CIA types were
                        getting their information? What were they seeing that you weren't
                        seeing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I have reason to believe that they had a very good source, very close
                    to the government. Everybody knew everybody else in Cyprus, and after I became
                    Cyprus Desk Officer and did read their reporting, I tried to figure out who the
                    source was. I finally decided that it was A, B or C. I tried this on one of my
                    old Agency friends from Cyprus, telling him that I never could figure out who
                    that source was. “Who do you think it was?” he asked. I replied that I thought
                    it was A, B or C. He replied laughingly that those were good guesses but that he
                    could not tell me more than that. I now think I know who it was and it was
                    indeed a very good source close to the center of things in Nicosia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you getting, both from Ambassador Wilkins and
                        the rest of the Embassy who were dealing with it, and you yourself, about
                        Makarios at the time, how effective he was, for example? What was your
                        impression of how he was handling the situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: I say with hindsight that the person most responsible for the failure
                    of the London-Zurich Agreements was Makarios. While we recognized that he was
                    determined to amend or revise the agreements, I am not sure we really knew how
                    far he was prepared to go, and in truth Nancy Crawshaw, the British writer and
                    authority on Cyprus, says that Makarios was taken aback by the reaction to his
                    suggestions for constitutional amendment. The government was a presidential
                    system, with, constitutionally, a president who was always Greek Cypriot and a
                    Vice President who was always Turkish Cypriot. Of the ten cabinet ministers, 7
                    were Greek, 3 were Turkish. (Of course, Makarios gave the Turkish Cypriots the
                    less important ministries, he thought, though it did not work out that way
                    entirely.)It bears mention that certainly in 1963, and maybe even earlier,
                    Makarios thought he had UK support for constitutional reform. I myself accept
                    that the Brits did indicate some support for reform, and must perforce accept
                    some of the blame for the blow-up. As a footnote, this is documented in
                    Clerides's book.</p>
                <p>With Makarios, one never knew where the line between president and priest came,
                    since he continued to exercise such priestly duties as performing marriages,
                    presiding at engagement ceremonies, baptizing children, etc.</p>
                <p>Another thing that has bothered me in retrospect is that I think we never
                    realized that, under his clerical robes, there was a Cyprus peasant priest. He
                    was very shrewd, you might say cunning, but underneath he was a Paphos peasant
                    who wanted to put the Turkish Cypriots in their places. He was determined from
                    the very beginning to revise the constitution, even though the London-Zurich
                    Agreements did not allow revision. The popular perception of Makarios was that
                    he was a wise, intelligent, world figure who could hold his own on the world
                    stage. I believe, as I said above, that he was a very shrewd village priest
                    skilled in the way of the Byzantines, always pushing his adversary to the brink,
                    but always with his eye on the prize, which was a Cyprus dominated and governed
                    by the Greek Cypriot majority with adequate safeguards for the Turkish Cypriot
                    minority,</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was his determination to revise the constitution supported
                        by most of the Greek community that you talked to? Were there real problems,
                        or were there perceived problems with the Turkish minority?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>M. McCASKILL: While some Greek Cypriots may have been more moderate than others,
                    all, deep in their hearts, felt that the Agreements were unfair and that the
                    constitution needed revision. For all of its shortcomings, the London-Zurich
                    Agreements could have worked with a modicum of good faith on both sides. I
                    think, for example, if Makarios had given freely the 30% of the civil service to
                    the Turkish Cypriots, if he had been more generous with the Turkish Cypriot
                    community, it might have worked. The Turkish Cypriots were simply not up to
                    partnership with the Greek Cypriots, and they would have been overwhelmed by the
                    Greek Cypriots in time. I am speaking here of the long term. But in that regard
                    we must remember that Cyprus became independent in 1960, 33 years ago. Who knows
                    what might have evolved, peacefully, by now. I personally feel, as I may have
                    said previously, that Cyprus would be a unitary state dominated by the majority
                    Greek Cypriots.</p>
                <p>The Turks were very aware of what London-Zurich had given them, and they would
                    have opposed each Greek encroachment strenuously. But I still feel, that over
                    time, the Greek Cypriots would have had things their way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather that it was a fairly submissive, not overly
                        educated community. In other words, it did not have strong leadership?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: The Turkish Cypriot community had one real leader, Rauf Denktash, very
                    bright, very fast on his feet, and heads and shoulders above anybody else in the
                    community. Fazil Kucuk was the nominal leader, but in truth Denktash had pushed
                    Kucuk aside. I believe that, after the troubles started, no solution but
                    partition was acceptable to Rauf Denktash, and the Greek Cypriots played right
                    into his hands. In the late 1950s, the Turkish Cypriots had countered the Greek
                    demands for union with demands for partition. In fact, the Turkish Cypriots had
                    traditionally taken that tack. So partition was not a new concept.As I indicated
                    previously, Denktash was very, very bright. He had been a Queen's Counsel, in
                    Cyprus, and had tried some very delicate Greek Cypriot cases during the EOKA
                    period, I think maybe the first cases of Greek Cypriots sentenced to hang. It is
                    not beyond the realm of reason to assume that the British pushed him to the fore
                    in the Turkish Cypriot community. It is the kind of thing the UK did throughout
                    the former colonies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have the feeling that the Greek Government in
                        Athens was meddling in Cyprus's affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: On the contrary, Athens was carefully trying to distance itself from
                    Cyprus in those early days after independence. The two Greek Ambassadors during
                    that four years were highly able career men who were apparently under
                    instructions to try to make London-Zurich work. At least one of them, to my
                    knowledge, would become very irritated with Makarios's headstrong ways, and I
                    personally heard him talking about Makarios in very uncomplimentary terms at a
                    cocktail party. I thought, in fact, that his remarks on that occasion bordered
                    on indiscretion. When Makarios was hellbent on constitutional reform, then Greek
                    Foreign Minister Evangelos Averoff wrote him a rather strong letter advising
                    against such a move. Averoff himself told me once in Athens when I was last
                    stationed there that those first three years of Cyprus's independence were “a
                    real honeymoon” between Greece and Turkey. Averoff blamed Makarios for the
                    blow-up, and made no effort to hide his resentment concerning the way things had
                    gone. In that regard, the London-Zurich Agreements were concluded when Averoff
                    was Foreign Minister, so he had a personal stake in seeing them work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about Grivas and the other EOKA people? Where were
                        they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Grivas had left the island by that time. I can't remember just when
                    but he left after the Agreements were signed. He went to Athens where he formed
                    a political party, I believe, and fell flat on his face. He did not go back to
                    the island until 1964, after the troubles had started again. Many of the
                    original EOKA fighters had been taken into Makarios's government, many of them
                    as members of the Parliament.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the blow-up happen? How did you and other in the
                        Embassy see this thing? Give us some personal accounts.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: We had good information from the Agency that both sides were arming,
                    were forming paramilitary units to oppose the expected attacks of the other.
                    That both communities were arming has been confirmed by Glafkos Clerides, the
                    present President of Cyprus, in his book entitled My Deposition. The Greeks had
                    even begun patrols around the Turkish quarter of Nicosia, under the leadership
                    of the Minister of Interior, a former EOKA fighter and real gunman. Apparently
                    the Greek Cypriots had information that the Turks had received several shipments
                    of rifles that they were going to distribute. Each side knew the other was
                    arming and tension was escalating between them.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>On the night of December 22, 1963, a Turkish Cypriot car with four Turkish
                    Cypriots in it was returning to the Turkish quarter. They were actually in the
                    red light district of Nicosia, a sort of no man's land between the two quarters,
                    though in thinking about it I guess the red light district could not, per se, be
                    a “no-man's land”. Anyway, the Turks were stopped by a group of Greek Cypriot
                    policemen and ordered out of the car. Shooting ensued — who knows who fired the
                    first shot — two or three Turkish Cypriots were killed and a Greek Cypriot
                    policeman was killed. That started it. An incident like that started it.</p>
                <p>We were having a party that night; it was the day before our wedding anniversary
                    and we were having some friends from the Embassy in for dinner. We went ahead
                    with the party despite the fact that the tension all over town was unlike
                    anything I had ever experienced, an almost warlike-atmosphere all over town.
                    Houses were shuttered up, traffic was at a minimum, there was a feeling that
                    people were preparing for something.A Turkish Cypriot Embassy driver who helped
                    at parties was to work at our house that night. He stopped by about 5:00 p.m. to
                    say he could not work: he may have been exaggerating, but he told me that if he
                    were not shot coming out of the Turkish quarter, he would be shot going back in.
                    He was obviously terrified. He got back into the Turkish quarter all right and I
                    did not see him for three or four months. He could not come to work, and I made
                    arrangements to go into the Turkish quarter one day three or four months later
                    and see him.</p>
                <p>We made it through the party and our guests got home safely. The next day, a
                    Sunday, December 23, dawned clear and tense. I will never forget the tension
                    throughout town. Nobody moved. People were obviously hunkered down. A firefight
                    broke out in the early evening about a mile as the crow flies from my house. You
                    could smell the gun smoke in my yard. The whole staff headed over to the
                    Embassy, though I can't remember what we did except to try to get a handle on
                    the situation and report it to Washington. Everybody on the staff seemed to
                    realize that that was the beginning of what would be a very bad period.I can't
                    remember the details, but I know that we went on to a sort of war-time footing,
                    certainly an emergency footing. We set up an Operations Room (I think that's
                    what we called it) which followed events closely and began regular sitreps to
                    the Department. Our DCM was on home leave at the time, so we were missing one of
                    our substantive staff. This threw some burden on the rest of us. As I recall,
                    the Political Officer, the Consular Officer and I manned the Control Room; the
                    Consular Officer and I did a good part of it. It is my recollection that I
                    actually drafted many, if not most, of the sitreps. We were working long, hard
                    hours, with almost no time out even for Christmas dinner. For a time, we were
                    working around the clock.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>An interesting note: we had, to my knowledge, three overflights of two planes
                    each by the Turkish Air Force in the period right around Christmas. In a
                    Security Council meeting of December 26 or thereabouts, the Turks denied all but
                    one of the overflights, and I believe the Turkish Ambassador in Washington
                    denied the reports when he was called in by Assistant Secretary Phil Talbot. The
                    Department instructed us to be very careful in reporting overflights, but there
                    was no doubt in the minds of many of us that overflights had occurred. Who else
                    would be breaking the sound barrier over Nicosia in fighter planes with red
                    markings?</p>
                <p>Ambassador Wilkins and the Acting British High Commissioner, Cyril Pickard, were
                    very active in trying to dampen things down and work out a cease fire. (The
                    British High Commissioner was in England when the trouble broke, for reasons I
                    cannot recall.) The city had rapidly become divided, as the Turkish Cypriots
                    withdrew into what was obviously a preconceived position in the northern part of
                    Nicosia in the direction of the small port of Kyrenia on the north coast.
                    Information available to us indicated that their emergency planning called for
                    them to take the Kyrenia road as far as the pass in the Kyrenia mountains, since
                    Turkish relief for the Turkish Cypriots would come through the north and into
                    Nicosia through the Kyrenia pass. That is in fact what happened in 1974 when the
                    Turks invaded. The northern coast of Cyprus was only 40 miles from the Turkish
                    mainland and that was the logical route for an invasion force.</p>
                <p>But right away the city became divided, a sort of miniature Berlin. Sir Duncan
                    Sandys, I believe Commonwealth Secretary at the time, came out to try to help
                    keep the situation under control and cobble together a cease-fire. The Green
                    Line, the line dividing the two communities, came into being when a British army
                    officer engaged in the peace efforts drew a line on the map with a green crayon.
                    The Green Line stands to this day, though it has undergone some changes in the
                    30 years since it was drawn.</p>
                <p>One time, Ambassador Wilkins was returning from the Turkish quarter where he had
                    gone on official business, and he was stopped at a checkpoint and some young
                    punk, a member of one of the paramilitary groups roaming the city, pointed a gun
                    at the Ambassador's head. Ambassador Wilkins never confirmed that story to me,
                    but I have always believed it. It gives a little of the atmosphere in the city
                    at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying you all were working around the clock.
                        What were you, as an Embassy, doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: As I said, we were manning the Operations Center, reporting
                    developments on the island in as great detail as we could. Remember that the
                    possibility of war between Greece and Turkey seemed very possible and we were
                    doing anything, everything we could to dampen down the situation to avoid
                    Turkish action. We wanted the Department and Athens and Ankara to be as fully
                    informed as possible since they were working as hard as we to avoid any further
                    tragic developments. All Embassy staff reported everything they heard to us for
                    reporting and we reported up everything we got.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Other than reporting were we playing any role?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Of course. Ambassador Wilkins was in touch with the government all
                    along. For example, there was a reported sighting of a Turkish flotilla off the
                    northern coast of Cyprus. This was the sort of thing that could have provoked a
                    reaction from the Greeks; it terrorized the people on the north coast, including
                    some of our FBIS people. It was assumed of course that the Turks were headed
                    toward Cyprus. The Embassy checked this out with Washington, which checked it
                    with Ankara, and we were able to tell the Greeks and Greek Cypriots that it was
                    only a “Turkish exercise”. Of course, it was gunboat diplomacy, a show of force,
                    but we played a key role in reassuring the Greeks and Greek Cypriots that they
                    were not under immediate threat from the Turks.</p>
                <p>When we received that word, the Ambassador went to the Presidential Palace to
                    inform Makarios. He could not find Makarios so delivered the message to some of
                    his people there. When the Ambassador twitted Makarios about this later, the
                    Archbishop said he figured that if the Turks were determined to invade, there
                    was nothing he could do to stop it so he said his prayers and went to bed.</p>
                <p>But that was the kind of thing we could do: act as middle man between the Turks
                    and Greeks, and try to put out the fires as best we could.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you getting much from out embassies in Athens and
                        Ankara? Did they appear to have “gone local”, as some of our embassies have
                        been accused of doing? Or did you find reporting from there pretty
                        professional?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: I think we found them very professional. They were advising caution
                    and restraint, certainly in Ankara. In Ankara Ambassador Hare was advising the
                    Turks not to do anything precipitously because we did have reports from Ankara
                    that the Turkish military was very steamed up about how Turkish Cypriots were
                    getting killed. There was one awful incident that understandably aroused the
                    Turks: a Turkish army officer's wife — remember that there was a Turkish army
                    contingent on the island in conformity with the Treaty of Alliance — and three
                    children took refuge in the bathtub, where they were found by some Greek Cypriot
                    paramilitary forces and killed right where they had tried to hide. Pictures of
                    the bodies were circulated in Cyprus and on the mainland, and according to
                    reports, really got the Turkish military steamed up. So the Turkish government
                    needed to be cautioned to exercise restraint. The reporting from Ambassador Hare
                    was, as would be expected, very professional and very helpful.</p>
                <p>There were three very real invasion scares in the space of several months. One
                    was the last week of December; one on Friday, March 13, 1964; (I remember well
                    because I was the Embassy duty officer; Ambassador Hare really thought they were
                    coming then); and one was in June. When the so-called Johnson-Inonu letter was
                    sent to Ankara calling off the Turks in very blunt terms.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you leave Cyprus?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I didn't leave until July, so I was there for seven months of the
                    emergency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During that seven months, what were the main things you
                        were doing and experiencing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Well, we were reporting on what was going on, as I have mentioned. I
                    did not do a lot of economic reporting during the seven months after the
                    troubles started, since it was difficult to focus on it when the island was
                    threatening to go up in smoke. I was doing more political work, getting out and
                    talking to people.</p>
                <p>It was interesting how the violence spread from town to town. I have forgotten
                    the precise sequence, but it started in Nicosia, and went from there to
                    Limassol; from there it hopped over to Paphos; then to Famagusta, and finally to
                    Larnaca.</p>
                <p>The United Nations peacekeeping Force in Cyprus, known popularly by its acronym
                    UNFICYP, came in March, and we followed its progress as it settled in. In
                    addition to the peacekeeping force, two high ranking UN officials came to the
                    island about the same time: the UN Mediator, Former Finnish Prime Minister
                    Sakari Tuomioja, and the Secretary General's Special Representative on the
                    island, former Ecuadoran President, Mr. Galo Plaza. There was also a UN police
                    contingent. We kept in touch with all of these organizations and people,
                    exchanging information and views in order to broaden our understanding of the
                    situation.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were there, was it true that the Greek military
                        was beginning to get involved again?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes. This became known to us in the summer of 1960. Before I left the
                    Greeks had started putting troops on the island surreptitiously because they
                    felt that if the Turks took action, Greece would be at a marked disadvantage.
                    The Greeks were, in effect, trying to get a jump on the situation. I would have
                    to check the numbers, but they stayed until the confrontation of 1967 when
                    Athens agreed to withdraw them. It is interesting that they went in in 1964,
                    when George Papandreou was in office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you hearing about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes, the Agency was getting reports on it, but the troops were pretty
                    well hidden up in the hills, in restricted areas. The Greeks and Greek Cypriots
                    did a good job keeping it quiet, bringing the troops in at night, drawing the
                    curtains on the buses, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By the time you left, what was your feeling, and that of
                        the rest of the Embassy, about whither Cyprus?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: When I left the island I think the general feeling in the Embassy was
                    that the situation could not go on for long. The Turkish Cypriots were suffering
                    some privation. Fresh vegetables and seafood were limited in the Turkish quarter
                    because of travel restrictions on the community; a friend of mine who had been a
                    ranking officer in the Ministry of Agriculture told me that they received only
                    two gallons of gasoline a week. This same friend said that he felt “terribly
                    hemmed in”, with no place to go. Make no mistake about it: the Turkish Cypriots
                    were under siege. They had only two telephone lines in and out of the Turkish
                    quarter at one time. Their electricity and water were never cut, simply because
                    cooler heads on the Greek side knew that such drastic action would bring Turkey
                    in for sure and prevailed on the more radical elements. When I told one good
                    friend goodbye, the day before I left the island, I honestly felt that they
                    could not hold out another six to eight months. And there, of course, was one of
                    our basic mistakes. I think my view was held by many people, but we were
                    obviously wrong. I see in retrospect that the Turkish Cypriots, with Turkey's
                    support, were prepared to sit there until hell froze over. But I think many of
                    us felt that the Turkish Cypriots would, within several months, probably fold
                    up. One mistake we Americans make in diplomacy is to think in short terms; in
                    the Middle East, a year is as a day, or something like that, and things move
                    slowly, slowly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a feeling that the Turkish Government could not
                        stand by and watch them fold up?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: When I say “fold up”, I think we were thinking that they would come to
                    terms with the Greek Cypriots, decide that anything was better than the way they
                    were living, and just decide to live together again on the Greek Cypriots'
                    terms, that is, with the Greek Cypriots as the majority, the Turkish Cypriots as
                    the minority with certain safeguards.</p>
                <p>One of the primary goals of the United States then was to avoid seeing Turkey
                    humiliated. We simply would not stand by and see Turkey humiliated by a
                    settlement. The Turks knew that, of course, and they exploited it for all it was
                    worth. This has become institutionalized in the Department, I believe, and this
                    attitude, perhaps modified over the years, continues until today.</p>
                <p>In the spring of 1964, there was a rumor in the Turkish quarter that we were
                    considering an exchange of populations settlement. I am sure this was kicked
                    around in the Department but I do not know that it ever reached the Seventh
                    Floor. Our reply to inquiries concerning solutions was that we would support any
                    solution arrived at by the parties. We were obviously very much involved in the
                    search for a solution — i. e., the Acheson mission in the summer of 1964 —
                    though we would have denied that we would try to force a settlement on the
                    parties.I have wondered over the years if the Cyprus Problem were not a
                    Muslim-Christian problem, and I am not sure that is not at the root of it. I
                    could never satisfactorily explain why people who otherwise seemed normal would
                    want to go out and wantonly kill their fellow islanders.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Look at what is happening today, in 1993, in Yugoslavia
                        particularly. Ethnicity is such a strong, strong force that it permeates
                        everything. And this seems true of some of the Muslims, who carry the virus
                        on many grounds. At least they make the ground fertile.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I just wanted to make one last point before we break, and that is that
                    there seemed to be a sort of lemming instinct in Cyprus. Certainly the Greek
                    Cypriots seemed hellbent on self-destruction. We used to talk about this in the
                    Embassy and agreed that it was true.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is September 21, 1993. You said you wanted to add
                        something about the Ball visit and how the system worked?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: Under Secretary Ball came to Cyprus in mid-February (1964) with a
                    peace plan, accompanied by Mr. Sisco, then Assistant Secretary for International
                    Organization Affairs, Ambassador Jack Jernegan, an old NEA/GTI hand who was then
                    a Deputy Assistant Secretary for NEA, and I believe a Mr. Greenfield, who was
                    Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs. Mr. Ball apparently decided during the
                    trip that the problem required a change in Ambassadors, and after his return,
                    Ambassador Wilkins was called home on consultation.We learned soon after he left
                    that then FSO-2 Taylor G. (Toby) Belcher who, you remember, had been Consul
                    General in Nicosia from 1957 to 1960, was coming out to “cover” in Ambassador
                    Wilkins' absence, a most unusual sort of move. The DCM, who had returned from
                    home leave, was pushed aside and was understandably irate, since this didn't say
                    much for the Department's confidence in him. Toby told us in a staff meeting
                    that he would actually be the new Ambassador. But it was an embarrassing
                    situation, for Wilkins, for Toby, and for the DCM. The Department was late in
                    getting Toby's orders to return to Washington to him, so he was still in Nicosia
                    when Wilkins arrived back. We had, at one time, Ambassador Wilkins,
                    “Ambassador-Designate” Belcher and a DCM, all there together. To say it was a
                    bit awkward is putting it mildly, and the Department handled it very, very
                    poorly.</p>
                <p>On the action side, in early February a bomb exploded at the Embassy and
                    Ambassador Wilkins rather quickly ordered the evacuation of all dependents. It
                    was a controversial move, but he announced it on Cyprus television the evening
                    after the bomb exploded and he could not back down. Whether we should have
                    evacuated would probably still be argued among those of us who were there. Not
                    all of the Embassy wives had left by the time Mr. Ball arrived and I heard that
                    he was furious that some were still there and gave the remaining dependents just
                    a few days to leave. My own wife and sons were among those who had not left and
                    as I remember they had about two days to get packed and get a booking home. I
                    felt then and still feel that evacuation was probably not called for at that
                    time, but in truth there was a large American community — communications
                    dependents, etc. — and I think Ambassador Wilkins felt personally responsible
                    for them all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came back to the Cyprus Desk where you served from
                        1964 to 1967?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Actually I was assigned to NE/E at first. In those days there were
                    four offices in the old NEA Bureau: the Office of Near Eastern Affairs (NE); the
                    Office of Greek, Turkish and Iranian Affairs (GTI), where the Cyprus Desk was
                    located; the Office of South Asian Affairs (SOA), which included India,
                    Pakistan, Afghanistan, and Sri Lanka; and an Office of Regional Affairs. I was
                    assigned to the economics section of NE and I worked on Arab/Israel economic
                    affairs for about six months. Gordon King, the Cyprus Desk Officer and a friend
                    of mine, wanted to make a change and left to go to the Peace Corps.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>When I went to GTI, every Desk Officer in the office had served in the country
                    for which he was responsible or otherwise had experience in the area: I had
                    served in Cyprus for four years and my number two had served in Turkey; the
                    Turkish Desk Officer and his assistant had both served in Turkey; both officers
                    on the Greek Desk had served in Greece, and both of those on the Iranian Desk
                    had served in Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A very strong office.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: We thought so at the time. The Office Director herself had actually
                    served in Greece, Turkey and Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Kay Bracken. I think she was an FSO-1 at the time. Her deputy, John
                    Howison, had served in Iran and I believe Turkey. So we had a tremendous amount
                    of area expertise in GTI. I think those two years in GTI may have been among my
                    most enjoyable in my 35 years in the Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were on the Cyprus Desk, what were the main
                        issues you had to deal with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: The main issue, of course, was the Cyprus Problem and a solution for
                    it. We had very knowledgeable people not only in GTI but in all of Washington. I
                    felt at the time that there was probably as much Cyprus expertise in Washington
                    as there was in any capital. We spent an inordinate amount of time “looking for
                    a solution”, trying to get a mix that we thought would fly. We were an ad hoc
                    kind of group: we had coffee together, we had lunch together, we took a walk
                    after lunch during the day, all the time bouncing ideas off each other.</p>
                <p>A corollary was keeping the Greeks and Turks apart. The UN peacekeeping force in
                    Cyprus was a relatively large force when it came into being in March, 1964,
                    6-7,000 men.</p>
                <p>I might digress to tell you an interesting anecdote. Dr. Ralph Bunche, the Number
                    Two in the UN, visited the island in March, 1964 to see the problem for himself
                    and report to the Secretary General. At his departure statement he said that he
                    was glad that he had come to Cyprus to see this “incoherent war” for himself,
                    since one could not always understand it from New York. However, he went on,
                    once in Cyprus, one could not always believe what one saw. I still have the
                    clipping reporting his press conference and even started a paper one time
                    entitled “The Incoherent War”, giving Dr. Bunche the credit for the very apt
                    description of the situation.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>Cyprus was obviously getting top billing, with a Bunche visit, and the
                    appointment of Mr. Tuomioja and Mr. Galo Plazo, both of whom I have
                    mentioned.</p>
                <p>To get back to my original point, another focus of our activity was keeping the
                    Greeks and Turks apart with the help of the United Nations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There wasn't a real line was there? I mean there were
                        Turkish villages and Greek villages all intermingled.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: There was the line in Nicosia which I have mentioned known as “The
                    Green Line”. There were fairly clear dividing lines in all the five towns, where
                    the Turkish Cypriots had withdrawn into the Turkish quarter for security
                    reasons. But in the countryside, there were still some mixed villages. There was
                    not much interchange between the two communities, and even the villages were
                    divided to some extent, but not to the degree the towns were divided.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying you were sitting around with your
                        colleagues trying to find a solution. Was there any consensus? I mean, what
                        did you feel were some of your options, and what were the thoughts at the
                        expert level?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: It's hard to remember what some of those were. One of our first
                    approaches was to try to find out precisely what Turkey wanted so that we could
                    work with them from there. We had the problem of trying to find a solution that
                    included ironclad safeguards for the Turkish community. I think we believed that
                    the Turks could not hope to regain their “equal community” status they had
                    gotten from London-Zurich.</p>
                <p>I have wondered over the years where the “equal community” concept came from and
                    have concluded that it was an outgrowth of the old Ottoman millet system, when
                    the Ottomans administered minority communities in the Ottoman Empire through the
                    community heads. In Cyprus, for example, the head of the Greek Cypriot community
                    was the Ethnarch, who happened to be the Archbishop of the Church of Cyprus at
                    the time. All taxes, administrative decrees, etc., directed at his community,
                    were administered through him.</p>
                <p>Our task was to find some balance that would satisfy the Greeks and the Turks,
                    with security the first consideration. We got some indication of the Turks'
                    requirements out of the Ankara, four or five things that all meant the same
                    thing: no domination of one community by the other, equal participation of both
                    communities in the government, and that sort of thing. The Turks spoke about
                    “not upsetting the balance of the Treaty of Lausanne in the area” but one hears
                    little of that out of Ankara since Turkey itself upset the balance with its
                    invasion in 1974.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>We spent a lot of time working on this. We considered such things as territorial
                    compensation for the Turks if the island were united with Greece. For example,
                    former Secretary Acheson's mission in the summer of 1964 envisaged a permanent
                    Turkish base on the island. This was unacceptable to the Greeks; when it was
                    scaled down to a long-term lease base for the Turks, they rejected that. In
                    looking back, it may have been impossible to find the right package at that
                    time. And that itself is meaningful, that is, “the right package at the right
                    time”, since timing was extremely important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the general feeling that the Greeks would not treat
                        the Turks kindly if they got control?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I'm not sure that feeling was prevalent. I think there was a feeling
                    among the working level types that it should be a “Greek Cypriot solution”. The
                    Greeks were, after all, 80-82% of the population. I think that we all felt that
                    it had to be a majority rule. The precedent in Greece led us to believe that the
                    Greeks would not, could not, persecute the Turks without fear of intervention
                    from Turkey. Still, the Greeks looked upon the Turks as the hewers of wood and
                    drawers of water, and would not be happy until they were firmly relegated to
                    that status. The Greek Cypriots, like all Greeks everywhere, felt themselves
                    culturally superior to the Turks, and would find it difficult to accord the
                    Turks anything but minority status.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard people come back and say, when all is said and
                        done, that the Greeks really aren't very nice to the Turks.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Let me answer that with an anecdote. When I gave the party in Limassol
                    I referred to previously, I was standing at the door of the restaurant greeting
                    my guests. I was chatting with a Greek Cypriot businessman from a rather
                    prominent family, when another guest approached. When the man was within
                    earshot, the Greek Cypriot said to me “Oh, Mr. McCaskill, here comes Mr.
                    So-and-So. He's a good Turk.” I thought that if I had been that Turkish Cypriot
                    I would have hated that Greek Cypriot's guts. Mind you, if the shoe had been on
                    the other foot the same attitude might have prevailed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you think it could be solved?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I think I did then. I must have. I was told one time by a colleague,
                    who was then Political Counselor in Ankara, that I never “gave up”. So I must
                    have thought so then. I've become jaded over these 30 years. I've lost some of
                    the enthusiasm I had then, but I can only believe that I must have thought so at
                    the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the thinking in the higher reaches of NEA, and
                        even further up in the Department about Cyprus. Was this just a pain in the
                        neck, fouling up NATO? Also how was Makarios viewed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Cyprus had top level attention in the Department from late 1963 for
                    several years. There was some commitment on the Seventh Floor, where our efforts
                    were led by Mr. Ball, that Cyprus would not be allowed to destroy NATO. Mr. Ball
                    himself tried to put a solution together, again determined not to let Cyprus
                    ruin NATO. It is hard for me today to remember the amount of very high-level
                    this problem, which seems small potatoes when compared to the Balkans, was
                    getting.</p>
                <p>I have mentioned our concern with the Communist menace. I don't think I mentioned
                    that three of the five mayors in the island were Communists. I mentioned the
                    large Soviet mission. Cyprus was disrupting NATO; the southeast flank was
                    impaired by Cyprus. President Kennedy, before his death, felt we should do
                    something, though I never saw what he wanted to do spelled out.</p>
                <p>Makarios was looked upon back in Washington as a very unsavory, untrustworthy,
                    unpredictable man, and, I might add, very uncooperative. That was in part
                    because he had taken Cyprus into the Non-Aligned Movement in 1961, looking ahead
                    to the time when he would need Non-Aligned support in the UN. Mr. Ball had a
                    very bad impression of Makarios, regarding him as very slippery (though he
                    referred to Makarios once as one of the most intelligent people he had ever
                    dealt with.) Mr. Ball never really understood that Makarios was a genuine
                    Byzantine. Andreas Papandreou referred to Makarios once as a “tribal
                    chieftain.”</p>
                <p>I don't remember where I got the impression, but to recall that President Kennedy
                    and Makarios got along very well during the Archbishop's official visit to
                    Washington. This is in fact another example of the attention being given to
                    Cyprus. Kennedy told him, much to Makarios's chagrin, I assume, that he thought
                    the London-Zurich Agreements were about the best he could get and that he should
                    in effect grin and bear it.</p>
                <p>People back here did mistrust Makarios a great deal. He was not yet, at that
                    time, known as “the Red Priest” or “the Red Archbishop”, or the Castro of the
                    Mediterranean”. This mistrust carried over to the Kissinger days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In an interview with Bill Crawford, regarding the meeting
                        of Kissinger and Makarios in the elevator, Kissinger remarked that “In
                        person, Your Beatitude, you're really very charming.” Makarios looked at him
                        and said, “It only lasts a little while.”</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: Actually, a man who knew Makarios very well, Patroclos Stavrou, told
                    me that Makarios was at heart a royalist. Peter Ramsbottam, the British High
                    Commissioner in Cyprus back a number of years ago, said the same thing in an
                    article he wrote. Stavrou told me that Makarios had pictures of the King and
                    Queen in his bedroom, and that if Makarios were anything, he was a royalist. He
                    was a Cypriot royalist, if we believe these two men who knew him well. He was on
                    fairly good terms with Greek King Constantine, Greece's last king, though I
                    can't remember whether it was Stavrou who told me that or Ramsbottam who
                    mentioned it in his article.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From your vantage point, what were our priorities in that
                        part of the world? Obviously we were concerned about the Soviets, and
                        worried about the southeast flank of NATO. In the Greco-Turkish
                        relationship, we always had to observe a kind of balance. I always had the
                        feeling that Turkey really was the military leader, and we just had to sort
                        of keep the Greeks happy for its real estate, but not much else. What was
                        your feeling?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: As I mentioned earlier, I think our tilt toward Turkey has become
                    institutionalized over the years. I can well understand the military/security
                    priority given to Turkey: its control of the Straits, its long land border with
                    the then-Soviet Union, etc. You only have to go through the Straits as a tourist
                    — as I have — to recognize their strategic value over the centuries. But the
                    Turks have exploited their advantages, as I have said before, and this was
                    always a matter of great chagrin to the Greeks.</p>
                <p>The Greeks traditionally point to the fact that they fought with us in both world
                    wars (while Turkey did not), that they have a big Greek-American community here,
                    and on and on. But down deep, I think they have come to accept it. Karamanlis
                    and Andreas Papandreou have both said publicly that “the road from Athens to
                    Washington passes through Ankara” or something like that. A Greek Foreign
                    Minister, addressing a group of American visitors some years ago, said that if,
                    for the sake of discussion, we accorded Greek and Turkish membership in NATO a
                    weight of 100, Turkey would be 65 of that and Greece would be 35. But, he said,
                    if Greece should withdraw from NATO, Turkey by itself would not be able to carry
                    the whole load, and would not be weighted at 65 by itself.</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>Over the years, Turkey has created the perception that it is the more dependable
                    ally, due in large part to the influence of the American military. But I wonder
                    if this would bear close scrutiny. For example, I have heard, but never
                    confirmed, that Turkey would not permit us to use our bases in Turkey when we
                    were mounting the effort to free our hostages in Iran. Secondly, Turkey would
                    not allow us to use our bases for the re-supply of our people in Lebanon in
                    1982-83. And there have three military governments in Turkey since 1960, though
                    Washington Turkologists are quick to point out that Turkish military governments
                    are “different” in that the Turkish military mounts coups to preserve
                    democracy!! I cite all of these things because the Greeks are aware of them and
                    it intensifies their chagrin at what they regard as Turkey's favored position in
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>The ratio in military assistance was set at 10 to 7, I believe in 1976, though I
                    am not sure whether it is still in effect. As I remember it, in 1976, a
                    multi-year agreement was negotiated with both Greece and Turkey, but never
                    signed, giving Turkey 1 billion dollars worth of assistance, and 7 hundred
                    million to Greece, an obvious ratio of 10-7. The Greeks grabbed on to this,
                    since it enabled them to maintain some parity with Turkey, which had suffered
                    somewhat from the arms embargo following the invasion of Cyprus in 1974. The
                    Greeks felt that 10-7 was to their advantage, and fought to keep it in effect.
                    As I noted, I do not know whether we still adhere to it, but I think that we do
                    not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the Greek Lobby when you were on the Desk? How
                        did they affect you at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: The Greek Lobby really was mobilized only after the invasion in 1974.
                    They were not a political force when I was on the Desk, though AHEPA and the
                    Archbishop were not averse to throwing their weight around if they thought it
                    would be helpful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there certain Congressmen, particularly of Greek
                        ancestry, sort of on you? Or was that a fairly benign period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: It was a benign period, as far as that was concerned. We had other
                    worries, of course, that arose when Greece and Turkey almost went to war in 1967
                    and Secretary Vance went to the area to promote a settlement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I can't remember which happened first, Vance going out or
                        the April 1967 coup? Which happened first?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: The coup occurred first.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you on the Desk at that time:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I was on the Desk when the coup took place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you talk about how that came? I'm sure you must have
                        been involved and what were the reactions to it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Much of this is hazy to me, because we Cyprus types were not directly
                    involved. The Greek Country Directorate, as it had become in 1966, had primary
                    responsibility under the direct supervision of the Assistant Secretary and the
                    Deputy Assistant Secretary.The coup occurred on April 21, 1967. Greece had been
                    terribly unstable politically since Karamanlis resigned in 1963. You may recall
                    that he had some difficulties with the palace over an official visit of Queen
                    Frederika and her daughter Sophia to Britain. The Greek constitution required
                    that the royal family had to secure permission of the government before any
                    member of the Royal Family could travel abroad. There was a rather famous old
                    Greek Communist, Tony Ambatielos, who had been imprisoned by Greece during the
                    war and who, after his release, was still involved in anti-government
                    activity.</p>
                <p>Ambatielos's wife Betty, who I believe was British, was quite active in Britain,
                    particularly in anti-Greek demonstrations, etc. She threatened, with
                    considerable support from communist/leftist groups, to demonstrate again
                    Frederika and Sophia if they visited Britain. I've forgotten the details of the
                    trip, but I believe the British Royal Family had invited Frederika, and I have
                    forgotten why Frederika was so determined to go. But the Karamanlis Government
                    refused to give her permission. She went anyway, there were demonstrations
                    against her, and she and Sophia on one occasion had literally to run from a mob.
                    Karamanlis resigned over the issue — I believe in July of 1963. A caretaker
                    government was formed, elections were held in November, 1963, and George
                    Papandreou obtained a plurality. Since he did not have a working majority, he
                    took a chapter from John Diefenbaker's book and right away dissolved the
                    Parliament and called new elections in February 1964. Papandreou and his liberal
                    party won a good working. I've forgotten what they called the party by then but
                    it was essentially the old Liberal Party.</p>
                <p>George Papandreou governed until 1965 when the great “apostasia” occurred: enough
                    of Papandreou's deputies were bought off — and I mean that literally — to bring
                    his government down and from then until the coup in 1967 Greece was in a period
                    of great political instability. There was a succession of weak governments until
                    elections were finally called for May 1967.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>It soon became clear that Papandreou was running very, very strong and would
                    probably win. It was being bandied about that if Papandreou were indeed elected,
                    a coup would take place. This centered for the most part on speculation
                    concerning the so-called “palace coup” or “generals' coup”, a coup by a group of
                    high-ranking Greek officers with palace blessing.When the coup finally took
                    place, on April 21, 1967, it was led by three colonels: Papadopoulos, who
                    emerged later as the real brains of the group; Pattakos; and Makarezos. They
                    were unknown in Washington. I called a contact in Langley the morning the coup
                    occurred and asked who Papadopoulos was. My interlocutor professed not to know,
                    though I think in retrospect that he was probably dissembling with me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Colonel Papadopoulos was on their payroll at one time but
                        there are a lot of Papadopouloses.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: But it is a fact that my contact told me, and as nearly as I can
                    remember his words, “We don't know who he is.” Let me repeat that we thought
                    that if there were a coup, it would be a palace coup at least with palace
                    blessing. And Embassy Athens was doing what it could to head off that
                    possibility. When it came, it was a real shock here. I would like to say again
                    that the Cyprus people were on the fringes of what was going on — we worked
                    closely with the Greek people, of course — and some of my recollections of this
                    period are hazy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was our feeling? I mean once the word came, what were
                        you all doing in NEA in your particular office?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I think, first, that we — NEA — were trying to figure out who these
                    guys were and what we might expect from them. And, of course, recovering from
                    the shock of a military coup in a NATO country. I learned later, from Merle
                    Miller's biography entitled Lyndon that there was some concern in the American
                    academic community that Andreas Papandreou, whom the junta had imprisoned, would
                    be shot. At J. K. Galbraith's request, Johnson intervened and whether or not
                    that was decisive, Papandreou was obviously not shot. When the exercise was
                    over, Johnson sent a message to Galbraith through Nicholas Katzenbach that “I've
                    told those Greek bastards to lay off that son of a bitch, whoever he is.”
                    Papandreou told this story himself sometime when I was last in the Embassy.</p>
                <p>But what the Department was doing, as I recall, was trying to determine who was
                    in charge, what had happened to the democratic process in Greece, whether our
                    old friends in Greece were in any danger, whether people were being arrested and
                    imprisoned, and so on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there concern about the NATO side of things at that
                        time or was it felt that this was going to be pretty much an internal thing
                        and this wasn't going to affect Greece internationally?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: As I have indicated, I am a bit hazy on much of this. Certainly as I
                    said before, we were concerned that a military coup had taken place in a NATO
                    country. Andreas Papandreou has always said that the colonels used a NATO plan
                    at the base of their own plans. It was considered a very efficient coup as coups
                    go. It was boom-boom and all over and done pretty quickly. I can't remember when
                    the question of recognition came up. The question of military shipments came up
                    — whether these would continue.</p>
                <p>I think history has established that what triggered the coup was the fear of the
                    election of George Papandreou and the role of Andreas in the Papandreou
                    Government. You recall that Andreas had returned to Greece in 1959, and had
                    immediately gotten into politics with his father. The Greek military had a deep
                    seated fear and mistrust of Andreas. It was the perception among the military
                    that if George were elected — and it was increasingly apparent that he would be
                    — Andreas would have a key role in the government. The military felt that that
                    would be disastrous for Greece.</p>
                <p>Let me give you an example of the influence he had on his father. You recall that
                    Dean Acheson had been asked by George Ball to go to Switzerland in the summer of
                    1964 to help the parties work out a solution to the Cyprus Problem. He was in
                    fact there for several weeks. This resulted in what has come to be known as the
                    Acheson Plan for Cyprus, generally regarded as an enosis solution, with Cyprus
                    going to Greece in return for the Turkish base I referred to earlier, first in
                    perpetuity, secondly on a 99 year lease.</p>
                <p>When I was last stationed in Athens from 1979 to 1983, I heard from two people
                    who were in a position to know — one of them in Papandreou's cabinet — that
                    Papandreou was prepared to accept the Acheson Plan. According to one version I
                    heard, Papandreou actually informed the cabinet meeting one evening that he was
                    prepared to accept. Then Makarios got to Andreas, Andreas got to his father, and
                    the Prime Minister reversed his decision. There is little doubt that he did have
                    considerable influence on his father. I believe that Christopher Woodhouse, in
                    his little book The Rise and Fall of the Greek Colonels, mentions that Andreas
                    persuaded his father to back away for support for the Acheson Plan.</p>
                <p>There was fear in the Greek military that Andreas was “leftist”, “radical”, etc.
                    Papadopoulos and his cohorts were all rabidly anti-communist, actually more than
                    a little unbalanced; they were men who had earned their bars fighting in the
                    communist guerrilla war. I think it is true that a man of Andreas's stripe could
                    have so aroused their fears and suspicions that they took the ultimate extreme
                    of implementing a military coup against the legitimate government of Greece.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the reaction from the Cyprus Desk? Here were some
                        ultra nationalists, known to be super nationalists. You were sitting on a
                        powder keg. What was you concern about Cyprus with this new crew in
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: We were concerned about how they would move, as indeed they did in
                    1974. Greek Army officers in general were always dedicated to enosis, the union
                    of Cyprus with Greece. They also had a deep mistrust of Makarios, whom they
                    considered “red”. There was a meeting in Alexandroupolis, near the Greek-Turkish
                    border, to try to negotiate an enosis solution. There were other meetings with
                    the Turks where they tried to negotiate an enosis solution, a rather serious
                    effort in Madrid. Makarios was repulsed by the very idea of a military coup, and
                    was as suspicious of the colonels as they were of him. He, Makarios, knew they
                    would try to negotiate a settlement of the problem with the Turks and impose it
                    on the island.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the plans for enosis that they were talking to the
                        Turks on of a practical nature did you feel? Was there any chance of
                        anything”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I would have to go back and check the provisions of various
                    negotiations. I have the recollection that the Greeks were surprised that the
                    Turks did not accept the proposals. Toby Belcher always said that the greatest
                    mistake we made with Makarios was in thinking we — meaning Greece, Turkey, the
                    UK, the US, NATO — could impose a solution on the island. Toby felt, and history
                    proved him right, that Makarios would find a way to scuttle any such efforts.
                    The failure of London-Zurich is itself proof of this, since as I said before, it
                    was Makarios who engineered the scuttling of the Agreements.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was our reaction as the Papadopoulos regime was
                        beginning to settle in? It was obviously very anti-democratic and aroused an
                        awful lot of opposition, certainly within the European intellectual
                        community, and somewhat within the American academic world. How long were
                        you dealing in NEA at that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Actually I left Cyprus Affairs in the summer of 1967, shortly after
                    the coup occurred. I was assigned to Farsi training in September 1967, with an
                    onward assignment a year later to the Political Section in Tehran. At that time,
                    we were still feeling our way in Greece.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was not a regime that we (1) expected, or (2) were
                        comfortable with. I served in Greece from 1970 to 1974, when Greeks pointed
                        the finger at us saying “Oh, the CIA did this and this is your
                        government.”</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: I don't believe that for a minute and have always refused to accept
                    it. I do think it was a surprise to us. I had a dear friend in Northern Greece
                    who said the same thing to me. When I denied it, he told me that he believed me
                    when I denied that I knew anything about a coup. But, he was always quick to add
                    — and we discussed this more than once — I was too junior to be privy to that
                    kind of information. You are right; it was a government that we had not expected
                    and we were not comfortable with it. I think we grew more comfortable with it
                    later. Greeks were always quick to point to the number of high level visitors to
                    Greece, including Spiro Agnew. As you know, the Greeks must blame somebody for
                    their problems, and this was a good example of that unfortunate trait.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is one of their traits. So what prompted you to go into
                        Farsi training, and go to Iran where you served from 1968 to 1972? What got
                        you going on that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I felt I needed to get out of Greek-Turkish-Cyprus affairs, and the
                    Number Two job in the Political Section in Tehran was opening up. I would
                    ordinarily have gone out in the summer of 1967, but the incumbent extended for a
                    year, leaving me in limbo since I had given up my Cyprus job. The NEA Personnel
                    Officer, then Orme Wilson, suggested that I go to Farsi training.</p>
                <p>I ended up getting a 3-3 in Farsi, which delighted me since I was the oldest of
                    the three students and the other two were really very good language students.
                    The tutor told me later that they rated me second among the three, which pleased
                    me no end. But then he might have told the other guy the same thing for all I
                    know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Iran from 1968 to 1972. What was the situation
                        there at this point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Iran was a strange place in many ways. I worked very hard the four
                    years we were there, and at the end I did not feel that I left many friends
                    there, Iranian, that is. The Iranians were hard to get close to. Life was good,
                    housing was good and easy to find. The Shah was a fascinating figure. But there
                    was really very little for political officers to do in Tehran because our
                    ability to get around was limited. For example, we talk about the mullahs today:
                    I doubt if anybody in the Embassy ever knew a mullah. They were inaccessible to
                    us. We speak or spoke about the Bazaaris; again, nobody in the Embassy knew any
                    Bazaaris. If we had wandered around the bazaars, somebody would have reported it
                    to SAVAK, the Shah's secret police, and we would have had a fairly severe
                    reaction from the government. In the Embassy, we knew a small number of the
                    establishment — government types, “politicians” (and I put that in quotation
                    marks since there was no politics as we know it), bankers/merchants, etc.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>And, of course, reporting was circumscribed in the Embassy. There were some
                    things just not reported. For example, a young officer in the Political Section
                    prepared an airgram to the effect that things were not as rosy in Iran as some
                    of our reporting indicated and as some people seemed to believe. The airgram,
                    not seen in the front office until after it went out, caused great consternation
                    there. An instruction subsequently came down that nothing was to go out of the
                    Political Section without the Political Counselor's clearance. This in turn
                    caused some chagrin in the Political Section. We felt that the Embassy's
                    reporting was not altogether honest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This brings up something that recurs all the time but
                        particularly during the latter part of the Nixon Administration. Kissinger
                        didn't want to hear anything bad. What was your feeling?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. McCaskill. I think that is true. Let me cite an example. I did a memorandum
                    of conversation one time based on a conversation with an Iranian journalist
                    representing an American wire service who was very pro-American, pro-Western,
                    who spoke good English, etc. The memorandum covered several subjects, one
                    entitled “Military Trials” or something to that effect. My interlocutor had told
                    me that there were political trials every day in the military courts because the
                    civil courts were full. The Political Counselor, my boss and a friend of mine,
                    would not approve the memcon, despite my protestations that I was only reporting
                    what my contact had told me. When I asked why it could not go, he replied that
                    there were some people in the Department and the White House, and possibly
                    others, who did not want to read anything unpleasant about Iran and did not want
                    anything detrimental to Iran to circulate in Washington. There were some people
                    in Washington, particularly on the Hill, looking for such things.</p>
                <p>At a Chiefs of Mission Conference in Iran in 1969 or 1970 when I was the note
                    taker, I heard the old cliche that Iran was “an island of stability in a
                    troubled area” a number of times. I think sincerely that this was our policy,
                    based on inadequate reporting. We simply did not want to report anything to the
                    contrary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There are two things here, extremely important. One is
                        that you don't want to rock the boat, create waves, and you won't be paid
                        attention to. That's one reason why one wouldn't report unpleasant things.
                        The other is even though you might feel — this is often the case of
                        corruption or something like that — if you report it back to Washington, the
                        way paper multiplies, that it will end up and be used against the regime
                        even though there may be mitigating circumstances. The other one is you
                        don't want to make people unhappy.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: I think it was more of the second in the case of Iran. I think there
                    were people in Washington looking critically at Iran from time to time. And I
                    think were was a genuine belief offsetting that that the Shah was our best bet
                    in that part of the world and we did not want to report anything that reflected
                    on him. We did not want anything to upset the flow of arms, so to speak. I think
                    there was a very strong feeling that he was our man in that part of the world.
                    We put a lot of time and effort into the Iranian army and air force, even though
                    we used to joke in the Embassy that that fiercest of armies in that part of the
                    world had never heard a shot fired in anger. But to repeat, we did not want
                    anything to reflect unfavorably on the Shah, did not want to report anything
                    unpleasant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about the Political Section. I have an
                        interview with Andrew Killgore who talks about his great frustration at the
                        time when he was in the Political Section that he was told just what he
                        could not report. This is what we're trained to do. You came from a place
                        where you were reporting, and you were talking to everybody in Cyprus from
                        all accounts, and here you are in this never-never world where you said you
                        were a political reporter who essentially did not report. Also talk
                        particularly about the junior officer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Well, it was the more junior officers that it affected mostly. The
                    most meaningful reporting was done by the Ambassador and/or the DCM and the
                    Political Counselor. Only the Ambassador saw the Shah, the Minister of Court and
                    the Foreign Minister. The DCM ran the Embassy, really, a sort of executive
                    officer.I was fortunate my last two years to be given responsibility for
                    reporting on the Persian Gulf. The British had announced publicly that they were
                    pulling out East of Suez, and Iran was being armed by us and groomed by the
                    British to fill the void when the Brits left. This was an extremely important
                    reporting function at the time, since there were significant developments every
                    two or three days. The career man in the Foreign Ministry responsible for the
                    Gulf on the Iranian side was apparently under orders to keep us completely
                    informed.</p>
                <p>The junior officers did the domestic reporting, such as it was. One junior
                    officer was assigned to do bio reporting and almost nothing else. As a result,
                    we had the most extensive bio files I ever saw anywhere. It was one of those
                    junior officers who wrote the youth airgram that caused the front office
                    flap.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Arnie Raphel, who, you may remember, died in that plane crash in
                    Pakistan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was Ambassador to Pakistan?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes, Ambassador to Pakistan. He was a brilliant officer who was a
                    pleasure to work with. It was his airgram that raised the front office's
                    hackles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the cold light of day, away from all of this, it sort
                        of negates everything we're supposed to be doing. Obviously, we're all
                        operating under orders, but when you see the obvious disaster ten years
                        later, you must wonder.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Iran is an obvious case where you can look back and ask “Who lost
                    Iran, when did we lose Iran?” I think there was some genuine belief in
                    Washington that Iran was the “island of stability”, based in part on inadequate
                    reporting from the Embassy over a long period. For his part, the Shah was
                    surrounded by sycophants who told him what he wanted to hear. I've done almost
                    no reading on Iran since I retired since I have been preoccupied with writing
                    and lecturing on Cyprus. So I don't know what the experts and scholars are
                    saying. And it may be a long time before the real story is told. I do know that
                    the initial mistake may have been the overthrow of Mossadegh and the restoration
                    of the Shah to the throne in 1953.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I hope we can use some of these conversations we're having
                        for future political officers to absorb how things happen. You say we
                        couldn't get to the mullahs, couldn't get to the Bazaaris. Do you see any
                        way at that time that we could have done more in getting to those people?
                        Were there any restrictions? Or was it just language, cultural? What was
                        stopping us from getting out, putting some junior officers out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: If we had put junior officers out wandering around the bazaars,
                    talking to people in the bazaars, and so on, somebody would have reported it to
                    SAVAK, the secret police, who would have reported it to the Palace. In the first
                    place, those mullahs and Bazaaris were very xenophobic, as the last 10-15 years
                    have shown. Secondly, as I noted, SAVAK would have picked it up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then what would have happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: And then SAVAK would have reported it, and somebody in the government
                    would have said to somebody in the Embassy, “Look, one of your guys has been
                    wandering around asking embarrassing questions and nosing around, and we don't
                    want that. If you want to know something, ask us and we'll tell you.” And I'm
                    serious. The young officer might well have found himself with another assignment
                    in another country. There is, I believe, at least one case where this happened
                    to a junior officer, a Farsi language officer who was a bit too active.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I understand completely. A couple of things about the
                        climate at that time. We had a huge American community didn't we?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And these were essentially gung-ho Americans, perhaps not
                        very sophisticated, probably anathema to the mullahs. This is the wrong
                        group to plunk in the middle of a nation with so many zealots in it. Were we
                        monitoring this, or did these people tend to “screw up the works”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I don't remember any specific such cases. It was all pretty well
                    policed. Certainly the military policed itself closely. There was a large
                    American Club complex, with a big club house and restaurant, swimming pool,
                    tennis courts. There was even a teen club where American teenagers could hang
                    out, and that was healthy. The noncoms had their own big club.</p>
                <p>There were several American military installations around the city well known as
                    such. There was a rod and gun club, and since my boys and I liked fishing and
                    hunting, it was a place we would go on a Sunday afternoon. And, of course, there
                    was a big American school; this was not a military school while I was there, but
                    the military was increasingly anxious to have it so classified since then the
                    military would run it.</p>
                <p>The commanding officer of the Military Assistance Advisory Group, the MAAG, was a
                    two-star general. I can't remember how big the mission was altogether, but it
                    was considerable. But I don't remember any untoward incidents involving the
                    military. There were times when one wondered who ran the show, the military or
                    the Embassy. I served in two countries with large military missions, Iran and
                    Greece, and we had a navy contingent in Cyprus. India was the only country in
                    which I served in which there was no US military presence, and I thought it was
                    purer foreign service experience, without the military presence, if I might put
                    it that way.</p>
                <p>Finally, there was a relatively large big business community, most of it
                    oil-related. The oil people were relatively unsophisticated, but they were also
                    quite careful as I remember. One time when I was duty officer, an American oil
                    company employee, a rather pleasant middle-aged man, hit somebody with his car
                    and we had to get him out of Iran because there was always the possibility of a
                    reaction. But offhand, I don't remember any untoward incidents among the
                    business/oil people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the impression in the Political Section of the
                        Shah at that time? And his program?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: The Shah had done some very admirable things. He had a reform program,
                    called the White Revolution, in which draftees were given a sort of alternative
                    service; instead of going in to the military, they did such things as teach,
                    serve as medical technicians in villages without doctors, and so on. I have
                    forgotten the number of such corps, but they really seemed to be making a
                    difference. The Shah had also begun land reform, which had not gotten very far
                    since the old landlord class was extremely powerful in the country.</p>
                <p>But the Shah was authoritarian at heart. I mentioned that he had surrounded
                    himself with sycophants who told him what he wanted to hear. He had no common
                    touch and was cut off from what was going on. He had allowed so-called political
                    parties but it was all a sham since the candidates were all hand-picked, the
                    elections a farce, all a charade.</p>
                <p>The Shah told Ambassador Armin Meyer one time that the Iranians were not “ready
                    for democracy.” The Americans were always pushing him toward more and more
                    democracy but did not understand that the Iranians were not ready for it, he
                    said. I think the Shah believed that. I am a little at a loss to know what I
                    believe since the revolution. After seeing what has happened, the Shah may have
                    been right all along. Maybe they weren't ready. While the so-called parliament
                    was really kind of ludicrous, maybe he was trying to “bring them along.” But
                    maybe they weren't ready for democracy. Maybe they still are not ready. . .
                    .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of how Armin Meyer operated, the
                        first ambassador when you were there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I liked him very much, and thought he was an excellent career
                    ambassador. He seemed to have a good rapport with the Shah and members of the
                    government. The second ambassador I served under was Ambassador MacArthur.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Douglas MacArthur II.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes. I never felt as close to him as I did to Ambassador Meyer.
                    Ambassador MacArthur was a very cold, demanding man. His Embassy was just not a
                    very nice place to work. The third ambassador was a political appointee, Joe
                    Farland, I believe from West Virginia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did MacArthur relate to the Iranians from your vantage
                        point?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: We had the feeling in the Embassy that he never really liked Iran. The
                    rumor around the Embassy was that he had not wanted to come to Tehran (his
                    previous post was in Europe, I believe.) He was said to think of himself as more
                    a European man, and he just never seemed to relate to Iran. This may be terribly
                    unfair since, as I said, I wasn't very close to him. I do know of one instance
                    where he treated his staff aide and the two front office secretaries very, very
                    shabbily over something very minor.</p>
                <p>I think his attitude toward Iran may have been colored by the attack on his life
                    by the Iranian urban guerrillas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're trying to get a feel for the Foreign Service world,
                        and Mrs. MacArthur was known as one of the dragons in the Foreign Service.
                        Did this have any effect? I mean her demands. Did this permeate the Embassy,
                        or was this a problem? Did it bother people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: We had heard rumors of Mrs. MacArthur's reputation long before she
                    arrived in Tehran. I think her worst days may have been behind her when she got
                    there. But she showed some signs of her reputation from time to time, and one
                    who crossed her — unknowingly — regretted it. As you know, an ambassador's wife
                    can make life miserable for the staff, but in truth I think Mrs. MacArthur's
                    toughest days were behind her.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did we view the Soviet problem from Iran?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: The increasing commercial relations between Iran and the Soviet Union
                    when I was there were a great concern to Ambassador MacArthur, who seemed to be
                    viewing the Soviet Union from Vienna rather than from Tehran. As the foreign
                    relations type in the Political Section I had to compile, every month, a list of
                    commercial transactions between the Soviet Union and Iran. I asked my boss to
                    try to talk him out of it, to tell him that this was nothing new. I thought
                    then, and continue to think now, that he was reading far too much into something
                    relatively insignificant.</p>
                <p>Something brought to his attention that there was considerable trade between the
                    two countries, and he wanted it followed in some detail. I think after a few
                    months of reading the same thing he began to see that it was nothing to get
                    steamed up about. The Iranians were wary of the Soviets, dating back to 1946.
                    Iran and the Soviet Union were, after all, neighbors, and the volume of trade
                    between them was relatively significant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you see — I think they were called the Mujahideen —
                        the communist guerrillas who tried to kill MacArthur, was this a particular
                        problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: This is what I referred to a bit ago, but I think they were called
                    “urban Guerrillas” then, a movement that grew fairly rapidly the last two years
                    I was there. I do not recalled that they were known as the Mujahideen then.</p>
                <p>Anyway, as I understood it at the time, Ambassador and Mrs. MacArthur had a very
                    close call. As I heard the story in the Embassy — and it was kept quiet for a
                    long time — it was a classic maneuver, with the guerrillas' cars forcing the
                    Ambassador's car to the side of the road next to the jube, the open water drain
                    carrying water from the hills down through the town. One car was in front, one
                    in back. As I heard it, several armed men got out of the car in the rear and
                    started toward the Ambassador's car. At that moment, the Ambassador's driver
                    noticed that he had just enough space between the front car and the jube to get
                    through, and he gunned the Cadillac as fast as he could and got out. I was told
                    that Ambassador MacArthur always felt that his driver saved his and Mrs.
                    MacArthur's lives. I heard that the gunmen opened fire on the Ambassador's car
                    and that shots ricocheted around inside the car.</p>
                <p>Then when Nixon and Kissinger came to Tehran in 1972, we had a couple of
                    shootings. The commanding officer of the Air Force section of the MAAG had a
                    bomb rolled under his car; the explosion killed his driver and broke both of his
                    legs. Then at the tomb of the Shah's father (I think that is what it was), a
                    bomb exploded there shortly before Nixon was to visit the tomb. Obviously that
                    stop on the schedule was canceled. I seem to recall another shooting at the time
                    of the visit, but I can not recall just what it was. This was all in May,
                    1972.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The visit of Nixon and Kissinger later on was a sort of
                        by-blow of a visit to the Soviet Union at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: He went to Romania and the Soviet Union, but he was in Tehran for a
                    couple of days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From what I gather practically a blank check was given to
                        the Shah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: That's what I was about to say; that's when the so-called blank check
                    for military assistance was given to him. This was supposed to be the opening of
                    the floodgates. Former British Ambassador Dennis Wright, at one time the British
                    Foreign Office's foremost Iranologist, fluent in Farsi and close to the Shah,
                    told me in 1976 or 1977 when I saw him in India that he thought the Shah had
                    “gone off the track” in 1973 with the great rise in oil prices after the
                    embargo. The Shah really began to “lose his bearings” then, Ambassador Wright
                    thought, and really began to lose touch with reality. Ambassador Wright had
                    retired by the time we met, but I place some stock in his opinion in view of his
                    long experience in Iran over a number of years and his closeness to the
                    Shah.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the view of Iraq during 1968 to 1972 when you
                        were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: We followed relations with Iraq very closely, as did the Iranians.
                    General Bakhtiar, a former chief of SAVAK who had broken with the Shah, had been
                    given refuge in Iraq and the Shah seemed to expect the general to cross the
                    border with his forces at any time. And there was the question of Iranian and
                    Israeli support for the Iraqi Kurds. The Kurds were actually fairly active in
                    those days under a colorful figure Mustapha Barzani. It was well known that
                    Israel was furnishing arms to the Kurds through Iran.</p>
                <p>And of course, the old perennial between Iran and Iraq, the Shatt-al-Arab River
                    which formed the boundary between the two countries in the south. When the
                    British withdrew from the area in the 1930's, they arbitrarily fixed the border
                    between the two countries at the high water mark on the Iranian side of the
                    river, rather than at the thalweg or channel of the river. This meant, of
                    course, that the entire river was in Iraq. They did this, I was told, so that
                    Basra would have responsibility for maintaining and dredging the river, keeping
                    it clear. In international law, when a river is a boundary, the thalweg is
                    normally recognized and you will find few cases where the border is at the high
                    water mark. This was a real source of bitterness to the Iranians, and in truth I
                    always felt they had a legitimate gripe. In any case, the two countries had
                    arrived at a settlement in 1969, when the Shah declared that the border was to
                    be at the thalweg, or channel, and Iraq accepted it.</p>
                <p>One of the more interesting developments vis-a-visIraq when I was there was the
                    apparent decision by Iraq to allow the Iraqi Jews to leave the country. While
                    some of them seemed to “escape” at first, we concluded that the Iraqis were
                    closing their eyes to the Jews' exit. The Jewish community of Baghdad was one of
                    the most famous in that part of the world, a very prominent community, wealthy,
                    solid.</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>I was fortunate enough to meet one of the first families to get out, the Shemtob
                    family. One of the two brothers, Jacob, had been living in London for many
                    years; he returned to Iraq to visit his brother and sister, and could not get an
                    exit permit to leave. Jacob masterminded the flight for the family — four adults
                    and four children, as I recall — by presumably arranging a summer vacation for
                    the family in the mountains to escape the heat of Baghdad. He had previously
                    contacted Kurdish groups in the mountains, into whose hands the Shemtobs placed
                    themselves. They literally went underground with the Kurds, and finally worked
                    their way to the Iran-Iraq border, where they were pretty well welcomed by the
                    Iranian border forces. They were the first of a rather large number of Iraqi
                    Jews who got out that way. Jacob actually set up this pipeline which many of the
                    Jewish community used to escape the country. I think the Shemtobs may have been
                    the first family to use the underground Jacob had established rather than “one
                    of the first”, and Jacob deserved considerable credit for having started it.It
                    was an exciting and interesting development and I was pleased to have been
                    involved to some slight degree and happy to have gotten to know the Shemtobs. As
                    a footnote, the Jewish agencies were very well provided for in Tehran, and
                    received the full cooperation of the Iranian authorities. And, it was said, with
                    the full knowledge of the Shah. The Jewish agencies welcomed those coming
                    through and arranged their onward travel to Israel, the U.S. or wherever they
                    were going. My wife and I had the Shemtobs in for dinner one evening, and had a
                    wonderful evening with them. They were very cultured, refined people who had
                    lived under constant threat in Baghdad. You remember that four Jews — I think it
                    was four — were hung in the square of Baghdad in 1968 or thereabouts on trumped
                    up charges. That was the kind of threat the Shemtobs lived under.</p>
                <p>I have not followed this question in the 25 years since I was there, and do not
                    know what has been revealed since that time. But, as I said, we concluded in the
                    Embassy that the Iraqis probably decided that holding the community hostage was
                    no longer worth the trouble and closed their eyes to the Jews' departure. This
                    in no way minimizes what the Shemtobs and other Jewish families did, since going
                    into the underground to get out required considerable nerve and daring.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was Vietnam playing in Iran from the people you talked
                        to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I don't remember a thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a good answer: it didn't play. Is there anything
                        else we should talk about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I don't think so. I can't think of anything.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I must say I've never known anybody who really stuck to
                        one area, Near Eastern Affairs, as you did the entire time. And you really
                        covered it. You went to Bombay, 1972 to 1976. What about this
                        assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I had completed four years in Iran, and the Department informed me
                    that the Number Two job in the Consulate General there was open and asked if I
                    would like to be assigned there. It was considered a pretty good job. This was
                    before open assignments, when things were much easier I thought. I accepted and
                    went there in July of 1972 on direct transfer from Iran.While I went on direct
                    transfer, the Department authorized some consultation in Washington which
                    enabled me to visit my mother who died before I would have gotten home on leave
                    the next year. This was one of the reasons I loved NEA; we may have been in-bred
                    and incestuous, but NEA looked out for its own. I think Howie Schaffer, who was
                    NEA Personnel Officer at the time, was behind it. I have never discussed it with
                    him, but I have always been grateful to him or whoever did it.</p>
                <p>To get back to Bombay, the job turned out to be a good job, and we stayed there
                    until March, 1976 when I went over to Madras as Consul General.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in Bombay?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I was economic-commercial, but more economic than commercial, since we
                    had a full time commercial officer. It was a relatively big consulate general,
                    and I backed up the Consul General in many ways. I helped supervise the consular
                    section sometime, since we had lots of consular work there. The job was really a
                    Deputy Principal Officer job, and I believe it was actually called that before I
                    left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was Consul General most of the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: David Bane for about half of my tour. He was succeeded by Bill
                    Courtney. David had been Ambassador in Gabon, and before that Consul General in
                    Lahore. He told me he thought the Bombay job was underrated. Bombay was an
                    exciting city in which to serve: big, dirty, crowded, filthy, but exciting and
                    fascinating with lots of interesting people who were easily accessible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Western India at the time you
                        were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Things were not altogether easy for Americans then. Remember that this
                    was just after the Indo-Pak War in 1971, when the U.S. tilted toward
                    Pakistan.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was Kissinger's famous tilt toward Pakistan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes. You may remember that the Soviets rushed in in support of the
                    Indians. There was considerable anti-Americanism all over India. Still we could
                    get around and see people. The Indians had a way of giving us the needle
                    whenever they could; they professed not to understand how we could support
                    Pakistan over India, “the largest democracy in the world.” They never let us
                    forget that. And Soviet influence was strong.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say that Soviet influence was strong. Who was the
                        Prime Minister?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Indira Gandhi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would have thought that the mating of India and the
                        Soviet Union an unlikely one.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: It was an unlikely mating, but the Soviets were quick to exploit the
                    situation. For example, India had been in the midst of a severe drought when I
                    arrived. The monsoon had not been good, and the wheat and rice crops had both
                    been off for a number of years. The so-called “Green Revolution” had not yet
                    taken hold and India needed wheat rather badly. Who provided this wheat? The
                    Soviet Union. And at a time when the Soviets were buying wheat from us. A Greek
                    merchant captain whose ship brought “Soviet” grain to India told me in Bombay
                    that he was certain that the wheat being shipped to India from the Soviet Union
                    was American wheat. We did not pursue this since but it is an interesting
                    question. He told me he had seen American ships unloading American wheat into
                    the same facility out of which he loaded wheat for India. Indira Gandhi publicly
                    stated that the Soviets were always a friend in need for India. When India
                    needed friends in 1971, she said, and the Soviets were there. By the time I got
                    there, the Soviets were the principal arms supplier for India, whether by grant
                    or on credit. The huge steel mill in eastern India was built by the Soviets. It
                    served the Indians right, but I understood from some Indian business friends
                    that India got old, outdated technology in the steel mill. You'd see Soviet
                    missions of various kinds all over the country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the Indian intellectuals comfortable? Were the people
                        you talked to comfortable with talking about their great brother, the
                        Soviets?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: The people we socialized with did not see a lot of the Soviets. The
                    Indian educated elite much preferred Americans to Soviets, there was no doubt of
                    that. But journalists, for example, felt comfortable with Soviets and with the
                    Indo-Soviet friendship. I will tell you an interesting anecdote that illustrates
                    Indian thinking.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>I was having lunch one day with the editor of an Indian paper in Bombay, a very
                    nice, likeable man supposedly very close to Indira Gandhi. He said to me that we
                    Americans had never understood nonalignment. Americans had always felt that
                    nonalignment means being equidistant from the great powers, being, in fact, in
                    the middle. Indians felt that nonalignment did not mean equal distance between
                    the great powers and that, in fact, “you can be more equidistant or less
                    equidistant.” I know what he meant, but it struck me at the time as rather
                    humorous and typical of the fuzzy wuzzy way Indians tended to think — more
                    equidistant or less equidistant!!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Particularly in the upper classes the Indians enjoy
                        talking. Was this a strain sometimes? As a consular officer did you find
                        things got talked to death?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: No. Indians were really very good conversationalists, very good
                    company, if more than a little self-righteous and insensitive at times. As I
                    think I noted, upper class Indians felt much closer to the United States than to
                    the Soviet Union and the Soviets. Upper class Indians liked good food, good
                    conversation and good company. But, as I said, they could be insensitive and
                    even rude.</p>
                <p>One evening at a lovely dinner party, shortly after we had arrived in Bombay, a
                    young Parsi doctor was telling me, in perfect English, how much he and his wife
                    loved the U.S. They loved the U.S. and the American people he said, but “I don't
                    like your President very much.” I was so taken aback by this that I didn't
                    defend my President adequately, and it bothered me. It never dawned on him that
                    it was rude of him to say something like that to an American diplomat.</p>
                <p>While I never had the occasion to use it, I decided that if another Indian ever
                    said that to me, I would reply that I knew lots of Americans who loved India and
                    the Indian people, but didn't like Indira Gandhi very much.</p>
                <p>Still, we left more good, close friends in India than we did in any of our other
                    posts, so I may be the one who is being insensitive here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there during the Watergate period. Was there
                        understanding of what it was all about. I was in Greece at the time and the
                        Greeks never understood what Watergate was about.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: The Indians did not understand Watergate. Most Indian politicians are
                    corrupt, so they could not understand what Watergate was all about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Watergate was sort of small potatoes from most other
                        countries' point of view.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: As big as India is, it could be terribly parochial in many ways. India
                    bought some foodgrains from us in late 1973 or thereabouts, and found that one
                    shipment had Jimsonweed in it. Jimsonweed, known as “loco weed” in the American
                    West, is poisonous to humans. Indians bought the grain for human consumption, so
                    people receiving it had to pick out every grain of the Jimsonweed before they
                    could eat it. This received a tremendous play in the press all over India, with
                    the press implying if not stating openly that we had taken the Indians on this
                    or that we had had some evil motive in selling India grain that was laced with
                    Jimsonweed.</p>
                <p>In fact, India had bought very cheap, inferior foodgrains which were known to our
                    grain people in the States to contain Jimsonweed. The GOI had cut corners and
                    was then trying to blame us for what happened. It was a good example of getting
                    what you pay for. That is the kind of thing that would get a tremendous press
                    play in India, while Watergate received no attention.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the ConGen staff adopt a wait-and-see, “this too shall
                        pass” attitude at this time. These things come and go with Indo-American
                        relations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I think we did, since things seemed to be improving. But Mrs. Gandhi
                    never really liked us, and we had that to contend with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did we view the Communist Party? Did we see the
                        communists ever taking over India?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: No. The party was there and from time to time would lead
                    demonstrations by the consulate protesting such things as the Allende ouster in
                    Chile. We would always close the gates when demonstrations occurred and
                    disregard the demonstrators. Once when I was in charge the young Political
                    Officer suggested that we accept the demonstrators' petition. I think it was one
                    of those “Allende” demonstrations. I refused to accept it on the ground that
                    accepting it would imply involvement that we were not guilty of. The Embassy
                    telephoned down to ask how I was handling it and agreed entirely with my
                    approach.</p>
                <p>There were actually two communist parties in India: the CPI, the Communist Party
                    of India, the “usual” type party, and the Marxist party, the CPM.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Patrick Moynihan was the Ambassador for a while when you
                        were there. Did you get any feel for how he operated?Or was he too far
                        away?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: I need not say that Ambassador Moynihan was and is a great mind,
                    admired far and near for his great intellect. But he was a difficult man to work
                    for. I knew his staff aide rather well, and he told me just how unpredictable,
                    how volatile Moynihan was. It was impossible for the staff aide to predict his
                    reactions. I think his main goal when he went to India was to negotiate the
                    Indian indebtedness to us off the books. I've forgotten the precise figure, but
                    on the books, we had something like 2-3 billion dollars of PL 480 money.
                    Moynihan felt that our relations with India would never improve as long as the
                    Indians felt indebted to us. It was a tough negotiation, but it was a successful
                    one and he and the economic staff of the Embassy deserved a lot of credit.</p>
                <p>Indians liked him because they saw him as a real intellectual. But on the
                    personal side, being in Bombay was about as close as I wanted to be to him, 3-4
                    hours away by air.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are continuing November 11, 1993. You were in Madras
                        from 1976 to 1979. What were you doing there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I was Consul General in Madras. The previous incumbent, Jack Eaves,
                    left rather suddenly to become DCM in Kathmandu. When Jack left, Ambassador
                    Saxbe, who had replaced Moynihan, asked me to go to Madras as CG. I was ready to
                    leave Bombay, and I felt that South India was sufficiently different from
                    Western India that it would be like a new assignment. And of course there was
                    the satisfaction of going from Number Two to Number One.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find your staff there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: The American staff when I arrived there was adequate, with some strong
                    points and some weak ones. The young administrative officer was quite good, the
                    best member of the staff. The Indian national staff was outstanding, easily the
                    best national staff of my career.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're talking about 1976 to 1979. Could you tell me in the
                        first place what your consular district covered? And what was the situation,
                        economic and political?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: The Madras Consular District consisted of four states: Tamil Nadu,
                    Andhra Pradesh, Karnataka, and Kerala. Each had its separate language. At the
                    time of my transfer, Tamil Nadu was governed from Delhi, under what was called
                    “President's Rule”. The leader of the regional party in power in Tamil Nadu was
                    at odds with Mrs. Gandhi and she summarily dismissed him and initiated rule of
                    the state from Delhi. This was during the period of the “Emergency”, the
                    suspension of parliamentary government in India and rule by Indira Gandhi. This
                    authoritarian rule, for which “The Emergency” was a euphemism, had been imposed
                    in 1975 by Mrs. Gandhi, when she took the full rule of the country into her
                    hands, really executing a bloodless coup. This was a very dark day for India. I
                    should point out that “President's Rule”, under which the government in Delhi
                    could dismiss a state government, did not start with the Emergency; I do not
                    know its history, but it is the kind of thing that could come from the
                    Brits.</p>
                <p>Anyway, when I arrived in Madras, Tamil Nadu was under President's Rule. There
                    were two men from Delhi, very senior career civil servants, actually running the
                    state. I established rather good contacts with one of them, an excellent man by
                    the name of P. K. Dave, as I mentioned a senior career government official.</p>
                <p>The consular district had a population of 150 million people. Andhra Pradesh and
                    Karnataka were generally in Mrs. Gandhi's camp (Mrs. Gandhi's party was the
                    Congress Party, the old party of her father); at the time I arrived, the
                    Congress Party was in power in Kerala, but with a very slim majority. The
                    communists were very strong in that state, as you may recall. When Mrs. Gandhi
                    lifted President's Rule in Tamil Nadu, another regional party was elected and
                    governed the state for a number of years. A regional party was elected in Andhra
                    Pradesh a few years later. Interestingly, the leaders in both states were movie
                    actors, said to derive their political power from their exposure throughout
                    their states in movies.</p>
                <p>We need not go into the details here, but the leader of Tamil Nadu had had a very
                    long movie career in which he always played the good guy, and in his films, good
                    always triumphed over evil. His movies were quite simple but the villagers
                    reportedly loved them. Local Madras pundits told me that the villages tended to
                    blur the movie man with the real man. Whatever the reason he was Chief Minister,
                    which was the title of the leader of the state government, a good many
                    years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As the Consul General, was there much interest in the
                        American connection? How did you deal with these poor states?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: I like to think I was fairly well known and relatively popular. We had
                    lots of travel money left over from the counterpart funds, and I tried to visit
                    each state capital every six months for three or four days. I had three Indian
                    national political employees: one for Andhra Pradesh, one for Karnataka, and one
                    for Tamil Nadu and Kerala. They all were excellent, and knew whom I should see
                    and whom I should not see. They would make appointments ahead of time, USIS
                    would get my visit and maybe a picture, in the papers. It was a very good public
                    relations operation, even if I do say so. We used to joke in the office that I
                    was probably the best known foreigner in South India, which was something when
                    you consider the size of the area.</p>
                <p>On the personal side, I liked the South very much. It was a great tourist area,
                    with lots to be seen, including some magnificent old Hindu temples. I set up a
                    train trip for Ambassador Saxbe, on which we had several private railway cars
                    which were dropped off in a tourist center, and later tacked on to the back of
                    another train a day later. It was a wonderful way to travel, and sort of took us
                    back to the days of the British Raj. Word of the trip got around, and a number
                    of other people in the Embassy asked me to arrange one for them. It was a
                    once-in-a-lifetime kind of thing, something that could probably only be done in
                    India. As a footnote, the Indian Railways were quite good, and the service
                    provided for the VIP bogey was outstanding.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Didn't Kerala have a communist government at one time, and
                        wasn't that an irritant to us, a communist government in this big democracy
                        during the Cold War. I recall that it was the focus of a lot of attention.
                        Did you give Kerala more attention because of that, or had our concerns
                        dissipated?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Our concerns regarding that had largely dissipated by then. I don't
                    remember specifically but it is my general recollection that my relations with
                    those communists I met were fairly cordial. I don't recall meeting many of them,
                    in fact.The Soviets had a big consulate in Madras, and their CG and I became
                    fairly good friends. He mentioned one time, I suppose at a party, that he was
                    traveling over to Kerala. I kidded him that he went to Kerala a lot more than I
                    did, and I asked what he did there; did he call on all those communist leaders
                    over there? He responded quite openly that “of course” he did. You call on the
                    Congress people, he said to me, and I call on the Communists. He went on
                    good-naturedly, “What do you think I do?” This man and his wife were very
                    decent, likable people, and we figured that he was probably a career foreign
                    service type; his number two was a bull, however, as subtle as a 47-ton tank. We
                    concluded that he was KGB.</p>
                <p>To return to your original question, I don't recall that we were concerned about
                    Kerala when I was there. I think we had learned to live with it. As you know,
                    India took some getting used to, but it could also be a wonderful, fascinating
                    place to serve. Obviously I was not a career subcontinent type, but I did learn
                    to love India.As a footnote, Krishna Menon, who succeeded in antagonizing nearly
                    everybody at the UN in the late 1950s and early 1960s was a typical, fuzzy
                    Keralan.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Later, particularly today, the Tamil problem spills over
                        to Sri Lanka. How did we look on the Tamil separatist movement at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: We did not focus on it when I was there. There had been language riots
                    in Tamil Nadu as recently as 1966-69, and resentment on the language issue
                    continues below the surface to this day. But I don't recall any focus on the
                    separatist movement. Once I asked a close friend, a London School of Economics
                    graduate, if the language problem bothered him. I was surprised when he answered
                    affirmatively and vigorously. But I don't remember seeing anything on the
                    separatist movement then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Madras must have seemed far, far from Delhi in many ways.
                        How did we look upon Indira Gandhi at that time? What was the general
                        opinion of how she was governing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Mrs. Gandhi was the Congress Party. She was, surprisingly, fairly
                    popular in Tamil Nadu. After she imposed the Emergency in 1975, when she would
                    call elections was the burning question. I think I mentioned that the Congress
                    was strong in Andhra and Karnataka, less so in Kerala. Intellectuals and
                    educated Indians deeply resented the imposition of authoritarian rule, and
                    repudiated Indira Gandhi at the ballot box when she called elections for 1977.
                    We concluded, I think, that she had so cut herself off from the electorate that
                    she had no idea that she would be so soundly rejected. It was obviously a gross
                    miscalculation on her part.I personally went to India with no preconceived
                    notions about her or the country, and I left loving the country and with a very
                    low opinion of her. She was a very political animal, but I didn't think she was
                    terribly smart. She certainly had no vision of where the country would go, or
                    where it needed to go, except to keep her in power. I was always surprised that
                    such a big country produced so few leaders; American Indologists could probably
                    explain this, but I never could. In a country of 600 million then — it's
                    considerably bigger now — there were very few political leaders. The Indian
                    business community was an outstanding group, and I knew some very able
                    businessmen in Bombay and Madras but they avoided politics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We obviously have all kinds of differences with the
                        Indians. When you called on Congress Party leaders, what would you talk
                        about? Was there anything special you were pitching? Or was it really just
                        how things were going?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: Much of our discussions concerned the general situation in the states,
                    or a particular situation between states. And a great deal of local stuff. I
                    would not have dared, on an official call, to ask one of them what he thought of
                    Mrs. Gandhi, for example. Overly-sensitive Indians would have been quick to
                    consider that interfering. I would take my time, and sometimes some very
                    interesting material would come out. I would sometimes get into state elections,
                    but one had to be careful since they were so sensitive about what they
                    considered interference in internal affairs. I think I actually generated some
                    trust among some of my contacts. The Chief Minister of Tamil Nadu, the movie
                    actor to whom I referred, and I were fairly close. He had needed eye surgery,
                    and I went out of my way to help his people arrange things for him and to give
                    him a good reception, even though he was the equivalent of a state governor.</p>
                <p>A word on the “prickly” relationship;. It was prickly, but at the same time it
                    was a sort of love-hate relationship between Indians and Americans. They seemed
                    almost hurt that we didn't give them more attention. And they never forgot the
                    tilt of 1971. They could never understand why the world's greatest democracy did
                    not support the world's largest democracy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned the press. How did you deal with the press?
                        Did it worry you that there were land mines everywhere you stepped as far as
                        the press was concerned?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes. I had to be very careful. I did not deal with the press any more
                    than I had to, and I left that to our very good USIS office in Madras. I
                    actually stayed away from the press fairly much. I did have one incident when I
                    was on a speaking tour in an isolated provincial town and something I said was
                    taken out of context and blown up in the press all over the country.</p>
                <p>When Ambassador Saxbe arrived in India in early 1975, he let it be known that he
                    was not really looking for Mrs. Gandhi to persuade her of anything or to offer
                    her anything. He had not come to India bearing gifts, he let it be known, and he
                    had no US assistance to be “forced” on India. He sort of put it out that if Mrs.
                    Gandhi wanted him, he would be on the golf course playing golf or in Kashmir
                    fishing. I thought his approach was just right for the time. The Indians were
                    very sensitive to what they perceived as our “forcing” aid on them, and I think
                    Ambassador Saxbe played it just right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Over the years, Indians have perceived that the
                        Republicans have tilted more to Pakistan and Democratic administrations are
                        more inclined to support India. You were in Madras when the Carter
                        Administration came in. In addition to the hoped-for tilt, Carter had a
                        personal tie with India through his mother who had served in the Peace Corps
                        there. In your area, did you see any positive or negatives about the Carter
                        Administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: I think there was the feeling that you described, that the Democrats
                    were more pro-India than the Republicans, and in general, our relations were
                    better under Carter. Remember, too, that Morarji Desai had succeeded Mrs.
                    Gandhi, and that was a definite plus as far as our relations were concerned. The
                    most impressive thing Carter did was the appointment of Ambassador Goheen to
                    Delhi. Ambassador Goheen was born in India, the son of a medical missionary. I
                    think some of his grandparents had been missionaries. He had long, deep ties
                    with India, and a deep affection for the country and the people. He said when he
                    presented his credentials that he was deeply touched to be representing his
                    country in the land of his birth.</p>
                <p>I think he was tremendously effective, as word of his “Indian connection” was
                    widespread. He and I went to Andhra Pradesh to what had been a TB sanitarium
                    where his father had performed thoracic surgery many years before. Dr. Goheen's
                    first patient was found and attended the program the sanitarium had set up.
                    Ambassador Goheen told me that his family's long ties with India meant a great
                    deal to him and he was indeed very proud of them.</p>
                <p>To repeat for emphasis, he was a fine ambassador and a fine man, and I was glad I
                    had the chance to work for him. Also as I noted, the Indians interpreted his
                    appointment as an indication that we wanted to improve relations, and they
                    welcomed him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were relations pretty steady when you left in 1979?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes, pretty steady. As I said, the Desai Government was much more
                    favorably disposed toward us than Indira Gandhi had been. Carter made an
                    official visit in 1979, and while there was one flap during his stay, things
                    were in general upbeat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We move now to your last assignment, when somebody threw
                        you back into the briar patch. You went to Athens in 1979 as Political
                        Counselor. The assignment obviously makes since. Did this come as a
                        surprise, or did you ask for the assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I asked for it, as the result of some fortuitous circumstances. Irv
                    Cheslaw, then the senior assignments man in Personnel, was going from Delhi to
                    Colombo, with a change of planes in Madras. Fortunately for me, as it turned
                    out, he had an unexpected delay of several hours. I met him at the airport, took
                    him to the office and later to the Residence for lunch. During the several hours
                    we spent together, he asked where I would like to go on my next assignment. I
                    mentioned DCM in Athens, which he said would be difficult, since I was a very
                    new OC. He then said that he was looking for a Greek language OC to fill the
                    Political Counselor spot. I replied that I was the original Greek language
                    officer in the Department, and I would have expected my name to come out of the
                    computer. Irv replied that things weren't that easy, but said that he thought he
                    could get that assignment for me.</p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>If Irv had not come through Athens, I might well not have gotten the job. I had
                    been overseas then for over ten years, and was not at all familiar with how the
                    open assignments system worked. Anyway, he put my name in the mill, and I heard
                    in several months that I had gotten the job. We left Madras in June, 1979, and
                    arrived in Athens in August for four years.</p>
                <p>I might say here that, in retrospect, I feel that I was overseas far too long.
                    When my four years in Athens ended, I had been overseas fifteen years, 1968 to
                    1983. While I enjoyed every minute of it, I think you tend to lose touch with
                    the way things are done in Washington and are at a disadvantage in competing in
                    the open assignments system.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the political situation in Greece when you
                        arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: When I arrived in Greece, there were several questions pending, each
                    exciting and interesting. These were: (1) Greece's return to the military wing
                    of NATO from which it had withdrawn after the Turkish invasion of Cyprus in
                    1974; (2) Greece's entry into the European Community after years of preparation;
                    and (3) the possible move to the Presidency by Karamanlis and the election of a
                    new party leader who would lead the government.</p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>The first of these was the most pressing. Greece wanted back in NATO, but Turkey
                    had imposed conditions on Greece's return which Athens found unacceptable. A
                    good many people spent long hours trying to find the right mix, and there were
                    times when it seemed that agreement was near. NATO did most of the detailed work
                    on this, and the Rogers Plan, named for SACEUR Bernard Rogers, in 1981 seemed to
                    offer a solution. The government of Karamanlis's party, New Democracy, seemed to
                    accept, but then Andreas Papandreou was elected in 1981 and rejected the whole
                    thing. It was sort of in limbo when I left and I must confess that I do not know
                    where it is right now.The second, Greece's accession to the EC, was equally
                    exciting. This was really the fruit of Karamanlis's labor; he apparently
                    concluded long ago that Greece's future was more secure “in Europe” than in
                    alliance with us, that Greece's rightful place was in the EC. Greek membership
                    in the EC may well be Karamanlis's most meaningful monument. Margaret Thatcher
                    once referred to Karamanlis as “The Grand Old Man of Europe”, and I go along
                    with that. Greece's road in the EC has been a rocky one from time to time, but
                    nobody can blame Karamanlis for that. Taking them in was a masterful stroke and
                    he deserves full marks for that. As indicated throughout what I have been
                    saying, Karamanlis was still Prime Minister when I arrived, having been called
                    home from Paris when the coup against Makarios brought on the fall of the
                    military junta in Athens. He had won two elections, I believe, and there was
                    already talk when I got there that he would move up to the Presidency in 1980.
                    Constantine Tsatsos, a faithful friend and follower of Karamanlis, was said to
                    be keeping the seat warm for Karamanlis. It was just assumed that Karamanlis
                    wanted it; it was even said that he had been looking ahead to becoming president
                    when he insisted that the new constitution provide for a strong presidency.
                    Anyway, the thought of Karamanlis moving up and a new prime minister coming on
                    the scene was very exciting. While we all expected Evangelos Averoff to win
                    leadership of the party, George Rallis, a long-time follower of Karamanlis
                    actually emerged with the prize. I always thought that was a real shame, since
                    Averoff really deserved it; he had given Greece long, long service, and he was
                    well-regarded internationally as well as at home. I thought he would have made a
                    lot better prime minister than Rallis, who was just short of a disaster.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before Papandreou came into power in 1981, he had been a
                        difficult person for us for a long time. How were we looking upon the
                        possible rise and assumption of power of Andreas Papandreou?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: We were looking on that possibility with some trepidation since he was
                    the antithesis of most of what we supported in Greece. He said publicly on a
                    number of occasions that he would take Greece out of NATO; he said publicly on a
                    number of occasions that he would take Greece out of the EC; he said repeatedly
                    that he would throw the American facilities out of Greece if he were elected. He
                    repeated these things long enough that people — including us, I think — believed
                    at least some of them.</p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>Papandreou was a fascinating character himself. I accompanied our ambassador, Bob
                    McCloskey, on a call on Papandreou one time and found the private Papandreou
                    altogether different from the public Papandreou. I've forgotten the point
                    McCloskey wanted to make — it was on Cyprus as I recall — and Papandreou
                    accepted what McCloskey said, stating something like “if you tell me that, I
                    accept it.”</p>
                <p>But when he got up on the stump, the balcony, he was a different person. He was
                    superb on the balcony, if totally unpredictable in what he might say. I went to
                    the final rally before the election of 1981, and there must have been 200 to
                    300,000 people in Constitution Square. For a Greek political junkie, it was
                    something to see, an unforgettable experience. I had seen his father speaking at
                    Thessaloniki in 1958, but I think the son was better on the balcony than the
                    father.Of course, he did none of the things he said he was going to do, but we
                    kept him at arm's length his first terms in office. For example, it has become
                    traditional that the president of the EC — it is a rotating presidency on a
                    six-months basis — be invited to the US. Papandreou was the first president not
                    to be invited. He was shunned and I think it was a mistake in retrospect. I've
                    read that the White House has already invited him, though I know none of the
                    details.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He's just become prime minister again. He must be pretty
                        long in the tooth.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I think over time we realized that we had to look at what Papandreou
                    did and not at what Papandreou said. He obviously didn't take Greece out of the
                    EC; he obviously did not take Greece out of NATO. And he did not throw the bases
                    out overnight. The British historian from Oxford, Richard Clogg, said the other
                    day in a lecture at the FSI that rather than being socialist, he considered
                    Papandreou more a populist. This may be so. I don't think we worry about him
                    anymore; he is obviously in very bad health and one has to wonder who is
                    governing Greece.</p>
                <p>One of the most irritating points about Papandreou's people was the fact that
                    they were not accessible at first. They simply would not see us, and we actually
                    heard that there was a committee in his party, known by the acronym PASOK, that
                    had to clear contacts with foreign diplomats. The Ambassador had access, since
                    he had known Papandreou years ago, but at my level and below it was very
                    difficult to see members of PASOK. There was one member of Parliament in
                    Papandreou's party, a man who had been an American citizen and still might have
                    been, and he simply gave me the runaround. When he finally realized we were only
                    interested in normal diplomatic contacts, we began seeing each other and he and
                    his wife came to our house for dinner more than once.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the Embassy people? Were we adopting a bunker
                        mentality? How were we dealing with it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>McCASKILL: Well, as I indicated, we kept at it. I came to know the Deputy
                    Minister of Foreign Affairs fairly well, professionally, that is. And even more
                    important, I came to know a man in Papandreou's inner circle very well. He only
                    spoke Greek, and three of us from the Embassy, one Greek and one other American
                    Greek speaker, would get together with him and two other Greeks and talk very
                    frankly. He reached the point where he felt very comfortable with me, and he and
                    his wife had a small going-away party for my wife and me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about our military? Were we telling people on our
                        bases to keep their heads down?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Everybody did keep their heads down, and tried to be less obvious. A
                    bus was bombed, killing one US military man, but that was after I left
                    Athens.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there mobs parading in front of the Embassy at any
                        point while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Yes. The anniversary of the November 17 student uprising — which has
                    come to represent the beginning of the end of the military junta — was always
                    marked by a demonstration with a decided anti-US flavor. The demonstration would
                    end with a march past the Embassy. Margaret Papandreou, herself an American
                    citizen born, led the march several times, which was a bit much for me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about terrorism while you were there? There had been
                        killings, which continued.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: A Turkish diplomat and his family were gunned down, but that was
                    Armenian terrorism. Our Ambassador, Monty Stearns, received a threat, as I
                    remember. A prominent conservative small newspaper owner was gunned down, and
                    his killer never found. The Chief of the Naval Section, a Navy captain, was
                    gunned down shortly after I left. Senior officers had guards on their homes, and
                    we took all the usual precautions, so there was considerable awareness of
                    terrorism. Security at the Embassy was tight. It was not the Greece I had known
                    when I was there previously. I liked it more the old way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Cyprus flair up while you were there, or did it remain
                        on a steady course?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: The Greeks and Turks were having troubles, but little of it was
                    related to Cyprus. The questions at issue were the so-called Aegean issues —
                    overflights, definition of the FIR (Flight Information Reporting zone), command
                    and control in the Aegean, definition of the territorial seas, etc. These were
                    all potentially more explosive then than was Cyprus.</p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>When Papandreou first took office, he paid an official visit to Cyprus, the first
                    Greek Prime Minister to have done so. He declared Cyprus “a national issue”,
                    which got a big play in Cyprus. The president of Cyprus visited Athens. If the
                    Cyprus Problem were solved, it would have a salutary effect on the Aegean
                    issues. But I thought then, and continue to feel, that the Aegean issues were
                    more important to Greece than Cyprus. I may have mentioned earlier, but it bears
                    repeating here that I have always thought that 1974 established that Greece
                    would not fight for Cyprus. It would fight for any of the Aegean islands, for
                    any of the Greek islands, but Greece will not fight for Cyprus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To return to NATO: was Greek departure real? France is not
                        part of NATO and hasn't been since the 1960s, yet France is pretty well
                        included in NATO. How about Greece? Were the Greeks really out of NATO?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: The Greeks were in and they weren't in. They would refuse to
                    participate in military exercises because of the question of remilitarization of
                    Limnos or because of other reasons. Yet they were certainly a part of the North
                    Atlantic Council, the political body of NATO. In some ways they were having
                    their cake and eating it too.</p>
                <p>It is interesting now, with the end of the Cold War, that Greece has been
                    disarmed as far as we are concerned, as has Turkey to some extent. Neither is
                    the security factor it was 25 years ago. Neither is vital to the West. This will
                    be difficult for the Greeks — and the Turks — to take. I am a bit out-of-touch
                    on this, but I think Turkey is reacting poorly to the fact that the parameters
                    of our relationship have changed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All of this needs reevaluation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: A lot of reevaluation. Papandreou will no longer have the bases to
                    hold over us. Instead of threatening to get out of the EC, he will probably be
                    hanging on to his EC membership by his fingernails.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From what I hear, it sounds like the EC would like to get
                        rid of Greece.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: The EC may be unhappy with Greece, but Greece will never leave the EC
                    since it has a veto over the Turkish application for membership. Turkey has
                    wanted for some time to get in, but has not managed to do so.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there for almost two years of Papandreou's first
                        term. Were you seeing signs of what was going to happen? Were people pushing
                        him to get out of NATO, out of the EC, or to get rid of the bases?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: It became clear soon after the election that most of his threats were
                    hollow. What we did see was his embrace of Arafat, an almost-Third World kind of
                    foreign policy. I think it was Ted Couloumbis, a Greek academic, who said that
                    Papandreou had one foot in the East and one in the West, or something like that.
                    He was a real renegade and would deviate from NATO or EC policy as it suited
                    him. The EC was desperately striving for unanimity of EC foreign policy, which
                    they called “political cooperation”. On such things as the shooting down of the
                    KAL airline, they would be unanimous, except for Greece. I know from some of my
                    EC friends that many members of the EC found this very galling, since Greece was
                    considered a kind of poor, country cousin in the EC.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the Reagan Administration react to Greece?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I think Papandreou drove Washington up the wall. As I may have
                    implied, he was one of those politicians who can not resist an open microphone
                    and who is not responsible when he gets one in his hands. The fact that he had
                    lived here for so many years and had been a US citizen at one time made his
                    behavior particularly difficult for many Americans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Washington trying to make things difficult for
                        Greece?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I don't think so. I think we were just trying to live with what we
                    had. I mentioned that we would not invite him to Washington. There may have been
                    other things but I just can not remember them now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about Soviet influence on Papandreou during this
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: While he was fuzzy, even third- worldish in many ways, I would be
                    inclined to discount Soviet influence. Karamanlis himself had started the
                    opening to the east, with a trip to the Soviet Union in 1979, and had developed
                    what he referred to as Greece's multifaceted foreign policy. I would need to
                    refresh my memory but I can't recall that Papandreou's relations with the Soviet
                    Union or the East Bloc were all that significant.Remember, as I said previously,
                    that Papandreou belonged in the non-aligned camp, philosophically. He was
                    described somewhere by somebody as NATO's only non-aligned member. I did a paper
                    for publication some years ago in which I developed the thesis that Papandreou
                    was really non-aligned in his heart.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the Greek Americans look on Papandreou? Did they
                        find this difficult for them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Most Greek Americans that I know did not really care for Papandreou,
                    and they realized that his election had weakened Greece's position in Washington
                    to a significant degree. They would still go to bat for Greece on such things as
                    the 10-7 ratio, for example.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the Greek government and the Greek lobby were not
                        united as they have been in the past?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: There were some efforts to repair relations. Margaret Papandreou came
                    to the US shortly after the elections and snubbed the AHEPA (the American
                    Hellenic Education and Protective Association). AHEPA was upset about it, we
                    heard, and soon sent a high-powered AHEPA delegation to Greece to try to mend
                    fences. I've forgotten whether Papandreou attended their luncheon or whether he
                    sent his wife, but it was generally conceded that they both realized that they
                    needed each other and agreed tacitly to bury the hatchet. As I remember, it was
                    an uneasy relationship after that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the influence and knowledge of
                        the CIA when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I think the Agency's influence — and its expertise — was considerably
                    less during this time than it had been. The Station Chief my first two years
                    there was not very impressive, and I met nobody in the entire four years who had
                    the horse power of, say, a Dick Welch. Still, the last Chief of Station was an
                    old pro. In general, I just do not see how you can send a person into that
                    atmosphere with no background in Greek affairs and expect them to be very
                    effective in intelligence work. I think the high point of Agency effectiveness
                    in Greece had long since passed by 1979, for a number of reasons: lingering
                    belief that we, through the Agency, had been involved in the coup of 1967, the
                    stubborn perception that we were somehow involved in the coup against Makarios
                    in 1974, and on and on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Greek Americans often had preconceived opinions about what
                        was going on in Greece, and might have been a problem in the Agency.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: I do not recall too many Greek Americans in the Agency my last tour
                    there, though there were many of them in the early years, some of them very good
                    officers. We had some of the same internal problems with the Agency from 1979 to
                    1983 that we've always had, with cover, for example. You had to watch them or
                    they would be all over the lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One last thing: could you talk about the style of
                        operating of Ambassador McCloskey, and then the style of operating style of
                        Ambassador Stearns.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McCASKILL: Ambassador McCloskey never seemed to enjoy being Ambassador to Greece,
                    for a reason I could never fathom, and he never seemed to take to Greece or the
                    Greeks. He was not very outgoing, certainly around the Embassy. But I think the
                    Greeks respected him. A well-known Greek journalist once told me that if
                    McCloskey told you something, you could believe it, that McCloskey was “a man of
                    his word.” As you know, you either like Greece or you don't like Greece, and I
                    was never sure McCloskey liked it.</p>
                <p>Monty Stearns was another story, the consummate professional where Greece was
                    concerned. He liked Greece, and spoke excellent Greek. He and Mrs. Stearns
                    (Toni) read two or three newspapers every morning. I used to joke that Monty
                    needed only an Administrative Counselor and a Consul General since he knew so
                    much about Greece and handled so much of the substantive output of the Embassy
                    himself. Monty had years of experience, had always wanted to be Ambassador to
                    Greece, and was an outstanding one.</p>
                <p>But working for McCloskey was better in many ways, since he relied on his staff
                    more than Monty did. I know I personally enjoyed working for him more. McCloskey
                    relied on me more on political questions, and I appreciated that. McCloskey
                    would never have Stearns's feel for Greece or Stearns's contacts. But the senior
                    staff had more role to play under McCloskey, if you can understand that. In
                    short, I admired Monty tremendously and considered him the almost perfect choice
                    for the job when he was there, an excellent career ambassador. But I felt more
                    useful with McCloskey, and felt that I was somehow making more contribution to
                    Greek-US affairs under McCloskey. I suppose that sums it up pretty well, and is
                    a good note on which to finish.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
