<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000910">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Charles H. Percy</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>SENATOR CHARLES H. PERCY</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial Interview date: June 11, 1998</p>
                <p>Copyright 2001 ADST</p>
                <p>[Note: Additional remarks by Senator Percy in 2001 are included in brackets.]</p>
                <p>Q: Today is June 11, 1998. This is an interview with Senator Charles H. Percy. It
                    is being done on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training.
                    I am Charles Stuart Kennedy.</p>
                <p>Senator, let's start at the beginning. Can you tell me when anwhere you were
                    born, why you were born there, and how your parents met?</p>
                <p>PERCY: I was born in Pensacola, Florida. Stu, I'm just delighted to have this
                    opportunity to work with you in the Foreign Affairs Oral History Program and the
                    Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training, in which I have been interested
                    for a number of years.</p>
                <p>I was born on September 27, 1919. My mother was originally a Chicagoan. Her
                    mother had been born in Stuttgart, Germany. My grandmother lived in Stuttgart
                    until 1922, when I was three years old and she moved to Chicago to be with us.
                    My mother was a violinist and for 26 years was head of a quartet. The members of
                    the quartet traveled around the country on the Chautauqua circuit, giving
                    concerts. The quartet was scheduled to be in Pensacola, Florida giving a series
                    of concerts. A southern gentleman kept coming to every concert. He was a little
                    shy, did not speak to members of the quartet but continued to attend the
                    concerts. Finally, he came to a concert in the afternoon and asked the violinist
                    if she and three other members of the quartet could have dinner at a restaurant
                    with him the next night. She talked to the other members of the quartet and then
                    said: “Yes, we'd love to have dinner with you.”</p>
                <p>So they had dinner together. During the dinner he leaned over to her, so they
                    told me years later, and whispered to her: “Miss Harting, after dinner, could we
                    go to a movie? “ She answered: “Oh, yes, I think that we'd all love to go to a
                    movie.” My father whispered again: “I don't mean all of you. I mean just you and
                    me.” She replied: “Well, all right,” and so they went to the movie.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>That began their romance. They saw each other frequently after that in Pensacola.
                    Months later the quartet went on a concert tour, but they kept in touch with
                    each other and when she returned to Pensacola they were subsequently married. I
                    was born about a year and a half after that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your father's occupation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: He was a banker. He was born in Mobile, Alabama. He had worked in a bank
                    there and then went over to Pensacola, Florida, because during World War I
                    Pensacola had become a very important naval base. He went to work also for an
                    automobile dealership in Pensacola, Florida. But he returned to banking when we
                    moved to Chicago in the spring of 1920.</p>
                <p>My father later claimed that when I was six months old in Pensacola, Florida, I
                    stood up in the baby crib, shook the bars, and laughingly said: “This is no
                    place for a Republican! [Laughter]. Let's go north to my mother's city of
                    Chicago!” So he used to say to friends, “I took my son's advice and every winter
                    after that, I regretted it,” having lived in the south all his life.</p>
                <p>He became a banker in Chicago. He was finally vice president and cashier of his
                    bank. We lived on Sheridan Road in the Rogers Park section of Chicago, just a
                    block and a half from the shore of Lake Michigan. When I was a young boy, I used
                    to go down to the lake with my parents and friends to swim, and I swam in Lake
                    Michigan for almost 50 years, because later on, when I was married to Loraine,
                    we bought a house on Lake Michigan, in Kenilworth, Illinois. I just loved living
                    on the lake. We lived in that house for 17 years before we went to Washington,
                    DC when I was elected to the Senate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the name of this bank?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: It was the Rogers Park National Bank of Chicago.</p>
                <p>As a boy I loved to work. When I went to school and was about seven years old, my
                    mother would give me money to go and buy groceries at the store. She would give
                    me a list, and I would buy the groceries, pay for them, and bring the groceries
                    back home. She'd give me 10 cents for this job. My mother always called me
                    “Charles,” by the way, but other boys, my school friends then, called me,
                    “Charley.”</p>
                <p>We lived in a third floor apartment. One day she called down to us, as I was
                    playing in the courtyard with my school friends. My school friends had been
                    calling me, “Charley.” She called down and said, “Boys, his name is 'Charles.'
                    It's not 'Charley.'” Well, they told me that they couldn't call me “Charles.” So
                    they called me “Chuck,” and I've been called Chuck ever since then, by
                    everyone.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>My mother spelled her name, Elisabeth, with an “S.” I once said to her, “Mother,
                    why do you spell 'Elisabeth' with an 'S'? All of the friends I have in school by
                    that name spell it with a 'Z.'” I never could say anything to her without her
                    having a ready answer for my question. She said: “Well, Charles, it's spelled
                    twice in the Bible with an 'S.' Isn't that good enough for you?”When I was eight
                    years old I started a little shopping business. I was getting 10 cents from each
                    of the neighborhood women for whom I was doing the shopping. It would sometimes
                    take an hour to go to buy the various things from the stores and bring them back
                    in my wagon. I remember one woman, Mrs. Barett, who used to order only one can
                    of Campbell's tomato soup each day I shopped for her. On one occasion, when I
                    brought the groceries home to her, she said: “Now Charles, I only ordered one
                    can of Campbell's tomato soup, and you brought me three cans. Why?” I said:
                    “Well, today they were on sale. Three cans of Campbell tomato soup for 39 cents.
                    So you saved 10 cents by buying three cans. Every time I shop for you, you buy a
                    can of tomato soup.” She said: “Well, aren't you a smart boy! Here, here's an
                    extra nickel for you.” So that got me started on profit sharing. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>One day, when I was pulling my wagon along Pratt Boulevard, right near Clark
                    Street in Rogers Park, on my way back to our apartment, a man drove up to me and
                    called from his car window. “Sonny, come over here.” I went over to him, and he
                    said: “How much do you make carrying those groceries? I see you going back and
                    forth frequently.” I said: “I make 10 cents.” He held up a dollar bill and said:
                    “How would you like to make a dollar?” I said: “A whole dollar! How?” He said:
                    “Just sell this pile of magazines - the Saturday Evening Post, published by the
                    Curtis Publishing Company.”</p>
                <p>So that was how I began to sell The Saturday Evening Post. I also began to sell
                    their Ladies Home Journal and then The Country Gentleman. It was hard to sell
                    The Country Gentleman in the city. However, then I went down to my father's
                    bank. I started to sell The Saturday Evening Post there first. I was a little
                    kid at the time, but was the son of the cashier of the bank, and I was able to
                    go right behind the counters, talk to the tellers, and say: “Would you like to
                    buy a Saturday Evening Post?” I remember what a teller said to me one day.
                    “Well, I already bought a copy last night on my way home.” I said: “Well, would
                    you wait next week until I come, and I'll bring it to you each week.” He said:
                    “Of course. Next week and every week bring it to me.” So this was when I learned
                    what “clout” meant. Practically everyone in the bank bought The Saturday Evening
                    Post from me. Then I started selling The Ladies Home Journal and The Country
                    Gentleman, in addition to selling the magazines to many of our neighbors and
                    other people in the community. One year I won a year's scholarship to the
                    Evanston YMCA from Curtis Publishing Company for selling more Country Gentleman
                    magazines in a city than any other sales boy in the United States. Then I got a
                    newspaper route also, when the so-called “Great Depression” [economic downturn
                    of the 1930s] came. During the Depression, my father's bank failed.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>The New York stock market crashed in 1929. The Rogers Park National Bank failed,
                    and my father later went into bankruptcy. Not in the sense of bankruptcies now
                    in the news, concerning which Congress is passing new laws. My father did not go
                    into bankruptcy until some time later, after he was out of a job. While working
                    at the bank he had borrowed a lot of money to invest in his bank's stocks, and
                    still owed a substantial amount of money on these loans. When the bank failed,
                    he was out of a job, and the stock was worthless. Without a job, there was no
                    way he could pay his debts much less provide for our living expenses. So he went
                    into bankruptcy.</p>
                <p>By then I could type. I had learned to type in grammar school. I typed something
                    like 20 letters to companies on my father's behalf. Only seven of these
                    companies even replied, saying something like: “He's too old. He's over 40. We
                    have no jobs available,” or something like that. At that time during the
                    Depression companies weren't hiring people who were that old. My father just
                    couldn't get a job in Chicago.</p>
                <p>By then I enjoyed working and earning my own spending money, as well as helping
                    feed my mother, father, sister, and brother. I started getting more important
                    jobs which paid more money. I had a morning newspaper route. I left our
                    apartment at 4:30 a.m. to deliver The Chicago Herald-Examiner, a William
                    Randolph Hearst newspaper back in those days. I also delivered the paper on
                    Sundays, seven days a week.Because of our poverty we became eligible for one of
                    the federal “relief” programs started by President Franklin D. Roosevelt. On
                    Saturday mornings, every week, we received a bundle of groceries, delivered to
                    our apartment. We lived at that time on the third floor, in a tiny one bedroom
                    apartment. There were five of us living there, including my brother Howard,
                    sister Doris, both of them younger than I, myself, and my father and mother. My
                    brother and I slept in the dining room on the floor.</p>
                <p>I had no closet for my clothes. Whatever clothes I had we just piled them in a
                    corner of the dining room floor. My brother and I slept there for several years.
                    However, one day when the relief agency delivered our food, they made a mistake
                    and got us mixed up with a nursing home or something like that. They left 100
                    pounds of sugar instead of the usual 5 pound bag.</p>
                <p>My father was a very honest man. Mother kept the change and managed the household
                    accounts. He said to my mother: “Can I have a nickel [5 cents] please to go
                    across the street to the drug store and use the telephone? “I want to telephone
                    the relief people and tell them that they made a mistake.” But mother said: “No,
                    let me sleep on this matter tonight and maybe call tomorrow morning.” So, the
                    next morning, my father said: “Now can I have the nickel to go over and phone
                    the relief people and tell them that they delivered too much sugar to us?”</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>My mother said: “No, I prayed last night, and the thought came to me that the
                    Lord brought that sugar, and only the Lord can take it away.” She then said: “My
                    thought is that Chuck is delivering his newspapers and magazines. He's up every
                    day, early every morning and during the afternoon, calling on people to get more
                    subscriptions. Then he goes and collects money for what he sells.” I did have to
                    collect weekly for every copy of The Chicago Herald-Examiner that I delivered to
                    people's homes. The newspaper didn't have a collection system at that time. I
                    had to collect on its behalf, but was paid extra for this additional service.
                    Then I would take more time and solicit people for new subscriptions and so
                    build my list of subscribers, against competition from the huge Chicago Tribune,
                    then a competitor of The Chicago Herald-Examiner. My mother said, “While he was
                    out there doing this, I could make cookies and brownies with that 100 pounds of
                    sugar. Charles could sell those, and we could make enough money to buy more
                    ingredients to expand and continue our new business and even pay the relief
                    agency for the original 100 pounds.”</p>
                <p>We did make enough money from selling the cookies so that we could buy another
                    100 pounds of sugar, and she kept doing this. I look now and see some cookies
                    selling for over a dollar apiece, when I had been selling ours in 1933 for 15
                    cents a dozen. Imagine that!</p>
                <p>Then, after President Roosevelt was inaugurated, he proposed, and Congress
                    approved, the establishment of the “New Deal” with the WPA, or Works Progress
                    Administration. An important part of it provided jobs to 8-1/2 million
                    unemployed American people, including my mother. One of the programs under the
                    WPA was the sponsorship of the Illinois Symphony Orchestra. So Mother applied
                    for a job as a violinist with the WPA-sponsored Illinois Symphony Orchestra and
                    received it. The Illinois Symphony Orchestra gave concerts in many of the state
                    schools, retirement homes, and for the public. It was a wonderful program. The
                    income from this job made it possible for us to get off of relief then, because
                    Mother was making enough money from this WPA program to feed our family. We
                    finally had dignity once again.</p>
                <p>I first became really interested in politics in 1932 when Republican incumbent
                    Herbert Hoover ran against Democrat Franklin D. Roosevelt. My father was a
                    “Southern Republican,” which, in those days, was very unusual.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>On the occasion of the November 1932 election day, at age 13, I took their hands
                    and walked between them going to the polling booth in Rogers Park, Chicago. I
                    saw them vote. Then, while walking back home to our apartment, my father said:
                    “Well, I sure do hope that Hoover wins.” Mother didn't say anything. Then my
                    father said to my mother: “Well, Dear, don't you hope that Herbert Hoover wins?”
                    She looked up at him and said: “Hoover won't win with my vote.” My father
                    shouted: “What! You voted for Roosevelt? Why? Why?” I'll never forget what she
                    said. “I voted for Roosevelt because he promised to help the poor and bring
                    relief and jobs to the unemployed.” Mother was right because Roosevelt did
                    establish the WPA (Work Progress Administration) when three out of four U.S.
                    workers were unemployed. Often people vote from their stomachs. When you look
                    today at President Clinton's favorable rating despite his tragic personal
                    problems, if the economy was “down” and unemployment was high, and more people
                    were on relief, and so forth, he wouldn't have as favorable ratings as he has
                    had.</p>
                <p>Q: Oh, yes, they really do. I think that this is one of the things that you are
                    pointing out. There was a lot of complaining about the WPA, particularly by
                    Republican supporters. They made fun of it in general. Yet, it was the first
                    time that jobs were actually created. There were WPA programs in support of
                    local symphony orchestras, the arts, and all of that. These programs really gave
                    people jobs and, as you said, a sense of dignity. This was a very important
                    consideration.</p>
                <p>PERCY: Another thing that occurs to me is that I had been attending in Chicago,
                    Armstrong Grammar School. Then I attended Sullivan Junior High School and then
                    Sullivan High School. Since then I have continued to receive their bulletins. I
                    was made “honoree” of the year of Sullivan High School a couple of years ago. We
                    still have reunions of that group.</p>
                <p>At that time the Chicago public schools were very poor. They had been bad for
                    years. During the Depression there were interruptions in paying the teachers.
                    The city authorities couldn't pay the teachers for months on end at times. In
                    many cases the teachers simply refused to teach. We students still had to go to
                    school, but we just had to sit there in the classroom. We had no instruction for
                    several months. It was a terrible situation.</p>
                <p>Finally, my father, even though Dad and Mother had very little money at the time,
                    decided that we just had to do something to find a solution to the education
                    problem. We scraped together enough money to pay one month's rent in advance for
                    a house in Wilmette, Illinois. It was probably the lowest cost house in Wilmette
                    at the time. So by the beginning of my junior year in high school, since we had
                    moved to Wilmette, Illinois, I did enter New Trier Township High School. This
                    was known then and since, as a truly great high school, one of the best in the
                    USA.</p>
                <p>I used to play tennis with a great friend, Doug Coyle, in Rogers Park. I liked
                    tennis. Doug Coyle told me about a fellow that he played tennis with, a great
                    tennis player, named Arthur Nielson, Jr. Doug said that Art Nielson was a
                    student at New Trier Township High School. He suggested that I look up Art
                    Nielson when I enrolled at New Trier.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>By a strange coincidence, on the first day of my junior year in September 1935, I
                    was assigned to Mr. Condon's “home room.” I went to this home room at 8:00 a.m.
                    I sat down and put my hand out to the fellow next to me and said: “I'd like to
                    introduce myself. I'm Chuck Percy.” He replied: “Don't tell me that you're Chuck
                    Percy from Rogers Park! I know of you from Doug Coyle.” I said: “You don't mean
                    to say that you're Art Nielson!” He said: “Yes, I am.” Years later, I told this
                    story at a memorial program, when I was able to present Art Nielson with an
                    award. He still remembered that story.</p>
                <p>Q: You're talking about school. Could you tell us a little bit more? Here you
                    were, getting up at 4:30 a.m., every morning, running errands, and doing all of
                    these things. What about schooling in the sense of reading and getting yourself
                    educated? How was this coming along?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Well, I worked hard at school. I loved education. Previously, at my
                    various schools I cannot remember a teacher that inspired me very much. I had
                    wonderful friends at Armstrong Grammar School and Sullivan High School, and we
                    kept up with each other.</p>
                <p>However, by comparison with my other schools, the teachers at New Trier High
                    School were absolutely outstanding. They were paid more than many college
                    professors. New Trier was and still is one of the great high schools, if not the
                    best high school in the USA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My brothers went there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Yes, it's just absolutely a great high school. I was chairman recently of
                    my 55th reunion at the University of Chicago and I attended the 60th reunion of
                    my class at New Trier Township High School in 1997.</p>
                <p>When I began attending New Trier High School in September 1935 as soon as my
                    family moved to Wilmette, I went to the school Registrar. I said that I really
                    needed a job. If there were any kind of a job in which I could be helpful, I
                    needed to make money to help support my family. We really needed to raise the
                    money to pay the next month's rent on our house. I said that we didn't have
                    enough money now to do that.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>Most of the families of the boys attending New Trier High School were reasonably
                    wealthy. Chicago's north shore was one of the wealthiest communities in the
                    country. Practically none of my classmates needed to work. The Registrar said:
                    “Oh, absolutely. Does your family have a car?” I said: “No, not at all. We don't
                    even have a telephone.” So the Registrar said: “I'm going to put you in charge
                    of organizing this.” He said: “Some of the students drive to New Trier in their
                    family cars, or their families drop them off. We need someone to be in charge of
                    parking the cars.” Then he also helped me get a job working with the local
                    Rotary Club [then a national and now a worldwide community service
                    organization], dealing with problems of delinquency involving boys who got into
                    trouble with school officials and sometimes the police, counseling them. Then I
                    became owner and manager of what we called the “Fraternity Cooperative
                    Purchasing Agency” at the U of C.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, I got a job as an usher at the “Teatro del Lago” movie theater in an
                    area known as “No Man's Land,” right between Kenilworth and Wilmette near Lake
                    Michigan. I worked there every single night, seven nights a week. In those days,
                    there were no laws regulating hours of work. I would go to work at 5:00 p.m.,
                    work until 10:00 p.m. at night, and then every Saturday and Sunday from noon
                    until 10:00 p.m. My father also was able to get a job selling fruits and
                    vegetables at a food store in Wilmette. Then we could pay our rent for the house
                    and other expenses. My wonderful younger sister, Doris, and brother, Howard, did
                    well in school and also in their work.</p>
                <p>Then, on the basis of my scholastic record at New Trier High School, I was able
                    to apply for and was offered scholarships by three different universities, two
                    of them outside Illinois, including one in Pennsylvania and one in California,
                    in addition to one at the University of Chicago. The scholarship at the
                    University of Chicago covered just half of the tuition which amounted to only
                    about $300 a semester in those days. I had to make the remaining $150 to cover
                    the tuition at the University of Chicago, plus room and board and still
                    continuing to help my father, mother, sister, and brother to pay their expenses.
                    But the U of C was a great university with Robert Maynard Hutchins as
                    president.</p>
                <p>So, I then established residence in Burton Court, which was a residence hall at
                    the University of Chicago, and being in Chicago I could visit my family
                    frequently in its suburb, Wilmette, going to and coming back on the elevated
                    train. The supervisor of the residence hall appointed me a “Proctor of
                    Discipline” which covered my room cost.</p>
                <p>Also, I had a job in my freshman year, waiting tables in the residence hall,
                    which paid for my board. I remember very well one time when I was serving the
                    freshmen and sophomores then living there. I was told that a candidate for a
                    “Ph.D.” [Doctor of Philosophy degree] was coming to visit the residence hall. He
                    was described as a “very important student,” one of the most important students
                    at the University of Chicago. I was advised to be “very careful” when I served
                    him and to take good care of him.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>So that night I first served him his main course. Then I majestically put the
                    dessert down in front of him, like this, with a “swirl” of my arm. It was pecan
                    pie with whipped cream and sauce on top of it. I looked down and saw, to my
                    horror, that there was no whipped cream or sauce on top of the pie. Instead, it
                    was all over his coat's shoulder! [Laughter] He gave me a kind of angry look. I
                    thought: “Oh, here I am supposed to take special care of him and look at what
                    I've done!” But I said to him: “Oh, don't worry about that,” he sort of relaxed,
                    and then I said: “I'll get you another piece of pie.” [Laughter] He had to have
                    his coat cleaned. I'll never forget that incident.</p>
                <p>Then I was invited to join Alpha Delta Phi fraternity. I said: “Really, I can't
                    afford this. I need all of the money that I can make. I can't afford the annual
                    dues.” The fraternity people said: “Well, we have a 'fellowship' arrangement
                    here.” (It still continues and is now part of the Title I (C3) program set up
                    under federal law.) They told me that they could give me some fellowship
                    assistance at the fraternity and that I would have a job as a waiter and steward
                    of the fraternity for its meals. They told me that they understood that I had
                    experience in buying food. They said that I could buy the food for the
                    fraternity and wash the dishes after the meals. They said that I could do that,
                    and that would pay for my room and board at the fraternity.</p>
                <p>So I gave up my job over at the residence hall and moved over to the Alpha Delta
                    Phi fraternity house. After I had been steward of the fraternity for some time
                    and was buying the food, I saw a fellow pushing a cart, with fruits and
                    vegetables on it, selling them from door to door in the Woodlawn area. I said to
                    him: “I've bought some fruits and vegetables from you, and they're always very
                    fresh and good. Where do you get them?” He said: “Well, I've managed to buy them
                    from the truck which buys them from the central food market and then delivers
                    them to the university area. I go over and buy them and then have to push this
                    cart about a mile to get to this university neighborhood to sell them.” I said
                    to him: “Instead of going from door to door to sell them, I could form a
                    “fraternity purchasing agency” and how would you like to sell them all to us?
                    All these fraternities are reasonably close together, and I am working with the
                    Inter-Fraternity Council here. Why don't I propose to the Council that you buy
                    the fruits and vegetables, not just for the 40 members of my fraternity but for
                    about 500 members of other fraternities? With that volume, you and we can get
                    lower prices.” So he agreed to try that and was enthusiastic about the idea.</p>
                <p>He then needed money to buy a truck. I went to a bank, where our fraternity had
                    an account. I had a good relationship with the bank because of my father having
                    been a banker. From time to time I had borrowed money from the bank and always
                    paid it back. So I got this man a loan to buy a small, used truck. His name was
                    Maurice Rinella. Some years ago, my wife, Loraine, and I attended his 50th
                    wedding anniversary. By then he had become the largest purveyor of fruits and
                    vegetables in the Chicago area, selling to many of the large hotels. He was just
                    a wonderful, wonderful man. Now his son is head of the company and they have a
                    large number of trucks.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>I had a Sunday School teacher at age 16, in 1935, Mr. Joseph McNabb, at the First
                    Church of Christ Scientists in Wilmette, who was president and a large stock
                    holder of a company called Bell &amp; Howell. I said to him one day: “My father
                    needs a better job. He's a very talented banker and accountant. Now he's just
                    got a job as a nighttime hotel receptionist. Could you have somebody interview
                    him to see whether or not he could get a better daytime job with Bell &amp;
                    Howell?” So they interviewed him and soon hired him. He was put in charge of the
                    mailroom at Bell &amp; Howell, handling all incoming and outgoing mail, a much
                    more dignified job, and day work hours.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Bell &amp; Howell doing at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: They were in the motion picture camera and projection business, but as a
                    modest-sized company then with a few hundred employees or so. That was when I
                    was in high school at New Trier. When I later went to the University of Chicago
                    in 1937, Mr McNabb asked if I would like to work for Bell &amp; Howell as an
                    apprentice. He said that he was impressed with how I wanted to help my father,
                    mother, sister, and brother, and said I could come up north by the “elevated”
                    train system to the Bell &amp; Howell plant from the University of Chicago,
                    since I was living on campus. The fare just cost 10 cents in those days. He said
                    that I could work any hour of the day or night, because Bell &amp; Howell had
                    three shifts per day, and work any number of hours consistent with my scholastic
                    schedule.</p>
                <p>So I became an apprentice for the Bell &amp; Howell company in 1938. I worked
                    there as an apprentice for four years, the whole time that I was at the
                    University of Chicago. That was one of five jobs that I had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My God!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Robert Maynard Hutchins, who was president of the University of Chicago,
                    said to me when I was a sophomore: “You are the exact kind of student that I've
                    been trying to keep out of the university, ever since I've been in this
                    university business!” He continued: “While going to the University you are
                    working at five different jobs. Why didn't you make enough money first so that
                    you could then come to college and then spend full time studying?” I said:
                    “Well, I felt that I should get my college education when I did, but help my
                    family at the same time.” I had worked hard at doing this. He said: “I know,”
                    but he seemed unconvinced. But in my senior year at the University of Chicago, I
                    was elected by the faculty, “Marshal” to President Hutchins, who also happened
                    to be a member of the Alpha Delta Phi fraternity from another university. In my
                    senior year, 1941, I was president of the Alpha Delta Phi fraternity and of the
                    University Inter-Fraternity Council, and captain of our water polo team.
                    President Hutchins, however, was also against so much emphasis on
                    intercollegiate sports.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I know.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: President Hutchins was very much against baseball, which he banished from
                    the University of Chicago. He didn't see why I should spend time on sports.
                    However, during his tenure as president of the University of Chicago, this was
                    the last time that the university won a “Big 10” championship. When I was
                    captain of the water polo team, the water polo team did win the “Big 10”
                    championship [the “Big 10” was and is an association of Midwestern
                    universities]. I went out for water polo because I liked to wrestle and I liked
                    to swim and in my freshman year was doing both. The two coaches, for water polo
                    and wrestling, told me: “You ought to make up your mind as to which one you
                    want. One sport strengthens your muscles and the other one loosens them. So the
                    two sports may be working against each other.” I was combining the two sports
                    when I switched to water polo, where you kind of wrestle in the water against
                    your opponents. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>Q: Let's talk a little bit about the University of Chicago. Robert Maynard
                    Hutchins brought in the “Great Books” program, which was basically focused on
                    the classics, and everything filled out from there. However, the classics were
                    the core of the program. What were you studying at the University of Chicago,
                    and how did the “Great Books” program appear to you?</p>
                <p>PERCY: I took the “Great Books” course taught by President Hutchins, who taught
                    this one course together with Dr. Mortimer J. Adler, a well-known professor at
                    the University. It was in my junior year at the University of Chicago. Only 30
                    students were selected who were allowed to take that program. Getting into it
                    was very competitive. Academically, I was doing well so I was encouraged to take
                    this very special course. That's when I really got to know Robert M. Hutchins
                    well. That's when he first repented for what he had said to me originally about
                    holding so many jobs while at the U of C. I loved the “Great Books” course and
                    still love the books covered in it. That course had a marked impact on me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Chuck, in what way?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: It was one of the best courses that I've ever taken. After I had graduated
                    and was working at Bell &amp; Howell I still continued to study the Great Books
                    with a treasured friend, Dr. Robert Goldwin.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>In my opinion now, it is important for every American, and perhaps even more so
                    for those who hold public office, to study the great works of Western
                    Civilization. In these writings we encounter the original and authoritative
                    source of the fundamental principles that shape our country. From Plato's
                    Republic and Aristotle's Politics and Ethics, we learn the first teachings of
                    justice and law. In the writings of John Locke we encounter the teachings about
                    civil rights and religious tolerance that so powerfully influenced the American
                    founders and to this day distinguish our system of government from so many
                    others in the world. And of course there are the Federalist Papers, the great
                    exposition of the way the United States is constituted, written by the principal
                    authors of our Constitution, James Madison, John Jay, and Alexander
                    Hamilton.</p>
                <p>In addition to the political works, which I naturally tend to emphasize, there
                    are the great works of literature - the Greek tragedies and Shakespeare, to
                    mention only the most obvious - that have so powerfully shaped our understanding
                    of the meaning of life. And, finally, I would put The Bible at the top of my
                    list as the one I have found to be indispensable and that I read with my wife
                    daily.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you see yourself as “pointed” toward anything in particular? Here you were
                    working long hours at your various jobs. I'm not quite sure whether you got any
                    sleep during the time you mentioned. Did you see your education at the
                    University of Chicago “leading” to anything, other than just getting an
                    education?</p>
                <p>PERCY: My education, particularly specializing in economics, plus the jobs that I
                    held, really led to a business career after graduation, because I related so
                    much to business. However, I also started to get interested in public affairs.
                    After all, public affairs, in national trade, and in economics, were important
                    factors of life in those days.</p>
                <p>However, going back to my experience with Bell &amp; Howell, when I graduated
                    from the University of Chicago, I still needed money to help support my family.
                    My brother and sister had their own needs. My sister, for example, had vital
                    dental work which she needed to have done, and they didn't have the money to pay
                    for that. So I paid for her dental work.</p>
                <p>That reminds me of something which I had forgotten to mention. After I had worked
                    for Bell &amp; Howell for four years and was graduating from the University of
                    Chicago...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean when you were about to graduate from the
                        University oChicago.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>PERCY: Well, by that time I had worked as an apprentice for Bell &amp; Howell
                    Company for four years while I was at the University of Chicago. Towards the end
                    of my senior year in 1941, the university invited business representatives to
                    come to the campus to interview those of us who were about to graduate and
                    wanted jobs. I was interviewed by the representatives of many of these
                    companies. One of them was the Armstrong Cork Company. They offered me a job to
                    replace a district sales manager, because they said that I was good in marketing
                    and had an impressive working experience. They offered me a job that paid twice
                    the salary that anyone else in my class had been offered.</p>
                <p>So when Bell &amp; Howell asked me what I would like to do after I graduated from
                    the University of Chicago, I said that I felt obligated and deeply grateful to
                    Bell &amp; Howell. My father had a challenging job with them now, and things
                    were moving along better for my family. However, I said that I felt an
                    obligation to accept this job offer from Armstrong Cork, as that paid too much
                    for Bell &amp; Howell to match. I said that Armstrong Cork was a much bigger
                    company. The job they had offered me was a wonderful job. I said that I didn't
                    expect to be paid as much by Bell &amp; Howell.</p>
                <p>In response to this comment the Bell &amp; Howell Personnel Manager in May 1941
                    said: “Well, look, if you came to work for Bell &amp; Howell, what kind of a job
                    would you like?” The Personnel Manager then said: “You've worked in practically
                    every department of Bell &amp; Howell. You worked as an apprentice even in the
                    Engineering Department. You were in the Manufacturing Department, and spent a
                    lot of time out in the shop as well as in marketing and accounting. What
                    department would you like to work in if you came to work for us on a permanent
                    basis?” I said: “Well, I would have liked to work in a department that doesn't
                    exist.” He said: “Well, what department would that be?”</p>
                <p>I said that all of the metals I had worked on in the shop were “light weight”
                    metals, such as aluminum and magnesium for cameras and motion picture sound
                    projectors that they sold for use by adults but also by children in school. They
                    had to be made out of “light metal.” I then said that I thought that the United
                    States might get into the war, that we were going to be drawn into it, somehow.
                    If we were drawn in, the USA was going to need many more military aircraft. The
                    U.S. Government would requisition all of the light metals for aircraft for war
                    production. I asked whether then Bell &amp; Howell would have to make cameras
                    and projectors out of lead? How could the kids in the schools carry lead
                    projectors around their school classes? So I thought that Bell &amp; Howell
                    would then need to get into war work. That's the department that I would want to
                    work in. However, as I had told him, Armstrong Cork had offered me too much
                    money compared with what Bell &amp; Howell could offer and I needed the extra
                    money for me and particularly my family.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>The Bell &amp; Howell Personnel Manager said: “Well, would you continue to work
                    here for awhile and let us think about this?” I said: “Okay,” as I hadn't quite
                    graduated from the University of Chicago as yet. Two days later the Personnel
                    Manager called me in and said that Bell &amp; Howell would increase the salary
                    they offered me beyond what I had been offered by Armstrong Cork. I said: “What
                    job would I have then?” He said: “We're going to create a War Coordinating
                    Department, if that's what you want to call it.” So I said: “Well, who will head
                    it that I would report to?” I was then told: “It was your idea, and you'll head
                    it.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were then, what, 21 years old?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Well, that happened in May 1941. Yes, I was then age 21. So the Personnel
                    Manager said: “You'll not only head this new department but you'll report
                    directly to the president of the company, Joseph McNabb, because he thinks that
                    this is such a great creative idea.”</p>
                <p>We started this department. I was very much interested in the U.S. Navy, and soon
                    obtained a contract for Bell &amp; Howell to manufacture “gunsight aiming point
                    cameras” to put in Navy aircraft. I also was able to get Bell &amp; Howell a
                    contract from the Navy for “torpedo directors.” That was totally different from
                    anything that the company had previously manufactured, but they had the
                    necessary skills. I knew that they had the engineering and manufacturing skills
                    to do it. So we were “under way” with both of those contracts. Then on December
                    7, 1941 Pearl Harbor was bombed by Japanese naval aircraft and the United States
                    became deeply involved in World War II. So the Navy sought me out to procure the
                    lenses for these two and other devices. At the time, Bausch and Lomb was the
                    only lens company of any size in the United States. We had previously bought a
                    lot of lenses from Germany and Japan. Now those sources of supply were cut
                    off.</p>
                <p>So I applied to the U.S. Government Defense Plant Corporation for money to build
                    a plant to manufacture lenses on Bell &amp; Howell property. This was a project
                    involving millions of dollars, and we were successful in getting the money to
                    build that plant. Then the Navy designated a Commander to be in charge of this
                    project and to be in contact with us from Washington. He was in charge of war
                    work being handled by Bell &amp; Howell. He went back and forth and I worked
                    with him for about two years.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>The military draft program was in operation but the Wilmette, Illinois Draft
                    Board had exempted me from military service because they said that I was more
                    valuable here, with the military work I was doing. That made me “draft exempt,”
                    and I was informed that I would never have to go into military service. This
                    bothered me because my friends, such as Art Nielson, were almost all going into
                    military service, and here I was still back home. I finally went to see Mr.
                    McNabb and said: “President McNabb, I just have to tell you that my conscience
                    is so hurt by my staying here in civilian life. I love this work, and I run for
                    Bell &amp; Howell a department that you say is going well. I have a replacement,
                    however, who can fully take over my duties. I feel that I must resign from Bell
                    &amp; Howell and enlist into military service.”</p>
                <p>President McNabb said, “Well, Chuck, I was afraid that this might happen. I fully
                    understand and know how you feel. Would you promise one thing to me? Because it
                    was your idea about what we should do before the war broke out, and we are doing
                    well, while you're in military service, think about what Bell &amp; Howell
                    should do after the war. Just write me a letter, say, every three months, and
                    tell me what you think we ought to do after the war. Don't resign - take a leave
                    of absence from Bell &amp; Howell and we'll keep you on a partial salary, so
                    that you'll have a little extra money, which you can save or do whatever you
                    want to do with it.” I said: “Well, I may even want to get married! We'll see. I
                    accept with pleasure.”</p>
                <p>However, I added, “What I'd like to do is apply to enter the Navy Air Force but I
                    am afraid that the Navy might not take me because I need glasses.” I said: “Let
                    me talk to the Commander assigned to Bell &amp; Howell and see what can be
                    done.” I talked to the Commander, who said: “Chuck, I will do everything that I
                    can do to see that you get into the Navy. I think that I can get you into the
                    Navy in what is called the “G-7” program.” However, he said: “You'll start in
                    immediately as an Apprentice Seaman and you'll have to go to some place like
                    Dartmouth College for a 60-day basic training program. If you complete this
                    program in 60 days, you'll be commissioned an Ensign as an officer in the Navy.
                    Promise me that you'll come to work for me in Washington for one year. Then
                    you're free to go any place that you and the Navy want you to go.”</p>
                <p>So I did that. He arranged for me to serve in the Naval Air Force as a gunnery
                    officer. I went to Dartmouth University, had a wonderful 60 days of training
                    there in the Navy. I loved the Navy. Then, after completing this training, I
                    went down to Washington, DC and reported to him for a few months. I also
                    proposed marriage to a young woman whose family lived in Kenilworth who had
                    graduated from Northwestern University, Jeanne Dickerson, that I had been dating
                    when I was going to the University of Chicago. We had a saying at that time:
                    “Get your education at the University of Chicago and get your dates from
                    Northwestern University!” [Laughter] She was a lovely young woman. I proposed to
                    her, and we were married the first year I was in the Navy.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>When I originally proposed to Jeanne Dickerson she said: “You know, I have
                    ulcerative colitis and must take drugs for it. Her mother was a chronic invalid
                    and was more or less always in bed. Her family lived in Kenilworth, Illinois,
                    near Lake Michigan. Jeanne was sort of “flustered” by this situation because she
                    took constant care for her mother. I said: “Well, I know that you have it, but
                    that's all right. We can pray and we'll hope to solve this problem. It's caused
                    probably by extreme anxiety and concern. You have concern about your mother. You
                    can be healed.” Then Jeanne said: “What you don't know, and what you have to
                    know is that the doctors tell me that I can't have children.” I said: “Well, if
                    that's true, and I hope that it isn't, we can always adopt children. The nearby
                    Evanston Illinois Cradle is the best adoption center in the country, I have
                    heard.” I said that I was not marrying her just to have children. So Jeanne
                    said: “Yes,” and we were subsequently married.</p>
                <p>We lived in the Washington, DC area, in Arlington, Virginia. I took a bus every
                    day to my office in the old Naval Munitions Building, on Constitution Avenue. It
                    was so very hot in Washington that first summer of 1943. There was no
                    air-conditioning on the buses, which were very crowded in those days. I usually
                    had to stand up on the crowded buses and was dripping wet by the time I got to
                    my office. I worked for this commander, who had in his very large office
                    quarters only one window air conditioner. He sat near the air conditioner. As I
                    was only an ensign then, the lowest officer rank, I sat practically out in the
                    hall! It was uncomfortable, but I was there for a full year.</p>
                <p>Then, at the end of the year, the commander said to me: “You've been wonderful to
                    stay with me for a year. Now, I know that you want to 'get going' and get out
                    there with the fighting Navy with greater activity. Go over and talk to Bill,
                    the Chief Petty Officer who writes the personnel orders. There's an organization
                    that we have just created called Advanced Base Aviation Training Units. I want
                    you to get a job as head of ABATU, as we will call it. Tell Bill to write the
                    necessary orders for you, and I'll see that they are signed.” I've told him to
                    write good orders for you, very flexible, as you will see, commensurate with
                    your strong business background.”</p>
                <p>So this Chief Petty Officer wrote the orders. I was ordered “to proceed to the
                    place or places that you see fit in the performance of your duties. You will
                    have a Class 3 Priority on Navy aircraft, with permission to fly and the right
                    to draw whatever services and goods you need from any Naval Air Station.” I was
                    also given the right to request the assignment of Navy personnel to help me to
                    carry out my duties in the Advanced Base Aviation Training Unit. They wanted me
                    to start out training people, including pilots and ground crews on Naval Air
                    Bases, to put the fires out on aircraft that crashed and to try to save the
                    lives of the pilots and the other crew members of these aircraft. To also train
                    gunnery officers to use gunsight aiming point cameras that had been manufactured
                    by Bell &amp; Howell. I was ordered to begin work immediately on this
                    project.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>What I did was to requisition sailors who had had some experience in these
                    activities. I put the request in to get skilled personnel. I decided to move my
                    headquarters base to the Naval Aviation Station in Alameda, California, across
                    the Bay from San Francisco, because there were aircraft carrier planes coming in
                    there on ships frequently. They went out from there into the Pacific Theater of
                    Operations starting with Hawaii. So it was agreed that the headquarters of ABATU
                    would be at the Naval Air Station, Alameda, California, so I took my wife out
                    there with me.</p>
                <p>After we'd been there for a year or so, Jeanne became pregnant. Apparently our
                    prayerful calm life together had eased her ulcerative colitis condition. When
                    she started to have labor pains, we phoned the Naval Hospital at the Oakland
                    Naval Air Station and were instructed to come right down. So I just dashed down
                    to the hospital with my wife. The Navy doctor looked at me and said: “You
                    certainly are flustered, aren't you? I said: “Yes, I certainly am. How did you
                    know?” He said: “Well, you're wearing one black shoe and one brown shoe with
                    your uniform!”</p>
                <p>I went back to the house to get my wife's clothes as the doctors said that she
                    should stay overnight. Then they called me when I was at home and said: “Your
                    wife has just given birth to a baby.” I said: “What? She's had the baby
                    already?” The doctor said: “Yes.” I said: “What is it, a boy or a girl?” The
                    doctor said, “She's had twin girls. They are very small but fine.” I dashed down
                    to the hospital. And so Sharon and Valerie were born. I'll pick this up later,
                    when we had a boy, before my wife died. I'll tell you then how she passed
                    on.</p>
                <p>On arrival in Alameda, I gave a copy of my orders to the Duty Officer at the
                    Alameda Naval Air Station when I reported in for duty there. The orders just
                    said that I was to report to the base or bases as I saw fit in the performance
                    of my duty. I said that I had decided that the Alameda Naval Air Station was the
                    best place for ABATU to fulfill its purpose.</p>
                <p>Two days later the Commander of the Alameda Naval Air Station sent for me. His
                    name was Admiral Ragsdale. He said: “You know, I've been in the Navy for many
                    years. However, I've never seen a set of orders like this. How did you ever get
                    orders like that? It's unbelievable. However, I'm going to do exactly what these
                    orders say. I'll see that you get a good office right down next to the landing
                    field at the Air Station. We will see that you have whatever personnel and
                    services that you need to carry out your duties.” So I ended up with about 300
                    men reporting to me to undertake all sorts of aircraft gunnery training. We
                    selected 50 of them who had previously been professional fire station attendees.
                    We went out on the aircraft carriers to train the crews.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>Then months later, oddly enough, Admiral Ragsdale said to me: “You know, here in
                    San Francisco, at the Cow Palace, there's an organization of people that started
                    working at Dumbarton Oaks initially in Washington, DC. At the Cow Palace they're
                    creating something to be called, when organized, 'the United Nations.' I'd like
                    to know, and the Navy would like to know, what is going on there. Let me see if
                    I can get permission for you to go over there. Take a jeep. You can just drive
                    over or have someone drive you over. You can stay there and report back to us
                    each day on what's going on there, what's happening there, other than what we
                    see in the newspapers, so that we can understand it better.”</p>
                <p>So that's how I really got interested in the United Nations. This interest
                    continued, and ultimately I was sent as a delegate to the United Nations during
                    my early Senate years. I have strongly supported the United Nations ever since
                    then. I still take the position that we ought to pay our dues to the United
                    Nations. But more about this later.</p>
                <p>Q: I'd like to stop here and just ask you if you could talk about your time when
                    you were observing the development of the United Nations? What was your
                    impression of it?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Well, I thought that bringing together representatives of all of these
                    countries was a great idea. I thought that it was important for them to talk
                    with each other on a regular basis. Not just one country deciding to talk to
                    another country, but rather to bring them all together for the purpose of
                    deciding what kind of world we should be living in and what improvements we can
                    bring, especially to bring more peace to the nations of the world.</p>
                <p>The official United Nations was established in 1945, shortly after World War II
                    ended and I had returned to Bell &amp; Howell. Its purpose was to try to prevent
                    such a world war ever starting again. A charter of the United Nations was drawn
                    up and about 50 nations signed it in 1945. Afterwards, as we know, more than 100
                    other nations joined including our former enemies, such as Germany, Italy, and
                    Japan, and they have contributed leadership and funds greatly to the UN.</p>
                <p>Seven principles of the United Nations were established. They are 1) All members
                    have equal rights, 2) They will carry out their duties under the charter, 3)
                    They agree to the principles of settling their disputes peacefully, 4) They
                    agree not to use force or the threat of force against other Nations except in
                    self-defense, 5) Members agree to help the UN in every action it takes to carry
                    out the purpose of the chapter, 6) The UN agrees to act on the principle that
                    non-member states have the same duties as member states to preserve World peace
                    and security, 7) The UN accepts the principle of not interfering in the actions
                    of a member nation within its own borders, providing these actions do not
                    adversely affect other nations.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>The charter of the UN also lists four purposes of the United Nations. The first
                    purpose is to preserve world peace and security. The second purpose is to
                    encourage nations to be just in their actions toward each other. The third is to
                    help nations cooperate in helping to solve their problems. The fourth purpose is
                    to serve as an Agency through which nations can work towards these goals.</p>
                <p>The major divisions of the UN with which I worked while in the U.S. Senate were
                    1) the General Assembly, 2) the Security Council, 3) the Secretariate, 4) the
                    Economic and Social Council, 5) the International Court of Justice, and 6) the
                    Trusteeship Council.</p>
                <p>I represented the U.S. Senate at the General Assembly of the UN but had to keep
                    up my Senate work at the same time, with the help of my great staff. But I
                    remember one day in particular that I had to fly from UN headquarters in New
                    York to the Capitol in Washington, DC three times to vote on important issues
                    and return each time to New York for the UN session that was also under way.</p>
                <p>On August 4, 1999 The Christian Science Monitor newspaper carried an article by
                    me concerning the United Nations finances and the U.S.' non-payment of our dues.
                    I worked with Susan Eisenhower, Director of the Center for Political and
                    Strategic Studies, Washington, DC and former U.S. Senator Paul Simon on this,
                    and a copy of the article was also inserted into the Congressional Record by
                    Senator Peter Fitzgerald of Illinois.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this effort to organize the United Nations involve
                        mainlAmerican and foreign diplomats? Was this a “confusing period”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: No, there were diplomats, politicians and other political office holders,
                    and various foreign agents and representatives from the various Embassies in
                    Washington. Many countries sent Foreign Ministers from time to time for these
                    discussions. It was a big organization, and it was well handled.</p>
                <p>To go back to my service in the Navy, when I reported back to my Navy commanders
                    at the Alameda Air Station a couple of times a week, they were just thrilled
                    with these preparations for the United Nations. Of course, I kept up my
                    supervision of ABATU at the base as well as on aircraft carriers in the
                    Pacific.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the concerns of the U.S. Navy? You were going to
                        thessessions as a Navy observer.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>PERCY: Well, the Navy's concern was what the world was going to be like after the
                    war. Actually, the Navy knew that I was interested in what the world was going
                    to be like after World War II. I had talked to the Commander at the Naval Air
                    Station in Alameda about that. That's why he said to me: “Here's a real chance
                    for you to see the formation of an organization which may have an impact on the
                    world after World War II is over.” So that is what we did.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Q: Today is the 10th of July, 1998. To begin with, the war is over in 1945. Were
                    you pretty well decided you were going back to Bell &amp; Howell?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Oh, yes, no question about that. I'd never really left Bell &amp; Howell
                    but was put on leave of absence. As I mentioned before, they kept me on the
                    payroll at part-salary, providing I would write letters to the company. I wrote
                    a letter every three months to President Joseph McNabb - and he usually
                    acknowledged them. What should Bell &amp; Howell do after the war? The essence
                    of what I was saying was that they should globalize. They should become more
                    international in Europe, not just a company in the United States and Canada, but
                    go worldwide, particularly with our allies such as Great Britain, France, and so
                    forth, but also with our enemies - with Germany and Japan - taking into account
                    my solid belief that political friendships through the centuries have tended to
                    follow the trade lanes. Therefore, we should resume relationships with those
                    countries, not in war, but in peace and in trade, to bind our economies
                    together, to make our friendship and relationships more lasting. So when I
                    returned to Bell &amp; Howell after the war had ended in victory, they
                    immediately put me in charge of the globalization program. I flew over to Great
                    Britain, sat down with an outstanding producer there, J. Arthur Rank, who was in
                    the motion picture business, producing films and so forth, and jointly formed
                    the idea for a Bell &amp; Howell-Rank Company, to be established right there in
                    England, a factory to manufacture Bell &amp; Howell equipment there for what I
                    hoped would be at lower costs, so we could sell them into Europe and other
                    markets competitively.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had Bell &amp; Howell always had a movie element?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Yes, I should say so. It was founded by Donald Bell and Albert Howell in
                    Chicago (then the movie capital of the nation) in 1907. They started business
                    making movie cameras. Their original products were rooted in much older
                    photographic products, but they made modern movies possible, silents at first
                    followed by sound. Later, the most expensive lens made was developed by Bell
                    &amp; Howell called cinemascope. And that began a whole new industry of
                    wide-screen movies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cinemascope.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>PERCY: For professional, as well as for amateurs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just prior to the war starting in 1939 in Europe, what was
                        thprofessionals' movie camera?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: We had competition obviously from Eastman Kodak who were a very huge
                    company, and of course, they were the biggest maker of film. So the more cameras
                    we made, the more film they sold. So that's why I wanted also to get into the
                    film business. And we did work our way into that field.</p>
                <p>Q: Yes. I was just wondering, I would have thought that going back to Britain,
                    it's a good idea, obviously, to get your foot in the door, but movies,
                    particularly small cameras, are a luxury. We're talking about a bankrupt
                    Britain, a destroyed Germany, a destroyed France, and a destroyed Japan.</p>
                <p>PERCY: After the war we successfully did business with Britain, France, Germany,
                    and Japan. Our biggest manufacture of products was in producing cameras and
                    projectors for these countries. We made a projector for sound movies, so
                    educational films could be shown in their schools. Our biggest market for sound
                    projectors were the schools - universities, high schools, grammar schools. They
                    could show films of the war, films of biology, psychology, history, everything
                    that was being produced. We could enrich the lives of children by bringing the
                    world to them on screen. This was before big television days, of course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: J. Arthur Rank. Did you find at that point that the
                        British waof doing business was different than the American way of doing
                        business?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Our marketing was more creative and war production had modernized our
                    manufacturing procedures. Researching and engineering war products had given us
                    the means to develop more approaches for products sold overseas. Obviously we
                    got along well with the British, as we had the same language and we had fought
                    the war together. We were friends and they did not commercially manufacture
                    lenses, so we sold all the lenses to them from the lens plant at Bell &amp;
                    Howell for the cameras and projectors they manufactured. I had helped Bell &amp;
                    Howell build a large lens plant before I went in the war through a contract I
                    obtained from the U.S.' Defense Plant Corporation, to build a large factory in
                    Lincolnwood, Illinois, just outside Chicago. Bell &amp; Howell then moved their
                    headquarters from Chicago to Lincolnwood, Illinois. We had to import, before the
                    war, lenses from Germany and Japan. They were cut off with the outbreak of war.
                    So, after this war, we became a big manufacturer of lenses for the U.S., Canada,
                    Mexico, Europe, and other countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the time you went to see J. Arthur Rank, did you also
                        look aGermany and France, too?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>PERCY: Oh, yes. On those trips, I would go over to Germany to see whether we
                    couldn't open up a branch there and in France. I urged them to trade together.
                    When I was in Bell &amp; Howell and later in the U.S. Senate, I worked with
                    European countries to develop trade with us and each other. We kept talking
                    about the fact that Europe had been a source for centuries of battling and
                    fighting. Yet here we have America, with minimal guarded borders between the
                    U.S., Canada, and Mexico. They're our biggest trading partners. We have infinite
                    friendship. I told them that they must start to trade together. We encouraged
                    some of the early trade between former enemies France and Germany. I was
                    thrilled when in 1999, France and Germany became each other's biggest single
                    partners in trade. After a century of conflict and fighting, you can't imagine a
                    war between Germany and France now.</p>
                <p>Q: As you were working on this, how did you see Germany? The Olympus and other
                    cameras? Were you trying to develop ties with those factories, the ones that
                    moved over to the West?</p>
                <p>PERCY: We had no compelling reason to work with German manufacturing companies.
                    We did manufacture ourselves, and then we sold, from England to Germany. But
                    after a while, costs got very high. Labor unions were tough and seemed to be
                    having very great difficulty. And that's when I decided to go over to Japan.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>I did go over to Japan and subsequently made many trips there. We built a factory
                    there. I talked one of our top production men, George Stryker and his wife, into
                    moving over to Japan so that he could be the head of our Japanese company. Also,
                    I established relationships with Japan's government right away. As soon as I
                    came back from World War II and was put in charge of the international work for
                    Bell &amp; Howell, we received a letter in 1946 from Yoshio Osawa, who pre-war
                    had been the exclusive agent for Bell &amp; Howell Company equipment. He had
                    been the exclusive Japanese agent for distributing Bell &amp; Howell equipment
                    before the war but was obviously cut off after Pearl Harbor in 1941. He said in
                    his letter: “Now I'm bankrupt. I haven't any money to buy Bell &amp; Howell
                    equipment, but what I would like to do, when you appoint a new agent to
                    distribute your cameras and projectors in Japan, as I did before, I would like
                    to work as a consultant to them.” I wrote back and said, “I'm sorry Yoshio, you
                    cannot be a consultant to any new agent of Bell &amp; Howell. Here's why: We
                    were required by law to seize all the deposits you had made with us, that is all
                    the money you had deposited with us to buy equipment before the war. We seized
                    approximately $100,000, as you will remember. We took the money and invested it
                    in U.S. war bonds. Now it has become $125,000, we will give this amount of
                    credit to your account. You can start to buy immediately. We want you to be our
                    agent once again.” But I told him also that a modest part of this money should
                    be used to enable his son, Zenro, to go to Princeton University (where Yoshio
                    had graduated years ago). But also Zenro could be an apprentice at Bell &amp;
                    Howell each summer and learn the business and I could provide summer lodging for
                    him. And all this happily came about. Therefore they became our agent, and they
                    were so overwhelmed. I went over later for his company's anniversary party.
                    While he told that story after the banquet dinner, to the crowd that was there,
                    he started to cry, but then told about how grateful he was that we forgot the
                    animosity, and he was able to start again in his business with his son Zenro
                    someday to succeed him. He became our distributor and did extremely well in
                    Japan. Later, when I flew over again to establish a factory in Japan, we formed
                    a new company. The law in Japan at that time was that no outside company could
                    own more than 49 percent of a Japanese company. We formed a company with Bell
                    and Howell owning 49 percent but providing 100 percent of the financing with
                    just a verbal understanding that whenever the law permitted us to go higher, we
                    would hold a majority and then control the company. But we guaranteed Osawa he
                    would always have a minority interest in it. Several years later, the law was
                    changed in Japan. What we did then was take 90 percent of the company and left
                    10 percent to be owned by Osawa. But we by then manufactured many products there
                    that provided more worldwide distribution for us because their costs were very
                    low at the time compared to ours.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was when? When did you set up this production line
                        iJapan?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: It would have been early in my presidency. That would be ithe early
                    1950s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very early on. As far as installations went.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>PERCY: Yes. But I'd established relationships with Japan righafter the war in
                    1946 when they became our distributors once again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find Bell &amp; Howell when you came back? Was
                        it changed place?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: I was away three years. Of course when I came back it was somewhat
                    different. But we now had to convert from war production products back into
                    essentially motion picture equipment. But then I started the process of
                    diversifying the company and getting into other product lines. We got into
                    microfilm, and acquired other companies.</p>
                <p>Q: I was wondering, with movie equipment. I can see it as a rival - television. I
                    mean, were you watching television, as you did this, as a growth industry?</p>
                <p>PERCY: We never really looked upon television as competitors, even as
                    substitutes. I began investment in television broadcasting for Bell &amp;
                    Howell. We began the whole philosophy of news programs that would be related to
                    things that were extremely important to the world, knowledge of which would be
                    for the good of the country. That eventually led to my involvement with public
                    broadcasting.</p>
                <p>Q: During these early years, I think around '48, '49, did you find yourself tied
                    at all into the Marshall Plan? European reconstruction at least? Were you
                    talking to people in Washington about putting more investment into more
                    countries?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Oh, yes. I worked very closely, especially with President Dwight
                    Eisenhower. His brother, Milton, who was president of Johns Hopkins University,
                    was a treasured friend also and I worked very, very closely with him. That would
                    lead me into the whole process of my starting work with the Republican Party.
                    Early in his Presidency, I convinced President Eisenhower to create a Committee
                    on Program and Progress. It would be a committee established in 1959, and would
                    show where the United States ought to be 25 years from then and how to aim
                    towards getting us there. He agreed and appointed me chairman of the committee.
                    We issued a report and I'd like to add extracts from the report that we made to
                    President Eisenhower. That committee report led to my being asked to be chairman
                    of the Platform Committee for the Republican Party Convention in 1960.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's move back a bit. You were saying, after the war,
                        sort of on the personal side, your son Roger was born shortly after the war
                        in 1946. Your wife became ill?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>PERCY: Well, as I have said, she told me that she had ulcerative colitis. Now,
                    when she came back to Illinois, the doctor said to me, “We have an operation we
                    could perform on her that would completely cure her of that. As it is she is
                    much better now than she was before your marriage.” They said, “We know you're a
                    Christian Scientist, but we can just assure you that this is an operation that
                    she wants.” He had talked to her. I said, “Are you sure it's safe? Is there any
                    risk involved?” They said no. I said, “If you say there's no risk, and that she
                    wants it, then I guess you will go ahead.” They did it and it worked out fine. A
                    few months later, they said, “There's just one more operation we have to do and
                    she'll be completely healed of it.” “Any risk?” I asked. “No risk whatsoever,”
                    they said. But she was allergic to penicillin and died a week later in the
                    hospital at the age of 27. The pastors and doctors at the hospital were very
                    humiliated. They couldn't apologize enough.</p>
                <p>It just struck all of us in the family so hard. We decided we would have to find
                    a way to keep on going. I decided I would just raise the children with the help
                    of a housekeeper that worked for me and lived in my Wilmette house. Every trip I
                    took, if there was a possibility of taking the children with me, I took them
                    with me. After many months, my friends were anxious that I find someone else to
                    marry and help raise my three children. Art Nielson, one of my dearest friends
                    from high school on and still is, had a sister-in-law who was not married. And
                    he told me he'd like to have his sister-in-law date me. So I took her out. She
                    went with me on a sailboat that I had. When I was racing in Lake Michigan on my
                    sailboat, kept in the Wilmette harbor, if a boat was trying to cut in on me, I'd
                    generally yield to them. When she sailed with me one time, she would just call
                    out to them. I've forgotten what words she used, but the essence was, “Get out
                    of our way!” So we just kept going and we won the race, the first time that I
                    ever did. She was a very wonderful young woman, but I just wasn't interested in
                    getting remarried. So for several years, I just raised the children myself. But
                    I needed an excuse not to date so I went to night law school at Chicago Kent
                    College of Law. But after January, 1949, when Joe McNabb died (McNabb was
                    president and CEO of Bell &amp; Howell Co.), he had left a sealed statement in
                    the company safe. He had told the lawyers - one of whom, Ed McDermott, head of
                    McDermott, Will &amp; Emory Law Firm, had been on the Bell &amp; Howell Board of
                    Directors for years and he was the director that proposed that I be on the board
                    originally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying that when McNabb died, he'd left a
                        statement ithe company safe?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>PERCY: Yes. In which he'd indicated that as the largest stockholder, he felt it
                    would be desirable to have me elected CEO, and the board knew me because I'd
                    been a board member since I came back from the war. They had read my memorandums
                    to Joseph McNabb on what we should do after the war - Harold Geneen, who was
                    vice president and comptroller and was a member of the board, knew me very well,
                    seconded the motion made by Ed McDermott and on January 4, 1949 I was elected
                    president and CEO. Albert Howell, co-founder of Bell &amp; Howell Company and
                    chief engineer, was elected chairman on my nomination, but always asked me to
                    conduct the board meetings. The public interest was pretty high at this point.
                    It was described in a book published in 1982, long after I had left the company,
                    called “Bell &amp; Howell Company - a 75 Year History” by Jack F. Robinson, pp.
                    78-89.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I recall that. I recall it was quite well known.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: It was very high. In fact, I won a national award at age 29 for being the
                    youngest president of a major American business company, without a relative that
                    was head of it before me. There was a tremendous amount of interest in it. I had
                    enrolled at a Chicago night law school because I loved the creation and
                    enforcement of laws, but also to have a good reason to not have to date anyone
                    at night. I'd finished two years of law school. Ed McDermott discovered that I
                    was still going to night law school months after I had been elected president
                    and CEO and he said at a board meeting: “Here he is becoming the new CEO at Bell
                    &amp; Howell Company and now still going to night law school! How unbecoming!”
                    So I dropped out. I'm a law school drop-out! But I maintain that I'm the only
                    law school drop-out I know of that now has 22 sitting federal judges, that I
                    named, sent to the president and confirmed by the U.S. Senate; including John
                    Paul Stevens, who is now the Senior Justice on the Supreme Court. He was one of
                    my earlier recommendations. He was a fellow member of my class at the University
                    of Chicago, Class of 1941. I was head of the Inter-Fraternity Council and he was
                    head of the Senior Men's Honorary Society because he was smarter than I was.
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>I, about that time, had been asked to join the Board of Directors of the Chase
                    Manhattan Bank, by its chairman, David Rockefeller. After one of the Chase
                    Board's meetings in New York, I told him that I wanted to diversify Bell &amp;
                    Howell and asked if he knew of an outstanding investment banker I could approach
                    to help me in making acquisitions and mergers.</p>
                <p>Incidentally, now let me tell you, I first met David Rockefeller, as I mentioned
                    earlier, at the University of Chicago in the late 1930s. He was getting his
                    doctorate degree there and I was getting my bachelor. We became friends there
                    and that's when he introduced me to a great many of the students at the
                    University of Chicago from foreign countries. I loved going over and having
                    dinner or lunch with him at International House, built by the Rockefellers, with
                    foreign students from around the world. That's what first caused me to become
                    interested in foreign countries' affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you move to your second wife, then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Two months after I was elected head of Bell &amp; Howell, there was so
                    much to do about it on radio, TV, and press conferences. I was asked to be on
                    radio and TV programs. I said to Harold Geneen, our comptroller: “Why don't we
                    get out of here for a bit; get up in the mountains, ski, and let's just plan the
                    next five years for our company. Just sit down, think about the future for Bell
                    &amp; Howell, and quietly talk and not have all the pressures?”</p>
                <p>He agreed and we flew out to Sun Valley, Idaho. One morning, I was on the ski
                    lift, going up, about 9:00 a.m., on Dollar Mountain at Sun Valley, and while on
                    the lift, I saw this young woman skiing down the mountain, and just as she got
                    underneath my elevated chair as I was approaching her, she fell and hit her face
                    in a snow bank. I hollered down, “Are you all right? Are you hurt?” She pulled
                    her head up, smiled and quickly wiped the snow off her face and called up, “No,
                    I'm fine.” I noticed the clothing she had on.</p>
                <p>I didn't see her on the mountain again that day. The next morning, however, I got
                    on the bus to go over to Dollar Mountain, and there she was in the same clothes
                    sitting in a seat with an empty seat next to her. I said, “Aren't you the young
                    lady who fell yesterday?” She said, “Oh, are you the man who was up on the ski
                    lift?” I sat down with her and that began our friendship. We skied together
                    quite a bit with Harold Geneen. Then she had to leave. She was there after her
                    father had recently died. She lived in Altadena, California, just outside
                    Pasadena and Los Angeles. So she was invited to come up with a friend's family
                    skiing. They invited her to get her away from the sorrow of her father's death,
                    the funeral, and the sadness of it. She could celebrate there the joy of their
                    family life together. When I invited her to come to dinner with Hal Geneen and
                    myself, she said, “No,” but then invited me to have dinner with her friend's
                    family that night. I sat next to her. She had a boyfriend there, too, but I said
                    to him, “You take the place of honor down there next to our hostess.” So I sat
                    next to Loraine and we had a friendly conversation.</p>
                <p>But soon she and her family friends went back to Altadena. I said to Harold
                    Geneen, “On our way back, instead of going right to Chicago, let's fly down to
                    Los Angeles and visit our Hollywood office. I haven't been in the office and our
                    Hollywood factory since becoming president. Why don't we both see that?” Harold
                    said, “And see Loraine, too?” [Laughter] “Well,” I said, “That would be
                    nice.”</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>So we went to Los Angeles. I went over to her house in Altadena, met her fine
                    mother, who was a Christian Scientist, and her two great brothers, David and
                    John Guyer, all of whom were very cordial. It was the first time I'd ever seen a
                    city home where they had orange trees in the front yard, where they picked fresh
                    oranges for their breakfasts. They had a lovely swimming pool there also. I said
                    to Loraine, “Harold Geneen and I are going to the MGM movie studio this
                    afternoon. I suppose having lived near Hollywood all your life, you're tired of
                    seeing studios, but if you'd like to come, you can certainly come with us.” She
                    said, “I've lived here all my life but I've never been to a film studio. I'd
                    love to come.” So we went and Les Peterson took us around as public relations
                    vice president of MGM, and in one section a new movie was being shot. He said,
                    “You want to see this? There's a new unknown leading young lady who's only 17
                    years old. She's playing the female lead. And Van Johnson is the male lead. I
                    said, “What's her name?” Les said: “Elizabeth Taylor.”</p>
                <p>So we watched the picture being produced for an hour or so and afterwards Les
                    Peterson had a picture taken of us with Elizabeth Taylor, Van Johnson, Loraine,
                    and myself. That's the first picture we had taken together. It was in 1949. The
                    next picture I had with Elizabeth Taylor was after I was married to Loraine in
                    1950 and I went into the Senate, which was in 1967. John Warner, to whom she was
                    then married, was thinking about running for the Senate and she came to see me
                    to ask some questions.</p>
                <p>I will tell you this much. She came down the hall to my office, with 15
                    photographers following her. It was unbelievable. She walked into my office
                    reception room, and there was the picture of her with Loraine, Van Johnson, and
                    myself on the wall. She shrieked, “Oh, I was never that young!” Then we went
                    into my office and I now have a picture of us in my office holding that original
                    picture.She said, “You're the only U.S. senator I know. My husband, John Warner,
                    wants to run for the Senate. Should he run? Would he like it? Do you think he
                    would win?” I said, “Well, I can tell you this. He can win, if you travel with
                    him when he's campaigning, and stay with him just like Loraine stayed with me
                    when I ran for office, as did my family. You will help attract a crowd wherever
                    he speaks. And I do think he would win because he's a good man. Second, would he
                    like it? I think he'd love it. Will you like it? I'm not so sure. I'm not so
                    sure my wife likes the Senate from the standpoint of family life. You have no
                    control over your time. You can't even get home for dinner many nights. You
                    leave early in the morning, you get home late at night many times. You spend all
                    the time you can in your home state traveling around. I don't know whether
                    you'll like it or not.” But anyway, that's the way it worked out. She did
                    campaign for him, and he did win and has been a treasured friend and colleague
                    of mine ever since.</p>
                <p>Q: Anyway, you established Bell &amp; Howell as an international corporation that
                    you're dealing with. How did you find the market? Was it a growing market?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Yes, it was, but David Rockefeller had a great influence on my ability to
                    expand Bell &amp; Howell's business abroad. Much about that later.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you been at all political during this post-war period?
                        Hayou kept up with the Party or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Following the war, I became more politically-minded because federal
                    government policy involves such vital decisions as to whether you get into war
                    or not, whether we win or lose, the state of the economy, rate of inflation,
                    unemployment, relations with other countries, and in general the well-being of
                    the American people. I was really captivated always by the thought that
                    political friendships through the centuries have tended to follow trade lanes
                    and exports and trade between countries is terribly important. Even though we
                    did have a lot of foreign competition, I still thought that free trade would
                    keep tariffs down and open markets so that they could import and compete with
                    us, providing us with the added incentives to become more efficient. I've always
                    been a free trade advocate.</p>
                <p>Q: I would have thought that being so internationalist coming out of Chicago is
                    difficult. I mean, you had Senator Taft - I think of some of the powerhouses
                    that were politically active at the time and particularly in the Republican
                    Party. I mean isolationists weren't dead. They were dormant during the war and
                    then started to creep up again. Did you find yourself, I mean was this making
                    you, I'm talking before you officially entered the list. How'd you find yourself
                    looking at...</p>
                <p>PERCY: I was known as a progressive, moderate Republican but also as a
                    financially conservative person. That made some enemies on the strictly
                    conservative side with the Republican Party. Sometimes they even voted against
                    me or pushed me into a primary election. Sometimes they felt strongly about it
                    in general elections. But also I was known for the free trade position. They
                    also knew that I was very open on the integration of Blacks, now more regularly
                    called African-Americans. When I became president of Bell &amp; Howell, I had a
                    meeting with my foreman, and I said, “We have not a single black employee. I
                    served in the war with Blacks to defend our country. We must integrate our
                    company.” I did recall that during my earlier years at Bell &amp; Howell, the
                    relatively few Negroes we had at one point were laid off after there was a night
                    shift fight between the Whites and the Blacks. It was a very bad situation. It
                    was said that the Blacks were in error and were not hired thereafter. I said, in
                    1949, “We're going to begin the policy of hiring Blacks on an equal basis, based
                    on ability and past records. (We didn't call it “affirmative action” in those
                    days.) We're going to lean now toward trying to find jobs for these people and
                    adding more women executives.”</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>My mother had a great influence on my life. I had been raised by a mother who was
                    a dynamo, a great violinist, an earner, the leader of our family, really. We
                    didn't have enough women executives in our country in the early 1950s. This was
                    a policy I talked to our board about. They agreed on it. “We're going to
                    diversify our company and board even more. I need experts in various fields. I'm
                    going to try to get high tech CEOs of great companies with backgrounds in
                    engineering, marketing, manufacturing, legal, and accounting.” Sears Roebuck for
                    instance - the chairman of the board of Sears Roebuck &amp; Company became a
                    director of our company.</p>
                <p>I said at a meeting of all of our department heads, “Any of you who don't agree
                    with this policy of adding Blacks to our work force and upgrading women to
                    executive positions, based on ability, and will not adhere to that policy in
                    your department, your resignation from the company will be accepted.” They all
                    agreed. Not a single one left. We began to hire African-Americans. We were way
                    ahead of any legislation on it. We started to hire more women for important
                    positions. Several years later, I did get an award from the Women's Business and
                    Professional Association of America for having more women executives at Bell
                    &amp; Howell than any other company our size in America.</p>
                <p>Also, I belonged to the Chicago Club. At a meeting I said, “You know, there's one
                    thing wrong with this club. Only on rare occasions can women, or wives even,
                    come in. It's an all males club. We don't have a single woman member. I just
                    think that's wrong. I would like to nominate a woman.” They said, “Well, who
                    would it be?” I said, “Her name is Hannah Gray. She's now at the University of
                    Chicago (and later became president). She's intelligent, thoughtful, a great
                    conversationalist, she's terrific.” They interviewed her and subsequently voted
                    for her to become a member, which she accepted. Other women followed, joining
                    the club as members.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good. Tell me, how did you start putting your toe in
                        thpolitical waters?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>PERCY: I think in the late 1940s. When I came back from the war, I founded an
                    organization we called “North Shore Veterans for the Republican Party.” I later
                    became a GOP precinct captain in Wilmette, Illinois. One winter night a young
                    man came to my home, after we had moved to Kenilworth, Illinois, knocked on the
                    door, and said, “You're interested in the Republican Party and you've done some
                    fundraising for them and been a Republican precinct captain. I want to run for
                    Congress in this District. The incumbent has retired. I think my philosophy is
                    close to yours.” I said, “Don't stand in the doorway. Why don't you come in and
                    let's talk about it? What's your name?” “Don Rumsfeld.” So I talked to him for
                    about an hour or more, and as he left I said, “Don, you've got my support. I'll
                    campaign for you. I'll make a contribution to your campaign,” and I did. That
                    got me started with a man who served as congressman from my district from 1963
                    to 1969 and subsequently Secretary of Defense and Chief of White House Staff for
                    President Ford and then as ambassador to NATO in 1973 and in 1983-84 as Special
                    Negotiator for the Middle East problems for President Reagan. [In 2001, he
                    became Secretary of Defense for President George W. Bush.] He has always been a
                    treasured friend also. I just kept on going with ideas for the Party including
                    fund-raising. I was chairman of a Committee which developed a new policy for the
                    Party in Illinois - a more progressive program. Then I was selected to be
                    finance chairman for the Republican Party in Illinois. I then became vice
                    chairman of the National Republican Finance Committee. Through fund-raising, you
                    make a widespread field of acquaintances, supporters, because if you ask people
                    for money for the Republican Party they give you a reason many times why they're
                    not going to give the Party money. That gave me the chance to learn what could
                    be done to overcome objections. So gradually I did more and more in politics as
                    time permitted. And then I finally decided in 1963, to run for Governor in 1964.
                    Before I did that, I had a meeting in my home in Kenilworth in the living room
                    with every family member including my wife, Loraine, my brother, Howard, and
                    sister, Doris, our children, my mother, who was only age 78 then. The only
                    non-family member who was there was Bob Galvin, the CEO of Motorola, and a
                    treasured friend. He also later became my campaign fund-raising chairman.</p>
                <p>I proposed that we have a vote as to whether or not I should take a leave from my
                    position as president of Bell &amp; Howell and run for public office. “I would
                    like to, but I do not want to unless it would have your wholehearted support. I
                    say that because it would change your lives, it would affect your lives, if I do
                    something like this. It's one thing to work as a volunteer in all of these
                    political activities, but it's another thing to actually run for office because
                    that does involve the family and I'd love you all to participate and be part of
                    the effort. For instance, Mother could be chair or head of the Senior Citizens
                    for Chuck Percy Committee.”</p>
                <p>They all voted. It was unanimous that I should run for office in 1964. I ran for
                    Governor of Illinois and had a fine campaign, but lost. And Barry Goldwater
                    himself, at the next meeting of the Republican National Committee, stood up,
                    giving his speech after his disastrous defeat. He pointed down at me and said,
                    “There's Chuck Percy. I feel so badly about his loss. If I hadn't lost the
                    Presidency in the same election by over 700,000 votes alone in Illinois, his
                    state, he would have won, because he lost by only a fairly small margin.”</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>After I lost the election, I formed a committee again to see if I couldn't carry
                    out the pledges I had made as to what I would have done if I were elected
                    governor. We called it the “New Illinois Committee.” I began with volunteers in
                    poverty sections of Chicago, having volunteer tutors train children, black
                    children essentially, in a private volunteer program. It included immigrant
                    children that came in from Mexico or other foreign countries, who couldn't speak
                    English at all or very well. We taught them English. We tried to help with
                    housing for needy families so that we could help them. So the New Illinois
                    Committee began quite a program which I greatly enjoyed working at, with the
                    help of family members, friends, and other skilled volunteers, some of whom had
                    helped in our governor's election campaign. Then one day Senator Everett Dirksen
                    called and wanted to see me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was a senator from Illinois.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: The senior senator from Illinois. And he wanted to see me at my Bell &amp;
                    Howell Company office. He said, “I want to bring with me some friends.” He
                    brought about 10 CEOs of companies, all of whom had helped Dirksen in his
                    political life. He said to me, “I brought them along with me to hear the
                    proposal I'm making to you and to hear the pledge that I'll also make to you.
                    You lost the governorship because of Barry Goldwater - but also before that you
                    had a primary within the Republican Party which you won overwhelmingly. It was a
                    new conservative Republican who ran against you. And he spoke against you.” Then
                    Senator Dirksen said, “I think a lot of the conservatives in the Republican
                    Party didn't work or vote for you in the Governor's race. You supported Governor
                    Nelson Rockefeller to run for president originally, even though you did actively
                    support Goldwater when he ran with you in 1964, even though some Republican
                    candidates for governor in other states did not want to be with Goldwater when
                    he came into their states. When Bob Taft was running in Ohio and Goldwater came
                    in, he would go to the other end of the state. He wouldn't be available. When
                    Goldwater came in, you met him at the airport or the train, and took him with
                    you. You pledged to support whoever was nominated, even though you had backed
                    Nelson Rockefeller against him at the convention. You said, “I will support the
                    candidate who is the choice of the Republican national convention.”</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>Senator Everett Dirksen then said, “Now, I know you want to run for governor
                    again in four years, but Paul Douglas is now the other Illinois senator, and
                    he's running for reelection in '66. We want you to run against him, because
                    you've got the best state-wide organization, but we know you'll never win, as he
                    is unbeatable. I said then, “He was my professor in economics at the University
                    of Chicago. I liked him immensely.” Dirksen said, “He'll understand. But if you
                    run against him, we'll get back some of the seats in the House of
                    Representatives that we lost. We'll get back the Illinois State Legislature
                    seats that we lost. We had a disaster with Barry Goldwater on the ticket. You'll
                    do better against Paul Douglas than anyone else and it will help every other
                    candidate that runs. Then, I will guarantee you, and these men deep in finance
                    here and in the party will guarantee you, too, they will try to prevent any
                    primary against you. So when you run for Governor again in 1968, you won't have
                    a primary election, you won't have Goldwater on the ticket, you'll be able to
                    win. All I'm asking you to do is do the best you can to get as good a vote
                    margin as you can, but you won't be able to win.”</p>
                <p>So I agreed I would, and I called Paul Douglas's office in Washington, DC. It
                    turned out he was in Mexico at the time. I finally reached him by phone there
                    and I explained the situation. He said, “Well Chuck, I was afraid you might find
                    yourself in this position. I understand.” I said to him, “I pledge to you,
                    professor and senator, that we will have a fair campaign. There will not be
                    personal charges. It will just be on issues. I do honestly differ with you on
                    some issues, but we'll have a clean campaign.” He said, “We'll have a clean
                    campaign, but I understand why you must run against me.” So I ran against him,
                    but actually won!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is 1966.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Yes, 1966. What I did say about him is that “He is a fine person, but (I
                    didn't say he was old.) a man of old-fashioned ideas.” For instance, he formed
                    an organization called “A Million Americans to Keep Red China Out of the United
                    Nations.” Keep China out of the UN? And I would then simply say during the
                    campaign: How can you have a United Nations when you would want to keep out of
                    it the largest nation on earth? I was in on the founding of the UN and it would
                    be wrong to keep China out.</p>
                <p>The other major thing I differed with him on was the Vietnam War. He was all for
                    the Vietnam War. I was very much against it. I kept saying it was the wrong war,
                    the wrong place, the wrong time. It was not in our national security interest.
                    We will never put enough into it, like we did World War II, to win it! And it's
                    too far away! It's going to divide our country. That's what happened. It really
                    divided the USA badly. And that became quite apparent to everyone. So I was
                    elected to the U.S. Senate in November 1966 and sworn in as a member to
                    represent Illinois in January 1967 and served for 18 years.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>Q: I would have thought that the Republican Party, particularly conservatives,
                    and certainly Senator Everett Dirksen ranked as a conservative, would have found
                    that this idea of doing anything with China would be abhorrent because if there
                    was anything that marked out the conservative Republican - it still does today -
                    is somehow you don't deal with Red China. I mean, it's sort of an article of
                    faith almost.</p>
                <p>PERCY: I know. But I seemed to attract the attention of the young people
                    particularly, and I was able to tell the story about how I'd seen the United
                    Nations put together at the Cow Palace in San Francisco when I was in the Navy
                    Air Corps, during World War II. That made a deep impression on me as to what it
                    could accomplish and do in the world to help bring peace to the world. Because,
                    after all, we had two world wars. Are we going to have a third? A fourth? But
                    now we've got nuclear weapons, as have other nations. What is it going to lead
                    to but disaster? We've got to find a basis for peace, and the United Nations can
                    be the foundation on which we can work, but you've got to have the countries in
                    there that will be the ones that will affect the world. The former communist
                    countries, Soviet Union, China, and others, should be members of the United
                    Nations as well as the World Trade Organization and others.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you find, I would have thought you would have found the same reluctance -
                    even more - on the part of the conservatives in Illinois, Republican
                    conservatives, by taking this stand.</p>
                <p>PERCY: Well, I did have, but on the other hand, Paul Douglas was very vulnerable
                    from several standpoints. As I say, the Vietnam War I think was a very, very big
                    issue. And it divided the country, as you know. It was terrible. That was why
                    the young people, particularly, could cheer me. They didn't want to go to
                    Vietnam, whereas my experience with World War II was that virtually everyone
                    wanted to go! In fact, I was draft exempt because Bell &amp; Howell established
                    a Defense Department that I headed. But I just couldn't let my friends go to war
                    and leave me sitting back there at Bell &amp; Howell Company making a big
                    salary. So I did volunteer and joined the Navy Air Corps and became a gunnery
                    officer.</p>
                <p>Q: With this election, how did it hit the Republican Party when you arrived at
                    the Senate because you were supposed to be a sacrificial lamb and all of a
                    sudden here you are?</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>PERCY: Well, I was treated very, very nicely. After all, Everett Dirksen was the
                    Republican leader in the U.S. Senate there. He embraced me. Things began to
                    happen right away that they began to really work with me on. I began working on
                    issues that I had worked on running for the Senate and running for the
                    Governorship. Home ownership for low income people became an early piece of
                    legislation that I proposed and worked with my staff to enact into a new law. I
                    just told the story to the Senate of the observations that I had made in my
                    lifetime as to the difference it made to us when we were able to finally buy a
                    house after renting apartments and one small house all our lives. The difference
                    was even more apparent to me as I visited families in government-owned public
                    housing which they provided to low income people. They had no ownership in it
                    whatsoever. They'd throw the garbage down the stairs; windows were frequently
                    broken; and the apartments weren't taken care of. When I went into homes that
                    were modest homes, but owned by people, maybe families had just struggled to buy
                    a house, they were usually very well kept. Even those in public housing, if they
                    had an old, broken-down car that they were able to buy cheap, and had that car,
                    they shined it, kept it clean, and so forth because it was theirs. That was the
                    difference between a dwelling that wasn't theirs and one that was. We made it
                    possible, through this legislation, for people to pay as little as one percent
                    interest, and to not have to pay the loan back until they had earned enough
                    money to make payments, but actually owning a home gave them much more incentive
                    to increase their earnings. Home ownership for low income people became the law
                    of the land. Within a matter of a few years, we had 500,000 people and families
                    who took advantage of the legislation. And it became a piece of legislation that
                    was looked on by my colleagues and Illinois and the country with great
                    favor.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>I was also part of the initial conceptualization of a national public
                    broadcasting system. I had been asked by Robert Maynard Hutchins, when he left
                    as president of the University of Chicago and became president of the Ford
                    Foundation, to come to New York City and have a meeting with him to see if I
                    could do something in adult education to continue education for adults. Would I
                    be the founding volunteer chairman of a fund to encourage such an activity? I
                    accepted. We decided to call it the Fund for Adult Education of the Ford
                    Foundation. He said, “Who would you suggest to be on it?” And I said, “Well,
                    I've gotten to know Milton Eisenhower, the President's brother.” He was an
                    educator then, but became president of John Hopkins University later, and was a
                    wonderful man and treasured friend, and I asked him to be vice chairman and a
                    director of it. The two of us worked together with the board we selected to look
                    for a big idea, just like the Carnegie Foundation did, to start so many public
                    libraries throughout the USA and the world. And so I asked our board to vote on
                    this program to establish public broadcasting television and radio stations
                    throughout the country. We provided money from the Ford Foundation source, to
                    start a couple of local stations such as WTTW in Chicago. When I got to the
                    Senate in January 1967, very early on, I said, “This is something that ought to
                    be done - to set aside a national network now for public broadcasting.” We
                    didn't want to have just a couple of stations; we could have a whole network of
                    stations across the country. And one vacant TV national channel was left. ABC,
                    NBC, and CBS supported our concept, either because they thought it was a
                    basically sound idea, or could it have been that they didn't want another
                    network that also advertized products and services! Our Board knew that there
                    was another channel that could be set aside for public broadcasting and be
                    called PBS. We decided to draft legislation that would set that aside. I
                    remember Senator Margaret Chase Smith on the floor of the Senate objected to it.
                    “What business do we have spending money for public broadcasting?” I said
                    something like, “Well, to have TV and radio stations that emphasize education,
                    that emphasizes the quality of the programs they're doing, would be very much in
                    the national interest.” So we won the fights and passed legislation that
                    designated a network for education on public broadcasting. PBS was set up. I
                    never dreamed my daughter, Sharon Percy Rockefeller, would become a leading
                    director of National Public Broadcasting. Now she continues to be a director of
                    it, and for years has been CEO and president of one of the most important
                    stations, WETA in Washington, DC! And she has devoted more than a quarter of a
                    century of her life to public broadcasting - when it originated programs such as
                    “The McNeil/Lehrer News Hour,” now “The News Hour with Jim Lehrer.” Among the
                    cornerstones of WETA's current productions are such traditional favorites as the
                    “National Memorial Day Concert,” which ran again on May 28, 2000, and “A Capitol
                    Fourth,” two stellar holiday events broadcast from the lawn of the U.S.
                    Capitol.</p>
                <p>“Washington Week in Review” has been a trusted source of news and analysis for
                    more than 33 years, and “The Kennedy Center Presents” has been a gala salute to
                    the icons of music, dance, and drama. Other great programs with large numbers of
                    steady viewers would include “All Things Considered,” “Morning Edition,” “Wall
                    Street Week,” “NOVA,” “The American Experience,” and many other truly great
                    programs.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>“Imagination, Discovery, Laughter, Learning, Understanding” is what WETA's
                    extensive children's programming is all about. “Sesame Street” and “Barney and
                    Friends” to “Wishbone” and “Reading Rainbow” offer young viewers the kind of
                    innovative, quality programs that teach as they entertain, “all made possible by
                    members like you.” [Sharon Percy Rockefeller, President and CEO of WETA, added
                    this insertion in the February 2001 issue of WETA Magazine:</p>
                <p>“One of the most important aspects of WETA as a public broadcaster is the
                    station's relationship with the community we serve. Founded almost 40 years ago,
                    WETA remains committed to creating and broadcasting educational and entertaining
                    programs accessible to all. A particular strength of WETA's television and radio
                    programming is our diverse slate of cultural offerings that bring the arts from
                    our community - at the center of the national stage - into your living room.</p>
                <p>Each month WETA creates and airs captivating local performance and arts programs,
                    from the Dumbarton Concerts series on 90.9 FM to TV 26's ongoing concert series
                    In Performance at the White House and The Kennedy Center Presents and Washington
                    Opera productions such as La Rondine. In the nonperformance arts genre, WETA's
                    offerings are also plentiful. The weekly program Around Town offers unique and
                    valuable insights on arts tours of major local art exhibitions in programs such
                    as John Singer Sargent: Outside the Frame and Van Gogh's Van Goghs. More such
                    cultural shows are always in the works - presently in production are a program
                    on the art of painter Mary Cassatt and a Kennedy Center Irish gala.”]</p>
                <p>My expectations expressed to the Senate for public radio and television
                    programming have been far exceeded by everything being done by public
                    broadcasting's achievements today.</p>
                <p>Q: How did you find the Senate when you first arrived as far as ability to work
                    within it? Was it a contentious place when Johnson was President? Who was the
                    Senate Leader at that time?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Senator Mike Mansfield (Democrat) was Majority Leader from 1961-1977.
                    Everett Dirksen (Republican) was the Minority Leader of the Senate from
                    1959-1969. The Senate was not nearly as contentious then as it is now and not
                    nearly as partisan. I treasured many, many Republican friends, but also had dear
                    friends on the Democratic side. Senators Ted Kennedy and Bob Kennedy were very
                    good friends. Ted and I were fellow directors for 18 years of the Kennedy
                    Center. Senator Mike Mansfield was also a dear and treasured friend as well, as
                    were many others.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>When the idea for the Kennedy Center initially came up, even just as an idea, the
                    suggestion was made by the White House that the Senate have two representatives,
                    a Democrat and a Republican on the Board. And Everett Dirksen said to me, “Why
                    don't you represent the Republicans on the Board of Directors? Your mother was a
                    violinist in orchestras and you've been raised in music and support it. You
                    helped bring the Lyric opera to Chicago.” So I joined the Board of what we were
                    to call the Kennedy Center and I was then elected the founding vice chairman.
                    The founding chairman, Roger Stevens, a long time Broadway play producer, lived
                    right across the street from us on 34th Street (Georgetown area of Washington,
                    DC). So we worked together constantly. I had a hearing problem from World War II
                    as a naval aviation gunnery officer. I'd have breakfast at our home with him
                    every morning we had a board meeting so I'd understand fully what he wanted to
                    bring up. I told him the issues that I thought we ought to work on because I was
                    getting the money from Congress for the Kennedy Center then, so he and I worked
                    closely together for years. He and his wife, Christina, were treasured friends
                    of Loraine and myself. The biblical admonition to “love thy neighbors” was
                    certainly implemented by the four of us and still is with widower Christine
                    Stevens.</p>
                <p>That was one of our greatest accomplishments in DC. I'd worked so hard in
                    Chicago, for the Lyric Opera Company to bring opera to Chicago and make it a
                    greater city. To be able to do that with the Kennedy Center for the Performing
                    Arts was one of my greatest challenges in DC. The Kennedy Center, with
                    headquarters for many of the performing arts, would enrich life there and make
                    Washington, DC a truly greater city.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Performing Arts.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: I think helping to build that was so wonderful, and now I'm working on the
                    Georgetown Waterfront Park Commission. I'm now the founding chairman of that
                    organization, working with the city officials and leaders and the National Parks
                    Service and many wonderful volunteers. We want to beautify the city with a great
                    park right on the Potomac riverfront. Here is what former General Colin Powell,
                    chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, had to say to me in a letter dated August
                    11, 1997:</p>
                <p>“Dear Chuck,</p>
                <p>Congratulations to you for accepting the chairmanship othe Georgetown Waterfront
                    Park Commission.</p>
                <p>I am confident that under your leadership and with the dedicated help of your
                    colleagues and partners, you will bring about a restoration of the Georgetown
                    waterfront that removes an eyesore and adds a place of beauty to the nation's
                    capital.</p>
                <p>Best of luck,Colin”</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you get on the Foreign Relations Committee?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Very early. The first committee Everett Dirksen got me on was the Banking
                    Committee. Everett Dirksen said, “You usually have to wait quite a while to get
                    on that committee.” But he also said, “Your father was a banker and I know
                    you're a trustee at the Harris Trust and Savings Bank in Chicago and David
                    Rockefeller asked you to be a trustee of the Chase Manhattan Bank in New York.
                    So you know a lot about banking. You should be able to go on the Senate Banking
                    Committee now.” So I went on not only the Banking Committee but also the Select
                    Senate Committee on the Elderly because of my long interest in the aging, an
                    interest that gets greater each year that passes! He got me on these committees
                    my first year in the Senate. In several years, I was selected to serve on the
                    Foreign Relations Committee and later became its chairman when my Hollywood
                    friend, Ronald Reagan, became President.</p>
                <p>By the way, I want to discuss with you also another responsibility senators had.
                    Both senators [of each state] have to sign on for any district court judges and
                    judges for the Circuit Court of Appeals. Candidates for judges are officially
                    nominated by the President, but they must be approved by the U.S. Senate. So the
                    President always wanted to have most nominations come from the Senate. For
                    Illinois, Everett Dirksen did this as the senior senator. But he had to have my
                    signature on each nomination also, as the junior senator, to have it approved by
                    Senate rules. So I set up a committee of senior lawyers, heads of law firms, and
                    former judges - just a small committee - to help me appraise his selectees.
                    During my two years of night law school, I developed a great respect and learned
                    a great deal about the legal system of our country. So I said to Everett Dirksen
                    when he gave me the names of nominees, “I will send them to my committee for
                    their review first and give him their recommendation.” On the first nominee they
                    said, “This guy did nothing but raise money for Everett Dirksen. He's not really
                    qualified to be a judge. His staff has advised him badly on this one.” Everett
                    Dirksen's staff said to me, “Look, we've got no other way to pay these guys back
                    and also we think he is good.” And I said, “They have to be approved by my legal
                    committee, and I just won't approve him, despite my very high regard for
                    Everett. I'm terribly sorry.”</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>I always went to his office to look at the names. Finally he came to my office,
                    after we hadn't named a judge for almost a year. He came to me and said, “Now
                    I've got a name that you'll approve.” I said, “Fine, who is it?” He said, “I
                    know you'll approve him. My staff says he's great.” I looked at it and I said,
                    “Why do you think I would approve him?” And he said, “I understand that he was a
                    lawyer for Bell &amp; Howell when you became president and CEO.” I said, “Yes,
                    he was. But did he tell you what happened to him?” “No, what happened to him,”
                    he said. “Well, he was a lawyer for us, that's true. About three months after I
                    became president, he asked for an appointment with me. He came in to see me. He
                    said, “I'm a lawyer for Bell &amp; Howell, as you know, but I've never had any
                    dealings with you because your predecessor always wanted to handle these things
                    with me directly. For instance, I do the taxes, too, and approve them. The Cook
                    County official that sets our taxes with our accountants is a good friend of
                    mine. I take good care of my friends, if you know what I mean! We pay about a
                    third in Cook County what they normally charge a company our size. He's really
                    good to us.”</p>
                <p>I said, “You mean to say the taxes that are used to pave our streets and
                    sidewalks, that are used to educate our children, and to pay the police to
                    protect our citizens, we're making money by cheating the government?” He then
                    said to me, “Well, I wouldn't put it that way.” So I told Senator Everett
                    Dirksen that I then said to this lawyer, “That's not the way I want to make
                    money for Bell &amp; Howell. So as far as I'm concerned, you're fired now. We'll
                    get another lawyer to replace you.”</p>
                <p>I said to Everett Dirksen then, “For that reason, I certainly woulnot want to see
                    that man a Federal judge.”</p>
                <p>Everett Dirksen in his own remarkable way said, “Well, you set up this new unique
                    system. It is remarkable. I'm a lawyer, but you did at least go to night law
                    school. I'll tell you what I'm going to do. I'm so busy as Minority Leader on a
                    lot of other things, why don't I turn over the responsibility to you to name all
                    these new judges, and you show me their background and your advisory committee's
                    comments. I will probably accept whoever you'll name and sign the form with
                    you.” That even strengthened the wonderful relationship I already had with
                    Senator Everett Dirksen.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>Early on the Committee came up with the name: J.P. Stevens. I asked if that was
                    John Paul Stevens? They said yes. I said, “He was a classmate with me at the
                    University of Chicago. In our senior year, in 1941, he was chairman of the
                    Senior Men's Honorary Society, while I was chairman of the Inter-Fraternity
                    Council. [Laughter] He was the smartest senior in our class. He's a brilliant
                    fellow; he's a wonderful man.” I tell you that name was the perfect name for me.
                    That was one of the three names they gave me. “I'll interview the other two but
                    I don't have to interview him.” But I did interview him because the other two
                    were also outstanding. But I determined he was the best. So I told him he would
                    be our selection. Instead of accepting immediately he said, “Let me think it
                    over and talk to my family. I just can't give you an answer now.” He went home
                    and called me back the next morning and said, “No, I can't do it. I've really
                    got to educate my kids. I've got to make enough money for that and other
                    expenses. Why don't you name me six years from now and that would be fine.” I
                    said, “Look, John, in six years, I may not be a senator. In six years, we might
                    not have a Republican president either. In six years, you ought to be on the
                    Supreme Court. This appointment is the Circuit Court of Appeals. This isn't the
                    district court. It's the Circuit Court of Appeals. The next step could be the
                    Supreme Court. Take another night, talk again to your family, and think it
                    over.”</p>
                <p>He then accepted the next day. In five years, he was on the Supreme Court, and
                    now he's the senior judge. I've named 22 judges to the federal courts so I'm the
                    only law school drop-out with 22 federal judges sitting there now and they've
                    all been wonderful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the personal side, do you want to talk at all about
                        thtragedy of your daughter, Valerie, or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Yes, I will. On Sunday morning, September 18, 1966 at 5:00 a.m., in our
                    home on the shore of Lake Michigan in Kenilworth, Illinois, my wife, Loraine,
                    was awakened and heard my daughter moaning. Her bedroom adjoined ours. With my
                    hearing loss from World War II, I couldn't hear that moaning. But Loraine heard
                    it, and she woke me up and said, “I'm going in Valerie's bedroom to see her.”
                    Valerie was Sharon's identical age 21 twin sister, but they had separate
                    bedrooms. She opened the door and looked in and saw this man standing there with
                    a flashlight. He had stabbed Valerie, we learned later, 13 times. We don't know
                    how he happened to come in that room but he dashed out of the house immediately
                    and left in a car, we presume, with a driver accomplice. He had broken a glass
                    window in our home's first floor, then put an arm in and opened the door on the
                    lake side, and for some unknown reason went up into Valerie's room, probably
                    awakening her. What I did was immediately turn the alarm on, connected to a
                    siren on the roof. The siren went off. Three houses down, on Sheridan Road, was
                    a well known doctor. He heard the alarm go off while in bed. He knew it was in
                    the direction of our house and ran down to our door just as we were calling the
                    police. He came up, examined Valerie, and told us his conclusion that there was
                    no heartbeat.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>The Kenilworth Police, of course, came immediately. They'd never had a murder in
                    the city of Kenilworth to their knowledge, and they didn't know how to handle
                    it, so they turned it over to the Chicago Police. (Charles Ramsey knows about
                    it. He left the Chicago Police force to become Chief of Police in Washington, DC
                    in 1998).</p>
                <p>They worked hard on it. The FBI came into it and kept the case open for 14 years.
                    But they never solved the mystery. The supposition was that it was related to
                    the story of an Illinois politician who had died while running for office again.
                    They found in his house a lot of money in cash. It was a big story in the
                    newspapers. It could be that they thought, Chuck Percy has raised money for his
                    campaign and might have some of it in his house. President Eisenhower had come
                    out to Chicago to campaign for me and he addressed a very large fund-raising
                    dinner. Actually, I never saw a dollar of it. It all went into the bank account
                    for the U.S. Senate campaign. Bob Galvin, a treasured friend and chairman of
                    Motorola Corporation, was our finance chairman. On September 18th, they broke in
                    and probably were looking through the house for campaign cash.That Sunday
                    morning, we didn't go to church. We read the Bible lesson with the family
                    grouped around us on the porch. At the end of reading the Bible lesson, I said
                    to the family, “Let's just do this. I'm going to suspend my campaign for the
                    Senate. I'm going to announce this tomorrow. Let's just go away together
                    someplace and get away from here to think and pray. Maybe go out to California.
                    But let us spend the rest of our lives doing the kinds of things that would make
                    Valerie proud of us. Certainly she was a wonderful daughter to Loraine and
                    myself, sister, and granddaughter to you. Her spirit will go to Heaven. She did
                    so much good, particularly with the children, minorities, the disadvantaged, and
                    low-income families in Illinois. We can all be very proud of her.”</p>
                <p>Valerie had been in charge of “Volunteers for Percy.”</p>
                <p>Then Senator Paul Douglas, whom I was running against, and it couldn't have been
                    more thoughtful of him - suspended his campaign for two weeks. Finally the
                    thought came to us in California, what would Valerie want us to do? It was
                    unanimous with the family that she would want us to go back to the campaign. We
                    had just another month, and then November and the election.</p>
                <p>I called Senator Paul Douglas and thanked him very much indeed for suspending his
                    campaign, and I expressed my deep appreciation to him for that. But I said, “Now
                    let's both go out and do the best we can.” So I did, and the family all returned
                    to the campaign and we won.</p>
                <p>So we have a grandchild now, Sharon and Jay's daughter, who was named Valerie,
                    after Sharon's twin sister. She is the godmother now of one of our other
                    grandchildren, Raina, our other daughter's (Gail's) daughter, and also [in May,
                    2000] was married at National Cathedral in Washington, DC to a great young man,
                    James Carnegie, from Australia and is living there now.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>Q: I was thinking this might be a good time to stop. I've got a car parked and
                    all that. I thought we might pick it up the next time when you're in the Senate.
                    We've already covered the judicial appointments and your work on housing for the
                    poor. I think then we should pick up the rest of the Senate, particularly
                    because of our particular focus on the International Relations Committee and all
                    that.</p>
                <p>PERCY: Very good.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Q: Today is the 20th of July, 1998, and we thought we would go back and look at
                    your development of your interest in foreign relations even prior to your coming
                    into the Senate. We'd already touched on the United Nations effort early on.
                    Before we move even farther, I'd like to ask again, what was your impression
                    when the United Nations was being developed when you were in San Francisco? You
                    were a young man. How did you feel about it?</p>
                <p>PERCY: I had my first experience with the United Nations when based at the
                    Alameda Naval Air Station, across the bay from San Francisco, while the idea was
                    being put together and organized, as I told you. I was terribly excited about
                    it. Because after all, we were in a war and the whole country was concentrating
                    on the war, foreign policy, relations between countries, between ourselves and
                    Germany and Japan and so forth. All of these things were so important and so
                    engrossing, that to find a way to get countries to work together like our states
                    work together, and like we work together with Mexico and Canada, seemed terribly
                    important to me. I did develop my early interest when I realized that we were
                    quite unique in that the only original native inhabitants of the U.S. are really
                    native Indians. Almost everyone I knew, including myself, had origins that went
                    to other countries outside the United States. For instance, the origin of my
                    father's side was in England. They came to the United States before the American
                    Revolution, settled in the South, in Virginia, Mississippi, and Alabama. My
                    father was born in Mobile, Alabama, but his family had a long heritage in Great
                    Britain.</p>
                <p>My mother's family came from Germany. So here we were in World War II, Germany,
                    our enemy, was one of our enemies and my mother's heritage from Germany and my
                    father's, Great Britain, our ally. Fortunately, while I was stationed at the
                    Alameda Naval Air Station outside San Francisco, California, we did have
                    training working with British pilots and gunnery officers, so I then had an
                    opportunity to talk with them about the future of the world afterwards, what
                    were we going to be doing after the war, how could we work together, how we
                    could find a way to get together peacefully with Japan and with Germany? That's
                    what led me, of course, to take very positive steps at Bell &amp; Howell Company
                    to internationalize.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>In my freshman year at the University of Chicago, I met David Rockefeller. He was
                    getting his Ph.D. at the time I was getting my bachelor's degree. He knew that I
                    was a poor boy and was working my way through. He was the richest student on
                    campus. His grandfather had founded and financed the University of Chicago. At
                    that stage in his life, and then throughout his life, David Rockefeller was
                    interested in foreign countries, and he spent a good deal of time over at the
                    University of Chicago's International House, which was also established by the
                    Rockefeller Foundation. He frequently invited me over for lunches and dinners to
                    sit down with students from various countries - from Europe, from Latin America,
                    from Asia. We had a great many foreign students at the University of Chicago. We
                    would sit and talk with them about their countries - why they came to this
                    country for their education, what were they going to do when they went back, if
                    they're going back, or were they going to stay in the U.S.?</p>
                <p>And that developed in me a great interest in foreign affairs aneducation, though
                    at that time I had never been out of our country.</p>
                <p>And that led me, years later incidentally when I left the U.S. Senate in 1985,
                    the first thing I did was to take on the job as president of the Institute of
                    International Education (IIE), which handled all foreign students in the U.S.,
                    and all U.S. college students that went abroad to study. International House at
                    the University of Chicago gave me the first opportunity I had to discuss at
                    great length the differences between the people, culture, business, and
                    government of the United States and the rest of the world.</p>
                <p>While mentioning IIE, I will add that just after leaving the Senate in January
                    1985, President Ronald Reagan asked me to join him and Secretary of State George
                    Shultz in the Oval Office at the White House for a talk. He said to me, “You
                    have had a longtime relationship with India and have had a close relationship
                    with every Prime Minister since 1952. George Shultz and I would like you now to
                    be our U.S. ambassador to India. Would you accept this appointment?”</p>
                <p>I quickly thought, that I desperately wanted to spend more time with my wife and
                    family because of the tremendous demands on my time during my 18 years in the
                    Senate, and my mother was then 92 years old and I did not want to put 6000 miles
                    between her and my whole family even though Loraine could go with me. (Later in
                    our conversation I told President Reagan that.) I thanked them both for their
                    thoughtfulness, but then said, “I am sorry, I cannot accept your kind and
                    exciting offer because I have just accepted another job offer to be chairman and
                    CEO of the Institute of International Education (IIE), and the salary I would
                    get as ambassador to India is fully taxable, but the salary I will get at IIE
                    has no tax on it at all and I need funds to pay off my large campaign debt.”</p>
                <p>The President looked startled, and then said, “Well, tell us, homuch is the
                    salary that you will be receiving?</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>I said, “Mr. President, I was afraid that you might ask me that. It is a
                    volunteer job, but they promised to pay me $1.00 a year, but they also promised
                    to never give it to me, so there is no tax!”</p>
                <p>Then I told them the real reason about the family, but thanked theagain profusely
                    for the offer.</p>
                <p>He then replied, “I know your family and I know what your schedule has been for
                    18 years and I fully understand your reluctance to go to India despite your love
                    for it, its democratic government, and its people, Amen!”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're going back now to the development of your feeling
                        towardinternational affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: That's right. I mentioned the British pilots and gunnerofficers who were
                    training in the United States and I worked with them.</p>
                <p>Before I went in the Navy, I did get a contract from them when I was put in
                    charge of defense operations at Bell &amp; Howell Company, as I said before. And
                    now to expand on this subject, I called it the Defense Coordinating Department
                    and I was head of it. I did very soon get a contract from the Defense Plant
                    Corporation of the U.S. Government to authorize a transfer of land in
                    Lincolnwood, Illinois for us to build a plant there. We moved our main offices
                    from 1801 Larchmont Avenue in Chicago to 7100 McCormick Road, Lincolnwood,
                    Illinois. It was a very large plant and by the time I went into the Navy, the
                    plant was finished so that Bell &amp; Howell could manufacture their own lenses.
                    Before the war, most of our lenses came from Germany and Japan. The purpose of
                    the whole building was for Bell &amp; Howell to contribute to the military to
                    build products that would help train Naval aircraft gunnery officers. A gunsight
                    aiming point camera was developed in 1941 by us that was first used in training,
                    but later used in combat to record the accuracy of machine gun fire. Bell &amp;
                    Howell sights were described at the time as the “eyes” of the B-29 bomber. And
                    the Bell &amp; Howell new EYEMO camera, as it was called, was adapted to
                    military use therefore and became a very standard military camera. It was
                    commonly and humorously rumored in the Naval Air Force that everybody above the
                    rank of a First Lieutenant should get a Bell &amp; Howell EYEMO camera! They
                    thought it was such an exciting product.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>In the earlier years, it was the company's British affiliate that produced many
                    of the lenses, but war conditions, of course, changed that. I worked out the
                    arrangement for us to purchase Taylor, Taylor, and Hobson Company in England and
                    we used them to train our personnel so that we could become manufacturers of
                    optics and lenses at our Lincolnwood plant during World War II. Bell &amp;
                    Howell then maintained the largest engineering and research laboratory in the
                    world, devoted to development of motion picture and applied apparatus
                    exclusively, and was fully equipped with machine tools and trained personnel
                    necessary for such precision manufacturing. Among the major World War II
                    products that did not fit the pattern of a pure mechanical device was the
                    “flight simulator.” This device was used for training airborne pilots,
                    navigators, and bombardiers in the use of radar by simulated flights over enemy
                    territory and bombing targets, specifically in the Pacific area. The flight
                    simulator was a very large and complex device incorporating technologies with
                    ultra-high radio frequencies, ultra-sonics, optics, and mechanics. This very
                    unusual device was on demonstration display in Chicago's Museum of Plant and
                    Industry many years after World War II. The advent of the 16 mm motion picture
                    sound projectors in 1932, four years before my time at Bell &amp; Howell, of
                    course, became very famous during the course of the war in training and
                    upgrading the quality of our soldiers. I frequently used Bell &amp; Howell
                    equipment, as did my large staff, during my three years of naval service during
                    World War II in the Pacific Ocean area.</p>
                <p>Q: 1945.</p>
                <p>PERCY: I returned to Bell &amp; Howell in 1945 after the war ended. It was a
                    private company until then, but when I came back, I strongly supported President
                    Joseph McNabb's idea that in order to get enough money to do the kind of things
                    we wanted to in the post war period, to globalize ourselves, we needed to go
                    public. All the impressions I'd had while in the Navy, and while at the
                    University of Chicago, led me to believe that Latin America, Europe, Asia,
                    Africa, and other parts of the world, would be great future markets for American
                    products, but for us to reach them would require far more funds.</p>
                <p>Therefore, we did go public. The change required the transfer of four and
                    one-half million dollars from earned surplus to the capital account, thus making
                    available 150,000 shares required for Bell &amp; Howell Company to be listed on
                    the New York Stock Exchange. The directors, of which I was one by then, accepted
                    the offer of Joseph McNabb, the president and CEO. I was granted a stock option
                    by the company and by the directors. At that time, I did not own a single share
                    of our stock. Joe McNabb sold 37,625 of his shares but he wanted to buy the same
                    number of shares back when it became a public company. The official statement
                    was issued, and they did offer 150,000 shares of common stock, and 30,000 shares
                    of cumulative preferred stock to the public. The banks we worked with as I
                    recall were the First National Bank of Chicago, Investment and Loaning Bank,
                    City Bank, and Farmers Bank and Trust Company of New York.</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>Q: Let's talk about during your time at Bell &amp; Howell, you did mention that
                    you had taken a trip to Germany and to France, and to England after the war to
                    see about developing trade. The Chicago area had been the heart of isolationism
                    at one point prior to the war. Senator Taft and his group, Borad, and others
                    were mid-Westerners. Was there a residue of isolationism in the area and people
                    you knew? Were you fighting that? Right after the war did you find that there
                    was a feeling among some of the influential people maybe to return to a certain
                    amount of isolationism or not?</p>
                <p>PERCY: There were a great many businessmen in the Middle West in those days,
                    including Chicago, that were isolationists, who believed that the United States
                    should hold itself separate and aloof from other nations. Isolationists believed
                    that it was a mistake to get involved either in international trade agreements
                    or in mutual assistance pacts.</p>
                <p>The America First Committee was formed just before my 21st birthday in September
                    1940, and became the most powerful isolationist group in America before we
                    entered World War II. It had more than 800,000 members who wanted to keep
                    America neutral. It tried to influence public opinion through publications and
                    speeches. However, America First was dissolved 4 days after the Japanese
                    attacked Pearl Harbor on December 7, 1941.</p>
                <p>Some isolationism still remained but I remained a strong free trader and my
                    wartime letters to Joe McNabb proposed postwar globalization. I did go to
                    England very soon after returning to the company. I was, by the way, elected a
                    director in 1945 at age 25 when I came back from the Navy Air Corps. I was the
                    youngest director they ever had. I was given the responsibility to globalize the
                    company. So I did first go to England to meet with the notable J. Arthur Rank,
                    and suggested the idea of our establishing a joint company in England with the
                    Rank organization and Bell &amp; Howell. We would build a factory outside of
                    London and manufacture our line of products in England so that we could also
                    have a distribution office there, where we could then develop agencies all
                    through Europe and distribute into that area.</p>
                <p>Q: Were you thinking of doing anything sort of connecting with any political
                    powers in, say, the Chicago, Illinois area about internationalism at that
                    time?</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>PERCY: I did join the Chicago Club. I became interested in the Council on Foreign
                    Relations in Chicago and became the youngest member of both of those
                    organizations. They did have business members who had interests abroad. The
                    lectures and meetings they had were very good indeed. I did concentrate a
                    majority of my time on company activities. But of course I had my three children
                    (Sharon, Valerie, and Roger) to look after alone, although I had bought a house
                    in Wilmette, Illinois, and had good household help. After I was elected
                    president (I told you the story of when I was elected president and then went
                    out to Sun Valley.), I met Loraine March 7, 1949, while skiing, and we were
                    married in 1950. We lost our first baby at birth, but subsequently did have two
                    children, Gail and Mark. I was concentrating on family concerns but also did do
                    a great deal of work in continuing Bell &amp; Howell's worldwide expansion
                    efforts because Loraine, who was a wonderful mother to all my children, was also
                    very interested and helpful, as she had lived abroad for several years. She
                    loved to travel with me and sometimes we were able to take our children. Both of
                    her brothers also lived and worked abroad. John Guyer joined the Peace Corps in
                    India, and was country director of the program in Afghanistan. Later he started
                    and was director of the Asia Foundation project in Sri Lanka. David Guyer was
                    with the United Nations and later was president of Save the Children Foundation
                    in New York. So we had a family that was very much interested in international
                    relations and worthy causes, as were their wives (David's wife, Carol Penny
                    Guyer, and John's wife, Diana Guyer). Meanwhile, the Bell &amp; Howell sales had
                    gotten up as high as 22 million dollars in 1945, the year the war ended. But
                    they dropped down the next year to 10 million, less than half.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was mainly because no more war work. Was that
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: That's right. Even by the time 1949 came, my first year as president, the
                    sales were only $13,238,000. The net profits were only $447,000. The number of
                    employees were 1813 in 1949 when I was elected president. From that time on it
                    was my responsibility to build the company. We did so by internal growth through
                    intensive research, engineering, manufacturing, and marketing, and also by
                    merging with or purchasing other companies. Some of the companies we purchased
                    had operations abroad already, which helped us very much indeed. One big
                    purchase got us into the microfilm business. I had long wanted to diversify the
                    company and get into other fields. We purchased the microfilm division of Pathe
                    Manufacturing Company in July, 1946. Our microfilm division included
                    engineering, production, sales, and services which we organized. After we had
                    the company two years, we expanded it with recorders, readers, and automatic
                    feeders, so the recorder could photograph more than 23,000 checks in 80
                    minutes.</p>
                <p>We also signed a contract in 1948 with Burroughs Adding Machine Company, making
                    them the exclusive worldwide distributors of the entire line of microfilm
                    equipment. We started to really get going then. We felt that we ought to be
                    doing far more abroad.</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>The death of Joseph McNabb, Bell &amp; Howell president and CEO, occurred late in
                    1948. It was a real setback for us and hurt me deeply as I treasured his
                    friendship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During the fifties, you became president in 1949, was
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: January, '49.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you didn't run for the Senate until 1967?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: I ran for the Senate in 1966 and entered in January 1967, buI had made the
                    decision in 1963 to go into public life.</p>
                <p>Q: Oh, yes. In that period from '49 to '63, how did you find, for example, the
                    Council on Foreign Relations? Did you find this a useful place? What was your
                    impression of it?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Oh, yes, very much so. Mainly businessmen or academicians, presidents of
                    universities, professors, doctors, and so forth, were members. There was a good
                    cross- section of people that were members of that organization (and I am still
                    a member), and also in the Chicago Club. But the general impression I had from
                    the members, and the thing I learned most from them, was that we needed a
                    stronger and more creative political system in our country. Very much so. And so
                    I did get interested in politics and became a Republican precinct captain. I
                    never did get into politics at all when I lived in Chicago, but I didn't move to
                    the North Shore of Chicago until I became a junior at New Trier Township High
                    School, and I had that volunteer position there in Wilmette.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying you were a precinct captain in
                        Wilmette.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>PERCY: Right. In Wilmette, Illinois. Acting as a GOP precinct captain got me
                    interested in causing people to come out and vote, having meetings to encourage
                    them to vote. I wasn't telling them how to vote, but on the other hand, I was a
                    Republican precinct captain. I wanted them to look at our party and study it
                    carefully. The Republican Party was a popular party on the North Shore of
                    Chicago, whereas Chicago then was largely a Democratic city. But we were a
                    northern suburb. Then I began to indicate that raising money for the party would
                    help candidates get elected. As I mentioned earlier, later in life, when I had
                    married Loraine and we lived in Kenilworth, Illinois, Don Rumsfeld, whom I had
                    never even met, came to our home one evening. When he introduced himself to me,
                    I said, “Don't stand outside. Come on in.” We sat down and talked for an hour
                    and he said we both had graduated from New Trier High School and he was
                    interested in running for Congress. As he left, I said, “I will absolutely
                    support you without any ifs, ands, or buts about it. I'll support you, and we'll
                    see if we can't help you financially as well as with political support.” That
                    began a young man's distinguished career.</p>
                <p>Q: What about on the North Shore, as a Republican, getting out the vote? Was
                    there much of an ethnic vote there? I'm thinking of Chicago, one thinks of the
                    Germans, the Jews, the Poles, maybe others. For the group you were aiming at,
                    were they pretty much what today we would call sort of WASPs?</p>
                <p>PERCY: No. I think of the very fact that after I got in the Senate, Mayor Daley
                    invited me to come to Chicago when Pope John Paul II, head of the Vatican in
                    Rome, made his first visit to the United States, and having come originally from
                    Poland, he didn't come first to Washington, DC, he didn't come to New York City,
                    he came direct to Chicago. He went through the New York airport, but flew right
                    on to Chicago. When he landed at the airport, the Mayor and I met him there. I
                    stayed with him for three days. He came there first because Chicago was the
                    second largest Polish population city in the world. Ethnic groups were terribly
                    important in Chicago particularly. Attracting the ethnic groups, showing your
                    interest in their countries of origin, was always very important.</p>
                <p>Q: I was just wondering whether during this period, before you got into the
                    Senate, was the Republican Party able to make much of an inroad into the ethnic
                    groups in that area? You think of the Democrats for years, for generations, had
                    been sort of the ethnic party; the New Deal and all that. I was wondering
                    whether you were one of those working to make the Republicans reach out
                    more?</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>PERCY: I became, later, chairman of the Republican Illinois Finance Committee and
                    after that I became vice chairman of the National Republican Finance Committee.
                    Cliff Folger was the chairman. My principle orientation in both jobs was toward
                    businessmen and women, but also many important ethnic groups. You get them
                    organized behind you, interested in your candidates, and when I ran for office,
                    to ask their support in electing me. Many of my Polish friends, for instance,
                    would say, “This man understands Poland; he's been there, he can work with us.”
                    That was the way we approached them, by working very, very closely with ethnic
                    groups. We always had a chairman for each ethnic group in any particular
                    campaign, particularly when I ran for the Senate the first time in 1966.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find when you ran for governor, you ran for
                        governor when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: In 1964.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1964, when you ran for governor, how did the ethnic
                        vote comout for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: In that particular race, the ethnic group was influenced greatly by the
                    fact that Goldwater was on the ticket. He was running for president. My
                    preferred candidate originally was Governor Nelson Rockefeller. I thought he
                    would appeal to a broad section of the ethnic group. But Goldwater didn't have
                    those interests and he didn't have the kind of attraction that would appeal to
                    ethnics. However, I had pledged I would support whoever won the Republican
                    nomination. So I did support Goldwater in 1964 when I ran for governor and that
                    helped defeat me, which turned out to be a blessing for me because I love my
                    life after the Senate, but also loved my 18 years there.</p>
                <p>Q: Because we're concentrating on the international side because of our
                    organization and we're trying to get an American senator on the Foreign
                    Relations Committee during a very crucial time and where he was coming from
                    politically, what about during the senatorial campaign - this was 1966 - you
                    said you'd developed an ethnic captain, so to speak, for various things. Can you
                    talk about what did this cause you to do? I mean, how would you deal with a very
                    large Polish vote, for example?</p>
                <p>PERCY: In that particular race, it wasn't as much the ethnic vote as it was
                    dominated by Vietnam. That was the big issue. That became a major issue in the
                    campaign as well as, as I mentioned to you, Paul Douglas was the founder of an
                    organization called “A Million Americans to Keep Red China out of the United
                    Nations.” Those two things - Vietnam and the United Nations - became the two
                    biggest issues that we debated constantly in that campaign - as to whether we
                    should be in the Vietnam War and raise all the resources that would be necessary
                    to win that war, or whether this was wasn't really in our national security
                    interest, as I constantly maintained.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>Q: I would have thought that the Polish American vote, that many of the ethnic
                    votes, would have been more to support our cause in Vietnam than not. I mean,
                    these are people who traditionally come from countries where there were
                    communists and opposed to communism. And have traditionally been a solid
                    supporter of military action. I mean, many people go into the ethnic places;
                    this is how you move up in society by going into the military, moving that way.
                    Did you find this true, or not?</p>
                <p>PERCY: No, I really didn't. I didn't have any trouble getting the support of the
                    Poles. They really supported me. They realized that I had been a strong
                    proponent of Poland against the Soviet Union, for instance.</p>
                <p>Q: How did that, I mean, during the campaign and all, were there any attempts to
                    sort of label you as a Red if you were for opening the UN to China and you were
                    opposed to our action in Vietnam? I would have thought this would have made you
                    sort of vulnerable to be known as a real left-winger.</p>
                <p>PERCY: I was looked upon as a moderate in social issues, but as a businessman in
                    economic matters. You don't generally look on a businessman as “liberal” - we
                    fight for the free enterprise system, we fight for the competitive system, we
                    fight for democracy against communism - and there were no ifs, ands, or buts
                    about my anti-communist feelings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about China - the recognition of China? This was
                        prettearly on. How did that go during the campaign?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Well, I felt very strongly about this issue and I think there was a
                    general feeling that the largest country on earth ought to be in the United
                    Nations. It is the United Nations and why not bring them into it to see if we
                    couldn't bring peace to this area and make them a friendly member of the
                    international family? I had the strong feeling that political friendships
                    through the centuries have tended to follow the trade lanes. That therefore we
                    really ought to emphasize much more trade with China. And that's why I started
                    so hard right after World War II to encourage trade with Japan and Germany. Look
                    at what that has done now to bring us together to become allies and friends
                    through the years. Just as I mentioned, the strength that Germany now has with
                    France for the first time is largely in trade. They've become in 1999 their
                    respective largest trading partners. You couldn't imagine another war between
                    France and Germany as a result of that now.</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>Q: What about Taiwan? I'm sure that in debates if you were talking about
                    recognition of China, that's always been the most complex. It's a problem that
                    hasn't been solved yet. There were very strong proponents in the United States
                    Senate, particularly on the Republican side, but also there were some on the
                    Democratic side, of great support for Taiwan. Of course, Senator Knowland from
                    California, Senator Cranston at the time. But, you know, I mean, how were you
                    dealing as a Republican candidate for the Senate, with the Taiwan issue?</p>
                <p>PERCY: I've always supported Taiwan's right to be a member of international
                    organizations. But China has always considered me a good friend despite this. As
                    I mentioned, they asked me to head the first delegation from Congress that ever
                    came to China sponsored by them, after relationships were opened up by Nixon and
                    Kissinger. Yet they knew that I had questions about their Taiwan policy. They
                    just didn't want me to make a big issue of that on that trip. [Laughter] But
                    they knew and were fully aware of the fact that I did have respect for Taiwan's
                    right to greater independence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You got into the Senate in '67.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: I was sworn into the Senate January 4, 1967.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your initial committee assignments?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: My initial committee assignments were the Banking Committee and the Select
                    Committee on Aging and also Government Affairs. I wrote a book, “Growing Old in
                    a Country of the Young.” I spent a lot of time in my early public life going to
                    the elderly, making them a part of our public affairs program, to seek them out,
                    male and female. Not too many politicians did that in those days. I also went to
                    the poor, the low income families on the south side of Chicago, the African
                    American community. Jesse Jackson, early on, became a friend and met with me
                    occasionally. The elderly were a group that I really worked hard with, to make
                    them a part of the organization and to see everything that we could do to help
                    the elderly renew their purpose in life. I worked heavily on all the legislation
                    to assist and help the aging, such as Medicare.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you go on the Foreign Relations Committee?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: I went on in 1972. I would have liked to have gone on earlier - but I was
                    put on very early at that. I was put on the Banking Committee early by Everett
                    Dirksen, another more difficult committee to get on. Did I tell you the story
                    about when I resigned from the board at the Harris Trust and Savings Bank and
                    the Chase Manhattan Bank?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't recall that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: I was on the Banking Committee and I just decided that it would be wise to
                    resign from both the Harris Trust and Savings Bank Board in Chicago and the
                    Chase Manhattan Bank Board in New York. I felt that I should devote my time
                    entirely to the Senate. Going to board meetings would take me out of DC. In 1967
                    there were no laws or regulations requiring me to give up these positions. (Now,
                    of course, the laws and regulations have changed.) But I said to the Chase
                    Manhattan and its chairman, David Rockefeller, that I felt I should resign now
                    that I am in the Senate, and they said, “Oh, no. You're on the Banking
                    Committee! More than ever, we want you to stay on our Board.” I said, “Look, if
                    I am on the Banking Committee, and a vote comes up on an issue affecting
                    banking, that would affect either the Harris Trust or the Chase Manhattan, I
                    would personally feel obligated to simply tell the committee and the Senate that
                    I would not be voting on that issue because I'm on a bank board that would be
                    affected. Whereas if I resign from the Board, I'd still have my whole banking
                    background. You know how strongly I feel about the banking industry and its
                    remarkable effect on our personal as well as our business lives. Then I could
                    vote. And I would be voting in a way that would be very favorable to the future
                    well-being of the banking industry. But if I'm accepting a fee as a director,
                    then I don't feel it would be right for me to vote on any of those issues.” Many
                    business people thought I was wrong and foolish for resigning when I was
                    director of two important banks. When I told the other directors I would abstain
                    from voting on bank issues if I stayed on the Board, they could hardly wait till
                    I resigned! When I left the Senate, the Harris made me a life trustee. And the
                    Chase invited me back to an annual meeting at the Rockefeller Estate for many
                    years.</p>
                <p>Q: Of course, you are absolutely right. In fact, it's rather difficult to
                    understand the reasoning of people who would be in a position and do that. Talk
                    about conflict of interest. On the Banking Committee, did any international
                    issues come up? During the time you were there, did any issues that dealt with
                    foreign banks, foreign trade, come up?</p>
                <p>PERCY: I don't really remember any particular things that would be important from
                    the foreign standpoint except our relationship with the World Bank.</p>
                <p>Q: While we're on it, though, during the time you were there, what would be the
                    major domestic issues that were dealing with the Banking Committee?</p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>PERCY: Mergers, of course. And should investment companies get into banking or
                    should they be separate? But I had done so much merging in Bell &amp; Howell,
                    which I headed. In 1946, we took over the manufacturing and distribution of
                    products abroad by merging with J. Arthur Rank Organization in England. The
                    international division of Bell &amp; Howell was established in 1947, two years
                    before I became president. We worked with banks in all of those countries we
                    were in - they were extremely important, so I just felt that our banks over here
                    could expand if we encouraged other countries to do business with us. There were
                    many who really wanted to be isolationists and put tariffs on imports. I came
                    down and testified before the Senate when I was at Bell &amp; Howell, in favor
                    of freer trade. Kodak and others didn't want foreign companies to be shipping
                    products into the U.S. I said, “No. We have to expose ourselves to business
                    relationships abroad, and if they are more efficient and lower cost than we are,
                    then we've got to know how they're doing that, and learn how to compete by
                    lowering our costs and still increase our efficiency and quality. That's why I
                    went over and studied companies abroad, studied how they were operating. That
                    led President Dwight Eisenhower to appoint me as chairman, after the war ended,
                    of a mission to go to Italy. I selected six CEOs of diversified companies to go
                    with me, including Arthur C. Nielson. We went over to help reconstruct the
                    economy of our former enemy, Italy, and help them rebuild. But we also said, “We
                    are opening our markets to you. Rather than fighting us, let's trade and work
                    together that way.” I invited them to come over and see our headquarters and our
                    Chicago area factories, tour our manufacturing plants, go through them and see
                    what techniques we were using.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any issues, you came in in 1967, and you didn't
                        get othe Foreign Relations Committee until when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: 1972 was very soon. It was unbelievable that I got on that early. I had
                    seniority over everyone in my class that came in. Senator Howard Baker was in
                    that 1967 class, as were Senators Mac Mathias and Ed Brooks. I was the first one
                    to get on the Foreign Relations Committee and was elected chairman from 1980
                    through 1984, when Ronald Reagan was President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Prior to that, say early '70s, Vietnam was going strong
                        betwee'67 and '71. Did you make any trips to Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>PERCY: Yes, I did. In the fall of 1967, I decided to go to Vietnam - a decision
                    that I never realized at the time would be a near fatal one. I talked to Scott
                    Cohen who was my chief staff adviser on foreign affairs. We began preparation
                    for this trip. Scott Cohen had previously been with the CIA and Army
                    Intelligence, and he and his wife Rita continued to be dear treasured friends of
                    ours in Washington, DC. In the fifties he had established and operated a bureau
                    of Broadcast Information Service in Saigon, and, since then, had followed
                    developments there very closely. We had hoped to leave in early October 1967 but
                    it was postponed until November because my Home Ownership Bill for Low Income
                    Families was hanging fire in the Senate. Home ownership for low income families
                    was just so precious and dear to me, to see if we couldn't pass a bill that
                    would make it possible for low income people to own their homes rather than just
                    be renting and then just not caring enough about the property. My bill would
                    make it possible for them to have practically interest-free loans so that they
                    could more easily buy a house for their family, and feel the pride of ownership,
                    so I delayed the trip to Vietnam, but in the first week of December 1967 (my
                    first year in the Senate) we left for Saigon, Vietnam, spending a day first at
                    Stanford University with an Asian studies specialist.</p>
                <p>My wife, Loraine, went with us. We had together visited Vietnamese orphanages and
                    hospitals in the United States to get a little feeling for habits and customs of
                    the Vietnamese people. We didn't want to confine our talks to government
                    officials and politicians; we wanted a much broader view. In the U.S. we had
                    talked with Vietnamese newspaper correspondents and business and professional
                    people to make sure that we had an understanding of both the anti-communist and
                    anti-government positions. Our ambassador to Vietnam was Ellsworth Bunker and he
                    had invited us to stay at the home in Vietnam of an American official who was in
                    the United States at the time. Instead, we arranged to be quartered in the home
                    of an American businessman in Saigon. We hired private guards to ensure our
                    security. Scott Cohen went out a week early and stayed at the Caravelle Hotel
                    where many U.S. and foreign correspondents were living. Everett Martin, Newsweek
                    Bureau Chief - Mertin Perry and Francois Sully of Newsweek, Georgianne Geyer of
                    the Chicago Daily News were based there. Tom Buckley of The New York Times, and
                    from The Christian Science Monitor Miss Beverly Eap were there also, and Peter
                    Arnett, a New Zealander, of the Associated Press, who won a Pulitzer Prize for
                    his coverage of the Vietnam War.</p>
                <p>We visited Guam en route to Saigon, and we were interviewed by the editor of a
                    paper from the Utah State University, Jack Peterson, about my feelings about
                    Vietnam. I said to him at that time, “I have always felt that our greatest
                    mistake in Vietnam or Southeast Asia was that we have taken the initiative of
                    the war away from the Asians. This was a land war in Asia and the Asians, I
                    said, must be prepared to sacrifice for it and take the initiative and
                    responsibility. Our withdrawal would be a disaster for the South Vietnamese and
                    yet they refused to commit themselves wholeheartedly to the conflict. This is
                    why I had proposed an All-Asian Peace Conference to be attended only by Asian
                    nations.” And that I made as a very strong point to the Senate and the U.S.
                    public on my return.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>My wife, Loraine, was interested in the care of orphaned children, the poor and
                    the disabled, and the sick. She gathered information for an article that
                    Redbook, a women's magazine, asked her to write for them. I felt that we should
                    have knowledge of the Vietcong atrocities. I decided, therefore, that I wanted
                    to go to Dak Son, a newly abandoned village in the highlands where the previous
                    week, “the Vietcong, in a flame throwing rage, had burned to death more than 200
                    people.” The pilot of the embassy's helicopter that was to fly us to the village
                    of Dak Son, and who made the arrangements, assured me that officials now
                    considered the area reasonably safe. The ambassador seemed to also feel that
                    there was no problem about our flying out there. So I took Scott Cohen and my
                    wife, Loraine, out in the helicopter. Our group also included Kenneth Schmid,
                    who was owner of a Chicago Printing and Engraving Company, who had been a Navy
                    aerial photographer in World War II and had brought his equipment with him to
                    Vietnam. Actually it was Schmid who took the very dramatic action shots of
                    myself and our group under fire. Fred Ward of Black Star, one of the nation's
                    top news photographers, was with us also on assignment.</p>
                <p>After we landed, we walked away from the helicopter in Dak Son, but Loraine
                    intuitively said, “I'm going to stay on the plane.” So the rest of us went out,
                    Scott Cohen and I and the others, went into the village and as we roamed around
                    looking at the burned-out shacks, the place where so many had died, and children
                    had suffocated (there were pictures in Time Magazine of this terrible village
                    atrocity). All of a sudden we heard gunfire and the heavy thuds of mortar shells
                    around us. I started to run to get away from the firing and all of a sudden one
                    of the rubber garters that held up my socks broke and I stumbled over it and
                    fell right down on the ground. I just stayed flat on the ground, and that
                    probably saved my life!</p>
                <p>When the firing started, the helicopter immediately took off with Loraine on
                    board. We thought, what do we do now? We learned later that the helicopter pilot
                    had immediately radioed to tell the embassy what had happened. U.S. planes soon
                    came in view with their guns blaring on both sides. The only one of our party
                    who was armed was Dennis Smith of the Mutual Security Agency, who was with us.
                    He had a carbine and a .38 caliber snub-nosed pistol, which he handed to me. It
                    was while we huddled in the dirt bunker that the helicopter pilot took off,
                    flying Loraine to the town of Song Ven about a mile and a half away. Loraine
                    said, “There was nothing I could do about it but pray.” But she knew that they
                    were notifying the embassy and military forces. After the helicopter landed, a
                    nurse came up to her that was treating the horribly burned victims of the
                    December 5 attack and counseled with her. Our helicopter, which was accompanied
                    then by four U.S. Army helicopter gunships, returned to Dak Son to rescue us. We
                    saw these four helicopters come in. It was absolutely wonderful! None of us were
                    seriously hurt. We were merely scratched and bruised. Scott Cohen said his main
                    reaction during the brief episode was one of disbelief. “I couldn't believe it.”
                    He said, “Why were we in this situation? We were told this area was secure. If I
                    get seriously hurt here, how can I explain this to my wife and baby?” That's
                    what he recalled. The reaction in Saigon was very strong. They really felt that
                    we had tried to do something to highlight the plight of the poor people in the
                    village of Dak Son. Another U.S. helicopter flew out to pick us up, despite the
                    gunfire.</p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>After we came back to the Vietnamese capital and embassy, reporters questioned us
                    and on television they asked us all kinds of questions. I told the story about
                    the garters. When I returned to DC, I received 10 pairs of used garters from
                    people that had seen our television interviews, who sent garters to me, and the
                    only garter company left in the United States sent me a couple of pairs of new
                    garters. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After your talks with Ambassador Bunker, how did you feel
                        abouwhat we should do in Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: I just had the conviction that this is something the Asian countries had
                    to work out, that we could not serve our interests by war. That we had to find a
                    way to mediate it and negotiate.</p>
                <p>Q: By the time you got on the Foreign Relations Committee, what about your
                    colleagues? Say you came back from Vietnam talking about negotiations. What were
                    you getting from them?</p>
                <p>PERCY: It was a mixed feeling. But on the other hand, I think the decision was
                    made that we would try and negotiate this out. I constantly got more support for
                    an All-Asian Peace Conference.</p>
                <p>Q: One of the problems was it's very difficult to get the other side, basically
                    the North Vietnamese, to negotiate. And also the South Vietnamese, because
                    essentially the North Vietnamese wanted to take over all of the South, and the
                    South Vietnamese didn't want them to. In a way, the way the things ended was the
                    North Vietnamese did take over the South. So, with all negotiation, were you
                    getting the feeling from others that you can't negotiate unless somebody's
                    willing to negotiate with you?</p>
                <p>PERCY: I supported the concept that we should keep American troops out there just
                    to have them available to steer off the North; if we took those out, that would
                    impede any peace efforts. There wouldn't be any North Vietnamese incentive there
                    for them. But an outright, all-out war, I just didn't see that that would have a
                    purpose. The Vietnam War was dividing the United States very badly. It was just
                    so unbelievable. Did I mention to you what happened at Stanford University and
                    the University of Chicago?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, you didn't.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>PERCY: The University of Chicago asked me, as a U.S. senator then but also as a
                    graduate in 1941 and as a trustee of the University of Chicago since 1950, to
                    speak to the students in a large assembly hall. The students had recently seized
                    in anger and violence two university buildings and would not even let the
                    professors in them administer or teach. They were so enraged about the Vietnam
                    War. The president of the U. of C. asked me to speak because they all knew that
                    I had opposed our entry into the war and the students would really listen to me.
                    The meeting went well and they accepted my condemnation of their violent
                    reactions.</p>
                <p>That same year our son, Roger Percy, was graduating from Stanford University.
                    Then the chairman of the board of trustees called me and said, “We want to warn
                    you that there is a lot of difficulty and violence here. We want you to address
                    our students on their violence. If you don't want to speak, we'll
                    understand.”</p>
                <p>I knew I was going out for my son's graduation anyway so why not try to help out.
                    So I told the Stanford chairman and then the president, “I feel even stronger
                    about the fact that I ought to come out and speak, because of what's happening
                    on my own University of Chicago campus as well as yours. So I did go out with my
                    wife, Loraine. In my talk, I mentioned that the students had wrongfully taken
                    the law into their own hands. Here in school, they were studying democracy, they
                    were studying how to live together and how to work together. And they had broken
                    the law by destroying property. I said that future students and faculty would
                    condemn those that participated in violence, including those in this graduating
                    class. I was booed by some of the students; not all of them, but some of
                    them.</p>
                <p>But then, I said, “On the other hand, I do feel and I know why you're so upset
                    because I do feel strongly about this Vietnam War. I think it is splitting the
                    country, just like it's splitting your campus and my campus at the University of
                    Chicago. We have to find a way to stop this violence and stop this war and solve
                    the foreign problems diplomatically. Some of the right-wing parents booed me for
                    saying that I was against the Vietnam War, but others applauded. Afterwards,
                    some of the trustees told me, “We're so glad you did this. We're so glad we
                    decided to go ahead with the assembly because you really laid it in to the
                    students, but they ended up basically with you.” That was a very interesting
                    event that my family will never forget and an exciting graduation for our son,
                    Roger. But one of the things you face when you're in public life, is you have to
                    take positions and you can't always take positions that are popular. You must
                    take a position that you think is absolutely right - that you believe in and can
                    live with the rest of your life.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you find yourself - and we're talking before you went on the Foreign
                    Relations Committee - the Tet Offensive was in 1968 - did you find yourself -
                    was there a particular grouping about the Vietnam War who sided with you within
                    the Senate? I mean, did you coalesce around this idea?</p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>PERCY: I had fine support from some of my colleagues. Senator Ed Brooke was with
                    me, and Senator Howard Baker was with me, my Republican classmates. I had a lot
                    of support for my position, including Democratic Senator Mike Mansfield, a
                    leader of the Senate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I thought we might stop at this point and I'll put where
                        wshould go from here on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Thanks.</p>
                <p>Q: We haven't talked about your view of the Soviet Union. We talked about the
                    time you went into the Senate before you got on the Foreign Relations Committee,
                    '67 until around '71 or '72. So next time we'll talk about your view of the
                    Soviet Union and the Soviet Bloc and also about China.</p>
                <p>PERCY: That would be in what year?</p>
                <p>Q: About '67 to about '72. And then we'll go on to when you went on the Foreign
                    Relations Committee, but we haven't touched that yet. And were there any other
                    issues, foreign relations, that you got at all involved with? For example, were
                    there any problems with Canada when you first came on because I'm sure in
                    Chicago, Chicago looks more towards trade in Canada than anywhere else. Chicago
                    is very oriented towards Canada. Not just Chicago, but all of Illinois.</p>
                <p>PERCY: Oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any particular problems with our relations with
                        Canadthat you came to know?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: No problems, as I had a great relationship with Canada. First of all, I
                    had an office in Canada. I opened an office in 1948 and established a small
                    plant up there for Bell &amp; Howell which was a dramatic thing at that
                    particular time. Then I joined the International Advisory Board of the Bank of
                    Montreal and used to go up there frequently for board meetings and had close
                    relations with Canada during my 18 years in the U.S. Senate.</p>
                <p>Q: When we pick this up the next time, we'll pick up this early period before you
                    were on the Foreign Relations Committee. We've talked about Vietnam, but we'll
                    talk then about China, the Soviet Union, Canada, and were there any particular
                    problems with Western Europe during this particular time? Trade problems or
                    anything dealing with foreign affairs? So we'll pick it up then.</p>
                <p>* * *</p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>Let's follow through on Canada. During the time you were, again, in the Senate,
                    both before you went on the Foreign Relations Committee and until the time you
                    left the Senate, were there any particular areas that you dealt with as a
                    senator concerning Canada that come to mind?</p>
                <p>PERCY: First, again while at Bell &amp; Howell Company, in the early 1950s, we
                    not only built a plant up there, but we gave them preference on products and
                    product lines that were scarce after World War II. My belief that political
                    friendships have tended through the centuries to follow the trade lanes, not
                    only strengthens one country but binds them with another. You see around the
                    world so many adjoining countries that quarrel and fight with their neighboring
                    countries over border problems. India and Pakistan have had terrible
                    difficulties through the years. But to strengthen our relationship, bind
                    ourselves together, and to have Canada be the first country we would ship new
                    scarce products to, at Bell &amp; Howell Company, for instance after the war
                    ended, was the right thing to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I am trying to concentrate on the time you were in
                        thSenate.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: That background kept me constantly connected with Canada. Everything that
                    came up, whether it was a problem with Vietnam, problems with the Soviet Union,
                    problems with China, I worked with the Canadian government always, to be certain
                    we were speaking with one voice. This gave us a more powerful voice, when we
                    could say that Canada, and Mexico, were with us, countries on both sides of us.
                    I replaced Senator Mike Mansfield as chairman of the U.S. and Mexican
                    International Council. That strengthened our position in the United States
                    immensely, when we were speaking and could say that both Canada and Mexico
                    agreed with us on a position that we were taking on a particular international
                    issue.</p>
                <p>Q: Did Prime Minister Trudeau cause any problems? He took a rather strong stand
                    against our role in Vietnam, but also in other things. Of the various Prime
                    Ministers he seemed the prickliest toward the United States. Did you get
                    involved with that at all?</p>
                <p>PERCY: I didn't get particularly involved in it then. I did work with him later
                    in his second term 1980-1984, when he was prime minister and I was chairman of
                    the Foreign Relations Committee when Ronald Reagan was President. I did help
                    Trudeau when economic recession struck Canada in the early 1980s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before you got on the Foreign Relations Committee, what
                        was youview of the Soviet Union particularly, when you were in the
                        Senate?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>PERCY: I looked upon them as a great power to be taken fully into account. If we
                    could not find a way to live with them, it could be an extraordinarily dangerous
                    situation. And for that reason, I went to the Soviet Union, as a matter of fact,
                    with my wife's brother, David Guyer, who was president of Save the Children and
                    also had been an officer with the United Nations. The most important trip I made
                    to the USSR, however, was in November 1980, just after President Reagan was
                    elected.</p>
                <p>Some in the USSR government had a distrust of his predecessor, President Carter.
                    As a matter of fact, they did finally reach an agreement on arms control between
                    the two countries. The President signed it, but he could not get the Senate to
                    ratify it. So I flew over to the Soviet Union, with Bob Galvin, CEO of Motorola,
                    just after Ronald Reagan had been elected President, to see Ambassador Tom
                    Watson, former CEO of IBM. He was a treasured friend, as was Bob Galvin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tom Watson at that time, he was either the ambassador or
                        hibrother was the ambassador to Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: His brother, Dick, had been ambassador to France but Tom waour U.S.
                    ambassador in Moscow at that time.</p>
                <p>So we flew over to see him. That was when Anatoly Dobrynin was the USSR (Russian)
                    ambassador in Washington, DC. The night before we left for Moscow, Prime
                    Minister Kohl of Germany, who was visiting Washington, DC., invited me to have
                    dinner at the German Embassy and I sat next to him, because they knew that I
                    would be the ranking senior member on the committee, and I would be elected the
                    new chairman. He said to me, “You are going to the Soviet Union I understand
                    tomorrow. I am sure you will see the Prime Minister, the President, and others,
                    but you want to be sure that you try to see the Defense Minister Ustinov. None
                    of us have been able to meet with him. He is a tough and very able, and powerful
                    man. Try to see him.”</p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>The Defense Minister was apparently under orders not to meet with any foreign
                    leaders. Even at receptions he would not talk to foreigners. So I called
                    Ambassador Anatoly Dobrynin, who had been a good friend and with whom I'd had
                    many meetings, and said I would be meeting with Gorbachev and some others. But
                    then I said I particularly wanted to meet with Minister of Defense Ustinov while
                    I was there and that I was leaving for Moscow that very day. He said to me, “Why
                    would you want to meet with him? You are going to be the chairman of the Foreign
                    Relations Committee. Why would you want to meet with the Defense Minister? He
                    just doesn't have meetings.” And I said, “Well, I want to meet with him because
                    after all, isn't it a fact you have Russian troops now in Afghanistan, and you
                    are fighting in that country? Isn't that a matter of foreign policy? Besides,
                    Anatoly” (because I did know him well as a friend despite the Cold War
                    atmosphere and he'd been for dinner and lunch in our home), and with a laugh
                    said, “I'm just asking to see whether you've got any clout back in Moscow, to
                    see whether you can get me an appointment with him, because no foreigners can
                    get an appointment with him!”</p>
                <p>So when I landed with Bob Galvin, there was Ambassador Tom Watson at the airport
                    to meet us. And I said, “Do we have any appointments?” And he said, “You know,
                    I've been here six months and have not met but a few official people. This is a
                    Cold War period. I just thought we could go down close to the border of
                    Afghanistan, to talk to people down there to see what is happening there with
                    the USSR invasion.”</p>
                <p>There hadn't been time for Ambassador Anatoly Dobrynin to arrange anything yet, I
                    knew. We went down to the Afghanistan border and stayed for two days. Then we
                    flew back to Moscow and Ambassador Watson's chief of staff was at the airport to
                    meet us and said, “You won't believe this, you have a meeting with Mikhail
                    Gorbachev at 4 o'clock this afternoon, followed by the Foreign Minister. But
                    now, hold your breath. Tomorrow at 10:00 a.m., a meeting had been set with
                    Defense Minister Ustinov. And no one from the U.S. has ever had a meeting with
                    him since the Cold War started!”</p>
                <p>So we did have a meeting with Defense Minister Ustinov. We discussed the fact
                    that heretofore, no agreement on arms control had been ratified by the U.S.
                    Senate under President Carter. But in the recent election, Reagan had carried 44
                    states and Carter only six states and DC. I convinced him that with Ronald
                    Reagan now President, that whatever arms-control agreement he agreed to sign,
                    President Reagan was tough-minded and could carry it much better with Congress
                    to passage. I assured Defense Minister Ustinov that as the new chairman of the
                    Foreign Relations Committee, I would be able to see to it that whatever he
                    agreed to, that whatever he negotiated with President Reagan, would be confirmed
                    by the Senate and would become law. When I returned to Washington, DC, I
                    reported fully to President Reagan and to the Foreign Relations Committee about
                    our meetings.</p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>And, as a matter of fact, it did work out that way. The Defense Minister pushed
                    forward to get another agreement and they were able to visit with President
                    Reagan, deal with him and got along well with him, and we got an outstanding
                    agreement. We never ratified SALT II. Reagan said he would abide by it, as did
                    the Soviets. The next treaty we negotiated was START I, which was ratified later
                    (possibly as late as early Bush) without any problems. So, in this case, a
                    so-called hard-liner conservative like President Ronald Reagan was the one who
                    was better able to deal with this difficult situation.</p>
                <p>Going back to the importance of Afghanistan, in late 1979 and early 1980 Russia
                    invaded Afghanistan with thousands of troops to battle against the so-called
                    freedom fighters. The fighting continued until the mid-1980s. The Russians and
                    Afghan government forces bombed many villages. Large numbers of villagers were
                    forced to flee. Many moved to neighboring Pakistan.</p>
                <p>Q: This was often the case. Nixon going to China. Just very recently Ariel Sharon
                    of Israel being involved in peace negotiating with the Palestinians in the last
                    week. You sometimes need somebody with credibility with the most difficult and
                    obstinate side in order to get something done.</p>
                <p>During the time you were in the Senate, did the Afghan invasion, which was in
                    December 1979, and lasted for four or five years, did that make quite a
                    difference in how we approached the Soviet Union?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Very much so. It was a very devastating thing.</p>
                <p>Q: I would imagine that many people in the Senate who had hoped that maybe we
                    could do some business with the Soviets, would have found that this sort of
                    ended that for awhile.</p>
                <p>PERCY: You are right.</p>
                <p>Q: How about with China? What was your feeling towards China? We had opened
                    relations under Nixon with China. During the time that you were in the Senate,
                    was that met with approval, basically, within the Senate?</p>
                <p>PERCY: When President Nixon went over there, he and Henry Kissinger opened things
                    up. During my 1966 campaign I focused on this as one of the major issues with my
                    opponent, Paul Douglas, who had formed an organization called “A Million
                    Americans to Keep Red China out of the United Nations.” To keep China out of the
                    United Nations, the largest nation on earth, was just nonsense. Now, post-war,
                    we want a new kind of world, one of peace and prosperity and progress for
                    nations. But you shouldn't keep huge China out of the UN. I fought him on that
                    and it was one of the major issues that we had.</p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>I think I told you the story about when the Chinese ambassador, Han Sue, came to
                    see me and asked if I would select a group of senators and congressmen to come
                    over for the first visit that senators and House members would make as guests of
                    the Republic of China, and said we could also bring our spouses. I agreed and
                    first selected Senator Claiborne Pell, and Senator Jack Javits, who ranked over
                    me in seniority and whom I greatly admired. After we had selected our group, I
                    talked to the White House chief of staff, who said he would talk to the
                    President and they would think about helping us in any way they could.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Han Sue said to me that China wanted me to be chairman of the group. I
                    said I couldn't be chairman because Senator Jack Javits had more seniority than
                    I had and so he should be the chairman of the group. The ambassador said no,
                    that they were hosting it and I had seniority by their rules because I had, for
                    longer than anyone in the Senate, argued that there should be good relations
                    between China and the United States and I had beat “that bad man” Senator Paul
                    Douglas. I said that he was not a bad man, but a good man and I liked him. He
                    said, “No, he is a bad man because he had formed this organization called a
                    Million Americans to Keep Red China out of the United Nations, and you
                    fortunately beat him. So we want you to be the chairman.”</p>
                <p>I told this to all the other members of our group at an impromptu meeting, and
                    said I thought maybe I could be a vice chairman. They said I should start
                    serious negotiating as chairman, and Senators Javits and Pell could be vice
                    chairmen, as the Chinese were the hosts of our visit, and wanted me to be
                    chairman.The White House then said they would provide us an airplane to fly us
                    over and fly us back. It would be a two-week visit, we could take our wives,
                    too, as there would be plenty of room on the plane. So we went and it was a
                    fabulous trip that we made over there. The Chinese couldn't have been nicer and
                    it brought our relationships much closer together.</p>
                <p>Q: One of the very hot issues that remain with us today is birth control,
                    particularly abortion. The Chinese are a quarter of the world's population, so
                    obviously birth control and abortion are major issues. Did this come up at
                    all?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Oh, yes, I was a pro-choice senator. I urged the Chinese to do whatever
                    was necessary to control population growth so that the food they were producing
                    would be adequate. I recommended very strongly that birth control practices be
                    used.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this a hard position to maintain within the Republican
                        Partduring most of your time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: It was. I loved Italy and went there many times, but at that time
                    Catholicism was very much opposed to birth control. Now Italy is one of the few
                    countries in the world with a declining population. They have changed, with a
                    lower number of children per family.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Knowing the Italians, I think, probably abstinence is not
                        thpreferred method.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>With China, how did the Chinese Embassy work with the Senate? You know, some
                    countries understand working with Congress, and some don't. I was wondering with
                    China?</p>
                <p>PERCY: They couldn't have been better. While in the Senate every ambassador had
                    been a good friend of mine. You know, a lot of the embassies just had the
                    feeling you should come to them. The Chinese many times came over to see me. We
                    still continue going to the Chinese embassy, as Loraine and I have good
                    friendships there.</p>
                <p>Where I differed with them was Taiwan.</p>
                <p>Q: I was trying to ask, on Taiwan, because the Taiwan representation, which is
                    now the American Institute Taiwan, and they have a trade representative, how did
                    that work during the time you were in the Senate?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Well, I took the position that we wanted peace out there in Asia. Our
                    country had the right to declare independence from Great Britain in 1776. The
                    great feud that we had originally with Great Britain, we worked out, and I think
                    that Taiwan can some day work this out with China and still maintain a good
                    relationship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But did you find that the Taiwan representatives were
                        prettaggressive in their dealings with the Senate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Not too much, not too aggressive. I didn't feel any reapressure from them
                    at all.</p>
                <p>Q: Particularly when you were on the Foreign Relations Committee, I know for
                    example that Chicago is the second largest Polish city in the world, next to
                    Warsaw, and this is probably true. I don't know about German Americans, but I
                    assume with Czech Americans, did you find representing Illinois, which has a
                    very large, particularly Central European population, second and third
                    generation, did you find that this was something you had to keep in mind all the
                    time?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Oh, yes, of course. After all, my father's family originally came from
                    England; my mother's came from Germany. My grandmother, when I was three years
                    old, came over from Germany and lived with us for the rest of her life. So I
                    quite naturally felt somewhat close to the UK and Germany and understood the
                    loyalty that many Americans had to their families' native countries.</p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>Yes, I did have many Czech and especially Italian and Polish American friends and
                    they were very helpful to me in my political campaigns. When I was in the Senate
                    and Pope John Paul II first flew to the United States, people were astounded
                    that he didn't fly to New York City or Washington, DC, first as he hadn't been
                    to either during his life. He did come to Chicago first as I previously
                    mentioned.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, now, did you find during the time you were in the Senate, Poland was
                    working hard under Lech Walesa and others to free itself from the Soviet Bloc?
                    Did you find that you were getting involved in this process?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Very much so, and when I did go over with my brother-in-law, David Guyer,
                    we went first to Poland and then Russia, and they knew that we had just been in
                    Poland. But I simply said to them as strongly as I could, that they had to have
                    and should work out an agreement, an arrangement with them, and I began urging
                    that they start trading with Poland and have an intermix of the two
                    economies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there groups within Chicago, Polish-American groups,
                        thawere pressing you to be more anti-Soviet at all or did that come up?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: I didn't have that feeling. They knew that I had publicly taken positions
                    with respect to the Soviet Union. During the 1966 campaign, for instance, my
                    position against Douglas on the Soviet Union and China was well known. But they
                    didn't try to push me too hard.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Talking about the Soviet Union, Ambassador Anatoly
                        Dobrynin was quite a fixture in Washington, the Soviet ambassador, for
                        twenty years or so. Did he work the Senate? I mean, was he up on the Hill,
                        entertaining, meeting, discussing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Richard Nixon, when he became President, said to me one day, “I know that
                    you and Ambassador Dobrynin are good friends, I know that you have meetings, I
                    understand, and lunch together at least every month or every other month. You
                    rotate back and forth between his Embassy and your house.” He then said, “Could
                    you have him over,” and this is now summertime, “Could you have him over and
                    just talk in the garden, and have lunch in the garden?” He knew my house.</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, what if it rains? Why do you want him in the garden?” And he said,
                    “Well, we're concerned they feel we're taping everything they do through the
                    CIA, and I want him to be absolutely free from any concern about that. He only
                    would be in your garden. Then I want you to find out from him what it is that we
                    need to do to find a way for the U.S. and the USSR to live and work
                    together.”</p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>So I invited Anatoly Dobrynin and we had a wonderful conversation in the garden.
                    He talked about the things that were necessary to bring us together. That led to
                    some very definite agreements. But, as I say, it was very hard to get
                    ratification by the Senate of any treaties or agreements with the USSR at that
                    time. That changed when Ronald Reagan took office as President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about Henry Kissinger during the Nixon
                        Administration? Wahe sort of difficult to work with from the senatorial
                        side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: No, not at all, because Henry Kissinger and I were very good friends. We
                    had worked together on many projects. We had a very good working relationship,
                    very friendly, and we saw eye-to-eye on many things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, during the time he was National Security Advisor did
                        you have many informal meetings and all, keeping the Senate well
                        informed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Yes. As a matter of fact, you see, I got to know him through David
                    Rockefeller. He was a top staff officer for Nelson Rockefeller, and that's when
                    I started, really started, a close working relationship with him. Henry
                    Kissinger did a lot in opening up our relationship with China.</p>
                <p>Q: Oh, yes, oh, yes, he was the key person. What about when the Carter
                    Administration came in '77, to the beginning of '81. Did you find this a
                    difficult Administration to work with?</p>
                <p>PERCY: President Carter and I got along wonderfully well then, and that
                    relationship continued after he left office. I arranged for him to have a book
                    signing in a bookstore, just a half a block from my first private office after I
                    left the Senate, in Washington, DC. It was on the corner of H and 19th Street in
                    NW, Washington, DC. He came and signed all books being bought and then gave me
                    an autographed one also. We kept up our good relationship. He was always working
                    for peace, prosperity, and progress as well.</p>
                <p>Q: During the Carter Administration, one of his major concerns was the Panama
                    Canal, coming up with a Panama Canal Treaty which was really far out and for the
                    most part, particularly the more Conservative Republicans, but also some
                    Democrats, were quite opposed to this. How were you on the Panama Canal?</p>
                <p>PERCY: I was in the leadership working to have an agreement with them. I felt
                    that what we needed, and what they needed, were compatible, and we could work
                    that out. And I really worked hard on it and I led the fight to get the Treaty
                    approved as it was.</p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>Q: You must have had some real difficulties with your colleagues on that.</p>
                <p>PERCY: Yes, I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were some of the people you had more problems
                        with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Oh, even my seatmate for years, Senator Strom Thurmond. But we got along
                    very well, despite some differences, such as the Panama Canal treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about with Israel? The Camp David Accords, or even
                        prior tthat. What had been your relationship with Israel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: The relationship was very close for many, many years. I did receive from
                    Jewish-American Associations several awards. Dr. Robert Goldwin, who is still a
                    dear friend, was my long-time special tutor for me on the Great Books. Scott
                    Cohen was also a Jewish friend and I appointed him chairman of the Foreign
                    Relations Committee staff. He later went with me on a large Middle East peace
                    tour that I headed for the Pax Foundation of Washington, DC. Because I did have
                    a good relationship with the Soviet Union, as Israel was trying to expand its
                    population, I negotiated immigration rights for tens of thousands of Russian
                    Jews that lived in the Soviet Union to get out of the country and to be able to
                    migrate to Israel for permanent living.</p>
                <p>But when Ronald Reagan became President, Israel used our arms that we had given
                    them for their own protection, to invade parts of Lebanon and Syria - they used
                    our arms to seize land from a sovereign country and take it away from them, such
                    as Lebanon. I said to Israel at the time, “It was easy for you to get into
                    Lebanon, but it will be very hard for you to get out.” And AIPAC, Israel's
                    American lobbying group, went after me hard on that issue. Also AIPAC fought
                    President Reagan and me on our right to sell AWACS intelligence planes to Saudi
                    Arabia. AIPAC just vigorously opposed this as did the Israel government oppose
                    it. President Reagan was very distressed about this situation.</p>
                <p>When Israeli Prime Minister Begin came to Washington, DC. I hosted him at lunch
                    in the Foreign Relations Committee room with 20 Senate members and staff. After
                    lunch finished I said, “Now we'll take time for questions. As chairman, I'll ask
                    the first question of you. Let me put it this way, setting aside the AWACS
                    question and the desire of Saudi Arabia to buy these planes from us, putting
                    that aside, I want to ask you another question. Don't you feel it best for the
                    United States to have a good strong trade relationship with Arab countries,
                    because that then gives us much more leverage to work with Arab countries to
                    support your independence and well-being and, I hope, eventually your trade with
                    them?” Prime Minister Begin said, “Oh, Mr. Chairman, you mentioned AWACS. Let me
                    talk...”</p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                <p>I said, “Now just a minute, Prime Minister, I said, besides that.” He said, “Oh,
                    no, you mentioned AWACS.” Begin then just tore in on reasons why the United
                    States shouldn't sell AWACS to Saudi Arabia, as he knew President Ronald Reagan
                    wanted to do.</p>
                <p>Then Senator Pell asked a question that had nothing to do with AWACS, he didn't
                    even mention it, and Begin answered more on AWACS. The next question came to
                    Senator Howard Baker, who was Minority Leader but second to me in seniority, but
                    still had decided to serve on one committee, the Foreign Relations Committee. He
                    said, “Mr. Chairman, no matter what question we ask, the Prime Minister is going
                    to answer on AWACS. Why don't we just let him get it off his chest, and then we
                    are finished with it, and we can get on to other issues?” So, he did continue on
                    AWACS and spoke at great length condemning our proposed sale of AWACS planes to
                    Saudi Arabia.</p>
                <p>I called up President Reagan afterwards and told him about that. I said, “You are
                    going to see Prime Minister Begin soon, I just want you to know what he did. He
                    had promised you he wouldn't.” President Reagan confirmed that he [Begin] would
                    not take a position while he was here as our guest against this particular AWACS
                    plane sale.”</p>
                <p>Well, President Reagan was really angry, and he then started having meetings with
                    the key senators, with me present. We had eight different meetings, because
                    there was a bill coming soon in the Senate authorizing the AWACS sale by the USA
                    to Saudi Arabia. We had the vote in the Senate, and we won, but by just two
                    votes. That is the only time that AIPAC, the Israel lobby, has ever been
                    defeated on the floor of the Senate that I know of. President Reagan was just
                    thrilled with the vote, that we had saved the right to sell the intelligence
                    planes toSaudi Arabia that otherwise would have been sold to them by the UK or
                    Germany. They didn't invite me for the Israeli National Day celebration at the
                    embassy for a number of years after that vote.</p>
                <p>A California wealthy activist, Michael Goland, a trustee of AIPAC, illegally
                    spent $1.6 million in my 1984 reelection campaign against me, when my own
                    Illinois citizens, as well as anyone else, were limited by law to $1,000 each.
                    Two years later, they found him guilty, and fined him $5,000! Imagine that! But
                    that was a year and a half after the 1984 election, which I lost.</p>
                <p>Now, however, in recent years, the Israeli ambassador has thoughtfully invited me
                    each year to their National Day celebration. When he took me around the first
                    year to greet other guests, many people would say to me, “You were so right
                    about these two issues. Invading Lebanon, we are still stuck there, and the
                    AWACS intelligence planes are what saved Israel from President Saddam Hussein of
                    Iraq, who was not intending to just go into Kuwait. One man said, “Like
                    Nebuchanezzar 25 hundred years ago, he intended to go in and take over what is
                    now Kuwait, Saudi Arabia, and then Oman, and they would have controlled 60
                    percent of all the world's oil resources.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, we're talking about 1989, '90, during the Gulf
                        War.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Right, the Gulf War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Within your constituency did you find that your
                        Jewisconstituents pretty well followed the line of AIPAC?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Very much so. However, some came out against AIPAC and voted and worked
                    for me. AIPAC was the strongest, most influential lobby in the United States at
                    the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now how did you find it within the Senate, was
                        AIPAparticularly powerful?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Very powerful.</p>
                <p>Q: But in certain areas. I would imagine New York and Florida and California? How
                    was one able to put together a coalition to vote for the AWACS system?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Well, we just did it. President Reagan and I sat down with these senators
                    and convinced them how important it was to the safety of the United States that
                    we sell the AWACS plane to Saudi Arabia. Our requirement was, as we told them,
                    that they could not fly those planes without one USA intelligence person on
                    board so we would be able to see everything that was happening, whereas the
                    competition against us, both German and British firms, who were trying to sell
                    them similar planes, had no such requirement. They used the argument, that they
                    could have our planes and it was up to them what they did with them. But on the
                    other hand, the AWACS were better intelligence planes, and enabled them to
                    better protect themselves, and other Arab countries, even more. So they bought
                    the U.S. AWACS.</p>
                <p>Q: This is for the historical record, the AWACS is an airborne radar control
                    system, very sophisticated, which allowed airborne radar to peer into countries
                    such as Iraq without penetrating air space.</p>
                <p>Did you feel, too, that the way Begin conducted himself when he came to visit
                    before this in a way helped your cause because he was so difficult to deal with
                    in the Senate?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Once we confirmed we were going to do defense matters in the interest of
                    the United States, we decided that no other country could force us into a
                    position where we do things contrary to our own national interest.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying once you had gotten it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Again, I was chairman of the PAX Foundation Commission, that went over to
                    the Middle East, and we selected a commission of former members of Congress and
                    leaders knowledgeable in the Middle East, some key Arab-Americans, and there
                    were nine prominent Jews on it, including a rabbi from Chicago and Scott Cohen.
                    It was not a fact-finding trip. Everyone was well aware of what was happening in
                    the Middle East and were experts in it. But everyone had to agree that they felt
                    that a Palestinian State, a homeland for Palestine, was essential for peace in
                    the Middle East. And the nine Jews in the group agreed to that, including the
                    rabbi, as did my Chief of Staff of the Foreign Relations Committee, Scott Cohen.
                    Our aim was to meet with the heads of state for a number of Mid-East countries.
                    We had 42 members of our group. The first country we planned to stop at was
                    Syria and that was where we had expected trouble. President Assad said he would
                    be happy to meet with me again and even Congressman John Anderson who was our
                    vice chairman, but not with the whole group. He had never met with a whole group
                    of foreign visitors, he said. I told him that this would set a bad precedent for
                    the other countries where we planned on meeting with the heads of state with the
                    entire group. I also said that if he had enjoyed our own previous meetings, I
                    assured him that he would learn and enjoy more meeting with the group. He
                    finally did agree to meet with all of us, and after 45 minutes I suggested to
                    the Foreign Minister that we could end the meeting then. The Foreign Minister
                    talked to President Assad and then came back to me and said that I shouldn't end
                    it yet because he was enjoying the meeting and he was learning a lot.</p>
                <p>The next day the newspapers noted how unusual it was for President Assad to have
                    such a large meeting. The key note of our discussion was the Palestinian-Israel
                    relationship, a subject of great importance to him.</p>
                <p>It was just a wonderful experience that we had with him. And that was the first
                    meeting of our PAX Foundation trip, which set a pattern for our subsequent
                    meetings with the chiefs of state and foreign ministers of Israel and Saudi
                    Arabia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was when, after you had left the Senate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Oh, yes, in 1985 shortly after I'd left the Senate.</p>
                <p>Q: Within your Jewish constituency, your statements about Lebanon, about the
                    invasion of Lebanon, this was not very popular with a fairly broad sweep of
                    Jewish Americans. I mean, did you find that this was as much of a problem as
                    AWACS, as far as your stand?</p>
                <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                <p>PERCY: Well there were two things they hit me on at AIPAC. The first was my
                    criticism of Israel for using arms supplied by us to Israel not only for their
                    own defense, but using them to invade and occupy parts of the sovereign
                    countries of Lebanon and Syria. Second was supporting President Reagan's desire
                    for Congress to approve the sale of AWACS planes to Saudi Arabia. Of course, I
                    should have given AIPAC a present afterwards because I have greatly enjoyed my
                    life after the Senate. Eighteen years was enough time for me there. And my wife
                    didn't want me to run again, anyway, so she was just as pleased as could be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The election you lost was when? PERCY: November,
                        1984.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your opponent?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Paul Simon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now did he take a strong pro-Israeli stand?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Oh, yes. He was elected because of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find yourself getting pushed into a corner on
                        Israel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Yes, it was a controlling issue. But also, I must say, I wouldn't give
                    them full credit for defeating me. [For further information, please consult
                    “They Dare to Speak Out,” Paul Findley, Chicago Review Press, Inc., 1989.]</p>
                <p>I was forced into a primary election first by right-wing Republicans. I won the
                    primary easily, but many members of the right-wing of the Illinois Republican
                    Party sat on their hands during my November 1984 election. Many of them didn't
                    want to see me re-elected because they had opposed me in the primary. But in
                    consequence they elected then a Democrat who was far more liberal. I was
                    moderate; he was a real liberal, but a great one! The combination of Israel and
                    AIPAC fighting against me, and all that money from Michael Goland coming in
                    against me, that was the thing that did it. But I have enjoyed greatly my life
                    after the Senate and it has all worked out for the best.</p>
                <p>Paul Simon and I have remained friends and, in fact, we wrote an article together
                    in 1999 that supported the USA paying its agreed upon dues to the United
                    Nations. The article ran in The Christian Science Monitor, a worldwide
                    newspaper, and was placed in The Congressional Record by a senator. [We have
                    also both become trustees of a commission on U.S. policy towards Colombia in
                    March 2001, a Republican and a Democrat.]</p>
                <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                <p>Q: Did you find in your trips to Israel and all, did you find that AIPAC was more
                    right- wing Israeli, than maybe Israeli public opinion in Israel itself?</p>
                <p>PERCY: I think so. They were extremists. I found much more moderate feelings
                    inside Israel. Even when I took the PAX trip, I met with Prime Minister Peres
                    and we had good meetings with him, and they knew that we supported a Palestinian
                    homeland strongly. The Palestinians have been there, their ancestors have been
                    there, as long as the Israelis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There is going to be a Palestinian State?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: I'm sure there is.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But it's very difficult to bring certain elements to
                        accept this.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>[PERCY: On August 4, 1999 The Washington Times ran an article that I wrote on
                    Peace, Prosperity, and Progress in the Middle East. That article answers your
                    question. Let's put it in this record now. It was inserted in The Congressional
                    Record also.</p>
                <p>Netanyahu was a great disappointment to me. I noted that he was a student in this
                    country, and upon leaving the Senate I headed the Institute of International
                    Education for five years, covering all foreign students in this country and all
                    American students who go abroad. I have found that when they are students here,
                    just like a majority of the King of Saudi Arabia's cabinet graduated, got their
                    Ph.D. from universities in this country, that they understand our country so
                    much better. Actually the relationship with Israel, they understand that much
                    better. I originally thought with Netanyahu there would be such understanding.
                    Not only that, he was Israeli ambassador in New York to the United Nations. But
                    he was very extreme. And I was terribly disappointed in the way he approached
                    the peace process. I was more hopeful of his successor, Prime Minister
                    Barak.]</p>
                <p>Q: It is a very difficult time. Tell me, within the Foreign Relations Committee.
                    What was your impression of the dynamics? How important was the minority and
                    majority staff there?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Both majority and minority were very important. Sometimes I had problems,
                    however, with colleagues like Jesse Helms. But we had a good personal
                    relationship, and we were friendly with each other, but on the other hand we had
                    a lot of different ideas and approaches.</p>
                <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                <p>Q: Well, with Jesse Helms, he is the chairman of the Foreign Relations Committee
                    now, and has been a very difficult person on foreign relations. I mean, he seems
                    to be against most things. What was your impression of, particularly when you
                    were dealing with him, where was he coming from? Was this just good politics or
                    did this come from within inside him?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Well, we got along fine. After all, he is from North Carolina and my
                    mother lived down there and I bought a house there for her and visited
                    frequently. My sister, Doris Straus, and her husband, Bob, live down there. So I
                    had some close ties with his state. He invited me back to a committee lunch
                    meeting after I left the Senate, when the Dalai Lama was there. Jesse was a
                    little stunned, I think, when I walked in the room a few minutes late. I had
                    told him I would be a little late, as I had another meeting. But the Dalai Lama
                    just stood right up when I came in, and came over and hugged me because we had
                    such a good long relationship.</p>
                <p>Q: What did you think was the source of Jesse Helms' attitude toward,
                    essentially, foreign affairs, which is very much in a way staying out of getting
                    too involved and then a certain willingness to accept rather right-wing type
                    people abroad?</p>
                <p>PERCY: Well, Howard Baker, when he became Minority Leader, resigned from a couple
                    of committees because he felt he should spend his time on the leadership. But he
                    stayed, he told me personally, he stayed on the Foreign Relations Committee and
                    he said he would only come to the meetings when I asked him to come to the
                    meetings. When I thought, for instance, I might have an issue with Jesse Helms,
                    for instance, that I might have trouble with, he would come and reason with him
                    also. So he did that, the whole time I was chairman. And Jesse Helms and I got
                    along fine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was mainly to keep Jesse Helms from getting too much
                        control?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: I suppose that's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why was Jesse Helms so almost anti-international?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: I don't know of any background to cause that. But we had some fun
                    together, too, because I was very anti-tobacco. I saw my father die too early of
                    it. He died at 70, 37 years ahead of my mother. Mother never smoked a cigarette
                    in her life and Dad smoked for many years before he finally was able to stop.
                    She lived to be 102. Senator Jesse Helms' state, North Carolina, was a big
                    producer of tobacco. Jesse Helms and I'd walk down the Senate hall together to
                    vote. (That was in the days when people could smoke in the hallways and in the
                    rooms.) And he'd see someone standing there smoking and he'd go up and he'd bow
                    his head to them and say, “I thank you for smoking.” And I would usually make
                    some comment back like, “I wish you wouldn't, if you want to live longer!”</p>
                <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                <p>Q: There may be something we haven't covered. I'll have this transcribed and if
                    there is anything more you feel we should discuss, we'll do it.</p>
                <p>PERCY: Wonderful. May I add: I have always been very religious in outlook. In my
                    original family, we had a Bible lesson every morning. We started and ended each
                    day with prayer. And my wife, Loraine, and I still do, and have for the past
                    [more than] 50 years of our marriage.</p>
                <p>For example, this morning, when I started reading The Bible and Science and
                    Health with Key to the Scriptures by Mary Baker Eddy, our little dog, “Candy,” a
                    tiny dog, a lovely dog, again jumped up on my wife's lap. Loraine listens while
                    I read the Bible and this leaves her hands free while she listens. So she pets
                    the dog around his ears and so forth. But I think Candy jumps up into her lap in
                    the early morning because Candy loves to hear the Bible stories about Jesus and
                    his disciples! [Laughter] We end by saying, “This is the Day the Lord hath made.
                    Let us rejoice and be glad in it.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Great. Well, thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PERCY: Okay.</p>
                <p>[Note: Additional materials provided by Senator Percy on his life and career are
                    available at the offices of The Association for Diplomatic Studies and
                    Training.]</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
