<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000695">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Ralph E. Lindstrom </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>RALPH E. LINDSTROM</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: October 28, 1994</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is an interview with Ralph E. Lindstrom, and it is
                        being done on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training,
                        and I'm Charles Stuart Kennedy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Ralph, can you tell me when and where you were born and a little about your
                    family?</p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I was born in 1925 in Anoka, Minnesota. Anoka is a small city, older
                    than Minneapolis, located at the junction of the Mississippi and Rum Rivers. I
                    went to grade school in Anoka and I graduated from the Anoka high school in
                    1943.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did your father and mother come from?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: My father was actually born in Sweden, and was not able to finish high
                    school because he had to support his parents and went into business in a small
                    supermarket business. My mother was also of Swedish extraction but born in this
                    country, and had become a nurse and graduated from high school in
                    Minneapolis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went to high school in Anoka, is that right? What was
                        the high school like there at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It was a very excellent school, and the standards were very much
                    comparable to those, as I learned later, in many private schools in terms of
                    really focusing on the a-b-cs, grammar, Latin, and all that sort of thing, and
                    had some excellent teachers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You graduated in...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: 1943.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which was...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: ...during the war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So that put you right in line for the draft. Did you get
                        into the military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes. I was drafted...actually I ended up volunteering for the Army and
                    served there for about one year. I thought I was going to go to the ASTP
                    training program but that was disbanded when I was at Ft. Benning so I was sent
                    to a regular...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ASTP was sort of a training program and all of a sudden
                        they ran out infantry men.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: That's right, and it's the same thing or equivalent to the Navy's B-12
                    program which was not disbanded but I had somewhat weak eyes and couldn't
                    qualify for the Navy. Then just as I was going to go to Boston University, so I
                    thought, they told us that the program was being disbanded, and I ended up in
                    Camp Livingston, Louisiana in a regular Army infantry division. Then about that
                    time I think I transferred to California and about that time I had taken an
                    entrance exam for the service academies. And I passed this exam, and I got a
                    telegram from my congressman who said, “You have a first alternate appointment
                    to go into the Navy, and you can leave the Army if you want to.” This was in the
                    middle of the war, so I did that and went to Bainbridge, Maryland when the Navy
                    had a Naval Academy Prep School. I finished that and took the exams successfully
                    but the principal got in; I was the first alternate. Then I was assigned to
                    regular duty in the Navy for about a year and a half, and I ended up in
                    Washington, D.C., of all places, in the Office of Naval Intelligence. We were
                    screening captured German documents, mainly the B-1 and B-2 missile
                    programs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These are rocket missiles. So you did that until
                        when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Until the summer of 1946 when I got accepted in Harvard and I went
                    directly up to Harvard from Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had four years at Harvard?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You graduated in 1950. What were you majoring in at
                        Harvard?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I was majoring in government, political science as they call it in
                    most places.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were they teaching you at Harvard? Was there any
                        thrust to the government courses?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No particular thrust. You could pretty much do what you wanted. I was
                    an honors candidate and did write a dissertation on Annamite Nationalism, or
                    Vietnamese Nationalism, I guess as we would call it today. They had some
                    interesting papers in Widener Library there during the period of World War II,
                    when we were actually helping Ho Chi Minh under Roosevelt's direction, rather
                    than the Vichy French. There were quite a few things on Ho Chi Minh who still to
                    this day remains a fairly enigmatic figure. So I wrote really basically a
                    combination biography of him, and the movement such as we knew it, and concluded
                    that it was primarily a movement for national independence. I remember one of my
                    conclusions, this was back in 1950, was that the last thing the United States
                    should do was get into a war of attempting to supplant the French. It was mainly
                    a war for independence, rather than a war against communism purely and simply,
                    although Ho Chi Minh was obviously a communist.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in that class that came in in '46. I guess it was
                        mostly veterans and very serious about getting ahead.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I'd say generally yes. We were somewhat overcrowded and it was the
                    largest class Harvard had ever had and has ever had since then, I think. And at
                    that time women were not integrated fully into it. They were still all over in
                    Radcliffe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you heard about the State Department, while you were
                        in the government course, or was this on your radar at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I think I had first gotten interested in it when I met Hubert Humphrey
                    back in Minnesota. I had actually gone to McAllister College for about three
                    months or so while I was recuperating from a hernia operation before I went into
                    the Army. And I went with him up to an international conference in Manitoba in
                    Winnipeg and it was really my first taste of foreign affairs, and it completely
                    changed me. Up until then I was thinking about being a major in some scientific
                    subject or mathematics. Then I had two and a half years in which to think about
                    this further while I was in the military, and by then I had concluded that I'd
                    like to go into the foreign affairs field.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you know of anybody during this time while you were at
                        Harvard, or met anybody in the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, but Harvard is a very large place. They did send a team up there
                    to talk to us a couple of times, that sort of thing, and some of my classmates
                    did end up in the Foreign Service. People like Bill Harrop, I think he was in my
                    class, but we didn't know each other.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was just thinking. I went to Williams and I can't recall
                        anybody from the Foreign Service coming by but we had a big contingent for
                        the CIA. I didn't go in but I made noises about going into the CIA, but it
                        was the same period. When you graduated in 1950, what were you up to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: In those days, as you may recall, one had to meet the language
                    requirement before you could pass the Foreign Service exam. By then I was
                    married and my wife was working in Cambridge in the Visiting Nurse's Association
                    and we decided to go to France on our own. Of course, the GI Bill was quite
                    liberal in those days so we took a ship over to France and first I was going to
                    study at ___ ___ and then I soon found out that the French universities were not
                    very much hands-on and gave rather cold lectures, and I further calculated that
                    I could use my GI Bill for semi-individual lessons in both French and Russian,
                    which I did do at the Berlitz school, of all places. My French got to a very
                    good fluency, and my Russian almost to passing level, and about time, or a year
                    or so later, I decided to take the exams and study in the American Library in
                    Paris on things I felt weak on, and did succeed in passing it. And one other
                    member of my class was also in Paris, Fred Chapin. We went back on the same
                    ship, the America, and took the oral exams over at the Walker Johnson building
                    the same morning, and both passed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The exam you took was the old three and a half day exam,
                        was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes. Then I passed it orally in French, but not quite in Russian. That
                    didn't really matter at that time to get into the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you recall your oral exam at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, I do, some parts of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were they probing for?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: The heaviest probing in my case was my knowledge, or lack of it, of
                    American history. I still remember one of the members of the board admonishing
                    me to become more familiar with American history. I had taken, as I recall,
                    probably only one major course in American history. But in other words, they
                    were probing just to see what kind of a person you were and how nervous you were
                    or not, I guess. So anyway then I went through the A-100 course for three
                    months. We were a group of about 18, including two women. Our assignments
                    finally came out at the end, we all got foreign assignments, and my assignment
                    was to Kabul, Afghanistan, which was a pretty remote place in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was in '52, in the middle of the Korean War. Can you
                        talk a bit about the role of the United States, and the Soviet Union at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: When I was still at Harvard there was at least some degree of interest
                    in international relations, but I think, again going back to that post-war
                    class, people were concentrating more on getting their education, and getting
                    through with it as quickly as they could. I did go to a couple of meetings of
                    the Harvard Liberal Union which turned me off completely. It was dominated by a
                    group of young communists types who were always voting for resolutions to do
                    this, that and the other thing, and it did not appeal to me at all. It wasn't an
                    intellectual discussion of politics or anything like that which you could have
                    with a faculty member or adviser. And even to our initial Foreign Service class,
                    again I don't really think that we were that aware of international relations
                    yet at the top of our agenda. Maybe we should have been.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a feeling that the Soviet Union was the enemy by
                        that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Oh, I think quite clearly by that time. Then there is another factor.
                    Bear in mind this was during the McCarthy period, and I think there was a lot of
                    concern about that sort of thing, and whether we wanted to go into an
                    organization. It didn't bother me that much, but certainly McCarthyism was
                    overhanging that period to some degree, with jokes about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there the feeling, particularly because of what was
                        happening to what was called the China hands, that you better watch your
                        step?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Oh, absolutely yes. It depended on the individual, but about the
                    closest thing I'd come to anything like that was my going to the Harvard Liberal
                    Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I must say at that time you had a lot of people coming out
                        and they were trying things on for size, and the young, at least
                        communist-leaning students, were exercising power, but they were turning an
                        awful lot of people off. This didn't take a real hold in the United
                        States.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I remember in my very first year at Harvard, there was an instructor
                    in English, I think it was, and our assignment was to write essays on whatever
                    subject we chose, and while I had been in the Army I'd taken to reading some of
                    the sort of left-wing publications, and anyway the emphasis was sort of the
                    popular thing to do as a young person, I thought. And I remember on one of my
                    essays I had a conference with my instructor and he said, and this sort of
                    shocked me because I thought everybody would be very liberal minded at a place
                    like Harvard, and he said to me, “Somebody must have given you a real left-wing
                    brain washing.” I can't remember exactly what it was I'd said in my paper. So
                    that sort of woke me up a little bit. There were other ways of looking at things
                    than just purely from a left-wing point of view.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went out to Kabul where you served from '52 to '54.
                        What was the situation in Afghanistan at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It is, of course, a very poor country and I had never seen poverty
                    like that up close before in my life. It's a country which still is, and always
                    has been, caught in between other major powers and crossroads of invasion, and
                    it had borrowed heavily from their neighbors. Their major political concern
                    during the period I was there was with Pakistan, and Pakistan's seeming efforts
                    to incorporate under their control part of Afghanistan which they referred to as
                    Pushtunistan. We were, on the other hand, under the direction of John Foster
                    Dulles, much more inclined to think about the Soviet threat. At that time we
                    were putting CENTO together, Pakistan, Iran and Turkey. And the Afghans felt
                    increasingly threatened by that. I was, during my first year or so, doing
                    consular and administrative work, and when I'd go over to the Quang__ ministry
                    on some visa case or something like that, or an American citizen matter, they
                    would make it very clear that they weren't happy with our policy of supporting
                    Pakistan and CENTO. They eventually, while I was still there, began turning to
                    the Soviets, and the Soviets came in with their first well publicized, small aid
                    program in a non-communist country, and built a bakery, and paved the streets of
                    Kabul, and those were the main things. And I used to meet more and more Soviet
                    diplomats who had been very well trained in Pushtu, a rather obscure language
                    that practically no American, with one exception, had studied. I remember the
                    (Soviet) director of consular affairs said to me, “You see, Mr. Lindstrom, this
                    is what you people should be doing.” So they were making an impression, a fairly
                    favorable impression in that respect.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I realize you were down the totem pole in a small embassy.
                        Our policy towards Afghanistan was sort of watching?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: And giving food aid, which was in many ways a mistake. It discouraged
                    farming, this has happened in many countries as I understand it. Afghan farming
                    became unprofitable in many instances, and began to create urbanization and
                    other radicalization indirectly over the longer term. And also we did provide
                    support and financial aid to some bigger programs through the Morrison-Knudsen
                    Company. It built big hydroelectric projects in the southern part of the
                    country. So we were trying to be friendly to them, supportive of them, but at
                    the same time we were caught in a bind. I don't think we truly realized it at
                    the time of the support of the anti-communist allies. So over the longer term,
                    long after I left there, the Afghans pooh-poohed the Soviet threat. They said we
                    know how to handle them. Increasingly they went to the Soviets for aid, and
                    eventually got into military aid, and military training programs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of how things were run by the
                        Afghans? Was there much of a central government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: At that time, the leader was Prime Minister Daud, who was in for a
                    time, was out, and then later came back in again. I think they had reasonably
                    good control over things, but the other provinces, and the non-Pushtu tribes
                    felt pretty much left out of things. But I think on balance they were making
                    progress. And again, they were very concerned by the Pakistani propaganda on
                    Pushtunistan. It was hard to have very much contact with them in terms of
                    conversations on political subjects, not impossible, but a little bit difficult.
                    I remember there tended to be cultural clashes of one kind or another. Women, of
                    course, were in complete purdah in those days. I think I only met three or four
                    wives of high ranking people who were not wearing purdah in their homes during
                    the period that I was there.</p>
                <p>We did bring in a Marine detachment while I was there. Before that we had relied
                    on civilian security guards, and of course the Marines managed to get a couple
                    of girlfriends despite the purdah, and this created an incident. They were
                    expelled, of course, from the country.</p>
                <p>Our leadership in the embassy was by one Angus Ward, about whom you have
                    doubtless heard before.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you describe him, and his method of operation, and
                        background?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: He was a naturalized American citizen, which I think was an important
                    part of his make-up, a Canadian. He was also not a graduate of a four-year
                    university, so he had chips on his shoulder, I think. He was a very smart man,
                    and he had specialized almost his entire career in the Soviet Union. He had been
                    consul general in Vladivostok. We had a post there then. He was a rather bitter
                    man by the time I got there. He had been incarcerated by the Chinese in Mukden,
                    and he then became sort of a political football to the China lobby. It made him
                    into an unlikely hero. And this was the reason he got the post. He had never
                    been an ambassador, and he was consul general in Nairobi. But the China lobby
                    put a lot of pressure on the State Department to give this fine, deserving man
                    an ambassadorship. They didn't have Ouagadougou in those days, so it was Kabul.
                    And my very first assignment, I had only been in the post for I think one month,
                    was to go down and meet him and his wife in Peshawar.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And his cats too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: And his cats, oh yes. Jack Korner was the Charg� d'Affaires who gave
                    me this assignment. I'm not quite sure what was in Jack's mind, but I was very
                    inexperienced to be doing this sort of thing, and Jack knew very little about
                    the man too, as it later developed. So anyway, I went down to Peshawar, and the
                    ambassador was delayed in getting there. And finally, I remember, I was diving
                    into the swimming pool at the Peshawar Club when somebody came up and yelled at
                    me, “The ambassador is here.” So that was the beginning of my not too happy
                    relationship with Ambassador Ward. He'd brought his own Cadillac in, and had
                    three cats, an East African cat, a Siberian cat, and something else, I can't
                    remember what, in the back seat with Hermgard, his Finnish wife. Then we made
                    preparations to go into Afghanistan in sort of a safari, two follow-up trucks
                    that had been furnished by the embassy, so he could bring all of his effects in
                    with him at the same time.</p>
                <p>So finally he said, “Let's go.” And I said, “Would you like me to lead the way,
                    Mr. Ambassador? It's kind of tricky going over the Khyber Pass.” I had an
                    embassy driver with me, and one old Chevrolet. “No, Lindstrom, I'm not going to
                    eat your dust all the way.” And, of course, he proceeded to get lost several
                    times. But finally we did get to the border crossing point. This was about three
                    or four days later than his expected arrival, and we had the usual tea at the
                    border with the Pakistani officials, and then they dropped the chain, and we set
                    off across the border. I told him there was probably going to be an honor guard
                    there for him, and, at that point, the paving ceased and it was all just dust
                    and dirt, and he again insisted on leading the way. And we did come up to this
                    company of troops who were then standing at attention in the sun. He stopped,
                    and I stopped and ran up to him, and he said to me, “Lindstrom, in Afghanistan
                    do they review from left to the right, or right to the left.” I said, “Mr.
                    Ambassador, I'm sorry, I don't know.” And he turned red in the face, very angry,
                    jumped in his car and left them in a cloud of dust.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>So we got up to the first border check point which was several miles in, and the
                    colonel of the guard came to my driver who came to me, and said, “Wouldn't the
                    ambassador please like to go back and review the guard because they had been
                    waiting for him all those days?” And I raised this with the ambassador, and he
                    sort of snarled at me, and said no. So we got off to a very bad start in our
                    relationship. And another thing, neither he nor his wife would eat any of the
                    melons that were laid out, and he explained to me that they often soaked them in
                    the ___(?). So I ate to be polite and I didn't get sick or anything like
                    that.</p>
                <p>So then we started out, and again he was going to lead the way. By this time I
                    realized, because I saw him racing up the mountainside on the left-hand side of
                    the road, which is the way they drive in Pakistan, that I had forgotten to tell
                    him to drive on the right-hand side in Afghanistan. And these big heavily laden
                    lorries were coming down and they finally stopped bumper-to-bumper on the
                    left-hand side of the road. So I had to go up and give my apologies. “Mr.
                    Ambassador, the rule of the road in Afghanistan is on the right.” Then we
                    proceeded on over the mountains and up to a point midway between Kabul and the
                    border where we were met by our Charg� d'Affaires, Jack Korner. And as I said
                    before he was not a very well briefed Charg�. He came running up. I can still
                    remember him with a thermos in each hand and said, “Mr. Ambassador, welcome. In
                    this thermos I have martinis, and in this one I have manhattans.” And the
                    ambassador said, “Well, Korner, we don't drink.” And Jack said, “Mr. Ambassador,
                    do you mind if Ralph and I have a drink?”</p>
                <p>Anyway, we over-nighted there. It was a German-run construction camp, and then
                    went on into Kabul. So my beginnings with the ambassador were not very
                    happy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He didn't seem to be very forthcoming to the Afghans. How
                        did he get along with them? What was your impression?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: He didn't get along with them terribly well. I remember an example, it
                    was in my own bailiwick in consular affairs. At that time we were under
                    instructions from Washington. There was new consular legislation that if we were
                    willing to sign an agreement with other countries, a reciprocal agreement, we
                    could liberalize our laws. Of course, it was being done all over the world. I
                    can't remember the name of the Act now, it was so long ago, but anyway...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The McCarran-Walter Act?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It may have been.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think it was the McCarran-Walter Act, in '52.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I raised this with Mr. Mohammed, the head of the consular section,
                    more than once. And he said, “Mr. Lindstrom, this is fine but I'd like to have
                    your ambassador's support on this. He could just say that this is a good idea
                    and mention it to the foreign minister, and then we can do this.” So I mentioned
                    this to the ambassador on more than one occasion, and all I ever got was a
                    lecture on the concept of reservoir of good will. That he didn't want to use up
                    whatever reservoir of good will he had for this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a very typical attitude of you don't mess with
                        consular visas. It's just too small a thing to mess with.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Apparently, but of course it didn't make a good impression on me, or
                    least on the consular part of the Foreign Ministry. And I'm pretty sure they
                    reported it elsewhere too, that the ambassador wasn't taking any interest in
                    this. But I had many adventures with him. I can still remember one. I was
                    working in consular/administrative affairs in a separate building from the
                    ambassador's office, and he wanted to see almost all outgoing correspondence. In
                    fact he made it very clear. And I remember preparing a telegram in response to a
                    welfare and whereabouts telegram from the Department saying that in effect we
                    were unable to contact so-and-so. And a while later the phone rang and it was
                    the ambassador on the phone and he said, “Lindstrom, I have this telegram, a
                    contact, isn't that sort of lower __ the knees?” I said, “I'm sorry sir, what
                    should you have said? I was unable to ascertain the whereabouts of so-and-so.”
                    “Well, that's better.” I could go on and on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, no. I like to hear about this because he's an
                        interesting character. I think it's worthwhile to talk about him a bit.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: He dressed very formally, morning clothes quite often, that kind of
                    thing. One of his little customs was, and he absolutely blind sided us on this,
                    was to call on people on New Year's morning. I never could figure why he was
                    doing this. Quite frankly it was quite a partying post, as small hardship posts
                    were, and in many ways I think the ambassador was a unifying influence because
                    almost everyone hated him. I can still remember, having been out to one of these
                    parties and being awakened by the servants about six o'clock in the morning, New
                    Year's morning, and the ambassador came in in his formal clothes, and made his
                    pretty little speech. I guess I put on a bathrobe over my pajamas. He did this
                    with everyone else too, and all the other officers on the diplomatic list.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mrs. Ward was difficult, wasn't she? Because she ranks
                        along with, I guess, Robert Murphy's wife, and Mrs. Loy Henderson. These
                        were some of the old dragons.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: She hated Mrs. Henderson. Mrs. Henderson was Swedish, if I remember
                    correctly, whereas Mrs. Ward was Finnish, and Mrs. Ward was very proud of the
                    fact that she'd gone to finishing school in St. Petersburg. She spoke this very
                    quaint French that they taught the Russians in those days, often a direct
                    translation of Russian. She'd say grande merci. I don't hear much people going
                    around saying grande merci.</p>
                <p>Oh, another thing that occurs to me, yes. My wife ended up being the senior—even
                    though the wife of a third secretary—the senior American-born wife in the
                    embassy, and this did not please Mrs. Ward one bit. She didn't really like my
                    wife, but still from a protocol point of view, we did get invited once in a
                    while to luncheons at the residence. So I remember Gloria, as the senior
                    American, ended up at the ambassador's left at this luncheon which was for...I
                    can't remember who it was for, but it was some foreigners of some nationality.
                    But anyway, we were just beginning the meal, and I was over on the other side of
                    the table, when I happened to look over in the direction of my wife and I saw an
                    orange flash, an orange streak, and my wife yelled, screamed, and started
                    mopping up blood on her arm, and the ambassador said, “That's all right, Mrs.
                    Lindstrom, that's Ranger's place.” That was one of the three cats, apparently
                    the cats outranked me, with the ambassador's wife. That was his only apology, as
                    she was sopping up the blood. You're ruining my career, I thought to myself.
                    Anyway, that was another little tidbit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard other stories about how he spent a great deal
                        of time working on some packing crates made of the very best wood for his
                        things, but also to have some fine wood when he got back.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Oh, yes, that was one of the things he did and I got tangentially
                    involved in that. I knew it wasn't the right thing to do, and I would not ever
                    certify it. John Bowie, one of my colleagues and more senior, said he would
                    certify it. It was very expensive, high quality furniture wood, which is
                    certainly not needed for packing cases. I remember once his driver came to me
                    and said he had used embassy grease to grease his Cadillac, so I sent him a bill
                    for that, and he got quite upset with me. But the board thing is certainly true,
                    and he sent them to Spain and made them up into packing cases.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he travel around the country very much?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: He did, yes. To his credit he did a fair amount. At that time our
                    embassies were very badly equipped. We did not have a nice front-wheel drive
                    vehicle or anything like that; whereas our AID mission did have those things,
                    and this also will tell you something about the ambassador's character. He
                    didn't want to be indebted to anyone. But when he wanted to take a trip, he
                    would call me in and say, “Lindstrom, I'd like to go to ___, or wherever, but I
                    don't really have a proper vehicle.” “Well, have you asked the director of AID
                    for this? They have some.” “Well, I thought maybe you could just talk to Bill
                    Lathran.” Bill was the other junior FSO. He had been assigned for two months to
                    the AID mission rather than to the embassy. So I would go up and talk to Bill,
                    and Bill would talk to Mr. Hayes, and would say, “Why doesn't the ambassador
                    have the guts to ask me directly.” So, yes, he did travel around.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What does an embassy do when you've got an ambassador who
                        is very difficult like this? How big was the embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: We had about 14 people on the diplomatic list. I can recall that from
                    the presentation of credentials ceremony. The AID mission was already quite
                    large, there must have been maybe 30-40 people in it including the people, not
                    just administrative people, who were actually working in the field on seeds and
                    things like that. The non-diplomatic American staff was probably 15 or 20, a lot
                    of them military, and communicators and people like that. So it was already a
                    sizeable staff for that period of time.</p>
                <p>Another thing that did not endear people to the Wards was Mrs. Ward's habit
                    of—she pulled this on every new wife—the hats and gloves problem, and if any
                    woman ever put her hand out to shake Mrs. Ward's hand with a glove on, she would
                    just shriek, and say, “No, I won't shake your hand. Haven't you been properly
                    brought up?” and all that. But I think she began to have some cronies. She did
                    get along to some extent with our embassy nurse, and they used to be able to go
                    on the attach� flights out to other countries. And Bill Lathran, this is no
                    criticism of him, he was just simply in a somewhat better position than I was.
                    He had goodies to offer, and wasn't directly under the ambassador, so I think he
                    could see some good points in Ambassador Ward.</p>
                <p>Another thing, I remember about Ambassador Ward and his bitterness, was he
                    mentioned to me criticism of Chip Bohlen, “Those young whippersnappers,” like
                    that. Very bitter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you inspected at that point, or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, we were and I can't remember who the inspector was. I guess it
                    was Gordon Madison.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was wondering, because when you're in a difficult
                        situation like that, and you have an ambassador who obviously is not only
                        difficult, but you're not getting along well with him, particularly on your
                        first tour, this is where you can see a very short career staring you in the
                        face. And often it's the inspectors who can understand the situation, and
                        kind of save one.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Actually it did. I ended up working that way and I can't remember if
                    it was that inspector's report or something else that there was contrary
                    evidence that maybe I had some potential. So I think when I went back to
                    Washington it worked out all right. I've forgotten the details of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the DCM business work out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Our first DCM was a man who didn't really stand up to Ward at all, and
                    not a terribly good DCM. I've even forgotten his name. He was later replaced by
                    a very good one just as I was leaving, Leon Poullada, who went on to distinguish
                    himself. I think he became an ambassador. Charlie Little was the first one, and
                    he was sort of in trouble himself with the Department, and I think he retired
                    not too long after that. Then we had a kind of a rogue CIA operation. I think
                    many people had that sort of thing in other posts in those days, out of control,
                    and he didn't do much to that. Again they had goodies they could give him to
                    keep him happy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The first taste of the Foreign Service, I take it, for you
                        and your wife must have been a little bit difficult to swallow, wasn't
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, and there were other hardships involved. My wife became pregnant
                    during that tour. And there was one Danish doctor-midwife there who said she
                    probably would have a somewhat difficult pregnancy and should go out to
                    Pakistan. The only way to get out to Pakistan was on the attach� plane, and I
                    went to the Air Force colonel about that, and he said, “You will have to pay
                    $1800, if we are going to make a trip like that.” And I said, “The State
                    Department doesn't have any funds for that.” And he said, “I can't help that.” I
                    think this case was one of the things that led to more support for evacuating
                    people when necessary, and, of course, in those days $1800 was about a third of
                    my salary. Well, we just didn't have it. So we decided she would stay and have
                    the baby in Kabul, which she did do and she was delivered of the baby. I was
                    there too and helping this Danish midwife. But it had been a long labor, 12
                    hours or something like that, and then everybody went home. Of course there were
                    no phones in Kabul at that time, and then she started hemorrhaging. She's a
                    nurse, so she told me what to do, get out the medical book, you have to massage
                    the placenta, that's the uterus when it goes limp, otherwise you'd bleed to
                    death. So I managed to get her bleeding stopped without getting in there and
                    massaging the placenta. So that was kind of an experience. And we put Karen, the
                    baby, in a whiskey box we'd lined with something, and then I got rid of the
                    placenta by giving it to the jewey dogs. That's the way you disposed of almost
                    everything on the streets of Kabul at that time. Finally everything did go all
                    right, but it would have been better had she gone out to the Seventh Day
                    Adventist's hospital in Karachi. But this wasn't possible. But I think that
                    incident, and maybe many similar ones, may have gotten the Department to realize
                    that they had to give a little more support to the Foreign Service personnel who
                    were overseas.</p>
                <p>And then about that time, when the baby had just been born, Vice President Nixon
                    and his wife came to Kabul. He was described as the highest ranking foreigner to
                    visit since Genghis Khan, which I think is essentially accurate. Again, I saw
                    Mrs. Ward lose her cool. I was talking to Pat Nixon, and they were taking some
                    pictures of us, and she was really quite nice, and all of a sudden Mrs. Ward
                    came in screaming, “Get out of here, out of here, out of here.” And Mrs. Nixon
                    said, to me, “Is she always like that?” And I said, “Well, sometimes, yes.” She
                    said, “We'll move on.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you left Kabul where did you go? You left in
                        1954.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Then I went to Paris, which was my first choice, and I guess they felt
                    I should be rewarded after that hardship post, and really got a very nice
                    assignment as an economic financial officer in the office of the Treasury
                    attach�. The Treasury rep, Don McGrew, who was famous for his skills in that
                    area, and for being a good training officer. So I worked for him for three
                    years, a very interesting assignment, and my main contacts were in the Ministry
                    of Finance. These were the post-Marshall Plan days, so the French were still
                    somewhat beholden to us and very willing to give out confidential information on
                    the state of their balance of payments, etc., which is one of our higher
                    priorities. At that point, I had never really studied economics to speak of. I
                    had taken one course at Harvard. It was a rather badly taught course in those
                    days and I barely passed the thing, and had no further interest in it. But I
                    learned a lot about the balance of payments from this reporting, and from Don
                    McGrew. So it turned out to be a rather rewarding assignment. I got good ratings
                    on that. And one of the other persons I worked for, and more directly, was Dean
                    Hinton. Both Dean and I were the two FSOs who worked for McGrew and he was quite
                    an able person obviously in his own right, and I got along well with him. He
                    only recently retired, I believe. There were other people around, Harry Bell,
                    who was very good in the economic field too. And Jack Tuthill came in as
                    economic counselor and took a liking to me. We had just had the Wristonization
                    program and we had had to take on three very senior people in various parts of
                    the economic section. Jack was getting very annoyed and I didn't like being used
                    as sort of his private spy or anything like that, but sometimes people do that.
                    He said, “You know, I can't understand, what is so-and-so doing, and so-and-so
                    doing? I don't see any written work, or anything like that, why don't you nose
                    around and find out.” So I did talk to these people, and they said, “Well, we're
                    still busy unpacking, and getting my wife settled and that kind of thing.” So it
                    was quite apparent they weren't doing much of anything that was of any value. He
                    managed to get one of them transferred down to a consulate, I guess it was
                    either Nice or Cannes. I can't remember which one. I guess it was in Nice, and
                    he turned out to be a disaster there. He and his wife got into all sorts of
                    sexual affairs and that kind of thing, and were an embarrassment to the United
                    States. By and large we had a pretty good embassy and Amory Houghton came in as
                    ambassador. He was a political appointee but quite sympathetic, and interested
                    in what we were doing in the economic-financial side, as well as in the
                    political side. In the political side, of course, we were already beginning to
                    have troubles with the French. de Gaulle was in the background and some of our
                    officers were able to talk to him, or his people, from time to time. The NATO
                    relationship was getting somewhat strained, but that hadn't broken apart yet
                    while we were there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the French bureaucracy in the
                        financial field?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: First rate. They're the best in the whole world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, that's the reputation.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Again I learned something by dealing with people like Ash Stuart(?),
                    who later rose to the top in the World Bank. That's one of their elite services.
                    They really are marvelous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did they treat you as an American, although they might
                        be beholden. I mean you're neophyte to this field and here you are up
                        against world class...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: They treated me very well. I always had to speak French. My French was
                    by then fairly good, but I know these people spoke English better than I spoke
                    French. But it was always in French which was good practice for me, and enabled
                    me to keep my self respect in dealing with them. That was a very positive
                    experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the embassy like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It was a huge embassy, and I guess still is, but generally a very
                    supportive and friendly embassy. We had many friends there. Our first couple of
                    years there we were not eligible for embassy housing so we lived out on the open
                    market up in Montmartre, which was very nice and we enjoyed it. Later for
                    financial reasons primarily, we moved to embassy housing on the other side of
                    Paris, because the housing allowance wouldn't really cover too much when you're
                    living outside. McGrew, the Treasury man as I said before, was really top notch,
                    and to his credit they always allowed me as a third secretary to maintain these
                    high level contacts with the French financial officials. They thought my
                    reporting on this was very good, so that was a morale builder too. So often more
                    senior officials try to do it all themselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you didn't feel, as sometimes one does, lost in the
                        embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No, I don't think I did at all looking back on it now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's this traditional thing about saying the French are
                        very unfriendly. Did you find that speaking French?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No, I never did, and never have. I never found this to be a problem.
                    But the French do like to use their own language certainly in the diplomatic
                    level, and I don't see anything wrong with that. We tend to use English on the
                    diplomatic level in our country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you left there in 1957, and went off to where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: To Hong Kong. That was a complete surprise.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was two years there, to '59.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: That turned out to be a very fortuitous and interesting assignment
                    with new people, and new problems. And my timing there was very good. It was in
                    the late part of '57. We had three consuls general when I was there. There was a
                    rapid turnover and one of them was Drumright.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Everett Drumright, an old China hand.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I remember meeting him, not a very friendly person. He wanted to know
                    where I'd been. I had taken full advantage of my home leave, and also time to go
                    across the Pacific on a ship, as well as the Atlantic. But, anyway, I finally
                    got in there and I was put in the China reporting section, along with Lindsey
                    Grant and Paul Caukle(?). Most of our reporting was, because we couldn't go into
                    China in those days at all, based on the press. Then we would switch portfolios
                    with the economic side of things. There was a companion political section. Tom
                    Ainsworth was in that, and the head of the economic section was a Wristonee, a
                    very good man, and I learned a lot from him. Anyway, my service there coincided
                    with the Great Leap Forward in China, when they thought they really had
                    discovered the secret of economic development and were smelting iron and steel,
                    if they could in the back yard. By then their relationship with the Soviets had
                    really soured. We didn't know much about that at that time but subsequently, of
                    course, it became very clear that they were separating themselves from the
                    Soviets, and the Soviets were repaying this by cutting down on Soviet
                    assistance. So I think this in part led to this Great Leap Forward that Mao
                    kicked off. It turned out to be, as we knew later, a tremendous failure, but at
                    the time the propaganda was such, and it was so hard to get in and see what was
                    really happening, that people in the western world began to believe it. That
                    they finally had found the secret of rapid economic development. So I ended up
                    being right in the middle of reporting, and the New York Times in particular,
                    and some of the other papers, became believers and were publishing daily stories
                    about the successes of the Chinese which we in the consulate general tried to
                    rebut, and tried to put into perspective. But it was difficult. We didn't have
                    hard numbers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's so easy now to look back and say, of course this
                        thing was stupid. What they were doing was melting down steel and iron
                        products which had been already done, and producing basically just hunks of
                        unusable metal. I would have thought the New York Times or some economist
                        would have tried to make some of these little furnaces themselves and see
                        what happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No, I don't recall anybody having done that. Again, it was very much
                    of a closed society, and the propaganda was pretty effective. People thought
                    they were going to take over all the export markets in the Far East, which they
                    may do now, but this is 40 years later when it's a much stronger country. But in
                    those days, they were a very poor country. I was talking to Ed Green about what
                    we might do about this to put it in better perspective. And he said, “Why don't
                    you go down to China Products...” I don't know if you know Hong Kong or not.
                    China Products is a retail outlet for Chinese products as the name suggests and
                    we were told by the Treasury Department in those days to never set foot in it.
                    It would be against U.S. law to buy anything in there. But, anyway, people said
                    I should go in there and see what's going on, what kind of things they're
                    selling, are there shortages, or do they have availabilities, or not. So I did
                    that over a considerable period of time. I suppose I was noticed by the Chinese,
                    but I was never prevented and I made notes when I got back outside. I didn't go
                    around with a note pad or anything like that. So finally I got together about a
                    18-20 page despatch on my findings, and it really established rather
                    convincingly that if there was this great supply of consumer goods, and other
                    exportable items it had vanished. It dried up in that store, which was a pretty
                    good indicator that this whole thing was a fraud. And, of course, we learned
                    many years later, it was just systematic lying within the Chinese bureaucracy
                    about what they were doing, and went all the way to the top, with people
                    apparently believing the reports that were coming in. So I felt I made my little
                    contribution by putting that into better perspective. I got a commendation for
                    that despatch from the Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just to get a feel for it. I mean Hong Kong was, and
                        certainly until very recently, was the place one watched China. It was the
                        only place we had that really had feelers into China, because we had nothing
                        in there at the time and for a long time. How did you go about your
                        business? How did you get your information?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Well, certainly the China mainland press was probably our biggest
                    source. We had a big translation operation we ran in Hong Kong. In fact, Bill
                    Thomas, one of my colleagues and Foreign Service classmates, was put in charge
                    of that. He was a Chinese language officer. I think they had 100 people working
                    for them. So that was one source, the China press, and very biased. Then we had
                    many very good local employees working for us directly in the political and
                    economic sections, who had come down from Shanghai and elsewhere. Then some of
                    our best contacts were with the consular corps people who recognized China and
                    who could go up there from time to time. So we cultivated them. I was on very
                    close terms with the Australians, and people like that. They would be pleased to
                    be debriefed when they came back from a trip to the Canton trade fair. So that
                    was another way of getting information. And certainly our Chinese employees,
                    although they never did anything you could call spying, or anything like that,
                    they could certainly help us interpret what was in the press.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you say, papers like the New York Times were buying the
                        propaganda. This happens from time to time. People in a way want to be true
                        believers. It's sexy, it's different, and in a way it's a stick in the eye
                        of the establishment in the western world. Did you in your position have any
                        dealings with the American press, or media, that was stationed there and
                        talk about this situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes. I used to, again as an additional source of information, go to
                    the Press Club regularly and meet many of the American and other correspondents
                    and that was very important to getting a balanced understanding of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get into, I won't say disputes, but find yourself
                        trying to present what you felt was the true picture as opposed to how they
                        were reporting this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: (?) Gurden(?) was the main reporter of this stuff and certainly Ed, my
                    boss, did try to enlighten him without too much success, and he was an old Far
                    East hand. I don't know why he insisted on doing this. But with other press
                    people I think we were all beginning to see that there was a fraud in the
                    building, and we all felt a little helpless as to how to deal with the
                    thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Although you're in the economic side, was there any
                        feeling about when and if we should recognize Communist China at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I think we could read the tea leaves back home, and see that it wasn't
                    too likely from a U.S. point of view with the China lobby, etc. The main problem
                    was our relationship with Taiwan, and we weren't about to jettison Taiwan. I was
                    there when the Chinese started giving these serious warnings to Taiwan, the
                    shelling of Quemoy and Matsu. And they started counting the serious warnings for
                    the Chinese to come and put numbers on everything. It got up to the 244th
                    serious one, I don't know what it was, while I was there. And in those days we
                    self censored ourselves to some extent. I don't think anyone ever told me, but
                    we always were careful to call it Communist China, or Mainland China, certainly
                    never People's Republic of China. So I think all of us realized that it would be
                    a long time off before there was anything approaching a normalized relationship
                    between the United States and China. Of course, it took Nixon and Kissinger with
                    their later opening that finally did it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about Vietnam? Vietnam had sort of split, '55 is when
                        both sides moved apart. Did you have anything to do, or see anything on
                        Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Not very much. We were virtually the only non-hardship post in the
                    area, so people from southeast Asia would come up from time to time. I didn't do
                    any peripheral reporting on Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We were taking a very hard line on trade with China,
                        weren't we?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Oh, yes. And right in the Consulate General we had this Treasury rep
                    who was in control of foreign assets, who was making certain that we only dealt
                    with clean money lenders. And by chance my wife and I had made very good friends
                    on a ship coming out there with some of the 'Queen's Chinese', so they called
                    them, people who had been knighted, and were a very nice merchant family. So
                    this gave us an entree into non-Communist Chinese society. It was very
                    interesting, and we learned a lot about etiquette, eating and all of that in
                    many course feast meals. Anyway, some time later our Treasury man, who was very
                    much of a sleuth, implicated that family with buying Chinese caught shrimp, and
                    marketing them in the United States as real clean shrimp. And that sort of
                    temporarily soured our relationship with this family. They'd say, “Here he is in
                    the Consulate, and he didn't even tip us off about that.” Not that I would have,
                    as I didn't know about it. The anti-Communist thing was there all the time, and
                    very strictly enforced. There was China Products and getting permission to go in
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just to go into the store. Then you left in '59 and went
                        back to Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, and then my next assignment was a year of economic training at
                    Princeton University, which was a very useful year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the state of economic training when you took at
                        Princeton?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It was in a way somewhat beyond me. I was already becoming
                    mathematical. But still on balance I was able to cope with it, and got quite a
                    lot out of it, and even had my efficiency report written by Bill (?), who was
                    one of the brightest economists still around. He was very young at that time,
                    and a theoretical economist, and I got a pretty good report out of him. I used
                    part of my time also to go over to the Woodrow Wilson School and I took some
                    courses over there, part political as well as economic. It was all-in-all very
                    good and a useful experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you came back to the Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, the Department, and I did not get the assignment I wanted, but
                    the word was out to put people in INR, and I ended up being assigned there. I
                    had wanted to be in the EB Bureau, and be on the policy side of things. That's
                    the way these things go. I got into Communist affairs, on the economic side and
                    then was assigned to language training at Oberammergau, later Garmisch
                    Partenkirchen, and had a year's Russian language training, which led to an
                    assignment in the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Backing up a touch, you were in INR for a little while
                        anyway?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From around what, '60-'62?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, and then I got my four year tour in with two training assignments
                    with the INR thing in the middle of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were in INR, you were looking at Soviet
                        economy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No. The main focus was on Soviet penetration of the third world. That
                    was the big thing then., Phil Habib was involved in that at a high level and a
                    number of us were put into it, and we started doing reports on everything every
                    time the Soviets moved a muscle. This was during the Cold War, and Roger
                    Hilsman, I think, was director of INR at that time. This was a big item always,
                    in the morning briefings which usually took place at some ungodly hour, 5:30 in
                    the morning or something like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was in INR during the Horn of Africa about the same
                        time, coming in...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Was Roger Hilsman there?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I remember he used to come in sort of bleary eyed. He was on the party
                    circuit with the Kennedys. And he had all these TDCSs crumpled up in his pocket.
                    It was obvious that he'd been out reading from those with his friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was our impression of what the Soviets were doing in
                        the third world, the Soviet Union influence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: They were doing everything they could to assert an increased Soviet
                    influence for all of these countries in the third world, and our major
                    focus...no, it wasn't only on Africa, but I think I got a little more involved
                    in that than other things, and we were very concerned about it, that they were
                    going to take over the world that way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Africa was very sexy at the time, too. Duly emerging, and
                        this was a great opportunity for the United States and for the Soviets, in
                        fighting over the soul of Africa. It seems a little hard to understand
                        today, particularly the Kennedy administration. What was your impression
                        though that you were getting of the Soviet ability to produce things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: We looked at these things as critically as we could, and of course we
                    knew that Soviet quality in terms of manufacturing and making things, was very
                    poor. They were not in a position to be very good exporters of that sort of
                    thing. But they would do as best they could, give scholarships, give food aid if
                    they could in some kind of a swap. So they were winning, they were making
                    inroads to some degree, but they weren't really getting permanent converts. I've
                    talked to many Africans and other third world people who had been educated in
                    the Soviet Union, and they ended up with no particular loyalty to the Soviets. I
                    remember once, this was some years later, traveling with my family on a Soviet
                    ship from Leningrad to London, and the ship was full of African and other
                    students who had been in Moscow for a full year at the Lumumba University, going
                    out for R&amp;R if you will. Then there were some that were especially
                    privileged, and I could see they would get special things on board the ship. I
                    suppose future KGB cops and that sort of thing. We did entertain them at our
                    embassy quite a bit and that gave them a way out. The Soviets didn't really like
                    it, but there wasn't too much of anything they could do about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One thing, what was your impression of how the information
                        you were developing was being used within the State Department and INR?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: This was a high priority at that time, whether it should have been or
                    not in retrospect, I don't know. But it was being used by the policy makers, by
                    Hilsman and others, no question about that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you always felt you were handing him top secret things
                        which he was sticking into his pockets.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No, I did see that a couple of times. I don't know if you did, the
                    early morning things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was during the Congo crisis and he was talking
                        about...he kept trying to use his experience in OSS in Burma in the Congo,
                        and Owen Roberts, who was the Congo man, every once in a while had to brief
                        Hilsman when he had the morning duty, to make sure he didn't try to turn the
                        Congo into an OSS type, and also World War II operations being thrust
                        through here. Very hard to understand the Congo, such small little tribal
                        conflicts.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>You'd already taken some Russian, hadn't you?</p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes. I first studied it in France and had a good basis, then I took
                    some classes at FSI. So I was pretty much up to the 2+ or 3 level, and then
                    assigned to Oberammergau, which tries to bring us up to at least the 4-4 level.
                    Some of my colleagues I was assigned there with, Bill Luers and Roger Kirk, both
                    had quite a bit more Russian than I had. All the courses, as you probably know,
                    were conducted in Russian on substantive subjects. We had a number of professors
                    of various extractions. We had one who was very good, a Serbian, his Russian was
                    excellent. And then we had many others who were pure Russians who had defected
                    at the end of World War II. One man I remember defected, he was a top aide to
                    Beria, the secret police chief, when I was in Kabul. He ended up in that school.
                    I remember my first interview with him. He had just been brought in there, it
                    was rather frightening, a typical secret police sort of interview asking all
                    these questions about your personal life. But that was a good school. It's still
                    running. One of my other fellow students was Bill Odem(?), who is frequently on
                    television now. He got three stars, and I remember his telling me, he was only
                    an Army captain, he said, “I never expect to go beyond Lieutenant Colonel in
                    this Army intelligence business.” He is a very bright guy, and a very good
                    analytical mind, so he's gone a hell of lot farther than that. So I met some
                    very talented people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is the 29th of November, 1994. Ralph, we basically
                        finished with you at Oberammergau, is that right? So you went to Moscow from
                        1963 to '65. How would you describe the relationship between the United
                        States and the Soviet Union? When did you get there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: In the middle of 1963, and Khrushchev was still in power. I'd say the
                    relationship was somewhat improving, but again against the backdrop of the
                    troubles with Vietnam. But Khrushchev himself did visit the United States as you
                    may recall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He might have come to the United Nations, but we'd gone
                        through his big visit, during the Eisenhower administration. Then we had the
                        missile crisis in '62, the Cuban missile crisis.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I guess maybe he had already made his major visit to the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He might have made a UN trip.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I remember seeing his train go by when I was up in Princeton. But
                    anyway, Khrushchev was a very interesting leader. I had a chance to meet him
                    several times in connection with American businessmen visiting the Soviet Union.
                    He became very much aware of the economic problems that were beginning to affect
                    the economy increasingly, and wanted to do something about them, but didn't
                    really know what to do. He put, of course, a lot of emphasis, as they did way
                    back to the Czars, on getting more ideas and inventions from foreigners, either
                    buying them, stealing them, or however you could get them. That perhaps would
                    solve some of the problems with the economy. He was, of course, deposed about a
                    year after I got there, and this amazingly created very little stir inside the
                    Soviet Union. I guess he was not particularly appreciated by the people. I went
                    down to Red Square on the night that he had been toppled just to see what was
                    going on, and there was absolutely nothing, no security precautions to speak of,
                    only one militia vehicle, and people coming out of the theaters located in the
                    Kremlin, and talking with each other. I sort of listened in to see if they
                    wouldn't be talking about the major event of the world, and there was not a word
                    about it. They were just talking about the theater, the weather, and personal
                    things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you went there, what was your position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I went there as an economic officer the first tour, and the second
                    tour, which was two years after the first, was back as Economic Counselor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about the first tour, the '63 to '65 one. What
                        was the embassy like at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Foy Kohler was the ambassador, and we were trying, despite all the
                    obstacles, to get some contacts with Soviets. It was almost impossible to do
                    useful reporting which was based to a considerable measure on the press, just
                    reading the press. It was a little easier for those of us who were in the
                    economic section. We weren't as harassed by the KGB as the people in the
                    political section, for example. The embassy was well run, comfortable, the same
                    old building as I think we are still using even today, and very much run down
                    now. It was much easier then to have contacts say with the artistic community
                    under Khrushchev than it was later under Brezhnev, when it became more of a
                    crackdown. This was of some interest. I managed to buy a few paintings and get
                    acquainted with a leading painter, my wife and I. She was able to get some
                    entree into the museums and that kind of thing, and go with other American
                    women. She'd had the opportunity to study Russian in Oberammergau as I had. So
                    there were openings there. You had to work at them, and we tried to travel
                    whenever we could. This was useful too. Often when you traveled you had more of
                    an opportunity to meet people, as you could talk to them, and they could talk to
                    you with relative impunity, in a railway car, or even sometimes in an airplane.
                    So we did quite a lot of that, as much as we could.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Here you're in the economic section, and we're now talking
                        in 1994 when what was the Soviet Union, now is a broken up mass, just an
                        absolute economic disaster, and the economic side the cause of disaster. The
                        system didn't work. But trying to go back to the time you were there looking
                        at this, how did we feel about the economic situation and the short-long
                        term prognosis for it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: We could see the weaknesses. I made it a point to visit as many
                    factories as I could, and I think I visited a couple dozen factories of various
                    types. It was one of the things they did permit you to do. Of course, they only
                    showed you the relatively nice factories, but even there you could see there
                    wasn't much, morale was very low in the work force. The factories were real
                    safety hazards. Russians are the least safety conscious people in the world, I
                    think. It's something about the character. Typically you'd go around in a
                    factory and there'd be pieces of broken frayed cable on the floors, grease on
                    the floor, and that type of thing. Although everyone was supposed to wear a hard
                    hat, they very rarely ever did. The crane operators were usually women, way up
                    high in these big high overhead cranes. And I remember taking a group of
                    American businessmen into a plant in Leningrad, its very much like the
                    Schenectady plant up in New York, and I asked him why are the crane operators
                    almost always women?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is tape 2, side A, an interview with Ralph Lindstrom.
                        You were asking about why the crane operators were always women?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, and the chief engineer replied to me, without any hesitation, in
                    Russian. “Because they don't drink, so it's a safety measure.” And in that time
                    I think Russian women were very sober and did not drink. I understand it has
                    changed quite a bit since then.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What I'm getting at is, that somehow or other we
                        acknowledge all the problems of the Soviet Union, yet we seem to think that
                        here was something that would almost go on forever, and that the controls
                        were such. How did we look at the economy in those days?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It was basically a command economy, run like a military institution,
                    and this could go on, and obviously did go on for quite some time without really
                    coming apart. They were beginning to see the weaknesses and the experimentation
                    with economic reform, which Khrushchev encouraged. But they were groping with
                    something obviously extremely difficult. They haven't really worked it out even
                    today, how to reform that type economy and make it work like an efficient
                    capitalist economy. So they started playing around with little indicators, and
                    really didn't get much of anyplace with those.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were any of the Soviet economists, or the people you were
                        talking to, reflecting any disquiet or asking questions, how does your
                        system work, or something like that, or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It was hard to get to see Soviet economists. They were beginning to be
                    concerned about it, no question about that. They didn't know what to do either.
                    Some good work was being done, I learned later, out in Novorossiysk(?) and this
                    scientific academy. One of the top economists there, eventually was brought to
                    prominence, I think during the Gorbachev era, but he'd been kept under wraps
                    during all that period. But yet he'd been allowed to continue doing his work,
                    and he was attacked in the beginning for trying to tackle these problems. How
                    can we make this economy more efficient? How can we borrow from capitalism? I
                    still remember once when Khrushchev said in one of his speeches, and again
                    acknowledging the problem they had, he said, “Even after the entire world has
                    gone communist, we'll have to keep one country around as a capitalist country,
                    so we'll know how to set our prices.” That was in a public speech, because how
                    do you set the prices in a system like that, and have them make any sense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's this old story about they pretend to pay us, and
                        we pretend to work, that type of thing. Were the indicators that it was a
                        very productive work force?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No, from what my observations were, they had a lot of problems.
                    Excessive use of alcohol for example, except perhaps by the women, and
                    absenteeism. And then again, it was a so-called planned economy and they would
                    have to towards the end of the month always have a storming—a literal
                    translation—to achieve the plan, and then everybody would work twice or three
                    times as hard as normal and somehow or other they would fulfill the plan. So
                    that was another obvious thing. But you could see it too in their growing
                    weakness vis-a-vis the rest of the world in terms of advanced technology. Their
                    aircraft industry was falling way behind. Yet they had one of the largest
                    airlines in the world, for example, Aeroflot. I remember being invited to go on
                    board—actually this was in my second tour, but I'll mention it, it seems to be
                    relevant—the IL-144, which was their answer to the Concorde, a supersonic
                    passenger aircraft. They had stolen the plans from the French, and done a pretty
                    good job of copying the Concorde, except they couldn't copy the engines
                    unfortunately, so they had great trouble flying it. But I went on board that
                    plane, took some American businessmen with me, and one of them was from a paint
                    company and he said, “Ralph, run your hand along the side of the fuselage there.
                    What does it feel like?” And I said, “Paint brush marks.” And he said, “That's
                    it.” So here they are, a supersonic aircraft and they don't even have the
                    technology to put spray paint on it, so you'd see a lot of things like that.</p>
                <p>They were very defensive, of course, about their backwardness. It came up over
                    and over again, and they really were aware of it. Many times when we were turned
                    down for travel it was not because it was a military city that we wanted to go
                    to. It was because it was an area with no paved roads and that kind of thing,
                    and just mud streets and they didn't want foreigners to be seeing that kind of
                    thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Foy Kohler was the ambassador. How did he
                        operate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: He was a rather quiet man. In those days it was difficult to have very
                    much contact with the Soviet leadership, but he did the best he could on that.
                    And he had good relationships with the staff. One of the things we did in
                    Embassy Moscow, and this went on for many, many years, was to have a press
                    backgrounder for the American press corps, as I recall, was on Fridays. About 20
                    or maybe more American press people would come by and the ambassador would try
                    to give them a few insights on what had happened. This generated a little bit of
                    information for us as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The press would respond?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: And sometimes, if not during the group, they never liked to talk in
                    front of the other people, some of them would pick up something that was too hot
                    to report that might lead to their expulsion but they would share it with us
                    individually. So this was a useful relationship to maintain, and all of our
                    ambassadors tried to do that.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about security problems there? Really basic life in
                        the Soviet Union at that time? I'm thinking of surveillance.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Surveillance was just terribly heavy at all times. But not
                    particularly heavy for the economic section, unless we did something very
                    unusual and then they would pick up on it almost immediately. But they were just
                    all over the military attach�s at all times. I remember a couple times taking
                    trips with people and we always used the buddy system. If my wife couldn't go
                    with me, take someone else, and if that person were more suspect than I was,
                    we'd usually have somebody accompanying us in a rather obvious way. So that was
                    a deterrent in many ways to getting to know what was going on in the country,
                    and that is what it was intended to be.</p>
                <p>Security in the sense of theft and that kind of thing was all right. For the most
                    part we didn't even have to lock our doors in those days because, of course, the
                    KGB was every place. I understand that has changed drastically. Once in a while
                    some Soviet embassy cars have been stolen here in Washington, and we'd have
                    tit-for-tat theft of vehicles from the American embassy in Moscow. But that
                    didn't happen many times that I can recall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there at the time Kennedy was assassinated,
                        weren't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that play out there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I remember learning about it on the Voice of America. Roger Kirk was
                    living in the same building with me and he came up to tell us that Kennedy had
                    been assassinated. We rushed down and listened to the commentary on Voice of
                    America. And insofar as the Soviets were concerned, Khrushchev personally came
                    over and signed the condolence book in the embassy and was crying. They're very
                    impressed by death, perhaps because at that time they didn't believe there was
                    any place else to go. I think insofar as the man on the street was concerned, I
                    was traveling at that time, and we talked to taxi drivers, and the typical line
                    was that Kennedy had been a great man. They didn't say so while he was alive.
                    But then they'd say that Johnson is a very bad man. No real basis for that, just
                    something they didn't like about Johnson's looks. It seemed to be almost a
                    standard thing you'd pick up all across the Soviet Union. But they clearly
                    seemed to be very sorry to see Kennedy perish that way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had to deal with Soviet statistics. How did you deal
                        with them?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Basically we'd leave the super interpretation up to Washington and the
                    large number of people we had working on that kind of thing and in all parts of
                    the U.S. government. This was an overwhelming task in trying to make some sense
                    out of those statistics. It's not something we could do single handed. So what
                    we did was just try to get whatever statistics we could get that wouldn't
                    otherwise be available to Washington, and get them into Washington. We'd make a
                    special effort to get an advance copy of the foreign trade statistics, which
                    weren't classified by the Soviets, but which were of great interest to us. So
                    that was our approach in the field to getting information, anything that
                    Washington wasn't likely to learn about through some other means.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know getting information out of China, for years our
                        China hands got an awful lot from local newspapers in China. How did you
                        find the local press for that type of thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I would say it was somewhat similar to what we used to do when I was
                    in Hong Kong reading the Chinese press. But we didn't have any large section
                    translating it for us. So we had to do our own reading and analysis of the
                    press, the major newspapers, to the extent we had time. And then, of course, we
                    sent on much more than we could read to Washington for further analysis. This
                    was certainly helpful to follow the workings of their economic reform programs
                    and that kind of thing. We did a fair amount of that. Another thing we did in
                    the economic section was to meet with our western counterparts at lunch, as I
                    recall about every two weeks or so, during which we would just talk business,
                    exchange information on our trips, and what experiences we'd had with the
                    Soviets. We knew we were quite likely being taped, but we didn't care since
                    there were not high grade secrets or anything like that. And I think it was
                    mutually beneficial. We continued that during the whole time that I was there,
                    both my first and second tours. And some of the other countries obviously had a
                    little more entree than we did, because we had so relatively little foreign
                    trade with the Soviet Union. Whereas the western European countries were making
                    a much bigger effort which gave them more of an opportunity to get other
                    insights as to what was really happening in the economy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned the fall of Khrushchev, and the rise of
                        Brezhnev. Did you see any curtailment in certain economic activities and
                        enhancement of others, or anything like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: One thing that became pretty clear was that Brezhnev and his people
                    didn't have much use for the quest for economic reform. They said it hasn't been
                    successful, which was true, just a waste of time, so we'll go on with our
                    military style economy, if you will. And that didn't completely cut off the work
                    that I mentioned before in the academies on economic reform. But he just didn't
                    feel it was yielding any great results, and thought all we've got to do is
                    continue on the old way, and keep up the pressures of one kind or another
                    through the planning system. It was much harder to get close to him, than it was
                    to Khrushchev to find out what was going on. We screened the press as best we
                    could and drew our conclusions from that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about agriculture? Khrushchev had made a great deal
                        about opening up virgin lands, areas which had not been under wheat
                        cultivation, for example. What was the impression we were getting about
                        Soviet agriculture during this period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It was also having a great many problems. In the Soviet Union the land
                    mass is not Iowa, and never will be. It doesn't have the same climatic
                    conditions that we have in this country. So they have good years sometimes, and
                    then very bad years, maybe two or three years in a row. I had the opportunity to
                    visit Khrushchev's new lands on a train trip once, which was quite interesting.
                    They took a group of diplomats out there just to show them what a fine harvest
                    they had had that year. And it was indeed a good harvest. I went with our
                    Agricultural Attach�, and he confirmed that. We would try whenever possible to
                    visit the farming areas, and report on what the status of the crops was, which
                    would help the Department of Agriculture make their estimates of Soviet
                    crops.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You then left Moscow for a while. You came back to
                        Washington from '65 to '67. What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I did a tour in what used to be called the E Bureau, the EB Bureau,
                    working on international finance primarily for Dick Cooper, who later became
                    Under Secretary for Economic Affairs. This was not a terribly interesting area,
                    because we're not the main movers and shakers in the State Department insofar as
                    international finance is concerned. It was more of a liaison with Treasury,
                    releasing their telegrams and going to meetings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went back to Moscow from '67 to '69. That's a rather
                        relatively rapid turnaround, wasn't it? How did that come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Well mainly I was offered the job. It was a class 2 rated job so I did
                    have to get permission from the Department...</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the old FSO-2, now Minister Counselor.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Right. So anyway I got the approval to go there. I liked my first tour
                    and I welcomed the opportunity to go back a second time, and of course could do
                    quite a bit more having the higher rank. One of the most interesting things I
                    did during that second tour was to negotiate the opening of Aeroflot and Pan
                    American service between Moscow and the United States. This process went on for
                    well over a year with daily instructional telegrams, and I would go back with
                    what the Soviets would tell me. It gave me some insights into the military side
                    of intelligence, GRU, because almost all of Aeroflot was staffed by GRU officers
                    and when I first started going over there they'd be in full military regalia. I
                    had never seen this before. As you may have heard, Aeroflot really started out
                    as just an arm of intelligence, and they never quite broke away from that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There must have been on both sides very concerned ideas
                        about what route they would fly, because obviously you have to assume that
                        there are cameras going off. Were their routes over the United States very
                        carefully monitored?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I don't think we were really worried much about what they might do
                    from that point of view. But I think they were more worried about us. One of the
                    things that complicated these negotiations was their insistence on introducing
                    this new all-jet(?) aircraft rather than the old turboprops that they were using
                    on their own runs, which made them look very backward. They were using these on
                    their run to Japan, and the Japanese press would poke fun at them all the time.
                    It really bothered them. So they insisted on waiting until this Ilyushin 62 was
                    ready for flight, and of course, it had never really flown anyplace. So part of
                    my job was to get the data on this, so we would be convinced that it was a safe
                    aircraft to bring to the United States. This was like pulling teeth. I learned
                    later they had never had to do this sort of thing. They just somehow or other
                    put these planes together without too much testing, what speeds they'd do, this,
                    that and the other thing. So I got these detailed instructions from FAA on what
                    kind of documentation they would have to provide us. This is one of the things
                    that slowed up the process a lot because the man who gave me this nicely printed
                    book on the character, and the qualities of the Ilyushin 62, confessed to me,
                    “We've never done this before.” In the meanwhile, Washington suspected that the
                    delay was being called by political reasons, and it wasn't political at all. It
                    was just technological reasons. But anyway, once I got this book NASA said could
                    I have an extra copy and he said, “There aren't any more.” I sent that in and
                    that quieted Washington down for a while. So finally they scheduled a proving
                    flight. They had the rights to fly to Canada, to Montreal, and they would go to
                    Montreal and there they would be met by a couple FAA pilots, and then they would
                    go down and make a missed approach over Logan airport in Boston, and then a
                    missed approach over Kennedy, and a missed approach over the Philadelphia
                    airport, and then finally down to Dulles airport. They weren't allowed to land
                    at any of these other airports, because the Port Authority in New York, for
                    example, wouldn't even give them the rights until they had gone through all the
                    tests on the ground. Finally we got around this because the federal government
                    owns Dulles airport and they had to accept that. There were some other things
                    that the New York authority required. I didn't go on that flight, but later I
                    talked to one of the FAA pilots and he told me, “You know, if it had been any
                    country other than the Soviet Union that sent these pilots over on this
                    aircraft, I would have sent them back.” But he said, “The pilots who he felt
                    were fairly good pilots came over and the only flight paths they had were
                    penciled lines on an old National Geographic map, over these congested areas.
                    That's all they had with them.” The pilots though did accept the idea of getting
                    additional training in the United States before they started flying. They could
                    see how terribly congested it was around the New York area. They had nothing
                    like that. But their bosses didn't want to agree to that. Again, Russian pride
                    coming out. Eventually they did agree to it.</p>
                <p>Oh, one of the things the FAA pilot told me about the inside of the plane was
                    that this was one of the early models. It was so badly balanced that the
                    attitude could only be kept on the level through big tanks of water which the
                    pilots with very strong arms(?) could shift the water around, two tons of water,
                    and showed how poor the plane was. They cracked up quite a few of those. I think
                    they had improved models later on. I think they still use it even today, but it
                    was four jets in the rear. So this gave me some additional insights into the
                    weaknesses of the great threat to the United States.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about Ambassador Llewellyn Thompson who was there at
                        that time? How did he operate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: He operated in sort of, to use his own terms, more or less in splendid
                    isolation. He kept contrasting what he did during this tour with what he had
                    been able to do much earlier. I can't remember the exact time frame, way before
                    I was there. He was able to have direct contact with Khrushchev in the earlier
                    Khrushchev period, and just be a one man embassy. So when he came back this
                    time, he said several times, “It doesn't really matter because my boys,”
                    referring to the counselors of embassy, “now can have contacts that they
                    couldn't have earlier.” This was generally speaking true. But he found it rather
                    frustrating, I think, not to be able to do that. I remember when I first met him
                    when I arrived he said, “Now remember, always distinguish between my telegrams
                    and embassy telegrams, if there's a first person in there I want to see it. It's
                    nothing new but he was very much conscious of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about your contacts? Did you find as
                        Minister-Counselor it was a different world?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It improved quite a lot, yes. I was doing more things such as that
                    Aeroflot business. But I also got involved in merchant marine affairs. This was
                    a very useful ministry, and I had quite a few contacts over there. This stemmed
                    from the fact that the Soviet's actually goes back to my first tour, had really
                    decided to import grain from the United States for the first time in history. I
                    had to go down to Odessa to look at the port, and see how we could get that
                    grain in because, Odessa had been created back before communism as a grain
                    exporting port, not an importing port, so everything was sort of wrong. I
                    remember negotiating with the Ministry of the Merchant Marine, and they said,
                    “Of course, you don't have most-favored-nation treatment on the shipping rates.
                    You'll have to pay the higher non-most favored rates.” And I reported that back
                    to Washington. I didn't know one way or the other. Washington came back and
                    said, “But we do have most- favored-nation treatment. We signed an agreement
                    with them in 1937, and we are pouching you the book on that, the published
                    volume.” So I remember taking that into the Ministry of Merchant Marine, and
                    they were really impressed, reading from this. So they had to acknowledge it and
                    I heard later from somebody else in one of the other ministries (this was the
                    talk of the Soviet bureaucrats at that time), that I had come in with that big
                    book of treaties and found something they weren't really aware of. So they
                    backed off. I found that if you did your guest list properly, you could
                    occasionally have working luncheons with Soviets. Not with other nationalities
                    usually, just Americans and Soviets, including someone who was a KGB type. That
                    relaxed them a little bit. So we did a number of luncheons like that. We all had
                    to speak Russian reasonably well to be assigned to Moscow in the first place,
                    and have the luncheons in Russian.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the feeling Leonid Brezhnev within the embassy?
                        He was fairly new on the scene as a leader. How did you all evaluate him at
                        that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: He was so much less visible than Khrushchev, that he was sort of a
                    puzzle, I think, to evaluate. This was something they worked very hard on in the
                    political section just using standard Kremlinological techniques. They got more
                    and more little insights into what the man was like and what he was doing. But
                    he had a very different style, of course, from that of Khrushchev.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Kremlinology is trying to figure out whose is doing what
                        to whom, and who is ranking where.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Oh, all that sort of thing. Reading the press very, very carefully,
                    looking for any little minor thing. It's a technique that did yield some
                    benefits, not an awful lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But in the economic field, you didn't have to worry about
                        that too much, did you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Not too much, no, except again we did our kind of detective work
                    looking to see what they were doing with economic reform, and major plans, major
                    industries and that kind of thing. But the real fine analysis had by necessity
                    to be done back here in Washington in INR or CIA. They had the staff to really
                    go through this stuff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that there was any economic analysis coming
                        out of the Soviet press? Or was it pretty much just displaying whatever the
                        bureau or the...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I wouldn't really call it analysis in our sense of the word very
                    often. Again, you're just looking for reporting of things that are going on in
                    particular industries, and their annual plan reports, and all of that sort of
                    thing. So there was not too much that we could rely on there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any insight into economic training at the
                        universities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I tried to, and I did get a card to go to the Lenin Library, actually
                    something of a privilege, which is quite an experience. The lady librarian there
                    said, “You're free to look at anything here. You go from one room to another.”
                    She had a key that would lock the door behind me. Also, I used to call, from
                    time to time, at part of the Academy of Science that dealt with economics and
                    these conversations were occasionally worth reporting. They didn't really open
                    up the office safe or anything like that, but they were allowed some academic
                    freedom.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Economics is such an international science. Were they at
                        all plugged into the economic international role? I mean would John Kenneth
                        Galbraith come over and talk or vice versa.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, sometimes somebody like that would come over. Galbraith came
                    over, but not to discuss economics. But we did have other luminaries and they
                    would be invited to go out to Moscow State University to give a lecture on some
                    topic. And the approved people, the advanced people in their university could do
                    that. But in terms of setting up anything that was equivalent to the kind of
                    training we have in this country for economics, no. I understand they have great
                    difficulty in even starting that up now. I read something just recently and they
                    were still using old textbooks from the Soviet era. So there was very little of
                    that going on. Yet there were some high level contacts—a man who was number two
                    in the powerful State Committee for Science and Technology. He developed and it
                    exists today, a special relationship with the Sloan Institute at MIT. He's a
                    very powerful figure, his name, as you might guess, is a Georgian name. The
                    Georgians would always get along, and he may have been involved in one of these
                    spy scandals earlier, but it didn't hurt him. I always found that the State
                    Committee for Science and Technology was a more useful place to go than the
                    Ministry of Foreign Trade. These were my two prime ministries. But it was very
                    much dominated by the KGB, and the GRU, the top intelligence organizations. But
                    they had very bright people, and they were sufficiently confident so that they
                    could talk to you. They were great door openers. If I wanted to go out to a
                    visit out to the Baltic states, for example, I would see if I couldn't get their
                    help and get me some appointments out there, as well as the Foreign Trade
                    Ministry. But the mission of the State Committee for Science and Technology was,
                    as the name suggests, to acquire foreign technology, by fair means or foul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there much interest in Soviet developments in science
                        from the outside? I mean outside the Soviet Union.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Oh, yes, a great deal. In fact while I was there, during my first
                    tour, we sent our first science officer over, Glenn Schweitzer, who has been
                    working the Soviet beat ever since then, not out of the State Department, but
                    out of the Academy of Science, our Academy of Sciences. I saw him just recently.
                    Since then we have always had a science officer there, and they've been able to
                    do some useful reporting. They were a little more independent insofar as
                    security was concerned than other parts of the Soviet regime we dealt with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Vietnam War play any particular role?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Oh, very definitely. It made it much harder for us to have really high
                    level contacts, and they were constantly indicating their displeasure with us.
                    However, it's interesting we mentioned Ambassador Thompson before. He retired
                    from that job before the end of his tour and, to our amazement, Gromyko gave a
                    dinner in his honor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was Foreign Minister at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, and selected people down to the consular level with wives. It was
                    one of the most interesting dinners I've ever attended anyplace, but certainly
                    in the Soviet Union. They had it in a special room in the Dome Media, the
                    Foreign Ministry's house, that we didn't even know existed. All of the
                    silverware, well it wasn't silverware, it was all goldware stuff they'd gotten
                    from the Czars, I guess. There were beautifully printed menus at each place, and
                    all the waiters were wearing white tie, and the seating was all according to
                    protocol in relative rank. There were the same number of Soviets as there were
                    American embassy people. There were some of their prominent Deputy Foreign
                    Ministers there. People that we had never really had much of a chance to meet
                    before. But basically you could not have much conversation with anybody except
                    your dinner partner. The two women surrounding me looked over with envy at my
                    wife who was sitting between these two very interesting ministers. One of them,
                    whose name escapes me now, was the one who was really running Czechoslovakia
                    (this was after the invasion of Czechoslovakia), often called the pro-consul. He
                    said a number of interesting things, and Ambassador Thompson did get a chance to
                    chide him about, “I hope you get out of Czechoslovakia soon,” and things like
                    that. But it was just a beautifully done dinner and must have cost an arm and a
                    leg.</p>
                <p>So despite the other frictions, they decided for some reason or other to do that.
                    I think they respected Ambassador Thompson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He played a major role in the Cuban crisis to help defuse
                        the thing. I don't know if they knew how an important a role he played.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, and certainly Gromyko would have known that. So that may have
                    been a part of that. I think you're right there. I don't know whether that
                    custom continued or not. I think Thompson was a very great exception.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the Czech...well, it was Czech spring of '68 and
                        Czechoslovakia seemed to be moving towards a much more liberal regime, and
                        then it was put down very harshly by the Warsaw Pact led by the Soviet
                        Union. How did that play on our relations?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Not so much on our own relations directly, but it was fascinating to
                    follow this. In fact I began to listen to Radio Prague at night and wondered how
                    they could ever say this sort of thing in their English language broadcasts. But
                    they also had Russian language broadcasts. I remember discussing the situation
                    with a Soviet economist who had just returned from Czechoslovakia where he had
                    lectured. I said to him, “Do you really think they pose a threat to you?” And he
                    led me over to the wall where there was a big map of Eastern Europe and
                    Czechoslovakia and you could see Czechoslovakia like a dagger aimed at the heart
                    of the Soviet Union. It was about a couple of weeks later that the invasion took
                    place. I first became aware of it as we had two Pan American flights. (After
                    we'd gotten the Aeroflot flights, we got that air service started.) So we had an
                    aircraft full of Americans trapped out someplace in the southern part of the
                    Soviet Union. They weren't really trapped but I guess they were quite
                    concerned.</p>
                <p>And I did personally help the Czech delegation get home. It also coincided with
                    the World Power Conference, which is something that still takes place every four
                    years or so. The head of it at that time was the Chairman of the Board of the
                    major utility in Detroit, I can't think of the name of it now, and he came to me
                    as Economic Counselor. I was backstopping them, and he said, “The Czech
                    delegation had come to him and they are so upset about what's happening to their
                    country, they'd like to get back home.” Then we somehow or other got
                    transportation for them. I said, “Aeroflot is the only answer.” So we did manage
                    to get an Aeroflot plane that flew their whole delegation back home, so they
                    could see their relatives. This certainly created great problems for the
                    Soviets. We had been following it closely and we still don't know to this day at
                    what point they put live ammunition in their tanks that were maneuvering on the
                    border. Still I don't know why they didn't go in and take Yugoslavia. Somehow or
                    other they were quite clearly planning...and the Yugoslavia ambassador, whom I
                    knew fairly well, was like a cat on a hot tin roof, very nervous about that.</p>
                <p>I remember talking to men and women on the street, at the skating rink about
                    Czechoslovakia, “Well, these ungrateful so-and-so's. Here Dubcek, he was one of
                    ours because he could speak excellent Russian. He had studied in the Soviet
                    Union, and for him to turn on us like that was just inexcusable.” Then of
                    course, I didn't see it myself, but they brought poor Dubcek in the back of a
                    truck to Moscow and, then the story was, he was later physically slapped by
                    Brezhnev. Brezhnev had had quite a lot to drink, I guess, and he was pretty
                    angry too. But poor Dubcek did eventually get back home, and went to Bratislava
                    and was given some kind of a job. I guess he's still living today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in 1969 and went back to the War College
                        for a year—'69 to '70. That was just after the Tet Offensive. How was the
                        Navy viewing Vietnam? What did you get from the people you were working
                        with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I think not only the Navy but I think all of us felt that this was
                    still, at the time, a war that should be won, and wasn't being won.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>The Naval War College at that time was a very fine place to study, had an
                    excellent library, and I was able to be a part-time student at Brown in their
                    political science department. The Navy expands. They had few out-reach programs
                    like that so it was an interesting experience just working with the Armed Forces
                    members of the other college on papers and that kind of thing, the same thing as
                    at other War Colleges. Anyway, after that I ended up with an assignment in
                    ACDA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Arms Control &amp; Disarmament Agency.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: The two fit together to some extent. I was chief of the Arms Control
                    Division, conventional arms, a very frustrating business needless to say because
                    nobody was interested in that subject either within the U.S. government or
                    elsewhere. I ran it as sort of a research operation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that time, the '70 to '73 period, it wasn't going
                        anywhere. Gerard Smith was the boss, wasn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I only saw him a couple of times, and he worked almost exclusively on
                    the nuclear side of things. I wasn't in that at all. It was very
                    compartmentalized.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were dealing with armament, is that right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Just conventional arms, not nuclear arms and there are very few
                    agreements in that field.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Nuclear is the place where the real concern is. How about
                        the Pentagon?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Well, again, there were very few things that came up for negotiation,
                    although this all contributed to my background which was useful in my next
                    assignment which was Kenya where I personally helped them acquire a whole
                    squadron of F-5s to deal with the threat from Idi Amin and from Somalia, which
                    the Kenyans were very much concerned about. We set up a special training program
                    for them in the United States and I came back for negotiations under the FMS
                    program. So all of this did...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's nothing like being in a disarmament agency to
                        understand how you can get armory to a friendly nation. I think the Italians
                        would describe this assignment as a parenthesis in a way. It was a holding
                        action. Then you went to Nairobi from '73 to '77 as Deputy Chief of Mission.
                        How did that come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Well, through the personnel system. I didn't have any inside pull. I
                    heard later on they gave the ambassador at that time, Ambassador McIlvaine,
                    three names. Mine was one of them, he knew the other two and didn't like them. I
                    don't know that. That may be wrong. So that was a fantastic assignment and it is
                    one of the nicest places in all of Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation, '73 to '77 period, in Kenya at
                        that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Well, at that time Kenya was one of the leading countries, in our
                    opinion, in Africa. It's a mixed economy but with a lot of freedom. It wasn't at
                    all like the Tanzanian economy when it was being choked by Julius Nyerere, and
                    other economies where they were pursuing a strictly socialistic approach. So the
                    Kenyan economy was quite prosperous. President Kenyatta was alive during the
                    entire period I was there. A very interesting old character, and a laissez faire
                    type of man, but still not a great delegator. They always had trouble when I was
                    dealing with military subjects. They'd tell me how difficult it was to get a
                    decision out of him, and how he wouldn't delegate. By then he was somewhat over
                    eighty, and his attention span was increasingly short. And one man told me, he
                    said, “Every day I go over with a stack of papers this high, and then I come out
                    with a stack about that high. Then I go back in the next day and I've got to
                    rearrange everything again; so some things never got to the top,” such as
                    creditation of diplomats, which tended to be lower priority. Kenyatta's mind
                    would wander quite a bit. I remember he had a certain speech that he'd say to
                    all ambassadors, or chiefs of mission. For long periods I was Charg� d'Affaires
                    because there was no ambassador there, and he'd say, “Please remember my door is
                    always open,” in English, which he spoke very well. I studied Kikuyu at one time
                    too during his late reign. The Kikuyuans were so dominant in that regime that
                    they would speak Kikuyu to each other in front of non-Kikulan Kenyans, which was
                    very bad form. So I thought, “Well, I'll start studying this language.” Terribly
                    difficult, and 32 noun classes, and that kind of thing, really almost their
                    secret language. But I did speak to Kenyatta in Kikuyu. I don't think he really
                    liked it. It's a little bit like Arabic. You run into that problem, too.
                    sometimes. But It's their secret language and if you speak fluent Arabic, which
                    I don't, but I have seen people do it, you must be from CIA. I ran into a little
                    bit of that psychology in Kenya.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long was McIlvaine there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: We only overlapped four days, and I was on my own. But he did stay on
                    in Kenya, not in any official U.S. government capacity, in a wildlife
                    organization. But it was fully a year before he was replaced by Tony Marshall
                    who was a political appointee. It was his third political appointment, and his
                    mother is Mrs..., well anyway, very monied and she had made a big contribution
                    to Nixon's campaign and he'd been held up because of that. He turned out to be
                    really an excellent ambassador. We worked very well together.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm surprised because usually after someone has been a
                        Charg� for about a year they become spoiled. They're used to running the
                        show, and then a new ambassador comes and so the word is it is best to get
                        rid of that person as quickly as possible because it doesn't work.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It worked it out very well. Somebody had talked to him in Washington.
                    Somebody who wanted the job for more of an Africanist than I. He said, “No, I'll
                    see how I do with Lindstrom.” One of the things I did to put him at ease was to
                    schedule a trip out of Nairobi just a few days after he got there. After making
                    some basic introductions, we went to visit Ethiopia with my wife, who had never
                    been there. Unfortunately our arrival in Addis Ababa coincided with the first
                    day of the revolution and we had to cancel all of our trips on Ethiopian
                    Airways. We had to cancel our trip to the old caves and churches in Ethiopia,
                    and retreat to Nairobi. But I didn't show up in the embassy. I went on down to
                    Mombasa and spent the rest of our vacation down there. But that gave the
                    ambassador a chance, I think, to be in direct touch with all of the other
                    embassy officers and he did not have to feel that I was keeping anything from
                    him. So we worked very effectively together during the rest of his tour.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were some of the major issues that you had to deal
                        with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: The most important ones really did tend to be in the security area and
                    the defense area. You may recall that the Entebbe raid took place at that
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You better describe what the Entebbe raid was.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: This was a raid by the Israelis on Entebbe airport to rescue Israelis
                    who were being held hostage by Idi Amin. It was quite a successful operation,
                    and they could not have done it without the complicity and support of the Kenyan
                    government. They had been in secret and very close contact with the Kenyans on
                    this; so the Kenyans gave them refueling rights, after they had made the raid on
                    the Entebbe airport, at Nairobi airport. They also dropped off their wounded who
                    were taken to the hospital in Nairobi. Of course, this became known to Idi Amin.
                    He was just furious about this, so he was determined forever after to get even
                    with Kenya. He had more armaments than the Kenyans had. He had some MiGs,
                    MiG-17s or MiG-19s. I'm not sure which, but it was more than the Kenyans had.
                    They had some old outmoded British aircraft. So they began to take this threat
                    seriously, and the head of the Defense Ministry with whom I dealt regularly,
                    made inquiries. He said, “We're not having much luck with the British. They
                    don't seem to think we need any more advanced aircraft. What about F-5s or
                    something like that?” So I said, “We can look into that.” So people from
                    Northrop did come in and make presentations to the Kenyans. This, of course,
                    didn't resolve the problem of how they would pay for them. That was another
                    matter for negotiation. But it finally all went through, and they did get a
                    squadron of F-5s, and the training to go with them, and stationed these planes
                    up in the northern part of the country. Once, before they got these planes, Idi
                    Amin was threatening to bomb Nairobi airport. We sent in all the way across the
                    Pacific some aircraft that the Navy had.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Orions, probably.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, and we had them land ostentatiously at Nairobi airport, and kept
                    them parked there for a time as a deterrent. It worked. Idi Amin, if he was
                    seriously thinking about bombing Nairobi airport, decided not to do that. On
                    another occasion, just to show support for the Kenyans, before they got their
                    own aircraft, we did a fly-over on National Day off a flat-top off the coast of
                    Mombasa. It worked quite well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A flat-top is a Naval aircraft carrier.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: A small aircraft carrier. These were not enough for regular fixed wing
                    aircraft. I remember later on my counterpart in the Soviet embassy was just
                    furious with me. He said, “Ralph, why didn't you tell me about that? My
                    ambassador saw these American planes come over and knew nothing about it.” And I
                    said, “Well, I'm sorry. We don't work for the same organization exactly.” So
                    then they landed the planes there in Nairobi, refueled them, and sent them back
                    later. Up until then the Kenyans had been planning again with their Israeli
                    friends. The Israelis had a very close relationship with them, as I mentioned
                    before. They said they would fly some of their planes over and would put on
                    black face. The ambassador and I thought that was the stupidest idea we'd ever
                    heard of. So we conjured up this idea of coming in with our own planes, which
                    were American planes, not with Israeli markings, or Kenyan markings, or anything
                    like that. It went off well.</p>
                <p>All in all, it was a very interesting tour. Both Ambassador Marshall and I did a
                    lot of traveling around, meeting people in all parts of the country, very
                    friendly people. I got to know more about Kenya than I did about the United
                    States, I think, in political terms. They are always willing to discuss
                    politics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the role of the British expatriates there at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: By then it was not very significant, and being phased out. The people
                    who were staying tended more to be just retired people. Some of them even had
                    gone to South Africa and thought it was so horrible they came back to Kenya. So
                    they were playing less and less of a role. In fact, the head of the Defense
                    Ministry, told me, “Well, Ralph, it's a very important day. This is the last day
                    any British presence will be in our compound.” And he said, “You're the only
                    person who can come in.” He would not allow us to bring in any attach�s or
                    anything like that. The Pentagon kept pushing us to put this up, “No, we don't
                    need it.” So I had my political counselor get training on how to do training
                    assignments for the Kenyan pilots. Curt Kamman, who is now our ambassador in
                    Bolivia, did an excellent job. He flew up to Germany and got the training
                    necessary, and another one of our political officers too. So that satisfied the
                    Kenyans that we weren't bringing in too many military people. We did later on
                    have to bring in technical people when the F-5s were delivered, but I wasn't
                    there at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about tribal politics? Does this play much of a
                        role?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, a very, very great role. As I mentioned earlier, the Kikuyuans
                    were overly dominant and were resented by the other tribes. And after Kenyatta
                    went, there was more diversification, and they tried to balance constantly. They
                    balanced within the armed forces. They'd have one tribe the head of the navy,
                    one tribe head of the army, one tribe head of the air force. But there was no
                    getting around that this was a major factor. The only troubles they had really
                    were with the Somalis who are very difficult to get along with, as we Americans
                    learned later on...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They're a contentious crew.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: There are about 400,000 Kenyans of Somali origin and the Somalis were
                    a real thorn in the side of the Kenyans. They would come over, not necessarily
                    government sponsored, probably not, raids way deep into Kenya territory to
                    capture cattle, and game trophies, and that sort of thing, all the way over to
                    Mombasa, and then up in the north. I later learned that they had this very
                    careful balancing among major tribes when I asked about the Somalis in the armed
                    forces. They said they had one, just a token. So they considered them to be
                    something very much apart. I used to meet with the Somali ambassador from time
                    to time for lunch, a rather interesting person. My ambassador didn't want to
                    meet with him, so I said, “Okay, I'll meet with him.” A very tricky sort of
                    person, spoke excellent English.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about with Tanganyika? What were relations like as far
                        as you were seeing them?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I went down there several times and crossing the border from Kenya
                    into Tanzania was like crossing the border from Europe into a communist country.
                    Immediately you got over to the Tanzanian side, it had that rundown, neglected
                    look. Everything was state owned. Tanzania was blessed by having a large number
                    of very small tribes, unlike Kenya which has a small number of very big tribes,
                    which makes Kenya a little more difficult to manage. But still the Tanzanians
                    did have one very aggressive and enterprising tribe that lived up around Mount
                    Kilimanjaro. They were the coffee farmers, about 400,000 strong. They could not
                    stand that socialist regime, so increasingly, since they weren't permitted to
                    grow coffee very well, they would vote with their feet and walk over to Kenya.
                    They were very much like the Kikuyuans in terms of attitudes. I've met many
                    Tanzanian diplomats down there when I visited people and we would discuss the
                    Kenyan way versus the Tanzanian way of running an economy. And, of course, they
                    would always defend what they were doing down there, but I don't think very
                    wholeheartedly. Since then Julius Nyerere has had to give up most of his
                    control. He had a British woman adviser for many, many years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was straight out of the Fabian socialist thing. I
                        think the Fabian socialists probably did more damage than Marx and Lenin
                        combined.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: And then I also did travel around. I did get down to South Africa too
                    because this subject kept coming up and this was very useful to see first hand
                    how things were in Johannesburg.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get over to Uganda?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Uganda, I did. I was sent there on an official mission to meet with
                    Idi Amin, which was one of the more interesting things I did. We had closed our
                    embassy by then because he had made it just impossible. Bob Keeley closed
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We sort of slipped out.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes. Anyway, the reason for my going out there was I guess I was more
                    expendable than our ambassador. Idi Amin, at the time I went there, was head of
                    the Organization of African Unity, first chairman. It's a revolving
                    chairmanship. So I went up with instructions to see if I couldn't get him to
                    support our policy on Angola. I flew up, all alone on a commercial aircraft, and
                    went to the leading hotel there. Fortunately I had taken food along with me, as
                    I used to in the old Soviet Union, because the hotel was so run down at that
                    time there was practically no food to be had there. Then the next morning I was
                    picked up by a government Mercedes and taken to one of Idi Amin's hideouts. I
                    discovered that the young man in the car from the Foreign Ministry was Russian
                    speaking, so I spoke with him in Russian. He had been educated in the Soviet
                    Union. And the German ambassador who was representing our interests there, also
                    rendezvoused with us at the hideout. So there were really only the three of us,
                    Idi Amin, the German ambassador who didn't participate in the conversation, and
                    I. I had a yellow legal tablet with me. Then there were two guys with tape
                    recorders, two military people. We had about a one-hour meeting...I think it was
                    actually longer than that. And the next day my picture was on the front page of
                    the Uganda newspaper with Idi Amin. He agreed to everything I suggested in my
                    talking points. He said, “All right, I'm going off to visit so-and-so, a couple
                    of African leaders. I will tell them what you presented to me.” And he actually
                    held that position all the way up until he could see it was going to go the
                    other way up in Addis, where the meeting was being held.</p>
                <p>But the more interesting thing was his personal pitch to me. “Please tell your
                    president that if you were as generous in your arms supply policy as the Soviet
                    Union is, every black African country would be your friend.” I said, “I would
                    report what you have to say, but I have no instructions on this subject.” And he
                    said, “Do you think I would have these inferior Soviet aircraft if I could get
                    first-rate American aircraft?” And, of course, there was absolutely no interest
                    in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is one of the major terrors of the time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: So I was quite relieved in a way when I was sitting right next to this
                    man who had personally and otherwise been responsible for so many untimely
                    deaths. He ran this so-called state research bureau, and looking into his eyes I
                    remembered people had said to me, “Well, the Israelis were peddling the story
                    that he has tertiary syphilis. Did you look into his eyes and did you see it?” I
                    said I wouldn't know what to look for, but he looked like a fairly healthy
                    individual.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He's still around in Saudi Arabia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, he was in Saudi Arabia when I was there, being sheltered by the
                    Saudis.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, why don't we stop at this point? And then we'll pick
                        up when you go to Dhahran.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Sure. I think I've said about all that's worth saying about the Kenyan
                    experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, unless you think of something.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Today is December 6th, 1994. Ralph, you were assigned to Dhahran, which is sort
                    of unusual wasn't it? You went there as Consul General, because you're not an
                    Arabist. You'd been in Africa before and had other things, and all of a sudden
                    to end up in Dhahran at a time when the area was particularly sensitive. Had the
                    oil shock hit at that point? Or one of the oil shocks?</p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It was just beginning to hit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that assignment come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Well, this was an unexpected assignment. My predecessor was
                    transferred I think somewhat unexpectedly, and the position suddenly came open.
                    Ideally, I think, you'd put an Arabist in there, but there weren't any available
                    and Joe Twinam, who was the Assistant Secretary, gave me a call and I went
                    around and talked to him, and he said, “How would you like to go there?” He gave
                    me about one month's notice, and I said I'd like to take a little bit of Arabic.
                    I took a couple of week's worth and then studied it at the post. But, of course,
                    with a difficult language you can't do a great deal there. One of my
                    credentials, of course, was my economic background because it is a very
                    important post economically and from the point of view of economic reporting.
                    But my arrival there coincided with some very major political developments.</p>
                <p>And coincident with my arrival, up until then everything was basically given to
                    us. There was all the data just put in the mail and delivered to the
                    Consulate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is through ARAMCO.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: The Saudis had been moving in a very Saudi-like way, to gradually take
                    over ARAMCO, and about the time I got there it was widely considered to be
                    Saudiized, and no longer would they be willing to give the details of their
                    natural resources.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Talk about your relations with the oil company. I was
                        there from 1958 to 1960. The Americans were running things completely
                        really. And our relations, of course, were very close, and also it wasn't
                        seen as critical at that time as it became. Here you had the Saudis taking
                        over all elements of ARAMCO. Could you contact the Saudis within ARAMCO, or
                        was this difficult?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: By and large, not. This was not a very rapid take-over. It was a very
                    gradual take-over. It's not necessarily even completed today, and this was
                    typical of the style of the Saudi ruling family, the royal family. Now I think a
                    couple of the senior Saudis are at the point where they are primary sources of
                    anything that is going on. But it was a very gradual process. I used to meet
                    with the people in government affairs to some degree, but they were shut out of
                    the thing pretty much once it became Saudiized. I mean in terms of being a
                    contact for me. They still have an office here in Washington, and once in a
                    while I run across a fellow who is working...I think he's the boss and then an
                    American. So a lot of those things remain as they were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had an embassy which had Petroleum Affairs and had his
                        contacts. What was your beat. What were you supposed to be doing on the oil
                        business?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Basically finding out what their production plans were, and how high
                    they could go. This was no longer publicly announced, as I mentioned before. It
                    was of great importance, I think, to the outside world to know what production
                    they could manage, what obstacles they were running into, and making up for the
                    Iranian shortfall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you gathering at least from the eastern province
                        point of view, which was your beat? Was the attitude of the Saudis that you
                        had contact with towards the Iranians, and what was going on in Iran at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I don't remember having any prolonged conversations on that subject. I
                    think they all opposed it, and, of course, the eastern province is where most of
                    the Shiites in Saudi Arabia live. This was one of the most important
                    developments during my tour there. You might say the politicization of the
                    Shiite community which we estimated numbered maybe 20,000-30,000 and maybe a
                    little more, partly in the oasis, and part in the oasis to the north. We
                    employed quite a number of Shiites from that community in the Consulate General
                    doing mechanics work, and that kind of thing. A very large numbers of Shiites
                    were employed by ARAMCO, and had been by ARAMCO for a long, long time. ARAMCO is
                    the one that first gave them their real opportunity to get out of real genuine
                    poverty. And they did very well in ARAMCO. They kept their religion to
                    themselves pretty much, and had not become political activists at all until
                    Khomeini came along. And this, of course, was about the time when I arrived
                    there. And then there began to be all sorts of political ferment, tapes of
                    Khomeini speaking Arabic, which is a religious language, were best sellers, were
                    going all around the province and in the worship houses, of the Shiites. I knew
                    some prominent Shiites, businessmen primarily, but didn't really seem to want to
                    get into political conversations particularly. But everyday the radios from Iran
                    in Arabic were aiming right at the Shiite community and Saudi Arabia, in
                    general, right across the gulf. And that added to the effect of the tape
                    recorders of Khomeini's religious pronouncements of one kind or another. So
                    everyone began to become much more conscious of security in ARAMCO at that time.
                    There began to be graffiti around, anti-Saudi graffiti on the walls in ARAMCO.
                    And yet, the Shiite employees were the ones working in the most sensitive
                    installations because they were the ones, the plumbers and mechanics and people
                    who worked with their hands, whereas the Sunni generally were the office
                    workers. So this created a problem, dilemma, for the Saudis in management of the
                    oil company. Some people they no longer trusted fully, working in the most
                    sensitive installations, Riyadh and Dhahran, the big pumping stations where the
                    big super tankers were loaded. Anyone with skill and intention, and had a mind
                    toward sabotage, could do an awful lot of damage there. Fortunately it didn't
                    happen. And I think it was a relatively small proportion of the Shiites who
                    became politicized, and later over time arrests were made and I don't know how
                    many people were finally detained by the government but there were quite a
                    number.</p>
                <p>Ironically, I think, some of the Shiites became somewhat anti-American, and yet
                    everything they had managed to achieve they really owed to an American
                    institution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just to put it in context, the Shiites were a minority
                        living in an area which had been strictly a province. They were
                        predominately almost fanatically anti-Shiite, weren't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, but still they aren't that new. They came there very quietly and
                    settled, and Sheik al-Ka told me about this. His family were a very important
                    merchant family, and very friendly with the Shiite, even though he's not Shiite.
                    They were there when they came and settled in that area, moving down from the
                    head of the Gulf. There were a lot of very interesting migrations there. But as
                    an example of their anti-American fervor among some of them, I was dis-invited
                    from a speech that I had planned to make to a group, not Dhahran, and the person
                    explained, he's was rather embarrassed about it, but he said, “There are a lot
                    of feelings now because of what's going on across the Gulf.”</p>
                <p>So then moving on, this is in the following year...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So we're talking about...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: '78, I arrived in the summer of '78, and of course the revolution was
                    just getting underway in Iran, and the oil was beginning to be affected. Then we
                    moved on into '79 and things were sort of going from bad to worse. We had the
                    taking of the Great Mosque, which I wasn't involved in, that was in the other
                    side of the kingdom.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was by Sunni radicals.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I don't know if they ever analyzed it fully. Not long after that, the
                    first day of the year 1400—and I can't remember what this was on the western
                    calendar, I guess it was in October or November—the beginning of Muharram, this
                    is when the Shiite traditional do celebrate the first ten days of the calendar.
                    I think they were already in a high state of tension because of the things that
                    had been going on, and the agitation by the Iranians. But on the, I think it was
                    the seventh day of Muharram, things had been quiet up until then, there was a
                    very serious incident up in the a Shiite town just north of, (its name escapes
                    me right now). The young Shiite boys were out throwing stones at passing
                    traffic, as they've always done. I've had stones thrown at me all over the
                    Middle East, in Afghanistan, for example. And along came a Saudi National Guard
                    vehicle, and if there's anybody that hates Shiites it's the National Guardsmen
                    who are real Wahhabis, and they didn't take kindly to having stones thrown at
                    them. One of them just picked up an automatic weapon, and sprayed the crowd,
                    killing four or five boys. This set off three days of what you might call
                    rioting, and they had to send in helicopter gun ships to put it down. This had
                    never been in the newspapers. We checked it out. My estimates of the number of
                    people killed were estimates that I did get from Saudi security officials.
                    Something like maybe 50 to 60 Shiite were killed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's very serious.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: This was mainly in Al Qatif where they started seizing police
                    stations. It was a real threat to security in the eyes of the rulers of Saudi
                    Arabia. Then they ended up even fighting over the dead bodies. The Shiite wanted
                    to collect their dead and not have them thrown out in the desert in Wahhabi
                    style. The Shiite believe more like as we do, having burial sites. So that led
                    to further skirmishes between the two factions. But throughout all this period
                    our Consulate employees disappeared. I remember when they did come back finally,
                    our gardener at the Consul General's residence was an old Shiite they called
                    Hajj because he had made the pilgrimages to the holy places in Iran. He wouldn't
                    think of going to the holy places in Saudi Arabia. Everybody called him Hajj. He
                    was in a really foul mood, and he came in and picked radishes from the garden he
                    had raised for us. I was later told by our cook that he just threw the radishes
                    at him, and said, “That's for these...” and calling us some kind of a name as
                    Americans. He had been radicalized like everyone else, which rather surprised
                    me. But again, the oil production did go on, and there was never any serious
                    incident of sabotage. I remember getting some rather strange phone calls in the
                    Consulate from people with sort of veiled threats, and wanting to meet with me.
                    For the most part I brushed those aside as provocations.</p>
                <p>So much was happening simultaneously that it's almost hard to pick up all the
                    threads and how they interrelated. One of the things, of course, that was of
                    great interest to the Saudis was the annual Hajj. That was a little bit before
                    the rioting of the Shiite. The Saudi police would count the Hajjis who would
                    come in at the border with Kuwait, and then notice that these same vehicles were
                    half empty by the time they got through the eastern province. It turned out that
                    a lot of them were mullahs, agitators. They were dropped off and stayed for a
                    while to preach. I never got really good numbers on this. I think many of them
                    did eventually go on to the Hajj. In subsequent years after we were there, this
                    became the standard form of Iranian agitation against the Saudi regime was to
                    have their own Hajjis do all sorts of disorderly things. This was really the
                    beginning of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q. This is tape 3, side A, an interview with Ralph Lindstrom.
                        With the Shiites, they would also go to Mecca, or were they making Hajj
                        to...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: They'd make both Hajjis. My gardener being an exception.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just to capture the spirit of the times, the American
                        political body, American populace, became very aware for the first time
                        probably of the difference between the two major sects of the Islamic
                        religion because of what was happening in Iran. Before that I don't think we
                        paid an awful lot of attention to it. Did they beef up our security at the
                        Consulate General?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, and very suddenly and almost unexpectedly. Unknown to me, I guess
                    the ambassador over on the other side of the kingdom, the embassy was still in
                    Jeddah at that time, had given an okay to the Saudi authorities that they could
                    improve security around the Consulate General in Dhahran. But we had no advance
                    notice of that, and all of a sudden lorries pulled up with National Guardsmen.
                    Of course, we'd had ever since your days there, a small contingent of probably
                    15 or 20 National Guardsmen living right on the Consulate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In my day we didn't have anybody.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: This dates back to another incident of the tearing down of the
                    flag.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think this was after the '67 war.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I think it was after that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think the '67 war, the Arab-Israeli war.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: But anyway, all of a sudden and unexpectedly these truck loads of
                    Saudi National Guardsmen showed up in the Consulate. Of course, my Arabic was
                    almost nonexistent, so as a practical matter in terms of dealing with the
                    situation, there wasn't anybody there to tell me why these people were there.
                    They were pointing their guns at my wife and me, and asking us to come out
                    behind the residence. So Gloria, my wife, said, “What's this all about?” I said,
                    “I haven't the faintest idea.” I said, “You better wear your hostage clothing,”
                    an extra pair of pants and that kind of thing. Well, of course, it was a mistake
                    on our part. It was just these people being friendly. Then for quite some time
                    they remained in strength in our compound, as protection against possible Shiite
                    actions or other hostile threats. I can remember once, actually my wife
                    witnessed this too, going back to our Shiite gardener. The Saudi National
                    Guardsmen, one time they, I guess, frightened him. They loaded their weapons,
                    and pointed them at him. They didn't shoot, but that's indicative of the
                    animosity. With them on the compound, I had to ask all the women in the
                    consulate to go around rather fully clothed. They could still go to the swimming
                    pool. We had a nice swimming pool by then, but they couldn't go around wearing
                    something that provocative with these National Guardsmen around there. Our whole
                    security situation was enormously complicated by the fact that we had this very
                    large American-run school on the compound by then. I forget when it started
                    exactly. So we had large numbers of parents and people coming in cars to drop
                    off their children, pick them up: I had asked the Marines to search the cars, to
                    make certain nothing was being brought in to the compound. That slowed up the
                    whole process, that there were no weapons or anything else.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>I remember during this period I got a phone call from, I think the New York Times
                    or Wall Street Journal correspondent. They had gotten as far as Saudi Arabia and
                    they wondered if they could come down and visit me. I said, “Well, it's pretty
                    dull here.” Actually we had a 50 caliber machine gun in the main entrance, and
                    30 calibers all around the compound. I didn't see anything to be gained by
                    having the newspapers in there. The Saudis were terribly tense about all of
                    this, understandably.</p>
                <p>One of the things I should mention is that unlike the Gulf posts, and this was a
                    Washington decision, the decision was made to leave our post fully staffed. We
                    didn't evacuate anyone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was after the take-over of our embassy in
                        Tehran?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes. It was one of the sparking factors and, of course, that almost
                    coincided with the Shiite uprising we had. And then there was something else
                    going on in Pakistan at the same time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, our embassy was burned in Pakistan. It was a very
                        tense time. This was around November-December of '79.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, that's right. Anyway, although my post, Dhahran, was located
                    right on the Gulf. All these Gulf posts were closed down. It was in the heart of
                    the Saudi oil industry, and the decision was finally made that we should not
                    drawdown, or close our post in the kingdom. Partly for political reasons, well,
                    in large part for political reasons, it might undercut the whole kingdom and
                    their major industry, thinking that all their oil workers go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's interesting because I've interviewed people who were
                        ambassadors to Oman and that area, who were screaming and yelling because
                        they had to drawdown their posts, and they were saying this sends a bad
                        signal, we had no problems, and why the hell do we have to do this? But
                        Washington would not listen to them—not close them, but brought them way
                        down...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Brought them way down, sent their dependents out of all of the Gulf
                    posts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But there you are in the middle of the thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: A stone's throw away from Iran. Yet I didn't have to close down. My
                    own judgement was that the threat was manageable. But the main concern, as I
                    understand it in Washington, was what it would do to Saudi morale, what it would
                    do to Saudi oil industry. Because once you started evacuating people, what are
                    you going to do about those Americans working in ARAMCO. What's that going to do
                    to oil production? I can understand that these people were unhappy in being
                    forced to drawdown, but I think they made a correct decision.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a problem with the staff and family morale
                        during this period of time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I would say no. I met with them all, including the wives, and
                    explained the situation as best I could. No, in fact one of the other things
                    that I did throughout my tour in Saudi Arabia was to meet regularly with
                    representatives of the American business community, and give them off-the-record
                    briefings on what was happening, which they greatly appreciated. I think that
                    had a somewhat stabilizing influence. And I said, “Let me know if you're hearing
                    any rumors,” and, of course, they were always hearing rumors and I'd listen to
                    them, and I'd say, “I don't think there's any basis for that one at all.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It sent tremors throughout the entire diplomatic world,
                        particularly within the United States. The seizure of our embassy, and
                        taking of hostages for 444 days by Iranians in Tehran. Did this weigh on
                        everybody's mind all the time in what you were doing, or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No, I'd say very definitely. My own regret was that I didn't take the
                    opportunity to visit Iran when I first got there, while it was still possible to
                    go over by air on Iran Air. Then when the revolution came. I had to give that
                    up. It would have been very valuable first-hand experience for me in view of my
                    subsequent assignment. One of the things about Saudi Arabia is that we were
                    always having high level visitors, the Department of Defense particularly, and
                    they would regularly meet with Prince Bandar, who is now the ambassador here. I
                    got to know him when he was Major Bandar, and the squadron leader of F-15s, and
                    a very interesting person, very bright, very brilliant. Of course recognized by
                    his father, although he was illegitimate...not an illegitimate child, but his
                    mother was a black slave originally. Of course she begot him the most
                    exceptional son of all, so that is why he has been pushed since then. When I
                    first knew him he was still in his twenties, and a very useful contact. Now he
                    only speaks with presidents. Anyway, that's sort of an aside.</p>
                <p>I guess I might as well mention, I think there are still some more things we will
                    discuss about Saudi Arabia; in January or February, the Assistant Secretary
                    of...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: January-February of?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Of 1980. Hal Saunders, who was our Assistant Secretary in the bureau
                    at that time, he'd come out a little bit earlier along with one of the cabinet
                    level delegations, so I had gotten to know him a little bit. He was back in
                    Washington then. I was up for reassignment the following summer, and they gave
                    me a choice of head of the Interests Section in Baghdad, or the Director of
                    Egyptian Affairs, or Director of Iranian Affairs. The feeling back there was
                    that they could put Iran back together again. This was just two months after the
                    taking of the hostages. This turned out to be a horrible decision. But it had an
                    impact on me. So out of the three jobs, I ended up picking the one that was
                    probably the least promising, the Iranian one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Back to Dhahran. What about the government? You had the
                        Emir of the eastern province. How were relations? Did you have much to do
                        with him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No. He was very distant, and a difficult person to get to know. I did
                    not really develop a successful relationship with him, and partly I think it was
                    his choice. His family was in there as a reward for something they had done
                    for...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The one I had known was one of the 13, or whatever it was,
                        who climbed the walls of Riyadh, and Saud. They were cousins. So he was sort
                        of an old hawk at that time, and this must have been the son or cousin, but
                        it was still in the family.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Not a young man, but not old, and a real non-doer. I would run into
                    him constantly, because as Consul General, at least during that period, I was an
                    honored figure along with the Emir of eastern province. But it was not a very
                    interesting relationship. I don't think even if I spoke fluent Arabic that I
                    would ever have gotten very much of interest out of him. He was a very timid
                    man, just didn't want to make any mistakes. Of course, many years later, it took
                    quite a while for the royal family to get up their nerve to remove him, and put
                    in some members of the royal family. I understand they put in some rather
                    competent people later on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Speaking as an old consular hand, what about consular
                        problems, arrest cases, detention cases?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: We had a lot of them. I had a first rate consular officer, a woman,
                    mind you, Andrea Farsakh. I don't know if you've heard about her, or met her. As
                    I understand it, the ambassador objected to Washington about accepting her
                    because she's a woman. She functioned perfectly well. She was married to an
                    Arab, and her Arabic was quite good, and a very reasonable sort of person. She
                    handled, I don't know how many prisoners, that had to be visited from time to
                    time—probably at any one moment it might have been 20-25, that kind of thing.
                    People who had committed offenses, such as alcohol related offenses, which the
                    Saudis took very seriously. So she would regularly visit these people. I would
                    send one of our top Saudi employees along with her to help with the
                    interpretation. Otherwise Saudi officials would not even have accepted her as a
                    woman alone, because they could be accused of doing something or other, and that
                    kind of thing. Anyway, she did a tremendous job. She would consult with me on
                    particularly tricky cases as to how we should handle them, and there were a
                    multitude of those coming in all the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have cases such as Americans being detained
                        because they were having business problems? How did you deal with it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: That was a continuing problem. There's no formula for dealing with
                    them exactly. You'd hope to mediate them, and get somebody in the economic
                    section or the commercial section to see what they could do to find out what the
                    root cause of particular dispute was. If they couldn't fix it, they'd arrange to
                    get the people out of the country, rather than have them imprisoned. This was a
                    very difficult area at all times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You must have had a lot of congressional letters trying to
                        explain what was happening. Did you feel any pressure, it may have hit
                        elsewhere, on the non-welcoming of American Jews to the area? Did this cause
                        problems on the part of the Saudis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It didn't, at least in the eastern province, partly because of the
                    presence of Prince Bandar. I sat in on a conversation between Bandar, two other
                    princes, I've forgotten their names now, and our Jewish congressman from New
                    York, who is now out. What's his name? It was a fascinating conversation, and
                    they discussed very frankly in English all of these outstanding problems,
                    everything from Jerusalem to you name it. This conversation went on for at least
                    six or seven hours into the evening. He had aspirations to become at least in
                    the position that Helms is going to go into now as Secretary of State, and it
                    all dashed down the drain. Anyway, he was very smart brained. And the next
                    morning Bandar insisted on taking him off to show him the line of F-15s, which
                    he had all at attention, and Bandar had the Saudia flight that was going to take
                    our visitor over to Jeddah stopped, just like that, royal prerogatives. So the
                    flight was delayed for fully an hour while Bandar proudly drove his guest around
                    the flight line.</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>But later on our visitor told me that when he reached Jeddah he was searched, and
                    they took away some magazines, Time magazine, on the grounds of possible
                    pornography because they censored all of the magazines coming in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was nominated to be ambassador to India, we can add
                        this. What about the defense side? Later Dhahran became the center. It was
                        on the nightly news because it was the center of our opposition to Iraq's
                        take-over of Kuwait. Were you involved at all in turning Dhahran into a
                        military hub?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No. But this process had been going on quietly for many, many years.
                    We had USMTM, (U.S. Military Training Mission), which was at that time located
                    in Dhahran, and headed up by a two-star U.S. Air Force officer, one after the
                    other. They were rotated through there. That was a very important relationship
                    for me, worked very closely with them. They were, along with the Corps of
                    Engineers—a very large contingent of Corps people, I think about 3,000 or
                    so—working for the Saudis, or being paid by the Saudis, on military
                    infrastructure, underground POL tanks. Then this fantastic military city in the
                    north of the country to protect against the threat from either Iraq or Iran. I
                    visited that in its earlier stages. Of course, this was fairly well completed by
                    the time the Gulf war came along. We had, I think, a better infrastructure in
                    Saudi Arabia (People didn't realize that), than we had in West Germany probably.
                    Anything money could buy, they would buy and they were putting this in. So
                    without that we would have had a pretty hard time winning the Gulf war. It was
                    never brought out very clearly in the reporting, how important these facilities
                    were to the U.S.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were relations, as you saw them, between the Saudis
                        and the Bahrainis, and the Trucial states?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I think, by and large, they were good. The Saudis, of course,
                    considered themselves to be the dominant power, at least from a protocol point
                    of view. To an increasing extent from a military point of view, although the
                    Saudi air force and other armed forces still remained pretty small, it had been
                    beefed up subsequently.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the third country nationals? I think of
                        Pakistanis, Indonesians, Koreans. These were the people who were doing most
                        of the work, weren't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes. Now I had in my own staff, just as an example, a Yemeni whom we
                    inherited from a predecessor, a Chinese whom we brought in from Taiwan, and a
                    Ceylonese whom we brought in from Ceylon. Three different religions, and kind of
                    interesting. The Saudis began, of course, during this critical period being very
                    nervous about people like the Yemens from a security point of view and were
                    beginning to discourage them from coming in. They already had restrictions. I
                    had a Yemeni driver and had to substitute somebody else, I can't remember of
                    what nationality, to go up to Ras Tannurah, because he was on the banned list,
                    while these Shiite of Saudi nationality could go in there. Very mixed up from
                    the way of running things. But the military relationship was already a very
                    important part.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of Saudi rule in the eastern
                        province? And also Saudi business people? Because we had an increasing
                        number of people coming back who had studied in the United States, or
                        elsewhere, but the development of a governing class, business class, what
                        was your impression?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Well, I had to do with the business class. These were people who were
                    somewhat independent of the royal family and would occasionally express their
                    views fairly candidly. I remember one man, a prominent business man in the
                    largest town near Dhahran, who occupied sort of a quasi-governmental
                    position—practically nothing was delegated. I remember how he would say, “For
                    each ten riyals appropriated up in the capital [at that time Jeddah], only one
                    riyal ever gets through to our public works projects here in the eastern
                    province.” I thought that was rather striking. There was somebody taking all the
                    way along the line, and a lot of it the royal family probably.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Each era one has a different view. I was there during the
                        late '50s, and we were kind of dubious about the Saudi system remaining
                        intact at that time. This was the times of Nasser. We thought it was
                        probably a dying institution. Now it's 30 years later, and they're still
                        around. What was the feeling when you were there? We're talking about the
                        late '70s, early '80s.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Well, I think we still had the same concerns. Those of us who came in
                    there and saw this remarkable institution of the Saudi monarchy said, “This
                    isn't real. This isn't in keeping with the age we're living in. It can't
                    possibly survive.” But yet it did. I used always to look around. Now who's the
                    guy who is going to lead the revolt against this? And I never really found him.
                    I'd look at some of these very good colonels in the Saudi army or air force, and
                    they never did. For one thing the royal family was so numerous. I've forgotten
                    now how numerous, up to maybe 2,000-3,000, I think at the time I was there, were
                    certified.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard figures of 9,000, and that doesn't include the
                        women.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: They were very good at getting into things like the army and the air
                    force, and that's a very good security device to be in by working there, and
                    being respected by and large.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm interested. How did you find them as a working crew?
                        Because I had the feeling, at least from my time, that there was a disdain
                        for getting out there and actually mucking around in the field and doing
                        something on the part of, not only the royal family, but of people who'd get
                        engineering degrees, and they would immediately head for the office and try
                        to run a firm and get money, rather than getting out and learning the
                        practicalities of the trade.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: There was a lot of that. There was a checkbook society, I call them.
                    The other answer to your question, I think, is how a stability has been
                    maintained this long? It's just simply one word, money. As long as you've got
                    this extreme amount of wealth, and almost everyone in the country has a piece of
                    that, except for the Shiites and then later they began to give them some too,
                    they realized that's a way of keeping them happy. But the young man coming back
                    from studying in the United States, and being given a business with all workers,
                    let's say, all he had to do was sit in the office and sign checks. So he could
                    be a manager. He was in effect bought off by the system. Now, how long this will
                    continue, I don't know, but certainly money has been a major factor.</p>
                <p>One of the interesting things I found too when I was there, was the treatment of
                    women. We got to know...this is something you could do in the eastern
                    province...we got to know quite a number of prominent Saudi women. We even gave
                    a discotheque dancing party one night for all Saudi couples, rather carefully
                    selected by them. They all checked their purdahs there in the front hall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The veils.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, veils, and the covering garment. They, of course, would have
                    $5,000 Paris gowns underneath, very attractive women. I was able to dance with a
                    number of Saudi women. I don't think many foreigners got that opportunity, but
                    as I say, it was a very carefully selected group. But within ARAMCO there were
                    several outstanding women who were trying to get ahead, advance things, and it
                    was very difficult for them because of the system. But they weren't as
                    downtrodden as some people might have thought. They still were not permitted to
                    drive cars.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could the American women drive cars when you were
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No. My wife could drive our personally owned Volkswagen on the
                    Consulate compound to the swimming pool, and that was all. ARAMCO had a very
                    limited thing just going out to Half Moon Bay, you had to drive out there if you
                    were a woman in ARAMCO. We got into some very strange situations where the women
                    were being encouraged to acquire skills, medical skills, for example, as nurses,
                    and in some cases doctors. But then the religious requirements are such that
                    they had to do absolutely ridiculous things. Westerners would go to get their
                    shots, and there'd be a hand coming through a hole in the wall to give them
                    their shots—a woman's hand.</p>
                <p>Then we had problems with religions, particularly in the personnel in ARAMCO, and
                    elsewhere, but more in ARAMCO. They had recruited a lot of Filipinos, and
                    Filipinas also. And Filipinos take their Catholicism rather seriously. Whether
                    they were out in a barge, or what have you. While I was there the religious
                    police came by and seized all of the...I don't know if you're Catholic. What do
                    you call the instruments, all the religious artifacts?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The chalice.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: There is a word for this. And this really upset, obviously, the
                    Catholic community in general, so petty, but so typical. I managed to have a
                    Christmas tree in front of the Consulate General the whole time I was there. But
                    I think some people were not too happy about that. This was a tradition that
                    went back quite a number of years. The Consulate General would always call
                    generally on the Bin Jaluwi, as well as on other prominent Saudis. And in return
                    they would call on my residence at Christmas. This was a custom that was started
                    by one of my predecessors going way back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, we certainly would call. We'd be called at something
                        like 4:00 in the morning and told to appear at dawn at the palace. And then
                        there would be the call back. I remember my first thing, I arrived and here
                        was a bodyguard in the middle of August wishing me a Merry Christmas,
                        because it was part of their Eid.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: We had a local employee, actually a Palestinian by the name of Fawzi,
                    a very good man and he had done a lot to promote these relationships. He kept a
                    very good relationship with the el-__ family for example.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A major merchant family.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes. At the time I was there they had a big hotel and many
                    other...</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were already big in Pepsi when I was there, but it
                        was small potatoes compared to what it is now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: But Fawzi had done a lot to encourage this cross-fertilization and
                    calling back. I even bought frankincense and myrrh, so we could pass the thing
                    around during their calls on me at Christmas time. Everybody would flap the
                    perfume around, they liked it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, it was kind of fun.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: It was really an exciting experience, it was so different. Although
                    I'd been in the Middle East before, I'd never been closer than Afghanistan, and
                    never really been in the Arab culture. I'm still sorry that there wasn't some
                    way in which I could have acquired better working knowledge of Arabic. But
                    Arabic is extremely difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And at a certain age you're just not going to get it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I don't know very many people who are certified Arabists who are
                    really very good in saying much more beyond the greetings. Once later on I
                    returned to Saudi Arabia and visited de Maurice, who was one of my successors.
                    He invited a couple of people that I had suggested, including somebody from the
                    consulate who spoke absolutely fluent Arabic. Whose name was Helms,
                    incidentally, and one of the Saudi guests said, “You must be from CIA, you speak
                    Arabic so fluently.” As I mentioned earlier speaking Kikuyu, sometimes it
                    doesn't really get you as far as you would like.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came back when in 1980?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Then I had agreed to take the Iranian job, and of course things just
                    went from bad to worse as far as the hostages were concerned. So I finally came
                    back, after consulting in the area. I did get a chance to visit Oman and the
                    Emirates, and Kuwait, and Baghdad, and came back in June or July of 1980. Henry
                    Precht was my predecessor, so I replaced him. But when I arrived there it was
                    really the very lowest of the low points in the whole hostage crisis. We had
                    just sent a letter signed by every congressman and senator to Rafsanjani, who
                    was already rising in power. It was delivered to him by the Swiss ambassador who
                    was acting on our behalf. He just gave a terrible anti-American diatribe. I
                    remember hearing Muskie say...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was Secretary of State.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: He said, “I can see the outline of a possible negotiation.” And I said
                    to myself, I didn't say this to anyone else, “These people are all batty if they
                    think they can make anything out of Rafsanjani's anti-American diatribe.” But in
                    a sense Muskie's observation turned out to be true, because there were some
                    points in there and we were able to get additional signals that indicated some
                    willingness. But still the mind set at that time was that the ___ had no
                    authority really to deal with the hostage crisis. It was just sort of hanging
                    out there. I worked in the Operations Center for the rest of the hostage period
                    and on for the first five or six months into the non-hostage period after their
                    release. I had a very large staff of volunteers, people from all parts of the
                    Department, to handle phone calls.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Basically for most of the time you were there, at least
                        the first part of the time you were there, it was just hostages. That was
                        it, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I'd say that was the center of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the freezing of Iranian funds?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: This was all a part of it, of course, and all the measures that we
                    took, and eventually the releasing of many Iranian funds as a part of the
                    release process. But I would say going back to the summer when I first got
                    there, the emphasis then was on maintaining contact. I mean, establishing some
                    kind of meaningful contact with someone who you might call a decision maker
                    inside of Iran. As I mentioned on Rafsanjani, he didn't seem to be asserting
                    himself as a decision maker at all. We had various people to maintain telephone
                    contact directly with Iran. Fortunately the telephones never went out during
                    this period. I had developed a contact with one of the leading Shiites in the
                    United States, in the Bay area. We used to meet from time to time, and I went
                    out and saw him in San Francisco. I first met him here, he had studied in
                    religious institutions, mainly in Iraq, where the best students were, many of
                    the present leaders in Iran, and the post-revolutionary leaders. He could also
                    get through on the telephone to some of them. Most of the people were pretty
                    afraid to talk, but he occasionally would give us some little tidbits of what
                    was going on. As Hal Saunders used to say, we just keep tapping on every door,
                    every window, in hopes of finding one that we eventually could open. So it was
                    sort of a shotgun approach to the problem, which I think was probably a
                    reasonable thing to do. We had contacts with some very disreputable people.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we able to...because one looks forward a few more
                        years to the Reagan administration to the time when you had what was known
                        as the Iran-Contra affair where the National Security Council got involved
                        with dealing with the so-called “Iranian moderates” and thinking that they
                        were working a deal again about hostages but this time in Beirut. Were there
                        attempts to get you into one of these deals with say disreputable people
                        where caution would say, let's not do it? Were we desperate? Were there
                        attempts to get you involved in things that probably would have been
                        discreditable?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No. That certainly wasn't a part of the picture then. But we did deal
                    with some people who had rather questionable backgrounds in an effort to get
                    information. This, of course, was all cleared with everybody. One of my daily
                    jobs from the time I first got here was to write a daily report on whatever
                    information we'd gathered from our sort of informal channels of one kind or
                    another. For example, I used to pick up from Henry Precht, the Frenchman in
                    Paris, who had supposedly good ties in Iran. Again, leaving no stone unturned.
                    We would report this to the Secretary of State, a daily report, and that same
                    report went, without his name on it, to the President, Jimmy Carter. He became
                    completely involved in getting the hostages out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were your relations with the National Security
                        Council?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I used to see Gary Sick, not a great deal. For example, they did keep
                    the State Department from knowing, other than Warren Christopher, about the
                    hostage rescue operation. Anyway, I did see a fair amount of Sick. This was more
                    after the hostages were released. Anyway, going up to their release there was a
                    lot of speculation about what held up their release to the last minute. I don't
                    find there's ever been any really satisfactory explanation. Gary Sick wrote his
                    book on so-called October Surprise, and I don't think this was something
                    deliberate on the part of the Reagan administration...so everyone, and not just
                    our agency, but in the whole government was working in one way or another. The
                    Treasury Department was very deeply involved in all of this money business,
                    constant meetings of committees to coordinate all of these things that were
                    going on. Again, the feelings about whether we were going to get them out, we
                    just simply didn't know, or if some of them were going to be killed. Rumors flew
                    hot and fast. Let me say, I was in on the original involvement of the Algerians.
                    This was, as I recall, it was on a Sunday—we worked 7 days a week—and I worked
                    very closely with Hal Saunders, and we got a call that the Algerian ambassador
                    wanted to come around to the State Department. He had something to say, and his
                    only western language was French, so I was asked to interpret for Hal. At the
                    same time up in the United Nations, a permanent Iranian had just come there. He
                    was the Prime Minister. He had been up at the United Nations, and the wife of
                    one of our hostages had met with him, and he seemed to be very sympathetic to
                    her. This was the school teacher hostage, and she had an hour. I think it had
                    some impact on him as a person. Then the Algerians also met with him. They came
                    around to see Hal and me on a Sunday afternoon, and he was proposing that the
                    Secretary of State might want to work jointly with the Foreign Minister of
                    Algeria to facilitate the hostage release since it wasn't going anyplace very
                    fast. The Swiss were doing an excellent job of representing us, but there were
                    limitations. They just simply didn't have the same credentials as the Algerians
                    had at that time. So we talked to him at some length about how this might go.
                    Hal made it clear from the beginning that it would be Mr. Christopher who would
                    be the U.S. representative, because he had the experience. Muskie could always
                    be brought in, but he was brand new and not familiar with this. So that's how
                    this special Algerian relationship got started. I remember initially Christopher
                    flew over to Algiers with a number of other people, and they really got this
                    other channel going. It fits in with what I mentioned earlier about having
                    multiple channels to solve this problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your feeling about the final agreement that got
                        the hostages back?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I think it was about as good as we could have got. There were a lot of
                    things that we did not give the Iranians. Of course there are some people that
                    say we shouldn't have given them anything. We should have gone in there
                    militarily. But we got every last hostage out alive, which we weren't sure of at
                    all. Some think, and sometimes I lean towards that point of view, that we could
                    have gotten them out politically, if we had not gone this very detailed route.
                    We could have gotten them out sooner. I don't really think that was the case.
                    Once you started down that path there were all sorts of technocrats on the
                    Iranian side, and the Central Bank, and all that sort of thing. It worked well,
                    but it worked slowly because as you know the hostages didn't get out until even
                    after the new President was in office. I can remember out to the hall going to
                    the men's room in front of the Op Center, seeing some taking down the names of
                    all the Assistant Secretaries from a board from the old administration, and
                    still we didn't have any hostages out yet. It was rather exciting when finally
                    they were allowed to take off. We were monitoring the flight of the two Algerian
                    aircraft. The Iranians did give us a military escort. The Iran-Iraq war was on
                    by that time, and they gave us an escort of three or four F-4s to go after the
                    Iraqis, if they should come there. Then finally we got the word that they were
                    over Turkish airspace. It was exciting, and then they refueled in Greece. Our
                    ambassador there wanted to get on and greet everybody, but the Algerians
                    wouldn't let him on. He was furious, I don't remember who it was. So finally
                    they got all the way over to Algiers and made a safe landing. We had some
                    threats that came in supposedly from Qadhafi, and that sort of thing. Nothing
                    materialized, and the Algerians planes went on and landed there.</p>
                <p>Incidentally, the Algerians did a tremendous job and never charged us a dime for
                    any of that. They would never take anything whatsoever for the use of their
                    planes, their people, and all that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Reagan administration came in and what happened? The
                        hostages arrived and Iranian affairs almost disappeared from the Department
                        of State radar, or what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No, not immediately. It was still a matter of continuing interest. In
                    a sense, yes, but there were lingering problems. We were concerned with our
                    property in Iran, for example, what was going to happen to that. And there were
                    a couple of other people to still get out who were sort of private hostages, you
                    might say, a woman. So it just sort of wound down more slowly. The Reagan
                    administration gave a reception on the White House grounds for the returning
                    hostages. They, as you know, spent some days getting back and were brought back
                    via West Point. I remember one of the things is that the Reagan administration
                    didn't seem to want to give much credit at all to the Algerians who played such
                    a key role, and that rather bothered me. But I continued to work with the
                    Algerians. They were managing our Iranian interests and I was still in that
                    job.</p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>One of the exciting moments, of course, too, was when not only the Algerian
                    planes exited into Turkish airspace, but we did get a phone call from the Swiss
                    ambassador in Tehran saying that he had 52 hostage signatures. Up until then we
                    didn't know how many we were going to get out. A lot of the delay was apparently
                    caused by disagreement among the hostage holders. A couple of the hostages
                    weren't brought to the airport until the last moment. So I don't think there was
                    any October Surprise, any conscious conspiracy, or anything like that. It was
                    just the customary Iranian disarray.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During the Reagan administration was there any change, you
                        might say, in attitude or anything else like that as far as you were
                        concerned in Iranian affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Oh, Yes. They wanted to go through the policy making process. We had
                    the SIG-IG thing at that time analyzing Iran and what it meant for U.S.
                    interests and all that sort of thing. That's where I first met Ollie North. He
                    came to one of our SIGs but stayed more or less in the background whispering to
                    his buddies from you know where. So, yes, there was considerable interest.</p>
                <p>But going back to one point, when we were trying to figure out how to deal
                    Khomeini. He had issued this rather mysterious proclamation. Most other things
                    seemed to call for our recognizing that we had been at fault in this whole
                    thing. We would consult with all sorts of experts on Iran to see how we could
                    satisfy this feeling. We started doing a lot of things in retrospect we weren't
                    terribly proud of. They're humiliating almost. But throughout this period, once
                    these basic contacts were established with the Algerians and with the key
                    players on the Iranian side, who had been authorized by Khomeini to negotiate,
                    it really went on pretty well. But there were always these uncertainties as to
                    whether they were really serious, whether we were really negotiating with the
                    right people.</p>
                <p>That's putting in a capsule an awful lot of happenings but then after that we
                    moved back up to Iranian Affairs in the NEA Bureau. There were some odds and
                    ends to tend to but mainly dealing with the Algerians over the things that the
                    Iranians were doing in the Interest Section, and trying to keep them under
                    control. The Algerians did a marvelous job as far as I was concerned under a
                    very difficult position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They're very professional diplomats.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Oh, yes. These are the people who now are being attacked by the
                    Islamic extremists inside their own country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left that job, your last job was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Yes, my last job was not a terribly exciting job. I was in charge of
                    economic matters in INR. I'd say the hostage business was the last really
                    interesting job that I had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any impression of how Alexander Haig as
                        Secretary of State...did you get any feel for his operation from your
                        perspective?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Well, I certainly was conscious, as was everybody who worked in the
                    policy area in the Department at that time, of Haig's idiosyncrasies such as
                    underlining key words in one-page memos, his military technique. That wasn't
                    that important, but you were already being as brief as you can. I didn't have
                    anything personally to do with him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were dealing with Iranian affairs, what about
                        the multitude of Iranian students in the United States? Were they any factor
                        at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: No. They were, of course, an irritant to President Carter when they
                    would come and demonstrate in front of the White House. He kept saying can't we
                    do something about this. The President had to be informed that they were
                    observing U.S. laws. To answer your question I don't think they had any
                    important bearing on...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we ever talking about checking visa status, and
                        sending them home?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: All of these options were considered. Of course, some of the Iranian
                    students were perfectly reasonable people. Others from our point of view...so we
                    didn't get into anything that was really punitive. I maintained quite a lot of
                    contact with Iranians that I had met earlier in academics. It was rather a
                    unique event in American history.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It certainly was. Well, when you left the Iranian job,
                        what was your feeling about whither American-Iranian relations. This is
                        '83.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LINDSTROM: I would say the last time we looked at it from a policy point of view
                    in a SIG context...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: SIG means?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>LINDSTROM: Senior Inter-departmental Group. We thought at that time, and it
                    turned out to be wildly optimistic, that within a few years the Iranians would
                    find it in their interest to come back and reestablish a relationship with U.S.,
                    other western powers, etc. It just simply has not happened. We don't see much
                    likelihood of it happening in the near future. We thought amongst other things
                    there would be sort of an end to the educated Iranians all over the country and
                    into western Europe, United States, etc. I thought maybe at one point they would
                    start returning, but they were too afraid to return. They would send their wives
                    back, because the revolutionaries wouldn't bother the wives. The wives could
                    sort of secure the family property for a time. But that's not really transferred
                    political power back into Iran, so it has turned out to be something more of the
                    nature of the Russian revolution in looking back. So I don't think most of those
                    people are ever going to go back. The center is still a very radical thing.
                    Rafsanjani was called a moderate by North. Well, maybe he is a moderate, if he
                    had his own way. He's never been sufficiently in control of the operation to
                    exhibit genuine moderate tendencies, and the radicals, our former hostage
                    holders...we did put them on our look-out list, every last one of them. We
                    managed to finally to identify all ten of them. But several of them became high
                    ranking officials in the Foreign Ministry. We did deny them entry into the
                    United States. We were afraid of having scuffles on the tarmac in New York. So,
                    anyway, the regime goes on with the radical factions within the Foreign Ministry
                    tending to control it. Those ties would keep them in Sudan, I think, and other
                    admiring governments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You can always add anything you want, including the name
                        of the congressman ...Steve Solarz is the Jewish congressman from New York
                        whose name we couldn't remember. Thank you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
