<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000285">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Dwight Dickinson </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR DWIGHT DICKINSON</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Thomas S. Estes </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 11, 1988</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>This is an interview with The Honorable Dwight Dickinson, the former United
                    States Ambassador to the Republic of Togo, on May 11, 1988 at the residence of
                    Thomas S. Estes, who is conducting the interview on behalf of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies. The Ambassador and I are old friends and colleagues in
                    the Foreign Service and consequently this interview will be marked by its
                    informality.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dwight, you wanted to make a general statement before
                        going into specifics. You are now on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DICKINSON: Well, Tom, going back to what you said about our being colleagues, I'd
                    like to say something about you first. You were senior to me and you were an
                    Ambassador earlier than I was and I always admired you a great deal and that
                    leads me to say what I want to say about the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>One of the very best things about it was one's colleagues. My best friends to
                    this day are almost entirely friends I made in the Foreign Service. This may
                    sound a little fortuitous, but you can't talk about your career in the Foreign
                    Service without saying what it means to you and to me. I know it meant really
                    everything. I enjoyed it. I enjoyed everything I did in it. If I could do it
                    over again, I think I'd do it exactly the same way. It might have been possible
                    to go farther than I did, but I'm happy the way I did it.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>One of the things I think we're supposed to tell you is a little bit about our
                    background in the Foreign Service, how we got into it. Very briefly I got into
                    it by being a Navy junior. My father was stationed in the Far East, and I lived
                    two and a half years in the Philippines and China—most of it in the
                    Philippines—I began to take an interest in what was going on as the Japanese
                    were beginning to harass the Chinese when we lived in Chefoo. Every time a
                    Chinese gunboat came in there were two Japanese gunboats right along side it and
                    it wasn't long before the Manchurian adventure began. I didn't really know much
                    about all that but I did discover there was something called a Consulate and
                    that there were Consuls and that was in the back of my mind when later on, as a
                    beginning college student, I began to think about what I'd like to do. I had
                    another really silly reason for wanting to be in the Foreign Service. I
                    collected stamps and I was fascinated with geography— fascinated with other
                    countries. And that led me directly to the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>My early career was not very distinguished. I had five years in the Navy and I
                    think that delayed my development in the Foreign Service. Being a Navy junior
                    and then spending five years in the Naval Reserve during World War II, I learned
                    a great deal about organization, but I also learned to carry out orders. It
                    never occurred to us in the Navy to question something we were told to do, and I
                    think I went into the Foreign Service with that view. I'm not encouraging young
                    people to be disobedient, or to be arrogant, but I do think one could have more
                    ideas than I had. I was basically trying to carry out what I thought someone
                    else wanted me to do.</p>
                <p>Eventually, of course, as most of us in the Foreign Service probably did, I came
                    to the realization that foreign policies were not made on the basis of US
                    national interest but on the basis of US political interest, or the interest of
                    a particular party that was making the decision. I'm convinced that if a
                    president were ever to rely really on the Foreign Service, on its information,
                    and on its views, and to encourage it to give its views, he would probably do a
                    darn sight better job than he does. But I believe foreign policy decisions are
                    made, coming from the White House as we now see with this National Security
                    Advisor who much of the time is more powerful than the Secretary of State—let's
                    say all the time, except when Henry Kissinger moved from the National Security
                    Council to the Secretaryship—but it just seems to me that the decisions are
                    based on what is good for the party for the moment, what will get you elected,
                    what will give you a high profile. And I don't think that they're based on an
                    objective analysis of what really is in the US interest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's very interesting Dwight. I'm going to check back
                        now to make sure that your voice level is right and that we're recording
                        your views properly.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>That's fine, that's fine, Dwight. Now why don't you highlight a few of your
                    assignments before you were appointed Ambassador that you think may have a
                    bearing on the objective of this oral history, or on your philosophy regarding
                    the Foreign Service. I'll suggest a few but please pick your own if you prefer.
                    For example, as you observe the situation in Lebanon the past few years, have
                    you recalled some incidents during your tour there as Economic Officer in
                    '54-'56 that you would consider clues to the future of that country?</p>
                <p>DICKINSON: Well, Tom, 1954-56 was really a very peaceful time in Lebanon. The
                    seeds of the disaster which has befallen Lebanon were there. As I'm sure you
                    know, the Chamber of Deputies was elected on the basis of a confessional
                    membership, that is, there would be a certain number of Christian Maronites, a
                    certain number of Greek Orthodox, a certain number of Shia, a certain number of
                    Sunnis, a certain number of Druze—even two or three Armenian deputies. This was
                    based on a census that had been taken sometime before 1954, maybe considerably,
                    maybe 1948— I'm not sure—I shouldn't even mention the date, I don't know when it
                    was, and it was based on the number of Christian Lebanese who existed, I
                    believe, and it probably included many who lived outside the country. (Note: I
                    have checked this point, since saying the above, and find that this political
                    mosaic was based on the “National Pact” of 1943.) At that time there were more
                    Christian Lebanese living than Muslim Lebanese. I don't know whether that's true
                    now, but many of them lived outside the country. Lebanon was unable ever to have
                    another census; it was unwilling and unable to face another census. This
                    resulted in the Maronite Christians having the presidency; this was assigned to
                    them. The Sunnis having the Prime Ministership. The Shia the Speakership, and as
                    I remember, at that time the Druze had to have the Minister of Defense, or
                    Minister of War. I think that may have changed but that was the way it was
                    then.</p>
                <p>The other aspect of Lebanon that already existed in '54-'56 was the presence of
                    some 70,000 to 90,000, as I remember, Palestinian refugees who had fled there in
                    1948. They had confidently intended to return to Palestine after the Arab armies
                    had defeated the Israelis, the Jews. That, of course, never happened; it never
                    has. They were just sitting there, doing nothing, bearing children. The Lebanese
                    were making no effort to integrate them; no other country was interested in
                    them. The children, as I say, were beginning to be born—the children that must
                    now have children who were born in camps. Nothing was done for them except
                    through the United Nations Relief &amp; Works Agency (UNRWA), to which we were
                    the largest contributor by far, as I recall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excuse me. Would you spell out that UNWRA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DICKINSON: Yes. Its UNRWA and I believe its the United Nations Relief &amp; Works
                    Agency. I'm glad you clarified that.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>The result of all this is that after the years and years in a way of neglect the
                    Palestinians didn't want to be integrated; the other Arabs, the Lebanese, and
                    others, didn't want to integrate them. But as a result they've had nothing to do
                    but grow up in these camps filled with hatred, and we see the result today.
                    Lebanon also, because of its many sects and parties, became a very weak country
                    and therefore a fertile ground for the Palestinians to develop their own
                    resistance in. I won't go any farther with that because there are so many people
                    that are going to be interviewed in this system who know a great deal more about
                    it than I, but I'm recalling the seeds of this, and it was the Palestinian
                    presence in Lebanon, I'm convinced, which brought about the destruction of
                    government in Lebanon. (Note: Although I failed to say so, the disintegration of
                    authority in Lebanon finally came about when the PLO leadership and military,
                    driven out of Jordan by King Hussein, moved to Lebanon and established
                    themselves in the already festering refugee camps.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. You spoke about the UNRWA, the Relief &amp; Works
                        Agency. If you haven't any other earlier assignments you'd like to comment
                        on, would you go to your assignment to the United Nations headquarters in
                        New York and follow that up with your assignment to the North Atlantic
                        Treaty Organization. The two seem to follow each other.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DICKINSON: Yes, they did. One followed the other, unfortunately I preferred the
                    first. This is not sequential in my experience. That wasn't my immediate posting
                    after Lebanon, but its worth a great deal talking about. My United Nations
                    experience, which consisted of membership in the delegation for the 15th General
                    Assembly session, where I represented the African Bureau (I was brought back
                    from Morocco for that purpose and returned to Morocco) and then my membership in
                    the regular delegation from mid-1962 until the end of 1965. These two
                    experiences were to me the most fascinating and by far the most interesting in
                    my Foreign Service career.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excuse me, Dwight. What's the date of this
                        assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>DICKINSON: The assignment—well, I had four months in '60, and then in June '62
                    until January '66. The second time, I was on the regular staff of the Mission, I
                    was called a Political Adviser. I worked for people younger than I, maybe even
                    junior. And this is an interesting key to service at the UN. You have to be
                    willing to do whatever has to be done and not have any sense of rank or
                    importance. I remember Foreign Service Officers who came there with the exalted
                    idea that they'd be terribly important advisers, and they were sent on errands
                    the same way I was to round up a recalcitrant delegate who wasn't in his seat.
                    Some people minded and some didn't. I liked it, but I also learned to like
                    something else, and that was that during the General Assembly, at least, the
                    place was like a 7-ring circus. There were seven committees. Each committee had
                    an Executive Officer. I was Executive Officer, for a good part of the time, of
                    (our delegation to) the Fourth Committee, which was the committee on
                    non-self-governing territories. The representative was usually a politico. Part
                    of the time I had Sidney Yates, a failed—he wasn't failed—the Democrats had
                    talked him into running against Everett Dirksen for the Senate. He lost his
                    (Congressional) seat and he spent the next two years as our representative on
                    the Fourth Committee and the Committee on the Granting of Independence to
                    Colonial Countries and Peoples, and would go home every Wednesday to Chicago to
                    attend to his law business and leave me in charge of the committees for the next
                    Wednesday, Thursday, and Friday and I had a lot of fun. But I learned what
                    really one could do. This is where I learned that one's own ideas might have
                    some value.</p>
                <p>The way we worked there, I think I mentioned this to you one time Tom, you
                    thought was interesting. As a matter of fact, you asked me the question, “How
                    did we get our instructions?” We got our instructions by asking for them. Every
                    evening after the work was over, you'd go and have a drink at whatever reception
                    was on—there was a reception practically every night of the year—and then you'd
                    go back to the Mission and request your instructions. And in the morning
                    somebody would have them for you from Washington. There was very little time to
                    clear them with all quarters so half the time you were told just to go ahead and
                    do your best. When I went back to the Mission, which was across the street, I
                    would call the Desk Officer—he wasn't called a Desk Officer- -but whatever
                    officer was responsible in the United Nations Affairs in the Department, and we
                    would discuss what we really ought to be doing. I would then send him a telegram
                    confirming that, although it didn't say so. It just asked for instructions and
                    suggested them, and in the morning he'd send me a telegram. When I got to work
                    there was a telegram giving me the instructions I'd requested and that he and I
                    had agreed on. And we seldom had to go very high because there was so much going
                    on with seven committees. Anyway, that was a great deal of fun.</p>
                <p>Perhaps one of the most marvelous things about working at the UN was working for
                    Adlai Stevenson. Adlai had just the attitude toward career advisers, career
                    foreign affairs advisers, that naturally I and many of my colleagues would think
                    anybody should have, any political appointee. He trusted us, he believed us, he
                    listened to us. He would express his views but he listened, and then he would
                    help you to get done what you wanted to get done.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>Of course, the way he helped the most was by being so terribly eloquent. I
                    remember one occasion—and everybody at the United Nations admired him. He
                    couldn't get out of an elevator without all the other Ambassadors making way and
                    saying, “You go first, don't stand in the line, Governor, go up to the head of
                    the line.” Of course, he wouldn't do that, but they didn't even want him to wait
                    behind them to shake hands with the host. They had tremendous respect for
                    him.</p>
                <p>But what he did, I can best give an example by the fact that when we had—I think
                    it was 1965—when we and the British and the Belgians decided that we had to go
                    into Stanleyville in the then ex-Belgian Congo, now Zaire, to rescue several
                    hundred foreigners who were held by Simba guerrillas and being mistreated by
                    them, some had been killed. We provided the transport. We landed at St. Helena;
                    we provided the transport for Belgian paratroopers. Britain provided the staging
                    area at St. Helena off the African coast. And then we flew from there the
                    Belgian paratroopers in to Stanleyville and all of the hostages were rescued and
                    I don't believe that any at all were killed in the rescue. Some had already been
                    killed; maybe a few were but it was absolutely essential that the rest be
                    rescued. Our method at this point was to call a Security Council meeting since
                    we were planning all this. We called it first to make our report. I was assigned
                    to call Ralph Bunche, then Under- Secretary General (for Special Political
                    Affairs)—call him at 5:00 in the morning and inscribe for the day, and I did so,
                    and at 9:00 a.m. or whatever it was, we had our meeting. Well, after several
                    days of this we got to our big point and we got a speech from Washington for
                    Adlai to give. Several of us read it, and it was just awful. The person who had
                    written it had just been assigned to write it; he knew nothing special about the
                    situation. So I volunteered to rewrite the speech and I was told, “fine”. I was
                    told that Adlai would be in—this was a Saturday, I guess—and I was told Adlai
                    would come in on Sunday and read the speech and give it on Monday. So I went in,
                    Adlai showed up all by himself, no ghost writers or anybody, and he read my
                    speech over and every now and then he'd pick up a pencil and he'd scribble in a
                    few words. After he'd given the speech and the New York Times reported it, every
                    word they quoted was what he'd pencilled in. His lovely language just caught the
                    eye immediately and made the point, and it was a wonderful thing to have a
                    representative like that who could not only deliver it eloquently but could
                    write the exciting parts of it.</p>
                <p>I'd like to say one other thing. While I was there in the delegation I handled
                    our participation in the Congo operation for nearly four years—three and a half
                    years. We did that through Ralph Bunche and the Secretary General. We did not
                    deal with the other elements of the Secretariat, and Charles Yost, of course,
                    was actually dealing with this subject— Stevenson, Yost and I. Yost, by the way,
                    for my money, is the finest Foreign Service Officer I ever met. He could
                    accomplish in a quiet, modest way more than others ever did with fanfare and I'd
                    like to pay that tribute to him right now. I had served with him already in
                    Morocco but three and a half years at the UN were a wonderful experience—working
                    for him and Adlai.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>Well, I should say one other thing about the UN and that's this. I started to say
                    this earlier and that is that many of my colleagues had no patience with the UN.
                    I said some, because they didn't want to be messenger boys, but basically they
                    didn't like losing votes. We lost our first (General Assembly) vote in 1960, the
                    first major vote that we ever wanted to win. We lost it and that was over the
                    establishment of the then Committee of Seventeen, which later became the
                    Committee of Twenty-Four which was the Committee on the Decolonization of
                    Dependent Territories— that's not the right name at all, it escapes me for the
                    moment. (Note: The Committee on the Granting of Independence to Colonial
                    Countries and Peoples, on which I was, for 1964 and 1965, Alternate US
                    Representative.) But the general American public, and many of the Foreign
                    Service officers, looked upon the UN as the enemy, the place where we always
                    lost the vote. And this is what I would like to say about that. What it seemed
                    to me we were doing was, basically, we were dealing with the problems of the
                    Third World countries.</p>
                <p>Major problems, such as Vietnam—I wasn't there during Vietnam— but major
                    problems, such as Vietnam didn't come up, they were beyond, they were too big a
                    problem for the UN to try to deal with and the United States was too powerful to
                    try to discipline or to have any effect on. But small countries, to me it seemed
                    that small countries had a wonderful opportunity, the only one they would ever
                    have to really make their voices known in the world. And they did this through
                    the weight of their vote in the General Assembly where a coalition of Third
                    World countries and the Soviet Bloc, which always took delight in supporting
                    them whether it agreed with them or not, they would win all the votes and this
                    would lead the American public to think the UN was anti-US It always seemed to
                    me that the problem was that we were voting against the Third World countries on
                    their issues, not they against us on our issues. And I think this is a fact that
                    has been missed a great deal.</p>
                <p>Another thing that the UN could and did do. If there was a problem that might
                    have led to a minor war, and somebody didn't want a minor war, all he had to do
                    was to go to the Security Council and the Security Council would say something
                    and honor would have been saved and actual hostilities were prevented. There are
                    many cases of this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's very interesting. I knew so little about him
                        (Stevenson). I'm glad to hear this and having served under Charlie Yost, I
                        want to second what you said. I think he's one of our great, greats in the
                        Foreign Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Now, tell us a little bit about your NATO, your North Atlantic Treaty
                    Organization assignment where you had the rank of Minister.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>DICKINSON: I'd like to contrast that with the UN. However, there's one thing I
                    would like to say about the UN. Everyone will have noticed. This wasn't my
                    experience, but it has just happened. When the Soviets decided to get out of
                    Afghanistan, they accepted UN mediation, with the US, the Soviet Union, Pakistan
                    and Afghanistan participating. They arranged the withdrawal through a UN
                    mediator, under the leadership of a UN mediator. So even big countries can use
                    the UN if they wish, and that's a marvelous example of it.</p>
                <p>My experiences at the North Atlantic Council were very disappointing. I found
                    right away that, although I admired many of the professional representatives of
                    the other country members, it was pretty hard to stomach the actions of their
                    governments. This was 1966-67, we were preparing during that entire period to
                    leave Paris, to move the headquarters from Paris to Brussels, but we still had
                    the work of the organization to complete, to carry out. And it always seemed to
                    me that the other governments, particularly the Low Countries, the Danes
                    perhaps, maybe the Canadians—I don't want to be unfair about the Canadians—but
                    so many of them were really egging us on all the time to defend Europe but they
                    were very, very unwilling to increase their own contributions to the defense of
                    Europe. (Note: It wasn't money that made Canada weak, but rather its fear of
                    offending de Gaulle, who was then wooing the province of Quebec.) That wasn't
                    entirely what disappointed me. I was used to, at the UN, the parliamentary
                    negotiations, the parliamentary maneuvering, the actual vote so that you had a
                    clear answer, the verbatim reports of committee meetings, and the summaries of
                    committee meetings. All of those things—you had something to work with. At the
                    North Atlantic Council the system was there were no votes. Everything was done
                    by consensus. The Secretary General, who was then Manlio Brosio of Italy, was a
                    marvelous man. His English was quite good on social occasions, but when he was
                    in the Council and when he was summarizing what had happened, he summarized it
                    in such vague English that every delegation went back to its office and wrote
                    its own report making things come out exactly the way they wanted. I don't know,
                    that just disappointed me a great deal. The whole organization disappointed me
                    and eventually, in fairly short order, I asked to go back to Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That leads me very nicely into the next question. In '67
                        you were sent to Rabat again, the second time. This time as Deputy Chief of
                        Mission and Counselor of Embassy. Isn't it unusual to be assigned to the
                        same post twice?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>DICKINSON: It probably is and I wish we did it more often. I was worried about
                    going back because I'd loved it. I'd been Political Counselor the first time.
                    Before I went to the UN I spent three years there as Political Counselor and it
                    was a great learning process for me. Incidentally, I was totally amazed when I
                    first went there in 1959 as Political Counselor—I'd only been out of Lebanon for
                    three years—I was amazed to discover that the Moroccans didn't give a damn what
                    happened in the Middle East. They weren't the least bit interested. When I left
                    Lebanon in '56 you couldn't have a conversation with a Lebanese Christian or a
                    Muslim without their bringing up our support of Israel, for example. The
                    Moroccans just didn't care. The government made all the right motions and the
                    King was great at holding Arab conferences and taking initiatives, but the truth
                    was that Morocco, which is the farthest away from the Middle East of the Arab
                    countries, just didn't care. I don't think the people care very much. And I
                    doubt they do to this day.</p>
                <p>I've forgotten what your question was, Tom, how you phrased it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Wasn't it unusual to be assigned a second time, and then I
                        was going to carry on. I think you've answered part of it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DICKINSON: It was, but I'll tell you frankly I can say this. Henry Tasca was hard
                    on DCMs and they were looking around for somebody who wanted to go there. When I
                    said I wanted to go back to Africa...the way I did that I told them I wanted to
                    go back to Africa and I heard that Joe Palmer, who was then Assistant Secretary
                    for African Affairs, was coming through Paris so I sent word to him—he was at a
                    conference in Tangier—and I sent word to him that I wanted to see him. He was
                    pretty busy in Paris but he had time to let me ride in the taxi out to Le
                    Bourget from which he was taking his plane back home. And in that time I told
                    him I wanted to go, and he brought up the DCM job in either Tunis or Morocco. I
                    thought, “Well, you shouldn't go back to the same place. I'll take Tunis.” I got
                    Morocco. What he did to me there was, they had Henry going through, Henry Tasca,
                    on a trip and I had an hour in the airport with Henry. And I made one of the
                    biggest mistakes in my life, I almost didn't get to Morocco. I told Henry that
                    all he had to do when I got there was go on leave, that I knew the country so
                    well. I'd had three years there and I knew everybody and he could just go on
                    leave, when I got there. Well, I almost didn't get the job. What actually
                    happened also was that after Henry chose me they had the '67 war and Dick
                    Parker, who was Political Counselor in Cairo, was suddenly available. He was out
                    of a job and my wife, I think, was home or something or other and she told me
                    that she learned that Henry had decided he didn't want me after all and he
                    preferred Dick. But then the Department wanted Dick so badly that Dick didn't
                    get the job and I did. And that's how I got to be DCM in Morocco.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>Dealing with Henry Tasca required great diplomacy. Henry was a marvelous man and
                    very bright but he didn't trust people very much. He started out throwing a lot
                    of little trials in my way and I mastered them all and eventually gained his
                    confidence and we worked beautifully together and I'm sure he was responsible
                    for my being appointed Ambassador to Togo.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you've led me again right into the next one because
                        I was about to say your excellent high-level service in Africa was rewarded
                        again in September in '67 with your appointment as Ambassador to the
                        Republic of Togo. You certainly got your wish to go back to Africa. Would
                        you like to talk a bit about our policy toward that country? How you carried
                        it out, and if you can, what modifications you may have recommended? How did
                        it work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DICKINSON: Well, Tom, our policy probably is best described in the terms of
                    Daniel Patrick Moynihan, one of “benign neglect.” It wasn't really benign
                    neglect but there are literally dozens of countries in Africa. They're tiny,
                    they're poor. They have really almost no effect on anything we do. We have very
                    little commerce with them. The French, for example, in the former French
                    colonies, dominate, as you know, totally dominate the commerce. But our only
                    real interest in the West African countries—our only real national interest, or
                    American interest—seemed to be in getting their vote at the UN for things that
                    were important to us, such as Korea—maintaining the UN force in Korea,
                    maintaining the Chinese representation in the UN. The only thing that happened
                    in the three and a half years I was in Togo that interested the Department at
                    all was the moment at which Mr. Nixon decided to have his so-called opening to
                    Communist China and at the same time had to pacify his right wing in American
                    politics. So he laid on us, and through the Department, the difficult and losing
                    chore of maintaining the recognition of Nationalist China by the countries we
                    were in (and of keeping the nationalists in the UN). It wasn't so much
                    recognition because the recognition took care of itself.</p>
                <p>During that period whenever a country wanted to get rid of the Nationalist
                    Chinese and substitute the representation of the Communist Chinese, all it had
                    to do was to accept the Communist Chinese and the Nationalist immediately
                    withdrew their ambassador. They never had to say, “Out with you”. The
                    Nationalist Chinese policy was to withdraw immediately and it was a self
                    defeating policy. They were going to lose out anyway but it was a self defeating
                    policy, it didn't work. And that's exactly what happened in Togo. I remember
                    that after Nixon had been to China the local newspaper—the only daily newspaper,
                    Togo Presse—had an editorial in which they applauded the idea of Togolese
                    recognition of Communist China and cited Mr. Nixon as their example. I remember
                    they said, “Nixon isn't red, he's not even pink, and he's recognized China.” I'm
                    not sure whether they were a little premature at that point.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>But it was at this point that our government decided to try to maintain two
                    representations at the UN—both the Nationalist Chinese and the Communist
                    Chinese, neither of which would have accepted that. However, we were under great
                    pressure to get the Togolese to vote for a two China policy of some kind, to
                    keep the Nationalist Chinese in. And that resulted in a telephone call from
                    Washington—from then Assistant Secretary of State David Newsom. He had never
                    called me before; it would have been a waste of time if he had. But he called me
                    and told me we had to hold the Togolese firm. We didn't succeed but he later
                    thanked me for my efforts. But that was the only time that the Department ever
                    showed any interest in Togo.</p>
                <p>I must say it was a joy to be Ambassador there. If Morocco was the country that
                    (my wife and) I loved the most for its savage beauty, its raw beauty and its
                    wonderful old cities, Togo was the country in which we were the happiest from
                    the point of view of the people. The West African people are simply the nicest
                    people there are. They're really lovely, delightful people. Somebody who has
                    served in Lagos would dispute that and I would too, but in the countries that
                    you and I served in, Tom, that's really true.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...absolutely, absolutely. Well, we've got a few minutes
                        left here, do you have anything else you would like to add?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DICKINSON: Yes. I'd like to add something in a general sense, something that I
                    feel very strongly about and it came upon me throughout the years in the Foreign
                    Service.</p>
                <p>For one thing, in the lower grades one is never told about CIA covert activities.
                    The US press didn't tell us about them in those days, didn't know about them, or
                    didn't tell us about them. But gradually peculiar things would happen and you
                    would begin to realize that something was happening that you didn't know about.
                    And eventually, of course, it all came out. The fact that we were not only
                    carrying out covert political actions to carry out our objectives, but that we
                    even—as we know in the case of Ollie North and Poindexter—we even had a covert
                    foreign policy which was kept secret from others including Congress, and as far
                    as possible, from the State Department. I'd just like to say here that I think
                    we should totally do away with covert political and military actions. I think we
                    lose a great deal more than we gain by them but since they're wrong to begin
                    with, they don't work. They corrupt the people who carry them out, they end up
                    by corrupting the presidents themselves. This isn't hindsight on my part. I have
                    articles that I've written for the newspapers dating back at least into the
                    '70s—mid-'70s—in which I predicted the corruption of government leaders,
                    including presidents, through their adherence and their dependence on this type
                    of action. I would just like to put my voice in. I would do away with the
                    capability, do away with it totally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, there certainly are many opinions on that and I
                        think you'll probably find some others who would agree with you.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>This has been a very interesting session for me, Dwight. As you know, I know
                    something about your career, aside from preparing for this interview, but you
                    have filled in a lot of spots that either I didn't remember and certainly some I
                    didn't know about. I want to thank you and to put on a more formal note at the
                    end.</p>
                <p>Thank you for taking the time to record your views for this oral history project
                    and thank you for your service to your country. I for one know its a pretty damn
                    good one.</p>
                <p>DICKINSON: Thank you, Ambassador Estes.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
