<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001507">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Robin White </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2007</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>ROBIN WHITE</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: June 30, 2005</p>
                <p>Copyright 2007 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is the 30th of June, 2005. This is an interview with
                        Robin White. This is being done on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic
                        Studies and Training and I am Charles Stuart Kennedy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Robin, let's start at the beginning; when and where you
                        were born?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I was born in Fall River, Massachusetts in 1950 about 50 miles south of
                    Boston, a depressed city that had been a textile town.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fall River. Is this Lizzie Borden's town?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It is indeed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Poor kid, she was an orphan, wasn't she?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, she certainly was after her father and stepmother were murdered. But
                    she was acquitted and lived to an old age.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you tell me a bit about your father's side, where
                        the family came from and then on your mother's side.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I come from a fairly traditional American family in that several ethnic
                    groups met up. My father had a German mother and a Scottish father. My
                    grandfather came from Glasgow when he was four or five years ago and they ended
                    up in Cleveland, Ohio. My father grew up there. He was the roller skating
                    champion of the U.S. for a couple of years and had a case of medals in the
                    basement. He joined the military in World War II and was in the Pacific in the
                    navy.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he talk much about what he did in the war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Not when I was growing up, though later he talked a bit about being on an
                    island and watching a volcano erupt on the other end where the Japanese were.
                    Luckily he wasn't involved in any heavy combat, or at least if he was he didn't
                    talk about it. When I was assigned to Japan I asked him how he felt about
                    visiting there given his war experiences. He said he would have some qualms
                    about such a trip, but in the end it was more practical and logistical problems
                    that kept my parents from visiting. I think that the very positive experiences
                    my daughter and I had changed his viewpoint about the Japanese.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did your grandparents on your father's side do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: My grandfather was a skilled blue collar worker. I don't think he was
                    educated past high school. My grandmother took care of four boys. My father went
                    to business school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did your father do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: As the war was ending he met my mother in Newport where she was working at
                    the naval base after going to secretarial school. When they married he settled
                    in Massachusetts and joined my maternal grandfather's business which was running
                    a small retail liquor store. He stayed with the business and became very active
                    in the national association.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about your mother's side of the family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: My mother is of Irish and French Canadian background. My grandfather's
                    family came from Quebec; there was a lot of intermingling of New Englanders and
                    French Canadians during that period. He ran several businesses including a
                    furniture store during prohibition days. He had owned a couple of restaurants
                    and clubs before that and finally ended up in the retail liquor store business.
                    My grandmother was of Irish background, one of four sisters. Her mother, my
                    great-grandmother, was the mainstay of the family and supported them by doing
                    laundry for the rich textile owners in Fall River.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have brothers or sisters?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I have an older sister who is three years older and a younger brother who
                    is three years younger. My parents believed that higher education was very
                    important and they were extremely supportive of us. My sister was the first in
                    the family to graduate from a four year college.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go to college?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I went to Georgetown School of Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Fall River like when you were a young kid? I
                        assume you grew up there, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I grew up in a town across the river called Somerset, which was somewhat
                    greener and more pleasant than Fall River, which at the time was rather bleak.
                    Fall River had been a textile center but many of the mills had moved south. I
                    worked in a mill during a high school summer, which convinced me the value of a
                    college education as it was a miserable job. The area kept its strong ethnic
                    roots. For example, the Catholic churches are still identified as St. Patrick's
                    the Irish church, St. John of God the Portuguese church, and St. Louis de France
                    the French church. St. Thomas More was for a mixed group.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you grow up as a Catholic?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the church's influence on you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It was part of the routine and ritual of life for almost everyone in the
                    area. Pretty much everybody went either to Sunday school for Protestants or
                    after school catechism classes if you were Catholic and you were identified in a
                    sense in that way. However there was no sense of separation or rivalries among
                    Protestants and Catholics. There were some Jewish families but very much a
                    minority. It was also a racially homogeneous town. There was one Chinese family
                    and that was about it at the time in terms of ethnic diversity, no blacks or
                    Hispanics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about elementary school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I went to a public elementary school three blocks away from my house. I
                    walked to school, home for lunch, and back to school under the guidance of 6th
                    grade patrol leaders. I also went to public high school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you like school?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>WHITE: I enjoyed school and didn't have many problems. I guess I was a fairly
                    bright student and hope not too much of a teacher's pet.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As a child and as you grew up, were you much of a
                        reader?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, I read a great deal and developed a love of libraries that I still
                    have. We didn't have summer-long camps or many organized activities, so those
                    were the days when you sat under a tree in the summer, played cards,
                    occasionally had a glass of lemonade and didn't have a schedule so did a great
                    deal of reading. Living in a small town I was able to walk to the library
                    whenever I wanted and early on discovered a wider world through books.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you think of any books as a kid that you really
                        liked?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I read the Nancy Drew books, which girls all did at that time. There was
                    an interesting series called the Lives of the Saints for children. Historical
                    novels like stories about Princess Elizabeth in the Tower of London caught my
                    attention so I've always had an affinity for British history, probably dating
                    back to childhood reading of stories about the monarchs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you went to high school. What high school was
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Somerset High School.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was that like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It was very much a typical high school of the '60s. There wasn't too much
                    teenage rebellion going on, in Somerset at least, so it was a very conventional
                    upbringing. I was active in yearbook and in the marching band playing
                    saxophone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your family's expectation about college?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: My parents just assumed that we three were going to college and lived very
                    frugally to save for it. I remember one incident when we were reading a book
                    called Wendy Scott, Secretary. That was my sister's name and my mother had
                    bought the book because the author had gone to the same school she had attended.
                    I read the book and it described a satisfying career for the main character. I
                    mentioned that maybe I could be a secretary. I remember my father saying very
                    strongly, “You're not going to be a secretary. You're going to have
                    secretaries.” I thought that was a pretty good vote of confidence in a
                    10-year-old.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have summer jobs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, I started working as soon as I turned 16. Before that I had been
                    baby-sitting and doing other odd jobs. I began working as a waitress in a
                    Friendly's Ice Cream store and did that for several years during the summer and
                    part time during the school year. I was also a swimming instructor for the town
                    program during the summer.</p>
                <p>A job I wanted — and didn't get — was that of a Congressional page. I wrote to my
                    senators and was told “no girls need apply.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In high school were there any courses that you
                        particularly liked and ones that you didn't like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: English, particularly literature, and history were always the courses I
                    found the most interesting. I got through math and science well enough, but my
                    interest didn't lie there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the outside world intrude much? You were in grammar
                        school when Kennedy was elected. Did the family feel engaged in that
                        campaign?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: No, not really, though the assassination in 1963 affected everyone deeply,
                    particularly Massachusetts Catholics. Vietnam was beginning to be a major issue
                    during my high school years, 1964-1968.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were in high school were you reading the daily
                        papers at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I was, but the local paper wasn't very good. It focused on local issues
                    with one page or so international news. Of course I was more concerned as I
                    approached the college years. In 1968, the year I graduated from high school,
                    Robert Kennedy and Martin Luther King were killed. At that time as I was getting
                    ready to go to Washington in July or August, Washington erupted in riots, which
                    must have made my parents quite nervous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went to Georgetown. Why Georgetown?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The School of Foreign Service. I always had an interest in other cultures,
                    and heard the phrase “Foreign Service” sometime in my high school years. The
                    guidance counselor suggested various women's colleges in New England and was a
                    little taken aback that I was so set on Georgetown. No one from my high school
                    had previously gone there.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went there in '68?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes. An interesting thing was that during my interview, the admissions
                    officer said quite bluntly that girls had to have college board scores 100
                    points higher than boys — and they did talk about boys and girls then. It was
                    clear discrimination. They only wanted a few girls because they assumed girls
                    would all get married anyway. At that time it didn't occur to me to rail against
                    the injustice; I just thought of it as a challenge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I suppose in every generation there are obstacles put up
                        that are perceived by the next generation as being obstacles but the
                        generation then just saw them as something to deal with.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, that's true.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned the Martin Luther King riots and the burning
                        and the troops in Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, that was the summer of '68 as I was preparing and packing up and
                    getting ready to go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your parents must not have liked seeing pictures of the
                        82nd Airborne on the streets of Georgetown.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Exactly. My sister had gone to a women's college Boston and was just an
                    hour away, so they certainly worried more about me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you been to Washington before, had you been on a
                        school trip or something like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: There had been a family trip when I was 10 or 12 and then I came down with
                    my father for an interview in the spring to see the campus, which I loved. And I
                    was happy to be in Washington, an exciting international city.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the first place, what did they do with the women in
                        those days at Georgetown?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>WHITE: For dormitories, they put us in with the nursing students, the college
                    with the most women, and the women in the School of Language and Linguistics.
                    There were two dorms close to the hospital, St. Mary's and Darnell Hall. St.
                    Mary's pretty much had all the freshmen girls. At that time they still had
                    parietal rules, which are rules for girls' behavior. We had to be by 10:00 on
                    weeknights and 11:00 or 12:00 on weekends and couldn't have any males in the
                    room. After the riots and the tear gas and upheavals of the next few years,
                    those rules disappeared completely. By the time I left in 1971 the “parietals”
                    had disappeared.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you concentrate on any particular area in the School
                        of Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I had taken French in high school but I had read a lot of Dostoyevsky so I
                    decided to take Russian. I began the language and took various courses in
                    Russian history, Soviet economics, etc., so that was my area of geographic
                    concentration. The Foreign Service students all took history, government and
                    economics courses, a triple major.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this your real first exposure to people looking
                        seriously at the world beyond?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It was my first exposure to a diverse group of people and first exposure
                    to city life and to an atmosphere where everybody was intellectually engaged and
                    ready to work hard. I enjoyed college.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you got there in '68 things were really cranking up
                        in Vietnam. What was happening on the Georgetown campus?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Most people were against the war and there was a sense already that it was
                    a war that could not be won militarily or politically. Student opposition was
                    not surprising since all the young men were subject to the draft at that time.
                    One of my vivid memories is watching TV in a dorm lobby with a group of friends,
                    male and female, as they read off the lottery numbers which were based on
                    birthdays. If a young man got a low number, he felt quite desperate, for that
                    meant Vietnam. Some of the reaction was self-preservation, but in large part the
                    feeling was that this was a bad war at the wrong time with the U.S. Army
                    supporting a corrupt regime. It was a difficult period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the campus authorities intervene? Were there
                        demonstrations?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>WHITE: There were no demonstrations, no taking over halls or disrupting classes
                    on the campus. However Georgetown students participated in the marches that took
                    place in Washington. There were several very large ones with several hundred
                    thousand people while I was there and I participated in them as well. One time,
                    perhaps 1970 or 1971, after Kent State, there were nearby incidents just off
                    campus. Tear gas was used and I got a dose when I walked outside my apartment
                    door. It was a miserable, unpleasant experience. Finals were postponed because
                    there was still tear gas hanging all over the campus. So things were disrupted
                    in D.C., but not specifically at Georgetown by Georgetown students.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the Washington experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It was an exciting city for many reasons. I was then and am still very
                    fond of classical music and hadn't had much opportunity to hear professionals
                    while in high school. In D.C. I went to Constitution Hall, the main site for
                    concerts before the Kennedy Center. I was at some of the opening concerts of the
                    Kennedy Center and that continues to be an important part of my life. I also got
                    involved in the campaign to lower the voting age to 18 and joined a couple of
                    international clubs. There were also stimulating professors and speakers on
                    campus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the view of the Soviet Union at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The view was that the Soviet Union was an unchanging monolith. It was a
                    system was going to exist for some time, and the U.S. had learned to live with
                    the situation. One of my classes was on the Soviet economy. While the course did
                    go into the problems of the economy, the sense was that the Soviet Union was so
                    big and had so many resources that it could continue to move ponderously
                    along.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any teachers that particularly engaged
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: A famous Georgetown personality was Professor Quigley. He gave the
                    freshman Introduction to Civilization course. It was an excellent course and in
                    addition to teaching about early history, he also taught logical thinking. He
                    had very clear ideas about how you were supposed to answer questions and analyze
                    events. Like many of his students, I still remember some of that. Another
                    interesting character was an elderly Jesuit, Father Fadner, who taught Russian
                    history. He would sweep into class in a black cape and a black beret and give
                    detailed, fascinating lectures. And I had very strong economics professors
                    beginning with micro and macro 101. I took those courses because they were
                    required, but my first professor was so good that I ended up spending much of my
                    Foreign Service career doing economic and trade work. I took no Asia-related
                    courses, which is ironic given my later career path.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were there did you find out more about the
                        Foreign Service and the State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: A lot of people at the School of Foreign Service were interested, but I
                    don't remember any visits from FSOs or any special contacts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the student body of the School of Foreign
                        Service? How did they strike you, where were they headed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: A lot of the students were headed for the business world and the
                    curriculum gave them a good basis for that. Only a few from my class ended up in
                    the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the expectations for a young woman at that
                        point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The expectation was that if you were there at the school, you were going
                    to be using your education professionally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean were people just assuming you would get
                        married?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Most people assumed they would get married at some point. In fact I got
                    married while I was in school to a classmate at Georgetown.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did he do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: He was an English major and ended up working for a couple of political
                    campaigns, including the McGovern presidential campaign. This happened right out
                    of school and political consulting became his career. Being in Washington and at
                    Georgetown, with opportunities in government and politics, greatly influenced
                    our lives.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find yourself attracted to the political side as
                        well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, I was very interested as were most of my classmates. After all, it
                    was the time of the Vietnam War and Watergate just a few years later. After I
                    graduated I ended up working on the Hill for a year.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I assume at some point you took the Foreign Service exam?
                        Was it while you were in college?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It was about a year later. I graduated from college in 1971, finishing in
                    three years with summer school. I joined the Foreign Service in 1973, so took
                    the written test in the fall of 1971 and the oral exam in spring of 1972.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a big step for a married woman whose husband was
                        on a different career track. How did this work out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: We thought it would work out somehow. In fact my first two assignments
                    were in Washington. By the time I was ready to go overseas we weren't married
                    anymore, not because of the career paths, but clearly it would have been very
                    complicated if we had still been married as his work was not mobile.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You graduated in '71 and so you went to work on the
                        Hill?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, I was looking for a job in government. I went to visit my
                    Congresswoman, Margaret Heckler, a liberal Republican from Massachusetts, to
                    make her acquaintance and talk to her staff. One of her staff called me a little
                    while later to say they'd lost their receptionist and wondered if I would be
                    interested. I did that job for a few months and then moved up in the office to
                    do casework. I did that for a year and a half.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mrs. Heckler later was an ambassador, wasn't she?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, she was ambassador in Ireland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find Margaret Heckler and working in her
                        office?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Mrs. Heckler was very personable and a very good politician and quite a
                    thoughtful boss. At my level I didn't have a lot of substantive interaction with
                    her. Working on the Hill was valuable experience and I would recommend it to
                    anybody for a short time. You learn about the system and political
                    personalities. I think it does have somewhat of a negative impact on people who
                    are there too long because they see themselves as the center of the world,
                    become convinced of their own importance, and lose touch with reality.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were things playing vis-�-vis the Vietnam War while
                        you were working on the Hill?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>WHITE: I don't remember specific votes. Mrs. Heckler was in a rather odd position
                    being a Republican in a heavily Democratic area, but she was popular in both the
                    Republican side of the district in the Boston suburbs down to the heavily
                    Democratic area of Fall River. She voted in a fairly liberal way, at least for a
                    Republican.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you took the written exam and you passed it the first
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I passed it the first time and then went for the oral a few months
                    later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you recall any of the questions on the oral or how it
                        went?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I took the test in the economics area. I remember a question about the
                    value-added tax and what effect it would have on the U.S. economy. Luckily I had
                    just read an editorial a few weeks before because I didn't remember it from the
                    classroom. Another question had to do with the Soviet economy and it didn't go
                    very well. Apparently they were trying to get me to talk about possible changes
                    that computerization and information technology could bring to a command
                    economy; I just couldn't pick up what they were driving at.</p>
                <p>I remember going into the test thinking I wasn't going to pass at all, unlike the
                    written test. I generally did well on written tests, but I didn't have much
                    experience with oral exams and I thought I would do poorly on one as notorious
                    as the Foreign Service exam. I went into it with a sense that it was going to be
                    an interesting experience and good training for a future effort, so my life
                    didn't depend on it. This attitude probably made me more relaxed and effective
                    than I would have been if I had been desperate to pass, so somewhat to my shock
                    I passed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the question raised about what your husband thought?
                        That wouldn't be allowed today.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I don't remember that coming up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then so you came in the Foreign Service when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I entered in June 1973. It was the Watergate period and a very intense
                    time in Washington. My then husband had worked for McGovern and so we suspected
                    our phones might have been tapped; people were rather paranoid, some with good
                    reason. When the Washington Post began its disclosures it was quite exciting to
                    run to see what the morning headline would be. I remember watching the Sam Ervin
                    hearings which enthralled me when I was home for six months with my baby
                    daughter.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the group in your A100 basic officer course
                        like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Our class was a large one for that time, about 50 people and quite a few
                    women. One notable person was Eleanor Constable who was coming back into the
                    service after being forced to resign when she got married. That archaic rule had
                    just changed and she was one of the first to come back. It was a very congenial
                    group and some people remain good friends 30 some years later. I think the A100
                    process is a terrific thing because it leads to bonding that continues
                    throughout one's career.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't want to dwell on the gender issue, but you were
                        there at an interesting time. Did you have the feeling that the Foreign
                        Service was learning how to accept women in the full role and not have all
                        the qualifications that they used to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: As far as I could tell, none of the women I who came in about the time I
                    did had a sense of constraint or limits. We assumed that we were professionals
                    and that we were going to do well and be treated properly. It was a healthy way
                    to start, but I can't, of course, speak to how all those careers developed.
                    Several women became ambassadors; in fact the first person to make ambassador
                    was Maryann Casey, who was ambassador in Algeria.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your first assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: My first assignment was in the East Asia Bureau in the Economic Policy
                    Office (EAP/EP.) I didn't have any East Asia background but wanted to work on
                    economic affairs. I began as moderately interested in Asia and ended up learning
                    a lot about East Asian economies. That was when I first visited Japan and knew I
                    wanted to return, as I did a few years later.</p>
                <p>EAP/EP was a small new office that covered regional economic policy. There were
                    three officers. It has now become considerably large because it is the office
                    for APEC matters, but at the time it was handling transnational issues and
                    relations with other agencies such as the Commerce Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I imagine at that point that textiles were a major area of
                        interest.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: This was after the major bilateral textile problems as multilateral
                    restraints were in place by then. Issues like mushrooms, footwear and of course
                    automobiles were starting to be problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the mushroom conflict with Pennsylvania and
                        Korea?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, Pennsylvania growers were trying to block Korean imports. That was my
                    first experience with political pressure for specific import restraints. It was
                    surprising for me — having studied economics in school which never mentioned
                    politics — to see the power of a fairly small group of politicians who faced no
                    opposition from other congressmen or senators because they might want similar
                    treatment for products from their states.</p>
                <p>During that time I took a couple of trips relating to interagency work to
                    regularize commercial programs. I went to Japan, Taiwan, Korea and Hong Kong.
                    This travel was my first trip outside of the U.S. so my first passport was a
                    diplomatic one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you consider language training? Were you interested in
                        becoming an Asia specialist?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes. I think it helped that on my first trip to Japan, literally my first
                    time outside North America, an A100 classmate was in Japan and showed me around.
                    Tokyo can be a very intimidating city but with a Japanese speaking friend I was
                    able to do more than just go to business meetings. I liked Japan from the
                    beginning and I think having that introduction helped.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And your next tour?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: My second tour was in the Trade Office in the Economic Bureau (EB) during
                    the Tokyo Round of multilateral trade negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you pass through the hands of Francis Wilson?
                        Unfortunately she has passed away. Anybody who was an economic officer of a
                        certain era knows Francis Wilson, the civil servant who had a big influence
                        at State. Could you talk about her a bit?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Francis Wilson was Executive Director of the Economic Bureau for many
                    years. She took a strong interest in people in the economic cone, junior
                    officers as well as the more senior, and kept a careful eye on her people. It
                    was the best kind of mentoring. She knew all the economic officers and she had a
                    strong voice in the assignment process. With Francis on their side, people felt
                    they were in very good hands.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That shows the power and influence for the good that
                        somebody can have within the bureaucracy.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>WHITE: At the time and probably still to a certain extent the political officers
                    thought that they were the most important people in the Service and that they
                    were the real Foreign Service Officers. Ms. Wilson and the people who worked
                    with her were determined that economic officers should get their just rewards,
                    including the most senior positions. It seems that a shift did occur in which
                    economic work was recognized as having equal importance. This was even more the
                    case in a country like Japan, especially during the period of serious trade
                    tensions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in the Economic Bureau?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I was mainly working on non-tariff negotiations in the multilateral trade
                    round. These were issues such as quantitative restrictions, subsidies and
                    countervailing duties, customs valuation. It was a complex interagency process.
                    The U.S. Trade Representative's office, USTR, chaired the interagency meetings
                    and delegations to Geneva talks</p>
                <p>In previous trade rounds the focus had been mostly on tariffs, but by that time,
                    developed countries tariffs had come down in most sectors, though they were
                    still very high in textiles, agriculture and other sensitive areas. But in
                    general tariffs weren't the big barriers anymore. The greater barriers were
                    non-tariff restrictions, or NTMs. One example is quantitative restrictions or
                    quotas. Even if the tariff on a good were zero, a quantitative restriction would
                    allow only a small amount of goods.</p>
                <p>Another major concern we had was subsidies. We were trying to develop a code to
                    define what is or what isn't an acceptable subsidy. For example, an acceptable
                    subsidy might be a government giving special funds to a poor part of the country
                    to develop infrastructure, whereas an unacceptable subsidy would be to give a
                    couple of million dollars to an industry to produce a product for export. We
                    were trying to set up a red light, green light, yellow light system, with yellow
                    acceptable under certain limited circumstances. There were a lot of yellow light
                    subsidies and defining them was difficult. A third issue I worked on was customs
                    valuation. Customs officials have a great deal of leeway to judge what tariff
                    classification an item falls under. That could make the difference between a 2%
                    or 20% tariff.</p>
                <p>The Tokyo Round negotiations marked the beginning of codes that are now in place.
                    At the time the organization was called the General Agreement on Trade and
                    Tariffs (GATT); it is now the World Trade Organization or WTO. I went to Geneva
                    a couple of times to be involved in the multilateral trade talks and once or
                    twice to Brussels to meet with European Union officials and to Paris for
                    Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) talks. It was a
                    good opportunity to learn about multilateral negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have problems with the Congress passing subsidies
                        while you were trying to limit them?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>WHITE: That certainly has happened with agricultural subsidies. We had some
                    pretty egregious non-tariff measure of our own, some of which were grandfathered
                    when the GATT began, such as sugar quotas that continue today. If there were
                    complaints from Capitol Hill, they were handled by USTR rather than State
                    directly. Our role was somewhat subsidiary because when it came to issues like
                    customs valuation, Treasury and Commerce had the lead. Nonetheless the State
                    Department wanted EB to be involved as a strong presence in the talks even if we
                    didn't have specific expertise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To get a feel for this when you say you were dealing with
                        non-tariff items and subsidies. What does that mean? What were you
                        doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: As I said, I didn't have the technical expertise that people in Customs or
                    Commerce did, but we tried to provide policy options. If the negotiation seemed
                    stalled, we tried to step back and look at the broader picture, suggesting an
                    approach from a different direction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for the international community? Were
                        there natural allies and opponents while the negotiations were going
                        on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It was a complex dance. At that time, with the major exceptions of
                    agriculture and airplanes, we had a lot of concerns in common with the EU and to
                    a certain extent with the Japanese because we were all trying to open up the
                    developing country markets. Probably the Australians, New Zealanders and
                    Canadians were the people who were ideologically closest to U.S. positions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved in sheep and wool with Canadians and
                        New Zealanders?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: No, because that was agriculture trade and that's a separate division in
                    EB. Luckily I didn't have to do that and the bilateral problems didn't have much
                    of an effect on the multilateral talks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel that your economic skills were
                        improving?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, I learned a great deal about the technical side of trade. I also
                    learned that you don't have to be a PhD economist to be a Foreign Service
                    economic officer because so much of what we do is political economy. It isn't
                    based on analysis and graphs and logical explanations of what will happen as
                    variables change. Occasionally in interagency meetings a well trained economist
                    would explain why a policy would be self-defeating or counterproductive —
                    speaking about a protectionist action usually. People from other agencies would
                    reply that if a politics demanded it, the economic analysis really didn't
                    matter. Of course it is important to take into account the economic analysis but
                    the reality is that politics are more the deciding factor in trade disputes and
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Geneva did you get a sense of the various countries and
                        their style of trade negotiations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Most delegations were well prepared with their positions, which some
                    explained at tedious length, but the horse-trading and bargaining took place
                    behind the scenes, often involving small groups. One trial was that at that time
                    at the GATT smoking was allowed in the meeting halls. We were sitting right
                    behind the Mexicans and they smoked all the time. Diplomatically speaking they
                    were fine to work with, but it must have been a welcome change for the American
                    delegation when non-smoking policies finally reached there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Everybody forgets today when you could smoke anywhere,
                        particularly on the airplanes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: In a tough negotiation that went into the evening it was hard to be in a
                    smoke filled room. People who didn't mind it really had an unfair advantage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your next tour?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Then I had the FSI economics course that I found very valuable even though
                    I'd had economics in college. It was an excellent intense review. At that time I
                    was bidding on jobs overseas. My marriage had ended so I took into consideration
                    living overseas with my five-year-old daughter. I was initially assigned to
                    Embassy Brussels, which sounded fine to me. I had information about schools and
                    apartments when they eliminated the job in April or May, quite late in the
                    cycle. I was rather perturbed about the last minute change.</p>
                <p>Then a job opened up in Rabat, Morocco. Because I had French I was qualified, and
                    I was soon convinced that it was a much better assignment than living and
                    working in Brussels. It turned out very well. From the substantive point of view
                    I learned a great deal working in a small economic/commercial section. It was a
                    fascinating country for travel, and a very easy place to live with a child.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When were you in Morocco?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: 1978 to 1980.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Morocco at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: King Hussein was a strong ally of the U.S and generally popular with the
                    Moroccans, who greatly respected him, but there were human rights problems. It
                    became politically very interesting when the U.S. Embassy in Tehran was taken
                    over in 1979 because shortly thereafter the Shah of Iran came to Rabat and spent
                    some months there and then in Marrakech. There was concern that Morocco would be
                    a target for the people who opposed the Shah. This was at the time when our
                    embassies in Algeria and Pakistan were attacked.</p>
                <p>That was the first experience most of us had had with any type of terrorist
                    concerns, so embassies across the Middle East and North Africa were told to
                    prepare plans. The planning was pretty basic compared to the anti-terrorist
                    steps embassies are forced to take today. Embassy Rabat was a lovely and quite
                    open building which at least at that time would not have been very defensible.
                    In case of an attack we were supposed to grab our classified files, run out the
                    back door, and put them in barrels the marines would then put gasoline on and
                    light. It was suggested that we then go over the back fence and find our way to
                    the British or Canadian ambassadors' houses. It was a nerve-wracking time
                    because of our concern about what was happening elsewhere, but we didn't have
                    any sense of real danger from the Moroccan people. We were all very worried
                    about people in the embassy in Tehran, one of them being the security officer
                    from Morocco who had gone there; his photo appeared right after the takeover, so
                    we did take it personally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. What was your job in Morocco?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I was an economic/commercial officer. It was a small section with three
                    people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have much contact with the Moroccans
                        themselves?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>WHITE: As I didn't speak Arabic, my contacts were with the French speakers, so
                    I'm not sure how representative they were of the general public. It was an urban
                    elite. I met more working class Moroccans because my daughter had friends in the
                    neighborhood. She made friends with the children of the maids and we
                    occasionally went to their gatherings where we were warmly welcomed. We didn't
                    communicate a whole lot, since most of them didn't speak much French or English,
                    but it was still very interesting culturally to go to these little parties in
                    the back of the big houses.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Richard Parker was the ambassador, a respected Arabic scholar, an
                    excellent leader, and it was a pleasure to work for and learn from him. We had
                    the sense that the king didn't really like him because he knew too much about
                    Arab society and had his own sources of information outside government
                    circles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, one of the things said about King Hussein is that he
                        liked political appointees because he usually ended up co-opting them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Ambassador Parker was followed by Ambassador Angier Biddle Duke, a
                    political ambassador but a good one. He had a very good presence and great
                    contacts in Washington. I was often invited to the residence by him and Mrs.
                    Duke because the Moroccans guests didn't bring their wives to dinner. It gave
                    me, a relatively junior officer, a chance to meet a number of interesting
                    people.</p>
                <p>Another point about being a woman in Morocco is that I think my life was made
                    easy by being a mother. Sarah and I traveled all over the country. We went to
                    Marrakech, Fez, Chaouen, down to the desert a couple of times. I never felt
                    threatened or harassed verbally while I think a single woman on her own might
                    have felt uncomfortable. Because I was there with a child I was a respectable
                    woman. My daughter adored Morocco and it had a great deal of influence on her
                    life. Morocco is a wonderful country for traveling and the people we met were
                    very gracious.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a significant expatriate community in Morocco at
                        the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: There were a lot of French and a small American community. There was an
                    American school that then went to 8th grade and many of the teachers were
                    American women married to Moroccan men. That was another way we met Moroccan
                    families. The American community more than doubled around 1979 because
                    Westinghouse came in with a large number of people. They were setting up a
                    communications project so a number of new families arrived.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had the hippie movement died off by that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: That was not visible in Rabat. I think probably Tangier and Marrakech got
                    the hippies. I didn't do consular work. I feel they saw a lot more of that side
                    of the expatriate community.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tangier seemed to get a lot of European and American
                        hippies.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: To me, Tangier was the least attractive city in Morocco. Unfortunately a
                    lot of Europeans and Americans came over just for a day from Spain and they got
                    a negative impression of the country from that city. There were many aggressive
                    men wanting to be guides and a lot of people trying to sell things so the mood
                    was not at all typical of other cities which were welcoming without that edge of
                    hostility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was going on economically in Morocco at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The country had a lot of potential that wasn't really realized. Several
                    trade missions and some high level visits were set up but American interest
                    wasn't high. The U.S. Generalized System of Preferences (GSP) was in place at
                    that time and I worked to educate Moroccan officials and businesses about the
                    opportunities that tariff-free treatment for certain goods might bring. The
                    major resources were fisheries and phosphates, but not much developed while I
                    was there. Phosphate development was complicated by the long war with the
                    Polisario in the Sahara.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about dealing with Moroccan officials? Did you find
                        them competent in the economic sphere, was there much to talk to them
                        about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I found it somewhat frustrating because at my level of bureaucracy, my
                    contacts were not very forthcoming. The economic counselor was able to approach
                    the more senior people and found them more willing to discuss details and make
                    commitments. At my level there seemed to be an uncertainty and nervousness about
                    talking to foreigners. I think that is a problem for junior to mid-level
                    officers in countries where people don't feel that they can speak freely. I
                    didn't really feel like I got inside the bureaucracy nor had very good
                    sources.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It seems that Morocco is a country with good ties to
                        France, good ties to the United States and the West and yet like many
                        Islamic countries, they don't seem to have developed a good working
                        infrastructure that fits into the 20th or 21st century. There isn't the kind
                        of economic development like in East Asia. Did you look at that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>WHITE: It seemed that there was not a strong entrepreneurial spirit. The
                    impression I got from some Moroccan business people was that they put more
                    emphasis on knowing the right people rather than developing a plan individually.
                    There was a fairly small business elite in Rabat, which was not the business
                    center. Casablanca was the big commercial city and there probably was a good
                    deal more entrepreneurship there. Morocco is a rich country agriculturally with
                    fertile hills and fields. There was great potential, but there didn't seem to be
                    the infrastructure to support trade. For example, we saw huge piles of melons by
                    the road for sale. All the melons ripened at the same time and they'd be sold
                    for just about nothing. If they could have been shipped to Europe there would
                    have been a lot of money for the farmers and a processing industry might have
                    developed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do in '80?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: That's when I bid on Japan. Thanks in part to my first tour in the East
                    Asia Bureau I was known to people there and assigned to the economic section in
                    Tokyo via two years of language training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk a bit about language training. How did you find
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I lack the language gene, so it was difficult. I worked very hard at it
                    and I got my 3/3 in Japanese, but it was constant work. I was at the Foreign
                    Service Institute (FSI) at Rosslyn for a year, which was not an attractive place
                    physically. We were in a high rise and in small airless rooms doing fairly
                    stressful work, though I enjoyed the teachers and my fellow classmates. The FSI
                    campus at Arlington Hall is a great improvement and much more pleasant
                    surroundings for students.</p>
                <p>Then I went to Yokohama, a pleasant environment. Yokohama is a great city as an
                    introduction to Japan. It is a large city, but seems much more relaxed and green
                    compared to nearby Tokyo. My classmates were interesting because the Foreign
                    Service Institute at that time also had Canadian, Australian and New Zealand
                    officials, which made for a nice mix. It was a good combination of backgrounds
                    there, and gave us a wider circle of friends and contacts when we moved on to
                    Tokyo. We also did field trips and travel, so it was a good year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you learned the language was the cultural and social
                        structure part of what you learned?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>WHITE: It was. I don't remember specifically what I learned in area studies,
                    which is ironic because I'm now teaching the Japan Area Studies class at FSI,
                    but students imbibed a sense of culture and social structure as they learned the
                    language. Japanese is a very hierarchical language and words and structure
                    reflect the way people interact. Women have a certain way of talking that is
                    very distinct from men's tones and vocabulary. You talk one way to your seniors
                    and one way to your subordinates. That is really the most difficult part of
                    Japanese. You're not learning one language; you have to at least be able to
                    understand quite a range of different manners of speech. We were taught basic,
                    standard speech, such as radio announcers would use, but it was always difficult
                    to understand when listening to TV or movies when people weren't speaking
                    standard Japanese or were talking in what might be considered slang.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It seems that a lot of Japanese women seem to speak in a
                        higher tone than necessary.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, it is considered a polite feminine form of speech.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did they teach foreign women?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The FSI teachers are careful to teach the students, male or female, to
                    speak a standard neutral Japanese. All the teachers in Washington were women, so
                    they were very careful not to give the male students certain mannerisms or
                    speech patterns that would be considered feminine. Neutral speech from a
                    foreigner is pretty much what the Japanese would expect. They don't expect most
                    foreigners to make the speech distinctions Japanese do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the writing system? It is like the Chinese,
                        isn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: There are two different alphabets based on syllables, hiragana and
                    katakana, the latter used for foreign worlds. There are also thousands of kanji
                    which are the Chinese characters. We were taught to read kanji. It was pure
                    memorization so students focused on their substantive areas and learned the
                    kanji for technical words. I was trained to read economic and trade articles and
                    was able to get a 3/3 reading economic articles, but had I been given an article
                    about missile defense, I wouldn't have been able to read it at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When in Yokohama, were you able to use your Japanese?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>WHITE: That was the great benefit of living and studying in Japan. From the
                    beginning we were living in Japanese neighborhoods, talking to the families, and
                    shopping in little stores. There were also “conversation ladies,” who came as
                    volunteers to chat with the students and get together for tea and casual
                    conversation. The Japanese really appreciate people trying to speak the language
                    and praise any effort. It is a positive atmosphere for learning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q.You went to Embassy Tokyo in 1982?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, in June 1982, and I stayed four more years in Japan. Former Senate
                    Majority Leader Mike Mansfield was the ambassador, one of our longest serving
                    ambassadors who served under both Republicans and Democrats. He was greatly
                    respected by everyone, a gentleman and a man of great integrity. Don Oberdorfer
                    wrote a good biography of him a few years ago.</p>
                <p>I was a mid-level officer in the economic section and I had a double portfolio.
                    The more demanding part was transportation. At that time, Japan's export of
                    automobiles was the major trade problem with the U.S., a very political issue.
                    Aviation negotiations occupied a great deal of my time and we saw a lot of
                    changes in the aviation relationship during that period. I also followed
                    shipping.</p>
                <p>The other half of the portfolio was reporting on Japan's relationship with the
                    communist countries. I reported on their trade with China, with the Soviet Union
                    and handled the COCOM issue, which related to controls on the export of
                    strategic materials.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q.Was Japanese essential for your work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Probably not essential. Most of the people I worked with in the Foreign
                    Ministry and in MITI, the Ministry of International Trade and Industry, spoke
                    English. The Ministry of Transportation people who were my other main contacts
                    were mixed in terms of language. The people in the International Division spoke
                    English but with some of the more technical bureaus we did things in Japanese.
                    My Japanese was adequate, but I must admit that it never reached a level of real
                    fluency where I could feel comfortable doing a negotiation without a Foreign
                    Service National (FSN) to back me up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know the feeling. In the early 1980's, how did you find
                        being a woman dealing with the Japanese? Was it a problem or were you just
                        the 800 lb. gorilla representing the United States and it didn't make any
                        difference?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>WHITE: I think it didn't make much difference. It was very different from how I
                    would have been treated had I been a Japanese woman. I was an American and
                    therefore dealt with as an American, and also had the advantage of being an
                    American diplomat. I think an American businesswoman or reporter would not have
                    had as easy access as I did, but they had to deal with me on government to
                    government issues. I also think that for some Japanese it was a novelty to be
                    sitting across the table from a woman. Speaking some Japanese helped, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On that subject, I don't know how it worked for embassy
                        people, but business people often had to go out drinking in the evenings
                        when the business was really done. Was this the case?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Certainly drinking after work hours is a major part of the Japanese
                    business lifestyle and also to a certain extent the government official's
                    lifestyle. It is considered important to cement business ties at a social level.
                    I occasionally went out to dinner with people and went to a lot of receptions
                    but didn't go often to smoky bars. Not too many embassy people did. Those who
                    spoke Japanese very well, particularly those who had lived in Japan earlier as
                    students, went out more with the Japanese. People in the political section,
                    especially those following the political parties, worked to make that sort of
                    social connection. Most people, especially those with families, worked long
                    enough hours and had to go to enough official functions that we limited the bar
                    scene to what was really necessary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's take the issues one at a time. On the transportation
                        side, what was the car situation at that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: That was the time when Japanese exports were really overwhelming GM, Ford
                    and Chrysler. To a certain degree it was a problem of American quality and fuel
                    efficiency. People had noticed that relatively inexpensive Toyotas or Hondas
                    tended to last and, being smaller, get better mileage. To the American
                    automakers' credit, they did restructure and started turning out much better
                    products, but initially the reaction was political. Given the trade deficit, it
                    was easy to generate protectionist Buy America campaigns and Congressional
                    pressure on the Japanese. Congress got involved with threats of legislation and
                    quotas; also the Super 301 amendment to the Trade Act was passed. That was aimed
                    at “unfair” trade practices of any country, but mainly was aimed at Japan.
                    Because the auto industry is such a major part of the U.S. economy, autos were
                    the prime target.</p>
                <p>It was also a problem because very few American autos were exported to Japan.
                    There were a number of reasons for that. One was that U.S. autos tended to be
                    quite big and gas guzzling and weren't practical in a Japanese city. Therefore
                    most of the U.S. automakers hadn't made much of an effort to meet Japan's
                    standards. For example, American steering wheels were on the wrong side for
                    Japanese roads, but American companies didn't make a right hand drive model.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>Foreign companies had a very hard time getting into distribution networks. There
                    were also some strange and complicated technical issues on the Japanese side.
                    You had to have fold down mirrors and special headlights. You had to have
                    special shields for catalytic converters. Due to the strict standards, it was
                    very expensive, about $1000, for every American car that came to Japan to be
                    reconstituted, ostensibly for safety reasons. I worked to get more American cars
                    into Japan. On my home leave I spent a good deal of time in Detroit visiting the
                    testing facilities of the major American companies. I wanted to see the emphasis
                    they put on safety in order to argue authoritatively that the U.S. safety tests
                    should be accepted. The Japanese were saying they needed to be done all over
                    again in Japan. What eventually developed was a program that allowed small
                    quantities, e.g. 1,000 cars, to come in without having to go through all the
                    tests and changes. It was a special exception made for political purposes.</p>
                <p>As to exports to the U.S., a “voluntary” restraint agreement (VRA) was put in
                    place in 1981 whereby a set number of cars was to be exported. I believe it was
                    186,000 cars a year. That left the Japanese government to decide who got the
                    quotas, which meant they looked at past export records. This favored Toyota and
                    Nissan. Honda, which was late in entering the U.S. markets, got a much smaller
                    quota so there was a lot of political concern within Japan about how to allocate
                    the 186,000 among their big three and smaller companies.</p>
                <p>The irony is that the VRA gave U.S. companies breathing room to restructure, but
                    it also really strengthened Japanese companies. Protectionist pressure often has
                    such negative results. Extra profit went to the Japanese companies as Toyotas,
                    for example, were in short supply in the U.S. Toyota dealers could ask for
                    premium payments above the list price, so the Japanese ended up shipping their
                    more expensive models because they could only ship a certain number. Profits in
                    the American market gave them large capital reserves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were Americans and Japanese looking at building Japanese
                        cars in the United States? My wife has a 2001 Toyota with a sticker saying
                        60% was built in the United States. Was this a factor?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>WHITE: Major Japanese investment in the U.S. developed during that time period.
                    From the mid-1980s there was a migration of auto plants to the U.S. Obviously,
                    since they couldn't ship all the finished cars they could sell, they realized
                    that they could assemble cars in the U.S. and they would be U.S. cars not
                    subject to the VRA. That caused political controversy too and at least initially
                    the critics were right that this was not real U.S. production. Companies were
                    sending over the most expensive, high tech parts like the engines and just
                    having them put into car frames by Americans, which wasn't doing a lot for
                    American employment. Because of the pressure for more American content, they
                    gradually increased parts production in the U.S. In many cases, however, the
                    parts suppliers were Japanese transplants as well, part of the keiretsu or
                    inter-connected company network. That caused many complaints as well. Still,
                    Americans got more jobs and many states benefited. Local content is now quite
                    high.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they talking to you or the embassy on this
                        subject?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The U.S. government encouraged foreign investment in the U.S.,
                    particularly the Commerce Department and the Commercial Section at the Embassy.
                    The purpose was to increase employment opportunities for Americans. The Embassy
                    was helpful to a lot of state governments that opened trade offices in Tokyo.
                    Those trade offices, which had been to encourage Japanese to purchase their
                    exports, became more active as investment promotion offices. Many states offered
                    good tax benefits to encourage companies to locate there. That worked well for
                    places like Kentucky, Tennessee, and Alabama, though not much investment went to
                    the traditional auto-producing — and unionized — states like Michigan and
                    Ohio.</p>
                <p>As more Japanese investment went in, and there began to be “buying of America”
                    concerns, the Japanese were clever enough to seek good labor relations, join in
                    community activities, contribute heavily to local charities. Now they are a real
                    presence in the U.S. and that has a political impact. Their employees are
                    voters, and congressmen see the benefits of foreign investment. If someone
                    proposed protectionist action against Toyota, for example, you'd see tens of
                    thousands of Toyota employees in the U.S. objecting. Toyota is a good case of
                    community involvement, as they now have plants in a number of states. One of
                    their good programs is to send high school teachers to Japan for a month each
                    year, at first from the states where they had plants but now from all over, I
                    think. Many of these teachers have never been out of the country before and
                    their students have little international exposure. They come back and talk about
                    Japan to their students and to their communities and it makes a difference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a cultural movement spurred by industry?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>WHITE: It was fairly calculating, e.g. we're going to be facing political
                    pressures for a long time, so let's find a way to be in the U.S. market and
                    develop a countervailing force against protectionism in the Congress. Many
                    excellent exchange programs have been developed, in part due to a political
                    motivation to gain greater American understanding of and sympathy for Japan.
                    Jobs were key, but education and cultural exchanges were and are very valuable
                    whatever the initial motivation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did automobile manufacturers and others in Japan
                        understand the American market and the political system or was it a learning
                        process?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: They got a lot more sophisticated in the 1980s. Japanese corporations put
                    a lot more money into hiring Americans. That led to domestic criticism of K
                    Street lobbyists hired for their political connections. They also hired people
                    to do analysis and publish studies, including economic work, and it was not
                    usually biased in favor of the Japanese. But nonetheless it was an ugly period
                    due to the trade tensions. At one point several congressmen took sledgehammers
                    and destroyed a Japanese automobile on Capitol Hill in full view of the cameras.
                    That was replayed many times on Japanese TV and Japanese still talk of it today.
                    There was an even uglier incident when some drunken unemployed autoworkers beat
                    to death a Chinese American because they thought he was Japanese.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember that. That was just terrible. .</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: That of course brought a lot of memories of the discrimination in World
                    War II when the Japanese Americans were put in interment camps.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the Japanese exclusion at the turn of the
                        century.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: That's right. So a lot of Japanese at first felt defensive, then
                    resentful, about why they were hated when they saw themselves as just working
                    hard and making good products. In the U.S. there were articles and books with
                    the theme that we won the war, but the Japanese really won in the long run with
                    their economic dominance.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>On a more thoughtful note, writers in the revisionist school of political
                    economy, led by people like James Fallows and Clyde Prestowitz, were writing
                    books saying that Japan could not be treated as a normal nation in terms of
                    trade policy. The theory was that countries like the U.S. and the EU worked
                    within in the GATT rules, but Japan, due to the structure of its
                    business-government relationships, simply operated outside the rules. The answer
                    therefore had to be managed trade in which there would be quotas and arranged
                    markets on both sides. So it was good policy to limit the Japanese to 186,000
                    cars a year in the U.S. market and require the Japanese to import 10% of
                    semi-conductors from foreign markets. That was a very strong trend throughout
                    the '80s. The pressure diminished in the '90s when it turned out that the
                    Japanese system was not as infallible and ready to take over the world as had
                    been feared; also the Japanese vigorously resisted pressure for more specific
                    numbers.</p>
                <p>Another revisionist concern was that that because Japanese companies' source of
                    capital and capital flows were different from ours, the Japanese companies did
                    not have to worry about profits. They could just concentrate on market share.
                    That was true, and it helped them grow for many years, but it wasn't
                    sustainable. In the '90s it turned out that because they hadn't had to worry
                    about profits they made a lot of unprofitable investments that then came home to
                    roost and led to a decade of stagnation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was no basic accountability.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes. Because banks rather than the stock market were the source of
                    capital, and because of close keiretsu ties between banks and corporations, you
                    didn't have a real cost of capital. Therefore there was no outside demand that
                    required it to be used in an efficient way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During the '80s there were books about how the U.S. should
                        copy the Japanese system. In many ways, we did with better quality control,
                        as in automobiles, which have changed considerably.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: There was a positive interest in quality control. Also some firms gave
                    workers more responsibility for pointing out areas of concern or for
                    improvement, and the ability to stop the assembly line if something was going
                    wrong. That was a lesson from Japanese factories.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about your relationship with your Japanese
                        counterparts? This was a very difficult time because of the anti-Japanese
                        feeling fostered by exactly what you were dealing with, particularly the
                        automobile issue. Did you find this reflected in dealing with your Japanese
                        counterparts?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>WHITE: On an individual basis there was no hostility. There was a
                    professionalism, a sense that regardless of what our governments or politicians
                    were saying, and certainly regardless of what the press was saying, we had to
                    work together to solve the problems. It helped that Ambassador Mansfield was
                    well respected by the Japanese and was considered very even-handed. That got him
                    into trouble back in the U.S., of course, because any ambassador who seems
                    sympathetic to the host country is considered to have gone over to the enemy.
                    But in fact while trying to explain to Americans where the Japanese were coming
                    from and why they took certain positions, he still pressured them hard for
                    market opening actions.</p>
                <p>The economic section handled a lot of delegations, usually led by USTR, sometimes
                    by the Commerce Department and there were long difficult negotiations. But there
                    was no animosity among the people involved. Americans from these other agencies
                    often were fairly new to work with the Japanese, but over the years developed
                    into very savvy negotiators who really understood the system.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I understand from a person from the Commerce Department I
                        interviewed that the Foreign Service National (FSN) Japanese staff was
                        invaluable during negotiations in being able to point out flaws and
                        inaccuracies on the Japanese side.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I think most embassies have extraordinary FSNs and benefit greatly from
                    their knowledge. At that time in Embassy Tokyo, there was a transitional period
                    because the first generation that had been hired after the war was retiring.
                    They had started working in the '50s or early '60s and were a great source of
                    advice. As you noted, they played a big role from the back row as they could
                    remember what had happened in previous talks. Short tour Americans were at a
                    disadvantage. The Japanese brought huge delegations into the room. They would
                    have 10 or 12 people at the table and 25 young people behind. The young people
                    were all taking notes as part of their training. This meant that they had very
                    good records and could go back and say something like, “In 1978 the deputy
                    assistant secretary said X, which contradicts what you are saying now.” We
                    didn't always know the background because we changed so much. The more senior
                    Japanese staff at the embassy were a big help there; I'm not sure they were
                    always invited to participate, but they should have been in the room. Also, as
                    other agency personnel don't change as much, a strong cadre of American
                    government experts has developed over the last 20 or 30 years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about bureaucratic practices designed to stifle
                        imports into Japan?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>WHITE: Japanese bureaucrats used the excuse of safety regulations to make things
                    very difficult. That was certainly true in the automobile case. Regulations on
                    things like the size or brightness of headlights had unnecessarily narrow
                    limits, things were obscure, and the bureaucrats were totally rigid about
                    things. But there were also misunderstandings. There was one possible non-tariff
                    barrier that people thought was an outrage until they found out the whole story.
                    Parking lots were refusing to allow foreign cars into their lots. The assumption
                    was that the Japanese had such deep anti-foreign car feeling that they wouldn't
                    let American cars be parked. It turned out that the yakuza, the Japanese
                    gangsters, were among the biggest consumers of black Cadillacs. That was a sign
                    of gangster prosperity. Not many other people would buy them for that reason.
                    The parking lot attendants said “no foreign cars” because they were terrified
                    that a Cadillac would get scratched and they'd have their kneecaps broken. You
                    do have to look below the surface sometimes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we look at retaliation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: We threatened more than we acted. A number of trade cases under Section
                    301 of the Trade Act were brought. The interagency group considered them, tried
                    to negotiate and drew up a list of items for retaliation, but very few of them
                    got to the retaliation stage. It was actually a failure if we reached the
                    retaliatory stage, for it meant that the U.S. hadn't been able to gain the trade
                    liberalization we sought. It was better to make a deal.</p>
                <p>Regarding import procedures, another issue I worked on related to customs
                    procedures. Japan has a terribly inefficient airport, Narita Airport, which
                    serves Tokyo. It was politically controversial from the time it was built
                    because the government highhandedly seized land of farmers to build the airport.
                    It was intimated that some of the land had been bought up by politicians'
                    friends so they ended up making a lot of money. A certain number of farmers
                    refused to move and it became a focus of violent radicalism.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember seeing farmers out on the runway and that sort
                        of thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes. Several guards were killed in the early days of fighting. Even today
                    the airport is ringed with heavy security. The bilateral complaints related to
                    the fact that once the airport was built, the continuing conflict meant they
                    couldn't expand it for many years to add a needed second runway, which seriously
                    limited foreign carriers who wanted to expand into a growing market.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>Narita also had a very inefficient customs process for goods clearance. Goods had
                    to be trucked to another facility 20 or 30 miles away which wasn't too bad if
                    you weren't dealing with something that was perishable or needed fast clearance.
                    However the U.S. wanted get efficient processing on our exports of agricultural
                    products, especially fruit. Apples, cherries, etc. faced all kinds of
                    phytosanitary requirements but slow customs procedures were equally
                    obstructionist.</p>
                <p>It became even more difficult when organizations like FedEx started what was new
                    at the time, an overnight small package delivery service. The shipments would
                    get quickly to Japan, but once on the ground the customs clearance was really a
                    hindrance. The customs officials worked basically 8:00 AM to 4:00 PM so for
                    overnight shipments the timing was all wrong. American flights arrived in the
                    late afternoon in Tokyo. We had constant battles to get the Japanese to hire
                    more people, extend their hours, have more facilities on site at the airport,
                    and get the stuff through the clearance process. That's the sort of bureaucratic
                    problem that applied on the surface to domestic and foreign interests but had a
                    more negative effect on American operations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Moving to the other part of the transportation portfolio,
                        what about railroads? Were we doing much with railroad products?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It wasn't a question of import/export with railways. We were interested in
                    the technology and occasionally the Embassy would handle visitors coming to look
                    at the Shinkansen, the bullet train, which was at that time the highest speed
                    rail in the world. They were also starting to experiment with a magnetic
                    levitation train in southern Kyushu. So this was an area of cooperation, not
                    conflict.</p>
                <p>A different problem in the transportation area related to road transport. One
                    non-tariff barrier that I worked on a good deal was a limit on high cube cargo
                    containers. The major American shipping lines, American President Lines (APL)
                    and Sealand, used a certain container that was the routine size of containers
                    all over the world. However it was about a foot and a half too high according to
                    Japanese regulations, so these companies went to great expense in taking cargo
                    out of the containers that came off the ships and putting it into smaller
                    containers so that they could be shipped on the Japanese roads.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they worried about high cube containers hitting low
                        bridges?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: That's what they said, but as I kept pointing out, the shipping companies
                    would obviously plan and take safe routes. It wasn't in their interest to run
                    into low bridges, after all. The bureaucrats were simply defending the status
                    quo— which, in this case, was negatively affecting Japanese companies as
                    well.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>On this issue, I worked a lot with the National Police Agency, which was one of
                    the more insular agencies, at least on the road transport side (as opposed to
                    cooperation on criminal issues) as they didn't generally deal with international
                    issues. One of the most undiplomatic things I ever did was when a police officer
                    said to me, “We can't have these high cube containers because Japan is a small
                    country.” I laughed out loud. Then I tried to recover by pointing out that Hong
                    Kong, which was considerably smaller, had managed to arrange their regulations
                    to accommodate these containers. We finally succeeded in getting them to allow
                    the taller containers. Not surprisingly, that was in part because Japanese
                    companies were switching to these larger size containers and put pressure on as
                    well, probably through political channels. Of course then the containers got
                    even larger and they asked for double container loads and things, but as that
                    was after my time I don't know how it stands now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some of these were American problems, but they weren't
                        uniquely American problems. You had Europeans exporting, too. Was there a
                        unified approach or it was everybody for themselves?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: We didn't usually coordinate on specific actions but we did have contact
                    and share information. I called on my European counterparts and we were close to
                    the British and Canadians in particular. Other countries saw the U.S. as the
                    country with the most leverage. They were helpful and told us what they were
                    doing, but the attitude was more to let us go ahead while they went in later and
                    supported us. They knew that the Japanese were more likely to listen to us
                    because of the size of the U.S. market.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you undercut by countries caving in to the Japanese
                        regulations in order to gain advantage over American exports?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I don't remember any specific incidents of that. The Europeans were doing
                    better than we were in exporting automobiles, particularly the Germans. It was
                    because Mercedes had a good reputation and Volkswagens were popular because they
                    were cute and small. Right hand drive and good gas mileage, along with a
                    reputation for quality, were key. But the numbers for imports were nothing like
                    the Japanese exports to Europe. That in turn was far less than exports to the
                    U.S. I believe that the Japanese exports to Europe were limited by EU import
                    restraints, both standards and quotas. They weren't getting the overwhelming
                    market penetration the U.S. was. In fact back in Washington there was a three
                    pronged effort where we tried to get the Europeans to get rid of their
                    protectionist legislation so that some of the flow would be diverted to Europe,
                    taking some of the pressure off the U.S. as the only big open market. The other
                    two prongs were working to get more U.S. cars exported and the Voluntary
                    Restraint Agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the aviation side you mentioned the airport customs
                        clearance problem. Were there any other aviation issues?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: This was a major issue and along with autos took most of my time. There
                    had been a treaty in the early '50s that was very rigid, as most bilateral
                    aviation treaties were at that time. Certain airlines were allowed in a market
                    with a set number of flights and prices were controlled. The domestic aviation
                    market had also been heavily regulated, but in the '80s deregulation in the U.S.
                    was well underway and companies wanted more flexibility in international
                    markets.</p>
                <p>The American carriers in the market were Pan Am, Northwest, and Flying Tigers.
                    Continental had a small route that went between Japan and Saipan that carried
                    mostly tourists and honeymooners. On the Japanese side the carrier was Japan Air
                    Lines (JAL.) The Japanese felt that they were disadvantaged because they had
                    only one airline in the market. That happened because at the time of the treaty
                    they had only one international airline, which was heavily government financed.
                    There was a lot of pressure on both sides from other airlines that wanted to get
                    into the lucrative trans-Pacific market.</p>
                <p>A new round of talks began when the Japanese asked for landing rights for Nippon
                    Cargo Air (NCA), which was a new cargo airline that was a subsidiary of All
                    Nippon Airways (ANA.) ANA is a large domestic airline in Japan while JAL had
                    always been the international carrier. ANA had aspirations to become a bigger
                    player in the international field, but some years before they had been slowed
                    down by the Lockheed scandal which involved Prime Minister Tanaka. It involved
                    kickbacks for buying Lockheed planes for ANA. So for a while they were quiet and
                    made no effort to expand into American markets.</p>
                <p>But in the mid-'80s ANA wanted to get involved and asked for landing rights for
                    NCA. They were looking at flying high-tech components as well as finished
                    exports to the American market, with rights to Chicago a major part of their
                    plan. The USG refused, though strictly speaking the treaty allowed the new
                    rights. But U.S. airlines had been seeking more rights both for existing
                    carriers to increase their flights and for new carriers. They saw no other
                    leverage than to refuse what was in fact a legitimate Japanese request. In the
                    meantime NCA had two huge Boeing jumbo cargo jets sitting on the runway losing a
                    lot of money, so the Japanese were furious and we began a long round of
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>The talks were led by State Department and Department of Transportation (DOT), as
                    was the pattern, but unlike most aviation talks, USTR and Commerce also got
                    involved. American companies opposed to NCA framed the question as example of
                    Japan, Inc. because NCA was associated with ANA and also because we'd had all
                    the other problems with customs clearance, high cube containers, etc. that
                    related to cargo operations. The talks became highly political on both
                    sides.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Using the term Japan, Inc. was a shorthand term of saying
                        both the government and business were very closely entwined.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, The argument was that ANA/NCA was a conglomerate that was going to
                    overwhelm the smaller American players like Flying Tigers, the cargo airline.
                    Needless to say Flying Tigers was very eager to keep out another cargo carrier.
                    Pan Am and Northwest were combination carriers, with passengers but also large
                    cargo operations, so they liked the status quo. They had a nice market because
                    it was a protected market share, a pie of a certain size and with all the same
                    players year after year.</p>
                <p>This series of talks was interesting because a lot of the negotiation went on
                    among the American side. There was Continental wanting to expand its operations,
                    and United, Delta and American Airlines wanting in the market and the new player
                    Federal Express (now FedEx) all pushing DOT and the State Department and the
                    Congress to negotiate a big package. Northwest, Pan Am and the Flying Tigers
                    were trying to keep the status quo and warning that constituents would lose jobs
                    if all the new players were allowed to come into the market and lower prices.
                    Negotiating with the Japanese was only half the problem for the American team as
                    it was impossible to keep all the American companies happy because there were so
                    many different desires and a lot of political people weighing in on behalf of
                    their local airlines. . It was a long hard negotiation but the two sides ended
                    up with a very big package in about 1985 where the old system was completely
                    broken apart and new players came into the market. ANA soon realized that a big
                    package could finally break JAL's monopoly on the U.S. market and eventually all
                    international passenger flights. So there were countervailing forces on the
                    Japanese side for liberalization. NCA finally got its landing rights. ANA got
                    international flights (which has made a lot of American negotiators happy
                    because you can fly nonstop from Washington to Tokyo on ANA, which now has a
                    code-share with United so you can actually fly it on government travel.)
                    Northwest and Flying Tigers were unhappy, though a few years later Flying Tigers
                    was taken over by FedEx. United went in in a very big way and eventually took
                    over the Pan Am operations.</p>
                <p>The new arrangement was not completely open skies, not a completely deregulated
                    system. Conflict continued with the Japanese about the number of slots and the
                    timing of the arrivals at airports because, as noted earlier, Narita Airport was
                    unable to expand as much as it should. Nonetheless the deal brought a lot more
                    capacity in the market and really helped the consumer. Prices went down and the
                    volume of passenger traffic went up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Ambassador Mansfield called in from time to time to
                        weigh in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, having been a senator he was sensitive to the politics and careful to
                    ensure that all the American companies got a fair hearing. During the many
                    months of the aviation talks he received a lot of the American companies who had
                    very divergent views. Some were very eager to get the market open so that
                    newcomers could come in, while the incumbent carriers were arguing against a
                    deal. It's hard not to take sides in something like that because either you
                    support the ones in the market or you don't. The general inclination of
                    economists is to support a freer market but that can be difficult to say for
                    political reasons.</p>
                <p>The Japanese companies also made calls and gave their point of view. Sometimes he
                    pushed them to consider alternative scenarios. I remember one interesting
                    meeting with the NCA officials who were just wringing their hands and
                    practically in tears at that point because they were losing so much money with
                    their planes grounded without landing rights. You've probably already heard
                    about how Mike Mansfield would make coffee for his guests himself. It was
                    instant coffee and he made it in a little alcove and refused help from his
                    staff. That stunned Japanese visitors because they always had a young office
                    lady to do that, but here was Ambassador Mansfield bringing them coffee himself.
                    At this meeting the NCA officials gave a 10 minute explanation about why NCA
                    should be allowed in the market, cited the treaty and said it really wasn't
                    fair. When they finished the ambassador took his pipe out of his mouth and said,
                    “I agree.” That's all he said. They didn't know what to say, so they basically
                    repeated their points again. I thought that was classic Mike Mansfield.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Moving to the controls, the Cold War was still going on
                        with China and the Soviet Union. What were some of the issues that you got
                        involved in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: There was a lot of concern about dual use items, high tech equipment that
                    could be going to the Soviet Union or other countries for ostensibly legitimate
                    purposes but that could be diverted to military use. The allied nations'
                    Coordinating Committee - COCOM - in Paris kept a specific list of sensitive
                    items. There were constant arguments among the developed Western nations about
                    which items should be on the list and which were legitimate for shipment. Many
                    of the decisions were made on a case by case basis.</p>
                <p>Japan got a lot of attention because Japan made computers, high tech ceramics,
                    electronics and other sophisticated components, more so than most countries.
                    Partly because of the general anti-Japan feeling in Washington, many people
                    believed that Japanese companies were unscrupulous and selling items under the
                    table, through third countries, with questionable invoices, etc. There probably
                    was a certain amount of that going on, as other countries' companies did as
                    well. The question was how you found out about it. There were certainly a lot of
                    things being shipped to third countries and then on to the Soviet Union, maybe
                    with the knowledge of originating companies while some may have shipped goods in
                    good faith. We quietly shared information on questionable cases with Japanese
                    government officials.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A case that got a lot of attention involved Toshiba.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, there were apparently deliberate shipments of goods that allowed the
                    Soviets to create very quiet submarines. It happened a year or two after I left
                    in 1987 or '88, so didn't deal with that one, but that was a classic case and
                    Americans were justifiably very angry that a Japanese company would put profit
                    over security, especially given that we had our troops defending Japan. I don't
                    remember what the sanctions were, but the Japanese government cracked down
                    harder because of that case. It is still remembered here and still resented.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In many ways it sounds like the economic side was a
                        driving engine in the Japanese American relations during this period.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>WHITE: I think it was. It certainly was what got the most attention. Of course at
                    this time there was a strong security relationship and good political ties. This
                    was during the Reagan years and Reagan developed a good rapport with Prime
                    Minister Nakasone. Nakasone was unusual in several ways. First he lasted more
                    than a year or two. A lot of American presidents have mediocre relations with
                    the Japanese prime minister because it's a different one every time they meet.
                    The Ron-Yasu relationship developed into a strong personal bond during the
                    period, so the political ties were quite good. And Nakasone was a strong
                    personality who made an impression on the American public. This is unusual as
                    many Japanese politicians aren't well known here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there the economic summits at the time you were
                        there? They're called the G-8 now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It was the G-7 at that time. One year it was in Tokyo and it very
                    interesting to observe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From your perspective how effective were the summits? Were
                        they trying to settle some problems or was it just people talking and
                        getting together?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: For the embassy it was a time for everybody to be involved in one way or
                    another, being a control officer for this site or that site, taking care of the
                    visitors of all levels. In terms of the bilateral economic problems handled by
                    the Embassy, I don't think much was accomplished. There were bilaterals and each
                    side had a laundry list of issues and talking points. A lot more emphasis was
                    put on the Treasury Department's concerns and the multilateral issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did it work with the Department of Commerce which had
                        its own Foreign Service? Were they a player in major negotiations or were
                        they really looking for commercial opportunities? How did you work with
                        them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The Foreign Commercial Service (FCS) people worked on both negotiations
                    and commercial opportunities. The commercial section and economic section were
                    both large sections in the embassy and also each had a number of Foreign Service
                    Nationals. Their main focus was to help specific companies get into the market,
                    but they were also involved, though to a lesser extent than the economic
                    section, in policy questions. Things could have gotten complicated if the
                    personalities in the two sections had clashed, but luckily the two sections saw
                    their roles as complementary so we didn't have problems. In negotiations like
                    automobiles the commercial officer was part of the delegation. While the
                    economic section focused on policy, the commercial section focused on practical
                    aspects and could bring evidence of specific problems that business people had
                    encountered when they tried to get in the market.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this time Japan was pretty expensive to live in
                        wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, when I arrived there in '81 to go to language school I think the yen
                    was about 240 to the dollar, but after the Plaza Accords the rate went up and
                    down so there was a lot of variation. Almost everyone in the embassy lived on a
                    compound, which was newly constructed at that time. It was very convenient
                    because one could walk to work in 10 or 15 minutes. You didn't have housing or
                    utility costs to worry about. There was a small store there that got goods from
                    the commissaries on the military bases, fresh milk once a week, that sort of
                    thing. Basic canned goods, cereal, were available. People with large families or
                    who did a lot of entertaining drove out to Yokota Air Base or Yokosuka Naval
                    Base to do their shopping although I only did that a few times.</p>
                <p>Travel was expensive, unfortunately, because people with bigger families couldn't
                    afford to get on the train and go to Kyoto or Hokkaido or other parts of Japan.
                    Train fares were high as was lodging unless you went really low scale.
                    Nonetheless we tried to visit various areas and get out of Tokyo as much as
                    possible. Tokyo is a very concrete city and every three months or so you needed
                    to get out and see some greenery. My daughter's school went on ski trips to the
                    Japan Alps and she and I traveled a good deal by air, train, bus, ferry, etc. We
                    especially enjoyed our trips to Kyushu.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in '86?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes. I was then fortunate to be given a year of mid-career training, and
                    got a Masters in Public Administration at the Kennedy School at Harvard. It was
                    an excellent year, as I took about half my courses at the Kennedy School on
                    public policy issues and half in the college taking courses relating to Japan. I
                    had several small graduate level seminars with excellent teachers like Ezra
                    Vogel and Ronald Dore. My classmates at the Kennedy School were also very
                    interesting as they were all mid-career people, mostly in their 30s, with a
                    variety of experience in federal, state and local government, non-profits, and
                    international affairs. And it was great to live in Cambridge with its wide range
                    of cultural and intellectual activities. I graduated in June, 1987 and returned
                    to Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go next?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I returned to the Economic Bureau to be deputy division chief of the
                    Office of Trade Agreements, which was handling bilateral trade issues. This
                    assignment was from 1987 to 1989.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you see a change in the American-Japanese
                        relationship? Was there still anti-Japanese feeling in the political
                        arena?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, that sentiment continued. I wasn't specifically working on Japan then
                    because it was in the Economic Bureau and our responsibilities covered many
                    countries. One of my roles was to be the State representative on the 30l
                    Committee, named after section 301 of the Trade Act. That section, as mentioned
                    earlier, called for retaliation against “unfair trade practices” of other
                    countries and Japan was often cited. Usually the cases involved firms making
                    claims of unfair trade practices they met when trying to export to another
                    country. They presented evidence of illegal barriers and asked for sanctions
                    against that country.</p>
                <p>There were a number of complaints, one of the largest being a Boeing complaint
                    against European subsidies to Airbus. Some cases were brought against developing
                    countries but those were a minority. Several large and visible cases were
                    brought against Japan, and anti-Japanese feeling on trade continued through the
                    early '90s at a pretty intense level. But even when the U.S. was ready to
                    retaliate, it proved difficult to find a retaliation package that didn't also
                    hurt domestic interests. The idea was to raise U.S. tariffs on items important
                    only to the target country. For example, the Commerce Department would draw up a
                    list of potential items for retaliation that might have 200 items, with the
                    target country the main supplier. The committee would think it would be easy to
                    reach $40 million, $40 million being the assumed damages targeted for this
                    market. There would be a notice in the Federal Register and a hearing would be
                    held. People would come in from all over the country and ask that a specific
                    product be left off because it was a necessary component, it was the core of
                    their business or for various other reasons. It was usually the case that only
                    the business bringing the case was for action, while dozens of others would be
                    against.</p>
                <p>So while it looked easy to retaliate, the deep economic ties between countries
                    made it hard to find items without a negative impact on some U.S. interests. In
                    fact people criticized the State Department saying State always blocked action
                    against Japan because we were too concerned with preserving the political and
                    security relationship. In reality it was hard to take action against Japan
                    without hurting some U.S. interests. I never heard State people make the
                    political/security argument to block action other agencies were determined to
                    take in a trade case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were working in the trade office was there
                        concern about the European Union becoming a closed market for the United
                        States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: No, that the relationship was very important with huge trade and
                    investment flows in both directions, though there were specific complaints on
                    both sides. Most trade officials felt that the European Union was a group we
                    could work with in trade negotiations in Geneva on most issues.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>There were several significant problems; one that my office worked on was the
                    Airbus subsidy issue, in which Boeing claimed that the European government
                    subsidies to the corporation were unfair and illegal. There clearly were loans
                    for various types of development and one of the questions was whether Airbus was
                    ever expected to pay them back — if they were going to be written off, they were
                    subsidies. There were talks going on then — and they continue — trying to define
                    an acceptable level of development subsidies. The Europeans make the
                    counterclaim that Boeing gets indirect subsidies from military research on
                    aviation that improves commercial development.</p>
                <p>The other big problem with the EU was agricultural issues, though there is
                    another office in the Economic Bureau that handles agriculture. Subsidies under
                    the Common Agricultural Policy were a big problem, as they are today. There were
                    other issues, e.g. they wouldn't allow the import of U.S. beef because of the
                    hormones in the beef. That issue went to a GATT tribunal and the U.S. won, but
                    they fought the verdict and didn't let American beef in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there complaints about our own protection of
                        agricultural products?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, many countries complained. For example, our sugar policy is very
                    protectionist. We had to argue that these existing quotas were grandfathered in
                    when we signed the GATT which is technically correct. The fact that they're
                    unfair and self-defeating for all sorts of reasons doesn't carry much weight
                    against the political power of the agriculture lobbies, here and in other places
                    like the EU and Japan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any issues during this time that you dealt with
                        relating to other countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: We were starting to look harder at developing countries' policies. There
                    were a few complaints against India and Mexico, but the bulk of the issues were
                    with the developed countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the issues raised at a recent G-8 meeting concerned
                        poverty in Africa, with people saying we have closed markets to African
                        products such as cotton.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Open markets for cotton and sugar certainly could make a big difference to
                    developing countries. More liberal agricultural trade policies on the part of
                    developed countries would clearly be more important to developing countries than
                    aid packages.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that an issue we looking at that at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, particularly due to pressure from Latin American countries arguing
                    that that if we opened up our markets they could grow much faster. There wasn't
                    much of a lobby in the U.S. that was arguing for liberalization. There was an
                    intellectual position that we should be liberalizing for the benefit of the
                    consumer and for international relations reasons, but as there is today there
                    was a resistance to more open markets.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And your next position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: In 1989 I became special assistant to the Under Secretary for Economic
                    Affairs Richard McCormack. I was handling his Asia portfolio. Japan took most of
                    my time. McCormack was one of the principals in the Structural Impediments
                    Initiative (SII) talks. The talks were set up to look at six broad areas of the
                    Japanese economy that the U.S. felt should change in order to create a more open
                    economy. The concept was that sector specific negotiations, e.g. focusing on
                    autos or semiconductors, were not getting to the root of the problems with the
                    Japanese system.</p>
                <p>When presented with this idea, the Japanese agreed to talks but said they had to
                    be reciprocal. They wanted to raise problem areas in our economy so that it
                    would be a balanced negotiation. They complained about the U.S. budget deficit,
                    for example, which was sucking imports into our economy and creating the trade
                    deficit, in their view. We complained about issues like their interlocking
                    business ties and low public spending. It was a very wide-ranging negotiation
                    and people from Treasury, Commerce, USTR, the Office of Management and Budget,
                    the Justice Department and State got involved. The USG officials did serious
                    papers, looked a lot at the academic studies on the Japanese market and came up
                    with six areas that we wanted to focus on.</p>
                <p>One of them was Japan's budget restraint. The idea was that they needed to loosen
                    up and put more money into government funding which would get the economy
                    growing faster and thereby encourage imports. Land use policy was another issue.
                    They had a lot of taxation policies that kept agricultural land taxes very low
                    because of the traditional view of the Japanese as rice farmers. It resulted in
                    unproductive uses of land. The concept was that if you could free up suburban
                    land there'd be more growth, more building, and more imports would be
                    generated.</p>
                <p>A third area was the distribution system and that's the one I ended up working on
                    for a number of years. The problem was that the small shopkeepers, the mom and
                    pop stores had an enormous stranglehold on the ability of larger stores to open.
                    Toys-R-Us became poster child for that as they were trying to get into the
                    market. They and other big stores, domestic and foreign, were blocked by the
                    Large Scale Retail Store Law that prevented large stores from opening if anybody
                    in the neighborhood objected to it.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>Keiretsu issues were another major problem. Keiretsu are large business and
                    corporate groups that have interlocking ties with one another. They held each
                    other's stock, which kept outsiders out, and they didn't buy intermediate goods
                    on price grounds but bought from their related companies. That prevented new
                    suppliers from getting in the market. Anti-trust issues were taken up seriously
                    for the first time and the Justice Department got very much involved in urging
                    the Japanese to strengthen their enforcement of laws that were on the books but
                    pretty much ignored.</p>
                <p>Working groups were set up at a fairly high level for each of these issues and
                    several under secretaries took the lead. Deputy USTR Linn Williams, Under
                    Secretary McCormack and Treasury Under Secretary Zoellick were the leads.
                    Treasury Deputy Assistant Secretary Bob Fauver was a key player and source of a
                    lot of the intellectual power. He later came over to State when James Baker
                    became secretary and was Deputy Assistant Secretary in the East Asia Bureau.</p>
                <p>Under Secretary McCormack was very interested in the actual talks, but didn't
                    have a lot of time given the nature of his job, which had global
                    responsibilities. So I ended up spending about 50% of my time preparing for the
                    talks. The staffs prepared huge briefing books with a lot of papers and the
                    Japanese were sometimes quite startled about how much we knew about the
                    intricacies of these issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You know, what you're talking about is that a U.S.
                        government official is saying to another country that you've got to change
                        your internal system. There may have been problems but it is like someone
                        coming to the U.S. a few decades again and saying I'm sorry, but you have a
                        racist policy in North Carolina and this is inhibiting our trade with you so
                        get with it and desegregate. It's almost that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Oh, yes. We basically were telling the Japanese to change the way they did
                    things domestically because their domestic policies were affecting external
                    markets. We had already negotiated most of the easy things. Governments are
                    expected to complain about quotas and tariffs, but we were going into the hard
                    core domestic stuff. People recognized that this was something different and
                    something that could easily cause a lot of negative reaction in Japan. The USG
                    team was sensitive to this concern and one result was that we worked on the
                    Japanese press quite hard to try to convince the Japanese that they were the
                    ones suffering from their government's restrictive policies.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>One of the things done early in the talks was a joint survey of prices by
                    Ministry of Trade (MITI) and Commerce Department officials. They'd take a
                    certain camera as an example. They'd look at the price in Tokyo and New York and
                    Osaka and Chicago in the same kind of store. They did that for a range of goods
                    and not surprisingly the goods made in the U.S. were more expensive in Japan,
                    but the Japanese goods were also more expensive in Japan. When the Japanese
                    consumers saw these results they suddenly got the sense that there was something
                    wrong with their system. The very high prices were in large part because of the
                    many layers of the distribution system. So we actually got some sympathetic
                    press. USG officials gave talks to different groups in various parts of the
                    country. In certain areas like distribution we made progress because we had some
                    Japanese allies, entrepreneurs who wanted to open larger stores themselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This price difference must show that somebody was getting
                        money out of this system, particularly politicians and business people. I
                        know that prices for food are renowned for being much higher than justified
                        in Japan. You had to be breaking a very large number of rice bowls in the
                        political field and also those with clout within the Japanese system.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: That was certainly part of the problem. I mentioned in talking about the
                    distribution system the fact that the mom and pop stores had a great deal of
                    power; this group was a very strong supporter of the Liberal Democratic Party
                    (LDP). The other two really strong supporters of the LDP were farmers and the
                    construction industry. So agriculture, construction and distribution are three
                    areas where not surprisingly we've had a lot of problems. Contributions from
                    these groups support the LDP and the LDP then gives back to them by subsidies,
                    contracts or protectionist legislation.</p>
                <p>What helped on the distribution side was that some domestic interests weren't
                    happy with the system. We worked with stores like Toys-R-Us that wanted to go
                    into the market in a big way but were block by square foot limitations and other
                    regulations. There were some Japanese supermarkets and others who wanted to
                    expand as well and they were being blocked by the fact that the little stores
                    didn't want competition. Enough countervailing pressure was generated on the
                    Japanese side that MITI did end up relaxing the size limits on retail stores.
                    Toys-R-Us eventually opened over 100 stores in Japan.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>One way that the Japanese government dealt with this domestically was by giving
                    out money to who were considered the losers. In Japanese cities, there were
                    little shopping arcade streets with small shops with fairly limited merchandise.
                    They had their charm, but prices were high and few of the goods were imported.
                    The plan was to give these small stores a big chunk of money and allow them
                    upgrade. There were also plans to create new malls in the downtown areas with a
                    big anchor store, with the small stores filling in and staying viable. It would
                    also keep people downtown. That was the plan and the money helped smooth the way
                    for changes. The problem they couldn't address, more apparent now years later,
                    is that young people weren't attracted to this kind of business so the little
                    stores are disappearing in some cities. People also have cars more and will
                    drive to big stores.</p>
                <p>Things have gotten a lot better on the distribution side for big operators and in
                    fact now there are even some discount stores in Japan, which was considered
                    heresy. Many Japanese officials claimed their people would never go for
                    discounts as they valued name brands and quality so much but the economic
                    slowdown proved the theory wrong. Of course the irony is that all the toys that
                    Toys-R-Us brings into Japan are from China, not the U.S., but at least we
                    achieved some market opening.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about dealing with MITI?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: MITI is the well-known Ministry of International Trade and Industry, now
                    METI for Ministry of Economy, Trade and Industry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, MITI has been seen as a power within a power. Was
                        this a responsive organization or was it a tightly disciplined
                        bureaucracy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It was a conflicted organization in a way because they represented the big
                    exporters like Toyota and Fuji Film, the cutting edge companies who were making
                    a lot of money and didn't want to see their trading partners discontented. MITI
                    also had divisions and bureaus that represented the old guard who just wanted to
                    protect the traditional, increasingly inefficient industries. There was — still
                    is — a dual Japan, with a very modern, very efficient manufacturing sector and a
                    very inefficient service sector. MITI had to balances these interests and of
                    course there were politicians on both sides. Some politicians supported Toyota
                    and other big exporters and others represented the small shopkeepers who wanted
                    to preserve their interests. That made it pretty difficult for MITI officials to
                    get an internal position, let alone come to agreement with other ministries with
                    their own agendas.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>One interesting thing about the Japanese bureaucracy was that they didn't really
                    talk to each other very much. You'd get into a negotiation and realize that the
                    Foreign Ministry and MITI people hadn't coordinated positions or talked much at
                    all before hand. It sometimes seemed that they were seeing each other for the
                    first time while sitting together across at the table from us. In comparison, as
                    difficult as the bureaucratic infighting could be in Washington, we were a lot
                    better coordinated and a lot more on the same page than the Japanese were in at
                    least a few of our negotiations.</p>
                <p>To sum up, the SII talks went at a pretty full speed for about three years and
                    then it slowed down and eventually became the deregulation talks. Initially we
                    achieved some really good effects. Ironically, the Japanese took a very hard
                    line against our push for them to improve their business practices, especially
                    to bring more transparency in the keiretsu, the interlocking groups of
                    companies. The subsequent long, damaging economic slowdown had roots in these
                    practices that they wouldn't change, that is, the closed nature of the
                    businesses allowed a lot of uneconomic business decisions. For example, it
                    allowed companies to focus on market share instead of profit, not a practice
                    that can be sustained in a transparent system. In areas where they did loosen
                    their tight control, such as retail distribution, the economy as a whole
                    benefited.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you leave this job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I was only there for a year and then I went to the Japan desk (EAP/J) and
                    became head of the economic section there. I began the summer of 1990 and soon
                    after I arrived Iraq invaded Kuwait, so that was the dominant problem for many
                    people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it the same issues on the economic side or were things
                        changing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: On the trade side we continued the Structural Impediments talks and I did
                    a lot of work on the distribution system. The Kuwait/Iraq war ended up consuming
                    a lot of our time. Japan was in a unique and uncomfortable position because of
                    Article 9 of their Constitution. Written by the American Occupation authorities,
                    it says that Japan is not allowed to have a military and not allowed to take
                    aggressive military action in international affairs. The Japanese embraced the
                    concept whole-heartedly after the miseries of World War II and became intensely
                    pacifistic as a nation (despite the fact that their Self-Defense Forces are well
                    trained and well equipped.)</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>When the coalition formed against Iraq, Japan couldn't put boots on the ground
                    both for legal reasons and because of public opinion. Many Americans didn't
                    understand these constraints. We got a lot of calls from congressional offices
                    asking how much of Japan's oil was coming from the Middle East. It was a very
                    high percentage, at least 80%, and that figure obviously showed up in
                    Congressional speeches, e.g. “Japan gets all its oil from the Middle East and
                    they're not sending any soldiers. They're letting us spill blood for their
                    economic growth.” The anti-Japanese feelings generated by trade problems were
                    greatly exacerbated by Japan's passive posture.</p>
                <p>On the economic side of the war, we got involved in heavy USG pressure on the
                    Japanese to contribute money and eventually they gave about $14 billion to the
                    war effort. They were the only country that actually raised taxes to pay for the
                    Iraq war and for the coalition. It was a difficult process and left bad
                    feelings. A high level official Treasury went in to negotiate this amount but
                    the agreement failed to specify whether it was going to be in dollars or yen.
                    The Japanese said they agreed to a certain amount in yen, but the Americans
                    expected the $14 billion. When the exchange rate went the other way, it got
                    quite unpleasant. There was no good record of the meeting for our side because
                    Treasury didn't allow any Foreign Service Officers in the room to take
                    notes.</p>
                <p>The end result of all these problems was that when the coalition had its victory
                    parade down Constitution Avenue, the Japanese weren't invited to sit on the
                    viewing stand with all the other members of the coalition despite the fact that
                    they basically paid all the American costs of the war. When Kuwait took out full
                    page ads in the New York Times and Washington Post thanking all the countries
                    that had helped them, the Japanese weren't mentioned. The Japanese were angry
                    and humiliated and they still remember the slights. The people in the Ministry
                    of Foreign Affairs who were working on these issues were very burned by that
                    experience and determined never to see it repeated. We saw the results in a much
                    more positive way after 9/11 when they were quick to respond and offer help to
                    the U.S. It shows now in their involvement in Afghanistan and Iraq today, which
                    is far more than I would have expected 15 years ago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this time you were dealing with a country whose
                        nose is out of joint and probably quite rightfully so.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>WHITE: The Japanese ended up doing things that were enormously difficult for
                    them, even though it was hard for outsiders to see that. Their political system
                    moved very slowly. While there were sophisticated people in the Ministry of
                    Foreign Affairs and the Prime Minister's Office who knew they had to take action
                    — send medics, send mine sweepers, make some physical not just financial
                    contribution — they were stymied by a rigid system. Because the U.S. had
                    provided a security guarantee, they had rested on their peace constitution and
                    hadn't had to define their military role in the world. They eventually ended up
                    sending some mine sweepers, and they did their best to send trucks and autos,
                    vehicles that the troops welcomed for their good air conditioning. U.S. forces
                    modified them for military use but even with the vehicles they made bizarre
                    distinctions. The public and politicians were so wedded to Article 9 that the
                    use of their vehicles in combat situations was unacceptable to them. The
                    vehicles could carry bandages, but not ammunition, that sort of thing. Of course
                    they were used in many ways and some Ministry people were well aware of this but
                    wanted it to be kept quiet. A number of Japanese worked very hard to be
                    supportive and it was hard for them to see the lack of public gratitude.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any warning signs about the Japanese economy
                        and the overinflated bank loans at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: What we started seeing at that time was the real estate price boom, the
                    bubble that got to ridiculous proportions. That started in the early '90s
                    because a lot of companies held real estate as collateral. They were able to
                    borrow on it and then it became like a pyramid scheme to the degree that at one
                    point the theory was that the Imperial Palace land was worth more than the state
                    of California. The high prices allowed companies to borrow against the land that
                    they had in Tokyo or other cities and then use that money for all sorts of
                    speculation.</p>
                <p>It became a bilateral problem when the Japanese began investing in a major way in
                    the U.S. On the one hand, states were trying very hard to get Japanese direct
                    investment in their states. Some states had offices in Tokyo and people working
                    to get companies to come with job-producing factories. They offered subsidies
                    and other incentives. The actual physical plant investment wasn't a problem, but
                    when the Japanese started buying Rockefeller Center and Pebble Beach Golf Course
                    people noticed. These purchases were so visible that there was a strong negative
                    reaction, e.g. “the Japanese are going to buy up this country.” At one point a
                    Time Magazine cover had the Statue of Liberty wearing a kimono.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>The other one that caused a lot of attention was Sony's purchase of MGM. I was in
                    the Under Secretary's office at the time, so it was probably 1989. He was one of
                    the people who sat on the investment review committee called CFIUS, Committee on
                    Foreign Investment in the U.S. They were asked to review anything that might
                    involve national security, which usually meant a European company buying up a
                    high tech manufacturing concern, but in this case somebody asked CFIUS to go
                    over the motion picture purchase, perhaps for fear the Japanese would use films
                    for propaganda purposes. McCormack's view was that the case should go through
                    the long process rather than an expedited review so that Congress and other
                    critics could be satisfied that a very careful look had been taken. In the end
                    the purchase was not blocked.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course nobody knew what would happen. It didn't seem
                        that Sony Pictures was going to produce Japanese language pictures.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: No, the fear was somehow Sony would become a propaganda arm of Japanese
                    business/government. One critic pointed to the film Exodus and how much an
                    effect it had in generating American sympathy toward Israel. What if the
                    Japanese started doing that? But that was a rather far-fetched idea, as people
                    are so sophisticated these days and were quite anti-Japanese and suspicious at
                    the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then there was a joke going around about a new ad
                        campaign, now we bring you the new Toyota by those wonderful folks who
                        brought you Pearl Harbor.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: People used the phrase “economic Pearl Harbor” and that indicates the
                    strong negative feelings toward the Japanese. But their economic onslaught
                    turned out to run its course, and they were actually buying land at highly
                    inflated prices that left them holding bad investments. And not just land. We
                    also saw the Japanese buying Van Gogh paintings for huge sums of money and many
                    purchases went downhill. They ended up holding on to vastly overpriced land and
                    buildings, particularly in Hawaii. They're still recovering from the prices that
                    they paid for buildings and hotels there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left that position in '91?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, and then I made quite a shift because I went to the Personnel Bureau
                    to work on the Board of Examiners (BEX) for three years from 1991 to 1994.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I always think its interesting when people talk about the
                        Board of Examiners. How were the exams conducted when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>WHITE: There had been changes in the exam and I think they had developed a good
                    process, but also a very strenuous day for the applicants. The oral exams were
                    given to people who had passed the written test and been invited to Washington
                    and various sites around the country for the oral exam. One thing that hadn't
                    changed was the long-running afternoon group exercise. I'll start with that
                    because that's the more traditional segment where five or six people sit around
                    a table with examiners observing. The applicants would play an embassy group
                    that received some foreign aid money. Each person was given a project that
                    he/she had to defend and try to get money for, but we told them right at the
                    beginning that you didn't win by getting your project funded, you were favorably
                    judged if you helped move the group to the best solution for everybody. Not all
                    of the people got that point and some argued strenuously for their own projects
                    even if they were projects deliberately set up to be the weaker ones. The people
                    who got the highest points were those who tried to negotiate a sensible
                    solution. The exercise revealed a lot about how the applicants behaved in a
                    group of their peers.</p>
                <p>The morning exercise was new at that time. We began with a demarche exercise. For
                    an hour the applicants read materials that we examiners had created. They
                    received a package which included an instruction cable from Washington telling
                    them to go in to another government and get that government's agreement on a
                    specific issue. They were given talking points and other things like newspaper
                    articles and other background pieces, so they had quite a bit to read in one
                    hour. They then came in and faced two examiners who had specific roles to play
                    and a script to follow. In each case the two examiners had different points of
                    view and usually were from different ministries. For example, I did a demarche
                    on opening Japan's rice market. The roles were a Ministry of Foreign Affairs
                    person who was somewhat more conciliatory and the Ministry of Agriculture person
                    who was not conciliatory at all. The examiners had specific talking points to
                    use in response to what the applicant said. It was quite a challenge,
                    particularly for a young person right out of college, to present a case, to
                    answer arguments and in some cases to counter some hostility from the examiner.
                    Sometimes we were told to get exasperated and judge how the person reacted. Then
                    their task was to go back and write a cable reporting on the discussion. They
                    had to remember all the points, what had been said, who had said it, and then
                    analyze and comment on the meeting, which is difficult for somebody who hasn't
                    had experience with that sort of thing.</p>
                <p>The final part of the morning, which continued after a brief break to let the
                    applicant take notes, was the hypothetical situations. In the consular,
                    administrative and public affairs area, we would put the applicant in situations
                    that might happen at an embassy or a consulate and see how they reacted. We
                    asked follow-up questions. It was a way to see how people thought on their feet,
                    what kind of logic they used and in some cases such as the consular questions
                    how much compassion they had for an American in trouble.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the candidates you were
                        seeing? You were seeing the ones who had passed a rather rigorous written
                        exam?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>WHITE: First, it was a great job because we were seeing people who were eager and
                    interested and had positive impressions of the State Department, which wasn't
                    always true in this country at the time. We got some right out of college,
                    others who were looking at second careers such as retired military. It was quite
                    a variety. We had a good mix of male and female candidates. I don't remember
                    what the percentages were, but they weren't totally skewed toward men. This was
                    at a time when there had been a lawsuit about bias against women in the written
                    Foreign Service exam, which I can talk about a bit later. Most of the people had
                    a few years experience. We occasionally saw a very bright 22 or 23 year old, but
                    the exam favored people who had some work experience. People who were very well
                    educated but with only academic experience, 28 year old Ph.D.s for example,
                    tended not to do as well. My theory was that they'd just spent too much time on
                    campuses to have a good sense of how you operated in the real world.</p>
                <p>Regarding the retired military, we saw quite a few and they were a mixed bag.
                    Some of them were superb, others were clearly non-starters. Some were very good
                    in the hypothetical situations given their practical experience, but others
                    could only follow the rules and refer decisions to their superiors, being unable
                    to think outside the box, which is not what we were looking for.</p>
                <p>The other interesting thing about personalities was that some people did
                    beautifully in the morning when they were facing two examiners who were in a
                    sense their superiors, and we'd assume that these people would be a sure pass.
                    Then they'd completely blow it in the afternoon session with their peers because
                    they were much too domineering.</p>
                <p>The process gave a really good sense of the personality. We were not looking for
                    intellectual knowledge at this stage. They'd proven that in the written exam.
                    What we were looking for was adaptability, flexibility, interpersonal skills,
                    leadership skills, negotiating skills. There was a whole list of personal
                    characteristics that we gave numerical scores.</p>
                <p>At this time I also did a certain amount of recruiting on college campuses. We
                    gave the test in different cities such as Chicago, Los Angeles, San Francisco
                    and some of the BEX people took the occasion to go to campuses to speak. That
                    was always a very positive experience, given the chance to talk about what
                    Foreign Service was, to answer questions and to give advice. We were interested
                    in visiting schools outside the traditional Ivy League or big name schools, and
                    were happy to talk to minority groups to increase their interest in and
                    awareness of the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the climate for recruiting for the Foreign
                        Service at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>WHITE: In the mid '90s it was positive. There were no strong feelings as
                    presumably there were during the Vietnam War, when many had a negative attitude
                    toward the government. The one thing that tended to cause people to stop and
                    think happened after they passed the oral. At that point two different examiners
                    who had read their files would interview them. I might add when the examiners
                    saw them in the morning and early afternoon, it was a blind test. We didn't know
                    if a person spoke five languages and had lived in 18 countries. We knew nothing
                    about them. However, the interviewers who saw the people who had succeeded that
                    far had read the information they had provided in the application. The personal
                    interview always started with the examiner asking if, “do you really know what
                    you're getting into? Do you understand that you would have to always defend the
                    policies of the United States? This means not just in public or with reporters
                    or other obvious situations, but even if you're sitting around a dinner table
                    with your foreign national friends. You're always on call and always
                    representing the USG. You have to defend the administration's position on global
                    warming or Palestine or whatever.” That gave some people pause. I think most of
                    them swallowed and said, well, administrations change and I'll manage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Were you feeling the effects of the clash between the
                        administration and Congress and the fact that the administration at that
                        time was not particularly prone to get extra funds. The State Department was
                        being pared down and starved a bit without a lot of new people coming
                        in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: That hurt the process because when people had passed all these stages,
                    they then needed a medical clearance and a security clearance which took time.
                    Once that was complete and they were on the rolls, they might wait for a year or
                    even two years for an appointment. If they weren't hired by then they had to
                    start over. That was pretty bleak for people to look at putting their lives on
                    hold and not knowing when there would be a position for them. I think we
                    probably lost good people during that time after they'd gone through all the
                    process and showed themselves to be good candidates.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were the candidates coming from? I mean colleges and
                        geographic distribution.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: My sense was that it was a fairly broad group of Americans. People from
                    the major D.C. schools like Georgetown and George Washington were always well
                    represented, but there were people from lesser known colleges and those not well
                    known for their international programs. There were applicants from various
                    majors, though those who majored in political science, international affairs or
                    economics predominated. And there were candidates from all different age groups
                    as well, which is a strength of the process. People looking for second careers
                    came with a strong sense of the kind of careers they wanted and with good
                    skills.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any particular push to get more women in?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>WHITE: It was pretty much an even playing field. There was no sense that we
                    needed to put a thumb on the scales or give anything extra to women candidates.
                    In the oral exam, the pass rates were proportional to the male/female ratio of
                    candidates. Where that issue was controversial was in the written test, and that
                    is one reason I stayed on an extra year.</p>
                <p>In my final year and a half I spent a lot of time going over the questions with
                    the people who produced the written test in Princeton. We were responding to a
                    class action lawsuit that had indicated that there was a failure rate for the
                    written test considerably higher for women than men. The question was whether
                    certain questions were biased. On several occasions we got sample questions from
                    Princeton and I called together a group of junior Foreign Service Officers. I
                    gave the test to them and then we looked at questions where there was a dramatic
                    difference between the men who got it right and the women who got it right. I
                    don't remember details, but we emailed those who took the test to ask why they
                    thought there was such discrepancy. We deleted those questions whether or not we
                    could figure out why it happened. My sense at the time was that it was simply
                    that the male students were taking courses that tended to be a more in the
                    political science and economic field whereas the women candidates were more
                    language and humanities majors.</p>
                <p>I had joined one of the lawsuits, not because I'd ever had problems myself, but I
                    was so struck by the disparity in statistics on promotion and assignments. I was
                    deposed by the lawyer at one point. She took a test from a recent and went
                    through question by question, finding examples that in themselves didn't seem
                    important, like what is the capital of Burundi. She would ask if that was
                    something you really need to know to be in the Foreign Service. I answered that
                    such specific knowledge wasn't needed, but the range of questions together
                    indicated a breath of knowledge that is relevant. We went through 40 questions,
                    with her asking the same thing and me giving the same answer. At any rate we did
                    work very hard to try to get a fair test.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By the time you were there you felt that you were getting
                        a good representation of women then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: My sense was yes, that it was pretty well balanced, perhaps 30-40% women
                    entering. We seldom had days with just male candidates. One time the group was
                    all women and they all wore navy blue suits which was kind of amusing. When I
                    did the introduction, I joked that they had heard about the uniform.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>Getting back to the question of background and preparation, I was often asked by
                    students what they should do to prepare. I gave my own view, which was that
                    political science was not necessarily the best discipline because it could be
                    more theory than reality. I recommended history, government, constitutional law
                    and economics. I also said they should read the New York Times and strongly
                    recommended The Economist.</p>
                <p>The other thing I recommended was that people shouldn't necessarily be
                    professional students. I suggested that after undergraduate work they should
                    take a year or two off and go teach English in Japan or Spain and maybe go on
                    for a masters, but said people shouldn't spend time just in one school after
                    another. Work experience really improved chances of passing the test.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The other thorny problem is minorities, particularly
                        African Americans and particularly African American men. What were you
                        doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: There was a program, the Pickering Scholarship, which helped minority
                    students with tuition to study international relations or a field that could
                    lead them to the Foreign Service. They had internships at State and embassies
                    during their school years. I believe that they were then able to go directly
                    into the oral exam. They skipped a step, but they still had to pass the oral
                    exam just as everyone else. In fact the examiners didn't know that they had been
                    given the fellowship. I don't know what the statistics were on pass rates and
                    how many of those continued with the Foreign Service. We occasionally saw the
                    students from the program and they were usually quite good and passed on the
                    merits, which is exactly what was intended. We also did a lot of recruiting when
                    we went to colleges and offered to give talks to African American clubs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When I was on the Board of Examiners we disagreed with the
                        emphasis on the traditional black colleges. We felt that to get good
                        candidates, you needed to go to Berkeley or to Harvard or Chicago. Was this
                        being done?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: We recognized that we needed to go to all types of schools, Ivy Leagues,
                    Big Ten, etc. That's why we tried to target certain groups or associations in
                    the larger schools. I didn't visit any traditional black colleges myself and
                    think the emphasis on those had lessened. A problem we ran into was that
                    excellent minority candidates got job offers from a number of places, banks and
                    corporations. In addition to higher pay and benefits, they could hire people
                    immediately, a problem with the Foreign Service process.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did this until '94 and then what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Then I went to Ottawa as trade policy officer.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This must have been an interesting time to be trade policy
                        officer wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It was interesting after having so much experience with Japan on difficult
                    trade policy issues to find out that with our dear neighbor Canada we have
                    equally intractable issues with an enormous amount of emotion involved. I think
                    it is partly because the two countries are so close. Also I found that the
                    Canadians officials who worked on trade policy issues were capable and nice
                    people but very defensive. Canadians see a ten to one American to Canadian ratio
                    and see most of their media coming across the border, so they really do have a
                    lot of cultural identity problems. I think they've relaxed a bit since then. It
                    was interesting to see how hard fought these issues were. Some of them never get
                    resolved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the first place where did the trade policy officer
                        work? You've got the Department of Commerce, you've got the U.S. Trade
                        Representative (USTR), you've got the economic counselor. Where did you fit
                        in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The embassy had an Economic Minister and I was in essence his deputy. In
                    addition to an excellent Canadian trade specialist, there were two American FSOs
                    working for me, one on trade policy and the second person who did finance and
                    macroeconomic reporting. He was a State person but reported to Treasury.
                    Treasury used to have one person in Ottawa but had eliminated that position.
                    Also in the econ section were a fisheries officer, science and technology
                    officer, and a transportation officer who handled things like aviation and
                    customs which were quite difficult because of the enormous border traffic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fisheries are a problem that goes back to colonial times.
                        The issues really don't get any easier. As the number of fishes decreases it
                        gets worse.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, Pacific salmon was very difficult. The tricky part of Pacific salmon
                    is that during the course of their lifetime they keep moving from American to
                    Canadian to American Alaskan waters and the question is whose fish are they?
                    There were also some Atlantic coast problems having to do with scallops and
                    other things. Yes, you go back to the 19th century and I'm sure they were
                    dealing with the same kind of issues.</p>
                <p>I worked very closely with the U.S. Trade Representative's office and the
                    Economic Bureau at the State Department as well as the Canada Desk in the
                    European Bureau. We handled a lot of delegations and negotiations. I also worked
                    closely with the Agricultural Counselor and the Agriculture Department.</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>Some of the issues really were border issues. There was a constant small and
                    long-running potato war going on between Maine and parts of Quebec that was
                    rather strange because it seemed that all the people involved seemed to be
                    related. They were families on both sides of the borders who had common great
                    grandmothers. It had to do with the size of potatoes and which ones could come
                    into Canada. It was a standards issue that never really got resolved. The Maine
                    senators were upset because their potatoes were being kept out of Canada because
                    they were the wrong size or shape.</p>
                <p>Of greater economic significance were the grain issues. Senators like Max Baucus
                    and other northern state Members of Congress were upset about the shipments of
                    Canadian wheat coming across the border. They felt that the Canadian Wheat Board
                    provided Canadian farmers with an unfair government subsidy. They have a very
                    complicated way of setting their prices which I couldn't begin to remember, but
                    which the American farmers and congressmen claimed gave an unfair trade
                    advantage. The Canadians countered by saying that the U.S. had export subsidies
                    for wheat, which meant that we were sending our wheat overseas, which meant
                    there was demand for Canadian wheat, particularly wheat used for pasta.
                    Therefore, the Canadians said, we're just meeting the demand.</p>
                <p>Canadians softwood lumber was the most difficult issue and it continued for
                    years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the issues in lumber?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The provinces have government control over the lumber, generally because
                    they own the land and set fees, so again it's a subsidy/ countervailing duty
                    issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you were saying it was a very complicated issue, but
                        how did you operate? I'm talking about you personally. Did you sit on
                        delegations and act as embassy spokesperson or the embassy observer or
                        participant or something like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I sat on delegations as the embassy representative but I didn't play the
                    role of intermediary between the Canadian and U.S. governments as much as I
                    might have in another embassy. For one thing it got to the point where people on
                    both sides knew each other well because these talks went on so long. Also
                    geography played a role. Because we were in the same time zone, if the deputy
                    USTR wanted to talk to the director general in Ottawa, he wasn't going to send a
                    message to me to deliver to the director general. He'd just pick up the phone.
                    There was a lot of direct phone contact, which took away the need for the
                    traditional role that embassy officers play. For example in Japan people just
                    didn't make phone calls like that. We'd get interagency cleared instructions
                    from Washington, then make an appointment to make a demarche to ministry
                    officials, then write a reporting cable. It was a bit frustrating for people
                    working on different initiatives at the embassy, as people in Washington did a
                    lot without them.</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard people say that one of the problems of dealing
                        with trade matters, negotiating with the Canadians is that they can put
                        forward a team that's been together and dealing with the issue for a decade
                        or more whereas we change the administrations and officials. Was this a
                        problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: In this case I don't think it was because the people who were working on
                    these issues really did spend a lot of time on them. On lumber, even the deputy
                    USTR was forced to learn the details fast because it was so political in the
                    U.S. They got up to speed pretty quickly. I don't think there was that much of a
                    disadvantage. The political fight was because softwood lumber in the U.S. is
                    grown in a number of states, particularly a wide band across the South. It is
                    used in construction. The American producers contented that the Canadian
                    “subsidized” lumber was coming in at such low prices that it was causing injury.
                    This got a lot of resonance on the Hill. What got totally ignored was the
                    interest of the consumer who actually benefited from having a good supply of
                    lumber. In fact there was one big meeting where one representative of a
                    construction association, representing those who wanted an abundant supply, was
                    there. We noticed that the State people and this man were somehow not being told
                    about all the meetings that the softwood lumber people were having with the
                    Commerce Department and USTR. There was a certain us against them sense at least
                    with some of the Commerce Department people. We wanted to find a reasonable
                    solution and they wanted their solution, which was very pro the softwood lumber
                    growers' position.</p>
                <p>The solution that was reached during that time was that the Canadians agreed to
                    what was essentially a voluntary restraint agreement that they would enforce a
                    certain level of lumber shipments and the U.S. would not apply countervailing
                    duties. It became a real problem for the Canadians because they then had to
                    divide the numbers up by province and the interests of the British Colombians
                    were very different from the interests of the Quebecers and others. I think they
                    realized that it just wasn't worth it to try to keep this agreement and
                    eventually they let it lapse and the U.S. put on heavy countervailing
                    duties.</p>
                <p>I saw something in the press a few years ago that the countervailing duties of
                    the U.S. government were judged illegal under NAFTA and the U.S. was refusing to
                    give back the money, which would seem to put us in direct violation of NAFTA,
                    though that happened after my time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you looked over the whole trade issue policy of the two
                        countries at this time, were they adjusting to NAFTA? This was a period of
                        learning because this was quite new.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>WHITE: It was new and we were working hard at it. I got involved in several
                    judicial proceedings under the NAFTA. The dispute resolution boards looked at
                    cases involving the U.S. and Mexico and Canada. I don't remember the details of
                    a lot of them, but people took it very seriously. There were long involved
                    presentations before a dispute resolutions board. The people on the board were
                    long time trade experts, academics and people who had worked on trade issues for
                    years. We respected the experts and the procedures and tried very hard to make
                    it work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you see our Special Trade Representative Mickey Kantor
                        in operation? What was your impression of how he worked?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: He was good working with his counterparts. The one meeting I remember most
                    specifically was a meeting that brought in the Chilean trade minister. It was
                    NAFTA plus what was supposed to be the next member of NAFTA, Chile.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: NAFTA was at that point completed but we were talking
                        about bringing Chile in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, a meeting was held in Toronto with the four trade ministers. Kantor
                    could be very tough but also diplomatic. He was good with people and had a
                    politician's touch. At the Toronto meeting, everyone was very positive about
                    Chile's economic policy and situation and how the country would fit well in
                    NAFTA. It still hasn't happened and that has been a big disappointment.</p>
                <p>Another Kantor trip to Ottawa was during a visit of the Clintons. I was with his
                    entourage in the hotel lobby just after arrival. A young man stopped him and
                    gave an impassioned two or three minute speech about how awful the death penalty
                    was in the United States and we shouldn't have it. People were standing there
                    looking a little upset that this person just came in and grabbed Kantor
                    unexpectedly. Kantor listened to him very politely and thanked him for his
                    opinion on a difficult subject. I thought that was very gracious of him given
                    the tumult and tight scheduling of a visit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find a lot of bureaucratic rivalries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It was a small trade community in Canada. One interesting thing is that
                    their Department of Foreign Affairs and Department of Trade was consolidated as
                    DFAIT. At any rate they didn't have the split that we had in the U.S. between
                    State and Commerce or State and USTR. We didn't see any obvious signs of
                    internal conflict. They were usually pretty up front about what their positions
                    were</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>Both the Canadians and the Americans had protectionist policies, with guilt on
                    different things, usually involving agriculture. The U.S. has a protectionist
                    sugar policy. The Canadians had an equally ridiculous poultry and dairy policy.
                    Even ice cream exports from the U.S. were restricted to protect Quebec farmers.
                    In domestic Canadian politics, there was always the complication of Quebec
                    separatism. Given how tense things were at the time, nobody was about to touch
                    the protection of their farmers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Cuba cause problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes. This was when the Helms Burton legislation was passed which put
                    sanctions on foreign companies that gained benefit from properties expropriated
                    in Cuba. One of the first cases involved a nickel producer in Alberta. The
                    company had major operations in Cuba and the head of it planned to continue
                    doing business with Cuba. There wasn't a lot the U.S. could do since one of the
                    provisions was to refuse officials of offending companies visas to go to the
                    U.S. This man didn't try to go to the U.S. and was happy with his business in
                    Cuba.</p>
                <p>Canadian attitudes toward Cuba were very different from those of the U.S. A lot
                    of Canadians went to Cuba on vacation because it was cheap. The Canadian
                    government objected to Helms-Burton because of its extraterritorial aspects, as
                    did most of our European allies. A dinner topic conversation was about how
                    ridiculous American policy was, but of course as a Foreign Service officer one
                    had to either keep quiet or make a lukewarm defense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, when you think about it the Helms Burton amendment
                        was not done with great care. Apparently one of the aims was to penalize
                        companies benefiting from property confiscated from Americans and Cubans who
                        later moved to the U.S.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, that is why this Alberta company was in violation. They either leased
                    or managed a property that had been expropriated and the owners not
                    compensated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about social life there? I've heard varying accounts
                        from people who had a wonderful time and those who found pervasive
                        anti-Americanism. How did you find it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>WHITE: I loved living in Ottawa. It's a small city. It doesn't have much in terms
                    of lively night life but I wasn't looking for that anyway. There was an
                    orchestra and a nice concert hall, though it wasn't particularly world class.
                    There were some good restaurants. There is a lively downtown marketplace where
                    stalls sell fresh foods and flowers, a great place on weekend mornings. At that
                    time the embassy was in an old building directly across from the Parliament.
                    Every summer day I could watch the changing of the guard, with a marching band
                    and ceremony. It is a picturesque area, great for outdoor activities. Quebec is
                    just across the river and the Gatineau Hills have places to hike. The Rideau
                    Canal runs through the middle of the city and one can walk along the path in the
                    summer and skate on it in the winter. So in terms of lifestyle it was very
                    pleasant.</p>
                <p>Canadians as individuals, not in their official roles, were friendly and pleasant
                    to work with. In their official roles they could be very prickly and sometimes
                    anti-American, but that tended to be a few individuals who I think just had been
                    looking at trade issues too long.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how about what the British call the chattering
                        class, the intellectuals?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: There was a certain amount of fashionable intellectual anti-Americanism,
                    particularly in Toronto. That's where the media and the media money were
                    located. They felt threatened by American magazines and other media. They had
                    rather ridiculous rules about what could be played on the CBC radio, the
                    Canadian Broadcasting Company, where there were quotas for air time. An artist
                    had to be Canadian, the song had to be written by Canadians or it had to be
                    produced by Canadians, two out of three. I believe that the songs of Celine Dion
                    didn't qualify because she had a production contract with somebody in the U.S.
                    and some of her songs had been written in the U.S. Even though she was the major
                    French Canadian singer and one of the biggest stars in the U.S., she didn't
                    qualify for the quota at least for a time. That was one of the absurd
                    examples.</p>
                <p>Culture was definitely a concern of some Canadians as they felt that their
                    culture was being overwhelmed by American culture. It was only natural, as most
                    of the population lived within 100 miles of the border and so they received
                    American TV and radio. It is too bad that they couldn't accept and be proud of
                    Quebec culture, Ontario literature, Maritime music as vibrant parts of a North
                    American culture, just like Cajun in the U.S. or country music from Texas. But
                    of course there were commercial interests involved.</p>
                <p>One interesting thing I'll mention is the military band marched down to
                    Parliament each day as the guard was changed and they always played marches. In
                    all the time I was there I never heard them play a John Philip Sousa march. That
                    shows how ridiculous their cultural hang-ups could be, as it takes a lot of
                    effort to find good marching songs and completely avoid John Philip Sousa.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've talked to people with kids at schools and all say
                        that their kids came back telling about teachers who were always criticizing
                        the United States. Was this a problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I heard such complaints, but I had no direct experience as my daughter was
                    then in college. Some teenagers seemed to deal with it pretty well and find it a
                    little silly, but it was hard for them when a teacher aimed pointed comments at
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In addition to the Quebec issue, were there a lot of local
                        and regional differences that affected U.S. interests? Canada is quite
                        decentralized in a way and Ontario is its own world. Quebec of course
                        everybody knows about, but also you have the Maritimes and then the prairie
                        states and British Columbia. Did you find that the differences manifested
                        themselves in your work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: This was very much a concern of the Canadian government and the Canadian
                    press at the time. I did one long trip where I basically started in British
                    Columbia and worked my way back across the provinces in order to do a long
                    report on devolution. I wanted to call the cable “you say you want a
                    devolution,” but people didn't get the Beatles allusion. The report didn't
                    attract much attention in the USG. It was internal politics and it didn't seem
                    particularly relevant to policy makers, except of course for the Quebec
                    question.</p>
                <p>I did sense clear regional differences and often a real lack of attachment to the
                    central government. In the Pacific Northwest, people felt they had so much in
                    common with Washington, Oregon, Northern California that they could see
                    themselves surviving without the central government in Ontario. Vancouver felt
                    very different with its strong Asian orientation. They felt disconnected from
                    Toronto and Ottawa. Alberta, too, felt quite independent because they had so
                    much oil and gas revenue and at that time a very healthy beef industry. They
                    were the richest province in Canada and they were developing politically along
                    what you would call red state lines. They wanted low taxes, little government
                    involvement, and wanted the central government just to stay away from them
                    because they were doing perfectly well by themselves, thank you very much.</p>
                <p>I went to Regina, Saskatchewan, and Winnipeg, Manitoba; there wasn't much
                    dynamism there. I remember asking about unemployment in Saskatchewan and the
                    official said it was very low — but because young people left after they
                    finished high school or college due to the lack of jobs there. The Maritimes
                    were similar in losing population because of the declining fishing industry.
                    There was some oil and gas revenue and some tourism but they felt without a
                    strong central Canada they'd really be in trouble. There were jokes that the
                    U.S. could help them by adding them to the New England states.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm told that the Maritimes look more towards Boston as
                        their capital.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: There are strong ties. I'm from New England and saw great similarities.
                    Names of people, styles of towns and houses in Nova Scotia and Massachusetts are
                    all the same. The other joke was that if the Maritimes wanted to join the U.S.,
                    the U.S. wouldn't want them because they were in such economical difficulty.</p>
                <p>The Quebec question of course was the most important political issue while I was
                    there. At that time there was a major referendum in Quebec as to whether they
                    would vote for independence. It was traumatic for many people in Ontario. I
                    don't think the western provinces were so deeply affected. We watched rallies on
                    the Parliament lawn where average people talked about what Canada meant to them
                    and begged the Quebecers not to leave. Everyone was glued to the TVs that night
                    as the very close vote was tallied. They had a kind of a gauge and it would slip
                    from 49% for to 51% for and then back to 49 � % against and it ended up
                    something like 51% to stay with Canada and 49% voted to leave. That seems to
                    have been the high point of the separatist movement.</p>
                <p>The U.S. had a tricky role to play because obviously we did not want to see the
                    Canadian government blown apart by this vote. It was by no means certain that
                    Quebec would have been able to leave as neatly as the proponents claim and there
                    would have been a period of instability. But we couldn't be seen as interfering
                    in their internal affairs. I used to get a lot of questions about NAFTA and
                    whether an independent Quebec could quickly join. Our position was that Quebec
                    should not assume that they would automatically be a member of NAFTA if they
                    left Canada, though that was their assumption. It wasn't something we wanted to
                    discuss publicly. In fact, Quebec would have faced tough negotiations as we
                    didn't like some of their textile exports in addition to the dairy protection.
                    Anyway it was a relief when the effort failed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go after Canada?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: In the summer of 1996, I became the Director of the Bilateral Trade Office
                    in the Economic Bureau. That had two divisions for developed and developing
                    countries. We worked various free trade agreements, including NAFTA, the
                    Generalized System of Preferences for developing countries and other bilateral
                    issues. We had to coordinate closely with the regional bureaus.</p>
                <p>The China Most Favored Nation (MFN) issue was a major issue during that time. We
                    worked with USTR and the China desk to get the Chinese government to improve
                    their trade practices but also faced a yearly Congressional vote on the
                    continuation of MFN tariff treatment for China.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the first place, were you working on adjustments to the
                        finished NAFTA or were you working on new members?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: NAFTA was still evolving. The dispute settlement process was developing as
                    cases were brought we wanted to make sure the procedures were in order. There
                    was increasing political opposition to free trade and a lot of it was focused on
                    the plan to expand NAFTA to include Chile. I don't think it came to a
                    Congressional vote because it was determined that it wouldn't pass, though Chile
                    met the economic criteria.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the problem with Chile?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It was hard to understand as Chile posed little threat to American
                    interests. Even the agricultural products would come in on a different cycle.
                    The opposition seemed to be more the ever-present populist sense that somehow
                    freer trade disadvantaged American workers. It was a feeling unrelated to
                    facts.</p>
                <p>More specifically, the opposition focused on the labor and environmental
                    provisions. The argument was that there would be a race to the bottom. Under
                    NAFTA the rule was the country had to abide by its own labor and environmental
                    standards. The labor movement felt that Chile's labor laws were too weak. I
                    assume that the environmental movement was also saying that the standards
                    weren't high enough and therefore it disadvantaged the U.S.</p>
                <p>Totally lost in the debate was the fact that there really weren't that many trade
                    barriers in the U.S. and there wasn't going to be a huge expansion of exports to
                    the U.S., while an agreement would ensure that the market would be kept open for
                    U.S. producers. NAFTA was very valuable to U.S. interests when Mexico went
                    through its financial crisis, as our trade continued while that of Europeans and
                    others with Mexico declined sharply, but it was an argument that we have never
                    really have managed to get across.</p>
                <p>I worked on trying to set up a public program whereby State Department speakers
                    could use talking points on trade as they went around the country. We tried to
                    get state by state statistics so if an assistant secretary was going to
                    Tennessee, for example, he would have statistics on the jobs that were created
                    by FedEx or UPS centers involved in international trade. The idea was to point
                    out that trade created jobs, not just sent them overseas. But apart from people
                    in the Economic Bureau the idea never caught on and there wasn't much support
                    from the public affairs people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the problem with China? Was it just because China
                        was communist and had lousy human rights?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>WHITE: The reason for the annual Congressional vote was the Jackson-Vanik Act,
                    which had originally been aimed at the Soviet Union. We didn't have specific
                    trade problems like today where China is the new economic giant with a huge
                    trade surplus and an undervalued currency, but there was still a sense that
                    China was a potential threat to the U.S. in economic and security issues. We in
                    EB worked with USTR, Commerce, Treasury and the China desk at the State
                    Department to prepare one pager summaries. These were used as background with
                    various audiences. For example, we wrote on issues as diverse as slave labor in
                    China and connections the Chinese military had with Chinese factories; these
                    were issues raised by labor groups, human rights groups and Congress. There were
                    probably 30 or 40 of these one pagers that set forth the claims or accusations
                    and then laid out the facts. Of course the reality in some cases was fairly
                    grim, but perhaps not as bad as the opponents were making out. We argued that
                    the U.S. and the west would benefit from drawing China further into the global
                    system, that by exposing the Chinese people to Western influences through trade,
                    they would become more aware of democratic trends and seek more of a say in
                    their own government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did the World Trade Organization fit into your
                        work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The WTO was handled by a neighboring office in the Economic Bureau. While
                    we kept informed about their activities and vice versa, my office didn't
                    directly work on the WTO.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would think that almost everything you were doing would
                        be connected. The World Trade Organizations as I understand encourages
                        liberal trade regimes, as your office does.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: We worked very closely with them. It was important that the bilateral
                    negotiations remained consistent with multilateral rules. There was, and
                    continues to be, a debate about whether bilateral or regional agreements help or
                    harm multilateral efforts. It is obviously much better for the world to be
                    following one set of rules, and a multilateral agreement avoids trade diversion
                    and rules of origin problems. But the counter argument is that it can be easier
                    to get a few countries to agree to a more high quality agreement; that can then
                    serve as a model for future multilateral talks.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately, then as now there was great resistance to trade liberalization and
                    it was difficult to bring about a wider accord. At that time the disastrous WTO
                    meeting in Seattle was held. It was supposed to initiate the current Doha Round
                    but ended up notorious for the rioting in the streets, with trade ministers
                    unable to get to the meeting because the roads were blocked by
                    anti-globalization demonstrators.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My son-in-law was helping block some of those when he was
                        younger.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, all sorts of people demonstrated against the talks and sadly it was
                    the violent ones who had the impact. There were union people and
                    environmentalists who were middle of the road but their message was lost in the
                    destruction caused by a group of anarchists. The multilateral system seemed to
                    be breaking down or at least not moving forward. The push toward more bilateral
                    and regional free trade agreements was growing stronger. Many of us who worked
                    on trade found that regrettable. It's much better to have a strong multilateral
                    system than a patchwork of different regional FTAs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then you were doing this until '94 to '96. Then
                        where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Then I became Director of the Japan desk and I was there from '98 to 2001.
                    This was in the East Asia bureau (EAP.) It was an excellent job at this time of
                    my career with a lot of management responsibilities. Also, for the first time, I
                    worked a great deal on security and political issues, much more so than economic
                    issues, so it was an interesting challenge to get up to speed quickly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the major security issues?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: In September 1998, about a month after I began the position, the North
                    Koreans shot a type of long-range missile, the Taepodong, which they claimed was
                    a test or a launch of a satellite that failed. It flew over Japan and the
                    Japanese reacted very strongly to that. It made them feel very vulnerable.
                    Before that, the public hadn't really felt that Japan as a country could be a
                    target. During the Cold War the feeling was that if Japan were to be a target,
                    it would be because the Soviet Union was targeting American bases in Japan. With
                    the missile shot and North Korea's nuclear ambitions, they suddenly realized
                    that Japan itself could be a target. They needed a lot of reassurance that they
                    were still under our nuclear umbrella and that we would come to their aid. One
                    Japanese official told me that the Taepodong missile had the same effect on
                    Japan as the takeover of the embassy in Tehran had on the U.S. It made a country
                    realize its vulnerability.</p>
                <p>The North Korean issue was very important throughout my three years on the desk.
                    At that time former Secretary of Defense William Perry had started a process
                    called the Trilateral Coordinating Group (TCOG) which brought the South Koreans
                    and the Japanese together before and after each U.S. negotiation with the North
                    Koreans. He was followed by State Department Counselor Wendy Sherman, who was
                    well respected. There was a great deal of coordinating work; it worked well to
                    keep the Japanese and South Koreans assured that they were informed of
                    everything going on in bilateral talks. The personalities involved worked well
                    together and I think it was an excellent exercise in diplomacy.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the Japanese and South Korean
                        relationship?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: It has always been a difficult relationship because Japan colonized Korea
                    in 1905 and there are still many negative feelings. The Koreans remember that
                    the Japanese punished Koreans for speaking Korean during that period. Many
                    Koreans were sent to Japan almost as slave laborers during World War II and the
                    comfort women issue remains very painful. However the animosity wasn't as strong
                    then as it is today. The TCOG process was significant because the Japanese and
                    Koreans met together with the Americans and put aside the history problems to
                    work toward a common goal, dealing with North Korea. It is sad that those good
                    working relationships never spread to a wider number of officials or to the
                    general public in both countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was our position at that time and what were the North
                        Koreans up to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The Agreed Framework was in place at that time so the plutonium that the
                    North Koreans had been reprocessing was under International Atomic Energy Agency
                    (IAEA) supervision. There were IAEA inspectors at the nuclear plant in North
                    Korea and the plutonium was in fuel rods under constant surveillance. The
                    question was who was going to pay for the quid pro quo. KEDO, the Korean
                    Economic Development Organization, had been set up after the 1994 crisis to
                    provide energy to North Korea through construction of two light water reactors.
                    I'll leave the details of that to the Korea experts, but it was important to
                    Japan because Japan and South Korea were going to pay the bulk of the money to
                    construct the power plants to replace the nuclear program the North Koreans gave
                    up. There were a lot of delays in that for one reason or other. The U.S.
                    Congress never like it and delayed sending heavy fuel oil, there was suspicion
                    about the North Koreans having an underground testing facility that had to be
                    investigated, and the North Koreans were not particularly receptive to the South
                    Korean technicians coming in. It went very slowly. However at least the North
                    Koreans were not making nuclear bombs, which is not the case today
                    unfortunately.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Did the Russian occupation of the northern islands
                        come up while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, the Northern Territories issue has been a constant problem and Japan
                    doesn't have a peace treaty with the Russians from World War II because of this
                    territorial complaint. The Soviet Union took over four islands north of Hokkaido
                    just at the end of the war.</p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>When I was following Japan's relationship with the Soviet Union back in the '80s
                    there was a sense that if only the two countries could have better relations it
                    would benefit both; Japan had the money and the technology and the Soviet Union
                    had the resources. It was always thought that the big turnaround was just around
                    the corner. When they could finally get things resolved politically and the
                    Russians became a little more reliable in their bureaucratic and legal policies,
                    people could do business. Well, that's never happened, largely because the
                    Northern Territories issue remains unresolved. Putin has gotten even more hard
                    line than people in the '80s. I don't see a political solution coming anytime
                    soon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we playing any role in trying to help them resolve
                        the problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I don't know what U.S. officials were saying to the Russians. We hoped for
                    resolution and we supported the Japanese, but there was not really a useful role
                    that we could play.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Northern Territories seem to be sparse and bare.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Not many people live there. But like so many of these little rocks or
                    islands, they have fish and other resources around them so whoever can claim
                    them gains fishing rights and possibly access to oil. There are also questions
                    of maritime passage and it becomes very symbolic of one's sovereignty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about our troops on Okinawa and other bases in
                        Japan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The U.S. military presence on Okinawa has been controversial for some
                    time. The U.S. held the islands after World War II and it wasn't until 1972 that
                    Okinawa reverted to Japan. The reversion talks were interesting, a successful
                    diplomatic effort at a time when the military hadn't wanted to return Okinawa.
                    It was in the middle of the Vietnam War. There were many troops based in Okinawa
                    who were flying to Vietnam, maybe not directly on bombing runs, but certainly it
                    was a key area for the military.</p>
                <p>The Okinawa issue continued to be difficult, however, because even after
                    reversion the Okinawans were left with such an enormous proportion of military
                    forces on their very small islands. There are about three main roads which tend
                    to be choked with military vehicles. It's very noisy there with helicopters and
                    planes constantly taking off and landing. The American bases are prime real
                    estate. The Okinawans see the country clubs and the nice housing and compare it
                    to their often cramped towns.</p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>On the other hand the bases are very important geographically because troops
                    there can reach all parts of Asia much more quickly than they could from Guam or
                    other places. They are an important part of the contribution that the Japanese
                    government makes to the U.S.-Japan military relationship. The Japanese either
                    provide the land free of charge to the U.S. government or they pay the rent to
                    the landowners. In Okinawa there are a number of landowners who have tiny plots
                    of land that they rent to the Japanese government for U.S. bases and some of
                    them are making a pretty good living out of that. The question of returning
                    bases has long been difficult in Okinawa.</p>
                <p>The American career military knows how important the bases are. Many genuinely
                    believed that the negative attitudes toward U.S. forces really came from a small
                    group of press and local politicians, while the bulk of the people really liked
                    having them there. To a certain extent people did benefit, the shopkeepers and
                    the people getting rents, but I think the military tended to close their minds
                    to the fact that the average citizen resented the noise and the confusion and
                    the occasional very upsetting incident.</p>
                <p>Nonetheless I think everybody recognizes that something needs to be done and at
                    the time I was on the desk the return of Futenma Marine Air Station major issue
                    was the major issue. Unfortunately, even today it remains unresolved. Futenma
                    Marine Air Station is basically a helicopter base located in the middle of a
                    very populated area. It is down in a bowl with houses all around it. People have
                    said for years that it's an accident waiting to happen which would be horrific
                    because of the density of population. Under the SACO agreement, Special Advisory
                    Committee on Okinawa, it was agreed that the Japanese government would
                    facilitate the relocation of this base to another place in Okinawa.</p>
                <p>At the time I came in one proposal was for an offshore facility to be used as
                    this helicopter base. A number of Japanese construction companies and steel
                    companies were pleased with this idea because it would have been an enormous
                    construction project, but even here in the U.S. some doubts were raised about
                    the feasibility of it, the cost of it and particularly the environmental impact.
                    That idea was on the way out when I came in.</p>
                <p>The new proposal was to create a new base in the Nago area, which was a bit
                    outside the more populated cities. During my time talks continued with the
                    Japanese government on that. The complicated fact was that the Okinawan people
                    didn't feel that the Japanese government was taking their wishes into account.
                    While we never negotiated directly with Okinawan local leaders and groups, we
                    often met with them and heard their concerns. Local press and politicians were
                    very vocal and their basic position was that they had the burden of too many
                    bases. Given the concentration there, their position was that if the base was
                    vital for the relationship, move the base somewhere else in Japan. That of
                    course ran into the “not in my backyard” syndrome which was very strong in
                    Japan. The governor said they would accept Nago as a site, but only with a 15
                    year limit after which U.S. forces would have to leave that base. That's
                    something the U.S. could not accept and never did agree to.</p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>State (EAP) worked very closely with the Office of the Secretary of Defense (OSD)
                    in talks with the Japanese government and efforts to accommodate the Okinawan
                    people as much as possible. Two key players were EAP Deputy Assistant Secretary
                    Rust Deming and OSD Deputy Assistant Secretary Kurt Campbell. Both knew Japan
                    well and worked hard and well to maintain the relationship. One way the Japanese
                    government tried to gain local agreement was to pour a lot of money into
                    Okinawa. The people in the Nago area were being promised a lot of central
                    government funding. When the 2000 G-8 Summit was in Japan, the Japanese
                    government decided to hold it in Okinawa. That was to recognize the role of
                    Okinawa, but also, in a sense to bring publicity and money and try to smooth the
                    way for a base. The hotel where the Clinton administration stayed in was in Nago
                    in a beautiful area with nice lagoons.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you sense a distance between the Japanese
                        establishment in Tokyo and people in Okinawa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: The Okinawans feel that the Japanese government discriminates by burdening
                    them with bases and that mainland Japanese look down on them. And the wartime
                    memories are very painful. There was terrible suffering during the Battle of
                    Okinawa. Just about every family lost family members and they blamed much of
                    that on the Japanese military, not on the Americans, for putting them through
                    it. The Okinawans considered that they were looked down upon as being a bit
                    racially different; the dialect is different. They felt like poor cousins and
                    thought that that's why they ended up with all the bases because they could be
                    sort of out of sight, out of mind. Also, economically the Japanese government
                    has poured a lot of money in and there was domestic tourism, but they haven't
                    done some basic things that would really help the economy like deregulating
                    airlines enough that there could be some start up carriers offering competitive
                    flights outside of tour packages. It's very expensive to get to Okinawa, so
                    businesses aren't locating there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any other major military-related issues?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>An important and tragic incident took place in February, 2001, when the American
                    submarine the USS Greenville hit and sunk the Ehime Maru in Hawaiian waters. The
                    Ehime Maru was a Japanese fishing vessel, but it was also a training vessel
                    where teenagers were being trained to be fishermen or maritime officers. They
                    had been training near Hawaii and had enjoyed some tourism before resuming their
                    work.</p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>There in Hawaiian waters the American submarine surfaced suddenly in an exercise
                    of rising quickly to the surface. It rammed right into the Ehime Maru and the
                    boat sank almost immediately. Nine people were killed, including four
                    17-year-olds. It was a terrible incident from many angles. First, there were all
                    these deaths, and they were so young. Second, the submariners were at fault for
                    failing to make sure that there were clear waters all around before suddenly
                    surfacing. Also, it was actually a demonstration for VIPs so had the aspect of a
                    joy ride.</p>
                <p>I was on vacation when it happened and it was shocking to see it on the
                    television news. I got back a day later to find the State Department had to
                    closely monitor what the military was doing. DOD and the Navy were doing all
                    they could to find survivors and remains, but while well intentioned, they
                    didn't have a particularly diplomatic touch with their public relations.</p>
                <p>First they wouldn't let the captain of the submarine vessel apologize, though an
                    early and sincere apology would have meant a great deal to the Japanese families
                    and public. Military lawyers were concerned that their legal position would be
                    compromised and that if the captain said he was sorry that would be taken as an
                    admission of guilt — though there was no question about who was at fault. Right
                    away the American and the Japanese cultures clashed. If he had come out and
                    bowed deeply to the families right at the beginning, a lot of the resentment and
                    bad feelings could have been avoided in my view. Later, after he left the Navy,
                    he said that he had wanted to do this. During a later court of inquiry, he
                    apologized to the Ehime Maru crew and some families. Some months later he went
                    to Japan and met families to offer his apology, but by then it was too late to
                    head off a firestorm of anger and grief.</p>
                <p>It was a major story for weeks — there were front page pictures in newspapers for
                    many days showing pictures of the young students in their aloha shirts in
                    Hawaii. It was terribly painful. The military did well to continue the search
                    for survivors/bodies for a long time. At one point, a week or two after the
                    incident, they sent word through to the Japanese government that they planned to
                    end the search as there was no hope of finding anyone. A Ministry of Foreign
                    Affairs official called me in the middle of the night to tell me they were
                    sending a deputy minister to the U.S. to stress how important it was for the
                    search to continue. He was about to get on a plane but we managed to convince
                    them that it would not be useful. In the end the military continued the search
                    at great expense throughout wider and wider areas in order to make the Japanese
                    feel that we were doing all we could.</p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>Another incident showed the different cultures between State and the military.
                    DOD drafted a presidential letter of condolence. When it came for clearance I
                    was a little upset by it because the first paragraph was a well worded sentiment
                    of condolence and grief. But then the letter went on for four paragraphs listing
                    all the Navy was doing in the search. It set totally the wrong tone, so we
                    managed to get it cut back to a very simple condolence, not a
                    self-justification. That showed the importance of working together because the
                    military was looking at the problem from their own point of view and doing their
                    best, but they didn't have a good sense of what the wider impact would be on the
                    Japanese public when this was made public.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. The fact that the captain didn't apologize early on
                        became quite a point of conflict. It does point out that as a rule, the
                        Pentagon lawyers tend to be very protective. They have their reasons, but
                        the point is that often it is the wrong thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, as I said, the absence of an immediate and personal apology really
                    hurt. The Pentagon quickly realized they had to compensate the victims and they
                    did pay compensation to the parents. There wasn't a lot of arguing about the
                    amounts, but still that was a little later in the game and the public reaction
                    to U.S. Navy maneuvers and methods remained very negative.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you talk about your impressions of this G-8
                        summits?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: For the Okinawa Summit, I worked mainly on the bilateral side of the
                    visit. There was a different group in the White House and the European and
                    Economic Bureaus who worked on the multilateral side. While I was there for the
                    whole summit, I was concentrating on the events that President Clinton did with
                    the Okinawan people. The main event was a visit to the Peace Park. This is a
                    park at the edge of the ocean where some of the most fierce fighting took place
                    toward the end of the Battle of Okinawa. Many Japanese either died or committed
                    suicide in the caves near there. It's very moving because there are a number of
                    marble plaques with the names of all the dead, not just the Japanese soldiers
                    but the Okinawan civilians and the Americans, Australians, New Zealanders and
                    others who died in the fight. Clinton gave a very good speech at that park in
                    broiling hot weather to a large crowd.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the Clinton administration and Clinton himself get
                        along with the Japanese? How was the relationship during the time you were
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>WHITE: Like most presidents, Clinton wanted to develop a personal relationship
                    with his counterparts, but in his two terms he met seven Japanese prime
                    ministers. Just about every time he went to Japan or to a G-8 Summit it was a
                    different person, so he never really developed a personal relationship. There is
                    such a difference in the Koizumi- Bush relationship because Bush sees him a lot
                    so of course they have developed a friendship. Clinton never had a personal
                    interest. He wasn't negative toward the Japanese, though not particularly warm
                    either. Early in the administration there had been a lot of more trade friction,
                    but I wasn't involved at that time. On the desk we worked well and closely with
                    the Asia group at the NSC but among the top people of the Clinton administration
                    there weren't many with strong Japan ties.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was happening with the Japanese political system? Did
                        we see changes in it? The Liberal Democratic Party (LDP) had been around for
                        a long time and I was wondering whether Japan might be becoming more
                        independent from the United States.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: At that time there was a lot of intellectual debate about Japan becoming a
                    “normal nation,” meaning Japan should take on more responsibility for its own
                    security. I think most of the Japan hands in the U.S. government thought that it
                    would be a good idea for them to become more self-reliant. We had encouraged the
                    Self Defense Forces to take more forward leaning roles as peacekeepers in
                    various regions. There was concern among pundits that if Japan became a more
                    normal, more independent nation, it could mean that they wouldn't always follow
                    our lead on a lot of issues. Most Japan specialists saw that possibility but
                    felt it would be a healthy development. The alliance was strong enough to manage
                    some disagreement and we had the same core values.</p>
                <p>One incident that illustrates this is that after the North Korean Taepodong
                    missile crisis, the Japanese decided they needed their own intelligence
                    satellites. They thought they hadn't been given enough intelligence by the
                    Americans — although they probably had and certain agencies just didn't share it
                    widely. When the idea was proposed, it seemed that a lot of the Japanese press
                    expected the U.S. to step in and object, saying that Japan didn't need its own
                    intelligence satellites. They seemed geared up to complain that the U.S.
                    wouldn't give them the technology needed to build them. That didn't happen.</p>
                <p>At State and DOD, we argued that the USG should support Japan. They needed the
                    satellites for their own self-image and sense of pride, and to make them feel
                    they were full partners in the relationship. It would have been harmful to
                    insist on what was in fact the case, that the intelligence we were giving them
                    was better than what they could get by building their own satellites; also it
                    would have been a lot cheaper. So they went forward with a plan to build four
                    satellites at enormous expense.</p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                <p>We had to negotiate an export control agreement to allow them to get some
                    sophisticated technology. I worked with very good people in the Political
                    Military Bureau who took the lead. It required a lot of interagency coordination
                    because there were other satellite related negotiations going on with European
                    countries and people were concerned that the Japan talks would set a precedent
                    about the type of technology we'd share. They finally built the satellites at
                    great expense. Ironically, I've have been told that commercial satellite
                    companies now produce photos as good or better than what they're getting from
                    their own satellites, but nonetheless it was important that they be able to do
                    it as a “normal nation.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the Clinton administration view the whole
                        relationship with Japan at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: They had come into office very hard-line on the trade issues which at the
                    beginning of the '90s were considerably more in the American public eye than
                    they were toward the end of the '90s. They had tried for a few agreements that
                    had numerical targets but the Japanese resisted mightily and it caused a lot of
                    bad feeling between officials of both countries. By the late '90s the concern
                    was much more that Japan's economy was floundering. The economic giant that was
                    going to take over the U.S. was now an enormous drag on Asia. Their growth rates
                    were so low they were not providing any stimulus to growth in other countries
                    and that became much more a focus. The attention shifted in a sense from what
                    USTR could do on specific trade issues to more concern about what Treasury and
                    U.S. businesses could do to urge Japan to get its economic house in order. The
                    banking system had huge amounts of non-performing loans, but it was very
                    difficult to get them to change because there's nothing more domestic than
                    monetary and economic policy. The U.S. government's policy at that time was to
                    promote deregulation of various sectors in hopes that a more free market
                    economy, while painful at first, would give Japan a chance to restructure and
                    use its assets more effectively and efficiently.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we pushing for something that today is very much in
                        the forefront, deregulating the postal bank, which is the main banking
                        engine in Japan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Postal reform has been Prime Minister Koizumi's main issue. At the time I
                    was on the desk we were not pushing hard to deregulate it completely because
                    that seemed politically unrealistic. What we were looking at then was the
                    insurance sector, which was related to the postal system. Because they were such
                    a big government organization they were able to offer various kinds of insurance
                    and banking services very cheaply, while we were trying to create opportunities
                    for American companies to compete. There were wider macroeconomic implications,
                    as postal savings money deposited by households in low interest accounts was
                    used to support favored industries and channeled to quasi-governmental
                    organizations. Koizumi later worked to break the system, which is having
                    considerable political impact within the LDP and the way they have operated.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also on the economic side, they've got two things which
                        seem to be rather inhibiting. One is the role of women in society. The other
                        one is the low fertility rate and the lack of interest in immigration to
                        augment the work force. Do you see any changes in these things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Well, they're connected. It's interesting that the most traditional
                    societies where women do tend to stay at home like Italy and Japan have the
                    lowest fertility rates of developed countries. Places where women are welcomed
                    in the work force and well supported like the Scandinavian countries and to some
                    degree the U.S. have much higher fertility rates. So, Japan's situation
                    indicates that stay-at-home wives are not having many children; it may be
                    because it is expensive to educate children, there is little childcare, and
                    husbands are still expected to work long hours. People have been talking for
                    years about the underutilization of educated Japanese women. You would think
                    that would change because they are having a shortage of labor. Instead of
                    bringing in immigrants, which they aren't comfortable with, why don't they just
                    give support to women?</p>
                <p>The role of women is changing certainly in areas where they can be more
                    independent as doctors, as small business people, as academics. Those women are
                    doing much better than they are in the corporate world, not surprisingly. The
                    fertility rate would probably improve if women find that there is child care
                    support and support for aging parents and better social services. Exhorting
                    people to have children as a civic duty doesn't help.</p>
                <p>It will be interesting to see how that develops because more and more young
                    Japanese women just aren't interested in getting married. We see many bright
                    women marrying foreigners or going to work for foreign companies. The embassy
                    has certainly benefited from that, as some of the best FSNs are women who prefer
                    the embassy to Japanese institutions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were on the Japanese desk at this time did you
                        find that in a way you were in competition with the China desk? In other
                        words, with China being a newly emerging power, a huge power, and Japan
                        suffering from economic troubles, did you have fight for attention from
                        higher levels?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Certainly the Japanese felt that way. They used the phrase “Japan passing”
                    throughout the Clinton administration, claiming that Washington wasn't paying
                    much attention to them compared to China. I often responded that it was because
                    China was a problem. If you have a problem, you're naturally going to spend more
                    time working the problem as opposed spending time with the good, steady, strong
                    ally.</p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>It sometimes was difficult to set up meeting with high level Japanese and senior
                    USG officials. For example there is a regular meeting called the Two plus Two
                    which we try to have annually. The four are the Secretary of State and the
                    Secretary of Defense plus the Minister of Foreign Affairs and the head of the
                    Japanese Defense Agency. We usually tried to do it in New York at the time of
                    the UN General Assembly. You could always be sure of having the Japanese Foreign
                    Minister and the Secretary of State there, but coordinating schedules for all
                    four people was always very difficult. Some of the Secretaries of Defense felt
                    it was just a formality and really not that interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During the 2000 election campaign, when Gore and Bush were
                        running against each other, did China come up as an issue?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I don't think Asian issues were very important, though it seemed to be a
                    fashion for one side to accuse the other of being soft on China, then when a new
                    group comes to office they realize that reality is tougher to deal with than
                    rhetoric. There was only one mention of Japan in the debates as far as we could
                    tell, so Japan was clearly not a campaign issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q. Did you get involved in the transition with the Clinton
                        and Bush administrations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes, but in a fairly routine way. We prepared paper and briefed people.
                    There was a fairly smooth transition at the NSC because they had a strong Japan
                    person, Michael Green, who headed the Asia office. He'd been an academic as well
                    as in and out of government and he knew all the players. The new Deputy
                    Secretary was Richard Armitage who had a strong Japan background and many
                    personal contacts. He had spent a lot of time in Japan both in his navy days, as
                    a consultant and at DOD. He understood Japan and he understood the importance of
                    meeting and greeting visiting delegations. Access to the 7th floor by visiting
                    delegations of Japanese politicians, for example, really improved because Rich
                    was always ready to sit down and talk to them — he knew most of them anyway. The
                    Japanese were very pleased. They saw quite a shift from what they saw as benign
                    neglect under the Clinton administration to having strong connections in the
                    administration. Jim Kelly who became Assistant Secretary of State had been at
                    the East West Center in Hawaii and also was very familiar with Japan and Japan
                    issues. In that sense you had real experts coming in and we certainly didn't
                    need to do a lot of briefing up on the major issues, particularly in the
                    security area.</p>
                <p>One of the final things I did was to work with Howard Baker to prepare for his
                    ambassadorial hearings. He was part of a long time of really superb ambassadors
                    that Japan has had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We've made a real point of putting our top people
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                <p>WHITE: Yes. They include Mike Mansfield, Mike Armacost, Walter Mondale and Tom
                    Foley. Ambassador Foley, who had been Speaker of the House, served in the last
                    years of the Clinton Administration. The Japanese were pleased that he was
                    followed by Howard Baker from the Senate side, who was well respected by
                    Democrats and Republicans. He was an excellent nominee. As his wife was Senator
                    Nancy Kassebaum Baker, most people thought either one of them would have been a
                    superb ambassador. His confirmation hearing was like a coronation. The room was
                    filled and all the senators on the committee were there. Nobody had any
                    questions. They basically just wanted to make their speech saying what a great
                    choice Howard Baker was. It was fun to watch and a nice change from so many
                    difficult ambassadorial hearings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had he had much experience dealing with Japan from the
                        Senate side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: He had a reasonably good background in Japan without being an Asia expert.
                    He traveled there and had a lot of contact with Japanese politicians and
                    business people. He had been serving as a lawyer in Washington since leaving the
                    Senate so he was well aware of the key issues and the concerns of
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you leave the desk?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: In June of 2001.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: I went on a two year tour — which turned out to the last two years of my
                    career — to the National Defense University at Ft. McNair. There is a program
                    whereby three State people teach at the Industrial College of the Armed Forces
                    (ICAF), which is where I went, and others go to the National War College which
                    on the same base/campus. It is a valuable exchange program. Usually there are
                    eight or ten State Department mid-level officers and civil servants in classes
                    with the military and other civilian government employees. I taught economics
                    and a Japan regional studies course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ICAF was concentrated mainly on logistics and the supply
                        of the military wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                <p>WHITE: That was part of the curriculum and that aspect distinguished it from
                    other senior military schools. Its mission was to determine how to maintain the
                    industrial base to supply the military machine and the logistics of getting
                    material to the right places. But the curriculum went far beyond that, with a
                    lot of broader strategic thinking as well. The school groomed lieutenant
                    colonels, commanders, captains and colonels to move on to the next level and
                    then on to the most senior positions.</p>
                <p>In the spring semester, there was an interesting program of industry studies.
                    Small groups divide into about 20 sectors, some of them clearly military related
                    like steel, shipbuilding, aircraft, space, but others with more broad
                    implications like biotech and education and health care. The groups have
                    speakers throughout the semester and do various field trips and spend two weeks
                    traveling overseas focusing on their industries. I was able to learn a great
                    deal by participating as a teacher in these industry studies. The first year I
                    followed biotech and the second year construction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the focus of the military people when you talked
                        about Japan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: In the fall semester the students chose a region or country to specialize
                    in. For the Japan class I tended to get some people who had been there and
                    wanted to know more about where they'd been, particularly those who had been
                    stationed in Okinawa, and others who either didn't get their first choice or
                    just wanted to learn a little more about an Asian country. There were about 10
                    classes during the semester and I gave a few on history, including the World War
                    II legacy issues which affect Japan's current relations with China and Korea.
                    There was a class on economics, but more of the focus was on Japan's politics,
                    security establishment, Self-Defense Forces, and the U.S.-Japan security
                    relationships. I gave a few classes myself and got speakers from around
                    town.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By this time you've spent an awful lot of time looking at
                        Japan. Drawing a line out into the future, where do you see Japan? What sort
                        of a role do you see Japan playing in Asia and globally?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: In terms of the U.S. relationship with Japan, I think it's extremely
                    important, though in the public eye it gets little attentioperhaps because it
                    has been so stable in political and security terms. The U.S. Japan relationship
                    really has been a foundation for this country in Asia. East Asia has a number of
                    potential flash points that point out the importance of having such a stable
                    security relationship. For example, the China/Taiwan question, North Korea's
                    nuclear ambitions on the one hand and great economic weakness on the other,
                    Japan's difficult history with its neighbors. There are a number of smaller
                    territorial disputes among countries</p>
                <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                <p>Economically speaking, despite Japan's slow growth of the last 12 years, it is
                    still the second biggest economy in the world. It is enormously advanced
                    technologically. It has a very educated hardworking work force. It has a great
                    many problems such as an aging population, a lack of creativity, and not always
                    beneficial complicated bureaucratic/ business/government ties, but its future
                    could go either way. It could come back and become a great economic power again
                    or it could just sort of slowly decline, but one way or another it's going to be
                    very important for U.S. interests.</p>
                <p>Finally, Japan is an enormously complex country and I think a fascinating study
                    for people who have gotten to know it. There are many contradictions that one
                    comes to appreciate when living there and visiting frequently — social
                    relationships, economic ties, etc. — and it takes a long time to begin to
                    understand the culture and society. But it is very rewarding.</p>
                <p>I got into the Japan field serendipitously. I had never studied Japan or even
                    Asia in college, but I am delighted with the way it turned out. It was a
                    wonderful place to live in the '80s and I have found it a very interesting
                    country to watch. I'm pleased to be able to continue as coordinator for the
                    Japan Advanced Area Studies here at FSI. That keeps me involved in the latest
                    issues of the day because I have to get speakers, find articles, find readings,
                    but also it gets me acquainted with the new generation that's going off to serve
                    in Japan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you retired when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: September 2003.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You're teaching at FSI now?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WHITE: Yes. The Japan Area Studies class is for the people who are studying
                    Japanese full time. We have area studies every two weeks for the year, covering
                    history, culture, politics, economics, social issues and current events. I have
                    a second part time job, which is running the Japan -America Student Conference.
                    That program brings 40 American college students and 40 Japanese college
                    students together each year in August, alternating countries each year. It's
                    been going on since 1934 so it's an excellent program and has created strong
                    bilateral ties.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's your impression of the new cadre of Japanese hands
                        that are coming out of FSI? Are they different?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                <p>WHITE: It is different because a lot more people now join the State Department
                    speaking Japanese. They're the ones I don't necessarily see because unless they
                    are studying Japanese, they're not taking area studies. A lot of them have come
                    through the JET program, which is Japan English Teaching set up by the Ministry
                    of Education in Japan some years ago to bring native English speakers from
                    Canada, U.S., India, Australia to Japanese schools. They are sent all over the
                    country to small villages and big cities and work with Japanese teachers in
                    English classes. It's a good thing for recent American college graduates who
                    come back with great enthusiasm for Japan and often good language skills. As I
                    say, that's a change. When I joined the Foreign Service, Japanese wasn't taught
                    at that many colleges and people like me started from scratch. It's been very
                    much to the benefit of the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q. Thank you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
