<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000136">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with William D. Brewer </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR WILLIAM D. BREWER</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Malcolm Thompson Initial Interview date: August 2, 1988</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>This is an interview with Ambassador William Brewer on August 2nd, 1988 at his
                    home in Falmouth, Massachusetts. The interview is part of the oral history
                    project of The Association for Diplomatic Studies. The interviewer is Malcolm
                    Thompson, a retired Foreign Service Officer.</p>
                <p>[Note: Some portions of the interview are out of sequence with the tapes as
                    Ambassador Brewer rearranged the transcript slightly in the editing for
                    clarity.]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To start with Bill, would you tell us when and why you
                        decided on a career in the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Yes, Malcolm, I'd be glad to because I decided definitively at a very
                    early age. I couldn't have been more than nine or ten when I got the idea that
                    government service in the State Department and the Foreign Service would be
                    something that I'd find fascinating. As people— you know grown-ups—asked me,
                    “What are you going to do when you grow up?” I would say, “Well, I want to be in
                    the Foreign Service,” and uniformly they, of course, would say, “Oh, that's a
                    fine ambition.” So I was a confirmed addict of a Foreign Service career before I
                    got to high school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you intend from the start to specialize in the Near
                        East and the Arab world?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Well, that came a little later but I still remember. I was in graduate
                    school, at Fletcher, and a friend of mine and I were in my room and we were
                    discussing what we would do in the eventuality that we might pass the Foreign
                    Service exam. And we decided that area expertise was probably to be sought
                    after, and I concluded at that time that the Near East, where I understood there
                    were tremendous reserves of petroleum, would be an area that would be
                    increasingly important to the United States and therefore I said to this friend
                    of mine at graduate school, “I think if I get into the Foreign Service, I will
                    specialize in the Near East.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good. I would like to concentrate on your more senior
                        assignments without overlooking any of your earlier posts. Is there anything
                        of special interest you would like to comment on involving these earlier
                        years? For example, when we served together in Damascus, in the early
                        1950s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Well, yes, there is, Malcolm, but if I could I would like to go back
                    before we met in Damascus to my second assignment which was in Saudi Arabia
                    because, although I was technically a very junior officer, I was in fact at the
                    post what would now be called Acting DCM for six months, and actually was in
                    charge of the Embassy in Saudi Arabia for a brief period—a week or ten days—when
                    I was a Third Secretary. So I had some experience even at that stage which I
                    think is of interest in connection with your project.</p>
                <p>And in particular two things occurred which I think are useful to comment on: the
                    first is that I was in Jeddah and keeping close track of the negotiations
                    between ARAMCO and the Saudi Arabian government which led up to the conclusion
                    in December 1950 of the first 50-50 profit sharing agreement between an oil
                    company and a Near Eastern government. Prior to that time there had been
                    agreements under which royalty had been paid and this system was not producing
                    revenue which the Saudi government wished, and ARAMCO had secured a ruling from,
                    I guess, the Attorney General, the Department of Treasury, anyway Washington,
                    that the tax deducted by Saudi Arabia as part of this 50-50 split could be
                    counted as a business expense in figuring their American income tax. So on that
                    basis there were very complex negotiations which— I don't need to go into in
                    detail—but which produced this 50-50 formula under which the profits were shared
                    equally between Saudi Arabia and ARAMCO.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your role in all this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: My role was in following the negotiations and in reporting them to
                    Washington because that was the first news that Washington had that the
                    agreement had been concluded. But parallel to that we at the Embassy were
                    considering how the Saudi government, could modernize its very antiquated fiscal
                    arrangements. In fact I often thought it was like being in the Middle Ages. If
                    you wanted to go down to send a cable, for example, you had to carry a large
                    sack of silver rials because the only currency in the country was this
                    full-bodied rial and it was very difficult to conduct large transactions with
                    these vast amounts of small heavy coins. And we thought Saudi Arabia very badly
                    needed a modern financial structure and in particular a central bank. And also,
                    in due course, paper currency.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>My role was to encourage and support the visits to Saudi Arabia by our Treasury
                    representatives from Cairo over a period of months. These Treasury
                    representatives made a number of preliminary suggestions and as a result of all
                    this activity we finally decided that the thing to do was to encourage the Saudi
                    government to request our assistance in providing some technical expertise which
                    would assist them in setting up a central bank. And this was done and the Saudis
                    agreed that they were going to need some assistance, and we cabled Washington,
                    and they agreed, and they went out and they found a man who had been financial
                    adviser, I believe, to Chiang Kai-shek, and had been an official in the State
                    Department at one stage of the game, Arthur Young, a very able man, to advise
                    the Saudis on setting up a central bank.</p>
                <p>He came out to Saudi Arabia, and I met him at the airfield, and briefed him and
                    we got him started and in due course he did propose what came to be known—they
                    avoided the term “bank” because, you know, the shari'a (Islamic Law) does not
                    sanction the payment of interest and the Saudis do not like the use of the term
                    “bank”, but essentially it's a central bank—he proposed the arrangements which
                    resulted in the founding of the Saudi Arabian Monetary Agency. And that is the
                    basis of the modern Saudi financial system which, of course, is now one of the
                    strongest in the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very interesting. That was in 1950 and '51. After that I
                        believe you were assigned to Damascus as a Political Officer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you care to comment on that assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Well, yes, I thought that was extremely interesting for my development as
                    an Arabic language and area officer because at that time—I don't know whether
                    it's still true—the Arab world as a whole could be likened to a tube of
                    toothpaste and Syria was the paste that always came out the end of the tube no
                    matter where you put the pressure. It was the cockpit, and also the prize, of
                    Arab politics. The two chief competitors were Cairo and Baghdad but somewhere in
                    the middle, although leaning more toward Cairo in the period you and I were
                    there, was Saudi Arabia, particularly with financial support. In fact I remember
                    when still in Saudi Arabia, the Saudis extending a $6 million loan which I think
                    turned out to be a gift to a Syrian dictator, Adib Shishakli shortly after his
                    coup d'etat which established him in power. So the opportunity to head the
                    Political Section in Damascus during this period gave me an unrivaled
                    opportunity to learn about the intricacies of inter-Arab politics, and I
                    wouldn't have missed it for the world because it was fascinating.</p>
                <p>(Footnote Added:</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>This was also the period which witnessed the earliest tentative Soviet moves into
                    the Near East, including Syria. The dynamics of this were made plain to me from
                    the Jisr Banat Yacub (”Daughters of Jacob Bridge”) diversion dispute in
                    September-October, 1953. The Israelis had begun earth- moving operations near
                    the bridge to divert the flow of the Jordan River, in an area which lay clearly
                    in the Syro-Israeli Demilitarized Zone (DZ) from which Syrian troops had
                    withdrawn after the armistice agreement between the two countries. The Syrian
                    position, which seemed to us clearly supported by the language of the armistice
                    agreement, was that no actions could be taken in the DZ without the concurrence
                    of both sides. Damascus accordingly sought redress via a Security Council
                    resolution condemning Israel. In the initial maneuvering over language, the USG
                    supported the Syrians. A seven-point condemnation of Israel was drafted.
                    However, at the last minute an eighth point was added to the effect that neither
                    side could indefinitely block “development” in the DZ. This was defended by our
                    UN delegation as “sounding a positive note”. Of course, Embassy Damascus
                    objected that this in effect undercut the entire resolution. For our pains we
                    were simply cut out of the final exchanges of telegrams with the Department. The
                    next text was put to a vote—and was promptly vetoed by the USSR.</p>
                <p>This Soviet action represented Moscow's first overt move to improve its position
                    with the Syrians and led to close Syro-Soviet collaboration by 1957. I have
                    always felt that we did ourselves no service by thus offering the Russians an
                    opening to move into the Near East.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good. Your next assignment apparently was in
                        Kuwait?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>BREWER: Well, yes, but maybe before we move on to Kuwait there's one other thing
                    that I ought to mention in respect to the assignment in Damascus. And that is
                    that, while we sought to develop good relations with the Syrians, we had great
                    difficulty even at that time because of the creation of the State of Israel and
                    our support for its creation. And you will recall that it was in 1954, I think,
                    or 1955, that the efforts that culminated in the Baghdad Pact began to be made,
                    the first being the Turko-Iraqi Pact which I think was in early 1955. And the
                    question came up about the adherence to this agreement of other Arab countries.
                    My recollection is that the Department encouraged all of us in the Arab world to
                    try and see if we couldn't encourage adherence in the interest of building an
                    effective barrier against the Communist expansion in that part of the world.
                    However, the closer we came to soliciting Syrian adherence, and indicating to
                    the Syrians that maybe there might be something in it for the Syrians, the more
                    the Department seemed to draw back from any involvement of Syria in the Baghdad
                    Pact. And, of course, as you know Syria never joined the Baghdad Pact. The
                    government at the time later fell and was replaced by an anti-western
                    government, and it has always been my speculation, but nothing that one can
                    prove, that our failure to move forward at that time, which I think we did
                    primarily because we were scared that the Syrians were going to want arms from
                    us, and we were not going to provide them because of the proximity of Syria to
                    Israel, that this contributed to Syria's turn to the Soviet Union and its
                    acceptance of Soviet arms in the ensuing period after you and I had left
                    Damascus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you believe that it could have been otherwise perhaps
                        if our policy had been different?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Well, I think it could have been because we after all did at a later
                    stage provide substantial arms to Jordan and those arms have not been used
                    against Israel.Had We provided similar arms to the Syrian government, we would
                    have had more influence with Damascus than we in fact had, while the arms would
                    not in fact have posed a significant threat to Israel but, to the contrary,
                    would have reassured the Syrians—who, of course, were concerned that Israel
                    might attack them. From a Syrian standpoint this was a question and concern to
                    them, and it might have facilitated an earlier settlement of this very knotty
                    problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In other words, it was probably more of a domestic
                        political decision that governed our policy in this respect. Shall we say
                        the influence of the Jewish lobby on the Congress?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Well, I'm not sure that it was that calculable at that time, but I think
                    those considerations probably were not absent from the minds of top
                    policy-makers in Washington. I do not recall that there was any outcry in the
                    Congress or anything at that time. This was after all in 1955 and still pretty
                    early in the game.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. Shall we move on to Kuwait? I believe your next
                        assignment was in Kuwait?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>BREWER: Yes, that's right. I was the Principal Officer there from 1955 to 1957
                    and that was a particularly interesting time because right in the middle of that
                    was the Suez crisis which had the effect of closing the Suez Canal and
                    immediately choking off temporarily the flow of oil from Kuwait, which was at
                    that time providing a very substantial part of the oil that moved through the
                    Canal. We had to watch the situation particularly closely because there were
                    those in Kuwait who were very sympathetic with Nasser and the Egyptians and who
                    were seeking to interfere with the flow of oil on land to the loading pier. I'll
                    never forget that at one stage all of a sudden there was this loud explosion
                    apparently and a pipeline was blown up which, however, turned out to be the
                    wrong line. It was not an oil pipeline but it was the line carrying gas from one
                    of the gathering centers to the water desalination plant in Kuwait town. That
                    meant there was a shortage of fresh water until they got the pipe repaired but
                    no interference with the outflow of oil.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is there anything else of significance that you'd like to
                        comment on during your Kuwait assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Well, I think we had very good relations with the Kuwaitis despite the
                    difficulties at the time of Suez because number one: it was a small post and we
                    were in close touch with the people, it was not an elaborate diplomatic post.
                    There were only two representatives there, the British political agent, and
                    myself. And we dealt on a relatively close basis with the leaders of the Kuwait
                    government and this was not only valuable experience, but I think it was useful
                    in explaining the United States' point of view on these issues to the top level
                    of the Kuwait administration at a time when they were still relatively
                    accessible before they became independent and established a modern government
                    as, of course, they now have.</p>
                <p>Another consideration which helped very much was the fact that, since we had
                    stood up in effect to the British at the time of Suez and forced them to
                    evacuate with the French from Suez, our standing in Kuwait relative to that of
                    the British, was high and we did not have the same kind of criticism as I'm sure
                    we fell under subsequently in the Arab- Israel war of 1967.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good. In 1957 you were reassigned to the Department
                        as officer in charge of the Arabian Peninsula affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>BREWER: I was Country Officer for the Arabian Peninsula. There was an
                    officer-in-charge of the Arabian Peninsula-Iraq affairs at that time but I only
                    worked in that job for a year before I was fortunately promoted and took over as
                    the officer-in-charge of UAR that involved Egyptian-Sudanese affairs. I did this
                    just at the time of the landing of the US marines in Lebanon in the summer of
                    1958. I might say in passing because it is kind of interesting, I happened to be
                    the first officer in the Department who was called about the coup d'etat in
                    Baghdad and the assassination of young King Faisal and the former regent of
                    Iraq. The Watch Officer—they had an antiquated arrangement in those days, not a
                    proper secretariat as they have now— they had just a couple of Watch Officers
                    who got in touch by phone with Desk Officers at their homes. He had called the
                    Iraqi Desk Officer but had gotten no answer and he therefore called me, since he
                    had had some dealings with me before and knew that I was in the same Office of
                    Near Eastern Affairs. The reason he hadn't gotten the Iraqi desk officer was
                    that he'd gone on vacation. So I immediately called my office director, and he
                    called the Acting Assistant Secretary and we all converged on the Department
                    about 7:00 in the morning of that Monday—I think it was the 14th of July
                    (1958)—and we worked there all day. And it was during that day that the request
                    came in from President Chamoun of Lebanon for assistance because he felt
                    threatened by what he interpreted as an area-wide rising up of leftist elements
                    incited by President Nasser. Since Lebanon had signed on to the Eisenhower
                    Declaration, why we felt that we had to comply and accordingly Marines were
                    landed early Tuesday morning, Washington time.</p>
                <p>I had the duty in the Department that night for the NEA Bureau and I will never
                    forget trying to get a few hours sleep on the Assistant Secretary's couch and
                    being awakened every hour on the hour by a colonel calling from the Joint Staff
                    in the Pentagon to report that it was now H- minus 4 hours and counting. I tried
                    to discourage this officer from calling the next hour but he said, “that was SOP
                    in the Pentagon,” and this was the way he did it.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>So, in any case, the landings took place and we soon had a new government in
                    Lebanon which was what should have happened without the landings, in my
                    judgement. While I think most of us in the Office of Near Eastern Affairs were
                    opposed to the idea of the landings at the time they took place, as we felt this
                    was a return to gunboat diplomacy which had been practiced by the British in the
                    19th century, on looking back on it, however, I became convinced that in fact
                    the way the landings were carried out did create an opportunity for us in the
                    Near East and led to a period of calm which lasted almost a decade. And my
                    reasoning is this: that the Arabs, who are very alert to the roles and positions
                    of the great powers, saw that one great power, namely the United States, was
                    able to insert troops into the Near East without anything more than verbal
                    objections from the Russians. And not only were we able to do that, but we did
                    not use the presence of our troops to change the situation in Lebanon to our
                    benefit. In fact, we permitted an election to take place which resulted in the
                    elevation to the presidency of the former Chief of Staff, General Chehab, and we
                    then left. We did not support President Chamoun's efforts to get himself
                    reelected. And for both those reasons I think the Arab world became less anti-US
                    in that the United States was prepared to act when it felt its interests were
                    threatened in that part of the world, and that at that time the Russians were
                    not able to do anything significant about it. I think that's very helpful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's interesting. It brings to mind a question. When
                        President Eisenhower sent in the Marines in 1958, as you have just recalled
                        for us, it seems to have worked out fairly well, and yet here in recent
                        times—was it 1985 or '86—President Reagan sent the Marines into Beirut under
                        different circumstances and I think everyone will agree it was a disaster.
                        Would you care to comment on the differences, why one policy worked out and
                        the other didn't?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: I think I've indicated why I think the first one worked. Under completely
                    different circumstances, we sent in the Marines several years ago, as I
                    understand it, largely to provide some assurances to Israel that the situation
                    would remain as it was while the PLO forces were being withdrawn from Beirut. We
                    didn't want Israel to go in and engage in fighting the PLO forces in the streets
                    of Beirut as this would have probably resulted in six months of terrible
                    bloodshed and destruction. And the Marines were provided as part of the deal
                    under which the withdrawal of the PLO units took place. But unfortunately once
                    the Marines were withdrawn, the right-wing and to some extent maybe pro-Israel
                    elements in the Lebanese Christian community proceeded to attack the refugee
                    camps in which were still living dependents of a lot of these PLO troops who had
                    been withdrawn. We therefore felt we had to send our Marines back in as a kind
                    of ex-post facto way of showing that we were sorry that these killings had taken
                    place in the Sabra and Shatila camps which apparently were to some extent—they
                    were not, I think, engineered by the Israelis but the Israelis did not seem to
                    pose an objection and it was suggested that these Marines go back evidently as
                    reassurance. So our Marines, and it was a very small unit, were then returned
                    under somewhat false assumptions and became sitting ducks for those who disliked
                    American policy because of the extent to which we had supported Israel in the
                    preceding period.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>Another thing that happened during the 1958 flap was a move to introduce Marines
                    into the Persian Gulf. This was an interesting tale because right after the war
                    broke out, Selwyn Lloyd flew over to Washington and there were high- powered
                    discussions at the White House about the crisis in the Near East and so on.
                    These discussions must have gotten into the question of protecting the oil
                    fields in the Persian Gulf because I suddenly got a call, and it's stayed with
                    me over these years because you don't get all that many calls from the top
                    officers of the Department—picked up the phone and this voice said, “This is
                    Freddy Reinhardt.” He was at that point the Counselor of the Department up on
                    the 7th floor, an office right across from Dulles'. I'd never laid eyes on him,
                    I just knew that he was a very senior man. He said, “Do you know anything about
                    the oil fields out there in Saudi Arabia?” And I said, “Well, yes a little. What
                    do you want to know?” Well it turned out he wanted to know where the oil fields
                    were, and so forth, and what about the oil fields in Kuwait, and would it be
                    possible to use troops to protect the oil fields in Kuwait and in Saudi Arabia.
                    And I drew a very sharp contrast between the situation in Kuwait where I said it
                    would be possible because of the small size of the state and the concentration
                    of the oil fields within it, actually physically protecting the fields by the
                    introduction of a relatively small number of troops. But I said in Saudi Arabia
                    the major Gawar field stretches for hundreds of miles and there are other fields
                    all over the Eastern Province, and I just did not think it would be physically
                    possible for any reasonable number of troops to have any impact on this
                    situation. He said, “Oh, you've been out there, have you?” I said, “Why, yes.”
                    Well he said, “Could you write me a memorandum simply describing what you've
                    been telling me over the phone?” So I wrote him such a memorandum, which was
                    essentially describing the geography of the Eastern Province, but I marked it
                    confidential and rushed it up to Reinhardt. And he said, “Let's go into the
                    Secretary with this.” We went in to see the Secretary but he wasn't there.
                    Reinhardt said, “I'll see that he sees it.” The Secretary was leaving the next
                    day for meetings in London. And I learned later from a friend of mine in our
                    Embassy in London that, when the question of troops defending the oil fields in
                    the Persian Gulf came up, Dulles seemed “extraordinarily well briefed on the
                    geography of the Eastern Province.” So I guess he must have read my memorandum.
                    Anyway, of course, no troops were introduced.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>However, also stemming from those first meetings in the White House, I judge the
                    Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff must have been present because the
                    Pentagon, without I believe official orders from anywhere, decided as a
                    precautionary measure to transfer from the Seventh Fleet a shipload of Marines
                    to the Persian Gulf, just so they would have them in the area because they had
                    nothing anywhere near the area. In case it was decided that Marines should be
                    used, you know, they'd then have them in place. And they began sending me daily
                    bulletins of the progress of these Marines across the Indian Ocean and Arabian
                    Sea. And I got more and more agitated with every passing day because here were
                    these Marines getting closer and closer to the Persian Gulf. And I called my
                    contacts in the Pentagon and said, “What are these fellows going to do?” “Oh,
                    don't you worry about that, the Joint Chiefs of Staff have this thing under
                    control.” When I asked, “What are they going to do when they get in the Persian
                    Gulf?” they answered, “They will circle over the horizon.” I said, “It's July.
                    Are these ships air- conditioned?” They said, “We don't know about that.” “Well,
                    if they're not air-conditioned” I replied, “you're going to have so many cases
                    of heat stroke that every hospital from Abu Dhabi to Dhahran is going to be
                    jammed with prostrate American Marines. This isn't going to be very helpful in
                    carrying on our foreign policy.” “Don't you worry about that,” I was told, “the
                    Joint Chiefs have thought about all these things and there's not going to be any
                    problem.”</p>
                <p>Well, I kept asking. Finally the Pentagon said to me, “The Marines tomorrow will
                    chop to CINCNELM.” I said, “What's that mean?” They said, “That means they will
                    come under command of the Admiral in London, the Commander-in- Chief of the
                    Eastern Atlantic and Mediterranean Fleet.” I said, “What's he going to do with
                    them? Is he going to send them into the Persian Gulf?” “We don't know because
                    they'll be under command of that Admiral.” So I called the Embassy in London and
                    I said, “Can you go along to CINCNELM staff and find out what it is they plan to
                    do with these Marines that are going to come under their command tomorrow.” So
                    they did, and they called back and said, “These guys had never heard of these
                    Marines. They don't have any use for them. They don't know what they're going to
                    do with them when they come under their command.” So, strengthened by that
                    information, and also the general situation having calmed down, I was able to
                    get that ship turned around the day before it came under command of CINCNELM,
                    and start it on its way back to Manila, I guess. And I was just a little amused
                    that on the way back, of course, they immediately asked for shore leave in
                    Karachi or Bombay, or Calcutta, or somewhere, because they'd been at sea for a
                    long time. The tensions were still such in that area, however, that no port
                    would permit the ship to land until they got back to Singapore. So there was
                    another instance where we prevented something happening which could have had
                    some unfortunate repercussions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good. Following your Departmental assignment I see
                        from your biography that you then attended the Senior Seminar at the
                        Department.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>BREWER: Well, that's right. But I wanted to make one or two points if I'm not
                    going on too long about our role—the office there, the Egyptian desk—in
                    restoring normal relations with Egypt over the period 1958 to 1961 and what we
                    called a normalization program and it worked. As I said, I think the atmosphere
                    was favorable because of what had happened as a result of the Lebanese landings,
                    but the fact of the matter was that I found on taking over the desk that there
                    were a number of annoying, niggling little matters on which the United States
                    was putting roadblocks in the way of normal contacts with the Egyptian
                    government. I can give you one example. For example, the Egyptian government was
                    not able to import from the United States axle grease for its civilian trucks
                    because someone in the Department of Commerce had concluded that axle grease
                    might also go into military trucks and we had a ban on any exports of items that
                    might be for military purposes and so the Department of Commerce, without
                    checking with the Department of State, had in effect extended the ban to include
                    items which were primarily for civilian use.</p>
                <p>Well, gradually over a period of months even years, we removed these what you
                    might call servitudes on our relationship. There had been no cultural exchanges.
                    We restored cultural exchanges. We made a great effort to assist in the clearing
                    of the Suez Canal. We facilitated this by providing, I think it was the largest
                    dredge in the world at that time which was the property of the US Corps of
                    Engineers. We got General Wheeler, who was in charge of the Corps at that time,
                    interested in this project, and he went over. And the Egyptians were, I think,
                    appreciative of these efforts on our part which we were not making primarily, or
                    even at all, because we thought the Egyptians were so wonderful. But simply
                    because we didn't see there was any particular need to penalize the Egyptian
                    government unduly. We had normal diplomatic relations with them and we thought
                    the entire relationship should be normal.</p>
                <p>Well, this normalization continued up to the stage that we finally went to annual
                    PL 480 Title I wheat programs because they had a terrible food shortage and we
                    had a huge surplus at that time of wheat. But we provided it to the Egyptian
                    government on a year-to-year basis. There were new negotiations every year and
                    the idea was that we would unload our surpluses, the Egyptians would get the
                    food, and the Egyptians would pay for it in Egyptian pounds which would then be
                    set aside for either economic development or use by our Embassy and for other
                    purposes as defined in the law that had passed the Congress not too many years
                    before.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>Now the question arose early in 1961 in the Kennedy Administration whether we
                    should not move beyond this in our relations with Egypt, because our relations
                    at that time were really back to normal. And I can still recall a discussion
                    with my office director and he said, “Well now, suppose we take the next step
                    and suppose we suggest a multi- year commitment for PL 480? What will that do?”
                    And I said, “Well my hunch is that the Egyptians will then ask us for arms,” as
                    they had in fact done back in 1953, I think it was, and been turned down. And
                    the director said, “Well, of course, we won't be in a position to reply
                    favorably, will we?” I said, “No, and so our relations with them get hurt.” He
                    said, “Then I think we don't wish to be in that situation, do we?” And I said,
                    “No, we don't.” So we decided that, while relations should be normal, it would
                    be a mistake to try and move beyond that stage because in doing so you would
                    raise expectations in Egypt which by the very nature of things could not be met
                    by the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bill, when we broke off you were discussing US- Egyptian
                        relations. Do you want to continue with that thought?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Yes, because I think it was a rather significant improvement in the
                    relationship that we worked out over a period of years there from 1958 to 1961.
                    And one of the elements in the improved relationship was our effort to assist
                    the Egyptians with respect to the Suez Canal. You will remember that in the 1956
                    war the Canal had been blocked by Egyptian vessels being sunk in the channel—I
                    forget, there were 20-25 vessels, the place was a mess. So when the war was over
                    the thing was, how do you clear this? And it was decided that the Corps of
                    Engineers of the United States Army could be helpful and we encouraged this
                    approach because our feeling was that we were not so much doing something for
                    Egypt, as we were doing something for international commerce. And our studies
                    showed that Egyptian use of the Canal was virtually nil, the major users were,
                    oh I don't know, Norway and Liberia and the United Kingdom and so on. So it was
                    very much in our interests, and in the interests of all maritime powers to get
                    the canal functioning again. And not only functioning, but the Egyptians made
                    the point that as the result in part of the war the world was now building
                    larger and deeper tankers. So that if they were not careful, even though they
                    had the canal reopened, it would not be used very much because a lot of the
                    ships would no longer be able to go through it. So there was a suggestion that
                    the canal should be widened and deepened and the Egyptians made an application
                    to the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development for funds to
                    accomplish this project which was to have been worked out using the very
                    substantial dredge of the Corps of Engineers that had made available to help in
                    the clearing process.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Now, friends of Israel and the Israeli government viewed this with a jaundiced
                    eye because in their view we were assisting Egypt and this was monstrous and
                    something that ought to be blocked at all costs. But we took the position, as I
                    say, that this was, in fact, something in the aid of international commerce more
                    than it was in the aid of the Egyptian state. We therefore decided that we would
                    go ahead and we would cast our vote in the IBRD meeting in favor of this project
                    and that that would mean, because of the weight that our vote had in IBRD
                    voting, that would mean that the project would be approved.</p>
                <p>But we decided that it would be important to head off what we expected to be
                    considerable adverse criticism from the Congress for this action. And my boss at
                    the time— Armin Meyer—had a first rate idea, namely send a letter in— we always,
                    as you know, were writing letters to Congressmen in response to their requests
                    for information or criticisms or whatever they referred from their
                    constituents—that's one of the things we spend a lot of time doing in the State
                    Department—but Armin thought that in this situation we should take the
                    initiative. And we should write every Senator explaining precisely the rationale
                    behind our vote and should send a similar letter to every member of the House
                    who had expressed concern to us on the issue. So I drafted such a letter and it
                    was worked over and approved and we got that letter on the desk of every member
                    of the Senate and every interested member of the House by about 10:00 in the
                    morning of a Monday on the day that the vote was going to be taken. The vote was
                    taken about noon. And we were astonished. We had only, as I recall, two or maybe
                    three letters from the Congress about that vote. Two of them were critical, and
                    one expressed appreciation to us for providing him in advance with the rationale
                    which he could use with his constituents if any of them inquired.</p>
                <p>So I think this shows the importance of accurate up-to- date and complete
                    explanation to the Congress in terms of smoothing the path for what might have
                    otherwise have been a controversial act by the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very interesting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Then there is something else that I think is interesting in this period
                    which is not directly related to my role on the Egyptian desk. But you may
                    recall that it was in this period that they began having non- aligned
                    conferences. The major non-aligned states were Yugoslavia, India, Indonesia and
                    Egypt, so I was involved from that standpoint. And the second non-aligned
                    conference was to be convened in Belgrade in, I believe August, 1961. And the
                    question came up in the spring as to what should our attitude be toward the
                    conference, toward attendance at the conference by countries we regarded as
                    friendly, what position should we take when the conference convened, etc.,
                    etc.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>And we decided in NE that the smart move was to recognize the basic rule of
                    diplomacy that, if you take the position that anyone who is not for us, is
                    against us, you windup with a lot of people against you. If you say anybody who
                    is not against us is for us, you wind up with a lot of people in your camp. So
                    we decided that the correct policy was to take no step to discourage attendance
                    at this meeting, and to take the position that it was perfectly legitimate
                    exercise of sovereignty on the part of the states concerned. And we naturally
                    hoped that they would view international issues at the meeting from an impartial
                    perspective, and that this was something that did not give us any particular
                    concern.</p>
                <p>Well, in order to try to get this view spread throughout the Department, and you
                    know how difficult it is sometimes to get clearances from the various geographic
                    bureaus, my name was sent up to the Secretary to be designated as coordinator of
                    US policy toward the non-aligned conference in Belgrade, and he approved this.
                    So I became the coordinator. What I took that to mean was that I was supposed to
                    prepare draft instructions to go out worldwide regarding the attitude that we
                    would take on the conference, and get those instructions approved and then they
                    would be sent out and that would be that. And I prepared such instructions along
                    the lines I've outlined. As I recall I had no particular difficulty clearing
                    them with every Bureau except the Latin American Bureau. And the Latin Americans
                    were just not going to accept this at all. They said, “This is ridiculous, this
                    is an abdication of our traditional role. We expect our friends to stand up and
                    be counted. We do not expect our friends to go to such a terrible meeting where
                    these sorts of crypto-Communists are likely to gather and accordingly we will in
                    no circumstances clear off on your instructions.”</p>
                <p>Well, at that point I figured I couldn't bargain with them. We held two
                    diametrically opposed points of view. So I said, “We're going to send our
                    instructions forward for approval by the seventh floor—I think it was the Deputy
                    Under Secretary for Political Affairs, Alex Johnson—and if you wish, you can
                    draft your own instructions.” So sure enough, they drafted diametrically opposed
                    instructions which they sent forward, which would have gone to their posts, I
                    think, not to others in the world. And one of my finest moments in the State
                    Department was to come in the next morning—you remember how the comeback copies
                    of the telegrams and airgrams always came in the first thing in the morning, so
                    you knew what had been signed, and what had been changed perhaps, and what was
                    sent out—and I came in in the morning and I found that Alex Johnson had signed
                    my instructions and had refused to sign theirs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bill, I'm going to interrupt you here because I think
                        we're coming to the end of our first side of the tape. All right, we're now
                        on the second side. Go ahead from where we left off.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>BREWER: Well, if I could just conclude about this non-aligned conference, 1961.
                    That really took care of my responsibilities except for an amusing footnote.
                    About a month later, as I recall, I heard from a friend of mine that a top level
                    meeting was being convened in the office of the head of the Policy Planning
                    Council to discuss US policy toward the non-aligned meeting. And this chap said,
                    “Don't you think you ought to be there?” And I said, “Well, yes, I guess perhaps
                    I should but I haven't been invited.” And I think he said, “Well, why don't you
                    come and sit in the back of the room and nobody is going to care.” So I did. And
                    I went up and sat in the back of the room and there all the high-powered types
                    in the Department were sitting around the table and the meeting was chaired by
                    the head of the Policy Planning Council. And it turned out it had been called at
                    the request of Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., one of the White House Special
                    Assistants who'd been asked by President Kennedy to follow this matter. So
                    Schlesinger was there and he said, “Well now, I just want to know what the
                    Department of State has been doing with respect to this non-aligned meeting
                    that's coming up in Belgrade?” And there was silence around the table, and
                    nobody spoke up, nobody seemed to know anything about my little effort and the
                    policy that we had approved. So finally with great timidity I spoke up from the
                    back of the room, and I said, “Possibly I can enlighten you, sir.” And I
                    proceeded to outline the steps that had been taken and the policy that we had
                    laid down. And when I got through Schlesinger said, “Thank you very much. I
                    don't think I have any other questions.” And that was the end of the
                    meeting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good. In 1961 you were assigned to the Senior Seminar
                        in Foreign Policy. Any comments you'd like to make on that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: None, other than to say that it was an extremely valuable year for me,
                    and if I had to stress one aspect of it I would say that the opportunity to
                    visit so many different parts of the United States, including Puerto Rico, and
                    become familiar with their problems, some of their industries, their economic
                    activities, and so on, was a tremendous help to me later on in the Foreign
                    Service. And I'm delighted to see that that type of tour is still being
                    undertaken by the Senior Seminar.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your next overseas assignment was as Deputy Chief of
                        Mission at our Embassy in Kabul, Afghanistan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Yes, and that was a fascinating assignment because Afghanistan, at that
                    time, was the only non- Communist country in the world that bordered both the
                    Soviet Union and China. And it therefore afforded an interesting vantage point
                    from which to observe, first the relatively good relations between those two
                    Communist countries, and then their rapid deterioration after 1961—'62, I guess
                    it was.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>When I went out the key issue in the briefings that I got seemed to be, as far as
                    Washington was concerned, whether the Afghan regime had, in the famous phrase,
                    “passed the point of no return” in its relations with Communist Russia. I took
                    this to mean the question of whether the government in Kabul had so come under
                    the influence of Moscow as to be considered a virtual satellite. Well, on my
                    arrival I found a little to my surprise that the Kabul government was nowhere
                    near being a satellite of the Soviet Union. It was quite true that it paid a
                    good deal of attention to Soviet views as might be expected from a country with
                    a huge common border with one of the two superpowers, but it sought to balance,
                    as far as it could, its relations with the Soviet Union with good relations with
                    the United States. And it seemed to me that our role should be to do what we
                    could to enhance the opportunity of the Afghan authorities to develop this
                    balanced relationship. And Ambassador Steeves, who was a first rate chief during
                    this period, certainly had the view that an effective bilateral relationship
                    could be continued and even expanded.</p>
                <p>I found on my arrival, for example, one of the things that I was told, as an
                    example of how nasty the Afghan government was to us, that “The diplomats were
                    not permitted to travel outside of Kabul.” And I said, “Well, why is that?” And
                    I was told: “Because we send notes to the Foreign Office as we are required to
                    do, requesting permission to travel to some particular province, and we never
                    get a reply, which constitutes a refusal, you see, so we can't go.” I said, “Why
                    don't we try this? Why don't we send them a note saying that we are planning to
                    go on such-and- such dates next month to this province, and see what will happen
                    if we do that.” I said, “My suspicion is that the Afghan bureaucrats in the
                    Foreign Office simply do not want to take a decision.” And this, of course,
                    turned out to be the case. So by modifying our own note we expanded our
                    operations and we were able to visit anywhere we wished in Afghanistan without
                    hindrance except the Wakhkhan Corridor which was a very restricted area and we
                    were generally not permitted to go there. So some of us did a good deal of
                    traveling in those years in Afghanistan. But that's simply one minor
                    illustration of how a change in approach can actually produce a modification in
                    policy which is helpful.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>Another thing we did. This was at a time when the Kennedy administration was
                    getting started and was pushing the Peace Corps concept. We decided that we
                    ought to try to negotiate a Peace Corps agreement with Afghanistan because it
                    was manifest that they needed the type of assistance that the Peace Corps could
                    provide. And since they wouldn't have to pay for it, it seemed that this would
                    be something that ought to appeal to the Afghan government. So I carried out the
                    negotiations with the head of the Economic Section of the Foreign Ministry and
                    they were indeed interested. And, in fact, in due course he informed me that the
                    Afghan government had decided to accept the Peace Corps and they would sign an
                    agreement. I said, “Fine. Now we've only got one question left and that is 'what
                    size unit do you wish to come first, how large, how many volunteers do you want
                    in the first unit?'” And he thought for a minute, and he said, “What is the
                    smallest Peace Corps unit anywhere in the world?” And I said, “I don't know, but
                    I can find out.” And, of course, I did find out. It turned out that we had a
                    unit of nine in Liberia. So I went back to him and I said, “We have a unit of
                    nine in Liberia.” He said, “Fine, we'll have nine.”</p>
                <p>The first Peace Corps unit into Afghanistan consisted of a mere nine volunteers.
                    They were personally selected, however, by the Peace Corps Director, who was a
                    very able individual, Bob Steiner who had grown up in Iran and spoke Persian
                    which was the language used in Afghanistan at that time, and had a very good
                    sense of the type of person who would go down very well with the Afghan
                    mentality. And as a result I think each of these nine individual volunteers was
                    in his or her own way outstanding. And so great an impact did they make, this
                    first unit, that the Afghans couldn't have enough of the Peace Corps thereafter.
                    I don't remember the exact figures, but I think the second unit was about 75,
                    and I think the third unit they wanted over 120 or something. They would take
                    all the Peace Corps volunteers that we could find as a result of that. We had
                    Peace Corps volunteers up near the Soviet frontier that didn't seem to bother
                    them. So that this made a tremendous and favorable impact on our
                    relationship.</p>
                <p>At the same time we continued a major AID program which had been going on prior
                    to my arrival because it was manifest that the Afghans needed road development,
                    agricultural development, and various other things at which we were working.
                    These projects were also helpful. They were not, as is sometimes seen, in
                    competition with the Russians. The Russians were also doing the same kind of
                    thing, but they were doing projects in different areas. And the Afghans were
                    rather shrewd in trying to coordinate the two. For example: their number one
                    national roadnet, which forms a “U” from Herat around Kandahar and then up to
                    Kabul; the Afghans had the Russians building the road from Herat to Kandahar and
                    the Americans building the road from Kandahar to Kabul. This gave rise to an
                    interesting exchange which shows that our relations were then not all that bad
                    with the Russians on the spot.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>The head of the Russian aid mission sought an appointment with the head of our
                    AID mission and he came in to him, and he said, “Look, you know these road
                    projects that we're working on...” He said, “Where precisely in Kandahar is your
                    project terminating?” And our man told him. And he said, “Well, that's what I
                    was afraid of. That's about three-quarters of a mile from where our project is
                    starting. Don't you agree that we ought to link these two roads up to avoid any
                    difficulty with the Afghans when the projects are finished?” And our man said he
                    certainly did. So they split the difference and each one extended the project
                    approximately one-half a mile or less, a third of a mile, and the two roads were
                    linked up in Kandahar.</p>
                <p>And this shows that sometimes when you get closer to a particular situation, the
                    relationships and the activity are not quite the exaggerated cold war nature as
                    is shown by the media back in this country.</p>
                <p>Another aspect of our AID program which I think was particularly helpful in
                    maintaining and developing good relations with the Afghan government was that,
                    even after Pakistan closed the border with Afghanistan, and we had brought all
                    our AID supplies through Pakistan because it was economic, Ambassador Steeves,
                    with our strong support, took the position that we should continue to bring in
                    supplies for the road via Iran even though it was more expensive because the
                    alternative, that is shutting down the project would turn out to be even more
                    expensive because of various claims that all the contractors would have on the
                    US Government. And that furthermore, by keeping the an option open for the
                    Afghans, that is not giving them the impression that they were isolated and
                    driven into a corner, the Afghans would be more likely to work out some sort of
                    settlement with the Pakistanis which, of course, was something that we
                    favored.</p>
                <p>Well, we had some difficulty convincing Washington of this but in due course we
                    did. And Washington therefore continued its assistance, although I think perhaps
                    at a somewhat reduced level of whatever could be transported across Iran. And
                    within a matter of, I think, two months—I have forgotten now exactly the time
                    schedule here—the Afghans were negotiating with the Pakistanis and the
                    Pakistanis had reopened the border. And I am convinced that if it had not been
                    for that position that we took at the Embassy—I think this is early 1965, maybe
                    late 1964—why the closure of the border would have been much more long lasting
                    and would have had a much more deleterious impact on the total western position
                    in that part of the world.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>While we were in Afghanistan occurred the famous White Revolution of King Zahir
                    Shah. He had been King for, oh I don't know, 30 years practically at that time,
                    because he became King when he was 19. But for most of those 30 years the power
                    in Afghanistan had either been one of his uncles or, after they died, his first
                    cousin, Sardar Mohammad Daud, who was Prime Minister when I got there. Well, the
                    King finally decided he'd had enough of this with his relatives in effect
                    running the country. And in 1963, I think it was, he took steps which prompted
                    Daud to say, “Well then, I resign.” Which was what the King hoped would happen.
                    Daud figured the King would say, “Oh, no, no, you mustn't do that.” But in this
                    case, of course, the King crossed him up and said, “Fine, your resignation is
                    accepted.” So Daud was out on his ear and they set up a commoner government.
                    This was a first for Afghanistan with a Prime Minister, who had an engineering
                    degree from, I think, Germany. The Interior Minister had a degree from, I think,
                    Columbia in the United States. It was a government, a cabinet of technocrats, of
                    commoners who were trained in the west outside Afghanistan and who had the
                    interests of their country very much at heart. And the King supported this
                    development wholeheartedly.</p>
                <p>We found this an extremely encouraging development and supported it as far as we
                    could. And at the time I left I would say that our relations with Afghanistan
                    were really excellent and there was no longer the slightest question of the
                    Afghan government going past the point of no return in its relations with the
                    Soviet Union. This perhaps was illustrated at the time of President Kennedy's
                    assassination because Ambassador Steeves arranged a very impressive memorial
                    service for the late President at his residence, and we invited all the Afghan
                    authorities including the Cabinet. And I was at the gate to greet the senior
                    people arriving, and when the Prime Minister came he said to me, “Would the
                    Ambassador mind if I said a few words during the service?” And I said, “I don't
                    think so. I'll ask him and I'll let you know.” And I did, and of course
                    Ambassador Steeves said, “No, there's no objection.” So Prime Minister Mohammad
                    Yusuf delivered a eulogy for the dead American president at this memorial
                    service. And I think that indicates the fundamental attitude of the Afghan
                    government at that time towards Americans and the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you left Afghanistan you returned to the Department
                        and were assigned to the Policy Planning Council. Do you have any comments
                        on that assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>BREWER: Well, I was the Near East, North African regional member of the Council
                    and it was an interesting opportunity to observe traffic from throughout the
                    region, and get to know a little something about North Africa which I hadn't
                    known before. But, frankly I found the assignment frustrating because it was not
                    a line agency in the State Department. By that I mean it was not one of the
                    groups whose concurrence had to be obtained if you wanted to modify policy. You
                    could write policy papers, and seek to influence policy by suggestions but there
                    was no way that your views necessarily had to be taken into account. As for
                    example the views of some of the geographic bureaus had to be taken into account
                    if the Bureau of Near Eastern &amp; South Asian Affairs wanted to do something.
                    And this I found very frustrating, and I think in fact it was a mistake. I think
                    that the clearance procedure should have been expanded to give more authority,
                    more influence, to members of the Policy Planning Council. But, be that as it
                    may, we had very little influence and we spent most of our time discussing blue
                    sky type of things such as trying to plan what US policy should be for the
                    1970s, and things of that nature, which were not, in my judgement, particularly
                    helpful in resolving the problems at hand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you were the Country Director for Arabian Peninsula
                        states?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Yes. I was very pleased to be transferred from the Policy Planning
                    Council after only a year, back to what I considered my home in the Department,
                    the former Office of Near Eastern Affairs. The office had been abolished and the
                    desks had all been upgraded so I became Country Director for the Arabian
                    Peninsula which included the entire area and, of course, the Persian Gulf
                    states, and Yemen and Muscat, and all the rest of it. So it was a big job and I
                    thoroughly enjoyed being back in operations and having more of an impact, I
                    thought, on day-to-day policy decisions.</p>
                <p>The first thing I did was to go out on a month-long trip to my new area and I was
                    able to circle Arabia by air though even in those days you could not do it
                    entirely by commercial flights. This was 1967. I had to get the Air Attach�
                    plane from Addis Ababa come and it took me from Sharjah to Muscat, and Muscat to
                    Aden. But otherwise...I guess from Aden we flew up to Yemen in an AID aircraft
                    from Yemen. But otherwise they were commercial flights. It was very interesting
                    to see the progress that had taken place in these areas since I had last served
                    in Jeddah and visited Yemen in 1949-1951.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>I don't know how much detail you want me to go into with respect to this
                    assignment. There were a number of things that I think we accomplished in the
                    Arabian Peninsula at this time, particularly with reference to the 1967 Arab-
                    Israeli war, which you remember broke out on June 6th. We were somewhat
                    peripheral to the main contest but we did seek as far as possible to reduce the
                    adverse impact on our position that would come from Saudi Arabia and other oil
                    producing states and might conceivably result in an oil boycott. As you
                    remember, of course, there was no significant oil boycott in 1967. One of the
                    things that I think helped had to do with the evacuation of American citizens
                    from the area because there was great discussion just at the time of the
                    outbreak of hostilities—I think perhaps the day before we knew hostilities were
                    coming—there was great discussion in the Department all during that day—what
                    about the evacuation of Americans from the area, and then what constituted the
                    area, and who should be evacuated. And some of our posts, I think Damascus was
                    one, were very reluctant to see Americans evacuated and as a result no
                    resolution to the problem had been reached by the time we went home about 8:00
                    at night.</p>
                <p>Well, the next morning I came in to work and found a comeback copy of a telegram
                    signed by the Deputy Under Secretary, who at that time was Foy Kohler, sent to
                    all our Near Eastern posts saying all American citizens are to be evacuated. And
                    I thought, “My gosh, what's all this?” Because this had gone among other places,
                    to Kuwait, to Dhahran, to Jeddah, and Aden, and there was no particular reason
                    in most of those posts why Americans should be evacuated. And in fact this would
                    send a signal to the Kuwait government and the Saudi government that we thought
                    the situation was even worse than it was, and we would get them even more upset
                    than they already were if we went ahead and evacuated from these areas. So I
                    said to my boss, “What are we going to do?” And he said, “Why don't you write a
                    telegram to your posts in effect rescinding the circular message. See if you can
                    get Mr. Kohler to sign it?” So I drafted something, I can't remember how I
                    drafted it but the idea was, of course, to avoid directly rescinding the message
                    while in fact getting across the word that nobody had to be evacuated. And I
                    prepared some Byzantine language and took it in to Mr. Kohler and he signed it
                    without batting an eye. Apparently he had simply cut the Gordian knot late the
                    previous night because the White House had gotten on the phone and said, “Look,
                    something has got to be done about this issue. The American people are going to
                    be very upset” or words to that effect. So he just fired off this message and he
                    was happy to have it restricted.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>Now, I should point out as a footnote. We had particular problems in southern
                    Yemen where Aden is located. And we had been debating entirely separate from
                    this whole issue, the desirability of evacuating Americans from Aden but had
                    reached no decision. So I decided that I would send the telegram rescinding the
                    Department's message only to Kuwait, Dhahran and Jeddah, but not to Aden. So, in
                    fact, the Americans were with withdrawn from Aden but I heard later that my
                    telegram arrived in Dhahran just as the first Americans were beginning to pack
                    up and go down to the airfield to get on a plane to get out of Saudi Arabia.
                    And, of course, everybody was very relieved. So I think that kind of action can
                    be extremely helpful in diplomacy and as I have thought about this interview
                    over the last couple of days, it seems to me that if, as, and when I've been
                    able to accomplish anything, it was more likely to be in the area of preventing
                    some bad thing from happening, than in achieving any positive good. But on the
                    other hand if you can prevent something bad from happening, the situation is not
                    made any worse. And that I think was helpful at that time.</p>
                <p>On the positive side, we encouraged the first Washington contacts with the Gulf
                    states other than Kuwait which were we thought probably going to become
                    independent fairly soon. And we arranged for the first state visit of the Ruler
                    of Kuwait to President Johnson. I think it was the final state visit paid to
                    President Johnson. And in general we tried to focus the attention of
                    higher-level people in Washington on the problems and potentialities of this
                    oil-rich region. At the same time I was particularly disturbed as signs mounted
                    that the British, who had had a naval presence in the Persian Gulf for over a
                    hundred years, were probably going to terminate this presence. And this seemed
                    to me entirely unnecessary because the expense was relatively modest—I think
                    they had maybe two frigates under a man with the wonderful name of Snopg
                    (”Snopgee”), the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf—and the expense was not very
                    great. They were doing in fact with mirrors what they had formerly done with
                    real force. So that, it seemed to me, this could be continued and furthermore
                    the various sheikhdoms in the region that were going to become independent were
                    very much interested in the British maintaining some position, since they were
                    nervous about their huge partner to the north, Iran, not to mention to some
                    extent Iraq. And I tried to get the Secretary to focus on this issue, and I
                    think we finally at the last minute did get him to sign—this would have been
                    Secretary Rogers—to sign a message to London saying that he hoped the British
                    would take no decision on this matter before a forthcoming visit of the Foreign
                    Secretary to Washington, which was scheduled for the next week or something like
                    that.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>Well, of course, the British who knew that we would seek to dissuade them from
                    this action naturally took the decision before the Foreign Secretary came to
                    Washington and took it unilaterally and announced they were going to withdraw
                    from the Persian Gulf in 1970. This, therefore, created a vacuum and I have
                    always felt that we could have done more to try and prevent the creation of that
                    vacuum because it would not have taken very much in my judgement to continue the
                    British presence there and it would have been of great assistance in maintaining
                    calm in the region in the 1970s, and I think in all probability preventing, by
                    the presence of the British, things like the Iran-Iraq war from breaking out.
                    But it was a breakdown of a system for regional security which had worked very
                    well in the Persian Gulf for a hundred years. I always regretted that the United
                    States did not take more initiative in trying to prevent this from
                    happening.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bill, we've just about reached the end of our tape, so why
                        don't we stop here and then we will continue with your appointment as
                        Ambassador to Mauritius.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Tape 2, side A</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Interview with Ambassador William D. Brewer. Bill, in 1970
                        you received your appointment as Ambassador to Mauritius. How did that come
                        about? Was it a surprise to you? Did you have any choice, or was that just
                        what you drew?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Well, it wasn't entirely a surprise because I was due for an
                    Ambassadorial assignment, and one or two posts had been suggested and I jumped
                    at the proposal that Mauritius might be the one because I had always heard about
                    Mauritius and I relished the opportunity to be the first Ambassador who would
                    serve in Mauritius. So it did not come as a complete surprise although, of
                    course, I was very pleased. You want me to continue with...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, why don't you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: I did go out to Mauritius in...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: First of all, had you ever been there before? Did you know
                        anything about the place?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>BREWER: No. Well, I knew a little about the place because I had collected stamps
                    as a boy and the Mauritian Penny Blue is the most valuable stamp in the world. I
                    might say, as a sort of digression here, that anyone interested in any kind of
                    international activity as an adult, whether it's the Foreign Service, or
                    international banking, or international business, could do a lot worse than
                    collect stamps, as a boy or girl, as a means of reinforcing his or her
                    understanding of geography. We've been reading in recent days about how
                    knowledge of geography in the United States has become so deplorable, and
                    certainly one of the reasons that my geography was perhaps not bad was because I
                    collected stamps as a kid.</p>
                <p>But in any case, I went out there in June 1970 and found it a wonderful
                    opportunity to set the tone of a relationship because we had not had an
                    Ambassador Resident there previously. The country became independent only in
                    1968 and we had had a series of Charges until my appointment. It was in many
                    ways an idyllic assignment. We had beautiful quarters. It's a lovely island,
                    very similar I'm told to the Hawaiian Islands in character, magnificent beaches,
                    I had a little sailboat, and so on. It was not, of course, in the first rank of
                    concerns of the State Department on policy questions. But there were a couple of
                    issues that were of some significance at that time.</p>
                <p>One of them was the question of Soviet naval penetration of the Indian Ocean and
                    this, I think, was one reason that we were interested in resuming this
                    relationship. And I say resuming advisedly because I found on being assigned to
                    Mauritius that in fact we had had an official relationship with Mauritius from
                    1794 to 1911. We'd had a consulate in Port Louis and we'd had Americans living
                    on the island, we had a very heavy American—in fact, there were more American
                    contacts with Mauritius than with any other area of the African continent except
                    Tangier going back further. This had been completely erased from the collective
                    memory of the State Department because, of course, nothing had happened since
                    just before World War I.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would the whaling ships have had anything to do with
                        this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Oh, yes. The whaling ships did. The Antarctic whaling fleet made Port
                    Louis its headquarters from about 1820-1825 until 1860. And, in fact, in that
                    year the then Consul went to the Mauritian authorities to protest a recent
                    increase in port duties and other charges because if these duties and charges
                    were not rescinded, the American whaling fleet would stop coming. Apparently the
                    Mauritians felt confident that that wouldn't happen, so they said in effect, “We
                    need the revenue, and we're not going to rescind the charges.” So they kept the
                    charges unduly high and the whaling fleet transferred to the Cape. And that was
                    the end of the most significant period of our relationship with Mauritius. So it
                    was very interesting to be able to kind of revive and recall some of these early
                    ties when I got out there.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>With respect to the Russian activity in the Indian Ocean, we also were interested
                    in improving our position in that part of the world. And one of the decisions
                    that was taken about the time I got out there was that we would build an austere
                    naval facility at an atoll—a thousand miles or so south of Ceylon—called Diego
                    Garcia. Diego Garcia used to be part of Mauritius when Mauritius was under the
                    British. It was no longer part of Mauritius but we in the Embassy in Port Louis
                    played a special role in the inauguration of the work on Diego Garcia and in the
                    support of the SeaBees who were up there doing the work during the construction
                    period.</p>
                <p>We had, for example, for one brief period of a couple of months—I think we had an
                    American naval ship a week in Port Louis—and as you may recall from your days as
                    a Consul, when you had a naval visit there was a certain amount of activity. So
                    we were working flat-out on naval visits, and we were assisting them in every
                    way we could. And the thing that was of real assistance was that for the first
                    ship to arrive—you see there was nothing on Diego Garcia, it was a sort of
                    abandoned atoll—the population, that had lived there picking coconuts had been
                    moved off. And so the SeaBees were going to arrive on the beach and start first,
                    I guess, putting up tents or whatever they do. And the question was, where were
                    they going to arrive from. The mother ship sailed from Norfolk, but it was felt
                    that there were not accommodations for all those SeaBees for that long ocean
                    voyage, and the question was where would they be picked up. And I proposed to
                    the Department that they be flown into Mauritius and transferred to the ship and
                    go on from there. The Department, the Bureau of African Affairs, initially
                    reacted very nervously to this. This would maybe upset the non-aligned character
                    of the Mauritian regime and this was something we ought not get involved in. So
                    I cabled, “Why don't we ask the Prime Minister? If he says no, he says no, but
                    what's the objection in raising this?” “Well,” they said, “Okay.” So I went
                    along and had a meeting with Prime Minister Ramgoolam, who was very cooperative.
                    He said, “I don't see any objection to this.” Then he turned to me a little
                    owlishly and said, “You don't think I have to raise this in the full cabinet, do
                    you?” I said, “That's entirely up to you.” I don't think he did. So, in fact, he
                    was probably the only Mauritian official who knew about this. But never mind, we
                    had our clearance and the SeaBees were flown into Plaisance airport, and we made
                    arrangements to transfer them to the port by bus. And they got on the ship and
                    sailed away to Diego Garcia without mishap and no news of this move ever
                    surfaced during my entire time in Port Louis. So it was a very effective first
                    step in the construction of this facility.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>The Mauritian government proved exceedingly hospitable to US navy visits, and
                    this was very encouraging to the Navy at a time when some other ports on the
                    Indian Ocean were raising restrictions because either of the suspicion that they
                    might carry atomic weapons, or simply a non- aligned view on the part of the
                    government of the time in the country concerned. It was very nice to be able to
                    work closely with a government that still recognized its fundamental ties with
                    the west. And we did all we could to improve those ties to the point that the
                    number two man in the government, Veerasamy Ringadoo, we actually sent to the
                    United States to Bethesda Naval Hospital where he had a major heart operation
                    which I believe he thinks extended his life considerably and enabled him to
                    become Prime Minister when old Ramgoolam finally retired. So that this was a
                    concrete way that we could show our appreciation for what the Mauritians were
                    doing to assist us.</p>
                <p>Another thing we did to develop the relationship was to introduce a small Peace
                    Corps operation. I signed the agreement with Prime Minister Ramgoolam, and we
                    brought in a number of units, never very large because, of course, the country
                    was small. We tried to fine-tune these units to the needs of the country. They
                    didn't need much English teaching, for example, but they did need anything which
                    would assist them in economic development. And one of the things we did which
                    seemed helpful at the time I left—I hope it turned out to be helpful—was to get
                    them started on a shrimp industry. Because Europe has an apparently insatiable
                    desire for shrimp and the Mauritians could raise shrimp but at the time we were
                    there, there were few suitable shrimp being farmed around Mauritius. So we got
                    several Peace Corps volunteers in there and they showed them how to build these
                    little ponds where the shrimp could propagate, and then we had a Hawaiian expert
                    fly in from Honolulu escorting five pregnant shrimp—one of which died on the
                    way—but never mind, four arrived intact and each shrimp apparently produces
                    something between 50,000 and 100,000 baby shrimps so that very swiftly you have
                    a substantial shrimp industry. And I went out and inspected it after these young
                    shrimp had been born and were swimming around, and it looked as if this was
                    going to get started and be an effective addition to the development of the
                    country.</p>
                <p>We worked with the Mauritian fisheries people. We also assisted on a number of
                    other projects and we helped Mauritius maintain and I believe slightly enlarge
                    its sugar quota in the United States. This was extremely important to Mauritius
                    because its major output, at that time, was sugar— something like 600,000 tons a
                    year. And there seemed to be no reason why the United States should close off
                    Mauritian sugar as had been at one stage proposed. We encouraged a visit by the
                    chairman of the House Agricultural Committee with, I believe, four of his
                    colleagues and they were wined and dined and I think they left with a favorable
                    impression of Mauritius. And as a result when the bill was voted it included a
                    slight increase for Mauritius and they were absolutely delighted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good. Would you like to continue on that assignment
                        on Mauritius, or should we move on to Sudan?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>BREWER: Well, I might say one or two things about personalities, although I don't
                    want to say very much because the country is very small. The Prime Minister,
                    while I was there, Sir Seewoosagur Ramgoolam, was a short roly-poly man who had
                    begun life as a doctor. He had been one of the first two non-Franco-Mauritians,
                    I think, to leave the country for training in England. And he had gone into
                    politics, he had a natural gift as a politician, and he had become head of the
                    dominant Labor Party. He saw the need to cooperate with the British who, at that
                    time, still ran Mauritius under a Colonial Governor. And he and the British
                    developed a very useful working relationship as the result of which, when the
                    country became independent, there was no difficulty about it whatever, and
                    Ramgoolam became Prime Minister, and his cabinet took over as an independent
                    cabinet. This, I think, might have been a model for a peaceful transfer of
                    authority.</p>
                <p>But there was one interesting thing about the transfer of authority which struck
                    me at the time I was there. You know, of course, the British do not have a
                    written constitution, but one of the things they insist for every colony before
                    it becomes independent is that it have a written constitution because they have
                    to have that document passed through Parliament apparently as a means of
                    constituting the act of independence, you see. So more or less automatically all
                    of the colonies that have become independent wind up with written constitutions
                    which means that thereafter they are much more interested in American principles
                    of judicial review, and following written articles and written constitution,
                    than in the British precedent way of doing things. And I was consulted more than
                    once by the Chief Justice of the Mauritius Supreme Court who wanted to get a
                    case or two from the Supreme Court files because they shed light on some case
                    that was coming up before the Mauritian Supreme Court. This is a little known
                    fact about how our legal system has, without any particular effort on our part,
                    been spread to many areas of the world simply because they now have written
                    constitutions as we do, and therefore go at the same question of judicial review
                    from the same standpoint as we do.</p>
                <p>The role of the British was very modest when I was there but they were still in
                    the background. They still had a significant role with respect to the Special
                    Mobile Force, which was the military force, or a kind of gendarmerie force, on
                    the island. And they still had one or two officials in the Special Branch in a
                    sort of intelligence and advisory role, and they were of assistance on security
                    problems. So the country really did not have much in the way of turbulence. This
                    began to develop during the latter part of my stay when the left-wing MMM
                    (Movement Militant Mauricien) came along under the direction of a number of
                    Hindu politicians and a Franco-Mauritian who had been very much impressed by the
                    student revolt, in France in 1968—he had apparently been a student there and had
                    been very much impressed by the movement to the barricades, etc., and he wanted
                    to carry out this kind of thing in Mauritius. They had some difficulties with
                    the MMM after I left. But I think that perhaps covers Mauritius. It was not a
                    very significant assignment, but a thoroughly enjoyable one and I hope that I
                    helped get our relations off to a good start.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good. Then in 1973 you were assigned as Ambassador to
                        the Republic of the Sudan. Was that a surprise to you again or would you
                        think of that in a kind of...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Well, this was much more of a surprise. I knew, of course, that there was
                    a vacancy because as you know my friend Cleo Noel had been assassinated, and I
                    was not clear whether the Department was going to fill that position or not. But
                    I was ready to leave Mauritius and so when they asked me if I would go to
                    Khartoum, why I thought that was a perfectly appropriate next move. Because
                    although it was in the African Bureau, in fact the Sudan had been part of my
                    parish when I was in charge of Egyptian affairs, and it is an Arab-speaking
                    country. The majority of the population regards itself as Arab, rather than
                    African. So I felt I was returning to the Arab world, and this, I think, perhaps
                    was the reason for my appointment.</p>
                <p>It was, however, a very much different assignment from Mauritius. The climate is
                    unpleasant, it is terribly hot, one is surrounded by desert, the Sudanese are
                    entirely different from the relatively sophisticated Mauritians. It was nice to
                    get back to the Arabic but there were lingering tensions as the result of the
                    assassination of Ambassador Noel and his deputy Curt Moore four months, I think,
                    before my arrival. So it was in every way a difficult but a very challenging
                    assignment.</p>
                <p>The reason I was sent—the reason an Ambassador was sent—was that the Department
                    had decided that the position to take, because of our overall interests in the
                    Sudan, was that we would continue relations on a normal basis on the
                    understanding, which we had been assured was correct by the Sudanese government,
                    that justice would be done to the perpetrators of these assassinations who had
                    been captured by the Sudanese. They were Palestinians, as you know, members of
                    Black September, and were going to be brought to trial, and presumably to be
                    sentenced. And as long as this was being done there didn't seem to be any reason
                    why we should not continue a relatively normal relationship. So that was the
                    basis on which I was sent out.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>However, I remember having a discussion with Assistant Secretary Newsom, I think
                    it was, before I went out. And I said, “Suppose, of course, that something
                    happens with respect to these people?” And we agreed that the first thing that
                    ought to happen is that I should be summoned home for consultation. We would
                    then see what we did. And during the fall, and during the winter we watched the
                    progress of the trial very closely. We had a Sudanese lawyer who was advising us
                    and who was observing the trial— they would not permit officers from the Embassy
                    to be present. And things went normally. I was concerned, however, that in the
                    end President Nimeiri, with whom I had developed a relatively good relationship,
                    would come under tremendous pressure to either pardon the defendants, or somehow
                    commute the sentences, or do something of this kind. And I therefore felt that
                    we had to weigh in with the President personally as soon as the verdicts were
                    announced by the court. And I even prepared a long telegram of instructions to
                    myself which I then sent to the Department and asked for their authority on a
                    contingency basis, because I didn't know how much time we would have to carry
                    out these instructions with the President once the trial court had announced its
                    verdict. Well, we all under-estimated the speed and cleverness of the Sudanese
                    when they wished to act. The Sudanese had indeed decided that they had to do
                    something, that these people represented a hot potato. They did not want their
                    missions abroad subject to attack by Palestinians and all the rest of it. They
                    were on the horns of a dilemma, they didn't want the Palestinians to get away
                    scot free, but on the other hand they really didn't want to hold them in
                    Sudanese jails for extended periods of time. So what they did, obviously
                    carefully coordinated in advance— and one of the things that we didn't do, and I
                    blame myself for this—we did not think that the Sudanese machinery would be
                    capable of doing this at the speed with which it did. I think it went something
                    like this—the trial was concluded in late June, 1974, and a verdict of “guilty”
                    was brought in about 10:00 in the morning. This was then appealed to the Supreme
                    Court. The Supreme Court was convened at about 10:30, and the Supreme Court
                    found in about 30 minutes that they confirmed the sentence which was then
                    referred to the President for ratification, and the President then confirmed the
                    sentence but ordered that it be carried out in Egypt— they having had some
                    contact with the Egyptian government, and the defendants were then put on a
                    plane under escort with a senior man from the Foreign Ministry, and flown to
                    Cairo, all by 2:30 or 3:00 in the afternoon. And we did not hear of this until
                    that evening because everything in the Sudan shuts down about 2:00—they have
                    these long siestas, you see. And the idea of anything like this being done at
                    that hour of the day simply never occurred to anyone. And the Sudanese had
                    obviously acted in order to avoid the type of appeal that I was in fact hoping
                    to be authorized to make.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>So the next thing was that I had to get orders to come home and after some
                    backing-and-forthing with the Department, because Secretary Kissinger, I think,
                    wanted to be personally involved in this, why I did receive instructions to see
                    Nimeiri, and read him the riot act for this action, and then tell him that I was
                    being recalled, and I had no way of predicting when our relationship might be
                    returned to a normal basis. And I can still remember seeing the President. I had
                    great difficulty getting an appointment because, of course, they wished to avoid
                    the appointment, but I insisted and they finally made him available. And I saw
                    him the next morning and he said they simply couldn't face the heat that would
                    be generated if they had hung on to these prisoners. They didn't have the
                    facilities and so forth to protect them. And I said to him that I recalled the
                    motto of President Truman, “If you can't stand the heat, get out of the
                    kitchen”. I said it had been a source of astonishment to me that the Sudanese
                    government, which had been so upright and prided itself on being such a
                    courageous and independent outfit, would take this craven-hearted action after
                    being courageous enough to hold these people for the better part of ten months,
                    and sentence them to seven or eight years, or whatever it was, in jail.</p>
                <p>Well, I don't think he had been well advised by his advisers. I don't know but I
                    have the impression that he had been told that the Americans would make a fuss,
                    but they wouldn't make much fuss, and that this therefore was the thing to do.
                    And I think he was somewhat shaken, and he seemed subdued, by the strong
                    reaction that we had.</p>
                <p>So, anyway, I went home and had a discussion with Secretary Kissinger about where
                    we would go from here in our relations with the Sudanese. And, of course, there
                    were points on both sides. On the one hand the Sudanese had had nothing to do
                    with the original crime. Their only blunder had been that they had handed the
                    defendants, once proclaimed guilty, off to Egypt where the Egyptians were
                    assuring us they were being held in close confinement. I was always a little
                    uncertain about that, but in any case that was the assurance from a regime which
                    was at that time fairly close to us. And it seemed to me that one of the
                    objectives of the Palestinians in staging these assassinations had been
                    precisely to drive a wedge between the United States and the relatively friendly
                    government of President Nimeiri, and I therefore thought that we should do all
                    we could to avoid having a wedge driven between us. And I took that position
                    with Secretary Kissinger, but on the other hand, he pointed out that obviously
                    certain steps had to be taken to show our displeasure, and I fully agreed with
                    that.</p>
                <p>The net result was that we froze the relationship at that point. We cut off any
                    further Export-Import Bank assistance, any prospect of any cultural exchanges,
                    all of the normal things that go into the web of relationships of two states
                    that have good relations. We suspended those, and I was instructed not to return
                    to Khartoum until further notice. And I did, in fact, not return until
                    mid-November of that year so I was away I guess it must have been four
                    months.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>When I got back I then began a campaign slowly, with the Department, to try to
                    get our relations back to normal because it seemed to me that we had certain
                    interests which were important in the Sudan, and that we were to some extent
                    cutting off our nose to spite our face by having ostensibly normal relations, an
                    Ambassador accredited, present and the Embassy functioning, but, at the same
                    time, having all sorts of special niggling bars on the type of exchanges and the
                    type of assistance, and so forth, that could be worked on. And I was concerned
                    that we might be getting into a situation similar to the one I had found in
                    Egypt when I took over the Egyptian desk where we had all these little niggling
                    things set up that I told you about. It didn't seem to me that that was very
                    useful. That is, either you lower the boom, you pull your Ambassador out, you
                    close your Embassy and you say we're going to have nothing to do with you, I
                    mean, you know forget it. Or you make the best of a bad job and you try and work
                    with what you've got and build a positive relationship.</p>
                <p>Well, over time I think I was able to achieve that and one of my proudest
                    achievements is by the time I left the Sudan was that our relations were again
                    very good. We had arranged to have President Ford receive Nimeiri when he made a
                    private visit to the United States. I'd arranged some special functions in
                    Washington while he was there, took him to the Marine barracks to see the
                    Tattoo. He was very pleased with that as a former military man. We introduced a
                    small AID program, it just began to get started but it was something that was
                    coming forward. In their turn they agreed to one or two naval visits that we had
                    over in Port Sudan. We hadn't had any for a long time. In particular, and this
                    is something that I should mention, President Nimeiri and his immediate staff
                    were personally exceedingly helpful to me in my efforts to get the release of
                    ten American hostages who were held over a period of months and even years by
                    the Eritrean Liberation Front in Eritrea. I don't know if this is generally
                    known, but it's not secret. The Eritreans grabbed a number of Americans,
                    presumably to put pressure on the United States Government to end its
                    relationship with the government in Addis Ababa. And, of course, we were
                    reluctant to do that. At the same time this was after the change of government
                    in Addis Ababa and we had very little influence there, at least in my judgement,
                    and therefore the only possibility of getting these people out was to get the
                    Sudanese involved because the Eritreans derive most of their support through the
                    Sudan. I don't believe this necessarily came directly from the Sudanese
                    government, but the Sudanese government either was unable or unwilling to block
                    the support and their supply lines came across the Sudan. So that, to put it
                    very crudely, the Eritreans had a very basic reason to keep the Sudanese
                    government sweet. And I made a very strong pitch to President Nimeiri about the
                    desirability of his playing a role in the release of these American hostages. He
                    obviously agreed and over a period—I forget—it was a long time because these
                    people were captured at various times and held for various periods, but over a
                    period of about a year, I guess, we secured the released of all ten in groups of
                    two or three. And they were all released by the efforts of the Sudanese
                    government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were these people? Were they AID personnel, Peace
                        Corps, or what?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>BREWER: My recollection is that almost all of them were private citizens working
                    for American contractors in Asmara and the area around, but one or two of them,
                    I think, were working for oil companies that were prospecting. But I'm not now
                    sure about all of them. I don't believe any were American officials. But anyway,
                    this also showed that the Sudanese were able and willing to play a useful role.
                    And one reason that I felt we could collaborate with Nimeiri was that Nimeiri
                    had been the architect of the Southern settlement.</p>
                <p>There had been a civil war in Sudan for a dozen years I think almost. And Nimeiri
                    had been the one to end it on the basis of a compromise settlement which
                    permitted considerable autonomy to the South, and there was a Southern regional
                    government, and they had a southern cabinet, and so forth. And in theory this
                    looked like an acceptable way to resolve this long-standing bitterness between
                    the Arab north and the African south. And as long as I was there this worked,
                    and Nimeiri was the glue that held the country together because he was the only
                    Northerner that the Southerners had much use for because the Southerners
                    realized that he had been responsible for this compromise settlement. Now after
                    I left, of course, the whole thing came apart and now we have another civil war
                    apparently going on out there. But during this time the situation improved very
                    much.</p>
                <p>I think there's something else I should say about that period in the Sudan, and
                    that is that while we were developing relatively good relations it seemed clear
                    that the Sudan could not soon develop on an upward track economically. I
                    remember when I first went out there I thought, “this country has absolutely no
                    limit to which it cannot go in economic development.” But it turned out that I
                    was mistaken and I remember my staff advising me saying, “Well, look Mr.
                    Ambassador, everybody arrives with these rosy ideas because the Sudanese have
                    200 million acres of under-used arable land, 90 percent rain fed, and there's no
                    reason they can't turn into the granary of the Third World, etc.” And in theory
                    this is true, but given the hugeness of the area of the country, and the
                    disparity of its people, and the inadequacy of its basic infrastructure, this
                    was simply not likely to occur anytime soon, and, of course has not in fact,
                    occurred. And there were just not the resources available. Certainly not in the
                    Sudan but not outside the Sudan either to come in and build the roads and
                    finance the port development and various other things. Had this occurred, it
                    would have then made investment in agriculture and other schemes really
                    worthwhile. So I think the Sudan still has tremendous potential, but it is going
                    to take an awful long time, and an awful lot of money, and an awful lot of
                    effort before the country can develop.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>One last item of interest about the Sudan has to do with the coup attempt in
                    July, 1976. This was an effort by the Ansar sect, the conservative western
                    Sudanese, many of whom were in exile in Libya, to creep back into Khartoum and
                    capture Nimeiri, and presumably kill him, and take over the government with the
                    support of the Libyan regime of Colonel Qadhafi. And how it came about was that
                    Nimeiri was returning from his private visit to the United States, that I
                    mentioned. He had stopped off in London, and I had returned directly so I was
                    back in Khartoum to greet him on his return and he was arriving—let us say at
                    6:00 in the morning. About 11:00 p.m. the night before I was called by the
                    Foreign Office to say that Nimeiri would actually be arriving at 5:00. And I've
                    always wondered whether this reflected some knowledge that they'd picked up, or
                    not, and I don't know. But in any case, he came in early and we were unclear
                    whether he was going to go to his home or simply stay at the airfield and then
                    go on because we did know he was leaving later that day to go on to either India
                    or Ceylon for a meeting, I think it was the non-aligned group. So we met him,
                    and I had a little conversation, and he then disappeared into the V.I.P. lounge
                    to give an interview to the Sudanese press. And we waited outside and after five
                    minutes I said to the head of the Foreign Office, “Well now, are we supposed to
                    stay here until the President leaves?” “Oh,” he said to me, “He's already left.”
                    Well, I was sort of astonished because he must have gone out the back way. And I
                    then returned to my car and on the way back to the car I heard what sounded like
                    celebratory shots, or perhaps fireworks, coming from the direction of Khartoum
                    itself. And I thought, well the Nimeiri partisans are going all out to welcome
                    their leader back after his visit. And when I got to the car my driver said, “I
                    think we're having a coup d'etat.” And I said, “Well, let's drive by the General
                    Staff Headquarters (which was near my residence), and this will give us an
                    idea.” And he said, “all right.” So we drove by there, and things seemed pretty
                    quiet, but as we drew abreast of the General Headquarters...</p>
                <p>—Tape 2, Side B.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>BREWER: As I was saying, when we drew abreast of the General Headquarters there
                    was this fusillade of shots, and I said to the driver, “You're quite right,
                    there is a coup d'etat. Let's go back to the residence as quickly as we can.”
                    And this inaugurated three days of street fighting in Khartoum which reminded me
                    of nothing so much as World War II. Files of troops crept down by the walls of
                    buildings, and opened fire at buildings across the street and this kind of
                    thing. We kept the Embassy open and some spent the nights there because they
                    didn't want to risk going back and forth to their homes, but I preferred to
                    sleep in my bed so I did go back and forth using back roads and trying to avoid
                    anything that might draw fire. We did have a couple of shots but fortunately no
                    damage. The final day of the coup as it was winding down, one of the
                    dissidents—and there turned out to be about a thousand of these people who had
                    infiltrated into Omdurman from Libya across the desert with their weapons, and
                    they had captured the radio station, and captured some of the other facilities
                    and virtually captured the airfield which was only about a block from where my
                    residence was—fortunately the Sudanese reacted very swiftly and Nimeiri went
                    into hiding so they were unable to find him. There was a rumor later around
                    Khartoum that he left the airfield in the American Ambassador's car. That was
                    not the case, as I say, he slipped out the door but I think he must have had
                    some advance word that something unfortunate was brewing. So he got out of the
                    way and at the end of it one of the last of the dissidents got on the roof of
                    our building because we were next to a hotel and he was able to come across the
                    roofs, and he fired a shot at the government troops from the roof of the
                    Embassy. We had the top two floors of a downtown office building, and I always
                    thought that he did this on purpose to draw fire on the Embassy. And whether he
                    did it on purpose or not, that's exactly what happened and the first thing I
                    knew I saw this line of troops drawn up across the street and leveling their
                    guns at my window and I got out of the way just in time, and this fusillade of
                    shots crashed out and broke most of the windows and the glass flew all over the
                    place. And they fired again a couple of times and I don't think that they
                    realized what they were firing at. I think they thought they were trying to get
                    this character who'd just fired a shot from the roof. Fortunately we had no
                    casualties, although there was a good amount of broken glass, and the government
                    forces proceeded to take over.</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>Our support for Nimeiri continued unabated during this time and one of the ways
                    it was shown was legitimate, but also amusing. The Sudanese government had the
                    very nice custom of permitting a Chief of Mission to record a message on radio
                    and television to the Sudanese people which would be broadcast on that country's
                    national day. And they'd asked me if I wished to do that, and I had said, yes.
                    So I had gone over to the studio in Omdurman in June and recorded a message to
                    the Sudanese people which was to be played on July 4. Well, the Sudanese did not
                    recapture the radio and television station until about noon on July 4th, and the
                    first message to come across it about 3:00—and, of course, everybody was home
                    because we had a curfew imposed, nobody was permitted to move in town, and so
                    on, and most diplomats were simply sitting by their radios and TVs trying to
                    figure out what was going on—the first message was from Nimeiri himself, saying
                    that he was all right and everything was under control, and the situation had
                    returned to normal which wasn't quite true but it was getting there. But the
                    next message that appeared was my Fourth of July message, and my colleagues all
                    greeted me afterwards with due respect because they said it must have taken
                    great courage to go over there so soon after the radio station had been relieved
                    to deliver this message. And I couldn't resist, I sort of said, “Well, you know,
                    it's all in the line of duty.” But obviously the Sudanese government broadcast
                    that message on purpose in order to give the impression, which they did, that
                    the United States Government strongly supported the Nimeiri regime, as in fact
                    we had during this failed coup and we completely opposed any attempt by Qadhafi
                    to interfere in the internal affairs of a neighboring country, which is what he
                    had tried to do. Fortunately he had failed.</p>
                <p>So, I think as I said, by the time I left the Sudan that the combination of our
                    efforts and Sudanese efforts, had put our relationship—our bilateral
                    relationship—on a very good basis and we were starting on a phase of very close
                    and mutually beneficial collaboration. And I felt very good about that when I
                    left for home in 1977.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good. A question comes to mind. Shortly thereafter
                        you retired from the Foreign Service. Was there any chance of your being
                        offered another Chief of Mission post, or would you have accepted one, or
                        had you made up your mind to retire?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Well, I hadn't made up my mind to retire, but I had already had two Chief
                    of Mission assignments, and I consider myself very fortunate to have had them.
                    So I did not really expect another one immediately. It might have been that I
                    might have had one, I was considered for another assignment but that didn't work
                    out. But for a variety of reasons, I began to think that maybe I'd had enough.
                    My tour had been very hard on my wife and family, and so on. If the Service had
                    offered me a very attractive assignment, I probably would have taken it, but in
                    the circumstances I figured it was time for me to retire, and I was happy to
                    find other employment which I found very interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That certainly is interesting and you've certainly had a
                        very rewarding and interesting career. Before we close, I would like to ask
                        you a couple of general questions, which I think are interesting. It has
                        often been said that members of the Foreign Service, particularly those who
                        served in the Near East, tend to be biased towards the Arab world as far as
                        the Arab-Israeli problem is concerned. Do you think there is any truth in
                        that charge. You've certainly spent years in the Arab world.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Yes, I did, and I think that's one of the vilest canards that has been
                    foisted on the American public in a long time. The fact of the matter is that
                    many of us Arabist have reason to mistrust the Arabs more than other Americans
                    because we have served among them. Some of us have been mistreated by them. As
                    you may recall, I left Syria under a cloud because I was accused of having had a
                    hand in the murder of the Syrian Deputy Chief of Staff. This was, of course,
                    nonsense but nevertheless this was the attitude of some Syrians. So there is no
                    particular reason for American officers to develop a very friendly relationship
                    with Arabs. Some of them have, of course, but this shorthand which goes around
                    Washington, and around the country, that if you served in an Arab country, and
                    if you speak Arabic, and if you put forward a view which is different from the
                    view that friends of Israel would suggest, that this must be the Arab view
                    rather than an American view, I mean this is absolute nonsense. The fact of the
                    matter is that most of my friends had their difficulties in the Arab world at
                    various times, usually as a result of American policy toward Israel. And our
                    proposals, and what we advocated as our policy, was put forward perhaps
                    erroneously, perhaps we were wrong but out of a firm belief, which I continue to
                    hold, that this is in the interest of the Government of the United States. It
                    may also be of assistance, in certain cases, to some Arab countries but that is
                    incidental. What is important is what are the United States' interests in that
                    part of the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well said. I couldn't agree more. During our interview you
                        several times mentioned the importance of communications. Would you like to
                        elaborate on that theme a bit?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>BREWER: Well I would because I think, particularly in this age, communication
                    seems to be downgraded. We all of us get these printout letters which appear to
                    have been hit by the charwoman in the middle of the night and there is no
                    indication that human eye has ever seen any of this stuff. It is important to
                    bear in mind what can be done with communications, and the Foreign Service,
                    during my period of years with it, was above anything else an organ of
                    communication. You had to be able to communicate in writing, both from the field
                    to Washington, and in Washington to the Secretary and the President, and if you
                    couldn't get your ideas on paper concisely and clearly, and speedily, you were
                    not going to be around very long. And in addition to being concise and clear and
                    fast, one also learned that communication can be turned to one's advantage. For
                    example—there are many examples—but people don't realize that how one phrases
                    something is extremely important. But if an Ambassador sends a message saying,
                    “I would like to be instructed to do so and so, please advise.” He is then
                    stopped from any action on that issue until he gets a reply to his message.
                    Whereas, if he sends a message saying, “I am planning to see the Foreign
                    Minister the day after tomorrow, and will make to him the following points—l, 2,
                    3, 4, 5—unless the Department objects,” you have then in effect written your own
                    instructions, and if you have not had a reply—you allow time, of course, for
                    there to be a reply—if you've had no reply, you've had your instructions and you
                    go ahead. And, of course, what you do is you will get a reply. You usually, in
                    my experience, get a very short reply saying, “Department approves line you
                    propose taking.” Because the man in Washington, who is very busy and very
                    harried, has just had some of his work done for him by having you write your own
                    instructions. But you haven't done it in a way which then leaves the ball in
                    Washington's court. Washington has got to respond, and got to respond very
                    promptly because you have said you were going to take this line in 48 hours, or
                    whatever it is, with the Foreign Minister.</p>
                <p>So this does not just apply in Foreign Service, but in a lot of lines of work.
                    How you cast your requests has a good deal to do with what you are permitted to
                    do thereafter. And I think that message is one that needs repeating in this day
                    and age when the art of communications appears to be eroding rapidly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I agree, and I think this is something that the Foreign
                        Service Institute could well pay more attention to.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Well perhaps if they are not—I'm not familiar with the curriculum of the
                    Institute right now, but certainly if they are not doing so, they should,
                    because it is very important. And incidentally, it was something the Institute
                    did not pay much attention to when I went through the Institute, but I did learn
                    it from some of my Chiefs, particularly Ambassador Hare and Ambassador Moose,
                    both of whom were brought up in the old school of drafting, knew the value of
                    words and would spend a great deal of time working with junior officers to train
                    them to draft correctly and concisely.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good. One final question, Bill, before we close our
                        interview. Given your experience and your many, many years in the Foreign
                        Service, would you recommend a Foreign Service career to your children or
                        anybody else's?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Well, I would not proselytize, on the other hand if someone came to me
                    and said, “I'm really dying to get into the Foreign Service, what do you think
                    of the idea?” I don't think I would seek to discourage that individual because
                    certainly the Service and the country needs good people. I do think, however,
                    that the Service is not as attractive a place in which to serve as it was when
                    you and I were officers. Because I think essentially what has happened over the
                    years, as a result both of actions by Department administrators, and by the
                    Congress, and by various Administrations, what you have had have been measures
                    which smack of pulling up the flower to see whether it's blooming. And
                    modifications have been made in the way the Department has administered, you
                    know, the number of classes, the time in class, what you can expect after such-
                    and-such assignment, and all of this, and to me this is ridiculous. You ought to
                    leave that sort of thing alone and you ought to take the attitude with critics,
                    if there are any of the Foreign Service, that the Foreign Service is doing a
                    pretty good job and let us get on with it, rather than to introduce some new
                    modification, at considerable trouble and expense, which then gets everybody
                    confused as to how things ought to be done in the future.</p>
                <p>I'm much more a partisan of the system which, I believe is the basis of the
                    British Foreign Service, namely: make the entrance examinations as tough as you
                    want. People who are successful in passing those exams, young people of both
                    sexes, are going to be so highly qualified that thereafter you can assume that
                    80 percent of them, say, ought to go to the top of the Service, and ought to
                    wind up as Chiefs of Mission. And this business of periodic attrition, you know,
                    selection out, keeping the pyramid very precise, introducing lateral entrants
                    for particular roles, all of this is to my mind foreign to the development of a
                    really first rate Foreign Service. And I was very sorry to see these steps
                    introduced, and if I could wave a wand and do anything about it, I would like to
                    see them rescinded.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fine. Well, unless you have any other comments, I think
                        this closes our interview. I want to thank you very much for, to me at
                        least, what has been an extremely interesting experience.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BREWER: Thank you, Malcolm, for taking the trouble to interview me. It has been a
                    pleasure to go over some of these things and I appreciate your input.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
