<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001280">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Gordon Winkler </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Information Series</p>
                <p>GORDON WINKLER</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Dorothy Robins Mowry </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: March 23, 1989</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Gordon, we'd like to hear something about your education
                        and your background and any of the professional developments after your
                        education which finally led you to join the Agency.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Bio-Sketch</p>
                <p>WINKLER: Dorothy, I was born in Chicago and raised there and in Los Angeles. I
                    went into the Army Air Corps in World War II, and flew bombing missions in B-24s
                    out of Italy. I had been at the University of Illinois for about a semester
                    prior to going into the Air Corps, and decided I wanted to go somewhere else
                    when I came out. I went to Dartmouth, majored in English, worked on the daily
                    student newspaper, The Dartmouth, and felt I wanted to go into the newspaper
                    field.</p>
                <p>When I got back to Chicago, after graduating, I went to work for the City News
                    Bureau of Chicago. The City News Bureau was owned by all of the Chicago
                    papers—there were four or five of them in those days, and the Associated Press.
                    It was a citywide wire service which backed up the coverage of the newspapers
                    and the AP and also trained newspaper people. After a couple of years at City
                    News, I went to work for the Chicago Tribune as a reporter.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately, in those days, journalists, particularly beginning journalists,
                    were paid what I recall as being the minimum wage or less, and I simply could
                    not afford the luxury of being a journalist. I was married during the period
                    that I was at the Tribune.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Whom did you marry?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I married a Chicago girl by the name of Margaret Mayer, who was at
                    Radcliffe when I met her. She left Radcliffe after a couple of years to get
                    married, but she continued her education overseas when we were in Ethiopia. She
                    attended courses at Haile Selassie University, and also took courses at other
                    posts.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>I left the Tribune after three years and took a job with a public relations firm
                    in Chicago. I was in the PR field there for about 11 years. I worked for two
                    different agencies doing financial public relations, product publicity, trade
                    association PR, and corporate public relations.</p>
                <p>Entrance Into USIA</p>
                <p>When John Kennedy became President, there was a kind of excitement throughout the
                    country. My public relations work took me to New York a great deal and to
                    Washington, D.C., about three or four times a year. The atmosphere in Washington
                    and elsewhere those early Kennedy years was terribly alive—the whole idea of
                    government service was positive in a way which it has never been since.
                    Kennedy's inaugural address made a lot of people think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Everybody remembers the excitement.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes, it was very exciting in Washington, and a number of very good
                    people from Chicago, a number whom I knew, came to Washington to take jobs. I
                    guess I kind of got the bug. I was also getting a bit fed up with commercial
                    public relations and the hand-holding of clients.</p>
                <p>I had no idea what I might be suited for in government. I knew nothing about
                    government service. I went to the Chicago Public Library and got some books. I
                    had no thought of going overseas; I wanted to go to work in Washington. But I
                    came across something about this outfit called the U.S. Information Agency, and
                    it looked like it was populated basically by PR and newspaper types. I thought
                    maybe it might be interesting to get a job there for a few years and go
                    overseas.</p>
                <p>So I called a friend by the name of Bill Rivkin, who had been very close to
                    Hubert Humphrey and had been appointed by Kennedy as Ambassador to Luxembourg. I
                    asked him if he knew anybody at USIA, and he said yes, he knew Don Wilson, who
                    was Ed Murrow's deputy in those days. He arranged an appointment for me with
                    Wilson, who thought that there were possibilities, and turned me over to Lionel
                    Mosley, the Chief of Personnel, who was one of the great figures, I thought, in
                    USIA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I agree with you. I think “Mose” really understood,
                        indeed.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>WINKLER: Mosley set up a panel interview for me on my next visit to Washington,
                    and said, “If your wife happens to be with you in Washington, bring her in for
                    the interview.” That would hardly happen today, but I figured that Peggy would
                    certainly be helpful to me. So I brought her along. The chairman of the panel, a
                    three-person panel, was Ned Roberts, who was then the area director for Africa.
                    I really didn't know much about the world, but with Peggy's help, I got by, or
                    we both got by. This was in the days when they took you in as a Foreign Service
                    limited reserve officer. I think I had a three- or a five-year appointment, and
                    then they could throw me out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's how I came in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1963 Initial Assignment: Addis Ababa</p>
                <p>WINKLER: Roberts said, “Look, we'd like to have you, but we can't hire you until
                    we have an opening for you.” So they went through the whole security
                    investigation. As that was winding up, I got a call from Roberts, and he said,
                    “I'd like you to think about the possibility of being information officer in
                    Addis Ababa.” That was probably the second time I'd ever heard about Addis
                    Ababa. The first being when Mussolini marched in there in the mid-1930s. Well, I
                    held my breath about that for a few days, and discussed it with my family. We
                    had three little boys, and we were living in a suburb of Chicago, but we decided
                    to pick up and go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A big adventure!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: It was a big adventure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Kind of crazy, but a big adventure.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: It was kind of crazy. I quit my job, and in September of 1963, I came to
                    Washington for two and a half or three months of orientation. Peggy and the kids
                    stayed in Glencoe, Illinois, and closed out the house. This was a task that
                    Peggy repeated in a number of posts where she had that kind of onerous
                    responsibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is always one of the joys of a wife in the Foreign
                        Service. She's always sort of left behind for a period of time to pick up
                        the pieces.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Right. So we left just before Christmas of 1963, spent Christmas in
                    Paris and New Year's in Rome, and arrived in Addis Ababa about the fourth or
                    fifth of January.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any language training?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: No language at all. Really, no one was trained. I had a fair amount of
                    Spanish in both high school and college, but I really couldn't handle it. Peggy
                    spoke French before she spoke English, because she and her sisters had a Swiss
                    nurse. Her French is quite good. But as far as the Ethiopian language, Amharic,
                    is concerned, maybe one officer in the embassy was trained in that, and some of
                    the Peace Corps volunteers, but nobody in USIS had it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was it like in Ethiopia at that time? This was in
                        January 1964. It was still under Haile Selassie?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: It was still under Haile Selassie. I keep relating my recollections
                    about Ethiopia to my recollections of my last post, which was Iran, because
                    there was a great deal of similarity in the political atmosphere. In both cases,
                    the United States was as close to being the metropole as is possible with an
                    historically independent country. These were countries that had been independent
                    for centuries, although, parenthetically, the Iranians might say that they
                    hadn't been that independent, given British and Russian influence in the country
                    since the past century.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Maybe longer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Maybe longer. But technically, they had been independent. But the United
                    States really had a very, very powerful influence and role to play in both of
                    those countries in the modern era—that is, since World War II.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How had the U.S. come to play such a role in Ethiopia? I
                        would have thought more the Italians.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: The Italians had been in Italian Somaliland, and they had been in
                    northern Ethiopia—Eritrea. It had been an Italian colony; the principal city is
                    Asmara. Following the war, Eritrea became an Ethiopian province, but never a
                    comfortable one. The Eritrean liberation movement was going on when we arrived
                    in 1964, and it is still going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I saw a bumper sticker this morning about Eritrea. “Free
                        Eritrea” or “Always Free Eritrea,” something to that effect.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Anti-American Feeling In Ethiopia</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>WINKLER: Our interests, to a large degree, in Ethiopia were military. We had a
                    very substantial communications facility in Asmara, at a base called Kagnew
                    Station. That, to a considerable degree, was a thorn in the side of many
                    Ethiopians, particularly young Ethiopians. But in comparing those two countries,
                    while we did hear in Ethiopia a considerable amount of criticism about the U.S.
                    role and we were conscious of anti-Americanism, it wasn't quite as clear and as
                    sharply defined as it was in Iran. I think it was just as strong, but I suppose
                    it relates to the character of the people and their culture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would it have to do with literacy and media?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: There were a lot of very literate Ethiopians; there was a media
                    presence. Newspapers were fairly rudimentary, but as in Iran, there were many
                    Ethiopians who were American-educated or European-educated. There was still the
                    connection, to a degree, with Italy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's an asset.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. We would hear criticisms about the United States role in the
                    country, but not quite as sharply as we would in Iran, because Ethiopians are
                    somewhat more reserved, less direct, less forthright. Iranians, as you know, are
                    not direct in the Anglo-Saxon sense, but Ethiopians are even less so. At the
                    same time we had close Ethiopian friends, and the country is beautiful. We lived
                    right in Ethiopian neighborhoods.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There wasn't an enclave?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Happily, there was no enclave. We could look out of our bedroom window
                    on the second floor of our house and see the neighbors defecating in their yard,
                    but that's the way it was, that's the nature of the town, and we got used to it.
                    There was a primitiveness, a considerable primitiveness when you got out into
                    the countryside, but the country was spectacular.</p>
                <p>Ostentatious Haile Selassie Banquet</p>
                <p>There was a huge dichotomy between the poor and the wealthy, which is standard,
                    of course, in most of the developing world. But in Ethiopia it was particularly
                    startling. I recall being invited to a huge dinner when Queen Elizabeth and
                    Prince Philip visited the Emperor, and the dinner was in a monumental dining
                    room about the size of a football field under a kind of straw roof. There must
                    have been 1,000 people invited to that. I obviously was way below the salt.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A guest of Haile Selassie?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: A guest of Haile Selassie. I'll never forget the beautiful china, the
                    magnificent crystal, the very costly silverware and linens on this absolutely
                    huge banquet table that seemed to go on for city blocks. The basic Ethiopian
                    drink is a honey mead called tej which I found to be cloyingly sweet. At the
                    banquet, there was crystal for about six or seven kinds of tej.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I bet it's very potent after a while.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I never drank that much of it, but this tej was good. The palace tej was
                    dry. I recall that every two guests at this banquet had a liveried butler or
                    waiter standing behind him or her in an 18th century costume—it may have been
                    satin. So the service was very good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is how it is at the palace in London, as I understand
                        it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Haile Selassie didn't want the Queen to feel homesick. The greatest
                    fireworks display I've ever seen followed the dinner.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did Haile Selassie's money come from? Was there
                        wealth in the country or land? Was it agriculturally viable those days?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: In those days, it was very agriculturally viable, but underdeveloped.
                    The country had terribly rich soil. In recent years they've had droughts.
                    They've had periodic droughts throughout history, but it would rejuvenate
                    itself. As in many developing countries, high-level corruption was rampant.
                    There was great wealth in the Coptic Church, which owned a huge amount of land,
                    probably most of the land. The country desperately needed land reform and tax
                    reform and never really had it. We were also putting in, of course, substantial
                    amounts of money through a very big military advisory group and an AID program.
                    An awful lot of Americans were there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you meet and encounter Haile Selassie? What kind of a
                        person was he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I never had a conversation with Haile Selassie. We were invited to the
                    palace as part of the diplomatic corps on a number of occasions, and I was
                    introduced to him and shook hands with him. He was a dignified, very small man,
                    who always had at his feet, or sitting on his lap, one or two Chihuahua dogs, or
                    Pomeranians.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is this where the stories come from about the lions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: We had horses there, and we used to ride several times a week. When we
                    would ride around the palace, I was often unnerved in seeing a lion sitting by
                    himself on top of the palace wall, and wonder if the lion was hungry! They told
                    a story about Kwame Nkrumah, who was the first president of Ghana, visiting
                    Haile Selassie, and as he was ushered into the palace by the Ghanaian
                    ambassador, he saw Haile Selassie seated at his throne with a couple of lions
                    walking around in the throne room, and the Ghanaian ambassador said, “Mr.
                    President, just ignore the lions or pet them.” Nkrumah is supposed to have said,
                    “You're out of your mind. I know better. I'm an African.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was, after all, your first post. You were the
                        information officer for the embassy. How was the transition from the private
                        sector, where, in effect, you were an information officer into the
                        government? Was it an easy transition for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes, it was. I think I was selling a better product in Ethiopia than I'd
                    been selling. There was an awful lot to do. We didn't seem to have funding
                    problems. We had enough money to spend. I had developed a habit in the private
                    sector—one had to—to work very hard and work very long hours.</p>
                <p>Access To Ethiopian Press</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were dealing primarily with the print media?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: With the print media and broadcast. Television came in while we were
                    there. Of course, all the media was government media. There was no private
                    media. We could get editorials written, and we could get a great deal of
                    material into the papers. The editors, though, were not patsies for us. Many of
                    the editors were European or American-educated. They often looked upon us with a
                    jaundiced eye. We had to become friendly with them. I saw an awful lot of them
                    socially and professionally.</p>
                <p>There was one fellow who went to Boston University, by the name of Tegegne
                    Yetashework. He was editor of the Ethiopian Herald when I was there. We became
                    very close. He'd come over to our house three or four nights a week, and sit
                    down at the dinner table with us—not to eat, but to have a glass of orange juice
                    and chew the fat and be with us and our kids.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>I'll never forget, when we sent Marines into the Dominican Republic, which must
                    have been 1964-65, I heard it on the VOA, went to the office, and got a call
                    about 10:00 in the morning from Tegegne. He said, “Come on over to the office if
                    you've got a little time. Let's have a cup of coffee.”</p>
                <p>So I went over there and we sat at a little sidewalk cafe outside of his office,
                    and he bought me a cup of coffee. He said, “This has nothing to do with your job
                    or my job, but I'm terribly disturbed. Tell me when I'm going to see American
                    Marines coming up that street.” I said I didn't think he would. They never have.
                    But I relate this anecdote because it was things like this, events like this in
                    various parts of the world, that concerned people about the U.S.</p>
                <p>Tegegne later became assistant minister of information. One morning in Iran, Peg
                    and I were at the breakfast table, and she was reading one of the Iranian
                    papers, which headlined the fact that in Ethiopia, the new regime which had
                    thrown out Haile Selassie, had taken 60 people out and shot them. The Iranian
                    paper listed the names, and Tegegne was one of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any censorship in that kind of a totalitarian
                        state? I don't know how totalitarian that was in comparison with Iran.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: It was totalitarian, as Iran was. There was an absolute monarch in both
                    places. There was a kind of self-censorship. The editors knew what they could
                    run and what they couldn't run. There was a weakly enforced Third Country rule,
                    which you're familiar with. They wouldn't take anything from the Russians that
                    knocked us, and they wouldn't take anything from us that knocked the Russians.
                    But in those days, the Russians really didn't amount to much in Ethiopia. They
                    had a small cultural center and library—a place to play chess—which was usually
                    empty. I walked through there a number of times. But the USIS post was very,
                    very busy, and we had an excellent library. For a country of that size, we had a
                    pretty substantial staff. We had seven Americans and about 35 Ethiopians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the PAO?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: The first PAO was a very able fellow by the name of Glen Smith, who had
                    some problems with the ambassador, who was a terribly interesting guy by the
                    name of Ed Korry. It was simply bad chemistry. Both men were quite talented.
                    After two years, Smith left and was transferred to Cyprus. I became acting PAO
                    for about six months, and then Eugene Rosenfeld, who had been PAO in Dar es
                    Salaam, and whom Korry knew from newspaper days, was sent in. The Rosenfelds and
                    the Winklers became very close, and still are. We coincidentally now live across
                    the street from each other. Influence Of Coptic Church In Ethiopia</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How very nice. These associations that you develop
                        overseas, there's nothing really quite comparable. I have one other question
                        about Ethiopia. I just wondered to what degree the Coptic Church was a force
                        of the sort that Islam is in Iran, in view of your own comparisons
                        here.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: The Coptic Church was a very substantial force in Ethiopia. I was much
                    more conscious of the religion in Ethiopia than I was of the religion in Iran,
                    believe it or not. Maybe that was one of our problems in Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was there during the year in which the religious fervor
                        escalated and the revolution finally broke out. It was a tremendous
                        escalation of religious power.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: We were, to a degree, in touch with the church in Ethiopia. There were a
                    few church leaders who were sent to the States by USIS on leader grants. There
                    was no restriction whatsoever by the palace on American contacts with the
                    church. A fundamental problem in Ethiopia was that very few of the church
                    leaders spoke anything but Amharic, and virtually none of us had the language.
                    There is something of an excuse for that, because it is one of the most
                    difficult languages in the world. It's just a frightfully hard language. The
                    church was a force. As in Iran before the White Revolution, the Ethiopian church
                    owned a tremendous amount of land, just as the Mosques owned a vast amount of
                    the land in Iran. So I guess there were similarities. But the revolution did not
                    come out of the church. It's a very fundamentalist kind of religion, Coptic
                    Christianity, and Ethiopia is one of the principal seats of it. But the
                    revolution came from other quarters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had two tours in Ethiopia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: No, I had two and a half years in Addis. Then I was assigned as public
                    affairs officer in Accra.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went home in between?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. We arrived in Accra in the summer of 1966, about four months after
                    the revolution there. Nkrumah was thrown out in February of 1966 and went to
                    Guinea for most of the rest of his life. Q: Did you request another African
                    post?</p>
                <p>Competition Between U.S. Embassies In Africa Winkler Case In Point—Addis Ababa
                    And Mogadishu Differences</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>WINKLER: No, but it was almost assured. I might say that one of the things,
                    getting back to Ethiopia for a minute, that surprised me about the management of
                    American diplomacy overseas was the seeming competition between American
                    embassies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean from one country to the other?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. During the period that we were there, Somali irredentism was at its
                    height. There was a lot of shooting in the Ogaden desert, a territory which the
                    Somalis felt belonged to them, and where Somali herders were grazing their
                    flocks. The Ethiopians felt it belonged to them. So this battle was going on
                    constantly, and continues to this day.</p>
                <p>I early got into the habit of going to the embassy at the end of the day and
                    reading the traffic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: USIS was in a separate building?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: We were in a separate building. We were downtown, about four or five
                    miles from the embassy. It was amazing to me how our embassy, which was under
                    the direction of Ed Korry, was at odds in its cable reporting to Washington,
                    with the embassy in Mogadishu, which, as I recall, was headed, I believe, by an
                    ambassador by the name of Thurston. I had the feeling, as a fledgling in the
                    Foreign Service, that here were two American embassies that were defending the
                    views of the countries they were in. It seemed to me they both often strayed
                    from coldly objective reporting on this very contentious issue between Ethiopia
                    and Somalia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we have a strong policy coming out of Washington on
                        the subject, or was it all sort of a locally developed reaction?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: My recollection is that we probably didn't, that our policy was, “This
                    is a local problem. Watch it.” U.S. interests in Ethiopia were, of course,
                    substantially more significant than in Somalia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they reported it differently?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: They reported it differently, and regularly contradicted each other in a
                    way that, on the one hand, the embassy in Mogadishu seemed to defend Somali
                    views as though it totally accepted these views, and our embassy, often did
                    likewise vis � vis Ethiopia.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they hadn't done their own research, either one of
                        them. Who was the head of the African Bureau at State, do you remember?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: “Soapy” Williams.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, that was the period for “Soapy”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes, this was the period when Africa was “hot.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, it was just really coming.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Africa was the place to be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Kennedy had come into power. Nkrumah had achieved independence in 1957
                    or '58, in Ghana, and that was the first country. Then they all began to get
                    independence. This was about ten or twelve years after India and Pakistan became
                    independent. While we were in Ethiopia, I recall Kenya, Tanzania, Uganda,
                    Zambia, Malawi, and others became independent. Nigeria had it before.</p>
                <p>Williams and Kennedy had decided that any sovereign state would have an American
                    embassy, and, I might add parenthetically, whether it needed it or not, or,
                    importantly, whether we needed it or not. But we had them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was only later they began to double up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: We still have them, whether we need them or not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now we double up a little bit, don't we?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: We don't double up. When I was African Area Director in the early 1970s,
                    I recall we had one ambassador covering those three countries around South
                    Africa, Botswana, Lesotho, and Swaziland. Now we've got an ambassador in each of
                    those countries. I don't know whether you've ever visited Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No. Africa is one of the blanks in my geography.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Disappointment Of Western Hopes For Newly Independent African Nations</p>
                <p>WINKLER: There was tremendous hope for Africa. Africa was terribly exciting, a
                    wonderful place to be. There was hope among the Africans. They had achieved
                    independence. There was a considerable amount of American aid coming in. There
                    was aid coming in from all over Europe. The Scandinavians were big donors. The
                    PRC was in, doing wonderful agricultural work. The Israelis also were doing
                    wonderful agricultural work. The PRC and Israelis were in there fundamentally
                    because of the U.N. votes the Africans had. The Peace Corps was there. Working
                    in a country at the beginning period of the Peace Corps was just marvelous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was such a joy, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: You'd go out into the bush, and there was no place to stay in Ethiopia
                    but in some hovel that a Peace Corps volunteer occupied. You'd take your
                    sleeping bag and you'd sleep on the wooden floor of his little cottage. They had
                    great verve and there was much excitement. The Peace Corps also has changed a
                    great deal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's somehow very sad that Africa has declined so terribly
                        in terms of just general morale and capacity. Have you any notions? There
                        was no sense of this in either one of your two posts?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: When the British left Ghana in Nkrumah's hands in 1957, it's my
                    recollection that the Ghanaian treasury had about $8 billion. When Nkrumah was
                    thrown out in 1966, nine years later, Ghana was about that much in debt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this sheer incapacity?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Literacy was low. There was very little understanding of work. There was
                    the whole problem of tribalism which overlaid everything. If the minister was of
                    one tribe, the people hired for his ministry would be of his tribe, whether they
                    were able or not, by and large. There was no escape from that. He had to do that
                    because they were part of his extended family.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's part of the culture of Africa.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: It's part of the culture. The culture demanded it. They were
                    fundamentally agricultural people, and the cities attracted them. They rushed to
                    the cities, and the urban areas couldn't handle them.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you were there before the urban problems began?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: The urban problems were certainly occurring in Ghana and in Nigeria and
                    other parts of Africa during my contact with Africa. People were rushing to the
                    cities. Education, to some degree, began to develop. The British, of course,
                    left universities and left preparatory schools.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They always leave the structure there, don't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. But then it was taken over by Africans, and they suddenly came upon
                    self-rule and all the possibilities for growth and didn't handle it well. There
                    was infrastructure in some of the countries, but there simply were not enough
                    people prepared to take over—and the possibilities for corruption were very
                    seductive. Here I am generalizing, of course. Some countries—such as the Ivory
                    Coast—did fairly well. One very important point about Africa is that it is very
                    dangerous to generalize. There are so many factors—historical, cultural,
                    economic, social, etc.—impacting on each country in different ways that to speak
                    about Africa collectively is a mistake.</p>
                <p>Ghana In 1967</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me a little more now about your time in Accra. How
                        long were you there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I was there for two and a half years. That was the most enjoyable post
                    we had, because of the people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean the most enjoyable of all of your posts?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Well, I've only had three posts. Ghanaian people are terribly attractive
                    and warm and outgoing and direct. There wasn't the kind of elliptical
                    personality one finds in Iran, and which is quite pronounced in Ethiopia. The
                    Ghanaians are very open people.</p>
                <p>In the days we were there, in spite of the terrible debt problem, they were
                    fairly happy times for the Ghanaians. They had just thrown out a tyrant, Kwame
                    Nkrumah, who had put an awful lot of people in jail, particularly in a place in
                    Accra called Usher Fort, spoken of with considerable fright by everyone. When
                    Nkrumah left, they opened the fort and these people were back in circulation.
                    Many were able technocrats—educated people.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>The Ghanaians were different in many ways from a lot of Africans. For the
                    British, Ghana was a kind of model colony. It was a colony—the Gold Coast—where
                    it was not too difficult for the colonial power to stimulate development. It was
                    relatively small. At the time of independence, the population was in the
                    neighborhood of six million. There was gold, there were diamonds, and, most
                    importantly, there was cocoa. The country has always been one of the chief cocoa
                    producers of the world. One of the problems is that so much of the economy is
                    based on cocoa, that when cocoa prices drop, the country is in deep trouble.</p>
                <p>There was bauxite in the country. Kaiser Aluminum built and brought on stream a
                    very large refinery in the port city of Tema while we were there. The country
                    had the water power. They built the Akasambo Dam on the Volta River about 150
                    miles upstream from the Atlantic. So there was plenty of power. They had to have
                    this, of course, for the aluminum operation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So this was all a part of development. Everything was
                        possible in Africa at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: That's right, but in Ghana, more so. If Nkrumah hadn't put the country
                    into such terrible debt, which exists to this day, Ghana may have achieved some
                    of the hoped-for success that all of Africa had expected.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How much of a staff did you have?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Ghana was a little bit smaller than Ethiopia. There were five or six
                    Americans, and we had 22 or 23 Ghanaian employees. It was the usual
                    configuration—cultural, information, library.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any special public diplomacy problems when
                        you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: No, I don't think so. That was also a pretty open situation. I've been
                    lucky in that I've been in receptive situations wherever I've been. Our cultural
                    programs were well received. I've never really been in a situation where we had
                    to vet nominations for grants with the local government, and where we did, it
                    was usually complied with in the breach. There was more of that in Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I used to have to go through that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>WINKLER: But it wasn't too onerous. We had a very good local staff in Ghana. I
                    later became Deputy Area Director for Africa to John Reinhardt for two years,
                    and then I was Area Director for two years. So I traveled all over Africa and
                    got a view of the local staffs. My recollection was that the Ghanaian staff was
                    as good, if not better, than any of the other African local staffs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you had good atmospherics and a good staff.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: In Ghana, there were three large universities. This was in a country of
                    6 million people, and that's a lot of universities in a developing country for
                    that many people. The principal one, the University of Ghana at Legon, which is
                    just outside of Accra, was, along with Makerere in Uganda and Fourah Bay in
                    Sierra Leone, among the best universities in English-speaking black Africa.
                    There also were several first-class prep schools on the English model, a famous
                    one called Achimota near Accra, where traditions had developed, prescribed
                    outfits were worn and generally the kids went to school like proper little
                    Englishmen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was always very interested in African education before I
                        went into the Foreign Service. We began to be concerned, however, that this
                        kind of very proper British education was not training people to cope with
                        the developing world, and that what they really needed was more agriculture
                        schools from the United States than this proper British education.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Kudos For AID And Peace Corps In Africa</p>
                <p>WINKLER: I think to a large degree that's true. I'll never forget going up
                    country in Ghana, up in the north, and seeing a huge Caterpillar tractor that
                    looked brand new, lying in a ditch, abandoned. We found out from a U.S.
                    agricultural advisor that it had been abandoned there, and it was virtually
                    brand new, because the fuel pump was broken. The fuel pump could have been
                    replaced for $50 or $60, and the thing would have been moving again. But that,
                    I'm afraid, was rather typical. Peg noticed with some dismay looking over a
                    student's shoulder in a school exam that the questions mostly related to the
                    agricultural products of East Anglia.</p>
                <p>I might say that the AID people I came across throughout my career, particularly
                    the agricultural people in the rural areas, impressed me. Most were experienced
                    farmers who were not afraid of dirt, and this was impressive to the Africans
                    with whom they worked.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They knew their job and they did it.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>WINKLER: There was a guy in Mali, I'll never forget, who was known as “Chicken”
                    Davis. He was famous all over west Africa. He ran a poultry development
                    operation there, and he was a terribly impressive, productive guy. We met many
                    such people; they were like the Peace Corps. These were people who wore blue
                    jeans and rough shirts. They tried very hard, they were highly motivated. They
                    wanted desperately to contribute to progress.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They had the same spirit as the Peace Corps people,
                        too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. The two countries, as I suggested a moment ago, that did very well
                    agriculturally were the Chinese and the Israelis. You would go into a market and
                    you would see a squash as big as a pumpkin, you'd see a pumpkin with a diameter
                    of two and a half feet, huge watermelons, wonderful beans and potatoes, and you
                    would know almost immediately that there must be an Israeli or a Chinese
                    agricultural project there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And there usually was.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you traveled around Africa a great deal, I take
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because of your assignments back in Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: About 20 trips over the four years.</p>
                <p>Nine Years In The USIS Program Gave WinkleGreat Opportunity To Observe Much Of
                    Africa (1964-73)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So your two posts were approximately five years, then
                        another four years. So you were involved with Africa for about nine
                        years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you see much change in that period?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>WINKLER: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there in the halcyon days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: From what I saw at the end of that period, I'm not surprised that really
                    nothing much has happened since. As I say, tribalism was pervasive, and I don't
                    think they've overcome it. The South Africans used to claim that the blacks in
                    South Africa were better off than people in the rest of Africa. On the surface,
                    it was probably true; except politically, of course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In physical terms.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Physical—the way they lived, even in the locations. I went to South
                    Africa three or four times during the period I was in Washington, and each time
                    I would spend a half-day in Soweto near Johannesburg. The worst living
                    conditions in Soweto and the other locations outside of Durban or Cape Town were
                    certainly no worse, and probably better, than the way an awful lot of people
                    lived in Lagos or Kinshasa or other places.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the spirit of the other people was a little bit
                        different, I assume.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: South Africa is a totally different story. I can't testify to what the
                    spirit of people was, for example, in the hovels of Kinshasa, but they were in
                    their own independent country. At the same time they have been subjected to
                    years of civil strife and repressive leaders.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any final things you want to say to me about
                        Africa or your thoughts about Africa and your two posts?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Fascination Of South Africa</p>
                <p>WINKLER: South Africa fascinated me. I used to enjoy going there, because I was
                    impressed by what USIS was able to do in South Africa. We were one of the few
                    places—and perhaps the only place in Johannesburg, our library and our cultural
                    events—where people of all colors could gather. The same was true of our homes.
                    We had some first-class PAOs there. The first one I visited was Fraser Draper,
                    who entertained people of all colors in his house and knew people of all colors,
                    and knew them well. Bob Gosende, who later was country PAO, was the branch PAO
                    in Cape Town during a good deal of my tour as Area Director. He and Mary Beth
                    were like Fraser and Howell Draper. The USIS people generally were very
                    comfortable in stimulating multi-racial events in South Africa—probably the most
                    comfortable of any part of the U.S. mission.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean than the embassy people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes, more than embassy people. This is possibly an unfair
                    generalization, but I believe it to be the case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's often the case, because USIS people tend to know a
                        broader range of people, I think, than many people in embassies, who focus
                        so much on either the politically elite or the foreign ministries.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Insensitive Ambassadors</p>
                <p>WINKLER: We have had in South Africa, on a number of occasions, political
                    ambassadors. There was one from Texas, who, I thought, was a serious problem. At
                    one point, he created quite a furor by his insensitivity in accepting an
                    invitation to shoot birds on Robin's Island. Robin's Island is off of Cape Town.
                    It's the prison for political prisoners. This is where Nelson Mandela spent
                    years. Mandela was there at the time. It seemed to me that he and his wife were
                    less than comfortable at mixed parties at Draper's house.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you want to name the ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: His name was John Hurd. A nice man.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's amazing that they would put a political ambassador in
                        a country like that, except maybe South Africa was not considered quite as
                        sensitive as it is now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Travels With Director Shakespeare</p>
                <p>WINKLER: This was in the Nixon Administration. This ambassador, however, did one
                    very interesting thing. On one of my trips there, I escorted Frank Shakespeare,
                    the Director of the Agency. Shakespeare had a wonderful ability to sit in a
                    living room or at a table in a dining room and articulately hold forth his views
                    of the world. I wasn't always in agreement with his views, but he was terribly
                    interesting, and he spoke very well. He was totally honest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That sometimes makes even unpopular subjects
                        acceptable.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>WINKLER: It made him unpopular with people who were not in sync with him
                    politically. We were at lunch one day in the country club in Pretoria with the
                    Ambassador. Draper was PAO then. Six or seven high officials of the Ministry of
                    Foreign Affairs, including the deputy minister were there. Frank, after lunch,
                    was expounding his views of the world and the importance of South Africa. He
                    talked about the importance of the minerals we were getting from South Africa,
                    the strategic importance of the sea lanes south of the Cape, the importance of
                    the Indian Ocean to us, the fact that we could depend on South Africa to keep
                    the sea routes open, and the fact that South Africa was a bastion of
                    anti-communism in Africa.</p>
                <p>When we came out of the country club, the Ambassador called him aside, and they
                    walked down the street for a block, talked, and came back. Frank got into a car
                    with me, and the Ambassador went on his way. Frank said, “I've been doing dumb
                    things. I was just told that I can't talk that way to them, because as I build
                    up their importance to us, it reinforces their feeling that they can continue
                    things the way they are here, that we're not going to do anything about it.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The South Africans.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: The South Africans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A very savvy kind of thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: It was savvy. And Frank never did it again. We were in South Africa for
                    at least another week, and we put him in a chair in living rooms all over the
                    country to talk to people, to talk to groups of journalists, academicians, and
                    others, and he learned. At that time he was the highest level U.S. official ever
                    to visit South Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A bright guy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Whatever you think of his point of view.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I liked Frank, though I didn't agree with him very much or in what he
                    believed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's good. We haven't interviewed Shakespeare as
                        yet.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>WINKLER: He'd be very good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We have to try to see what we can do, if he brings himself
                        back from Italy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes, the Vatican.</p>
                <p>After The African Tour, Iran: 1973</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Those are good stories. What did you do after your African
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I went to Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Directly?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes, in 1973.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there until when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Until July of 1977. I went there in April of '73 just after Dick Helms
                    had taken over as Chief of Mission. He'd interviewed me for the job in
                    Washington. I got called home from my last African trip, as a matter of fact, a
                    week or two early, to be interviewed by Helms. He was going out. I arrived about
                    six weeks after he did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Initially you had no particular interest yourself in
                        Iran?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes, I always had an interest in Iran. Iran seemed exciting. I can't
                    explain what it was. The idea of Central Asia seemed interesting to me. It also
                    was a considerably more developed environment. It wasn't Europe, but it was a
                    much more developed environment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From what you'd been having in Africa, of course. I did it
                        exactly the other way; I went from sophisticated Japan to Iran, which is
                        very different.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: You may have had some culture shock.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I did. If nothing else, I had a lot of culture shock on
                        distance.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>WINKLER: Traffic wasn't quite as bad as Tokyo's, but it was terrible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They reacted differently. They would get out and bang on
                        your car, or whatever was going on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Cultural Rudeness Of Some Iranians</p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. This sounds awful, but it's a fact. I used to say that I was crazy
                    about every Iranian I knew, and despised every Iranian I didn't know. You were
                    treated so miserably by strangers. I found many Iranians so discourteous, so
                    impolite. An awful lot of this, I'm sure, grows out of my feeling about the
                    traffic and the driving. But you know all the culture and all the idiosyncrasies
                    of Iranians. If I pulled up to a stoplight next to an Iranian driver, I learned
                    to try to achieve eye contact. I would lean out of the car and look at the
                    person driving the other car, and could feel him fighting against eye contact,
                    because if they didn't achieve eye contact, they could do anything. They would
                    pull out and cut right in front of you. If you achieved eye contact, then they
                    had to be polite. Their culture required it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they did this to each other.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Oh, yes!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that's got to be made clear, this is how Iranians
                        treat Iranians.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: This is interesting about Ethiopia, too. They often were dreadful to
                    each other. I went to a USAID agricultural conference involving about ten
                    embassy officers and about 20 people from the Ethiopian Ministry of Agriculture
                    at a rather nice motel outside of Addis. The Americans were assigned to share a
                    room with an Ethiopian. I was in a room with an assistant minister. I was in
                    bed, and he came in, after brushing his teeth, and got into the other bed. There
                    was a bed table between us. He put a gun down, a revolver, on the bed table.
                    (Laughs) I didn't know what to think. I said, “What's that?”</p>
                <p>He said, “That's my pistol.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, why is it here?”</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>He said, “Because I'm an Amhara,” which meant that he was of the dominant—but not
                    the biggest—tribe, and he always felt a sense of danger. An awful lot of
                    Ethiopian men carried firearms, and they were capable of shooting each other
                    when arguing. They treated each other very badly. To a degree, the Iranians were
                    much the same way. The Ghanaians were not like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm not sure if foreigners in Iran understood that this
                        terrible rudeness was kind of a universal; it wasn't anti-American. I think
                        people sometimes mixed that up. They didn't have the proper understanding of
                        the culture or the people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: But it was terribly difficult not to feel that it was directed toward
                    you; they seemed so insensitive. The Iranians that you knew socially and
                    professionally couldn't have been nicer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you and Helms get on? Why was Helms sent
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I gather he was sent there because Nixon wanted to put somebody else in
                    CIA. Who was it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Gee, I can't remember.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Who did Nixon put in? Did he put Bush in?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think Bush was later.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Richard Helms—An Easy Ambassador For Whom To Work</p>
                <p>WINKLER: Helms reputedly got eased out, and I gather he was asked where he wanted
                    to go. Of course, Helms had been in the CIA for 30 years. I think he was the
                    first career director. The CIA connection with the Shah had been very, very
                    close for all these years, and Helms, so the story goes, asked for Iran.</p>
                <p>He and I got along very well. Our wives were very friendly. We played tennis a
                    good deal with the Helmses. We saw a lot of them socially. He was a fine guy to
                    work for, because he allowed you full range. When I first got there, he said,
                    “Gordon, you've got the experience to run the USIA operation here. If you have
                    problems, or troubles, or need me for anything, walk into my office. If you want
                    me to go to any kind of a social or cultural event, let me know in advance and
                    get it on the calendar, and I'll be there. If you want me to give a talk, set it
                    up and I'll do it. Just do your job; I won't bother you.”Q: This is a blessing,
                    isn't it?</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. I think the fundamental reason was that Helms' previous job had
                    been so much more complex, so much more demanding, such greater responsibility,
                    than being Ambassador in even as important a country as Iran, that he had no ego
                    problems. He had no need to get into everybody's hair. Other ambassadors do, as
                    you well know. But Helms was really fine to work for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And it was an easy job for him, relatively, compared with
                        what he had been coping with earlier.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes, I think so. He was very social. We seldom went to a party where he
                    and Cynthia weren't there. You know what that environment was. That social
                    environment was pretty heady. You went to dinner parties in houses with
                    three-acre backyards covered with Persian rugs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And tureens of caviar.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was exhausting. I know even in the time I was there, it
                        got to the point that by the time the weekend days came, I was often just
                        shaking with lack of sleep, because we always had a very early morning staff
                        meeting, and you were out. You'd go someplace and they never served dinner
                        until 11:30.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes, if you invited people for 8:30, that meant they'd be there at 10:00
                    and would drink until 11:00.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right. I used to eat twice. I would eat in order to
                        survive the dinner party.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Helms always had a sandwich before he went to a party. When I got there,
                    I arrived about two months before Peggy, there were three or four invitations,
                    including black-tie invitations, on my desk when I arrived. People I didn't
                    know!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they knew who you were.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Constant “Hedge” Of Iranians Around The American Embassy</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>WINKLER: They knew who I was. It was a wonderful way to get acquainted. The
                    problem was—and this goes to the basic dilemma—that all of the people we knew,
                    everybody on the USIS staff when I was there, and I'm sure everybody in the
                    embassy, or just about everybody in the embassy, saw the same group of Iranians
                    that our predecessors saw. We inherited them. We were the new generation of
                    Americans, and we inherited the friends of the preceding generation.</p>
                <p>The first week I was there, Jim Bill, then at the University of Texas, came
                    through. He's written a very good book. I don't know if you've read it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've read some reviews of it, but I haven't read the
                        book.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: It's worth reading. It's called The Eagle and the Lion. At any rate,
                    Bill and I got acquainted. He came by the office and talked with me for an hour
                    or two. He said he was doing a monograph. I'm not sure he's ever published it,
                    but it was a monograph about the American Embassy in Tehran. It outlined his
                    vision of the American Embassy, as having a kind of wreath or a shrub around
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Around the big campus.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Around the big campus. That mythological shrub was made up of all the
                    Iranians the embassy people saw, and that shrub was the same year after year
                    after year, and no one from the embassy ever got through that shrub. I guess one
                    of the reasons was that the Iranians making up the shrub were attractive people,
                    they were European - or American-educated, they were fun to be with, they
                    entertained us marvelously. When we had parties, they would come to the house
                    and stay late. We knew their children, we knew their uncles and their aunts. We
                    became very close. Today, here in Washington, I think we see as many Iranians as
                    we do Americans, because you make close ties. They made certain that they had
                    good contacts at as high a level as they possibly could in the American Embassy,
                    whether it was to assure getting a visa or whatever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The American Embassy had prestige.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes, it did. There were all kinds of attitudes, I think, towards the
                    American Embassy. I think an awful lot of these people saw us as being people
                    they could enjoy themselves with, because we were a touch of the modern world
                    for them, where they had been educated and spent a great deal of time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They'd go to Paris for new clothes or whatever it
                        was.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>WINKLER: That's right, Christian Dior or Saville Row. We were England and America
                    and France and Germany and Italy for them. They wanted to be around us, and they
                    made themselves very accessible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they were very attractive.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: They were very attractive, they were fun to be with, and they spoke our
                    language. But at the same time, I think that there were dimensions in their
                    attitudes towards us we did not sufficiently grasp. Some may have said, “These
                    fools. Their policy has been going on for 20 or 25 years, and it can't last.
                    Something is going to come a cropper.”</p>
                <p>Five Years Before Revolution, Iranian National Employees Of USIS Warned About The
                    Over-Close American Association With The Shah</p>
                <p>The first week I was there, two of our senior local staff came to see me and
                    unloaded. They gave me chapter and verse on Iranian attitudes about the U.S.,
                    about the Shah, and about our close association with the Shah. This was in the
                    spring of 1973, five years before the start of the revolution. One of these
                    staffers was the chief public affairs assistant, a man, and the other was the
                    chief cultural assistant, a woman.</p>
                <p>He came to see me alone, and then she came to see me alone. Then she insisted on
                    coming in with him, and he was never comfortable talking in front of her,
                    because I think he felt, even in those early days in '73, that she was an agent
                    provocateur. But they both said, “Something's got to be done in your policy, in
                    your relations to this country.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean U.S. policy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: U.S. policy and U.S. relations. They both said, “You're going to lose
                    this. Change things dramatically or you are going to lose this.” Interestingly,
                    when she was present, he wasn't quite as voluble as he was when he and I were
                    alone or went out to lunch. (Parenthetically, I should note that he was right
                    about her. He spent time in jail after the revolution, and she became part of
                    it.) But I got an awful lot of this. I got to know Helms well very quickly, and
                    I filled him in on all of this. Doug Heck was the DCM at the time, and he was
                    first class. He was very close to USIS, and had a very clear understanding of
                    the country. He and Helms made it very clear they wanted full reporting of
                    “everything you hear along these lines.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Back to Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>WINKLER: No, to them. USIS heard many things, because we knew an awful lot of
                    people, and a lot of the people we knew were not in government. They were
                    journalists or they were academicians. Of course, they were all in government to
                    some degree, but we picked up a great deal all over the country. So what
                    happened in 1978 and '79 certainly is no surprise to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How much got reported back to Washington? Was there much
                        in the traffic?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: That's a fundamental question. We put everything in writing: “To
                    Ambassador Helms from Gordon Winkler. Subject: Gleaning. Marilyn McAfee tells me
                    that she heard this from so and so. Our BNC director in Shiraz heard this from
                    so and so. I had lunch with S(inaudible) and this is what he said.”</p>
                <p>An awful lot of people—I'm sure you had this experience, also—would call you up,
                    after they got to know you, and say, “Can I come over for a drink some night
                    next week?”</p>
                <p>I would say, “Certainly. Anybody else I should have?”</p>
                <p>“No. Absolutely not.” They'd come in. The cook would come in with a brandy, and
                    the conversation would stop until the cook got out of the room. The person would
                    say, “Are you sure about your cook? What do you know about him?”</p>
                <p>“He's been a cook for six generations of PAOs here. He's a pretty good cook.”</p>
                <p>“Well then, what's in the bird cage, besides the bird?” They were paranoid about
                    the secret police.</p>
                <p>You would get an awful lot, but the problem was that you never got chapter and
                    verse. You'd hear an awful lot from faculty members about kids being picked up
                    on campus by Savak and not return. But there were seldom specifics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you almost begin to feel as if you were surrounded by
                        a kind of miasma of rumor or semi-rumor?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Rumors Of Discontent With Shah And Potential Revolt Were Widespread In
                    Mid-1970s—But Winkler Never Saw Reports About Them Going Back To Washington</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes, but there was so much of it, it couldn't be just rumor; it had to
                    represent fact. You would hear stories about the corruption of the court and
                    about Princess Ashraf, the king's twin sister. You would hear, “People are upset
                    about this military build up. People are upset that there's not enough money
                    going into hospitals and into education; it's all going to Grumman and Northrop.
                    You've got to do something about it.”</p>
                <p>Well, this is a long way to answer your question about whether anything ever got
                    back to Washington. The simple answer is that in spite of the fact that we were
                    giving the ambassador regular reports, I never saw anything in the traffic. He
                    may have been packing them up and putting them in an envelope and sending them
                    to Charlie Naas, who was then the Iranian country director at the State
                    Department. I don't know. I do know that I saw an awful lot more of the incoming
                    and outgoing traffic when Doug Heck was the DCM than when Jack Miklos, who
                    replaced Doug, was DCM, because every morning when I'd go to the staff meeting,
                    I'd go in and see Heck's secretary, and she'd say, “Here's your file.” My file
                    had the back channel traffic and other things Doug thought I ought to see. When
                    Miklos arrived, that stopped. I asked for it but never saw it.</p>
                <p>Helms, half a dozen times during that period, at staff meetings would cite the
                    USIS gleanings, and said, “I want more of that from other embassy elements.” I
                    wish I had all those memos. But the bottom line is that I never saw anything go
                    back to Washington. Some may have; but I never saw it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the questions has been, “Did the United States see
                        this coming?” They've asked that question in one version or another. By and
                        large, the answer you get from the outside is that the Americans at the
                        embassy were not privy to anything really important that was going on. I
                        don't mean to overstate it, but you see the point I'm trying to make.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I think a lot of us did have concerns, certainly at the time I left in
                    mid-1977. That was about six months before things began to fall apart. They
                    began to fall apart in January of 1978, as you recall. You were there then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I arrived as things began to collapse.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I knew, and others knew, it was a sick society. It was a very sick
                    society. It became so wealthy so suddenly. It had been quite wealthy, but then
                    when the Shah quadrupled oil prices in December of 1973, it became almost
                    insufferably rich; the epitome of a nouveau riche society. Like in Ethiopia, the
                    poor were very poor. They weren't quite as badly off as in Africa, but they were
                    pitiful. Social services were terrible, rudimentary, particularly health and
                    education. As in most developing countries very little got to the provinces.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We were talking about the gleanings and the results of all
                        that. When you were in Iran, did you travel around? I don't mean just to
                        visit the cultural centers, but did you get out and have a chance to see for
                        yourself at all? Or were you somewhat restricted? Fully the second half of
                        my time in Iran, my heavens, there were only certain days in which I could
                        even go to south Tehran. So you know how restricted I finally got. My whole
                        career, I was interested in getting out beyond the capital cities, to try to
                        feel what was happening.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I was the same way. It was very easy to do in Iran, simply because of
                    those Binational Centers, the American-supported cultural centers. There were
                    six or seven of them when I was there, and they were always a good excuse to get
                    out of the capital. I don't think I ever made a trip in Iran without going to a
                    BNC, but they made it possible to see a great deal of the country and to get to
                    know people in the regional cities such as Isfahan, Tabriz, Mashed, Shiraz,
                    Abadan, Ahvaz and other places.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We were talking about the fact that the embassy, Jim
                        Bill's concept of the wreath around it, and that we talked to the same
                        people whom we've been talking to forever.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: The same thing was largely true in the provinces. The people one tended
                    to meet in the provinces were not provincially indigenous. They were the same
                    kind of people one met in Tehran. They were sent to the outlying cities to
                    handle the major responsibilities. They were the trusted ones, of course. These
                    people were all very metropolitan people, very cosmopolitan. So I don't think we
                    ever really got a taste of the provinces. I think that also was a function of
                    not having the language. That was one of the greatest gaps in our preparation
                    for service in Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's Washington's problem, as far as I was
                        concerned. I finally had three months of Persian, and everything I had
                        heard, I even said, “Why don't you give me a good brush-up in French, which
                        might be better for the cultural attach�?” They said no. So I had
                        Persian.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Your predecessor, Bill De Myer, had excellent French, and he used it
                    with the chancellor of Tehran University. But that was about the only person he
                    used it with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was the split in the educational world between those
                        who were English-educated and those who were French-educated. But three
                        months of Persian doesn't do anything for you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Rumors Of Revolution Extensive, But No Hint That Religion—The Mullahs—Would Be
                    Its Source</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>WINKLER: That's right. You asked earlier whether we had a sense that things were
                    coming apart. I answered by saying that I was not surprised that the monarchy
                    was deposed. But I never had a clue as to the source, the mullahs. We never saw
                    any; never ever. I don't know what it was like when you were there. When I first
                    got there, there was a junior political officer who had good Farsi by the name
                    of Stan Escudero. Escudero, I would guess, was probably a grade 5, very junior,
                    at the time.</p>
                <p>Escudero sometimes came to staff meetings. He didn't come too often. His boss,
                    the political counselor, usually came. The political counselor would
                    occasionally report that Escudero had been to a mosque and talked to such and
                    such a mullah, had lunch with a mullah, did this or that with a mullah. I
                    overlapped with Escudero six or seven months. It seemed to me that Helms was not
                    terribly comfortable with this at these meetings, and eventually I learned that
                    the Shah had told us he didn't want us involved with the religious community at
                    all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He had told Helms?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: That's my understanding. In my presence at the staff meeting, Helms
                    wasn't saying to the political counselor, “Call him off,” but I felt he was not
                    terribly pleased by these contacts. That was my impression. I think he knew that
                    Escudero was leaving, and it would die there, because there wasn't anybody at
                    that table who could speak Farsi, and there was no way to be in touch with much
                    of the Islamic religious community without the language. This was all about 1973
                    or '74.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So that was a deliberate policy, really, then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. As far as I knew, we were totally in the dark. As far as the Shah's
                    illness was concerned, I recall, probably in late 1973, maybe early 1974, Helms
                    came back from the palace and reported to us at a staff meeting that he was
                    terribly worried; the Shah looked like hell.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: 1973?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: About 1973. It was early in my tour. He looked like hell, he looked like
                    he'd lost weight, he was pale, he was acting tired. The Shah was usually very
                    vigorous and with it and alert. Helms was quite upset and said, “We've got to
                    find out something about this.” Whether we did or not, I don't know. I have a
                    hunch we didn't. He must have had the lymphatic cancer at that time. It's the
                    kind of disease that people can have for ten years. Golda Meir had it for ten
                    years until she succumbed to it. I gather he had it.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>Shortly after this, the Shah went to Vienna for his annual physical checkup, and
                    I gather we got reports that that came out very well. Apparently, the French
                    knew before we did that he had cancer. Do you recall any talk about this?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I knew by the summer of 1978, when I was there. In the
                        summer of '78, there was a long period in which there were no pictures in
                        the media of the Shah, about six weeks. Our friend, Farah, I can remember
                        discussing this when I went up to the Caspian to be with her and her family.
                        But the great concern was that there were no pictures of the Shah doing this
                        or that or the other thing in the newspapers for an inordinately long period
                        of time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: This was unusual. His picture always was at the top of page one—palace
                    orders.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the word was out that he had cancer. This was also the
                        reason given for the fact that he was lethargic in reacting to the fire at
                        Abadan and all the other things that went on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: When was the fire in the cinema at Abadan?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The fire in Abadan was in August of 1978.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Was it that late?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was the considered the beginning of the absolute
                        end.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I figured that that was, too, when I heard about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've got my own stories that you and I could share, which
                        are not appropriate for here. I think I've said it on my own interview. But
                        that was the beginning of the end, because the Shah came out with a new
                        policy statement at the very end of August and the beginning of September,
                        which was placating, new approaches. But by that time it was too late.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>I'm interested in what you say about Helms, because I'm a great admirer of
                    Sullivan. I think Sullivan got all the Americans out of Iran magnificently. When
                    I think of what happened in places like Vietnam and other things, I think
                    Sullivan is to be congratulated. I keep wondering about Helms, who was a CIA
                    kind of personality, whether he was swallowing this information. When I was
                    there in 1978 to '79, we were told that the CIA was called off of any of its
                    normal field activities at the request of the palace, and therefore we didn't
                    have all the intelligence that we should have had. You are suggesting that Helms
                    may or may not have reported back the gleanings that you're talking about.</p>
                <p>Doubt As To How Much Of Information Picked Up By Embassy/USIS Personnel Ever Went
                    To Washington</p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. We'd report these things to Helms, and others around the table
                    would come in, reporting terrible situations, such as a repressive event at a
                    university, or Governor So-and-so was stealing such and such. Helms' position,
                    which I never felt you could argue with, was, “What you're giving me are rumors.
                    Give me specifics. I can't go into the palace with rumors. I'm perfectly willing
                    to take these things up with him (e.g., the Shah), but I can't go into the
                    palace unless I have chapter and verse.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was very close to the Shah, I take it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Very, very close to the Shah.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sullivan was, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Helms was . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Probably closer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I would say that Helms probably was closer because of the whole CIA
                    relationship. He was terribly close to an official by the name of Alam, who was
                    the minister of court. Alam had had every top job. He'd been foreign minister
                    and just about everything else but Shah.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't know that name.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>WINKLER: He was the minister of court, a very elegant, aristocratic person. Of
                    course, I think that Helms was terribly respected by them because of the CIA
                    background and because Helms himself is a rather Brahman type.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, he's a very attractive person. I don't know him well
                        at all, but he is a very attractive person.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: He was a very much sought-after person. Of course in most developing
                    countries the U.S. Ambassador is a celebrity—but Helms was special. There is a
                    strong point of view that the CIA operation in Tehran—and you're familiar with
                    this—was getting everything from Savak. It knew what Savak wanted it to know.
                    What we were getting from the Israelis, I have no idea. In most countries it has
                    seemed to me that they have remarkable intelligence gathering ability. I am sure
                    this was true in Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember a dinner party in which I think both Jack
                        Shellenberger and I were present. This was at the embassy. My heavens, there
                        were a batch of Iranian military brass. Jack subsequently was invited to a
                        lunch or something or other, and he indicated that he had been sort of told
                        not to tamper with the military, and this was the first and only contact he
                        had. He was surprised at the follow-up and all this kind of thing. It's
                        almost as if people were compartmentalized.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: We never were steered away from the military. I used to go to military
                    bases. We were distributing publications to the military.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you had contact with the military.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. We were setting up lectures on security issues and other issues.
                    There was a military academy or an officer school, something like the National
                    Defense College, in Tehran. I went over there at one point and talked with the
                    director, I think with De Myer. We set up a series of talks. When we dealt with
                    the military and brought somebody in to give a lecture, we always had to have
                    simultaneous translation, because an awful lot of military officers didn't have
                    English. That kind of made it a bit clumsy, but we did it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You never were at a post where there was this
                        complication?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>WINKLER: No. I went to military bases whenever it seemed worthwhile. It didn't
                    seem to be a particularly significant target for USIS, because we had so many
                    military that were dealing with them. It certainly didn't seem to me to be a
                    potential problem area for us. The whole subject of a potential coup d'�tat or
                    potential revolution was usually muted, and we relaxed because we felt the Shah
                    would maintain control of the military, and the military would . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Keep control of the country.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes.</p>
                <p>Question As To Validity Of Binational Center Operation</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the other programs that you had? What did you
                        feel was particularly important, and why?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I'll tell you what I did not feel was important—our biggest program
                    there, and that was the Binational Center.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Tehran.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: In Tehran. It was the largest U.S.-supported binational cultural program
                    in the world. I thought the English-teaching was very worthwhile. We were
                    teaching English to upwards of 25,000 different Iranians every year in the six
                    or seven installations that were involved. Aside from that, I felt the BNC was,
                    to a substantial degree—the cultural center, that is—a waste of time. We had a
                    total of three officers there, including the librarian. We had a director and an
                    assistant director. The board of directors was made up of American businessmen
                    and the kind of Iranians who were in that wreath; Jim Bill's circular shrub. All
                    of the board members were from the top families. These were the already
                    persuaded; these were the people who we were close to. Most are in this country
                    now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So we had a big operation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: We were talking to the converted. We'd go to great expense to put on
                    cultural events, and very few people came.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. I would walk in to hear a pianist or a violinist or a singer, and
                    there could be half a dozen people in the room, and maybe half of them were our
                    local employees.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lois Roth?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: No, Lois was not there. Phil Pillsbury, then Ted Kennedy were the
                    Directors during my tour of duty. It was a very different country from the
                    period when Lois Roth was there. First of all, even before the quadrupling of
                    oil prices, but certainly after, the indigenous cultural infrastructure in
                    Tehran was substantial. There was that splendid opera house, there were museums,
                    there was a concert theater. Do you recall that one in downtown Tehran?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I know. Downtown.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: We did much better when we would get cultural attraction from USIA
                    scheduled into one of those places. I didn't feel we needed the Center at
                    all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Center had so much geography and it had to keep the
                        geography filled.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Parking was difficult there. The traffic was terrible. Even the already
                    converted, who might come, were so busy because social life was so intense, that
                    they didn't come to many of our programs. The library, as far as I could tell,
                    the Abraham Lincoln Library, was full of American kids, very few Iranians. I've
                    got great questions about American libraries in most parts of the world, as a
                    matter of fact, if you want to get into that. But I asked for a study of the
                    Center after I was there a year. Jim Moceri was USIA's director of research. He
                    came out and spent a week with me talking about this, and he set up a research
                    project. He brought in a firm from Lebanon to do it. The upshot of the study,
                    which I got hold of just before I left, indicated that it wasn't a terribly
                    valuable institution for us, that there was an awful lot of wheel spinning there
                    and an awful lot of resources wasted.</p>
                <p>At the time I got there, we were putting in upwards of $100,000 a year in
                    budgetary support, and I was able to end that fairly quickly. But we were still
                    putting in the officers. I don't recall whether we paid any salaries of any of
                    the locals. I think that was all being supported by the profits from
                    English-teaching, which were unreal. English teaching was a cash register.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was very impressive.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>WINKLER: That was worthwhile. I would meet people all over the country, military
                    officers, academicians, government people, who would say, when you introduced
                    yourself as from USIS, “Oh, yes, you taught me English.” They never forgot
                    that.</p>
                <p>Are Libraries, World-Wide, Useful To USIS?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For a long time I kept arguing about using the
                        English-language teaching as a vehicle for more programming, using that.
                        What about libraries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I've got serious questions about libraries all over the world. When I
                    was Area Director for Africa, I urged the PAOs to take all the chairs out of the
                    libraries. (Laughs)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How can you function in a library without chairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Because they should be circulating libraries and reference libraries,
                    and people should come in, look for a book, find it, and take the book out.
                    Obviously, serious work in a library is worthwhile, but I'd walk into those
                    air-conditioned buildings and most people, with clothes falling off their back
                    and no shoes, were looking at the girdle ads in the magazines. That was it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a very controversial question.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: It still is today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I inspected our post in Germany twice, and I very seldom went into one
                    of those beautiful America House libraries where I saw anybody but two or three
                    Ethiopians or Africans. That was, of course, of value, but the libraries there
                    were aimed mainly at Germans, and I saw very few Germans in those libraries.
                    Seriously. But the USIS Director there didn't want to give them up, and nobody
                    else wanted to give them up. Actually, the whole question of our program in
                    Germany is worth another discussion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Germany is a very special kind of situation, I think. I'm
                        devoted to the written word, may I say, by comparison with other things. It
                        isn't that I don't recognize the value of other approaches, but having spent
                        so long in Japan, where the written word is critical, I think there are ways
                        to go about the library situation that is useful to USIA.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>WINKLER: I think the work we do in USIA is terribly important. I don't think it's
                    as important as some other kinds of diplomacy. But it's become increasingly
                    important. As more and more people in the world vote, we must reach large
                    segments of the population with our messages. But USIS programs are only as good
                    as the policies they represent. Better to have a mediocre information program
                    and a good policy than a great information program and a mediocre policy.</p>
                <p>Iran was one of the biggest posts in the world. At one time in the 1950s and
                    '60s, I would guess they must have had 30 Americans and 300 or 400 Iranian
                    staffers in USIS. When I was there, there were 15 Americans and 80 or 90
                    Iranians. I think we did a good job, and I think that the people who preceded us
                    did a good job. There were no inhibiting factors. We could reach anybody we
                    wanted except the religious community. But I'm dubious as to whether all the
                    books we distributed, all the lecturers that we brought in, the magazines we
                    produced, the interviews we had on television, the stuff we got into the papers,
                    really did a hell of a lot for us in a situation where the people fundamentally
                    questioned our policy, our role in Iran, and our motives, and where they said to
                    us, “You people control our country and you can change things.”</p>
                <p>The Peaceful Resolution Of Watergate Was The Best Example To Iran Of What The
                    U.S. System Is All About</p>
                <p>I felt genuinely that we didn't control their country and they had to change
                    things themselves. Now I'm not so sure. As I think back, maybe there are things
                    that we could have done, about which our Ambassador could have taken a more
                    forceful approach. We did have great clout with the monarchy.</p>
                <p>I was there during Watergate. Watergate may have been one of the best things that
                    ever happened to us in Iran, because the way Watergate turned out was a
                    startling eye-opener to Iranians. They just couldn't believe that a country
                    could get rid of a President and not have a revolution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And no troops in the streets.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: And nobody got hurt. They couldn't believe it! Peggy and I went to a
                    dinner party the night Nixon resigned, at the home of the chief aide to Prime
                    Minister Hoveyda. This man later became ambassador in London. He gave a very
                    small dinner for an Englishman who was the Mideast correspondent for Newsweek
                    out of London. Peggy and I were the only Americans there. There was this
                    Englishman and about a dozen Iranians. The host started the dinner party by
                    saying, “I've just got to raise my glass to the United States. Nowhere in the
                    world could something like this have happened. It is to the great honor of
                    American society that this exalted thing happened.”</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>And the Englishman said, “It's an exalting thing for the whole world.” I couldn't
                    speak. I almost had to leave the table, it was so emotional. But Watergate was
                    one of the best things that happened to demonstrate what our society is like.
                    And this is what many Iranians hoped we could in some way bring to their
                    country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The real strength of the democratic process and the
                        Constitution.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: That's right. When Carter came in and preached the gospel of human
                    rights in a very forceful way many Iranians said to me: “Finally America sounds
                    like we expect America to sound.” Unfortunately, Carter ruined it all by public
                    obeisance to the Shah. It's important in this connection to note that people in
                    many cultures simply expect more from America than from other developed
                    countries. In black Africa people would complain if an American rifle was found
                    on a Portuguese soldier during the last years of the colonial period in Angola.
                    We would explain that the weapon got to the Portuguese as part of their NATO
                    membership and was not to be used in Africa. Then we thought we would clinch the
                    argument by pointing out that the French were selling Mirage fighters to South
                    Africa. The usual response of a black African was, “Well, that's the French.
                    Don't compare yourselves to the French. More is expected of you.” Perhaps they
                    understood our history better than we did. When those special expectations no
                    longer exist, we'll be in trouble.</p>
                <p>Iranians Believed U.S. Had Power To Control Shah And Cure Excesses That Erupted
                    In Revolution</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think we could have changed the Shah and his
                        proclivities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I don't know, perhaps. Actually it might have hastened the revolution if
                    Iranians knew that we were making an effort or that we weren't quite as tied in
                    to the monarchy. What happened after the revolution might have been less
                    dramatic, not the horror that it was. I'm not necessarily suggesting that the
                    hostage experience would have been avoided.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But by mid-summer of '78, when I would talk to some
                        Iranians, they would say, “You Americans, you're the people who can do
                        something about this. Why don't you do something about this?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Of course, by then the revolution was in progress.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was not overt. It was not absolutely overt.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>WINKLER: There were demonstrations every 40 days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know there were demonstrations, but it was not
                        absolutely overt. There was all this preliminary. I would say, “But there's
                        nothing we can do. It's you who must do something about this.” I can
                        remember they would always come back to, “It's not we who can do something;
                        it's you who must do something.” All the time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: One of the things that most Americans don't understand or are not aware
                    of is the conspiracy theory of human events and human actions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Much of the rest of the world to a large degree believes it, that
                    everything is a conspiracy. We can't grasp this, mainly because it really is not
                    compatible with a culture based on individual initiative—people functioning on
                    their own.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It doesn't really work that way here.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: No, many Iranians saw us as part of a conspiracy with the monarchy and
                    that as the senior partner we could really call the shots.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's really very interesting. May I say, from my point of
                        view, it was very traumatic, the whole general situation and the progress of
                        events. You were still there when things were good.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>WINKLER: Well, they weren't so good. They were good on the surface, Dorothy, but
                    we were getting a monumental amount of criticism and complaints in face-to-face
                    situations. There was nobody—and I don't think this is an exaggeration—there was
                    nobody that I knew at the levels that I knew people, which obviously were at
                    fairly high levels, in journalism, academia, and in society generally, that if I
                    scratched a little bit, I couldn't get a great deal of criticism about the Shah
                    (and many were closely associated with the palace), about our relationship to
                    the Shah, about Princess Ashraf and her corruption, about the monarch's bizarre
                    priorities, about the choking political oppression. I had the feeling while I
                    was there that Iran was more closed than the Soviet Union. In those days we
                    would read about dissidents, speaking out to some degree in the USSR or giving
                    interviews. There was nothing of the sort in Iran. The really intensive negative
                    attitude about the U.S. followed the Nixon and Kissinger visit in May of 1972.
                    That may have been the low-water mark in relations, because they said to the
                    Shah, “You can have anything you want, anything you can pay for,” and the Shah
                    became the epitome of Nixon's Guam doctrine. The Brits had pulled out of the
                    Persian Gulf in 1971-72, so there was a political vacuum in the Gulf, and the
                    Shah wanted to fill it. He wanted to fill it with American-made frigates, F-16s,
                    F-14s, and the most contemporary electronic capability. He had plenty of money,
                    and he quadrupled that money by raising oil prices. He was one of the real
                    driving forces in that event. Our balance of payments were good. There were
                    years of close to $20 billion in orders. Top officials of Northrop and Grumman
                    and Lockheed and McDonnell-Douglas were commuting. Practically every business in
                    this country was at the Iranian door. Yale University was in there with a $50
                    million proposition. If they could have gotten it out of the Shah, it could have
                    been the biggest foreign grant to any American university.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From where I sat, the corruption, or the venality of the
                        American educational institutions, as they reached out to Iran for students
                        and grants to supply them with the wherewithal to continue their existence,
                        I'm not even talking about the Yales, I'm talking about the other
                        institutions who had no business to be in existence.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: It was a rich lode. The Iranians were the biggest group of foreign
                    students in the U.S.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But what problems! The orientation and everything that
                        went with it. Of course, the Iranians didn't want to learn; they just wanted
                        to go be with their cousins.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Some of them did. They wanted to be in America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They wanted to be in America, but they didn't want to
                        learn how to function in America, which is something else again.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>What were the best programs in USIS when you were there? You told me about the
                    Binational Center.</p>
                <p>WINKLER: The magazine was very, very good—Marzayenow. We put it out 11 times a
                    year. We printed 50,000 copies or so. I heard about it everywhere I went in the
                    country: “Oh, you're the man who puts out Marzayenow.” So that was excellent.
                    English teaching was very worthwhile. Cultural and educational exchange, as it
                    is in most countries, was very worthwhile for us. But I suppose if I was
                    launching a USIS program in Iran all over again, I would start with Marzayenow
                    (but probably with a new name) which was a four-color, life-sized knockout
                    publication in the Persian language. I'm sure I would be more careful in
                    managing distribution to make certain we got it through that “shrub” surrounding
                    the embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you would go back to Washington on the policy side,
                        you would go back essentially to USIA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: I would handle this mainly on the embassy level with the ambassador and
                    others. Of course there were letters to USIA in Washington, but the Agency never
                    has had much policy input at any level in Washington, so the best place for a
                    USIS director to have input is in the field. However, there really was little
                    opportunity for modification.</p>
                <p>Frequent Kissinger Visits, And Kissinger/Nixon Visit Of 1972 Probably Encouraged
                    Shah To Adopt Policies Detrimental To Iran</p>
                <p>Most of the time that I was there, Henry Kissinger was Secretary of State. He
                    really ran it. Kissinger came a lot. We had huge press conferences and events
                    involving him. All he had to do was wink his eye and there would be headlines in
                    the Iranian papers for several days. I had the feeling he relished the visits;
                    the Shah was his kind of guy, who implemented the Nixon doctrine in Iran, and
                    the Nixon doctrine in Iran was, I think, one of the things destructive for
                    Iranian society, because it led to domestic and foreign policies by the Shah
                    which turned out to be self-destructive. Our situation was going downhill for 20
                    years, and we did not know it. I think the coup de grace was the Nixon-
                    Kissinger visit in 1972. You see, it made possible an effort by the Shah to
                    chase an idea that must have been going around in his head for years—to make
                    Iran one of the world's leading powers. This does not mean on a level with the
                    U.S., the USSR, Japan, or Germany, but a power on a par with the U.K., France,
                    or Italy, ahead, for example, of India or Brazil. He equated international power
                    with military strength, and the May 1972 visit opened substantial possibilities
                    for military power.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you serve under Sullivan at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: For about six weeks. I found him very bright and quick, very crisp.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything final to say about Iran?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Iranian Revolution Is Probably Permanently Established</p>
                <p>WINKLER: I won't say that I think the revolution is a success, but I think the
                    revolution is established. I don't think the monarch is coming back, as fervent
                    as the crown prince is. It is a revolution that completed its first decade a
                    couple of months ago. They've had elections. They were not like American
                    elections, but they were elections. I think it's established. I have a hunch
                    that when the old man dies, somebody else will appear, hopefully less
                    troublesome, but I think it's going to continue, probably for many years, as the
                    Islamic Republic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a good final statement.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Happy. (Laughs)Q: Happy statement. Is that your “satanic verse”? After
                    Iran, what did you do?</p>
                <p>1977 Return To Washington—Director Press &amp; Publications Service; Then Deputy
                    Associate Director For Programs; Followed By Assignment As Chief Inspector
                    (1980)</p>
                <p>WINKLER: I came back to Washington under Director John Reinhardt as head of Press
                    and Publications Service, which was a job I loved. I think that's one of the
                    most professional operations in USIA, an operation with great pride and great
                    talent. It produces wonderful products in the wireless file and the
                    magazines.</p>
                <p>I was in that job for about 18 months, when Allen Carter was shifted to Area
                    Director for the Far East, and I replaced him as Harold Schneidman's deputy, as
                    Associate Director for Programs. I was in that job for about 18 months, maybe
                    closer to two years, and I liked that job. It was an important job then because
                    there was an awful lot under it—research, television, press, and publications,
                    speakers, and policy. Those were the days when Reinhardt and his deputy, Charlie
                    Bray, used to talk about the programs Directorate being the intellectual nerve
                    center of the Agency. We really were in touch, and were pretty much at the
                    Agency's center.</p>
                <p>Before he left, Reinhardt wanted me to go to India, but I didn't pass the medical
                    examination. That was about when Reagan got elected. Mike Pistor went to India,
                    and John Shirley was coming in to replace Schneidman. Schneidman retired. This
                    was 1980. I didn't really know Shirley, and I didn't know whether he was
                    interested in having me stay on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was a European type.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. I got to know and like him a great deal later on. Reinhardt asked
                    me, “Is there anything you'd like?”</p>
                <p>I said, “I understand Dick Curtis is retiring, and I'd like to be Chief
                    Inspector. I'd been on a special inspection team that Jim Keogh sent to Germany,
                    and then I went on a very interesting inspection in Brazil in 1976, when I was
                    in Tehran. So, in 1980, I became Chief Inspector. That was a fascinating job.
                    You saw an awful lot of USIS in various parts of the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You changed things around in that office, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: We changed the inspection process somewhat. This was in response to John
                    Shirley's views when he was counselor of the Agency. We went to Germany, six of
                    us, spent five or six weeks there, and produced a 125-page report. Shirley said,
                    “This is ridiculous. I don't think you ought to do a report that's more than six
                    pages, and you should never take more than three inspectors to any country,
                    India or anywhere.” We were about to go to India. Three of us went to India: Joe
                    Boerner, Ron Oppen, and I. We inspected India in four weeks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It seems to me I can remember.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Were you the desk officer? That was about 1981-82.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I was on the desk.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Then Boerner went off to some other post. I think he did Malaysia by
                    himself, and Oppen and I did China in about three-and-a-half weeks.</p>
                <p>Winkler's Concept Of An Inspection's Purpose: Personal Contact As The Basis Of
                    Successful Operation</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So the whole concept changed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: The whole concept changed, and the reports were much tighter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you look for different things?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>WINKLER: I was always interested in the post's contacts; who were the officers
                    seeing, and in what kind of milieu were they seeing them. When I came into the
                    Agency, it was made very clear to me that the success of my career would depend
                    on how well I did with people, how useful my contacts were. This was the way to
                    achieve basic goals. It was made very clear this was the most important thing.
                    I'm afraid the Agency and the Foreign Service has changed markedly in this
                    regard. It's very troublesome to me.</p>
                <p>In an inspection the first thing I would want to see was the representation
                    vouchers. I'd analyze them for each officer to see how often the same name came
                    up, how many different names there were and the kind of events in which contacts
                    were involved. What I found—and it's almost safe to generalize on this—is that
                    most of the representation was done at lunches, in restaurants, which, first of
                    all, were terribly expensive. The limited representation dollars do not go very
                    far in restaurants. You would find key officers, Deputy PAOs, Information
                    Officers, senior officers, who, over the course of a year, would see less than a
                    dozen people. They just weren't seeing people in a planned and intensive
                    way.</p>
                <p>You would meet with them and ask them questions: “But do you have people to your
                    home? Does your family get involved? Do you go on picnics with people? Do you
                    know the editor of so-and-so? Do you see him with his kids and your kids?”
                    Nothing like that, or at least, very little—mostly a few expensive restaurant
                    meals. The point is that if an officer can turn an essentially business or
                    professional contact into a more personal relationship, the possibility to
                    influence ideas and to glean information is dramatically enhanced. This was
                    standard operating procedure 25 years ago. I don't think it is today in the
                    Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>I have thought about this a great deal because it is so disturbing. I think the
                    whole change in the role of the spouse has contributed. I had an Information
                    Officer in Tehran, a career officer, excellent officer, whose spouse would not
                    come to parties at our house. She didn't think that was her responsibility. She
                    was right, technically. Very often he would come, but he was very family
                    oriented—nothing to criticize in that regard—but he very often excused himself
                    at 10:30. As we said earlier, that's when the Iranians were beginning to arrive.
                    Sometimes he'd go home without dinner. And there's little you can do about that.
                    So that's one thing. I think that it also grows out of a different motivation of
                    people coming into the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>When you and I first came in, we were told, “You're going to get so much for
                    representation from the government, and then you'll have to spend the rest
                    yourself, and it will be a tax deduction for you.” You can't say that to
                    somebody today. You can't say that you expect them to spend $1,000 or $2,000 a
                    year out of their pay to augment the paltry amount the government gives them.
                    And they don't entertain at home. They spend money in restaurants and after a
                    couple of good meals in Rome, it's gone. Motivation is just different.</p>
                <p>The Present Versus The Old Way Of Conducting Foreign Service Panel Exams</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>I spent six months as one of the panelists interviewing candidates for the
                    Foreign Service. That is, for the State Department and USIA. These are people
                    who had passed an awesome written examination. About ten percent pass it. They
                    would be scheduled for a day of oral examination. I've been paneled twice, once
                    when I first joined USIA, and then when I became a Foreign Service career
                    officer, I was paneled again. That was a long, three-hour discussion led by one
                    of the senior officers of the Agency at that time, plus two or three other
                    seniors, one from State. That experience began with a discussion of my
                    background, like we've had this afternoon. “Tell us what your motives are for
                    being in the Foreign Service. Tell us about your family. Tell us this and tell
                    us that.” They learned something about me, where I had been educated, why I
                    wanted to be there. Only then did they begin asking the standard questions to
                    find out what I knew. That was a good session. That doesn't happen today. The
                    only interview experience is actually two on one. Two officers go into a little
                    room with the candidate. The candidate has a name tag on. The first thing one of
                    the officers says to the candidate is, “All I want to know about you is your
                    name. We'll be together for 45 minutes. We are going to ask you six questions.
                    You have approximately six or seven minutes to respond to each question. Make
                    sure that in your response, you do not tell us where you went to college, or
                    where you're from. We don't want to know anything about you. You'll be asked a
                    political question, an American society or history question, an economic
                    question, a cultural question, and then two hypothetical questions.” They put
                    the person in a consular administrative situation. “What do you do if a plane
                    crashes in the mountains above Lima and you're the consular officer?” You see
                    how they respond. You see how they answer questions about American cultural or
                    world events. And that's all. Then they do some writing for you. There are two
                    writing projects.</p>
                <p>Then in the afternoon, six of them sit around a table, and they deal with a mock
                    embassy situation, and four evaluators are on the periphery, and they watch the
                    people to see how they interact, how their personal relations are. First of all,
                    it's very difficult to pick out a person with very good personal relations who
                    doesn't seem passive, because if they are too aggressive, they won't have good
                    interpersonal relations. At the same time, if they seem passive, you wonder
                    about their leadership potential.</p>
                <p>They finish that, and they do an in-box test, which is pretty good.</p>
                <p>But I relay all this to you to point out than an essential element of the culture
                    of American personnel management is eliminated; it's not there. That's the basic
                    personal interview. “Tell me about yourself. Tell me why you want this job. Tell
                    me what you can do in this job.” None of that is there. I understand one of the
                    reasons it's not there is that Congress is concerned about equal opportunity.
                    The evaluations might be unduly influenced if they learned that a candidate went
                    to Harvard, I suppose. But there are all kinds of people, I think, who are
                    passing these oral examinations who are bright, able, potentially hard working,
                    but we don't know anything about their personalities. We don't know anything
                    about their interests or their motivations.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They're technicians.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Or whatever. We don't know if they've got a sense of humor. We don't
                    know how they're going to get along with people. We don't know if they're
                    interested in people. We don't know if they have a gut need to get to know other
                    cultures, which is essential. In my judgment, it's a shabby selection process.
                    Have you ever been through a panel?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was through two panels.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Did they start off asking you about yourself?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The first one did, yes. It was a very personal panel. The
                        second time around was in Tokyo, the same kind of thing. They knew who I
                        was; I guess I knew who they were at the moment. But then we went on. There
                        was a State Department person and a USIA person. But it was a more human
                        sort of thing. I sat in on minority interviewees. It wasn't even mid-career.
                        They needed a more senior woman on some of these panels. We were three or
                        four people on those panels, and we had questions which were put in front of
                        us which we had to offer, but we could use follow-up questions.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: We did that, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But I often found that I was negative about the person
                        when the rest of the people said, “Well, technically they were fine.” But I
                        thought they would have a terrible time adjusting to the Foreign Service at
                        a mid-career or upper level, with the kind of attitudes and background and
                        so forth which they had.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: But you were getting information about their background.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: You weren't just asking six questions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, no. We knew. We had a bio and all that kind of
                        thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: So your decision could be based on a lot of things.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right. I also remembered my experience of coming in
                        as a lateral entry and what happened as a result of that, the kind of lumps
                        I took. But there was a tendency, as I say, on a lot of these panels, I was
                        the most negative person because I was concerned about the adjustment
                        process and, therefore, the capacity of the person.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: If you were on the Board of Examiners now, there would be no way you
                    could find out any of that. You could find out how much the person knew about
                    the Russian invasion of Afghanistan. That's what you would find out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's sort of like reading the newspaper.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: But you can't ask a person, “What do you really know? What book is on
                    your bed table?” That kind of question is verboten.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Gordon, if you're overseas and you're in the middle of a
                        revolution, by golly, what you're interested in is not how much that person
                        knows about some foreign policy issue. You want to know how they're going to
                        function and can they deal with a crowd, or what can they do. You know.
                        Because living overseas in a crisis situation is a very different kettle of
                        fish.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: Yes. The experience in the Board of Examiners was interesting from
                    another standpoint. We had these six questions. One was international politics,
                    one was on economics, one was on American history and society, and one was on
                    American culture. The responses to the American-culture question, by and large,
                    were so pitiful it was frightening. The easiest question was, “Name five
                    American novelists of the 20th century. Tell us the title of several of their
                    books and why they were important.” And from seemingly very bright young people,
                    you would get, “Well, let's see. Hemingway.” And it would stop right there.</p>
                <p>We had a question on the movies, which you'd think most young people would do
                    well on. That was a disaster. I designed a question on architecture to be given
                    to people who seemed particularly bright. You'd get somebody who would give you
                    chapter and verse on NATO, who would know everything that was going on in
                    Central America, could discuss in a very sophisticated way the debt problems in
                    Brazil and Mexico and so forth, and couldn't even dredge up Frank Lloyd Wright.
                    This country has got some problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did this come about, do you know? Is this a reflection
                        of the times? My own reaction on lack of the human quality overseas is that
                        some officers, after they've been in the Foreign Service long enough, are
                        just almost bored with another group of people, another society, that's
                        getting on with life.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>WINKLER: There are problems in being overseas. Spouses have difficulty getting
                    employment. Today the security issues are very, very serious. There are all
                    kinds of problems for teenagers; drug problems. Living abroad, I think, is a
                    much more fragile experience than living in an American urban area. You're
                    uprooting kids from school for two or three years, possibly throwing them into a
                    British school, then bringing them back. One of our kids went to 12 schools in
                    12 grades. I hasten to say he's normal. Q: Maybe his parents. The USIA entry
                    system is now completely linked to State.</p>
                <p>WINKLER: Almost totally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is this a good idea?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: That's another subject. I don't think that would be a bad idea at all if
                    the entry system was better. I think that USIA, as opposed to what most of my
                    colleagues, active and retired, feel, ought to be organizationally closer to the
                    State Department. I said earlier that I think the work we do is terribly
                    important, but I'm not convinced that we're the only ones who can do it. I think
                    that at the very least, the personnel systems should be combined, and there
                    should be one officer corps of Foreign Service Officers, not Foreign Service
                    Officers in the State Department and Foreign Service Officers of the U.S.
                    Information Agency. I think more political and economic officers should know how
                    to write a press release, how to talk to a journalist, how to be interviewed on
                    television, and conversely, I think more information and cultural officers ought
                    to know how to sit down and talk to a leader of a political party and get
                    information, get intelligence, or should know something about trade policy and
                    so forth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would suggest a change in training programs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: It does, but more importantly, it suggests a broader assignment policy,
                    where a good political officer can be sent out as a cultural officer and it
                    won't hurt his or her career, and a good information officer can be sent out as
                    an economics officer or a consular officer and it won't hurt that career. Then
                    more USIA people would have an opportunity to be ambassadors, because that's
                    been a serious weakness in our system.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If you're a USIA officer, you would just assume an
                        ambassadorship is not . . .</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>WINKLER: What I'm saying is maybe we should not have USIA officers. Perhaps there
                    should be some cultural centers and there should be a press service and a
                    speakers bureau and the kind of research we do, but the officer corps should be
                    from a central pool of Foreign Service Officers. “For the next four years,
                    you're going to be assigned to the policy office at USIA.” Or, “You're going to
                    be assigned to Worldnet for Latin America” (if Worldnet survives). Or, “Your
                    next assignment is as assistant pol/mil in India.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After all, Gordon, you ended up your career at FSI. This
                        is a training area. You were in area studies. Do you have any comments about
                        that? That's a different element which really deals with languages and
                        substance.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: My responsibilities dealt basically with substance. I won't get into the
                    details of how I feel about the pedagogical approaches, but I think we could
                    have done well with somewhat less in the way of lecturing and discussions, and
                    more in simulations and games. But that's being worked on now, and being worked
                    on by my successor, Jack Shellenberger, who also replaced me in Tehran. He is
                    now the second USIA officer to have been a dean over there. So it's good that
                    we've had that exchange with the State Department.</p>
                <p>It's almost impossible to overemphasize the importance of instilling a feel for
                    cross-cultural communications at FSI. I don't think we did or are doing enough
                    of it in the School of Area Studies. The School of Language Studies feels it
                    does a great deal because every teacher is a native-born speaker of the
                    language. They impart an awful lot of cultural information about their
                    countries, but they are not academics. Many of them have not been to college, so
                    one wonders as to the accuracy of the information and whether or not purely
                    personal prejudices creep into what they're telling students. But the sum, I
                    think, is worthwhile.</p>
                <p>But this goes back to the contact lacunae in the Foreign Service. I think that if
                    people had a greater interest in other cultures, if they understood, for
                    example, when they waited in line to get into a movie in an Arab country or in
                    India, that just because people were brushing up against them and touching their
                    bodies, they were not being antagonistic; that it's the way they are, and
                    because we're not that way doesn't mean that their way is wrong. I think there
                    should be an awful lot more attention to cultural matters, to habits, values,
                    behavioral patterns so that we can gain an understanding and a respect for
                    people of other societies. The more I got into it, the more I realized that
                    except for the people of a few northern European countries, we are probably more
                    different culturally from the rest of the world, than the rest of the world is
                    from each other, that is, as other cultures are from each other.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's quite a statement.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>WINKLER: When you hear lectures on cultural manifestations of Latin America or on
                    the subcontinent or in the Middle East or in the Far East, there's a great deal
                    of what, to our mind are idiosyncrasies, that are similar. The whole concept of
                    the family for example; it's shocking to people almost anywhere else in the
                    world, that we put older people in nursing homes. They don't do that in Japan,
                    they don't do that in Brazil, they don't do that in Africa. They stay in the
                    home. They're honored. They're with their grandchildren. They're not in the way.
                    They're in the way here. There are all kinds of examples of this sort.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it really means, what you're saying, we need to
                        appreciate the nature of our own society before you can go out and be an
                        effective Foreign Service Officer in other cultures.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: No question about it. But you have to be willing to accept that other
                    people are different and that is not necessarily wrong, not necessarily less
                    ethical and less worthy of respect than our own way of doing things, our own
                    values and our own beliefs. We have real problems in getting this across.</p>
                <p>The students at FSI will listen to this, because usually the lecturers who do
                    this for us are among the best. They're lively and they're funny and
                    interesting, so they can command attention. But what the students basically want
                    to know about is the political situation in the country of assignment; they want
                    to know about the economic situation.</p>
                <p>It's very difficult to get an American to understand that when he arrives in
                    Paris and he's a political officer, or if she's an economic officer, if, at the
                    first social event they can show some understanding of French literature, it's
                    going to be much more impressive to the French than if they can talk about the
                    French economy or French political parties. Our society doesn't prepare us for
                    that. You know very well in Iran how important it was to be able to know a
                    little bit about Saidi and Hafiz and Ferdosi. I'm sure nobody at FSI thought
                    much about those three poets when we were teaching area studies to people going
                    to Persia. Maybe somebody mentioned Omar Khayyam, who was a minor Persian
                    poet.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think you have said a great deal. Is there any last
                        word?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: You've been very patient.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You've said some very interesting things. I tend to agree
                        with much of this. Thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WINKLER: You're welcome.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
