<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000174">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Elizabeth A. Burton </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>ELIZABETH A. BURTON</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: January 20, 1998</p>
                <p>Copyright 2000 ADST</p>
                <p>Q: I wonder if we could start sort of at the beginning. Could you tell me where
                    and when you were born and something about your family.</p>
                <p>BURTON: I should have been born here in Washington, but technically I was born in
                    Reno, Nevada, because my mother was from a prominent Nevada family, and my
                    father spent 10 years in Nevada working for a man there, and picked up my mother
                    and brought her back here to Washington. We were an old Washington family. I'm
                    fourth-generation Washingtonian. The family came originally from Sussex County,
                    Delaware, before the Civil War. My father was a prominent banker, Clarence F.
                    Burton. I was brought up here in Washington, from the time I was about six
                    months or a year, I guess. So I've lived here all my life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where'd you go to school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I went to secondary school here in Washington, at GunstoHall, and then I
                    went to Sarah Lawrence College.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was it like growing up in Washington? Was it a
                        differencity than it is today?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I should say so. It was absolutely wonderful. In the first place, it was
                    very small, and so-called society was very small. The upper levels of the
                    diplomatic and military and congressional world and the so-called cave-dwelling
                    business people all knew one another and mixed together and saw one another all
                    the time, and their children grew up and knew one another. So, compared to
                    today, it was minuscule. As I recall, there were just a few embassies and
                    legations. The British had a legation down on N Street.</p>
                <p>Q: At Gunston Hall, did one sort of major in anything? I realize this was at the
                    secondary school level, but what were your particular interests at that
                    time?</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>BURTON: No, I don't think we majored in anything. But it was in many ways a
                    remarkable school, because it was, even in the primary school, geared toward
                    old-fashioned studies like The Iliad and The Ring of the Nibelungen and those
                    things, so that I was exposed to this at an early age. It was a very small
                    school, mainly Southern, and had a two-year finishing school for Southern
                    ladies, so that the overtones were very Southern.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get finished, or did you keep going?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I wasn't finished, no. I got out of there at the end osecondary school
                    and went to Sarah Lawrence College in Bronxville.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were at Sarah Lawrence from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Until '41. I'm Class of '41.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just in time for World War II.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you studying at Sarah Lawrence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Mainly the arts, almost entirely, but with a certain amount of economics,
                    which is what I lived on the rest of my life. I studied music with William
                    Schumann and I studied painting with two very prominent people in the field,
                    Kurt Rush, and Bradley Walker Tomlin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you say economics, what did economics consist of at
                        SaraLawrence during that period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I think it just consisted of some basic economic studies,economic history
                    more than anything.</p>
                <p>Q: Were the Sarah Lawrence students caught up in the events over in Europe? This
                    was, of course, a tumultuous time, just before the start of World War II, and
                    then World War II starting in 1939. Did this impact at Sarah Lawrence?</p>
                <p>BURTON: Not a bit.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: As if it didn't exist.</p>
                <p>Q: What was the view of the government then? There were some schools where
                    people, particularly the upper branches of society in the United States, came to
                    hate Roosevelt. Was this part of the ethos at that time?</p>
                <p>BURTON: I think that Sarah Lawrence was extremely liberal. I can remember that
                    the sort of the queen of campus was a Jewish lady who was very communistic, and
                    they thought she was wonderful. My father was a hate-Roosevelt type. He was just
                    about as reactionary as they could come. He was a Washington banker and detested
                    Roosevelt, although that didn't keep us from going to the Roosevelt
                    receptions.</p>
                <p>Q: I'm just curious, because you belonged to Washington society, was there much
                    of an intermix with the Roosevelts and the Roosevelt Cabinet and Washington
                    society?</p>
                <p>BURTON: Oh, yes, totally and completely. After all, there were no jets, and so
                    they were dependent on the local community to come to the White House. There
                    were parties that they had for the children, and the local kids were included. I
                    remember going to a dance there for Mrs. Roosevelt's niece, and going there with
                    my father to the judicial receptions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At home, did you get long discussions of “that man in the
                        WhitHouse” and how awful he was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: We certainly did. My father would be chuckling all day if Westbrook
                    Pegler came out with a particularly nasty article. And he detested Mrs.
                    Roosevelt. I think he was wrong, but he certainly felt that way.</p>
                <p>Q: Here you were, coming from this society, and both Roosevelts came from
                    essentially the same strata of society, but they were, particularly Mrs.
                    Roosevelt, not playing the game.</p>
                <p>BURTON: Not your normal woman of the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about a young student at Sarah Lawrence, and the other
                        onethere, how did you all look upon Mrs. Roosevelt?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>BURTON: I haven't the foggiest. I don't remember at all. I don't think it was
                    discussed. At Sarah Lawrence, we were interested mainly in the arts. And there
                    was a remarkable roster of professors there at that time, because they could
                    work a couple of days in Bronxville and then do their work in New York. A case
                    in point being Maxwell Geismar, who was one of my professors, and Bradley Walker
                    Tomlin, Joseph Campbell, and William Schumann, who became towering figures in
                    their field.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then you graduated in 1941. We're not at war yet.
                        SaraLawrence had not paid much attention to it. What happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Then I came back to Washington and studied art at the Phillips Gallery
                    for a year. After the war, I went to work for the Freer Gallery, for a man who
                    was the Islamic associate at the Freer Gallery. I was paid by the University of
                    Michigan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find Washington society changing with the
                        war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, of course. It emptied of all the young men that we had known, but it
                    filled up with all of the glamorous New Yorkers and then the Brits. So we had a
                    wonderful time. There was a party every night.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the arts, were they being patronized during that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: There was so little going on in Washington. It was negligible, really,
                    except for the standing exhibitions. I'd say nothing. There was a small
                    community of artists here that all knew one another.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you beginning at all to be sucked into the war
                        effort,postwar planning, or anything like that at this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I got a job during the war. I was working for the Board of Economic
                    Warfare, over on Q Street. I worked there until the end of the war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did your job consist of?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Mainly research. I can remember having to research all of the sewer
                    systems in Antwerp, for instance, at one point. I haven't the foggiest why.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the atmosphere at this office? Was it six days a
                        week,priority assignments?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, it was an engineering group, and they acted as advisors to whatever
                    they were advising. I don't really know what, because that was the upper level
                    of the department, and I was just a prole.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there many women doing research at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: No, I think I was the only one. It was a very small office. And I also
                    took care of the consulting engineers, two or three of them, including
                    Buckminster Fuller, who became a good friend.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Basically, would you get an assignment saying let's look
                        at thoil production of various places?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, that kind of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I suppose the main thing was...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I wouldn't be surprised if it wasn't mainly military targets. Q: I was
                    going to say bombing targets.</p>
                <p>BURTON: Targets for bombing, probably, but we weren't told what. Iwasn't much of
                    an issue. You just got an assignment, and you did it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find out about the sewers of Amsterdam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: The Library of Congress. It wasn't Amsterdam, it waAntwerp. I don't know
                    why I remember it, but I do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Library of Congress have a pretty complete...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, they did. You had to sniff around, around town, to sewhere you'd
                    find information, but it was available somewhere.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm just trying to think of how one would try to find out
                        about sewer system anywhere.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I really don't know now myself. In those days, I worked umy techniques
                    and knew where I was going. But it was a long time ago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the end of the war, with economic warfare, were there
                        angroups beginning to look at what happens after the war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, they tried to keep things together for a while, but gradually
                    attrition took care of it, and the office was dissolved. But I do remember they
                    were sending engineering groups out to, for instance, Ethiopia. I and another
                    woman had to write up a basic manual book for Ethiopia, and they went out to
                    Ethiopia and used this book. I don't remember much about it, but I remember that
                    was one of them. I don't know what they were doing in Ethiopia. Probably
                    advising the Ethiopian government on X, Y, or Z, I don't know what.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Italians had left there, and I guess they had to
                        figure ouwhat to do about it. Who was the head of the office?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I haven't a clue. I don't remember. I was working for a man named Alex
                    Taub, a very famous British engineer who had designed the Spitfire engine. I
                    don't know whether he was fundamentally an American. He was Jewish, so he might
                    have had overtones of family in Europe. I don't really remember, but I think he
                    was American. If he wasn't, he was English. But that was his famous thing, the
                    Spitfire engine, a famous British airplane.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you were doing this, did this remove you from your
                        interest iart, or did this keep up?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, it totally removed me from it. And I was very busgoing out every
                    night, too, so...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's easy to forget how hectic the social life was at that
                        time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: There was a party every night. It was just a question of getting on the
                    phone and finding out where it was. And everybody met every day at lunch at the
                    so-called snake pit, which was the Patio Room at the Mayflower Hotel. So you
                    always knew who was in town by going there for lunch.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>Q: It was a different world. I was a little bit younger, but I got some flavor of
                    this because I lived in Annapolis and from time to time I'd come up and meet
                    people up here. Washington was almost unbelievable as far as the pace.</p>
                <p>BURTON: Incredible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As the war came to a close, was this beginning to intrigue
                        you afar as getting into something else?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: No, I really didn't know what to do with myself. The office was
                    dissolved, and everybody was coming to an end of their government service during
                    the war. Everybody got fired; we just got a pink slip, is what it amounted
                    to.</p>
                <p>Then I looked around, and that's when I went with the Freer and worked for
                    Richard Ettinghausen, who was one of the great, towering figures, an Islamic art
                    historian who later taught at New York University and was associated with the
                    Metropolitan Museum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do at the Freer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I was his assistant for editing a book called Ars Islamica, which was a
                    very famous journal put out in three languages on Islamic art.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In that period, Islam seemed pretty far away from
                        everything.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: It was. There were only two places in the United States where there were
                    any Islamic studies. One was at Princeton, and the other was at the University
                    of Michigan. It was unique, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did that keep up?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: It kept up until I decided I wanted to go to Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was when? BURTON: This was in the summer of '49.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Europe was almost prostrate at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, but I had an opportunity to go with some Swedish friends to Sweden
                    for the summer. I was invited to go with them, and that's what precipitated my
                    departure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you tell me a bit about this trip to Europe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, one of the consultants that I was working for was a
                    Swedish-American, and I became very close with his family. They went back to
                    Sweden every year. She was from a prominent Swedish family. And they asked me to
                    join them, which I did. I spent the summer with them in Sweden. And then I
                    decided I didn't want to come home, so I went back to Paris, where I'd been for
                    about 10 days before I went to Sweden.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Looking at Sweden in 1949, what was society like there
                        when yowere there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: It was exceptionally elegant. Very old-fashioned, very, very elegant. I
                    would say it was about the nearest thing to the 18th Century you can think of.
                    Beautiful country houses, all flourishing. Races going in the afternoon.
                    Wonderful dinner parties. Very beautiful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there much talk about World War II at that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: No, except for one friend in this group that I knew very well. His name
                    was Aminoff, and he had been chamberlain of the Swedish court. Goering had come
                    up during the war to go hunting, and he'd been assigned to take care of him. And
                    he, in turn, was invited back to hunt with Goering. In the middle of the war, he
                    went there, and then went to London, or vice versa. In any case, I remember his
                    telling me that Goering was convinced that London was absolutely flat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From the bombing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes. And he said to him, “Do you know London well?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Yes, I do.”</p>
                <p>And he said, “Well, it isn't. I've just been there, and I'll takyou up one street
                    and down the other.”</p>
                <p>I think this was very interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Paris like in '49?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: It was lovely. It was empty, for one thing. There were practically no
                    cars. Everything was in short supply, except I didn't notice it much. When I
                    first went there, I was just prowling the streets and looking around. And
                    certainly the restaurants were flourishing, no problem.</p>
                <p>I went to England a couple of times while I was there, and I didn't realize what
                    privation they were going through. For instance, an egg for breakfast was
                    unheard of. It was ten days or two weeks later before I realized that you
                    couldn't go to somebody's house and expect an egg for breakfast.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about in France, was that different? Paris was eating
                        better?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, it was perfectly all right. There were no cars, because gasoline was
                    in short supply. So the French were awfully nice to us, because we had
                    everything. We had the silk stockings and the hooch and the gasoline and the
                    cars.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were you able to tap into this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: After I started to work, which was in the fall of '49, I had access... I
                    bought a car, which the French couldn't do. I bought it in dollars, so I had a
                    car and gasoline, and stockings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '49, what were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I wasn't doing anything to begin with. Then I realized I would run out of
                    money eventually, and if I wanted to stay in Paris, I'd have to get a job. So I
                    sniffed around through friends and connections. They were recruiting for the
                    Marshall Plan at the Talleyrand at that time, and I went in there and got a job
                    as a statistician in the Central Programming Office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was the Hotel Talleyrand, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which was the center of American activity, or was it the
                        centeof the Marshall Plan?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>BURTON: It was the center of the Marshall Plan, and gradually became the center
                    for all of the international diplomatic operations, not to be confused with the
                    embassy, which was on the other side of the square.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the head of the Marshall Plan when you started in
                        '49? BURTON: I can't remember, but I think it was Lincoln Gordon.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did they hire you for?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: As a statistician.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This goes back to your finding out about the sewers of
                        Antwerp?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I don't know what it was. I don't know why they hired me, but they did.
                    Maybe it was just that they had three slots to fill, and I was one of them,
                    fortunately. Once I got in there, I could sniff around and find other things as
                    need be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the sort of things that a statistician was
                        working on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I can't remember. I remember editing papers that they gave me. This was a
                    small office, and I think that anything you were equipped to do, you did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the work? Was it assembling statistics on
                        variouthings?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I'm sorry, I can't tell you. I simply don't remember. I was very new. I
                    was getting used to things and trying to figure out how the cable system worked,
                    things like that. I was working for a very brilliant man whose name was
                    Ostrander, who was handling the German distributions of the Marshall Plan stuff.
                    So I just did whatever he told me, I guess.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you characterize the spirit of the people working on
                        thMarshall Plan?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, they were very excited with what they were doing. There was a very
                    competent woman there named Mary Painter, who was apparently famous in the
                    economic field. She died only about three years ago. She had constructed a new
                    system for something in economics. But they were young, and they were
                    enthusiastic. I worked with Tom Shelling, later of Harvard. He taught me how to
                    use a slide rule. It was almost like a post-graduate group. A lot of very
                    bright, attractive, young people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you traveled about France, what was your impression of
                        wherFrance was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Looking back on it now, I realize that France was still in a pre-World
                    War II state. And by that I mean it was in a medieval state as well. Anytime you
                    got to a small village in the country, there wasn't much difference between it
                    and the Middle Ages. If you went into a house, plumbing, everything else like
                    that. But I didn't realize it at the time. I do now, because of the vast
                    difference between then and now. But it had remained absolutely untouched, I
                    would say, since the early 19th Century, the Proustian days almost.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any contact with the international community
                        whilyou were doing this first job? The French, the British.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Not professionally. Certainly socially, yes. I knew quite a few French
                    people from the French Embassy here, and they were very nice to me. I had entr�e
                    in France that was, at that point, spectacular. But even then I didn't realize
                    that. They were just old friends and they would ask me for lunch, that kind of
                    thing. So I had a view of Proustian Paris that I didn't realize I was
                    having.</p>
                <p>Q: This office basically was serving more or less the same way, I take it, that
                    your economic warfare office was, supplying statistics or information on
                    demand.</p>
                <p>BURTON: Oh, I think not. No, no, I think it was far more than that. The
                    Programming Office was the hub of where and what they were distributing to the
                    Marshall Plan countries. Everything that was allocated to the Marshall Plan was
                    siphoned though the Paris office, so that it was an extremely important hub of
                    what was going out. But I was just too young and too inexperienced to have much
                    part in that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Averell Harriman come across your...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I knew him later, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But not at this particular time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did this particular job last?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Two years, at least.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So we're moving toward around 1952 or so. What did you do
                        then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I remember coming on home leave for two months and then going back. But
                    then this so-called statistical office, which I don't think had much raison
                    d'etre to begin with, was dissolved. There were three of us in it. So I had to
                    look for another job. There wasn't one in that particular office, so I got
                    another one around the Talleyrand for a few months. And then I got picked up by
                    the office of the U.S. delegation to NATO, which by that time had moved from
                    London and was in Talleyrand and was becoming very important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you make any trips to Germany? I think you mentioned
                        yowent to Yugoslavia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Everywhere. I went everywhere I could possibly go. Anytime I had the
                    so-called bridge, which was a holiday on Thursday, I took the bridge and went
                    someplace. So I went all over Europe, yes. I didn't go to Berlin when I was in
                    Germany. I never saw the great destruction, which I regret very much. It was
                    mainly Wiesbaden or Frankfurt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said you made a trip to Yugoslavia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, I made a trip to Yugoslavia in April 1951.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you talk a little bit about your impressions of
                        Yugoslaviat that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>BURTON: That was a fascinating trip, because a friend of mine who was consul
                    general at Zagreb got permission to take me with him on his tour of the diocese.
                    We took boats down to Dubrovnik, stopping off in the islands. He had sent a car
                    down, which, by the time it got to Dubrovnik, was not only devoid of tires but
                    also wheels, so we had to wait there for a couple of days for the wheels to turn
                    up. And then we drove back through Mostar and Banja Luka to Zagreb. It was
                    horribly expensive, because the dinar was pegged at 50 whatever, and you got 500
                    in Trieste, so that will give you some idea, if you had to play it straight. And
                    there was very little food. There was no coffee, no sugar. I can't say little
                    food. There was food, but it was very limited. And they warned you that when you
                    went out in the islands that you might run into trouble with getting any kind of
                    food. There were hotels; they were running. They were very primitive. I went to
                    the various islands, to Rab, to Kor_ula, to Dubrovnik, and then down to Kotor.
                    It was a beautiful trip. There were absolutely no outside people of any kind. We
                    were followed the whole time. At one point, particularly in Kor_ula, someone
                    told us that anyone that we spoke to was being hauled in and interrogated. So we
                    were very careful who we spoke to from then on. I remember that there was an AID
                    agent in Dubrovnik that we went up into the mountains with, into the villages. I
                    don't know what he was doing. I used to see him around Washington afterwards.
                    But the friend I was traveling with became an authority on Yugoslavia and wrote
                    some books on its potential development. It was about a year after the
                    separation from communism.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were mentioning that Sarajevo was not a friendly place
                        athat point.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Well, all of it was not friendly. You got this feeling, as I say, of
                    being followed, and you had to be careful. But other than that, people were very
                    pleasant. They implored you for food. They were asking if you could possibly
                    send them some sugar or some coffee or something like that.</p>
                <p>One thing I can remember, it's coming back to me now, we took a boat from Rab, I
                    think it was, down to Zara and put in at Zara overnight. And my friend started
                    talking to somebody on the boat that night. There were soldiers all over the
                    boat, sleeping and singing all over the decks. This man that he spoke to wasn't
                    on the boat the next day, and he had intended to be. So it was sinister.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I take it the road system was almost nonexistent, or was
                        it easto drive?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Roads were very poor. There was nobody on the roads at all,nothing, as I
                    remember. We had a car and a driver.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get into Czechoslovakia?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>BURTON: No. No, no, we just drove from Dubrovnik down to Kotor, back again, and
                    then up through Bosnia through Mostar and Banja Luka and then to Zagreb.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were back in Paris, your job was NATO. You were
                        dointhat from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I think it was probably from around 1952 to maybe 1954. There, I really
                    did take care of the statistics. All of the statistics that came in from
                    Washington for all of the NATO countries, like off-shore procurement and
                    military assistance and defense budgets, all of that came over my desk. And I
                    stashed it away and kept it, so that if anybody came into the Marshall Plan
                    office there and wanted to know what we were doing for Turkey, or if the defense
                    minister from Turkey came to see the head of the NATO staff, they would have to
                    come to me to get the latest figures.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find this a form of power?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: No, not particularly. It was just a service. But I cornered the market.
                    Oddly enough, I've made most of my jobs in my life. It's a question of getting
                    in and sniffing around to see what needs to be done and doing it. Then, usually,
                    if you propose it right, they'll accept it. This has happened to me two or three
                    times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any particular problems in early NATO that you
                        saw?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: No, not at all. There were the great NATO meetings in Paris twice a year,
                    which meant that we were literally working 24 hours a day. The big noises would
                    go in the front offices, the officers and whatnot, and they'd come out at 7
                    o'clock in the morning, in deciding what they were going to do, how much money
                    they were going to give to this, that, and the other thing. They were just, at
                    that point, rearming Germany. And it was very exciting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the French play much of a role, from your perspective,
                        owere you pretty much tied to the Americans?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I had nothing to do with the French, as such. France wasn't any more
                    important than Turkey or Austria or any of the others. We just happened to be
                    located there. Of course, the French kicked us out later and sent NATO to
                    Brussels.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Within your sphere of working, who was the top boss that
                        you had?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>BURTON: I had a lot of them. William Draper, Sr., was one. A man named Milton
                    Katz was another. Averell Harriman was another. We used to laugh about Harriman,
                    because if something nice would happen, he'd come in at 5 o'clock and tell us to
                    take the afternoon off. They were all head of the U.S. delegation to NATO, and
                    those were the ones that I was working for. But I had somebody in between. I
                    remember a few of them. Q: Was the NATO staff that you were dealing with pretty
                    much civilian?</p>
                <p>BURTON: No, it was almost totally military.</p>
                <p>Q: You were dealing with a fairly technical part of NATO—statistics. Did the
                    military members work with you, or did they pretty much leave you alone to do
                    this?</p>
                <p>BURTON: I worked for them. Captain Shepard was one. And then a man named Admiral
                    Strauss, who's a personal friend at this point, was another. Whoever was at the
                    top of NATO would tell them what they wanted, that, for instance, the Turkish
                    defense minister was coming, and he would have to present such and such and so,
                    and he would come down to me to get the figures. That's how it worked.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there around '54 or so?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I think around '54, yes. If they needed a job done, they would look
                    around in Paris. It was less expensive, I guess, to get somebody in Paris, if
                    they could find them, than it was to recruit from the United States. Then I had
                    an offer of a very good job over in the Coordinating Committee, which was a
                    secret committee at that point. It was located in an old hotel off the Faubourg
                    Saint-Honor�, with a very small staff. It was a committee of the war allies to
                    keep strategic materials from getting to the Sino-Soviet bloc. We set up a
                    system of licenses and checkpoints and got the other governments to cooperate
                    with us. So that if we had a notice of a shipment coming in that might have been
                    transshipped in Rotterdam or Godinya, we'd notify the Dutch government and warn
                    them about it, and maybe they'd catch it, and maybe they wouldn't. We acted as
                    the regional center to disseminate this information to the embassies, and they,
                    in turn, would notify the cooperating governments to stop these shipments if
                    they could. They would go down and check the ships and check their manifests,
                    and sometimes they stopped them, and sometimes they'd already gone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you're talking about stopping shipments, what are we
                        talkinabout?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>BURTON: Ball bearings, for instance, or copper rod, at that point, and
                    theodolites were another one. I had a couple of CIA people working for me that
                    were quite remarkable. One of them could read Russian upside down about nine
                    feet away. He had perfect eyesight. I'd say, “There's a report of some ball
                    bearings coming in to Rotterdam headed for diversion. Why don't you go out and
                    see what you can find?” And he'd come back the next day and say, “They're gone;
                    they're already off.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were efforts by the Soviet Union to get these
                        things.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, they wanted the things they were missing. There were people, just
                    like the drug trade, that were in diversion activities. We worked very closely
                    with the drug people, actually, because usually people that are in one
                    underhanded business are in the other, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there much in the way of enforcement, if they would
                        catcthem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, yes, a lot, but it was done by the local governments. For instance,
                    I can remember my boss, Colonel Brown, going to Switzerland and intercepting a
                    railroad shipment of uranium sulfate, the stuff you make bombs out of. He came
                    back with a little vial of this “curry powder,” and he said, “Betty, you're
                    going back to Washington for Christmas. Will you take this with you and turn it
                    over to X, Y, and Z.” I said, “Sure,” and I popped it into my pocketbook. I
                    didn't think anything about it, and came home and turned it over to the people.
                    Apparently, when they got it, the Geiger counter went through the ceiling. They
                    never caught me at all coming into the United States through Customs. They
                    caught someone else with some radium on their watch, but they didn't catch
                    me.</p>
                <p>Q: Were there any particular areas where the system was particularly good at
                    cutting out things, and other ones where you felt that there was considerable
                    leakage?</p>
                <p>BURTON: That's hard to remember. The leakage was through Rotterdam and Godinya,
                    mainly, the shipments there. And then there were leakages in Switzerland,
                    shipments that were headed for Austria. I don't know whether it was leakage, I
                    wouldn't say that. I'd just say that they would get through Switzerland to
                    Austria. And if they got into the Soviet bloc in Austria, they were gone, too.
                    We had to catch it before they got there. So we had to have this advice ahead of
                    time. It was a very elaborate check system of intelligence coming in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was it called, the apparatus? Was it COCOM?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>BURTON: Yes. It was short for Coordinating Committee. That's all it was called.
                    And then there was the section that dealt with the committee itself, who sat in
                    the sessions and decided, for instance, what would be banned from going and what
                    would be on the forbidden lists. And then they would turn it over to us in the
                    enforcement operation to see that it didn't get diverted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the secrecy about this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: This was right after the war, after all, and I think they just didn't
                    want the Soviets to know that they were getting together and keeping them from
                    getting this stuff (not officially, anyway), and that they were cooperating so
                    successfully, particularly with countries like Sweden and Austria that had
                    supplied the Soviets with ball bearings. After all those years, suddenly they
                    were not cooperating. Later on, we found that they ruined their markets and
                    caused the Soviet Bloc to become self-sufficient, so this wasn't a very good
                    idea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get your intelligence? Where was it coming
                        from?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: It's hard for me to remember. I just remember we used to get cables in. I
                    would dare say it was CIA that was informing us. Also, the drug people, who were
                    mainly operating out of Italy. We worked together; they would give us
                    information, and we'd give them ours. There were, for instance, big operations
                    in Vaduz, Liechtenstein, and places like that. There were groups of people that
                    we knew were doing this, so that if they applied for an export license, let's
                    say, out of New York, to ship copper, it would probably go automatically to CIA.
                    The CIA would check up, and if these people were the people from Vaduz, they'd
                    probably let us know, and say it's on it's way, better watch out. I think that's
                    probably how it worked, because we worked very closely with CIA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the feeling about Sweden? This was a major
                        producer othings, and it was neutral.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I can't remember any particular feeling about it. I do know that we
                    ruined their ball-bearing export market to the Soviets, which was unfortunate
                    for them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were doing this until about when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Until 1958, I think. Then I decided I should come home.I'd missed too
                    many boats, and I decided I needed to come home.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1956, did the Hungarian Revolution intrude at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>BURTON: Not in the slightest. The Suez situation certainly intruded on us
                    personally, because everybody was scared to death. The only other big scare was
                    the blockade of Berlin. General Rea O'Hare, who was the U.S. military attach� in
                    Paris, was a close personal friend, and he was giving me instructions what to do
                    and where to go to get out right away.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Hungarian Revolution and Suez were both around
                        October.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Suez made a lot of difference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the feeling, that Suez might be the beginning
                        osomething?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, Suez was a big business. Everyone was scared of the Suez situation.
                    It was really scary. There was a threat of oil being cut off and all that, for
                    France, England, everywhere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you noticing, as time was moving on during the '50s,
                        less-than-cordial reception of our efforts by the French?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Life became more difficult and more expensive during the 10 years I was
                    there. I suddenly realized what I was paying for lunch every day. It wasn't a
                    question of getting a little snack somewhere. It was $10 to go out and have a
                    little of this and that and the other thing. And the parking became unspeakable.
                    You had to have special arrangements for parking. Before that, you could park
                    anywhere. The availability of everything became easier. Living there was very
                    cheap. I had wonderful, wonderful apartments to live in, and I paid $60 a month.
                    And I had maid service for nothing that pleated my nightgowns and one thing and
                    another. We lived high on the hog for nothing, nothing. I was living on a very
                    small salary, and I didn't get any help from home. I was living very well,
                    indeed.</p>
                <p>Of some interest, the ready-to-wear (pr�t-�-porter) was prohibitively expensive
                    or did not fit Americans. Thus, everything that went on your back had to be made
                    to order: garments, shoes, hats, lingerie. Imagine today fitting a nightgown!
                    Stockings were available from the PX. My copiest made me a dress per season from
                    the current collections. The Maisons de Couture (fashion houses) would lend you
                    a dress overnight to wear to a party.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You decided to go home when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: About '58, I think it was. My parents came over, and I camhome with them
                    in the fall.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '58, what were you up to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Nothing. I didn't know what I was going to do. I just came back here with
                    the idea of transferring over to something here in Washington, which is what I
                    did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned that you'd been brought in to the Foreign
                        Servicunder the Wriston program.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, that was by accident. I really didn't know what was happening to me.
                    I was just living from day to day and enjoying myself, enjoying my work and my
                    life. Paris in the '50s was an enchantment. It was just marvelous living
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you picking up any impressions, towards the end when
                        yoleft, of De Gaulle?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: None. No. I wasn't much concerned. I never could understand French
                    politics, to begin with. Just the surface repercussions. He was concerned with
                    the glory of France and keeping it there. One can't blame him. He was a
                    tremendous unifying element.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you came back in '58, you were in the Foreign
                        Service, scould you go to the State Department and look for a job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes. But they put me in a job that was connected between the treaty
                    office and an office in AID, which ran the investment guarantee program. There
                    were three people in it at that point. Later on, it became the Overseas Private
                    Investment Corporation (OPIC) and now has about 150. That just shows you what
                    can happen. The authorizing legislation required an agreement to operate in the
                    cooperating countries, and I did that. First, the European countries, and then
                    the countries of Latin America, and, later on, all underdeveloped countries. So
                    this kept me busy for the rest of my career.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there particular points of things we had to have that
                        othecountries did not really care to give on these treaties?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>BURTON: Oh, yes, yes. I think the most important one was in Latin America, the
                    so-called Calvo Doctrine, where they had been ripped off in the 19th Century.
                    For instance, the expropriation of the oil industry in Mexico would be a case in
                    point. The main issue with all of these agreements was the expropriation. What
                    we did was to ensure against loss due to expropriations. This didn't mean that
                    they couldn't expropriate, but if they did, that we would pay any difference
                    between what they paid, let's say 20 cents on the dollar versus the full amount.
                    So it was to the interest of companies investing, let's say in a copper business
                    in Chile, to get this expropriation insurance. All of the countries of Latin
                    America, particularly the Andean code countries, did not want to involve
                    themselves in anything that would remove expropriation decisions out of their
                    country. And they made a great point that their supreme courts and whatnot were
                    very fair. This became an issue, and stayed an issue, until very recently. And
                    only recently I think it's been resolved. I think the NAFTA legislation, if
                    memory serves me right, was one of the great breakthroughs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: North American Free Trade Agreement.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: But this was only a few years ago that the Latin American countries began
                    to realize that if they didn't do what everybody else was doing, they were going
                    to be out of pocket in the long run. I think it's very interesting, because this
                    is affecting Europe and Central Europe, and Central Asia now. And they're all
                    coming and wanting the agreement, but they're going to have to crank up their
                    receptivity to foreign investment and have it in a treaty before they're going
                    to get any.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Essentially, this is insurance.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: This is insurance, insurance against inconvertibility, insurance against
                    loss due to expropriation and loss due to war risk, civil disturbances.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Hickenlooper Amendment also involved?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes. Yes, it was. But I can't remember what it was. Ihad to do with who
                    didn't sign the aid agreement, wasn't it?</p>
                <p>Q: As I recall, the Hickenlooper Amendment was that a country could expropriate
                    anything it wanted to, but if it didn't adequately compensate, then all aid
                    would be cut off. BURTON: Yes. I think that was one of our big, big problems.
                    Any of those kinds of things. I just couldn't remember; there were quite a few
                    legislative restrictions. We had a lot of problems in the negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did your office do? Was it sort of backstopping the
                        lawyers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I was the coordinator. I didn't have any law experience myself, but I was
                    working with at least four lawyers. One of them would be the legal advisor in
                    State for economic affairs, one the legal advisor for treaty affairs, and one
                    the legal advisor for any area that was involved. And they would have to sign
                    off on any of this. They were the prime commanders of any agreements. These were
                    executive agreements that didn't require ratification on our part. Then, later
                    on, I was the only one in OPIC, so to speak, that was handling this. Later on,
                    we got other lawyers that were helping me out. But I would train them. For
                    instance, one of them handled nothing but Latin America, as he spoke Spanish and
                    was able to renegotiate some of these Latin American agreements that needed to
                    be redone. As I left, I was setting up the agreements for the Gulf countries and
                    also for Micronesia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you think of any countries that were the most
                        trouble?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, I should say so. Nigeria. Nigeria was dreadful. Q: What was the
                    problem with Nigeria?</p>
                <p>BURTON: Well, they're mean as snakes, anyway. They're very intelligent. And the
                    officials won't take any action unless everybody does it, so you can't get them
                    to agree on anything. And we had big claims there as a result of the Biafra War,
                    for instance. You couldn't get anybody to take a decision. I don't know how we
                    got the agreement through in the first place. We did, but then it was very
                    difficult.</p>
                <p>Oddly enough, the two places that are of interest were Cuba and Iran, where we
                    had nothing in Cuba, and in Iran, there was, I think, something like $40
                    million. Those claims went to the International Court in the Hague, and were
                    settled very easily, no problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were part of AID at this point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: We were part of AID until 1971. So I worked halfway between State and AID
                    until 1971. And then it was turned into the Overseas Private Investment
                    Corporation and became a separate government corporation. We were annexed to
                    State, and we were listed in the State Department address book. All of our cable
                    traffic went through State, and the State Department economic officer would
                    handle our affairs anywhere locally, except that if we had to do a lot of
                    traveling because there was nobody out there to take care of our affairs, and if
                    we ran into trouble, somebody would have to go out.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>Q: Did you find that there were times when your office was saying, “We've got to
                    get this guarantee,” and yet our embassy or our desk was saying, “Well, we
                    really want to get so and so to invest in this country, because we've got
                    political reasons and all this.” In other words, were you finding pressure
                    coming from the geographic bureaus to be easier?</p>
                <p>BURTON: No, I wouldn't say that. I would say that the pressure would come from
                    American companies that maybe wanted the coverage. And that would make it much
                    easier for us if we wanted to go into a country. I would say that in all of the
                    Islamic countries, they weren't the least bit interested until there was camel
                    that they wanted. Then they would start talking, but not until then.</p>
                <p>Of course, some of these countries were, at that time, very underdeveloped, and
                    still are... I can remember we got a cable in from Libya. I was asking, “Is
                    there any prospect of this agreement being concluded in the near future?” At the
                    end of the message I got back, it said, “There may be some prospect of success,
                    because the minister of economy is reputed to be able to read and write.”</p>
                <p>And then there was another famous cable that came in, I think from the Ivory
                    Coast, where there was a litany of what had happened, from the reporting
                    officer. It landed in the Congressional Record and a couple of other places in
                    the newspapers, because it just said what had happened to the documents, that
                    somebody had lost it, someone had disappeared, and someone had gone off to play
                    soccer with Togo and he wasn't due back for another six weeks. You know, just
                    total neglect on the part of the government of any serious business.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If you got these agreements, did they hold water once you
                        hathem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Oh, yes, I should say so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>BURTON: As I say, we had to take the claims to... The Iranian claims, for
                    instance, went to the Court of Justice in the Hague. And we had an OPIC officer
                    over there negotiating for us, presenting them to the Court in the Hague. They
                    all cleared through there, went through the process. They were based on the
                    fundamental agreements that the host country had agreed to. In the famous case
                    of Chile, they were exemplary in how they settled their claims. They
                    expropriated all the great copper investments in Chile, and they paid off on
                    everything. It took a long time. What would happen is that they would pay
                    whatever they paid on the dollar, let's say 40 cents on the dollar, and we'd
                    pick up the rest and pay the local investor the loss, and then we'd take over
                    the bonds, which might not be paid for 50 years. But the United States
                    government can afford to do that; a private company can't. We got our money
                    back, and they serviced their debt properly, so everybody was happy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any crises regarding servicing the debt?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: No, not at that time. Not in the case of Chile.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about Peru? At one point, they were taking over
                        AT&amp;T and, think, some other companies.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: We didn't have AT&amp;T covered. Wasn't the AT&amp;T in Chile? I think it
                    was. We didn't have them insured. Peru was probably one of the worst countries
                    we ever had to deal with. It was the number-one Andean code country, with this
                    Calvo clause. We never did get an agreement with Mexico on account of it. It's
                    in their constitution that they cannot agree to any outside arbitration, any
                    international arbitration, which was the final provision of the agreement, that,
                    ultimately, if we couldn't decide what we were going to do between the two
                    countries bilaterally, we'd go to the International Court of Justice. And they
                    wouldn't agree to this, ever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what happened with Mexico?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: It wouldn't agree to anything. We never operated there. Q: What was the
                    purpose of OPIC?</p>
                <p>BURTON: It grew out of the early aid assistance programs for Europe. They wanted
                    something that would supplement the grant aid programs, the outright grants, and
                    they hoped to get American investment to take the place of or to help the grant
                    aid programs to set up Europe after World War II. We operated only in Europe at
                    that time. Gradually, they got taken out of the programs of developed countries.
                    By that time, of course, the other countries had opened up, and so we operated
                    only in less-developed countries, as of a certain year. I don't remember what,
                    maybe early '70s.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were type of American firms were taking advantage of
                        this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: To begin with, these programs in the United States government were quite
                    different from similar programs in Germany, for instance, and Japan, which were
                    used as a sort of auxiliary of their what amounts to our Export-Import Bank. We
                    did it as an extra effort in the aid assistance programs. We had a small lending
                    program, as a lender of last resort for projects that were desirable in these
                    countries we wanted to help. And for businesses, let's say a cement plant that
                    could go in somewhere, by a U.S. business that had never operated outside of the
                    United States. So we removed the political risk.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were other countries—Germany, England, France,
                        others—tyininto this program in any way?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Not ours. They had their own. But they were nearly always export-import
                    tied in, which ours was not. The Germans had a very active program, and so did
                    the Japanese. We'd get together with them and exchange information on how things
                    were operating.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about countries such as Scandinavia dealing with
                        Tanzania?The Scandinavians seemed to love Nyerere and were putting a
                        big...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: They didn't have any programs. As I recall, Scandinavia never had
                    anything like it. Even their export-import things didn't operate that way. They
                    didn't have them. There were very few similar programs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left this when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Labor Day of 1986.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was that big cataclysmic problem in Iran in '79. Did
                        thiaffect what you all were doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Oh, yes. But, as I told you, we had practically no coveragthere. I think
                    there was $40 million worth of coverage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>BURTON: Just lack of investor interest, in the first place. It just didn't go in.
                    Didn't ask for it. After all, it was an insurance option, and people
                    volunteered, came in and asked for it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I guess the Iranians were taking care of their own. They
                        had oimoney, so it really wasn't an undeveloped country.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: No, it wasn't. I think you've got the answer to that, yes.</p>
                <p>Q: What about Africa?</p>
                <p>BURTON: We had big operations in Africa, yes. And I did all of the agreements
                    with all of the countries there, from the '60s. There were about 30 of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The American government was actually insuring these
                        things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did we do regarding many of the African
                        countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: There wasn't much investor interest, after all. If anybodcame in and
                    asked for it, they got it, but there wasn't much interest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the Pacific islands?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I took on the Pacific islands just before I left. I must have gone out
                    there something like eight times, and I covered all of them. I got agreements
                    with Papua New Guinea, Tonga, Fiji. One of the most fascinating places I went
                    was up in the Gilbert Islands, now Kiribati. I was there for a week, because
                    there was no way to get there than to get up and get back once a week on
                    weekends. And the Solomon Islands was another one that I did. Kiribati and the
                    Solomons never came through. I left before it was concluded, and nobody pursued
                    it. And then they had a terrible hurricane in the Solomons so that it was almost
                    impossible to get any response from the government on anything.</p>
                <p>Kiribati was the only place I encountered anti-female sexism. The beefy macho
                    officials had a hard time coping with a U.S. government female official. I put
                    on my grandmother's wedding ring and invented a husband and children. It helped,
                    but not much.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you do the Federated States of Micronesia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Just as I left, they were becoming independent, one or two of them. After
                    all, it broke off into five separate units. There was a Federation of
                    Micronesia, and there were the Marianas and then there were the Marshall
                    Islands. And they were all different, different status. And the ones that were
                    independent enough, I set them up just as I was leaving, and I don't really know
                    what's happened.</p>
                <p>Q: What was your impression of these islands? You had the agreement, but was
                    there much that they had to offer for people to invest in?</p>
                <p>BURTON: I know, they were such subsistence economies (in the case of Tuvalu, for
                    instance, my God, they have nothing but postage stamps to generate foreign
                    exchange), that if you got one project in there, it could make an enormous
                    difference for them. But it was awfully hard to convince them of this and to get
                    them to know what it was. Tonga was easy to cope with. They were very
                    intelligent about it and realized that if they could get money in there for,
                    let's say, a vanilla plantation, it would help. But it was awfully hard getting
                    anything through to some of the others. And it was awfully hard to get anybody
                    to negotiate with, because there is such a tiny level of operating officials
                    that have an education, and they're all the same ones. One thing that impressed
                    me was that they all know one another. In spite of the vast, vast distances, the
                    1,500 miles to Kiribati, for instance, everybody knows what's going on
                    everywhere in the region.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, they travel a lot.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: They travel a lot, and they all know one another, and they communicate.
                    They had a very good cooperating office of economic affairs in Fiji. If you got
                    something going in one place, they would be interested. You had to hit the eye
                    of the octopus, so to speak. It was very interesting to me, the whole area, but
                    unfortunately I left right sort of two-thirds of the way through it. And then it
                    collapsed. Nobody, I don't think, cared much after that. It's a shame, because I
                    think it's a very, very important area. For instance, in Kiribati there was a
                    terrible squawk here because they gave the Soviets a million dollars' worth of
                    business in the area, fishing rights. Well, a million dollars means an enormous
                    amount to them. Here, it's the 1,500 miles of islands between Hawaii and the
                    Philippines, and nobody's paying any attention to it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Japanese are in there now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: They were in there all the time, sniffing around everywhere.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that the Japanese were playing a different
                        gamthan, say, the Americans as far as this area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: No, except that they were moving in a lot into Micronesia, particularly
                    Guam and Pilau and places like that, with hotels, and getting the local people
                    who owned the land to support them, and doing backdoor deals in order to
                    circumvent land rights and those kinds of things. The Americans weren't being
                    very clever about it and let them go.</p>
                <p>Micronesia was administered by the U.S. Department of Interior, and they were not
                    very interested. I had a terrible time getting anybody interested in it. The
                    people who were, realized how vital it was, but they were very few and far
                    between. A marvelous man was in charge of the area for AID, a man named William
                    Paupe, but he left right after I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you sort of quit government, was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: Yes, I quit government entirely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '86. BURTON: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you left, did you feel that the United States had
                        made mucof an impact in these areas where you were working on
                        agreements?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: I think it was very, very useful at the time. As I say, we have these
                    financial projects, where we were the investors of last resort, some of them
                    quite small, that would not have been realized without us. I think that,
                    particularly during the Reagan administration, they missed the boat, because
                    they were supporting some of the great big oil companies, let's say going into
                    China and into other places, on the basis that we needed more oil and whatnot.
                    But the Congress didn't like it. They were saying, “What are you doing
                    supporting these big oil companies? They can take care of themselves. You're
                    losing track of the original purpose of this program, which was to help small
                    investors in countries where otherwise these projects could not have been
                    realized. In the case of oil, they're going to do it anyway.” So OPIC got into
                    trouble, and they almost didn't get their legislation renewed one year. Then
                    they had trouble about two years ago. I think they have a year or two to go.
                    Somebody will do something and keep it going, because they pay their own bills.
                    However, the early days after the war are really going. Now there are a lot of
                    private insurance companies that are into the business, and so why is there a
                    need for it? And these countries themselves are getting more sophisticated and
                    realizing that they've got to get their act together and put in their own
                    investment laws and their own investment structure, because if they don't do it,
                    they're not going to get the money they need. Asia is a case in point. We've got
                    big operations going in Asia.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, in many ways, what you were doing was sort of acting
                        as starter.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: As a starter. And I think there's a valid argument for saying that this
                    is not that useful anymore, as you consider that they're going to be saving
                    money and getting rid of things, except that, as I say, OPIC is one of the few
                    people that pay their own bills. It's an income-producing operation. And they're
                    only 150 people, so the main expense is paying retirement income.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, maybe we might stop at this point.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BURTON: All right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Great.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
