<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001056">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with John W. Shirley </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Information Series</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR JOHN W. SHIRLEY</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: G. Lewis Schmidt </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: November 21, 1989</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>Biographic Outline; Early Years in Yugoslavia And Hungary During WWII - Nazi
                    Occupation</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jock, I'm not going to talk much. I just want you to give
                        us a few remarks about your background and your education, how it was that
                        you got into the Service in the first place, and what motivated you to do
                        so. From that point, we'll simply go sequentially into your various
                        assignments and we'll cover various points there. So will you pick up from
                        here and start out with your background and your reasons for getting into
                        USIA work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I will preface talking about my background by telling the listener that
                    Lew Schmidt, who is interviewing me today, presided over the panel which
                    determined whether or not I was to enter the Foreign Service. Since he
                    presumably voted in favor of allowing me in he is responsible in part for any
                    subsequent mischief I may have done.</p>
                <p>To tell you how I first became interested in the Service I have to go back to
                    1939. I was a boy of eight, and my father and I sailed on his boat up the
                    Adriatic, eventually ending up in Split. We were there at the beginning of World
                    War II. I lived in Yugoslavia for two years, went to a boarding school in
                    Zagreb, and got my first taste of life in Eastern Europe. When the Germans
                    occupied Yugoslavia in 1941, my father and I attempted to return to the United
                    States. For a series of complicated reasons we got no further than Hungary,
                    where we still were at the outbreak of the U.S.-Japanese war.</p>
                <p>You'll remember that Japan attacked us on December 7, and four days later, on
                    December 11, 1941, Germany declared war on the United States. After that, we
                    were no longer able to leave Hungary, so I spent the entire war there, mostly in
                    a very good boarding school. I experienced the German occupation of Hungary — a
                    vicious period in Hungarian history — and experienced also the siege of
                    Budapest, the Soviet conquest of Budapest, and about nine months of the Soviet
                    occupation of Hungary.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>I witnessed things during the last months of the war and particularly during the
                    Soviet occupation, which marked me for life. By the age of 14 I was determined
                    to spend my life doing whatever little I could to reverse the process which the
                    Russians launched in 1944. That is shorthand for wanting to fight communism.</p>
                <p>There followed another year of Eastern European life in Czechoslovakia.</p>
                <p>In 1946 I returned to the United States and went to military academy, as most of
                    my family had done before me. By then I had already decided that I wanted to go
                    into the Foreign Service or become a professional soldier.</p>
                <p>Towards the end of my last year at military school, I decided that the Foreign
                    Service was it. I went to the Georgetown University School of Foreign Service,
                    subsequently entered the Air Force, and served for four years in Germany and
                    Austria in an intelligence unit where most of my work was directed at
                    Hungary—I'm almost bilingual in Hungarian—and East Germany.</p>
                <p>Entry Into USIA, 1957-1958—Almost Immediately Assigned To Zagreb As Junior
                    Officer Trainee (JOT)</p>
                <p>Toward the end of my Air Force years I met Jack Stewart who at that time was with
                    the Munich Radio Center. Jack, to whom I used to take illegal border crossers to
                    be interviewed for the Voice, wrote a letter to Barry Zorthian. When I returned
                    to Washington, Barry passed me on to Henry Loomis who hired me as a GS-7 in IRI,
                    the acronym for our Research Office at the time. Shortly thereafter I took the
                    Foreign Service exam and, thanks to Lew Schmidt, came on board as a JOT in March
                    1958.</p>
                <p>I'll back up to say that I initially came into IRI as a contract employee
                    immediately after the Hungarian uprising of October - November 1956, and that my
                    first duty was to translate all of the tapes of the Hungarian Service of the VOA
                    for an investigation which was being conducted by a congressional committee to
                    see whether VOA had in any way encouraged the Hungarian freedom fighters to
                    believe that we were going to support them. The committee found the Hungarian
                    Service innocent of the charge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was either late in 1956 or early '57.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: We are now in '57. I took the Foreign Service exam in November, 1957,
                    and I was sworn in on March 15, 1958.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that time, USIA had come into existence as USIA, so you
                        were sworn into the U.S. Information Agency at that point.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes, I was. I was in the eleventh JOT class, and I requested an
                    assignment to Eastern Europe, specifically to Zagreb. I received the assignment
                    and reported to my post in July, 1958. I remained in Zagreb for one year.</p>
                <p>It was a very satisfying year. I was thrilled with my responsibilities, anxious,
                    as I suppose everyone is, to do as well as I possibly could. And I had an
                    exceptional opportunity to do so because the gentleman who was BPAO was not
                    notably active and frequently ill. More often than not, I was in charge of the
                    post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your RAO at the time? Or do you prefer not to put
                        that on tape?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Is the recorder on or off?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's on now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Please switch it off. [Tape recorder turned off]</p>
                <p>No, he wasn't a terribly active man, so I was often in charge, but even when I
                    wasn't, I was able to do a lot more than most JOTs are allowed to do.</p>
                <p>I remember one particular incident which I'll tell you about. Louis Armstrong
                    came to Yugoslavia in late 1958 or early 1959. It was the first time that any
                    American jazz musician had been anywhere in Eastern Europe. Armstrong was flying
                    from Le Bourget to Zagreb for a concert in Ljubljana that evening. His plane was
                    delayed. There was something wrong with the runway lights at the Zagreb airport
                    and they weren't going to let the plane land. I then spent an hour or more
                    persuading the Zagreb department of roads to provide those little smudge pots
                    they put on roads at night. We lined the runway with the smudge pots, and Louis
                    Armstrong landed. At the end of that long day I felt that I had earned my
                    salary!</p>
                <p>1959: Assistant Cultural Affairs Officer (CAO) Belgrade</p>
                <p>When my JOT year in Zagreb was over, Heath Bowman, who was Country PAO, asked me
                    to come down to Belgrade to replace Phil Arnold, as Assistant CAO and an
                    Exhibits Officer. I happily accepted because I had already come to have enormous
                    respect for Heath, who, in many ways, was the most professional PAO I ever
                    worked for, but also with some feeling of trepidation, because I knew nothing
                    about exhibits. I felt ready to make foreign policy decisions, but I wasn't
                    quite ready to build exhibits!</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>My year in Belgrade — mid-1959 to September of 1960 — was a happy one. It was a
                    splendidly exciting time to be in Yugoslavia. Everything we did, from a small
                    window exhibit to a pavilion-sized show was seen by tens of thousands of people.
                    We were a window on America, a window on the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to ask a couple of questions now, partly going
                        back to Zagreb, but also getting into Yugoslavia. First of all, what was the
                        nature of your effort in Zagreb? Was there something in particular that you
                        were aiming at, or were you just taking events as they came along, running a
                        standard USIS program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I arrived in Zagreb thinking that I was going to be trained, but I
                    didn't get much of that. I was initially assigned specific projects. Fairly
                    soon, perhaps after two or three months, I was engaged mainly in picking up the
                    pieces dropped by the BPAO and in running the post. Towards the end, things got
                    awkward, particularly when Heath Bowman began communicating with me directly
                    instead of going through the BPAO.</p>
                <p>I remember that the first thing I was required to do was to write a report on
                    Zagreb's English-teaching program, which ten years later I would have considered
                    an excruciatingly boring task, but which at the time I thought was splendidly
                    stimulating. No, Zagreb was a good time.</p>
                <p>Being Exhibits Officer in Belgrade was intimidating. The only talent I brought to
                    the job was good taste, which Heath said I had. Did I find it satisfying? Yes, I
                    did, for the reason I mentioned to you before. People were so hungry for
                    anything Western, and particularly American. Attendance at exhibits was huge and
                    perhaps with the exception of the Voice of America, the tool through which we
                    could reach the largest number of Yugoslavs. Money spent on exhibits in
                    Yugoslavia was money well spent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This, of course, was some years after Tito had broken with
                        the Soviet Union. And I wondered what kind of experience you had in
                        Yugoslavia with reference to the attitude of the people toward America. You
                        said they were extremely interested in learning things about the United
                        States. Was there any overcast or overtone of antipathy toward the U.S., or
                        was it basically an open feeling about the Americans?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: People who have experienced communism like Americans, because to them
                    Americans are the antithesis of communism. Yugoslavs had certainly experienced
                    communism in an extreme form between 1944 and the break with the Cominform in
                    1948. Tito gradually loosened the screws, and by the time I got there in 1958,
                    ten years after the break with the Cominform, things had eased considerably, but
                    the system was still communist, indeed it still is today, 35 years later.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>Almost everybody in Yugoslavia had an uncle or a cousin or an aunt in the United
                    States. People were conspicuously friendly to Americans. It's always easy to be
                    an American in a communist country because the population looked to us as their
                    only real source of hope.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather, however, that the government still had its
                        suspicions, and I base this on a very limited experience. When I was in the
                        War College, since I had never been to Europe, I elected to take the
                        European trip. They always broke the War College into four or five groups
                        and visited different regions. I chose Europe, and that was the one year we
                        went both to Soviet Union and to Yugoslavia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Although the people seemed friendly enough, and the army seemed especially
                    friendly and very critical of the Soviet Union; nevertheless, we were watched.
                    We were stopping with a group of about 30 or 35 of us as part of a War College
                    group, and we were there at the official invitation of the Yugoslav government.
                    Nevertheless, I could see the gumshoes sitting across from me in the hotel lobby
                    and watching me. There were several instances indicating that we were being
                    watched. So I just wondered. That apparently was a governmental activity and had
                    nothing to do with the general feeling.</p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes. But in the late 1950s, I cannot say that I ever felt that I was
                    under personal surveillance, certainly not constant surveillance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think this was occasional, but . . .</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I did not experience constant surveillance, as I did during periods of
                    service in Poland much later on. If I had had an affair with a Yugoslav girl, or
                    if I had been drinking too much, something of that kind, they probably would
                    have come at me to see whether I could be blackmailed. But I had no such
                    experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know that you speak a great number of languages, an
                        unusually large number. Did you pick up your Serbo-Croatian initially during
                        your period of residence in the country, or did you study it and gain most
                        of it thereafter?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: By the time I came into the Foreign Service, I spoke French, German,
                    Hungarian, and Serbo-Croatian. I had lost a lot of my Serbo Croatian, but it
                    came back to me fairly fast. Within about 90 days, 120 days, I was probably
                    speaking at the three-plus, three-plus level. I subsequently learned Italian and
                    Polish, so I guess that makes a total of six. But McKinney Russell is the
                    Agency's great linguist. I was merely a polyglot.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm curious, and if you don't mind, what was your father
                        doing in Eastern Europe at the time that the war began?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: My father was and, thank goodness, remains, an eccentric American who
                    was living on his boat in Split. He fell in love with the Czech wife of a White
                    Russian emigre at the beginning of the war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's an interesting reason and no doubt a very
                        satisfying one for one individual, at least.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: No. It was a disaster. He caught up with the lady after the war, married
                    her, spent a perfectly miserable six or seven years with her, and then divorced
                    her.</p>
                <p>I would like to add that I have worked for PAOs whom I have greatly admired, and
                    I don't want to pick out a single one as the best. But Heath Bowman, who was
                    never appreciated in the Service as he should have been, was an extraordinarily
                    effective officer and to have worked for him was an immensely valuable
                    experience. He was intelligent, methodical, strict and sometimes irascible. I
                    learned much from Heath. Most of all high standards. He was exacting and he
                    expected people to work at their best all the time. That spirit I subsequently
                    tried to adopt myself, and to inculcate in others who have worked for me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said you had this one final comment to make.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: That was it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My question was that you were in Belgrade handling the
                        exhibits program. Did you ever have the Atoms for Peace exhibit?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it would have been that time, because that was the
                        period from about '55 to '58 that the Atoms for Peace exhibit was being
                        shown very widely around the world.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Well, were did you go then from there? Is that when you went to Trieste?</p>
                <p>1960: Trieste, As Assistant Branch PAO, Ultimately To Branch PAO. Creates
                    Binational Centers In Several Posts Otherwise Slated For Closing</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes. I went to Trieste in September, 1960. Eddie Pancoast was PAO and I
                    reported to him as his Assistant PAO. I was with Eddie for about a year when he
                    was replaced by another person who stayed for less than a year. I was promoted
                    Branch PAO on the second officer's departure.</p>
                <p>Trieste was my first independent command. Even if I was only the skipper of a
                    torpedo boat instead of a destroyer or a cruiser, it was a very good feeling,
                    being skipper. For the first time in my career I had the opportunity to put some
                    of my own ideas to work.</p>
                <p>Toward the end of my tour in Trieste, Joe Phillips, the CPAO, called me up and
                    said that the Agency was going through one of its periodic cutting exercises and
                    that one of the posts to be closed was Trieste. I told him that I would like
                    time to reflect for a day or two about what might be done. I called back to say
                    that I thought that I could put together an Italo-American Association which
                    would be self-funding, and I recommended that the senior national employee in
                    Trieste be kept on the payroll. Joe liked the idea and asked me to create a
                    formula that could be used country-wide since Turin, Genoa, Florence and Palermo
                    were destined for the same fate as Trieste. I came up both with a plan for
                    Trieste and with a proposal on how to save the other posts as well.</p>
                <p>The experience of putting together a binational association and setting up a
                    series of English courses to fund the activity was great. The Association still
                    exists, 30-some years later.</p>
                <p>In general, the Trieste PAO experience was a good one. It gave me an opportunity
                    to plumb my depths. It put me in a position to learn a great deal about Italy. I
                    was Acting Principal Officer from time to time, so I also learned something
                    about that end of the business. And I wasn't just PAO for the Trieste Consular
                    District, I had the Venice Consular District as well. Apart from the pleasure of
                    working in Venice, I also gained an insight into Venetian society, Venetian
                    culture, and that of the surrounding cities.</p>
                <p>1963: Rome As Press Attach�</p>
                <p>In 1963, after I had completed three years in Trieste, Ambassador Reinhardt came
                    for a visit. I wrote some speeches for him and ran his schedule. He asked that I
                    come down to Rome in some capacity or other. Joe Phillips arranged this with the
                    Agency, and I went to Rome as Assistant Press and Publications Officer.</p>
                <p>Six weeks or so after my arrival in Rome, Bob Amerson, the Press Attach�, was
                    transferred to Bogota as PAO. The Agency was going to send in somebody else as
                    press attach�, but Joe and the Ambassador decided that I should take the job,
                    and they prevailed.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>In that Press Attach� job I felt that I was riding a whirl- wind because it was a
                    senior job and I had been precipitated into it very early in my career. At that
                    point I was an FSR 5 or 6,two grades below the established rank for the
                    assignment. But it worked out, and of my USIA experiences, I think the two most
                    satisfying were being press attach� in Rome, and later in New Delhi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As the press attach�, you were the Embassy spokesman
                        then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>A. Italian Reaction To Kennedy Assassination</p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes. I was the Embassy spokesman. I was the Ambassador's speech writer.
                    When the Ambassador's aide was not there, I was often asked to fill in.</p>
                <p>Let me tell you a story. Everyone remembers where he was when he learned that
                    President Kennedy had been assassinated. On the day the President was killed,
                    the Ambassador had to fly to Padua to make a speech. His aide was out of town,
                    so I was doubling in brass. We flew up to Padua in a military plane. He made his
                    speech, and we were flying back when the radio in the cockpit — about two feet
                    from our seats — crackled. The copilot turned around and waived me forward. I
                    put on the earphones and the Minister, Francis Williamson, said, “Please tell
                    the Ambassador that the President has been shot and is dying.” I turned, but
                    before I could say anything the radio came on again. I put the earphones back
                    on, and Francis Williamson said, “Say that the President has been assassinated.
                    He is dead.”</p>
                <p>We landed at the military airport in Rome in the midst of a crowd; half the
                    Embassy was there. I stayed up all night writing my first full-length speech for
                    Ambassador Reinhardt: It was a eulogy to President Kennedy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I presume, as in most countries it was true, that the
                        Italians were emotionally overcome, also, and expressed great feelings about
                        the death of the president. Or was it not so?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: You know, Lew, it was the most extraordinary outpouring of grief that I
                    have ever seen. President Kennedy was loved by the Italian people, perhaps for
                    some of the wrong reasons. They loved him because he was young and good-looking,
                    because he was virile and had a pretty wife. The Kennedy myth persists in Italy.
                    Only a couple of years ago, people would ask me when Senator Edward Kennedy
                    would become president. When I explained that he had no chance at all, Italians
                    were unbelieving.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>But back to your question. The day after the President was assassinated, I was
                    sitting in my office working the telephones. A man called and my secretary said:
                    “You must talk to this person.” Hundreds of people were calling, and one
                    couldn't talk to them all, but this one she said, I had to. The man came on the
                    line and said, “I want to tell you how sorry I am about the assassination of
                    your president.” I thanked him and wondered why his call had got through. But he
                    continued: “There is something else I want to tell you. I have never seen
                    President Kennedy because I am blind, but I stood on the street when President
                    Kennedy passed by in his motorcade when he visited Rome, and I felt him.” By
                    then I could hardly speak.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were still in Italy, did the film “Years of
                        Lightning, Day of Drums” come to Italy for showing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I can't remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because that was a film which reduced practically every
                        foreign audience that I was with when they saw it to tears.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes. I saw the film a couple years later, in New Delhi with an Indian
                    audience, and you're absolutely right. It was the most moving film the Agency
                    ever made, perhaps the best film the Agency ever made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you know who made it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes. Wasn't it Bruce—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bruce Herschensohn.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Bruce Herschensohn made it, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would you say were the major accomplishments during
                        your period in Italy of the USIS program? Or don't any of them stand out as
                        particular highlights?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>B. Doubts About Continuation Of Some Long Standing USIS Activities In Italy</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I had some doubts then, as I did subsequently when I was CPAO in Rome,
                    about the effectiveness of a number of our programs. I thought that even then,
                    and I'm taking you back to 1963, there were programs which should already have
                    been eliminated and which were pretty expensive. We were not as bureaucratic
                    then as I think we have become in the intervening years, but it still took a
                    while to stop doing the things that were undoubtedly useful in the '40s, and
                    perhaps in the early '50s, when a magazine produced by us was a rare treasure.
                    By the mid-1960s, the people we were sending our publications to were already
                    suffering from information overload and hardly looked at what we sent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said that Joe Phillips was the PAO when you went to
                        Rome. Did he stay during all the time you were there, or did you get a new
                        PAO?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: The PAOs during my tenure were Mickey Boerner, then Joe Phillips for
                    most of my tenure in Rome, and finally Gordon Ewing.</p>
                <p>If I look back over a more than 30-year career in USIA, and if you asked me to
                    name of the person for whom I had the greatest personal affection, it would be
                    Joe Phillips; because of his grace, because of his manners, because of his
                    style, and because of his substance. Gordon Ewing and I also became close
                    friends, but Joe was much older than I and something of a father figure. He was
                    also a very comprehending, experienced and sympathetic chief.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And who were the Deputy PAOs when you were in Italy,
                        particularly when you were in Rome?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Ed Schechter was the Deputy PAO for a good part of the time, a man whose
                    Central European origins — he is Viennese, as you perhaps remember — made him
                    particularly good company to me. I listened carefully to what he said, and
                    minded not at all taking direction from him.</p>
                <p>I forget the next person to come along, perhaps because he was so
                    forgettable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that by any chance Dick Salvatierra?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes, it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dick felt he was out of place in Rome. He was essentially
                        a Latino by persuasion and experience, and I don't think he ever felt at
                        home in the Roman situation.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I would have to agree with your judgment that he was not comfortable in
                    Rome. I don't think he particularly liked Italians. I don't think he liked being
                    in a huge embassy, and I don't think he liked me. He didn't like the way I
                    spoke, and there was something about me and my manner he found off-putting. The
                    period between Joe's departure and Gordon's arrival was not a happy one for me.
                    Come to think of it, he gave me the only negative efficiency report I ever had.
                    Perhaps that's another reason why my memory of him is not so hot. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>C. Role Of USIS (Through Ed Schechter) In The 1963 Effort To Promote An Opening
                    To The Left</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't think we fully covered the question of whether you
                        thought there was any outstanding accomplishment or program in USIS during
                        your period in Italy. If you don't, or whether you do or not, I'd also like
                        to ask you a question. Ed Schechter is very proud of the role that he played
                        in the attempts of the embassy to further the opening to the left in Italy.
                        Did you have any part in that, or what was your opinion of that effort?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: No, I did not. I did not because I was too junior and because nobody was
                    asking my opinion about the opening to the left. I had an opinion which was, and
                    is, immaterial in terms of what happened. Ed was very sophisticated about
                    Italian politics. He had a wide-ranging group of contacts—to use one of our
                    favorite words—among important people. His Italian was excellent, even though he
                    spoke it with a heavy German accent through a pipe.</p>
                <p>He was very effective in carrying the Embassy's message to the press, and to a
                    lot of Italian political figures, as well. So if it is his judgment that he had
                    an influence, I would take him at his word and I would certainly concur in that
                    judgement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you, at this point, have any further comments and
                        suggestions or observations about your experience in the Italian
                        program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Not really. I probably will have some things to say when I get to my
                    tenure in Rome as Country PAO, but you're about 12 years away from that, I'm
                    afraid.</p>
                <p>Press Attach�, New Delhi 1965</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. Well, let's go on to your next assignment then. Was
                        that your New Delhi assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes, it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What year was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: We're now in the summer of 1965, the early summer of 1965. I was already
                    assigned to the Armed Forces Staff College, but Ambassador Bowles wanted an
                    experienced press attach�, and there were not that many in the Agency at the
                    time. So instead of Norfolk, I went to New Delhi.</p>
                <p>I came back to Washington in July of 1965. Ambassador Bowles happened to be in
                    town and I called on him to be looked over. He was a person whose name I had
                    known for many years. He had been Deputy Secretary of State, or Under Secretary
                    as it then was called, in the first year of the Kennedy Administration, and then
                    Ambassador-at-Large, and then he went back to India as ambassador for a second
                    time.</p>
                <p>He was an awesome figure for a young officer suddenly to be confronted with, and
                    I arrived at Ambassador Bowles' house in Washington—a friend's house,
                    actually—to find the Ambassador and Mrs. Bowles there, Mrs. Bowles wearing a
                    sari, as she almost always did. Bowles said: “We'll try you out. We have six or
                    seven Indian journalists arriving in a few minutes, and I'd like you to run the
                    press conference.”</p>
                <p>A: Baptism Of Fire: Outbreak Of Indo-Pakistan War</p>
                <p>I apparently passed the test and was told to get to Delhi as quickly as I could.
                    I arrived in Delhi, and I remember being met by my colleague, Merrill Miller.
                    Merrill took us to our hotel, which was the Delhi Claridge, not London Claridge,
                    I'm sorry to say. I went to bed at about 4:00 in the morning — planes in Delhi
                    always arrive at that time. Two hours later, I got a call to report to the
                    Embassy. A car fetched me, and off I went. When I arrived, I was told to report
                    to the Ambassador's office where we learned that Indian and Pakistani forces had
                    clashed in the Punjab and that there was a war on. Would I please get to
                    work?</p>
                <p>I had a glimmering of where the Punjab was, and I knew that Indians and
                    Pakistanis did not get on particularly well. Happily, my grandfather — I have an
                    English mother and her father was a career officer in the British Army — had
                    spent 20 years in India, and I had been brought up by him until I was six. I was
                    steeped in the lore of British India, but it was Mr. Kipling's India, not Mr.
                    Nehru's. Still it got me by the first weeks, and I did know quite a lot about
                    the military situation which fascinated me.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Within 24 hours we had 50 American correspondents on the ground, and within 48
                    hours perhaps 75 or 80. I did a morning briefing and afternoon briefing, always
                    after consulting with the Defense Attach�, with the Ambassador, with the DCM,
                    and with the Political Counselor, trying quickly to learn what was going on and
                    working out how to say it without getting the Embassy creamed by the Indians who
                    weren't telling anyone anything. I worked harder and with greater pleasure and
                    more enthusiasm than I ever had in my life before. It was a glorious week or ten
                    days of really being engaged and very quickly getting to know my way around.</p>
                <p>B: Happy Relationship With Ambassador Chester Bowles</p>
                <p>If you should ask me—which you haven't—which tour I considered my best tour
                    professionally, at which stage I performed the most efficiently, at which stage
                    I found my work the most satisfying, and at which stage in my life I had the
                    greatest chief, I would pick those three years in India with Chester Bowles.</p>
                <p>It's curious in life how one sometimes has chemistry with a person, even if one
                    has very different views of the world. Chester Bowles was a liberal's liberal,
                    and I was a prototypical Tory, but we got on famously.</p>
                <p>There were some interesting people on Ambassador Bowles' personal staff. Dick
                    Celeste, who is now Governor of Ohio, was his aide. Doug Bennet, who is now
                    president of National Public Radio, formerly Director of AID, formerly Assistant
                    Secretary for Congressional Relations, was his principal speechwriter, although
                    Doug left shortly after I arrived when I took on that responsibility.</p>
                <p>You know, press attach�s do not, as a rule, make their careers by disagreeing
                    with the chief of mission, or by arguing in a senior staff meeting, arguing
                    against something which an ambassador proposes. But Chester Bowles always
                    encouraged me to do just that, and always listened, even when I was speaking
                    nonsense. He also taught me whatever I know about writing. You'll remember that
                    Chester Bowles and Bill Benton were the founders of Benton and Bowles, and that
                    they practically invented market research. And Ambassador Bowles knew how to
                    write. Initially, it was a terrifying experience to write for him, but I learned
                    how to let myself into his mind. By the middle of my three-year tour, I was able
                    to write for him things which he changed very little. What he changed always
                    made it more felicitous, but in the main he let stand what I put before him. I
                    also had the opportunity in Delhi to be Staff Aide for quite long periods when I
                    would be both Staff Aide and Press Attach�. It was a fine opportunity to get an
                    overview of the work of an embassy, to understand the responsibilities of an
                    ambassador, and to learn what a diplomatic mission could and could not do. The
                    experience served me extremely well in later years.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>When I was a chief of mission myself, I thought back on those early years in the
                    Foreign Service and on the lessons learned from Chester Bowles. We became close
                    personal friends. Our house in Connecticut is only a 20-minute drive from his,
                    so I continued to see him after he retired. When he retired, he asked me to
                    leave the Service and do a column with him, but I couldn't afford it. I'm sorry
                    we didn't have that experience together. There was so much more that I could
                    have learned from him, but he was already in bad health and perhaps it would not
                    have worked.</p>
                <p>I might add about my Delhi experience that Bill Miller was PAO. There are so many
                    Bill Millers, but I refer to Delhi Bill Miller.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of them has died. Bombay Bill Miller died.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes, I heard that. Delhi Bill Miller was a good PAO. He understood that
                    it was valuable for him to have a press attach� who was close to the ambassador,
                    as I think I was. I kept him abreast of everything that went on in the chancery,
                    and we saw each other at least once a day. A lesser man might not have enjoyed
                    the fact that one of his subordinates spent more time with the ambassador than
                    he did.</p>
                <p>C: Indian Tendency To Moralize And Criticize America Was And Is Maddening</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At this time, of course, Henry Kissinger made his famous
                        statement that, “I guess we're leaning toward Pakistan.” Did that happen
                        while you were there, and did you have to put up with the reaction to that
                        statement?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I don't remember that Kissinger said it, but there was a general feeling
                    in India that we had a pro-Pakistani bias. I think it was probably right that we
                    did, and I think we had a pro-Pakistani bias for good reasons, the most public
                    of which was that the Indians constantly gave us a bad time.</p>
                <p>Indians have a tendency to moralize, which at best is irritating and, at worst,
                    maddening. I remember an incident, and I was very much involved in this, which
                    illustrates the point.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>In 1967, the crop had been catastrophic and about 40 million people in Bihar and
                    Uttar Pradesh were threatened with famine. A congressional delegation came:
                    Congressman Pogue, who was then Chairman of the House Agricultural Committee;
                    Congressman—now Senator—Dole; and then-Senator Miller of Iowa. Ambassador Bowles
                    sent Herb Spivack, the Political Counselor, and me with the delegation to tour
                    the famine-struck areas. The group returned to the U.S. persuaded that help was
                    needed.After a long travail, Lyndon Johnson signed off on an agreement to give
                    India ten million tons of grain. And on that day Indira Gandhi sent a birthday
                    cable to Ho Chi Minh. Lyndon hit the roof, and justifiably so. Ambassador Bowles
                    had to use every bit of his considerable political influence in Washington not
                    to have us go back on the agreement.</p>
                <p>But it was that kind of thing which made Indians difficult to deal with and which
                    no doubt contributed to our pro-Pakistan “tilt.”</p>
                <p>Effectiveness And Value Of USIS Indian Program</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. I must confess that my own contact with the Indians
                        has been very limited, and yet it's been enough so that I have almost
                        automatically been irritated with Indian contacts. I've had a few very good
                        Indian friends, but of all the people's I've encountered, they probably
                        irritate me more than any other foreign people I know. Do you have any other
                        observations about your tour in India, or any observations on the general
                        efficacy of the USIA program there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes, much more so than in Italy. Virtually everything the post did in
                    India was worthwhile.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “Span”.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes. “Span,” for instance, was an excellent, widely read magazine. We
                    also had a good twice-monthly news- paper. The cultural program, at least
                    exhibits and cultural presentations, that sort of thing, was rather less
                    important, and money spent on such things was probably wasted. On the other
                    hand, funds for the exchange program were well handled and yielded good
                    returns.</p>
                <p>The USIS post in India had an impact in both the long and short term. We
                    certainly did everything we could to make known our views through the press,
                    tried to insure that our views were accurately reflected, and spent a good deal
                    of time working with the Indian intellectual community.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, of course, first of all, the program in India cannot
                        be a mass program in the usual sense of the word because there is such a
                        vast difference in educational opportunities for the very low classes in
                        India and the poor, as compared with the more or less elite. But you really
                        feel that the program that USIS carried out in India did, then, have a
                        substantial effect upon those people who were in the educated and
                        knowledgeable class?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes. I think that it had the effect of bringing to a limited number of
                    people information and views they otherwise would not have had, or would not
                    have considered. The role of Ambassador Bowles in the USIS context was critical,
                    of course. He was an excellent PAO. The combination of the USIS program,
                    bolstered by the work of an exceptional ambassador, made a difference.</p>
                <p>I might tell you an anecdote.</p>
                <p>Stalin's Daughter, Svetlana Alliluyeva, Defects To U.S. Embassy</p>
                <p>One evening I was at the German Embassy at a dinner. One of the house servants
                    came and called me to the phone. Dick Celeste was on the line and he said that I
                    was to drop my knife and fork and come to the Embassy. I made my excuses and
                    left. I walked into the Ambassador's office and was told that we had “a
                    walk-in,” which was the term we used to describer a defector. I asked who it
                    was, and was told: “Stalin's daughter.”</p>
                <p>That was the evening that Svetlana Alliluyeva walked into the Embassy and made a
                    little bit of history.</p>
                <p>We managed to get her out of India the same night, on a Quantas flight to Rome.
                    There the story broke. I started getting telephone calls from every news
                    organization in the United States, but I couldn't say anything as we were deep
                    in talks with the Swiss about obtaining asylum for her there. I could not even
                    say, “no comment,” or “I really don't have anything for you on that,” since that
                    would have been tantamount to an admission. For hours I just had to fake it. I
                    couldn't lie to the press, but I could dissimulate: “What? Can't hear you. Bad
                    connection,” and so on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I had forgotten. When the story finally broke, was the
                        Swiss connection then disconnected? Did she go immediately to the United
                        States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: No. She stayed in Rome only a few hours, after about twelve hours in the
                    air from Delhi to Rome. The USG used those hours to negotiate with the
                    Swiss.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>A small parenthesis here about good diplomacy. Bowles did not want to put
                    Secretary Rusk in the position of having to decide what to do with her, so he
                    made the decision for him. He sent a flash cable to Rusk, but timed it so that
                    he would receive it when Svetlana was already on the way from the Embassy to the
                    airport. We knew, of course, that from the arrival of the cable in the
                    Operations Center until the time somebody with sufficient authority to wake up
                    the Secretary of State could be found, it would be too late for Rusk to involve
                    himself in the decision. Bowles gave Rusk deniability which he needed since he
                    was involved at the time in a sensitive negotiation with the Soviets.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long was she in Switzerland?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Six or seven weeks. Then she came to the United States. Since then,
                    she's been bouncing around.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, do you think that pretty well covers your experience
                        in Delhi, then? Do you want to go on to subsequent activities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I think exhaustively for the unfortunate person who has to listen to
                    this tape.</p>
                <p>1969: Return To Washington. Various Positions In Near East, South Asia Area
                    Office Then (1970) PAO Poland</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, it's all very interesting, and I think it's well to
                        get it on tape. Where did you go from Delhi, then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: From Delhi, I went back to Washington, first as Desk Officer for India,
                    Ceylon, and Nepal, an experience I found not very stimulating. Being a desk
                    officer was okay, but India had been so exciting, so pleasurable, and I had been
                    so close to Ambassador Bowles. I had felt that I was doing things that mattered.
                    To then suddenly find myself writing tedious letters to the PAO about the budget
                    was pretty grim.</p>
                <p>Henry Stevens was the Policy Officer in the Near East South Asia area office.
                    Alan Carter was Area Director, and a very good one. David Nalle was his Deputy.
                    Two very different people who made a good team. When Henry died — about four
                    months or so into my assignment — I was asked to take on the Policy Officer job.
                    It was preferable to being a desk officer, but I didn't much enjoy it.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>But salvation was at hand. Frank Shakespeare, — we're now in early 1969 — went on
                    a trip in Eastern Europe, and returned unhappy. He wanted changes. He felt that
                    only the Agency's “best” should serve in that part of the world. At about the
                    same time John Reinhardt asked whether I wanted to be PAO in South Africa. I was
                    on the verge of saying yes, when Pic Littell, who was East Europe Soviet Union
                    Area Director, offered me PAO Warsaw. I plunged into Polish language training
                    for a year, and in July of 1970 went to Poland. Life suddenly became exciting
                    again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there at the beginning of the Solidarity movement
                        then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Oh, no. I arrived in Warsaw in mid-1970. Solidarity didn't really get
                    going until '78, eight years later. But about six months after we arrived, just
                    a few days before Christmas 1970, there was an uprising on the Baltic coast. It
                    ended with the defenestration of Mr. Gomulka and his replacement by Mr.
                    Gierek.</p>
                <p>My ambassador was Walter Stoessel, a man whom I greatly admired. Indeed, we
                    remained great friends until his death. You remember that he was the only
                    Foreign Service Officer ever to become Deputy Secretary of State.</p>
                <p>We had an extraordinarily good Embassy, beginning with the Ambassador. It was
                    also my first time as CPAO, and I had a good staff. Mike Eisenstadt was my CAO.
                    Ed Harper, a kind of talented madman, was IO. There were also solid junior
                    officers. Eastern Europe had always been my primary area of interest, although I
                    also bounced around other parts of the world. Once in Warsaw, I felt that I was
                    back in an environment in which I could be more useful than in any previous
                    assignment.</p>
                <p>Great Value Of USIS/VOA Work In Poland And Eastern Europe/USSR Generally</p>
                <p>Let me generalize for a moment.</p>
                <p>I think that the Agency's work in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union — and I
                    very much include the work of the Voice of America — was in every respect more
                    important than anything we did anywhere else in the world. Throughout the 40
                    years of Soviet domination it was we — “we,” USIA; “we,” VOA and Radio Free
                    Europe, Radio Liberty, the BBC, and Deutsche Welle — who kept alive in the
                    peoples of those countries the hope that someday things would change and that
                    the West cared.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>Not only was it a matter of providing information, but also of sustaining their
                    hope by letting them know that we cared enough to broadcast to them, to have
                    exchange programs with them, to show them exhibits, to talk to them as
                    individuals, to send professors to their universities, to open libraries in
                    which they could spend happy and profitable hours. A dollar spent in Eastern
                    Europe was worth a thousand dollars. A dollar spent in many other parts of the
                    world was worth $10.00 or $1.00, and sometimes only 50 cents.</p>
                <p>You asked me earlier how Yugoslavs felt about Americans, and what I said about
                    Yugoslavs is doubly true of Poles. They are a splendid people, a brave people.
                    The Poles and Hungarians are cavalry peoples. They have cultures of honor. An
                    ordinary Pole — if there are any “ordinary” Poles — constantly thinks of his
                    honor, of his personal honor, his national honor, the honor of his wife and the
                    honor of his relatives. And to live among people who were able so well and so
                    clearly to articulate their hatred for the system which had been imposed upon
                    them, and who took such extraordinary risks saying things and doing things that
                    were anathema to the regime, was a constant stimulant. One had to admire them
                    and one had to believe that what one was doing among them made a difference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My brief exposure to them seems to impress me with the
                        fact that they almost don't give a damn about what they say. If they don't
                        like what they were subjected to within their own country, they have
                        absolutely no tendency to hold back — they say it. I don't know to what
                        extent they do that in Poland, but outside of Poland, they certainly
                        do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: They were the same inside Poland. Every Pole understands, viscerally
                    perhaps, what Mr. Jefferson told us about the need to water the tree of liberty
                    with the blood of patriots. And Poland, to survive as a nation and as a people,
                    to survive as a culture, jammed in there as they are between the Russians in the
                    east and the Germans in the west, has had to sacrifice on the field of battle
                    one generation in every two or three.</p>
                <p>And however unreasonable they may sometimes seem, however un-Anglo-Saxon, they
                    make wise, if desperate, choices. When someone is invading your country with
                    tanks, it may be foolhardy to charge those tanks with horse cavalry. But if
                    that's all you've got to charge them with, the Pole feels it's better to do that
                    than to do nothing at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My remarks and my question was provoked by the fact that a
                        couple of years ago I was at a reception in Tokyo at which the Polish
                        ambassador was present. And it was an experience for me, because the man
                        simply opened up completely about not only the Soviet Union, which he
                        thoroughly detested, but about his regime within his own country.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>Here is a man representing his country in a very important other country in the
                    world, and he had no compunction whatsoever exposing himself to me, as an
                    American, and giving his opinion of what was happening.</p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: This interview is taking place at a time when Eastern Europe, as we have
                    known it in the post-war era, is coming unraveled. It's important to remember
                    that in Eastern Europe there were never more but a handful of Marxists and
                    hardly any communists at all. There were plenty of opportunists, of course,
                    people who went along just to survive. But they shouldn't be judged harshly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were a lot of fascist sympathizers, weren't
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Yes. There were plenty of convinced fascists, not as many as you think,
                    but too many, to be sure. But of convinced Communists and convinced Marxists,
                    there were few. The only countries in the world where I have never had arguments
                    or even conversations, about Marxism, was in Poland and the other Eastern
                    European countries. They knew that Marxism was nonsense from the moment it was
                    imposed upon them, or at least a moment or two after it was imposed on them.
                    Indian intellectuals would blather endlessly about Marxism, but very few Polish
                    intellectuals would risk their dignity talking about rubbish.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, again, you feel that when you spoke about what we were
                        able to do, you were talking about such activities as the exchange program
                        and the exhibit program and all the three radio stations broadcasting into
                        Eastern Europe; had you then exhausted a discussion of what you were able to
                        do? Were you able to do anything in the press field or the publication field
                        in Poland, or was that pretty well restricted?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Well, it was much harder than elsewhere, but I had a large circle of
                    press contacts. I must have seen at least once a month 25 to 35 of the most
                    important Polish journalists. I seldom saw them in my office. It was almost
                    always in a social situation created by me.</p>
                <p>While we certainly did not influence what the party press wrote, we had a
                    substantial influence on the way journalists thought, and to some extent, what
                    they thought was reflected in what they wrote.</p>
                <p>To give you an example: There was and is a Catholic weekly in Krakow which
                    throughout the worst of times was always able to publish, although it was
                    censored. I saw the editor every few weeks. We provided him with dozens of
                    subscriptions to American magazines and books for his library. We were fighting
                    the same battle, and fighting it pretty effectively, as it turned out.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>We made a difference in Poland, as I think we did everywhere in Eastern Europe
                    throughout the Cold War. The people who were in that program can look back —
                    should look back — with the feeling that they did their part and that without
                    them, and others like them in other parts of our government and in Allied
                    governments, things would not have gone the way they have gone.</p>
                <p>1971: Poland Assignment Cut Short At End Of Two Years; Return To Washington And
                    Deputy Area Director For Eastern Europe, Then Area Director (1973) and Director
                    Of Recombined East And West Europe (1975)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think now you have covered what you did in Poland,
                        or do you have any further remarks to make about the Polish situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: No. I probably covered it at too great a length. My tour in Poland was
                    supposed to have been four years, but at the end of my second year I was asked
                    to come back to Washington to be Deputy Area Director for Eastern Europe and the
                    Soviet Union. I did that job for a year and then succeeded Kempton Jenkins as
                    Area Director. I remained in that job from 1973 until 1975. In 1975, Jim Keogh,
                    the Director to whom I was personally closest, asked me to put Western Europe
                    and Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union back together, and asked also that I
                    become Area Director for the whole shooting match.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You may remember, I came to see you one time about a
                        question concerning the consulting firm I was working through, and I thought
                        I remembered at that time that you were head of EUR, but I had forgotten
                        that that was at a time when they had already recombined the two.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: It was, yes. I do remember you came, and, yes, it was 1975.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It may be difficult for you to answer now, since you
                        weren't there at the creation, but what do you think about the validity of
                        having established a separate European entity for the Soviet Union and
                        Eastern Europe, say, about the time we did, which was around about 1963, '62
                        or '63, as I recall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I think it was a sound idea. Operations in Eastern Europe and the Soviet
                    Union were sufficiently sui generis to justify a separate area office. It was
                    further justified by the fact that as an independent office it had greater claim
                    on resources and prevented the big Western European programs from siphoning off
                    funds from where they were the most needed.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>Putting it back together again in 1975 was also right. There was no question in
                    Jim Keogh's mind that I was going to short change Eastern Europe, because my
                    focus had been on Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union. Also, somebody needed to
                    take a very close look at the still badly over-staffed and over-funded Western
                    European Area, and Jim knew I would do this for him, and do it with gusto.</p>
                <p>My first task was to look very closely at the Western European program. As I
                    recall, I reduced by hundreds our foreign national positions, 80% to 90% of whom
                    we retired. We tried not to perpetrate cruelties on people who had served us
                    well and loyally, many since 1945, but too many things were being done just
                    because they had always been done. And it was clear that for so long as there
                    were people to do them, things would go on as before. Virtually the only way to
                    reduce the size of the programs was to reduce the size of the staffs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'll ask you, then, do you have some further comments on
                        the four or five years you spent within the agency on various stages of the
                        European program direction?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: My four years as an Area Director coincided with Jim Keogh's tenure as
                    Director of the Agency, and with Gene Chop's as Deputy Director. I found them
                    very agreeable to work for; both are highly intelligent, both are excellent
                    managers, and both are gentlemen to the core.</p>
                <p>You could go to Jim Keogh for a decision and get it on the spot. Both he and Gene
                    had affection for the Foreign Service, genuine affection. They liked us and we
                    felt it, and I think we responded to that affection and to that trust by doing
                    our utmost to merit them. I think that both of them — each of them slightly
                    differently — understood the role of USIA and neither overvalued nor undervalued
                    our role. They did not allow themselves to believe, as some directors have
                    believed, that they were mini secretaries of state, but they knew that we had a
                    role to play, and they helped us play it efficiently.</p>
                <p>I record my feeling that Jim Keogh was a first-rate director of USIA, and that
                    perhaps because he is a quiet man, and in some respects a self-effacing man — he
                    is too proud to be the other way — that he is sometimes underestimated. And I
                    would say different, but equally complimentary things, about Gene Kopp. And I
                    will go on record also to say that the Agency is extra- ordinarily fortunate to
                    have him back as Deputy Director in this administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So then from the European area . . .</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1976: Return To Italy, This Time As PAO</p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: From the European area, off I went—or returned, really—for my third tour
                    in Italy, this time as Country PAO. This was at the beginning of the Carter
                    Administration.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>Until this point in my career I had always worked for people whom I respected
                    professionally, and for many of whom I also had affection. That now changed.
                    Ambassador Gardner and I did not get along, and the next three years were a
                    miserable struggle to be loyal to a person for whom I had scant respect. To be
                    fair, I must have been as much of a trial to him as he was to me.</p>
                <p>Curiously enough, some of my better work came in the early stages of that
                    assignment.</p>
                <p>A. USIS Role In Blocking U.S. Support For Italian Communist Participation In
                    Italian Government</p>
                <p>When the Carter Administration came to office, “Euro- Communism” was fashionable
                    in Washington. There was a notion, which I thought was deeply wrong, and which I
                    think events have proved deeply wrong, that if we only cooperated with the
                    European communists, we would change them, and they would eventually become
                    socialists.</p>
                <p>I passionately disagreed with this point of view and thought it terribly
                    dangerous. I thought that communism in Europe was already receding, including in
                    Italy. I thought that if we lifted our “veto” for their entry into the
                    government we would have strengthened them at the very moment they were
                    weakening. I believed that our anathema against them should continue. I argued
                    fiercely against lifting the anathema.</p>
                <p>At this point, the possibility that the communists would enter the government
                    suddenly loomed large, and Washington finally focused.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador suddenly changed his mind, probably because he did not want to be
                    the person who “lost Italy.”</p>
                <p>At this point it became easier to fight for a statement which, in effect, would
                    reimpose the anathema. I drafted a cable to the Department and the NSC which
                    succeeded in persuading Washington that something needed to be said. On January
                    12, 1978, a statement was issued.</p>
                <p>It served to block the entry of the communists into the government, which, had
                    they done so at the time, would have breathed new life into them, and which
                    would have done untold damage to our interest in Italy.</p>
                <p>B. Argument For Giving PAO A Political Counselor Role</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>Just a couple more quick thoughts about my tour as PAO in Rome. I didn't discover
                    this in Rome, but certainly the experience there strengthened my view that PAOs,
                    to really do their jobs well, should also be political counselors with a
                    slightly different mission. The traditional political counselor's constituencies
                    are the Foreign Ministry in the political world. The PAO's constituencies are
                    the Fourth Estate and the intellectual world. Each should relate to those
                    constituencies in essentially the same way.</p>
                <p>In most European countries, in most societies in fact, the intellectual world is
                    not what it is in the United States. I'm talking about how the politicized
                    intelligentsia, has as much, and in some cases, more influence on the direction
                    in which a given country is going to go politically than does the political
                    establishment. Thus the PAO's constituency is every bit as political, in some
                    countries and at some historical moments more so, than the political
                    counselor's. And what the politicized intelligentsia thinks should be reported
                    on.</p>
                <p>One of the reasons why departmental officers tend often to regard USIA Foreign
                    Service officers as second-class citizens is because the USIA officer seldom
                    ever reports on anything. It's not that he can't. When our people enter our
                    service as young men and women, they are man for man, woman for woman, every bit
                    as good as State FSOs. But subsequently they are not asked to use their minds as
                    much, or their skills as much. This has been a strong trend in recent years when
                    there's been far too much emphasis in USIA on management, and far too little on
                    substance. Seldom are our people asked to write anything beyond largely useless
                    reports to Agency administrators.</p>
                <p>I have one additional observation, and a final one, because after this, I don't
                    do any more PAOing: Even though we had looked at the Western European programs
                    carefully, and in the mid-'70s eliminated many functions which had lingered on
                    from the '40s and the '50s, there was and there remains a good deal of fat in
                    our West European operations. Which is not to say that people don't work hard.
                    They do. But many of them are working hard doing things that are a waste of time
                    and money.</p>
                <p>1980: Shirley Called Back To Washington To Be Associate Director For Programs,
                    But Suddenly Becomes Acting Director Of USIA</p>
                <p>But to turn to myself: I was promoted Career Minister in the summer of 1980, and
                    shortly thereafter John Reinhardt asked whether I wanted to come back to
                    Washington as Associate Director for Programs to succeed Hal Schneidman, a
                    distinguished USIA officer who had been the first incumbent in that newly
                    created job in USIA's rather sad, but happily brief, incarnation as USICA. I was
                    delighted to get out of Rome, and delighted with the job offer.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>My period as Associate Director for Programs was short. Had I remained in that
                    job for a longer period, I could have done some good. But I had only just begun
                    to work on trying to understand how to make the organization mesh, how to
                    properly coordinate the tremendously varied instruments I had in hand when, with
                    the election of Ronald Reagan, I became Acting Director of USIA.</p>
                <p>The six months of being Acting Director was pretty exhilarating. I was the first
                    career officer to have been formally named Acting Director by a President, and
                    the only one, I think, who had ever been Acting Director for more than a few
                    days at a time.</p>
                <p>I recognized, of course, that as an Acting Director, there were a limited number
                    of initiatives I could take. I remember — something I was proud of at the time —
                    that I introduced training programs in Marxism for outgoing officers because I
                    felt that most of our people knew very little about the theoretical side of
                    Marxism, and if they didn't know anything about Marxism, how were they going to
                    persuade people that it was wrong? I also set up a course on Western values to
                    try to get our people to think methodically about our own system.</p>
                <p>And many other initiatives as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think you said earlier when we were off the record that
                        these were not set up at FSI, that they were set up and given within the
                        agency. I'm curious. Who was teaching them? Who did you acquire to impart
                        this knowledge?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I don't remember names, but I remember that we went out and got some of
                    the better people in the country to run them. But I'm certain that we did not do
                    them in the FSI framework.</p>
                <p>1981: Advent Of Charles Wick As USIA Director And Creation Of Position Of
                    Counselor Of The Agency</p>
                <p>Charlie Wick, who was to be the next Director, started coming to his office in
                    April, about four months into my temporary incumbency.</p>
                <p>I found him an interesting, complex and difficult man. He was hard to work for;
                    the hardest I had ever experienced. For the first year and a half or so of his
                    tenure, he was extremely suspicious of the “bureaucracy.” He was predisposed to
                    believe that whatever we did was going to be inefficient and resistant of the
                    things that he wanted to do, and resistant also to the ideas of the new
                    administration. As time went by, he not only became easier to work with, but he
                    began to rely increasingly on the professional Foreign Service, although heaven
                    knows he brought far too many political appointees into the Agency.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>Looking back on his incumbency, I think it was a mixed blessing. He worked
                    terribly hard. He believed very strongly in the things he was doing, and about
                    some them he was right. He certainly got the Agency larger budgets than it
                    otherwise would have had, which was mostly good, but not altogether good.</p>
                <p>After he came on board, Wick asked me to create a job for myself. I looked at the
                    job description of the Under Secretary for Political Affairs at State. Around it
                    I wrote a job description for a Counselor of Agency with responsibility for the
                    work of the Area Directors to assume that the field would get professional
                    supervision, and included some pretty broad additional authority. About seven or
                    eight months later Mr. Wick decided that things were not going as he wanted and
                    he asked me to take on additional responsibility as “Chief of Staff.” At that
                    point all of the paper that went to the Director began to flow through me. Wick
                    generated a flood of memos, but somehow we managed. I ended up having an
                    Executive Assistant, three Special Assistants, and three secretaries. I didn't
                    want all that staff, but had to let the office grow to handle the paper flow
                    along with my other work.</p>
                <p>Politicization Of USIA Has Left No Honorable Career Place For A Senior Officer To
                    Go After Holding Major Agency Assignment; Agency Needs Restructuring</p>
                <p>Looking back after many years away from the Agency, and certainly quite a few
                    years away from 1981 when this job was created, I believe it was the right thing
                    to do. It is my view, and it's a strongly held view, that the officer who
                    becomes Counselor of the Agency should always be a Career Minister, and should
                    always be at the tail end of his career in USIA. I believe also that after he
                    ends his tour of duty as Counselor he should not have another tour in the
                    Agency, and that if he wants to stay in the Foreign Service, it should be as a
                    chief of mission.</p>
                <p>For two reasons. One, because I think Agency officers ought to have at least one
                    job at the senior-most level to which they can aspire, and which they know will
                    almost certainly lead to an assignment as chief of mission at the end of their
                    careers. And, two, because I think that the person in the Counselor's job should
                    be in a position to give his best advice to the Director of the Agency without
                    in any way feeling that he needs to trim his sails. My successor as Counselor
                    was Jack Hedges, who, as you know, died before he got his Mission. Stan Burnett
                    retired out of the job and John Kordek went on to be Ambassador to Botswana. The
                    present incumbent, Mike Pistor, is still relatively new in the assignment, but I
                    hope he gets his Mission and refuses another PAOship if that is all he is
                    offered.</p>
                <p>One of the problems USIA has is that the brighter the officer, the more difficult
                    the last 10 to 15 years of his career tend to be. By the time he is 45 or 50, he
                    will have been a country PAO two or three times. And how many times can you go
                    out as a PAO, working with State officers whom you knew when they were your
                    juniors and who are now DCMs and ambassadors? How can you retain your enthusiasm
                    and the will to work in that kind of situation?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think the increasing politicization of the agency by
                        which it came to a point where more political appointees were placed in the
                        most senior and responsible positions, has left the agency in an untenable
                        position. It's extremely difficult now for a senior USIA officer to aspire
                        to much of anything in Washington that he thinks in his view is equal to his
                        talents once he has had two or three major posts within the agency. I don't
                        know what the answer is. I just don't think it's going to work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: The answer has to be that the institution, as it's presently organized,
                    cannot correct the flaw that you have pointed to. The institution needs to be
                    reorganized. In essence, a fifth cone in the Foreign Service, a public affairs
                    cone needs to be created, and interchangeability between that and other cones
                    ought to be considerable. A political cone officer cannot be fully effective at
                    the senior levels unless he has served a tour or two in a public affairs
                    capacity. Similarly, a public affairs cone officer cannot be fully effective in
                    his specialty unless he has served a tour or two as a political officer, an
                    economic officer, or as a DCM. And unless changes are made to allow for that
                    kind of interchangeability, the problem will persist.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think, also, something that you and I discussed a while
                        back when we unfortunately had the machine turned off, is that I think one
                        of the reasons that Foreign Service officers in the USIA have not continued
                        along the line of reporting is twofold.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>One is that there are many ambassadors who are jealous of, and political officers
                    who would strongly resent that kind of reporting. The other thing is that if you
                    report to the Agency, the Agency really doesn't know what to do with it once
                    they've got it. So they don't make it known to State, and if they do, I'm not
                    sure what the reaction of State would be under the present circumstances and
                    organizational patterns.</p>
                <p>I agree with you. Some reorganization and some change has got to take place or
                    there isn't going to be a major career in the senior area for USIA officers.</p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I certainly agree with the last thing you said, although I'm not sure
                    that I fully share your view on how ambassadors regard imaginative reporting by
                    USIA officers. When I was a PAO in Eastern Europe I did a great deal of
                    reporting, straight to the Department with copies to USIA, and there was never
                    any problem. Neither was there tension between me and my political officer
                    colleagues, because I was reporting on things they were not reporting on, and
                    did not have either the intention or the time to report on.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>Obviously, a USIA officer should not sit down and write analytical telegrams
                    about the state of mind of the politicized intelligentsia of country X and then
                    send them back to his desk at the USIA. The desk officer will merely look at it,
                    perhaps mark it for the Area Director. And the Area Director will put a note on
                    it and say: “Joe has written an interesting report.” And that will be the end of
                    it. No, that is absurd. But there has always been a way, in my experience, of
                    reporting to the Department with copies to USIA, or to USIA with copies to the
                    Department.</p>
                <p>Nor do I think that ambassadors are resentful of this sort of thing. In my
                    experience, an ambassador's main concern is to do his job well and to look good
                    in Washington. If someone in his Mission is doing reporting which the Department
                    views as valuable, the ambassador doesn't much care who does the drafting, as
                    long as his Mission looks good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I guess I have my impression because I served under a
                        couple of ambassadors from the old school who were upset by it, and I've now
                        been out of the Service for 17 years. From what you say, things have vastly
                        improved, and I'm glad to hear it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I think they have. Ambassador Stoessel whose PAO I was in 1970-72 in
                    Warsaw, was considered an old-line Foreign Service officer, and he not only did
                    not object, but encouraged me and my officers to report. He was also the first
                    superior to recommend that I one day be a chief of mission. A man of judgement.
                    [Laughter].</p>
                <p>1983: Shirley Made Agency Deputy Director Ad Interim</p>
                <p>Well, to pick up on my own career, and to say a few things about the next phase:
                    in May of 1983 Director Wick decided to dispense with the services of
                    then-Deputy Director Gilbert Robinson, and asked me to become Deputy Director ad
                    interim until he could find a political appointee replacement. I said that I
                    would, but added that I had no interest in being the permanent Deputy Director.
                    I served as Deputy Director ad interim for about five months. In the summer of
                    1983 I asked that I be released by October, as I wished to retire after a year
                    as a diplomat-in-residence.</p>
                <p>The experience of being Deputy Director ad interim was not substantially
                    different from having been Counselor and Chief of Staff, although my
                    responsibilities were somewhat enlarged. I became exclusively responsible for
                    personnel decisions, relations with the Union, and so on. To tell you the truth,
                    after those three years as Acting Director, Counselor, and Deputy Director, I
                    was tired. Director Wick fired a tremendous number of people; a revolving door
                    in some of the senior jobs. And, of course, every one of his crises were
                    accompanied by endless meetings, recriminations, bitterness, anger, slamming
                    doors and raised voices. There were times when the job was pretty
                    distasteful.</p>
                <p>1983: Diplomat-In-Residence At Wesleyan University; Then Ambassador To
                    Tanzania</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>In October, I went to Wesleyan University as diplomat-in-residence and there
                    taught, keeping one lecture ahead of my students, a class in the History of
                    Contemporary Eastern Europe, and a seminar on the political intelligentsia in
                    Eastern European societies. I also had several tutorials. I enjoyed being at
                    Wesleyan and enjoyed being with young people. I enjoyed teaching, and I enjoyed
                    the luxury of being able to focus once more on what really interested me;
                    Eastern Europe. It was a happy time.</p>
                <p>Just before I left Washington the Department asked me whether I was interested in
                    becoming Ambassador to Tanzania. I said that I was. Both my wife and I had
                    always wanted to serve in Africa, and I had always wanted to have a tour of duty
                    as a chief of mission.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know you were hoping for it, but weren't you at one time
                        even considered as ambassador to Hungary?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I was on my way three times, but each time a political appointee went
                    instead.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is that the time of the famous story, or one of those
                        times of the famous story, when our b�te noire in Congress asked an
                        assistant of his who was a native Hungarian to take you out and see if you
                        really knew Hungarian?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: No. That happened while I was Area Director for EE and the Soviet Union;
                    in 1974 or '75. Director Keogh had me up in front of Wayne Hayes defending my
                    budget, and defending also that slice of the VOA budget attributable to Eastern
                    Europe and the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>Hayes was in the chair, and there was a huge crowd in the room. I don't really
                    know why. There must have been many agency officers, but there were a lot of
                    other people too. Wayne Hayes, as always, was surrounded by a bevy of young
                    women staffers.</p>
                <p>Hayes had had me in the hot seat for more than two hours. He was really working
                    me over, putting a lot of pressure on me. As I was addressing the question of
                    VOA broadcasts to Eastern Europe, Hayes said: “Well, Mr. Shirley, I don't
                    understand why you're asking for money for VOA. Everybody knows that nobody
                    listens to VOA in Eastern Europe. It's only the RFE that they listen to.” I
                    responded by noting that that was not quite true, that I had recently returned
                    from a trip to the area and had the opportunity to speak to many people who told
                    me how much they enjoyed, and how valuable they considered, VOA broadcasts. “I
                    was in Hungary,” I continued, “where I had extensive conversations with
                    Hungarians, and they confirmed this view.”</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>Hayes interrupted me and said that “like all Foreign Service officers,” I was
                    claiming to speak a language which I didn't. He would give me a test because he
                    knew that “Hungarian was one of the hardest languages in the world.”</p>
                <p>There was a lot of scurrying around, and one of the hand- maidens dashed out. She
                    returned with a nice-looking lady in a nurse's uniform who turned out to be a
                    1956 Hungarian refugee. She hardly had time to get to the desk where I was
                    sitting when Wayne Hayes said: “I want you to test this fellow's Hungarian,
                    because I bet that he doesn't speak a word of it.” The lady sat down next to me,
                    and I addressed her in Hungarian. We spoke for perhaps a minute. There was dead
                    silence in the room, and Hayes, with a look of expectant triumph on his face,
                    asked, “Well, does he?,” and the lady said: “Mr. Chairman, he not only speaks
                    Hungarian, he speaks it better than I do.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>There was a roar in the room and lots of applause.</p>
                <p>That's that story. I've heard so many versions told back to me that I thought I
                    had better set the record straight.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm glad to hear it, because I've heard so many versions
                        of it, too, that I wasn't quite sure what the situation was.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>An Aside: Discussion Of Charles Wick's Actions While Director Of USIA</p>
                <p>Although this is a little bit out of the sequence and from the subject matter at
                    the time we were discussing it, I have a question. I hadn't served under Wick
                    because I had gone considerably before he came on duty, but looking at it from
                    the outside, there were a number of incidents in which it seemed that the man
                    was simply incredibly naive, if not incredibly stupid, in what he did.</p>
                <p>One of the things that first raised quite a hassle among the alumni and the
                    alumni association was his speech right after the Grenada invasion when he was
                    up at the Edward R. Murrow Center for Study—</p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: At Fletcher, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At Fletcher. And he gave a speech. I can't remember the
                        precise occasion, but in it he said that it was perfectly all right for the
                        press to be completely excluded from any coverage of the Grenada invasion
                        because when the national security of the United States Government was at
                        stake, it was perfectly all right for the government to keep the press
                        entirely away from any area where they could report on combat operations.
                        That seemed to me to be slightly out of style for a person who was director
                        of the agency.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>There is another case in which he was ridiculed, and I don't know whether the
                    situation was as bad as it was reported in the press. He was about to make a
                    journey to Japan. He apparently sent a message ahead which was let out by the
                    embassy over there in which he asked for a motor escort from Narita Airport into
                    Tokyo. He asked for an armored and bulletproof glass sedan, he asked for
                    permission to carry his own pistol into Japan, and I've forgotten one other very
                    odd request that was made. I think he wanted a personal bodyguard all the time
                    he was there.</p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Wick was neither naive nor stupid. I'm sure he has a very high I.Q. But
                    he knew little about the world beyond our own borders, or foreign policy, and
                    not much about managing a large organization. As I said, he worked extremely
                    hard and did some good things. But he had neither the temperament nor the
                    training, nor the professional background for the job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You're on the verge now of going to Tanzania, but before
                        we get there, is there, is there anything else you'd like to comment on,
                        either with regard to your time as the ad interim deputy director, or going
                        back even to your period as the diplomat in residence at Wesleyan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: Administration after administration sends political appointees to direct
                    USIA, to deputy direct USIA, or to occupy important jobs in USIA. A high
                    percentage have no back-ground to suggest that they will be able to do their
                    jobs. I'm not objecting to political appointees. That's part of our system, and,
                    in the main, it works. But it works only if presidents send to departments of
                    government, and to agencies of government, people who have backgrounds which are
                    a reasonable guarantee that they will be able to handle their responsibilities.
                    And there shouldn't be too many of them.</p>
                <p>USIA has a particular problem, because there's a view among all but a very few
                    knowledgeable people that USIA is a kind of a glorified public relations agency
                    for the government, which clearly we are not. USIA was not created to perpetrate
                    acts of social science. USIA was created to perpetrate political acts. And half
                    of the people who have been directors of the agency have not understood that
                    simple fact. I expect that Charlie Wick, for instance, was sent to direct the
                    Agency because it was President Reagan's view that Wick was going to run the
                    government's public relations agency. USIA ought to be run by people profoundly
                    experienced in foreign policy. They should be people who have held senior
                    positions in the foreign policy establishment, people who understand what kind
                    of work USIA actually does.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>To criticize Wick for not being a foreign policy expert is unfair, unless one
                    criticizes in the same breath all the people in Washington, including people on
                    the Hill and in government, who think that USIA is a public relations agency.
                    USIA will only rarely be well led because the majority of the people appointed
                    to lead it don't know what they have got hold of, and don't under- stand what
                    they have got hold of is supposed to do.</p>
                <p>Shirley Speaks Of Experiences As Ambassador To Tanzania</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think we've probably pretty well covered now your period
                        of time in USIA, and I guess you'd like to go on now to your experience as
                        an ambassador in Tanzania. When you discuss this, not only would I like you
                        to discuss many of the situations that came up with which you dealt, but
                        also to the extent in which you feel your prior USIA experience was a value
                        to you as an ambassadorial appointee.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: A lot of people who have been ambassadors will tell you that being one
                    is not everything it is cracked up to be. I differ. I think being ambassador is
                    great fun. I liked being in charge. I liked having all the elements of the
                    embassy working for me, and I enjoyed the fact that I had to think about AID
                    problems, and Peace Corps problems, and other sorts of problems that I had not
                    been asked to confront in the past.</p>
                <p>I enjoyed the fact that during my tenure in Dar es Salaam Julius Nyerere was
                    still President of Tanzania. I found him an interesting and extremely
                    intelligent man. And since South Africa was in turmoil at the time, and because
                    Nyerere was, to say the least, not particularly sympathetic to the policy of
                    constructive engagement, my meetings with him were frequent, animated, sometimes
                    sharp, but never acrimonious. It was as intellectually stimulating to deal with
                    him, as it was to deal with Prime Minister Salim Salim.</p>
                <p>Did my experience as USIA officer help me be a better chief of mission? Insofar
                    as I was a good chief of mission at all, yes. A USIA Foreign Service officer who
                    has had senior assignments abroad in USIA, and senior assignments in the Agency,
                    is as well prepared to be a chief of mission as a political cone ambassador. If
                    he is an intelligent man, a thoughtful man, a well-read man, if he knows
                    history, and if he is a political animal, the USIA officer is as prepared to be
                    a good chief of mission as the fellow who has spent his entire life in the
                    political cone. In some respects, he is better prepared because he will have
                    managed large amounts of money and large numbers of people, whereas plenty of
                    political cone officers become ambassadors with virtually no management
                    experience at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were dealing with Nyerere, what language were
                        you dealing with? French?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>SHIRLEY: No. Nyerere's English was every bit as good as mine. He had been
                    educated at the University of Edinburgh.</p>
                <p>Shirley Outlines Views On How USIA And State Should Be Restructured And Operate
                    In Future</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When we started this interview, you indicated that you
                        felt perhaps that USIA had reached a point in history where it ought to be
                        broken up into its constituent parts and put under different jurisdictions.
                        Would you mind giving a few moments on how you feel about this and why you
                        feel that way?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I feel that way because I don't think the institution as it is now
                    constituted performs its job as well as it would if it were organized in a
                    different way.</p>
                <p>I think the Voice of America ought to be given a status much closer to that of
                    RFE/RL. USIA never has had much control over VOA except in extreme situations.
                    VOA subordination to USIA is really a sham, and that sort of pretense isn't
                    healthy. It would be better to stop pretending, and give VOA a Board and a
                    dotted line to the Secretary of State.</p>
                <p>The cultural affairs side of the house ought to stay in a successor agency to
                    USIA. It could be called the U.S. Cultural Agency, or something like that. All
                    of those functions which today are performed in the Educational and Exchanges
                    Bureau, and many of the functions of the Bureau of Programs, should go to the
                    successor agency. The press and information side of the house should in its
                    entirety be moved into the Department.</p>
                <p>For this to work efficiently, the Department would have to reorganize itself. It
                    would be necessary to create a position which could be called Under Secretary
                    for Public Affairs, and you would need also an Assistant Secretary for Press and
                    Information Affairs. The Under Secretary for Public Affairs would have some
                    responsibilities for the activities of the Cultural Agency, and it would be to
                    him that the Director of the Cultural Agency reports, not to the Secretary of
                    State.</p>
                <p>I would eliminate the position of public affairs officer, and I would have
                    instead press counselors, or press and information counselors, and cultural
                    counselors, each reporting separately and as coequals to the DCM. And I envisage
                    the press counselor's responsibilities very much as I described them earlier —
                    the PAO as a second political counselor. The cultural counselor's
                    responsibilities would be no different from those of a cultural attach�'s
                    today.</p>
                <p>Overseas it would be easy to do. Doing it in Washington would be harder, but I
                    think that for the press and information side of the house to be effective, it
                    is imperative that it be closer physically and intellectually to the place where
                    foreign policy is articulated.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I don't want to take up time to argue some of these
                        points on tape. I have some reservation about how the information side might
                        act under the State Department, I suppose because I was in the predecessor
                        agencies of USIA when they were under the State Department. I think a lot of
                        what we were able to do abroad only became possible when USIA got out from
                        under the strictures of the Department.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Maybe it will be different today. We're 30 years past that time. But that's my
                    own feeling. However, I wanted to get your opinion on tape, and I'll try to get
                    a little (unclear).</p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: I don't underestimate the difficulty of doing what I have suggested, and
                    I do not think that it would work unless the Department reformed itself at the
                    same time that USIA was taken apart. The likelihood of any of this happening is
                    very small. Chances are that we're going to continue with the present structure
                    for quite some time.</p>
                <p>I do hope that even without institutional reform, the Agency will look at itself
                    carefully. It needs to de-bureaucratize if it is going to be as vital as it once
                    was. This is not a comment on our people, on their training, or on their
                    dedication. But the Agency has tied itself into such knots that it no longer has
                    the flexibility which at one time was its greatest strength. USIA begins to look
                    like any other gray, tired, Washington bureaucracy, and that is saddening.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I find it very sad. I think that the arrangement as
                        it was under Ed Murrow, when I could call in and be in his office within
                        minutes and discuss anything I wanted to with him is no more. Any officer
                        has to act bureaucratically even to see the director in these days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Well, thank you very much for the interview, Jock. As we said before, we kind of
                    passed over some of your experiences as the director of the East European and
                    ultimately the combined European program. I hope that when you get the
                    transcript of this interview, you will be able to put back into it some of the
                    things that we happened to pass over. If you think of additional factors that
                    ought to be on there, you can add them when you get the transcript, assuming you
                    have time with this aid to Poland responsibility to manage. Thank you again.</p>
                <p>SHIRLEY: It was a pleasure, Lew. Thank you.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
