<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000419">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Theodore E. Gildred </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR THEODORE E. GILDRED</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Hank Zivetz </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: April 26, 1990</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mr. Ambassador, we usually start with a question about how
                        you got your position as Ambassador to Argentina. Yours was a political
                        appointment. Was there some background in Latin America that prompted an
                        appointment to Argentina?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GILDRED: I'm sure there was because I was born and raised in Latin America, spent
                    the first 15 years of my life attending school in Latin America and Mexico City,
                    then returned to Mexico some years later where I worked for about five
                    years.</p>
                <p>I had over 20 years of direct living experience in Latin America, and was brought
                    up biculturally and bilingually. My first language was Spanish, not English. The
                    history that I read was out of Mexican history books, not American history
                    books.</p>
                <p>Consequently, I probably have a little different perspective simply because of
                    the fact that I was born and raised outside of this country. As a matter of
                    fact, this background helped me a great deal in my dealings with Latin American
                    leaders and business people, as well as other elements that an ambassador has to
                    deal with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In my research on Argentina for the period in which you
                        served, late 1986 to the middle of 1989, I find that there were three major
                        issues that confronted the people and government of Argentina. One was how
                        to deal with the aftermath of the military dictatorship. This is the period
                        of Alfonsin, when you were there. Another was the economic woes that they
                        faced, high inflation, loans that had to be paid off. And then a question of
                        change of leadership.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Could we address the first one, the problems that the government faced with the
                    residue of the military dictatorship and the unrest of the military. There were
                    some issues that came up at this time in early 1987. A former general was
                    arrested in the United States and extradited to Argentina, as one example. Could
                    you elaborate a little bit on how intimately the embassy became involved, if at
                    all, in these problems faced by the Alfonsin government.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>GILDRED: Well, this became a very important issue in the second half of
                    Alfonsin's administration, the half that I experienced.</p>
                <p>In the first few years they were addressing other issues — namely inflation,
                    which was rampant in the mid-80s and had to be controlled, and a lot of union
                    issues. They let the military issue and human rights issue (the two are directly
                    related, one and the same almost) slide a little bit. I think that they,
                    unfortunately, paid a heavy price for disregarding or trying to suppress that
                    problem.</p>
                <p>As you know, Argentina has a very sad, long history of military intervention in
                    government. It goes back over 100 years. I am, however, not addressing the
                    earlier military role in Argentine history. I am addressing more the period of
                    Peron and thereafter . . .</p>
                <p>In terms of modern history, Argentina can almost be divided into two periods: the
                    pre-Peron period and the post-Peron period. I don't think anyone in the history
                    of Argentina had more of an influence — and in my opinion a destructive,
                    negative influence — on what has happened to make the country what it is, than
                    Peron. There is no question that Peron set the country back very significantly
                    by going to a very statist, paternalistic type of government.</p>
                <p>Then, in the 1970s when Peron returned to power and died in office, he left his
                    second wife in charge of the country. She had been named vice president and
                    inherited the presidency when the military was poised to take over. For years
                    the military had been adversaries of Peronism and they were, I think, convinced
                    that Isabel was going to undo the country. Through inept handling of the
                    government, she did in fact bring the country to almost total chaos politically
                    and economically by 1976 when the generals took over. From the general public's
                    standpoint, the military had a genuine mandate to take over. Unfortunately,
                    Argentine civilians themselves have often been part of the equation that brought
                    the military to power. Certainly in 1976, there was a general feeling that only
                    the control and the discipline of the military could correct a situation of
                    total confusion approaching anarchy — where the extreme Right and the extreme
                    Left were tearing the country apart. The military felt then, and feel now, that
                    they were doing a job that the people had asked them to do when they took
                    over.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>The excesses that were committed are very clear. I think the facts stand for
                    themselves. Probably nine to ten thousand people, and maybe more, literally
                    disappeared during the late ''70s when the military was trying to restore order
                    to the country. In their efforts to restore order, they went to the extreme.
                    This led to a lot of very flagrant human rights abuses, and in many cases,
                    outright criminal acts. Not all of those nine to ten thousand people who are
                    known to have “disappeared” vanished because of the military; there were other
                    elements that were also to blame, mainly the radical Left. Undoubtedly, the
                    Leftist groups that emerged took their inspiration from Che Guevara. Guevara, an
                    Argentine, was a key strategist in Castro's takeover of Cuba and became one of
                    the leading lights of the Communist regime there. When he went back to South
                    America to create turmoil and chaos, he did a good job. Che's revolutionary
                    influence played a big role during those years in Argentina. At the end of the
                    ''70s, the military finally managed to eradicate the Montoneros and things were
                    finally normalized, but only at great human cost.</p>
                <p>Also, the military were harshly judged on their performance and loss of the
                    Falklands War in 1982.</p>
                <p>So you have those two factors: the human rights abuses that can be directly
                    traced to many in the military; and the loss of the war, with the ensuing blame
                    that was placed on the generals and commanders for that sad experience. Again,
                    you have to remember that when that war was declared the Argentines were out in
                    the streets en masse with probably 90 percent of the people exuberantly
                    supporting the war against the British and determined to do whatever they had to
                    do to regain the Malvinas (the Falkland Islands). So, again, it wasn't just the
                    military.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately, the military, when it was all over, became the scapegoats because
                    the general society usually, and certainly in the case of Argentina, doesn't
                    want to accept its full responsibility. In Argentina, the military was probably
                    blamed for more than it justly deserved. In the presidential campaign of 1983,
                    Italo Luder, the Peronist candidate, was in favor of a pardon or general amnesty
                    for the military. Alfonsin was not in favor of a military pardon and, to his
                    credit, was one of Latin America's first presidents to make the military
                    accountable for their actions.</p>
                <p>Uruguay went through a similar experience with human rights abuses during its
                    military period. Sanguinetti, who became President of Uruguay at about the same
                    time that Alfonsin took charge of Argentina, addressed the problem differently,
                    confronting it early on with an amnesty and then a general plebiscite. He
                    probably handled the military problem more pragmatically and had less difficulty
                    in the long run.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>Alfonsin's administration delayed resolving the military issue. They knew it was
                    volatile but they had little understanding of the military mentality. This
                    situation was seething on both sides. There was pressure from the human rights
                    advocates, primarily the Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo who, towards the end, may
                    have been co-opted by Leftist elements more interested in creating turmoil than
                    in seeing justice done. They used the issue to cause trouble for the government,
                    and to agitate against the military. Initially, the movement of the Mothers of
                    the Plaza de Mayo was a very legitimate response to the tragic losses they had
                    personally experienced. It became something else.</p>
                <p>Soon after I arrived as Ambassador in 1986, the Radical Party began facing
                    increasing pressures from the human rights activists calling for stepped-up
                    investigation and prosecution of the military, who by that time were tired of
                    feeling like social outcasts, embarrassed to go out on the streets in uniform.
                    The military felt that they had unfairly borne the brunt, had become the
                    scapegoats for everything that had gone wrong during the years of authoritarian
                    government. They began to voice, in a militant way, their desire to be given
                    back their pride. They demanded a final resolution to their plight, a solution
                    that in their minds could only be one of general amnesty.</p>
                <p>The military had undergone a dramatic change from ten years before when it played
                    a strong and proud role in Argentine society. Then it had been a very respected
                    career. Certainly that was no longer so.</p>
                <p>Pressure mounted rapidly to bring this issue to a conclusion. In 1987 Alfonsin
                    chose what he called the “Punto Final,” which was an attempt to limit the
                    ongoing prosecution to documented cases involving only commanders that were
                    responsible for giving the orders. The “Punto Final” decree was enacted but did
                    not really address the overall problem to the satisfaction of the military.</p>
                <p>From 1987 to 1989, there were three military uprisings or concerted acts of
                    disobedience. These were not coups or attempted coups. They were manifestations
                    of dissatisfaction on the part of militant elements of the services — primarily
                    the Army — that were trying to pressure the government into an amnesty and
                    revindication of the military.</p>
                <p>The whole thing remained a very, very hot issue right through to '89 when Carlos
                    Menem was elected president. In normal circumstances, Menem would have been
                    inaugurated in December, but Alfonsin resigned in July and Menem took office
                    early. I think Alfonsin felt that he was losing control of the situation due
                    primarily to the rapid unraveling of the economy and felt that the only person
                    that might be able to put things back in some order would be Menem. Menem had
                    clearly won the general elections with the support of the military, the support
                    of the unions, and the support of the Argentine people.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>In 1990, Menem decided that he had to grant an amnesty for the military. I think
                    most Argentines felt the issue had become so disruptive to their society and had
                    gone on for so long that, if the country was going to come together and face all
                    of its other problems, an amnesty was the only way to put the matter behind.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Argentine populace view the United States as an
                        actor in all of this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GILDRED: No, certainly not in the elections, although we made it clear to the
                    military that we were opposed to any action that might undermine Argentina's
                    democratic process. The Carter administration was accused of intervention by the
                    military government in the late ''70s when we cut off all military aid to
                    Argentina on the basis of human rights abuses. This action taken by our
                    government, I believe, was the proper thing to do.</p>
                <p>Although we were always on record as to our position on human rights, the Reagan
                    administration was very sensitive to Argentina's wishes regarding the handling
                    of their own internal affairs. Certainly the issue of human rights was one of
                    the key issues Argentina faced, and we tried to help in a positive, yet
                    non-interventionist, way.</p>
                <p>We stayed away from approving or disapproving of an amnesty because, as I said,
                    that's a sovereign issue that had to have an Argentine solution. We could not
                    tell them officially or unofficially that they ought to do something to bring
                    about an amnesty or that they should continue prosecuting the military because
                    that would have been overstepping our bounds.</p>
                <p>So, in answer to your question, we didn't intervene. I don't think they ever felt
                    that we tried to direct them or instruct them on what was right to do or wrong
                    to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just one more question in this regard. Alfonsin went to
                        Washington in 1988. Did you accompany him at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GILDRED: Yes, I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this issue raised at all in these meetings in
                        Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GILDRED: Yes. It was raised by Secretary Shultz. It was raised insofar as how
                    that issue was going and was President Alfonsin comfortable that this issue
                    could be properly handled so that it didn't become overly inflamed and create
                    problems that could destabilize the democratic process.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>I think Alfonsin made it very clear that his administration was one of the first
                    Latin American governments that put the military on trial, which resulted in
                    many members of the military being jailed for crimes against humanity.</p>
                <p>I think that, in the history of Latin America, Alfonsin's bravery in holding the
                    military responsible for their behavior will go down as a real landmark action
                    that few governments have had the temerity to attempt. They have always been so
                    afraid of the military that they never did anything after the military stepped
                    down.</p>
                <p>Alfonsin did. He was very proud of the fact that he was a true defender of human
                    rights, had prosecuted the military, and would continue to prosecute. But he
                    also admitted that this issue was starting to pull the country apart and needed
                    a solution.</p>
                <p>We did find that his trip here generated a lot of interest from US human rights
                    advocacy groups — the banner carriers. There were several demonstrations on his
                    trip to the East Coast and then again on his visit to the West Coast — not major
                    demonstrations, but hostility toward Alfonsin for not doing more than he was
                    doing.</p>
                <p>And yet, there were many Argentines who felt that he had let the human rights
                    thing go too far and, if he didn't do something quickly to ease the situation,
                    the armed forces were going to rebel against the never-ending prosecutions. That
                    is, in fact, what began to happen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's shift to the economic problems that his government
                        faced and the involvement of the United States, particularly the American
                        Embassy in Argentina. From my understanding they had some real, deep-seated
                        economic problems in terms of inflation and debt. Was this a major concern
                        of the embassy in the period in which you served?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GILDRED: Yes, you certainly addressed one of the main issues of concern. My
                    instructions were quite general and gave me a lot of latitude. Basically, my
                    mission was to help the Argentine government consolidate its democracy and to
                    help the institutions that needed to become more democratic continue on that
                    path.</p>
                <p>By that, I'm talking about things that we did with the unions, using a lot of our
                    own union leaders to try to create a less conflictive situation in
                    Argentina.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>We were also very concerned with helping the Argentines re-establish the military
                    under civilian control, something that had not existed in Argentina in the past.
                    The military always had almost a fully autonomous position. They were a state
                    within a state. We felt it was very, very important to help the Argentine
                    government strengthen its democratic process. They wanted to change the
                    mentality within the military, to have them accept civilian control through the
                    Minister of Defense. The minister would be the only person that could make key
                    decisions for the military, which is the established system in most
                    democracies.</p>
                <p>We went about this, of course, with a lot of sensitivity obviously, because we
                    did not want to have the military feel that we were directly intervening in
                    their internal operations. But we did make it very clear to the military: There
                    will be no direct military-to-military dealing. From now on, it will be through
                    the government, through the Minister of Defense. He and only he will talk to the
                    Pentagon. He and only he will negotiate assistance matters with us, so that the
                    democratic civilian government can have proper control over the military.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And what about the economy? Was there anything directly
                        that we did to help Alfonsin meet the crisis that he faced?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GILDRED: Let, me, if I may, just backtrack to the previous subject for one second
                    because I think this is very important.</p>
                <p>I felt that the military issue was key because as long as the military had this
                    feeling that they could operate independently because they were the guardians of
                    the society, and they could, as an autonomous entity, act independently from the
                    government, they would continue to be a real danger to Argentina's ongoing
                    democratic process.</p>
                <p>I wanted to make it very clear to the Argentine military that the Minister of
                    Defense could effectively work for and fulfill their legitimate needs, so I
                    worked with Minister of Defense Jaunarena. We became very good friends. I
                    probably worked with him as closely as any of the ministers (with the possible
                    exception of the Minister of Economy, Sourrouille) in trying to re-establish a
                    supportive relationship between our countries.</p>
                <p>The military relationship between Argentina and the Pentagon was almost totally
                    severed by the advent of the Falklands War. We were viewed as having supported
                    the Brits — and the Argentines will not forgive nor forget that. So, for
                    certainly the first three years of the Alfonsin administration, communication
                    between the US and Argentine armed forces was very poor. Our military presence
                    at the embassy in Argentina was greatly reduced after the Falklands War (at
                    their request). Our military support team, made up of Department of Defense
                    attach�s and Milgroup staff, was reduced to the absolute minimum.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>I was concerned with this reduction because if we were going to try to help
                    Argentina, we had to help revitalize their military and at the same time help
                    them to become a more democratic institution. To do this we had to establish
                    ourselves as a viable ally able to provide the help that was needed.</p>
                <p>Now this was very difficult to do when, on the one hand, Mrs. Thatcher was
                    saying: “We don't want you, the United States, to do anything that would enhance
                    whatever military capabilities the Argentines might have. We don't want them to
                    be in a position to do again what they did during the Falklands War.”</p>
                <p>Yet we in the State Department, and I think the Pentagon, felt that we had to
                    re-establish a good, sound relationship with the military as part of our effort
                    to help Argentina democratize itself. This is why I spent a lot of time getting
                    Jaunarena, the Minister of Defense, up to Washington for a first meeting with
                    Secretary of Defense Weinberger.</p>
                <p>Weinberger, in my opinion, was not overly interested in Argentina. He was
                    certainly a great friend and admirer of the British, and the general feeling was
                    that there would be little help of any substance from the Pentagon on
                    Weinberger's watch. It was only in the second meeting (after Weinberger had
                    stepped down and Secretary Carlucci took over) that the renewed talks with the
                    Pentagon began to be meaningful. Carlucci, I think, reflected the feelings of
                    the State Department and the Pentagon that it was in our best interest to start
                    turning things around and re-establish a good relationship with the Argentine
                    military.</p>
                <p>The outcome of the meeting with Carlucci was the first assistance package
                    approved for Argentina in almost ten years. It was a first step toward
                    re-establishing assistance in the form of a small package to refurbish some of
                    their idle equipment. Instead of giving or lending them money or giving them a
                    lot of sophisticated equipment, we felt a logical first step was to help them
                    refurbish their existing equipment, which, for lack of parts or maintenance, had
                    been idled. We felt that, if we could help them put that equipment back in
                    operation, it might keep more of the military occupied and, therefore, help to
                    quell the discontent and trouble-making. A lot of the military were sitting
                    around in the barracks very disgruntled because they had no airplanes to fly or
                    weapons and equipment to train with. The war had devastated the limited
                    equipment they had.</p>
                <p>So this was one of the important efforts. Now that the Argentines and the British
                    have re-established almost normal relations — something we worked very, very
                    hard on — I think some real progress on the military aid relationship will be
                    possible. We certainly pushed behind the scenes to get them to normalize
                    Anglo/Argentine relations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this an American initiative?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>GILDRED: No, it was not an American initiative, but there was a strong American
                    involvement in assisting this initiative, which I would say (and I might be
                    biased) was probably more of an Argentine initiative than a British one.</p>
                <p>The British were standing back. They weren't putting out any meaningful gestures
                    to try to re-establish relations. If anything, their unilateral creation of a
                    protective zone of 150 miles around the Falklands and prohibiting the Argentine
                    Navy from going into those waters — which were international waters (and in the
                    Argentine government's view, Argentine waters) — were working against our
                    efforts to help them get together.</p>
                <p>This was a very frustrating situation for us. Menem, when he became president,
                    realized that these efforts were worthwhile even though they had been
                    unsuccessful during the Alfonsin administration. He addressed the issue early on
                    with some very capable people, primarily Ambassador Garcia del Solar, a
                    long-time career diplomat who had worked on the Falklands/Malvinas problem
                    before the war and was very familiar with it.</p>
                <p>Our efforts almost got there, but it didn't quite happen. When Menem came in he
                    must have said, “Let's put this thing to rest.” I don't know the final details,
                    but the general plan that we had worked on finally came together this past
                    February. The British and the Argentines initiated talks and, as a result, have
                    now re-established — after all these eight years — semi-normal relations with
                    embassies in their respective countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me put this question to you in a little different way.
                        Very often you can tell the major thrust of American policy in a particular
                        country by the way we staff our different embassy sections. Would you say
                        that the political section was more important in your embassy than the
                        economic, or was the economic more important, or was it a standoff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GILDRED: I think every ambassador has the ability to establish priorities, but he
                    has to work with what he's got. A lot has to do with the staff he inherits.
                    Obviously, the economic team at the embassy has to be very, very good because
                    this is one of the most important areas of focus. I'm not so sure that we had an
                    overly strong economic team when I got there and in the several years before. I
                    think greater emphasis probably should have been put on that section. I did what
                    I could to change this but, as you know, you're limited in the ability to move
                    people in government. I made a couple of changes in our economic section that I
                    think strengthened it and allowed me to deal more effectively with the Argentine
                    government and the Ministry of Economy.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>So even though I put a great deal of emphasis on our economic section, I may have
                    given more importance to our political section. That capability, in my opinion,
                    had to be very strong. Fortunately, my political counselor, Bob Felder, was one
                    of the most able political officers that I have had the pleasure of knowing. He
                    was of great assistance to me in all of our dealings which, although mostly
                    political in nature, transcended in many cases the realms of economics, trade,
                    drug enforcement, military affairs and other areas of concern. Everything comes
                    together in some fashion under the political section.</p>
                <p>But those two sections, along with our military people, became more aware that we
                    did want to work more closely with the Argentines in helping them put together
                    the right kind of a military, and this was probably my key focal point. These
                    sections had very specific objectives. The ambassador is the one who has a more
                    general mission, which, in my case, was to help consolidate democracy in
                    Argentina.</p>
                <p>How do you do that? Well, that's really up to you because Latin America is so far
                    down on the list of foreign policy priorities that, unless there is a major
                    crisis, the State Department lets you alone. It is my personal opinion (I think
                    shared by many) that many of us who were ambassadors in Latin America were given
                    a lot of free rein because the State Department was much more preoccupied with
                    other issues and areas of foreign policy. Certainly the East-West agenda has
                    usually dominated our thinking for the last 40 years. And what happens is that
                    many of our ambassadors in Latin America do have more latitude in dealing with
                    the in-country issues they give priority to. As I said, in my case, it was the
                    economic issues, military issues, and certainly the political issues that I
                    focused on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the major economic issues was the debt and the
                        effort by the Argentines and Alfonsin to reduce the debt in some way. I
                        think this was one of the issues that he raised when he came to Washington,
                        wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GILDRED: Alfonsin felt that Latin America was drowning under the weight of the
                    debt. He kept talking about a reversed Marshall Plan, where, instead of
                    development capital coming into Latin America, a tremendous hemorrhage of money
                    was flowing out just to service the debt.</p>
                <p>I'm afraid there was a certain amount of truth to it. The massive debt they have
                    taken on is posing a great burden to countries like Argentina that can't even
                    pay their interest. They have to spend a tremendous amount of effort addressing
                    that issue to just keep their heads above water by rolling over loans or
                    agreements with the IMF, the World Bank, and the international creditor banks. A
                    very sad situation — just keeping your head above water, with no ability to go
                    out and develop new projects because there's no capital to do so.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>Yes, this was a major Alfonsin issue. At the same time, I reminded Alfonsin that
                    it was too bad that Latin America (and Argentina), who had had access to
                    tremendous amounts of capital, over 400 billion dollars in loans, had very
                    little to show for it. The funds were, for the most part, mismanaged, misused,
                    or squandered by poor government and corruption. This reality, however, was not
                    easy for him to accept, saying, “This is not fair. We're paying this interest,
                    but now we can't develop our countries because we can barely cope with the debt.
                    Something has to change.”</p>
                <p>I am sure that what he was interested in was a very simple solution: total or
                    partial forgiveness. Certainly not very realistic but, again, it was hard for
                    him, as the product of a paternalistic, statist form of society where the
                    government is involved in everything, to understand that the debt was not
                    controlled by the United States government. Even if the United States government
                    wanted to cut the debt, it couldn't, because most of that debt was owed to
                    international banks. And of that bank debt, American banks played only a 30
                    percent part.</p>
                <p>There were no simple solutions. As much as he wished it, there was no way that
                    the United States could make the problem go away.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We find that around the world. We have just a couple of
                        minutes, I know you have another appointment. Could you very quickly then,
                        if you wish and if you're willing, give us an evaluation of Alfonsin, and
                        then as much as you knew about Menem because he did come in while you were
                        still there. How capable are these people, starting with Alfonsin, what did
                        he bring and what did he lack?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GILDRED: I had great admiration for President Alfonsin. I think he was a great
                    democrat, a man who will go down in history as probably the one person who
                    started the transition to a true democracy in Argentina.</p>
                <p>As much as Argentines talk about democracy, until very recently I don't think
                    they really understood it or even experienced it in its true form. Alfonsin
                    turned the country around to greater reality with a new democratic form of
                    government.</p>
                <p>His weakness was that he was very uncomfortable with most of the economic issues.
                    He was naive about just how free economies worked. Consequently, he didn't have
                    a real plan. He was looking for simplistic solutions, and those just made the
                    situation worse. Because of his naivete or lack of ability to get a handle on
                    the real economic problems and what measures to take, he didn't take the right
                    measures when he could have.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>He certainly had a Minister of Economy who understood economics, was trained in
                    the United States, and who, I'm sure, in many cases would have liked to have
                    done things that Alfonsin and the Radical Party did not do because they were
                    scared of the political cost.</p>
                <p>They had the perfect opportunity in 1985 when they announced the Plan Austral to
                    slow inflation and stabilize the currency. The country was ready for the
                    government to institute a strong plan and take forceful measures, even though it
                    was going to be painful. Unfortunately, Alfonsin didn't realize that. Alfonsin
                    simply did not do the things he had to do when he had the opportunity. He will
                    be remembered, I think, as the man who “could have but didn't,” because he
                    didn't really understand that the people were ready.</p>
                <p>He was a man who wanted to change the image of a self-destructive, irresponsible
                    Argentina to one of a responsible, predictable country willing to accept its
                    leadership role in the Latin American picture. To a large extent, Argentina did
                    become a respected player on the Latin American scene during his administration,
                    figuring prominently in Third World politics as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now how did Menem, in the short time that you knew him,
                        how did he differ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GILDRED: I got to know Menem certainly as well as Alfonsin during my stay in
                    Argentina.</p>
                <p>I took it upon myself to visit every one of the 22 provinces. In the first year
                    and a half, I visited each province and met with the governors and most of the
                    provincial legislatures. The first province I visited was La Rioja, where Carlos
                    Menem was the governor. He was the only governor in my visits to the provinces
                    who invited me to stay at his home with him, which I thought was a very special
                    gesture.</p>
                <p>He is a charming human being. I don't think there are many people who meet Carlos
                    Menem and don't come away impressed by his warmth of personality. He has a nice
                    personal touch. He also has a certain political canniness, a natural intuition,
                    that makes him an astute politician as well as a very personable man. He's
                    certainly not dry or austere as many politicians can be, but neither was
                    Alfonsin, who had very much the same charm.</p>
                <p>Carlos Menem is a man of the country, not the city. He was a small town country
                    attorney who got involved in Peronist politics early in his career. I, along
                    with others, have a suspicion that Menem is not a true Peronist in the
                    philosophical sense of the word. He's more of a pragmatist. I think there are a
                    lot of people today in Argentina who are saying it's impossible for this man to
                    be a Peronist because everything he is doing (and a lot of them are applauding
                    what he's doing) totally goes against the traditional Peronist platform.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>His efforts to privatize so many of the elements that need to be privatized go
                    against the Peronist grain. The Peronists never accepted giving up jobs. It was
                    always: How can we create more jobs? How can we have more control over industry
                    and government so that we can make more jobs?</p>
                <p>Menem is doing the right things and, in my opinion, taking action that Alfonsin
                    should have taken, and didn't. Here's a Peronist who most believed would take a
                    populist approach and, instead, is doing some very radical things. Not radical
                    in the sense of Argentine party politics, but very brave things, and it looks
                    like he's sticking with it. I admire him and wish him luck.</p>
                <p>Certainly there are many who thought that he was going to be a loose cannon.
                    During his campaign he said several things that concerned the State Department
                    and probably the Brits. He was a politician who seemed to do the expedient and
                    say what the crowd wanted to hear to get the vote. That may have been the case,
                    but I think he is turning out to be a much stronger, more aggressive, and much
                    braver leader than anybody thought he was going to be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you very much, Mr. Ambassador. I know you have to
                        go, so I think we'd better cut it off right here.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>GILDRED: Okay, thank you.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
