<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000314">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Robert W. Duemling </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR ROBERT W. DUEMLING</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: September 11, 1989</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before we start a review of your Foreign Service career, I
                        wonder whether you can give us a short description of your background.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: I grew up in Northern Indiana—Fort Wayne—until I was thirteen years old
                    at the beginning of World War II. My father, who was a dermatologist, joined the
                    US Navy during W.W.II and was assigned to the Naval Hospital in San Diego,
                    California. He moved the family there and I lived there from age thirteen to
                    seventeen. By the end of the War, we had all become so pleased with Southern
                    California as opposed to Northern Indiana that my father agreed upon discharge
                    that he would establish his dermatology practice in San Diego. My family in
                    effect was transplanted by World War II. I graduated from high school in San
                    Diego in 1946, just after the end of W.W.II and then went to Yale for four
                    years, majoring in American Studies. Upon graduation, I won a fellowship to
                    Cambridge University and spent a year at St. John's College studying
                    architectural history. Through my American studies I had became interested in
                    architecture and art as an expression of social and intellectual history. I was
                    more interested in the intellectual aspects of architectural history. I became
                    so interested that after that year at Cambridge, I went back to Yale, spending
                    two years in the graduate school getting an M.A. in the History of Art. In those
                    days, and perhaps still, Yale would only accept doctoral candidates. I was
                    therefore technically a Ph.D. candidate, but after two years and an M.A. I
                    decided that I had satisfied essentially my intellectual interests in that field
                    and I really wanted to get back to a more operational life. At that point, I had
                    a deferment because although the Korean War had begun, I was a graduate student,
                    but when I got my M.A. in 1953, I chose to enter the military, although I
                    suspect that I could have stayed out. I did that because I felt I had a
                    “deferred” obligation. So I went to the Navy's O.C.S. in Newport, starting in
                    November, 1953. I was a “pre-designated” into the intelligence program. I
                    graduated from Newport on April 1, 1954 and then went for some additional
                    training for intelligence officers. This is a very interesting field in the Navy
                    because it has to do with determining the strike missions of aircraft. I was
                    assigned to a squadron which was based in San Diego—my old hometown—but also
                    deployed to the Far East to Atsugi—the air station outside Yokohama. This was a
                    former Japanese air station taken over after the War by the Americans. This
                    particular squadron, which was designated VC-6, was a squadron which had the
                    capability of delivering both H- and A-bombs. Therefore, my job as an
                    intelligence officer was to plan the missions to deliver these weapons over
                    designated targets. There is a whole targeting program shared by the Air Force,
                    the Navy and perhaps the Army as well. There were designated targets. This is
                    back in the 1954-55 period when US relations with China were chilly. My squadron
                    had as assigned targets primarily airfields in both China and the Maritime
                    provinces of the Soviet Union, near Vladivostok. This was of course still peace
                    time, but that is when you train for war. Basically, therefore, we were training
                    pilots in how to plan a flight path into these targets avoiding radar and other
                    protective devices in so far as possible. My job was to plan attack missions
                    theoretically using both hydrogen and atom bombs, both of which were in the
                    inventory. I did that both at Atsugi and on board aircraft carriers in the
                    Western Pacific. I spent a total of a year deployed in the Far East.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In another interview, it was pointed out that the US
                        military during the Matsu-Quemoy crisis discussed rather blithely the
                        possibility of taking out enemy airfields unconcerned by the collateral
                        casualties that might be inflicted on millions of civilians. Were you, as a
                        junior officer, cognizant of this problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: The attitude of the military at the time was significantly different
                    from what it is today. You have to remember that in 1953-55, when I was in the
                    Navy, we were still very much in the midst of the Cold War. We were responding
                    to the attack that had taken place on the Korean Peninsula. Several years had
                    passed since the Berlin blockade of the late ''40s, but there was still a very
                    great concern throughout the US government and its military planners that we
                    could conceivably face a very serious military threat again at any time.
                    Therefore, the assumption was that these strategic targets, as opposed to
                    tactical ones, would only be attacked in the case of a full scale war. The
                    attitude of the squadron to which I was assigned was that the defense of the
                    United States was paramount and that whatever was required to defend the US
                    would be done. If the President of the US ordered that this would happen, it
                    would happen. I am quite sure we did not consider very much the prospect of
                    civilian casualties as a result of our actions. Incidentally, these airfields
                    were in very sparsely populated areas, mostly on the coastline of China and the
                    USSR. That isn't to say that nuclear clouds wouldn't be blown over populated
                    areas; they certainly would have been. But that particular consideration was not
                    in people's minds, despite the fact that we lived and operated from Japan which
                    had both Hiroshima and Nagasaki. I visited both of them when I was a young naval
                    officer and saw the museums there which recorded the devastation that had taken
                    place. Many years later, when I returned to Japan as a foreign service officer,
                    one of my responsibilities in our Tokyo Embassy was to be the liaison with the
                    Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission (ABCC) which is the US government's organization
                    in Hiroshima with a branch in Nagasaki to study the effects of the atomic bombs
                    on the victims. It also had a clinic to treat the medical consequences of those
                    devastating weapons. So I found myself looking at the other side of the
                    proposition many years later as a foreign service officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get into the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: While I was in the Navy, I met a friend who also subsequently joined
                    the Foreign Service and became an Ambassador—George Roberts. George and I shared
                    a bunk room on one of the aircraft carriers—the Hancock—when I went aboard with
                    my squadron. In casual conversations with George, I asked him what he planned to
                    do when he got out of the Navy and he said that he wanted to be a diplomat. So I
                    asked what that was. George then described to me what diplomacy was and I asked
                    how one joins the game. He explained the Foreign Service and its examination. I
                    thought that sounded very interesting because while I was an undergraduate I had
                    been very interested in international affairs. I was the chairman of an
                    international affairs discussion group and also very active on the daily
                    newspaper—”The Yale Daily News”. That got me involved in day-to-day activities
                    and current events. Therefore, while I was in the Navy, after talking to George,
                    I took the Foreign Service written exams. I passed them and then took the orals
                    and passed them. When I left the Navy, I had some options and spent the summer
                    of 1957 looking at them. I could have returned to Yale to complete my Ph.D. work
                    and then head for an academic career. I went to New Haven to discuss this avenue
                    with my old mentors. They encouraged me to follow this path. I also was
                    interested in journalism and through some friends I had an interview at
                    “Fortune” magazine, which indicated an interest in me. But I also went to
                    Washington to talk to the Foreign Service people. They said, that since I had
                    passed the exams, they could offer me an appointment in October or November. I
                    considered all this for two or three months and finally decided that the Foreign
                    Service offered me the opportunity to pursue more of the matters in which I was
                    particularly interested. Specifically, the Foreign Service and a career in
                    diplomacy offered the opportunity for constant learning, the expansion of one's
                    intellectual horizons—new languages to learn, new cultures to become acquainted
                    with, new political and economic situations to master. The potential
                    intellectual stimulation of the Foreign Service appealed to me very much. The
                    second important aspect was the opportunity to write. I have always enjoyed
                    writing and you do a lot of writing in the Foreign Service—telegrams, airgrams,
                    reports, memcons, etc. The third thing that appealed to me was the travel,
                    moving around the world, being involved in affairs and current events and with
                    other countries. I have traveled all my life—as a child, my parents took me on
                    numerous trips (my mother was a history buff and I took up her interests).
                    Travel and history go well together. It was all of these aspects that finally
                    persuaded me to join the Foreign Service, which offered me this range of
                    opportunities for which I felt a particular attraction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You entered in 1957. What was your first assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: My first assignment was in the Secretariat. I finished the A-100 basic
                    officer course and I was assigned into the Executive Secretariat (S/S). S/S was
                    a staff which essentially works for the senior officers of the Department. It
                    works for the Secretary, the Deputy Secretary and the principal Under
                    Secretaries. You are constantly dealing with the paper flow between the
                    Department, the Foreign Service and the leadership of the Department.
                    Conversely, also of course the flow back down—the decision memoranda that have
                    to be implemented. It is a very interesting staff which keeps in touch with the
                    senior officers of the Department and with the policy questions that are of
                    current importance in the Department. It is of course a superb place to start a
                    Foreign Service career. I think anybody who serves in S/S considers it a prime
                    opportunity to learn something.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was your first assignment in the Foreign Service.
                        What lessons did you learn about reporting and field operations that served
                        you well later?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: You learn a lot about how to manipulate the system. First of all, you
                    learn immediately what the structure of the Department is and how it
                    inter-relates with the Embassies. You come to understand how those telegrams
                    come in from all over the world. The system of course is different today from it
                    was in 1957. My first assignment in the Secretariat was, together with another
                    officer, to edit the “Morning Summary' of the most important telegrams that had
                    been received from all over the world during the preceding night. We came
                    extremely early in the morning—about 4 a.m.—and we would sift through all the
                    telegrams. In those days, you were looking at actual pieces of paper that had
                    printed on them the messages from overseas. My colleague and I would physically
                    go through these stacks of telegrams. It was our judgment as to what was key.
                    You might well ask how a junior Foreign Service officer on his first assignment
                    got assigned to a job like that. It was like being a newspaper editor. It
                    doesn't take very long to learn what is important and what isn't. There may be
                    some subtleties that you may miss, but major overnight developments are not
                    going to be terribly subtle. We would read through all the material and write
                    brief summaries of the telegrams. We prepared a document that had to be
                    available for the senior officers by eight o'clock in the morning. That was a
                    document that might be as long as five or six pages. It would be made up of
                    these precis of perhaps ten different items. You would attach the full telegram
                    to the back of the document so that the persons reading the summary, if they
                    were interested, could read the full text. You learn very quickly the virtue of
                    succinctness, the importance of being direct and putting the priorities in the
                    right order and of offering precise assessments as well as proposals for action.
                    You got some feel for the culture of the institution—the kind of issues and
                    problems that are appealing and which are of concern and which aren't, which
                    issues will be dealt with at highest levels and which would be pushed down the
                    line. You get a good feel for that when you are in the Secretariat. Serving
                    there hones your presentation skills: you learn how to write to the point; you
                    learn how to draft things with precision and succinctness. You learn how to
                    present a subject in a way that the person to whom it is directed will be able
                    to deal with it and make some decisions. You get an idea of priorities—what is
                    of concern and what isn't. Later on in my career I could frame things in a way
                    that I thought would enhance the likelihood of attracting attention both through
                    format and language and the organization of the material. That was process in
                    large measure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your first overseas assignment was to Rome in 1960 as a
                        political officer. What were your responsibilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: When I was coming to the end of my normal two year assignment in the
                    Secretariat, the standard personnel system was cranking up an onward assignment.
                    I was supposed to go to Trinidad. I was rather pleased with that because at the
                    time there was a lot of discussion about a Caribbean association of states which
                    would involve Trinidad, Jamaica and Barbados. It looked like an interesting
                    development. One morning I was delivering the “Morning Summary” to Loy
                    Henderson's office. He was an Under Secretary and one of two or three senior
                    people in the Department. His staff assistant, who was a very able and promising
                    officer, asked me where I was being assigned. I told him that it was
                    Port-of-Spain, Trinidad. He thought that something better could be worked out.
                    He thought it was not good enough and wanted to find something more interesting
                    for me. I said I thought that it could be very interesting, but he disagreed.
                    The next thing I heard was a phone call from the Office of Personnel. They told
                    me that my assignment to Trinidad would be canceled. I told them that I had just
                    been down to the Office of Transportation making travel arrangements and that I
                    was excited by the prospects of going to Trinidad. Personnel said that this
                    assignment was canceled, but could not tell me what else they had up their
                    sleeves. I demurred and they finally admitted that although it was not yet
                    final, they had an assignment in Rome in mind. I didn't say anything. The voice
                    at the other end of the phone finally said:”Hello. Are you there?”. I admitted
                    that I was and then the voice asked whether I wasn't pleased. I said:” I am not
                    sure. The situation in the Caribbean looks interesting and I am not sure that I
                    am that pleased about going to Rome”. The voice on the other end finally
                    said:”You are crazy”. I agreed to go to Rome and became the Ambassador's aide.
                    Having just left the Secretariat, I had all the skills necessary to be the
                    Ambassador's aide. The Ambassador at this time was Zellerbach, a political
                    appointee from San Francisco. A wonderful man, who had been the chief of the US
                    Marshall Plan mission in Italy. He had been a very successful industrialist—the
                    Crown-Zellerbach paper corporation. He was a huge success in Italy because the
                    whole Italian business community respected him very highly for his successes in
                    American business. He knew all about the Italian economy from his days in the
                    Marshall Plan. He was therefore a very successful Ambassador. I arrived in the
                    summer of 1960. In the fall of 1960, Jack Kennedy defeated Nixon and therefore
                    Mr. Zellerbach as a Republican appointee left the following Spring. He was
                    succeeded by Frederick Reinhardt, who was a career officer who had been briefly
                    US Ambassador in Cairo before Kennedy assigned him to Rome. Fred was a super
                    person, a very able officer who went on to be a great success as Ambassador to
                    Italy. I worked for Fred as his staff aide for about another year at which time
                    I moved to the Political Section. I spent a year and half in that Section. So I
                    was in Rome for a total of three years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you agree that there has been a considerable amount
                        of political micro-reporting from Rome on a political situation that has
                        been essentially stable since 1948? Were we getting too involved in the
                        minutiae of Italian politics?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: That is a very long story. We manipulated the Italian elections of 1948
                    in order to forestall a Communist regime. That experience deeply conditioned the
                    involvement of the Embassy toward the whole Italian political scene. What I
                    remember vividly from that period was the whole business of the opening to the
                    Left—The “Apertura-a-Sinistra”. That was considered a very controversial
                    proposition. Should we or shouldn't we encourage the idea of the opening to the
                    Left? That issue deeply divided the American Embassy staff. Our Deputy Chief of
                    Mission (DCM) at the time was Outerbridge Horsey, who felt very strongly that
                    the opening to the Left was a kind of Trojan Horse of the Communists. He very
                    much opposed the idea. Another officer in the Political section—younger than
                    Horsey—thought it made a lot of sense. He was in close touch with the Socialist
                    Party. In the Political Section we were all assigned to specific parties, so
                    that collectively we had a broad view of the Italian political scene. We had no
                    connections with the Communist Party, but we met with the Christian Democrats,
                    who formed the government, but also with the various branches of the Socialist
                    Party, the Republican Party, the Liberal Party, etc. I suppose what happens is
                    that with that degree of complexity in the local political situation, it draws
                    the Embassy' political reporters more and more into complex assessments and
                    evaluations. It becomes somewhat like counting angels on the head of a pin. It
                    gets carried to extremes. There was no question that the issue of the proper US
                    role in Italian domestic politics was a very major issue. Arthur Schlesinger,
                    Jr.—historian, Kennedy aide—was very interested in political machinations. He
                    came to Italy and made some political contacts—White House authorized—, but he
                    was not in touch with the American Embassy. He talked to some people on the
                    political scene in Italy. It aroused the ire of Outerbridge Horsey, who was at
                    this time the Charg� d'affaires, between Zellerbach and Reinhardt. The very idea
                    of a US representative visiting a foreign country officially without contacting
                    the Embassy infuriated Horsey. Reinhardt took a more balanced view of that
                    situation. My own involvement in this affair was very minor. I was the low man
                    on the totem pole in the Political Section. I was put in charge of writing
                    routine messages, biographic reporting and other pedestrian assignments.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1963, you were assigned to Kuala Lumpur. How did that
                        come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: I had been in the Navy in Japan and became tremendously interested in
                    Japan and particularly in Japanese culture and society. So much so that when I
                    left Japan at the end of my navy assignment, I said to myself that I had to
                    leave Japan right away because if I didn't I would become a Japanophile who
                    would settle down and just get deeper and deeper into the society. I did get out
                    of it, but when I came into the Foreign Service and was given an opportunity to
                    study a “hard language”, I decided to shy away from it and not study Japanese
                    because it was too soon after my entrance into the Foreign Service. I wanted to
                    get a broader view of the Foreign Service before plunging back into Japanese
                    affairs. But I was very interested in the Far East as a result of my naval
                    experience and my visits to a number of countries out there abroad the aircraft
                    carrier. So I told a friend in the Personnel Office—Christian Chapman— that I
                    would love to go back to the Far East after my Rome tour. He agreed and since he
                    was in charge of assignments into the Far East, he found me an assignment in
                    Kuala Lumpur which was not a language-requirement country, having been a former
                    British colony. Knowing Malay was therefore not essential. So I was assigned to
                    KL to be a one-man Consular Section. At that time, before the “track” system, it
                    was felt that a junior officer should obtain experience in different functions.
                    Having served as a political officer in Rome and knowing that I would prefer to
                    remain in the political area for the rest of my career, it was important that I
                    become acquainted with the other Foreign Service facets and aspects. I was
                    therefore very pleased to get this assignment as a one-man Consular Section.
                    That was much better than having to go to a huge Embassy in a visa mill where
                    you would get a much more limited experience. This way I would be performing all
                    the functions of a Consular Section—protection and welfare, immigrant and
                    visitors visas, passports, citizenship. So for one year, that was my job and I
                    learned a lot, getting the consular functions “under my belt”. There was very
                    good rotational program at our Embassy in K.L. and the DCM there, Don McCue, was
                    very good about trying to give a variety of experience to the junior officers in
                    the Embassy. He rotated people throughout. So after I had been there in the
                    Consular Section for one year, he assigned me to the Economic Section and I
                    spent about eight months there, responsible for all the basic reporting on the
                    natural rubber industry and the tin industry which were the Malaysian principal
                    export commodities at that time. That was very good economic experience. It got
                    me involved with US exports and imports into Malaysia. I learned a little bit
                    about the American business community in Malaysia. Then our Ambassador, Jim
                    Bell, decided that I would be the right guy to become the Consul in charge of
                    the small Consulate we had in East Malaysia, in Kuching, Sarawak. Therefore, I
                    went to Borneo, which is divided one-third —the old British Part—consisting of
                    Sarawak, Brunei and Sabah (Sarawak and Sabah joined Malaysia) and the other two
                    thirds consisting of Kalimantan which is part of Indonesia. I went to run the
                    Kuching consulate, which no longer exists. I was responsible for three
                    areas—Sarawak, Brunei and Sabah— reporting across the board on political and
                    economic issues. That was very interesting. This was at the time of so-called
                    “confrontation” between Malaysia and Indonesia. The only place where the two
                    countries abutted was in Borneo, so that when I was there, there were Indonesian
                    raids across the border into Sarawak. That was never much of a war. It was a
                    low-level guerrilla activity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a feeling that the incursions were not serious
                        or could be contained?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: The thought was that it could be contained without too much trouble.
                    Most people felt that it was primarily posturing on the part of the Indonesians.
                    No one thought that they would do much. In the meanwhile, there were these
                    guerrilla activities. There was an attack, for example, on a police station
                    seven miles outside of Kuching during which several people were killed. There
                    was always the concern about infiltrators. No one thought it would lead to full
                    scale war, but at the same time it was not anything that you could just ignore.
                    My territory also included Brunei. In those days it was a British protectorate.
                    It is now independent and we have an Embassy there. I did have the fun, while
                    Consul in Kuching, of representing the US President at the wedding of the
                    current Sultan of Brunei, who was then about 21 years old, marrying a young lady
                    of about 18. I doubt very much that the President knew that he was being
                    represented at the marriage of the Sultan and in fact I don't remember any
                    particular directions from Washington or the Embassy on what to do. I just
                    figured that we ought to have be there. I had to give some gift; I went to
                    Singapore and bought an American made silver cream and sugar set. That was given
                    on behalf of the President of the United States. This was all on my own
                    initiative. This is the sort of stuff that when you are in the Foreign Service,
                    way out in the boondocks somewhere, you take the initiative.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we show much concern with the fighting? Did we try to
                        bolster the Malaysian side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: Yes, we were. We didn't want to be drawn into the dispute publicly, but
                    essentially we supported the independence of the Malaysian states against any
                    potential Indonesian aspirations to take over Malaysia. We were supportive of
                    the Malaysian cause. One tends to forget the facts and the mood of the situation
                    at the time. We forget the Communist international of 1948 and their plans to
                    foment political unrest and disorder in various places. One of those places was
                    Malaysia. There had been the so called “emergency” which was a serious
                    insurrection which took place in Malaysia throughout the early 1950's. It was
                    not until it was effectively brought under control that the British granted
                    independence to Malaya in 1957. There was still concern when I was serving in
                    Malaysia and Borneo for the vestigial Communist party movement working out in
                    the jungles. There was a certain amount of political agitation going on. So
                    there was some interest and concern for what could happen.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any reflections about our Embassy in
                        Indonesia, which was then under Ambassador Howard Jones, who was viewed as
                        being too pro-Sukarno?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: There was a famous episode when Jones sat on the platform at a big
                    political rally with Sukarno. When introduced to the crowd by Sukarno, Jones
                    raised his fist and shouted “Defeat Malaysia” in Indonesian. This was totally
                    unauthorized and we thought that Jones had been carried away. It was totally
                    ill-advised. We laughed about it because we thought it was slightly loony. There
                    was a certain tension between our Embassies in Malaysia and in Indonesia and our
                    Consul General in Singapore as well. There were three different posts involved
                    in the Malaysia-Indonesia dispute: one was the Embassy in Kuala Lumpur, one was
                    the Consulate General in Singapore and one was the Embassy in Jakarta. It was
                    interesting to watch the telegraphic traffic emanating from these three posts
                    because they were each reporting on the viewpoints of the states to which they
                    were accredited. There was undoubtedly a certain amount of “clientitis” creeping
                    into the reporting. There were some small, subtle digs from each post about the
                    others. Singapore joined Malaya in 1963 to form Malaysia. I arrived in Kuala
                    Lumpur just after that event had taken place. Therefore, one of the factors on
                    the American side, was the Consul General in Singapore which had been an
                    independent post, but after the formation of Malaysia, had become a subordinate
                    post to the Embassy in Kuala Lumpur. That was a hard pill to swallow for the
                    Consul General in Singapore. That post had been independent for a long time.
                    That situation did not last very long because within a couple of years Singapore
                    left Malaysia. That was a fascinating evolution. I was in a position to see that
                    situation in considerable detail because shortly after I arrived in K.L., I met
                    the British Ambassador—High Commissioner— and his wife. We became life time
                    friends. We remained very friendly after all of us had left K.L. They invited me
                    to their daughter's wedding at Eton College some years later. I remained in
                    close touch with them until they died. In any case, I became good friends with
                    Lord and Lady Head. He had a very distinguished career—he had been one of the
                    youngest Brigadiers in the British Army. He left the British Army at the end of
                    World War II in order to go into politics. He was the Minister of Defense in the
                    Eden Cabinet at the time of the Suez Canal crisis in 1956. When Harold MacMillan
                    shuffled the Cabinet, Lord Head declined to stay at Defense because the Prime
                    Minister was planning to reduce the size of the British Army and, somewhat like
                    Winston Churchill, Head didn't want to preside over that. He then began a
                    diplomatic career—he was High Commissioner in Nigeria and then Malaysia. He was
                    a breath of fresh air in Malaysia because despite the fact that he was a
                    Viscount, he had started as a commoner. His wife was born into nobility, being
                    the daughter of the Earl of Shaftesbury. Both were vigorous types. Lady Head was
                    very liberal and despite her ancestry, in manner, speech and dress was a very
                    plain woman. She wore plain dresses; she wore flat shoes, she wore a kerchief
                    around her head. She thought that Malaysia was an extremely interesting place.
                    She got involved in many activities—she went to political meetings. While her
                    husband was dealing with the Prime Minister and other high level officials, she
                    was out in the boondocks. They were quite a political couple. We played a lot of
                    tennis together on their court. During this very turbulent political period, one
                    of the Heads' frequently unannounced visitors was Lee Kuan Yew, the Prime
                    Minister of Singapore who made Singapore independent again in 1965. I was at the
                    British residence on the day that in effect the Prime Minister of Malaysia,
                    Tunku Abdul Rahman, threw Singapore out of Malaysia. I'll never forget Lee Kuan
                    Yew rushing to the British residence unannounced because he was in such close
                    touch with the British government about these problems. He was in tears. He
                    consulted with the High Commissioner and then left. I asked Lord Head what was
                    going on and he told me confidentially that Lee just had a session with the
                    Malaysian Prime Minister who told Lee that he thought that he (Lee) had violated
                    a gentlemen's agreement regarding the forthcoming elections. The Prime Minister
                    thought that Lee's party, which was based in Singapore, would not contest any
                    elections on the mainland. But apparently Lee, after having made that agreement,
                    went back to his own Cabinet which over-ruled him. It decided that their party
                    would contest in two or three constituencies on the mainland. That was obviously
                    contrary to the agreement originally reached and the Tunku threw Singapore out
                    of Malaysia. This anecdote is interesting in part because there are many
                    versions of how the rupture between Malaysia and Singapore took place. One
                    version had it that Singapore and Lee took the initiative to opt out of
                    Malaysia. That was not the case. My sense was that Lee would have preferred to
                    stay in Malaysia because at the time there was considerable question about the
                    economic viability of a little city-state like Singapore. Singapore then, as
                    contrasted to now, was not the economic major player. It was a busy little place
                    with a certain amount of commerce and some manufacturing, but it was nothing
                    like Hong Kong. What has of course happened is that Singapore has become the
                    “other Hong Kong”. With the political changes that will take place before the
                    end of the century in H.K., Singapore may become the pre-eminent financial
                    center of East Asia. None of that of course was the case back then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went back to Washington in 1966 at the height of the
                        Vietnam War, to become Special Assistant to the Assistant Secretary for East
                        Asia. What were your responsibilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: I was asked to return after one year in Borneo to become the economic
                    officer for the Malaysia-Singapore desk. There wasn't too much to do in that
                    job. I was underemployed. I worked closely with Bob Barnett, who was the
                    Bureau's Deputy Assistant Secretary for Economic Affairs. Barnett was
                    intellectually very stimulating and therefore I enjoyed that aspect of my job.
                    The rest was pretty boring. Fortunately, Bill Bundy, the Assistant Secretary,
                    needed a new special assistant to run his office. He had spied me and knew that
                    I was underemployed. He therefore asked if I would be willing to fill the job
                    and I readily agreed. This was a little bit of a curse, having been in the
                    Secretariat at the start of my career, being a special assistant to an
                    Ambassador soon thereafter and now returning to a special assistant to an
                    Assistant Secretary. It tags you as a “staff guy”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But it all tagged you as a “comer”. It put you on a fast
                        track for moving up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: Correct. And that was the advantage of it. After one week on the job
                    with Bill, I went to him and pointed out that he was primarily occupied with
                    Vietnam, although his area of responsibility covered all of East Asia. I added
                    that he needed someone who could keep track of what else was happening in the
                    area. It was a role that I could play. I would help somewhat on Vietnam, but
                    essentially I would be his eyes and ears on all other matters in the area to
                    alert him to when he should get involved in issues. Of course, much that was
                    happening in the area was related to Vietnam, but still, there were a lot of
                    things happening in Japan, Australia, Indonesia and China that required
                    attention. I told him that I would focus on that and not get involved deeply in
                    Vietnam. Bill Bundy agreed and that is the way it worked out. I worked for Bill
                    and subsequently for Marshall Green—a change prompted by a political change in
                    the White House. I started working for Bill beginning in 1968 until early 1970
                    over a period of about two and half years. What was interesting about it was
                    that in those days, more importantly than now, there were inter-agency
                    groups—called Senior Interdepartmental Group (SIG) and Regional
                    Interdepartmental Group (RIG)—at differing organizational levels. They drew
                    together the key players from the various agencies interested in foreign
                    affairs. The chair was always the State Department's regional Assistant
                    Secretary. In my case, Bill Bundy chaired the inter-agency group on East Asia.
                    Ranking officers from the National Security Council (NSC), CIA, International
                    Security Affairs (ISA-Defense), the Joint Chiefs, USIA, and AID. This was a
                    policy coordinating group. I was the Executive Secretary of the group. I
                    organized the meetings, the agenda and so forth. Another thing I did when I
                    worked for Bill was to get the academic community together about twice per year.
                    Bundy had a scholarly bent and wanted to meet with academic experts on the Far
                    East. It was an advisory group. We had two panels: one on China and the other on
                    all the other parts of the Far East. They overlapped somewhat with three or four
                    persons of a total of about twelve for each panel, sitting on both serving as a
                    kind of hinge. These were very distinguished scholars from around the
                    country—people like Ed Reischauer, Lucien Pye, Bob Scalopino, Fairbanks from
                    Harvard. Very distinguished political science experts, some historians, some
                    economists. We would bring them together every six months for a three day
                    period. I would produce a selection of reading materials, mostly
                    classified—think pieces, key telegrams, etc. I would put them into a packet,
                    ready for the participants to read when they arrived in Washington usually one
                    day before the conference started. We would have policy discussions, chaired by
                    Bill, with these people. That was fascinating. We would have the inputs of these
                    people from all over the US academic world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the panels take an entirely different view from that
                        of the government, particularly on Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: No. As a matter of fact, what one would see were some people with great
                    reservations about what was happening in Vietnam; others essentially supported
                    the government's Vietnam policy. One thing which the academics agreed upon,
                    after Bill thanked them effusively for coming and taking time out of their busy
                    schedules, was that it was a tremendous opportunity for them. They had an
                    opportunity to learn from the readings and the discussions which they could not
                    obtain in their academic environment, where they were not involved in
                    operational policy problems. They obtained an insight into some of the gritty
                    realities which would not have come to their attention otherwise. For the most
                    part, they were rather diffident in their criticism of the government's
                    policies. They were certainly some reservations expressed about the wisdom of
                    the government's policy and about being dragged deeper and deeper into something
                    from which we were not getting the desired results in the desired time
                    frame.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have the feeling that things were being left
                        undone in the other parts of East Asia outside of Vietnam? Or that we were
                        being driven into doing things because of Vietnam which might have been
                        counter-productive?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: First of all, I thought that an awful lot of the Vietnam policy was
                    “wish-think”. I thought that in listening to some of the presentations—I used to
                    have this discussion with my friend and college classmate George Carver, who was
                    in CIA in an extremely responsible position both on the operational and
                    intelligence sides—they were much rosier and optimistic than they should have
                    been. I thought that there were an awful lot of people putting the best
                    construction on the data. In terms of Vietnam crowding out legitimate concerns
                    from other parts of the region, there is no question that this was the case. I
                    can't give any specific example, but I felt that sometimes our relationships
                    with the Japanese got somewhat skewed— we weren't paying enough attention to how
                    the Japanese economy was evolving through this period. We leaned pretty hard on
                    some of our allies—for example Johnson's efforts with Harold Holt of Australia.
                    That was distorting our relationships with some of the Southeast Asia countries,
                    which had their own agendas and concerns—economic development. To see these
                    resources being siphoned off into the military activities in Southeast Asia,
                    specifically Vietnam, one had to ask how constructive this policy really was. In
                    terms of paying attention, I think that Bill Bundy never lost sight of what was
                    happening elsewhere in the region. He couldn't perhaps give it as much time as
                    he might have wished, but Bundy was extremely able and intellectually superior
                    and could keep an awful lot of balls in the air, even though, he was preoccupied
                    with Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a change when Marshall Green came in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: Yes, there was, because Green's arrival coincided with the Nixon
                    Administration's and Kissinger's advent. This Administration decided to go for a
                    negotiated settlement. The whole policy changed and Green was part of that. I am
                    not sure to what extent Marshall was one of the architects of the policy. I
                    think he was. He was extensively consulted by Henry Kissinger who was
                    essentially the architect of the policy. You recall all the negotiations with
                    the Vietnamese in Paris. So there was a change. Marshall, also, as Vietnam began
                    to spin down a little, was able to devote a little more attention to other sides
                    of what was happening in Asia. I might interject here that on the subject of
                    Japan—I mentioned earlier that I became fascinated with Japan in the 1950s when
                    I was in the Navy. While in the Secretariat, I was involved in pulling papers
                    together with Secretary Christian Herter before he went off to a Cabinet level
                    meeting in Tokyo—we had an agreement with the Japanese that we would have
                    periodic Cabinet level meetings which would usually involve the Secretary of
                    State and at least one more Cabinet officer in discussions which would alternate
                    between Japan and the US. I remember preparing the position papers, one of which
                    had to do with what was then called “dollar liberalization”. That had to do with
                    the exchange rate between the yen and the dollar and its impact on trade and
                    trade balances. Even then, in the late '50s, we were trying to get the Japanese
                    to allow the yen-dollar exchange rate to ease up somewhat because we recognized
                    that even then the yen was being kept artificially low. The exchange rate was
                    360 yen to a dollar. We thought that it should slowly go down, raising the value
                    of yen vis-a-vis the dollar. The Japanese continued to stand us off on that
                    because they kept claiming that it was much too soon, that they were still
                    rebuilding, etc. In effect, we allowed the Japanese to have a clear trade
                    advantage with us. That was conscious on our part, but we were beginning to
                    worry about the longer range implications of that arrangement. I can recall to
                    my astonishment and chagrin that periodically—for example when I got back to
                    Japanese affairs when I was posted to Tokyo starting in 1970—when position
                    papers were being written on “dollar liberalization” for meetings with Japanese
                    officials they had virtually not changed. We were still trying to persuade the
                    Japanese to allow the yen to gain in value in relationship to the dollar. We
                    still had not persuaded the Japanese to do that. A lot or people, myself
                    included, had the feeling that the artificially low value of the yen was leading
                    us into some very serious economic trading problems with the Japanese. This is
                    of course a story which is now familiar to everybody. It went on for so very,
                    very long. When the dam finally broke, the yen appreciated very rapidly in a
                    relatively short period of time. In the meantime, it permitted the Japanese to
                    export into the US market at essentially a subsidized price by their own
                    government because of the low value of the yen. It put us in a terrible bind in
                    terms of trade imbalances which then got bigger and bigger. That situation is
                    somewhat akin to being a naval officer, who is “driving the boat”, trying to
                    turn the ship. You find out if you steering a big ship, that it takes a long
                    time between turning the wheel and the effect on the course of the ship. The
                    exact same thing is true when it comes to adjusting exchange rates. Nothing
                    happens overnight. It takes some years to redress the imbalances.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1970, you went back to Japan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: Right. I decided that I could go back to Japan and still maintain my
                    objectivity. By this time, of course, I was too old to become a Japanese
                    language officer, but I insisted on learning some Japanese. I was assigned to a
                    position that was not “language-designated”—that is it did not require a
                    Japanese speaker. I was supposed to go to Tokyo in the Summer of 1970, but the
                    incumbent of the job decided he wanted to extend for one more year. So the job
                    did not open up in the summer. But it was the period of the Exposition in Osaka.
                    I was given the liaison job between the American Consul General in Osaka and the
                    American Pavilion. That was again a staff job. That occupied me from April to
                    November 1970. That was a lot of fun and very interesting. It got me back to
                    Japan and I started learning Japanese with a wonderful Japanese who was on the
                    staff of Consulate General in Osaka. Because the job in Tokyo would not open
                    until summer of 1971, I went to Japanese language school when my assignment in
                    Osaka was ended. I had to persuade the system to let me go to the language
                    school in Yokohama. I found myself a tiny little Japanese-style house in
                    Kamakura, where the big Daibutsu is. I spent seven months in intensive Japanese
                    language training which got me at least a certain amount of speaking ability. I
                    didn't learn to read and write, but I did learn conversational Japanese so I
                    could get around, at least. Then in the summer of 1971, I went to Tokyo where I
                    headed the political-external section. The Political section in Tokyo was
                    divided in two parts: one part focuses on domestic politics and the other on
                    foreign affairs—Japanese foreign policy all around the world. We have a very
                    close relationship with the Japanese so that my job was essentially one of
                    liaison with their Foreign Ministry. I had an assistant and we covered all of
                    the foreign policy areas in which Japan and the United States each took a strong
                    interest, which was most of the world. It certainly included Asia, Europe, the
                    Soviet Union and China; less so Latin America and Africa. We were constantly
                    consulting the people in the Foreign Ministry to find out what the Japanese were
                    thinking about in terms of their own foreign policy positions vis-a-vis these
                    countries and then reporting back to Washington. One of most active things I did
                    when I first took the job was to become involved in preparations for the fall
                    session of the UN General Assembly which in 1971 was addressing the issue of
                    which government would represent China. There was a huge battle in the UN on
                    this issue-Taiwan vs. Peking. The US policy was to retain the Nationalist
                    Government in the Security Council seat. We worked extremely hard to line up our
                    allies and muster support to hold the line in support of the Nationalist
                    Government. In the meanwhile, as we subsequently found out, Henry Kissinger was
                    dealing privately with the government in Peking and in fact, a couple of days
                    before the final show-down at the UN, it was revealed that Kissinger was in
                    Peking. He was there on the day the vote took place at the UN. The vote went
                    against us by at least ten or more votes. I had been deeply involved, meeting
                    daily with the Japanese Foreign Office, because we coordinated very closely and
                    they were lobbying around the world, particularly in Asia, in support of the
                    Nationalist Government as were we. Of course, Henry Kissinger just pulled the
                    rug out from under this effort. That was the Nixon “shokku”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did this go over with your contacts in the Japanese
                        Foreign Ministry?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: The Japanese are very polite. I was embarrassed. I was flabbergasted. I
                    was chagrined. The Japanese, very politely and very directly, said to me that
                    Henry Kissinger had a double game going on. They didn't blame me because they
                    recognized that I had been totally uninformed about the US government's two
                    track approach. They said that my government had used me and had expected me to
                    be as effective as possible to carry out one track of this policy. They kind of
                    shrugged, but I did lose some credibility. But as Henry Kissinger has been
                    quoted on more than one occasion: “Who cares if some civil servant is
                    embarrassed?” He could care less. It is of course some kind of experience—deeply
                    unpleasant for a career diplomat because one's reliability and credibility is
                    the major stock in trade. The manual on this subject by Harold Nicholson, the
                    great British diplomatist, made it clear that above all else, Ambassadors and
                    diplomats at all levels have to be reliable and have to be recognized for their
                    integrity and credibility. When you have an experience like the one I just
                    described it is detrimental to say the least to one's image of integrity and
                    credibility. Fortunately, the Japanese realized that I was as much the victim of
                    the situation as they were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was some of the same impact on the Foreign Service
                        as a whole. After that event, it did not have quite the same faith in the
                        President and the Secretary of State as before. Would their future
                        directives be real or once again, intentionally misdirected?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: You may be right in pin-pointing that event as a changing force in
                    attitudes. There have been some very significant attitudinal changes within the
                    Foreign Service certainly in the course of the thirty years I served in it. The
                    trust in the leadership is one of them. Can one be sure that the policy being
                    given to you by the leadership is really the one that they will follow? One must
                    ask oneself : “Is this sensible ? Should I lend myself to it?”. Perhaps in some
                    cases, there should be some holding back. That's unfortunate. Of course, there
                    are other things that effected that. For one, the politicalization of the
                    Foreign Service. Increasingly, the Foreign Service officer's view is that if he
                    is to get promoted, he has to play politics—both within and outside the Foreign
                    Service. He has to find a mentor, a protector, a rabbi in the White House or in
                    the NSC or somewhere who is going to advance his cause. Increasingly, people see
                    that assignments to highly desirable positions are administered not within the
                    Department, but dictated from outside. That means you have to have your friends
                    outside the Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any other periods during your career, besides
                        the China events you have just described, during which there was a conflict
                        between Japanese and American policy directions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: During my time in Japan, there were some tensions over Japanese policy
                    toward Iran. They were heavily dependant on Iranian oil at that time. They had
                    to be very careful about how they treated the government of Iran. They were much
                    less enamored with the Shah than we were. They were much more cautious about
                    what might happen in Iran. The Japanese may have seen the coming demise of the
                    Shah before we did. They positioned themselves to be a little less involved with
                    the Shah. They may have been able to build some bridges to other Arab states.
                    That was equally true with respect to Israel. The Japanese have never been
                    strong supporters of Israel. In part that was because we are talking
                    “real-politik” here. They are interested in the energy resources of the Middle
                    East and therefore they have always been very anxious to maintain very good
                    relations with Arab countries. They don't want to compromise those good
                    relations by getting too cozy with the Israelis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left Tokyo in 1974.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: That's correct. I was supposed to go to the Senior Seminar, but in the
                    meantime, Bob Ingersoll, who had been our Ambassador in Tokyo and whom I had
                    served there—we had become and remain very good friends and I thought he was a
                    super guy—had been the Assistant Secretary for the Far East since his Tokyo
                    assignment for a brief period and then became Henry Kissinger's Deputy
                    Secretary. At that time, he sent me a message asking that I return to help him
                    run his office as his Executive Assistant. I turned him down because I felt that
                    I had been assigned to too many staff positions and I thought that the
                    assignment to the Senior Seminar would position me for a good subsequent
                    assignment after the year. I told the Deputy Secretary that I was very flattered
                    but that I couldn't accept his offer. The telegraphic response to my position
                    was that Ingersoll had talked to the Director General, who had said that all
                    other things being equal, if I would work for the Deputy Secretary, I could go
                    to the Senior Seminar the following year. On that basis, I agreed and returned
                    to Washington to work for Bob Ingersoll.As always happens, once you get into a
                    job, you find there is a lot going on. Bob had a lot of responsibilities as
                    Deputy to Kissinger and I found myself deeply engaged in running his
                    office—sitting in all of the important meetings, being his note-taker on some of
                    the most sensitive meetings, participating on the Ambassadorial assignments
                    committee, which is always an interesting matter, etc. I actually stayed for two
                    years. I didn't see how I could have left after one year. As it turned out, Bob
                    decided that he would leave after two years, so that both of our departures took
                    place at essentially the same time. As I was nearing the one and three-quarters
                    mark, I began looking around for another assignment because I had decided at
                    this point that it would not necessarily serve my interests to go to the Senior
                    Seminar. I decided to look for something a little more operational. At that
                    moment, Tom Enders, who had been an old friend since our undergraduate days at
                    Yale and with whom I remained friendly during our Foreign Service years, had
                    been assigned to Canada as Ambassador. He asked me whether I would join him as
                    his Deputy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just to return to Ingersoll for a minute. What was your
                        impression of the Ambassadorial selection process during the Nixon-Kissinger
                        years?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: The usual pattern in this process was that a new administration had a
                    long list of supporters who had to be taken care of. So that the pressure comes
                    at the beginning. It is a kind of balloon at the beginning of a new
                    administration. By the time I went to work for Ingersoll—1974-76— it was the end
                    of the Nixon administration and the beginning of the Ford administration. By
                    that time, most if not all of the demanding supporters had been taken care of.
                    There was less pressure therefore by that time than there would have been at the
                    beginning of the administration. Even so, the White House continued to have its
                    nominees and people they wanted to appoint. The process in those days would call
                    for the White House personnel office to send over to the Department—Bob
                    Ingersoll—resumes to be looked over. He would be asked to interview some of
                    these people. In some cases, you had the sense that the White House knew that a
                    particular aspirant had very little going for him. One of the ways that the
                    White House used to get these people off their backs was to send their resumes
                    over to State with a request that the Deputy Secretary interview them. At least
                    that gave the impression that the candidates were getting some attention. I
                    would sit in on those interviews and would do the draft assessments on these
                    political supporters. I gave them to Bob Ingersoll in draft and he would edit
                    them. He agreed 99% of the time with my findings and would sign off on them
                    without changes—occasionally he would add a sentence or two. These reports would
                    be sent to the White House. More often than not, these assessments would
                    indicate that the candidate did not have the qualifications necessary for a
                    position in the Department. That would largely take care of the matter.
                    Sometimes, there were some attractive people who were obviously people of
                    substance. Ingersoll would then send back a note indicating that the Department
                    would be willing to try to find an assignment for the candidate, if that was
                    what the White House wished. Then the Under Secretary for Management, who was
                    responsible for appointments, would be asked to look at individual bureaus to
                    see when there might be a suitable opening. There was always a concern for
                    quality and experience and qualifications.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the operational style and
                        effectiveness of Henry Kissinger?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: We discussed that question in part during my description of the US two
                    track policy toward China. We mentioned the problem of the Foreign Service's
                    credibility in this kind of a situation. There was an attitude in the Department
                    of some caution and concern about Henry Kissinger. There was also at the time a
                    great deal of resentment at the way Henry Kissinger was running US foreign
                    policy at the White House through the NSC. Most people found Secretary Rogers to
                    be a pretty weak sister compared to Henry Kissinger. When Bill Rogers resigned
                    and Kissinger became Secretary of State, there was a great deal of enthusiasm
                    among career Foreign Service officers, thinking that at least then the action
                    would have moved over to State. The Department then would be close to the
                    beating heart of American foreign policy and much more involved. To some extent,
                    that did come true. Certainly, the beating heart had moved to the Department.
                    The extent to which Foreign Service officers were or were not drawn more into
                    the picture would be hard to assess. I think the answer is that they were
                    probably drawn more. As for Kissinger himself, he is a brilliant man, he has an
                    extraordinary ability to think conceptually and globally, to formulate and
                    enunciate policy. He was enormously active and able and successful in projecting
                    the “mystique” of Henry Kissinger. When one considers the major players and
                    personalities in American politics, particularly foreign policy, there are very
                    few names that come to mind as people who dominated the stage as Henry Kissinger
                    did. Or John Foster Dulles in his time. Everyone was somewhat in awe of Henry
                    Kissinger and as far as I could determine, Henry went to great pains to make
                    sure that everyone stayed in awe of Henry Kissinger. I saw relatively little of
                    him. Bob Ingersoll saw more of him because Bob would attend his staff meetings.
                    Bob had tremendous respect for Henry and the way Bob played his job, was to do
                    whatever Henry wanted him to do. He felt that he was Henry's deputy in the full
                    sense of the word and that meant that whatever Henry wanted to “deputize” him to
                    do, he would do. Bob did take a great deal of interest in the internal workings
                    of the Department and the Foreign Service, which Henry Kissinger could care less
                    about. Henry was interested in the assignments of top personnel, but he wasn't
                    really interested in the workings of the Service as a Service or the health of
                    the Service as Service or the internal workings of the State Department. But Bob
                    Ingersoll was and was therefore perhaps the perfect complement to Kissinger.
                    Ingersoll brought a sense of management, stemming from his very successful
                    corporate executive experience—he had been the CEO at Borg-Warner. He knew the
                    American business community. Henry Kissinger leaned very heavily on Ingersoll
                    for his knowledge of the American business community because Henry was very
                    anxious that American business would support Henry and his policies. He saw Bob
                    Ingersoll as a very effective spokesman to the top levels of American business
                    because Bob belonged to those circles. Bob was happy to perform that function
                    and did it very well. Ingersoll was quite interested in the financial aspects of
                    the Department and how it managed its budget. He was appalled to find out that
                    we didn't have certain kinds of documents to keep track of things in certain
                    ways. He made some major changes in the internal fiscal administration of the
                    Department of State. For one thing, he tried very hard to get an Office of the
                    Comptroller established, in which he didn't quite succeed because Eagleburger,
                    who after being Henry's assistant, became Under Secretary for Management and
                    opposed the idea. He saw it somehow impinging upon his area of responsibility.
                    It would have been under his control in any case, but he didn't like the idea.
                    Shortly thereafter, however, the Office was created and remains an important
                    office to this day. There is even today a monthly report which is called the
                    “Ingersoll” report which has something to do with how much money we have left in
                    the till. So Bob instituted some major improvements in the management of the
                    Department. He was also the first Deputy Secretary of the Department virtually
                    in memory who took an interest in the Inspection Corps and in its reports. He
                    used to read those inspection reports and would talk to the Inspector General
                    and the Director General about some of the problems of the Service. He took an
                    interest in a lot of things that Kissinger did not. My sense of Kissinger was
                    for the areas that he singled out to be of primary importance and to which he
                    devoted himself, he handled with considerable skill and panache. Few ever liked
                    Henry, but that may be besides the point. The question might be whether his
                    style offended people and therefore compromised policy objectives. I doubt that
                    it did that in any significant way. Henry was able to maneuver and manipulate
                    successfully. When Henry wanted to turn on the charm, Henry could turn it on. He
                    was a very skillful practitioner.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you arrived in Canada in 1976, what were the major
                        problems facing the Embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: When I went there, Tom Enders expected me to perform the classic
                    functions of a Deputy—I would run the inside of the Embassy and Consulate
                    General structure. I was essentially the quality control officer and when Tom
                    had any reservations, questions or complaints about the performance on any of
                    the Embassy sections, he would come to me to express his concerns. I therefore
                    devoted a lot of time to being the principal quality control officer and that
                    needed a lot of attention. We had a weak Political Section and I spent a
                    considerable time working with them trying to help it, training and organizing.
                    I was also the principal over-seer of the six Consulate Generals that we had. I
                    visited them and wrote the efficiency ratings of the Principal Officers. I had a
                    big management job. In addition to that, I was drawn into a number of
                    substantive issues such as fishing on the high seas—specifically in the George's
                    Bank in the East and two places in Alaska in the West. These problems had to do
                    with fishing boundaries for salmon and cod, etc. Another major issue related to
                    energy and revolved around whether Canada would permit the export to the United
                    States of its natural gas and petroleum in sizeable quantities. One of the key
                    questions was on the need for a pipeline and while I was there, Tom and others
                    negotiated the agreement for construction of a pipeline from Alaska through
                    Canada into the US We had another low-key but tricky key issue. It was referred
                    to in Canada as the “Orlikow” affair. It had to do with a very unpleasant
                    situation which started in the early ''60s when a brilliant psychiatrist—Dr.
                    Cameron—working in Montreal on problems of mental illness became a pioneer in
                    “psychic driving” which involved medicating ill people in order to condition
                    their thinking. The CIA was very interested in this experiment. Through one of
                    its assets, it funneled some research funds to Cameron. Several years later,
                    Cameron, was killed while mountain climbing. Subsequently, some of his patients,
                    who were being subjected to radical treatments, became dissatisfied with that
                    experience and decided that they had been abused. In the late '60s, during the
                    great fuss about the CIA putting secret funds into different research
                    operations, it was discovered that CIA had been funding Doctor Cameron's
                    research. In fact, it only funded something like 3 percent of it. There was a
                    huge political out-cry in Canada. “The long arm of the CIA was destroying
                    Canadian citizens for its own pernicious research interests”. This became a hot
                    issue and the husband of one of Doctor Cameron's patients, who was a member of
                    Parliament, would raise the issue during the “Question Period” in Parliament.
                    Then the Foreign Office—External Relations—had to come up with an answer for the
                    Minister. That meant that they had to get in touch with the Embassy. I became
                    the principal conduit for the dialogue between the two Governments on how to
                    handle this whole situation. The CIA felt that they were getting a bum rap
                    because Dr. Cameron had started his experiments long before CIA funding came
                    into play. Secondly, CIA put a very small amount into it and therefore they felt
                    that if there was to be any litigation, it should first involve Dr. Cameron's
                    clinic in Montreal and then the hospital of which the clinic was part. The CIA
                    felt that if there were to be any criticism it should be directed to the clinic
                    and the hospital and not to the CIA. This was essentially a political football.
                    The M.P.—Orlikow—was a left-winger and some believed it was all an attempt to
                    embarrass the Government of Canada and the US government and the CIA. These
                    kinds of issues can take an enormous amount of time to sort through. Then there
                    were some trade issues, having to do with the auto pact and
                    transportation—trucking—into the United States. There were also some low key
                    defense issues, but they were not contentious because Canada remains one of our
                    very closest allies in the defense sector. We do a lot of things together and
                    there is an exchange of officers serving in the other country's military. I was
                    partly involved in these issues, monitoring them, visiting defense
                    establishments in Canada and the US Basically speaking, our relationship with
                    Canada is a very stable one and while I was in Ottawa, we did not have anything
                    as politically sensitive as the “Free Trade Agreement” that has just been
                    concluded and which has dominated Canadian politics for the last two years. But
                    we did have a political issue when I was there which was an internal Canadian
                    issue. I refer to Quebec separatism. That came to a head while I was there. Rene
                    Levesque won a provincial vote and formed the Government of Quebec Province. His
                    party was committed to seceding, thus creating a good deal of domestic political
                    turbulence, which was something that we had to follow very carefully because
                    Washington was very interested in the outcome. Essentially, US policy was
                    “hands-off”. We were not going to become involved; it was an internal matter for
                    the Canadians, but when pressed we did say that we thought that anything which
                    in any way diminished Canadian geographic integrity as a nation, was not in our
                    interests. There were other perceptions on this issue. I was interviewed very
                    extensively recently by a French-Canadian journalist who is writing a book about
                    this period. He was probing me very carefully on the subject of whether the
                    United States had not seen that if Quebec had split off from Canada and had
                    become independent, that the United States could have dealt much more easily
                    with two weaker powers than with united Canada, which would have been a stronger
                    power and could have more easily resisted US policies. I told him that this
                    issue had arisen during policy discussions, but was quickly dismissed as having
                    far more negatives than positives. He found that very hard to believe. He
                    obviously belongs to a school of politics which prefers to believe in
                    conspiratorial theses.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, our objective was much more practical and
                        stressed the desire to have a strong central government.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: That is self-evident to us, but obviously if you are a Quebec
                    nationalist, you would prefer to think that the US would support you because the
                    situation could be seen in other terms.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A number of people have thought that the US doesn't pay
                        enough attention to Canada. Did the Canadians really want the US to pay
                        attention?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: That is a question that arises all the time. When you first arrive in
                    Canada, you are greeted by this point. Canadians will immediately tell you that
                    the US doesn't pay enough attention to them. In a certain sense, that is true.
                    We don't pay enough attention to them for a variety of reasons. In the first
                    place, we have much graver problems in other parts of the world. Secondly, we
                    are very happy with the existing relationships with Canada. We admire the
                    Canadians, we think they are doing a fine job running their own country and we
                    don't see why we should have to devote a lot of time to worrying about that.
                    Thirdly, there is a real question whether the Canadians would want us to pay a
                    lot of attention because with that comes a lot of running around in Canada
                    taking a deep interest in some matters which may be the last thing that they
                    really want. That is usually a good riposte to anyone who complains about not
                    giving Canada enough attention. On the other hand, it is true and probably
                    immutable, we as a country exert such a powerful cultural image that the rest of
                    the world has to come to grips with us. In the case of Canada, it is
                    particularly compelling since we are right on their door step with 90% of their
                    population living within 100 miles of the border. Most Canadians have relatives
                    in the United States, visit frequently, those who can afford it spend the
                    winters in Florida. There are large Canadian enclaves in Florida and Maine. They
                    feel a little overwhelmed by the image we project and they feel compromised.
                    That's why they complain and that is also why they have taken steps to protect
                    their cultural and social identity. Some of the stickiest issues in US-Canadian
                    relations have to do with film distribution, television broadcasting—where
                    signals emanate from, what kind of advertising, who advertises because what they
                    hate, for example, is the fact that people on the Canadian side from Buffalo
                    love watching the Buffalo TV station inducing the smart Canadian advertiser to
                    place his advertisements on the Buffalo TV waves. The Canadians finally passed a
                    law making it very expensive for a Canadian entrepreneur to advertise on the
                    Buffalo TV station. Needless to say, we got into an argument about that because
                    we considered their action as a restraint of trade. On the general question
                    whether we pay enough attention to the Canadians, we will never pay as much as
                    they would like. On the other hand, happily, we will never pay so much attention
                    that they wouldn't like it. When I was faced with these questions, I would
                    usually treat them with good humor and I would try to offer a semi-humorous
                    response and try to change their frame of mind.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your next assignment, after the friendly Canadian
                        experience, was of a different caliber. You were assigned to the Sinai which
                        was territory between the Israeli and the Egyptians.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: That is right. After four years as DCM in Ottawa, I rather belatedly
                    went to the Senior Seminar which was a terrific experience that I enjoyed
                    greatly. The year I graduated was a bad time in the Department's history as far
                    as its personnel situation was concerned. Not a single one of my State
                    Department colleagues in the Senior Seminar—not one—had an onward assignment
                    when we graduated from the Seminar. We were told that we were on our own and
                    that we could roam the corridors to see whether we could find a job. It was an
                    appalling situation. I went looking around and happened upon the fact that there
                    was a new organization being started called the “Multinational Force and
                    Observers”. It was the successor organization to the observer teams we had in
                    the Sinai earlier. But this new organization had to be created to implement the
                    Camp David Accords. There had to be a combination of civilian and military
                    observer force. The State Department took the responsibility for getting in
                    touch with other governments to see whether they would participate in this
                    endeavor. Initially we had hoped for a UN peace-keeping force, but the Russians
                    were going to veto that in the Security Council. So the US had to sponsor the
                    effort. This was the first and perhaps the only multinational force organized
                    outside of UN auspices, except Vietnam. The Department went around and signed up
                    about eleven different countries, who agreed in principle. Then the US as the
                    lead country had to design this force—there was not really any prototype for it.
                    It was decided that what was needed were somewhere between 4,000 and 6,000
                    troops which included a helicopter component. Under the Camp David accords, the
                    Sinai was divided into three zones. The Israeli were going to withdraw and the
                    Egyptians would move in behind them incrementally, eventually taking over the
                    entire Sinai, which is the situation at the present. There were various levels
                    of armaments permitted and other agreements that required daily verification by
                    both military and civilians to maintain the integrity of the Camp David accords.
                    We had to set up this observer force. The commitments were made by about eleven
                    countries; then we had to go to these countries and fill in the blanks on the
                    table of organization. At the time, the countries had only committed in
                    principle, not to any specific mode or type of contribution. When I joined this
                    organization, it was still in the process of trying to design itself. It was
                    deciding what the table of organization would be, what units would be involved,
                    the nature and size of these units, and what the civilian role would be. The US
                    was going to provide all the civilians and a full battalion of troops and a lot
                    of logistic support, but we were looking to the other participants for two more
                    battalions, trucks and drivers and mechanics to support the transportation
                    fleet, helicopters and pilots and mechanics, a headquarters company, a signal
                    company, etc. There had been no agreements that anybody would do anything
                    specific. I was assigned to this organization to be a negotiator to go to
                    governments as we determined which we thought could fill the various
                    responsibilities. I would go as part of a team to persuade governments to give
                    us what we needed as opposed to what they might have in surplus and would be
                    willing to give us. In that capacity, I worked initially with Frank Maestrone
                    and a couple of others, but eventually I ended up leading the teams myself. In
                    addition, even if a country had agreed to give us what we needed, we had then to
                    negotiate the terms and conditions and the remuneration, the timing, the
                    logistics, etc. I worked with the Colombians in Bogota to work out their
                    commitments for a battalion of troops. I visited Montevideo to work out the
                    terms and conditions of the trucking unit from the Uruguayans. I visited London
                    and The Hague to discuss with the Dutch the assignment of a signals company and
                    with the British, the headquarters company. That was tricky, because we
                    initially had intended that the signals company be British because that is a
                    hard requirement to fill. This company needed highly skilled radio technicians,
                    who are in short supply in any country's military forces. You need radio
                    technicians who are communicators trained to the NATO standards, using English
                    and the NATO signal-books. That narrows the field. The British refused to
                    provide such a company because they didn't have the man-power. The only country
                    left was Holland. I was despatched as a “one man Mission Impossible” to go to
                    The Hague to try to persuade the Dutch military that they should provide this
                    company. I met with the commanding general of the Dutch army, who was very nice,
                    very polite. I laid out our problem and the reasons for having the Dutch—namely,
                    that they were virtually the only force that could do it. He listened to me and
                    then said that I was asking for the impossible. He said that the Dutch had
                    barely enough of those skills in their own army as it was. He pointed out that
                    the Dutch had a draft Army, which had very short periods of service—only six
                    months. Communicators had to spend another six months or more. By the time the
                    Dutch finished the training, they only had three months left in their service.
                    He pointed out that I had asked for six months assignments. He concluded that
                    the request was just impossible because the soldiers would have to re-enlist for
                    another three months to fulfill my request. He thought that was hopeless and no
                    one would do that. I asked him to do me a favor and to publicize the opportunity
                    to serve in the Sinai. If anybody wanted to volunteer, they would have to
                    re-enlist for another three months to complete a six months' tour in the Sinai.
                    He agreed to that for us, but didn't give it much of a chance. When he did
                    announce the program, there were 1,000 volunteers. These young people wanted a
                    little adventure. All we needed was sixty, so the Dutch were able to fill our
                    request. I take my hat off to the negotiators of the Camp David accords. They
                    made that whole thing work. You never hear about peace-keeping problems in the
                    Sinai because that whole operation is in place, very effectively administered
                    and we never had any problems with it. It continues to this day and you never
                    read about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your next assignment was as Ambassador to Suriname from
                        1982 to 1984. How did that come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: By this time, my old friend and colleague from Ottawa, Tom Enders, had
                    become Assistant Secretary for Latin America. As my time for re-assignment came
                    up—the Multi-national Force assignment was just a short-term one for 8-9 months—
                    Tom decided that I would be a very good person to put into this rather peculiar
                    job in Suriname. I say “peculiar” because this country is under the Latin
                    American Bureau, is in South America, but is Dutch speaking. It is therefore not
                    part and parcel of the Latin American package. It is sui generis. He asked me if
                    I would go and I agreed. It gave me an opportunity to have an Embassy of my own.
                    While the appointment procedure was in progress, I took intensive Dutch because
                    I didn't know any. I learned enough Dutch and I continued to study the language
                    with a tutor during my assignment. I got to the stage where I had passable
                    conversation skills and I could read documents. All of the local newspapers are
                    in Dutch, government documents are in Dutch and the television and radio are in
                    Dutch. So it was important that one should speak the language. There is bit of
                    irony in this because by derivation, I am half Dutch. My mother's family were
                    pure Dutch although they had been in the US for over 100 years in Grand Rapids,
                    Michigan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Holland, Michigan, is very close by. What was the
                        situation in Suriname when you got there in 1982?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: It was a very tense situation because there had been a peculiar
                    military coup that had taken place in 1980. The Dutch gave Suriname its
                    independence in 1975. The Dutch left it in perfect shape. It had everything
                    going for it. For a small Third World country it had paved roads, it had an
                    excellent and extensive electrical network which did not break down—no shortages
                    or outages—, it had a superb water and sewer system—better water than in
                    Washington, DC—, they had a trained labor force, an excellent school system, no
                    endemic diseases. The country had everything going for it. There was some
                    dissatisfaction among the military and the enlisted men decided they wanted a
                    trade union. That may sound funny to us, but the Dutch army has a trade union.
                    So the Surinamese army decided it had to have one. They petitioned for one and
                    the government turned them down. Then about thirteen sergeants decided to go on
                    a sit down strike. These sergeants sat down in front of the President's Palace.
                    At a certain moment, they were invited in to talk to the President who told them
                    that if they thought they could a better job, they were welcome to it and he
                    walked out, leaving them in charge of the country. There were a few shots
                    fired—very few. The government tried to use the police to get the sergeants back
                    to the barracks, but they refused. There were two people killed. It finally
                    turned out into a military coup. The sergeants were self-proclaimed Marxists of
                    a sort—of the kind that is very vague about Marxism, certainly not intellectual
                    Marxism. It was mostly dissatisfaction with the general situation. So the
                    military took over the government. Initially, it was a friendly operation. There
                    were a lot of people in the traditional establishment who were trying to be more
                    or less supportive of the new government. But things deteriorated rather quickly
                    because the military, in trying to run the government, didn't have the skills or
                    the education to do it. Government services began to fall apart and the economy
                    began to fall apart. People began to mumble about having lived in a democracy
                    with a Parliament and began to demand the return of democracy and representative
                    government. There was increasing agitation on the part of the civilian
                    population, including demonstrations, demanding the resignation of the military
                    government and the return of a democratic form of government. It became clear
                    that the military was in increasing danger of losing control of the country.
                    About this time, the dictator by the name of Bouterse—the lead sergeant, now
                    Lieutenant Colonel—invited Maurice Bishop, the head of the government of
                    Grenada, whom he considered to be his mentor and model, to come for a State
                    visit. Bishop came even though the visit was very unpopular because most
                    Surinamers didn't like Bishop and didn't like what he was doing in Grenada. He
                    was not given a warm welcome by the people; on the contrary, on the last day of
                    the visit, the government tried unwisely to organize a public meeting, which was
                    met by a demonstration which out-drew the government's meeting by about ten to
                    one. Among the people who was deeply involved in the demonstration was the
                    leader of the Trade Unions as well as others. We subsequently learned through
                    documents that Maurice Bishop had a long conversation with Bouterse and told him
                    that if he didn't get tough with the opposition, he would lose control of the
                    situation. He had to smash the opposition. Bouterse thought about that for about
                    one month and then in early December 1982 took his palace guard out in an
                    evening and picked up about 18 people, some of whom had been the ring-leaders of
                    the opposition. Fifteen people were tortured and then murdered. These included
                    some of the most prominent citizens of Suriname. That occurred about four months
                    after my arrival. That put a wholly different complexion on what was going on in
                    Suriname. It absolutely chilled the population. Initially there was a
                    twenty-four hour curfew. That was eased finally to a twelve hour curfew which
                    continued for about six months. Needless to say, the US reaction was extremely
                    negative. I was sent in to tell the Prime Minister, who was a figure head, and
                    occasionally the dictator, our views. Part of the problem was that we had had a
                    modest assistance program—the Dutch had a very large one—and when the Dutch
                    suspended theirs, we did the same. That put the country in a very serious bind.
                    The Surinamese always wanted to talk to me about the possibility of resuming the
                    program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Under the circumstances, why did the US appoint an
                        Ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: I was appointed before the slaughter. I went out at a time when our
                    relationship with Suriname was low-key, not terribly friendly because we could
                    not be supportive of a military government, particularly a left-wing one. We
                    wanted to continue the relationship because we were concerned about the
                    strategic location of Suriname. If it had a hostile government, it could
                    interdict the supply routes to and from the Panama Canal. Any traffic heading
                    for the Canal from the South Atlantic goes right past Suriname. The problem of a
                    hostile government became even more difficult after the slaughter because the
                    government then moved radically to the left. A new Cuban Ambassador arrived and
                    the government took on a very Cuban tinge. The Cubans were essentially calling
                    the shots.I had been assigned before this had happened to this degree. Then the
                    question was whether I should stay.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What policy were you recommending?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: In the first place, I reported in as much detail as I could what had
                    happened. It was extremely difficult to get any information concerning what
                    precisely was going on. I had a CIA office there and we just contacted those we
                    knew somewhat surreptitiously because of the curfew. We were doing the best we
                    could just to tell Washington what had occurred which was not immediately
                    apparent. It took a better part of a week to figure out really what had gone on.
                    The reaction from Washington was that I should remain. They wanted to have
                    someone in place to report on events. They thought it would be better to have
                    someone do that than to close the mission. This was a small Embassy and if the
                    Ambassador were pulled, it would not have worked very well. We had a DCM who had
                    been charge' for a long time before I arrived. He knew the country very well—in
                    some ways, too well. In this turbulent period that followed the December
                    massacre, the dictator called me in during January to declare the DCM and the
                    head of USIS personae-non-grata. They accused both of them of meddling in
                    internal politics. I denied it of course because from an objective point of
                    view, neither officer had been “meddling”. They had certainly been hustling
                    around asking people what was going on trying to keep track of events.
                    Unfortunately, both had done a couple of silly things that I did not know about
                    until somewhat later. One thing for example that the dictator told me was that
                    the government had tapped telephones and had recorded efforts by the DCM to
                    call, before the slaughter, the labor leader I mentioned earlier to ask him what
                    he intended to do about supporting the demonstrations. The government had all of
                    that on tape and they decided that this was provocation on our part. They
                    declared these two officers, who knew a good deal of what was going on,
                    personae-non-grata thereby reducing the staff considerably. Washington decided
                    that it made sense to keep me in Suriname, since these other senior officers
                    were no longer available as fall back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you agree with that assessment?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: I saw no reason for me to return because in the first place my
                    assessment was that the local actions were not directed against us, but rather
                    were an internal situation. We might have had a reaction, but it was not
                    directed against us. In the second place, I didn't feel in any great personal
                    danger nor did I think my staff was. I didn't have a Marine contingent to guard
                    the Embassy. Before I went to Suriname, I was asked by Enders whether I wanted a
                    detachment. I said “No, it is a small post and I don't see a need for them.”
                    Often in a setting like that, the Marines can often be more trouble than they
                    are worth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is often true. Young men who get drunk, chase the
                        local girls and in time of trouble, can't really shoot. They really don't
                        help that much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: I didn't see it as a necessity. Once we got through the slaughter and
                    the problems, it would have been difficult to get the Marines in because at that
                    point the government also was watching us very carefully. I thought that the
                    answer to the situation was to sit tight and continue a dialogue with the
                    government. We had a quiet dialogue and tried to find ways to establish some
                    rapport with the government to find out what they were doing. We did make some
                    small gestures, very small—I got CINCSOUTH and the CIA to come up with some
                    money to buy a couple of electronic score boards to install in a big gymnasium
                    that they had. The Surinamers were going to host an international basketball
                    tournament and needed the boards. There is an international association of
                    military sports. Our military forces belong to it as well as twenty other
                    countries. This association gets together and has a basketball tournament. For
                    some reason, Suriname was hosting and the US military were coming to play in
                    that tournament. I supported that effort as being fairly innocuous. We wanted to
                    maintain friendly relations with the people of Suriname who were very
                    pro-American. We didn't want to desert them. We were working towards an
                    evolution which would result in the return of a democratic government, which is
                    what is happening now—slowly. The point was not to “lose our cool” but to hang,
                    in taking some modest steps, but always telling them that they would not receive
                    any further assistance until they had cleaned up their act and returned to some
                    form of democratic government. As a policy matter, I didn't think therefore that
                    any purpose would be served by pulling up stakes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any opposition to this policy in
                        Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: Quite the opposite. The opposition to the policy, of which I learned
                    shortly thereafter, came from those who were considering the invasion of
                    Suriname. The Grenada invasion was on October 25, 1983. Earlier, in late
                    January, 1983 - only six weeks after the slaughter - my wife had traveled back
                    to the U.S. - she did that about one week per month because she is a very busy
                    person with lots of commitments - and had to be hospitalized for an emergency
                    operation. She was in the hospital for a week. I called Enders to tell him that
                    I had to come to Washington to be with my wife to help her through her
                    convalescence period for at least a week. He told me that he thought he could
                    not get permission for me to leave Suriname at that point in time. I told him
                    that it was critical and had to be done. He said he would check and see what he
                    could do. He called twenty-four hours later and said that although it had been
                    very sticky, he had gotten the Secretary's approval for a week's return to
                    Washington. It was not until I returned that I realized what was going on. At
                    the highest level of the U.S. government people were talking about invading
                    Suriname. This was about eight months before we actually invaded Grenada.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You might say that the gun was loaded and ready to be
                        fired.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: That's right. It was part of “Let's roll back Communism or let's not
                    allow further inroads” By this time, after the slaughter, with Bishop riding
                    high in Grenada and the Cubans increasing their influence in Suriname, the
                    situation in that part of the world was looking very unpleasant to the Reagan
                    administration. That is why there was a good deal of thought being given to
                    moving in and turning it around. But nothing much happened. I used to come to
                    Washington about once every three months and I would call on Judge Clark, who
                    was then the National Security Advisor, to tell him how things were going in
                    Suriname. This was very unusual that an Ambassador from a tiny country like that
                    would see the NSC advisor. He wanted to see me and every three months I would
                    report to him. He would push across the desk copies of telegrams and messages
                    that had R.R. written in the upper corner. Ronald Reagan was following on a
                    daily basis what was happening in Suriname.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you and the CIA reporting on the situation? What
                        was your level of concern?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: We were telling it exactly the way it was - that is to say, reporting
                    exactly what these people were doing, the clear left-ward drift of the
                    government, the increasing Cuban influence on the government. There were certain
                    contingency plans were being made. Washington was wondering whether it would be
                    necessary to evacuate the Embassy. We were developing evacuation plans. I think
                    in the Summer of 1983, during one of my visits to Washington, I was told in
                    advance that the Joint Chiefs wanted to talk to me. I was invited to address the
                    Joint Chiefs and went to their secure area in the Pentagon. Every member of the
                    joint Chiefs, with the exception of one who was represented by his Deputy, sat
                    around the big open square table with a number of subordinates around the wall -
                    there were sixty people in the room. I was in the middle of one side of the
                    table. The Joint Chiefs sat opposite me across the open hollow square. The
                    Chairman thanked me for coming and asked me to open the discussion on whether
                    the U.S. should invade Suriname. We discussed that for an hour and fifteen
                    minutes. They asked me to describe the situation. I sketched for them my
                    understanding and assessment of what was happening, what the country was all
                    about, what its relative importance in the scheme of things was, what degree of
                    threat it posed for a wide variety of American interests. I concluded by saying
                    that the defenses of the country were extremely modest, that although not a
                    military man, my own assessment was that a strike force of approximately 200
                    paratroopers should be sufficient to take complete control of the capital city
                    and the two military compounds. I did not see it as a major military problem to
                    take over the country if that were the decision. However, I added, that I
                    thought it would be very misguided to take over the country, easy and tempting
                    as that might be. In large part, I did not feel the threat was sufficient to
                    justify the expenditures, the military risks, to say nothing of the down-side
                    political situation in terms of the OAS and our image elsewhere in Central and
                    South America. Those were judgments to be made in Washington on an inter-agency
                    basis. It was not a judgment for the U.S. Ambassador in Suriname. The final and
                    probably most telling point I made was that I had been aware of the contingency
                    plans for sometime - we had had Delta Teams (the special high grade strike
                    forces of the U.S. military that comprise surface, air and water components)
                    surreptitiously introduced into the country to make assessments and take
                    pictures and gather intelligence. I knew about this because I had them in the
                    Embassy, ostensibly to assist us with some contingency plans. I therefore was
                    aware of all the military contingency plans that had been made, but I noted that
                    no discussion had taken place about what would be done after the country had
                    been occupied. On the assumption that on D-Day plus three, we had fully occupied
                    Suriname. The population would be 85-90% entirely friendly and all opposition
                    would be supine at that stage. But who will run the country? They have not been
                    able to run it for themselves for some time. My assessment was that it would
                    have been a very difficult task to run the country. It was very fractured
                    culturally, ethnically and economically. It was a nightmare of a little country
                    from the government's point of view as its recent political history
                    demonstrated. All that would happen would be that Uncle Sam would pick up the
                    can of worms. I didn't think we wanted to pick up that can. They listened to
                    that very attentively and thanked me for confirming certain judgments that they
                    had already made. That was the last that was ever heard of invading
                    Suriname.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>Having excluded invasions, there were still theoretically ways by which we could
                    work internally against what was taking place. For example, Bouterse had decided
                    that he wanted to come to the U.S. to attend and address the General Assembly.
                    He would have done that in October of 1983. As a routine matter, the Surinamese
                    Ministry of Foreign Affairs got in touch with the Embassy requesting visas for
                    the dictator and his entourage. They sent the passports under cover of a
                    diplomatic note. We made checks on all of these applicants - some we knew,
                    others we had just heard of. We found that among the principal bodyguards,
                    according to the CIA files, was a Cuban with military and security training who
                    had been detailed by the Cuban government to run the personal security detail of
                    the dictator. He was posing as a Surinamer, which is not hard to do because
                    Suriname is an ethnic mixture. There are a number of Hispanics. The bodyguard
                    had a fictitious passport. The photograph was of the right guy, but the name,
                    birth date and place of birth were fictitious. We were able to zero in on this
                    fraud and to identify who he was. We dutifully visaed the passports and I signed
                    off on the returning diplomatic note. I hand carried the package to the Foreign
                    Minister with whom I had established a good personal relationship. I had always
                    made an effort to maintain correct and in some cases, cordial, relations with
                    the members of the government on a personal basis. I did that even with the
                    dictator because I used to meet with him periodically usually at my request. We
                    always treated each other with great courtesy and politeness. That worked out
                    very well. I think it is the right way to do these kinds of things.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>So I had a very good personal relationship with the Foreign Minister. When I
                    called on him, we chatted I and handed over the passports. I asked him how much
                    he knew about the chief bodyguard. I noted that this particular gentleman was
                    operating under a false identification; we knew it was false and we knew who he
                    really was. I told him that normally we would not have put a visa on a
                    fraudulent document, but as a courtesy to the dictator, I was taking personal
                    responsibility for doing so. The Foreign Minister was much taken aback and
                    thanked me. I told him that this episode had me wondering a little bit about how
                    delicate the situation was getting with all this Cuban influence. There was some
                    question in my mind on who the Cubans were supporting - there were already some
                    divisions taking place among the military dictatorship. There were certain
                    people that the Cubans favored and there were lots of rumors to the effect that
                    the Cubans would have liked to push out Bouterse and replace him with someone
                    more congenial to the Cuban point of view. I told the Foreign Minister that I
                    sensed certain problems within the government on the subject of Cuban influence
                    and support. I was little puzzled why the dictator wanted to have a Cuban in
                    charge of his security in light of these rumors. The Foreign Minister looked at
                    me wide-eyed - these are fairly naive people - and said that this was an
                    interesting thought that he had not considered. That conversation proved
                    ultimately - we found that out through intelligence sources later - to have been
                    a very important seed to plant. The conversation was duly reported to the
                    dictator, who was paranoid in any case, and he began to worry. He did not take
                    the Cuban to New York and may in fact not have gone himself, I don't remember.
                    As October wore on, the problem of Cuban influence became increasingly difficult
                    and I was constantly playing on this with anybody I could get to. It was clear
                    that the Cuban Ambassador was overplaying his hand. The dictator was getting
                    more and more nervous. He was losing control to the Cuban Ambassador and those
                    supported by the Cubans.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>In an extraordinary confluence of events, on a Friday in late October we got wind
                    of the fact that Bouterse was going to throw out the Cuban Ambassador and those
                    who had come with him. He was going to close the Cuban Embassy for meddling in
                    internal affairs. He was supposed to make this speech on Saturday night, but he
                    was still working out some problems in the speech. We didn't know what they
                    were, but he didn't make the speech or the announcement until Tuesday morning.
                    It just happened that on the previous day, the U.S. had invaded Grenada. The
                    dictator nevertheless went ahead with his speech. Of course, everyone in
                    Suriname thought that the two events were related. Bouterse, not surprisingly,
                    was mad as hell because he had no inkling of the U.S. action in Grenada and
                    neither did I. We totally took the play away from him by sheer coincidence. A
                    lot of people thought that it had been a quid-pro-quo with one of the spin-offs
                    of our invasion of Grenada being the expulsion of the Cubans from Suriname. That
                    was not of course the case since Bouterse had already made the decision before
                    the invasion. He of course might have been prompted to do so if he had not
                    already made the decision, but the sequence of events clearly indicates that his
                    decision preceded the invasion of Grenada. The sequence of events made him look
                    like he had cut and run which made him very mad, but in any case, he went
                    through with it, he did toss out the Cubans and thereafter he decided that the
                    country had to be returned to some degree of democratic government. From that
                    point on, the Cuban influence was eliminated and he began talking again with
                    various elements in the Suriname body politic about ways of creating an advisory
                    council initially, and ultimately an assembly. That's the path they have
                    followed and today there is more popular influence - not yet democratic, but
                    they have had elections, and have a consultative assembly with some powers. It
                    is a more democratic state than before. It is moving in the right direction, but
                    too slowly. The Dutch have resumed their assistance. I left Suriname in about
                    August, 1984 and by that time, the situation had stabilized.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>I invited Bouterse to come to our July 4 celebration which in Suriname is very
                    small - the diplomatic corps and members of the government. The American
                    community has its separate party. He came and brought his senior military and
                    government people. People were quite surprised because he never represented the
                    government at national day receptions. Our reception was held at mid-day. People
                    would have the usual toast to the government and the two national anthems - your
                    own and the Suriname ones, usually by recorded music I got two girls, an
                    American and a Canadian, who had beautiful voices, who sang both national
                    anthems - ours and the Surinamese sung in Sranan which is the lesser official
                    language. This reduced Bouterse to tears. He was very impressed that anyone
                    would have taken the trouble to do this and particularly that it was sung in
                    Sranan. He was a very strong nationalist and the very fact that we did it in
                    Sranan live, doubly impressed him. He shook my hand very warmly. It was this
                    kind of thing that I tried to do to maintain a relationship even when our policy
                    differences were very clear and when we discussed them openly. That does not
                    preclude some human touches to try to keep a relationship going somehow. I think
                    it is important particularly when the great majority of Surinamese are very
                    friendly to us and we want to keep it that way. We don't want to alienate the
                    people of Suriname; we don't want them to think that we don't care about them
                    because we do. When I left the country a month later, to my astonishment, at a
                    little formal reception and dinner that was given to me by the President, he
                    proceeded to give me the highest decoration the government of Suriname can give
                    to a foreigner. This medal was of a grade never before given to a diplomat. The
                    President explained to me privately that he and his government well understood
                    that the relationship between the countries had had very tense moments in the
                    last few years and there had been some difficult problems. But he felt that I,
                    as an Ambassador, had managed those problems as well as anyone could have and
                    that therefore the government wanted to acknowledge that fact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned earlier the “strategic importance of
                        Suriname.” In looking back over your career, was Suriname really of such
                        strategic importance? Had not the importance of its geographic location been
                        overtaken by modern technologies?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: The fact of the matter is that the Pentagon, in my view, is always
                    excessively concerned by the security dimension of real estate. That is a
                    primary concern for them and I don't fault them for that. The question is one of
                    degree. If you choose a little country like Suriname on the North-east shoulder
                    of South America, you have to ask yourself the level of importance of such a
                    piece of real estate, even granting that there is some. It was of considerable
                    interest in World War II because the U.S. Army built a large airfield in
                    Suriname which is still there and functions as the international airport of
                    Paramaribo. During World War II, it was one of the stepping stones for the route
                    across the mid-Atlantic over to Dakar. It was of great importance then.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>Today, it is of much less importance. Given the range of aircraft and this being
                    the age of missiles, it does not have the same importance. It has some limited
                    interest with respect to the sea-lane approaches to the Panama Canal from the
                    South-east, but that is about it. I would conclude that it has no great
                    strategic importance today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With reference to the Suriname case specifically, would
                        you please discuss your relationship with the CIA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: During the course of my career in the State Department I always felt
                    that I had excellent relationships with my colleagues in the Central
                    Intelligence Agency. I found them for the most part highly knowledgeable
                    professionals, interesting and dependable. I always felt that as a Foreign
                    Service Officer, working for the entire U.S. government, it was imperative that
                    we work as closely with the Agency as we did with other Federal agencies.</p>
                <p>There was an interesting episode while I was the Ambassador to Suriname which had
                    to do with the attitude of my own station chief - the raking CIA officer on my
                    staff - in terms of his attitude towards the State Department. This episode
                    arose during a tense moment of internal Suriname politics. I mentioned earlier
                    that while I was in Suriname, the country was under the control of a military
                    dictator, Bouterse. He had been a sergeant and he together with other sergeants,
                    led a coup in 1980 and had taken over the country. Only two people were killed
                    in an episode that lasted about two or three days before they had secured power.
                    Not surprisingly there had been a certain amount of rivalry among the military
                    who were running the country. There was a certain amount of social and political
                    turbulence in the country generated by the fact that Suriname had been a
                    democracy and there were a number of people agitating for a return to that
                    state. It was a politically unstable situation.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>Bouterse had as a principal deputy a man by the name of Roy Horb. Horb became
                    increasingly disaffected from Bouterse and the strong arm tactics that he
                    employed, particularly when the dictator, under the influence of Bishop, the
                    head of Grenada, decided to arrest about sixteen of the most prominent citizens
                    of the country, who were his political opponents or agitators in support of
                    democracy. He had them arrested in the middle of the night of December 8, 1982.
                    He tortured them for twenty-four hours and killed them. That very brutal episode
                    apparently alienated Horb, who felt that this kind of violent suppression of
                    criticism of the government was uncalled for and was wrong. Within the ruling
                    military circle, Horb was arguing against such tactics and behavior and for
                    greater accommodation with the political opposition. Horb had been approached by
                    the CIA and much that we knew about the situation we knew from the CIA. He was a
                    contact, a resource, of the CIA - a rather valued one given the fact that he was
                    in the inner circles. In January, 1983 a letter was slipped through the
                    Embassy's mail slot one morning, addressed to me. It was brought to me about
                    9-9:30 in the morning. It purported to be from Horb who claimed that he was
                    being held prisoner against his will by Bouterse at a military base not too far
                    from Paramaribo. The letter made a great number of accusations against Bouterse
                    and said that Horb was entirely opposed to this. He opposed the Bouterse
                    dictatorship and feared for his own life - he did not think he would survive,
                    but he wanted it known that he was in opposition.I immediately summoned the
                    country team, including the station chief to discuss the letter. We spent an
                    hour and a half analyzing this letter. We came to the conclusion from other
                    evidence that we had that this letter was a provocation - that it was not a
                    legitimate document. For one thing, it was Xerox copy, pasted together with
                    Horb's name apparently forged unto the document. I prepared a very long analysis
                    of the document, based on the country team discussions. I was about to dispatch
                    this analysis with the text to Washington in about mid-afternoon when I got a
                    phone call from the Department, followed by a “Flash” telegram, asking me what
                    was going on with a document from Horb. Washington wanted to know what was going
                    on as soon as possible. I was surprised that Washington already knew, because I
                    thought it was understood within the country team that we were preparing a
                    collective analysis. What in fact had occurred was that the station chief
                    unbeknownst to me and unauthorized, had simply sent the text of the letter to
                    his own Agency through his communications channel without informing me. That
                    immediately aroused State and Defense Departments and the NSC. Everybody got
                    very excited and wondering what was happening. I thought that the station
                    chief's action was disloyal because we were trying to analyze the document and
                    put it into some perspective. I dispatched this long analysis which was the
                    proper way of handling this sort of event since there was no great urgency about
                    it. The point was to provide Washington with the text of the letter and some
                    points of reference for analytical purposes and a recommended course of action.
                    This should have been submitted as a package. You don't send the document and
                    say that the matter is under consideration and that analysis follows. Sending
                    the document alone only gets people excited unnecessarily. Washington was very
                    interested in our analysis and agreed with it and our recommendations - namely
                    that it was a provocation and that we would stay alert to see what would develop
                    next.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>Within a couple of days, I received a telephone call one morning about 9 o'clock
                    from the Foreign Ministry saying that Bouterse wanted to see me right away. I
                    was told that I would be received in the old office of the Prime Minister at
                    about 10 o'clock. I arrived promptly and was ushered into the old Cabinet room.
                    Waiting for me were three people: Bouterse, Horb and the Foreign Minister, a
                    strong leftist with ties to Cuba and no particular friend of the United States.
                    I was asked to sit down and if I wanted to have coffee. I accepted that.
                    Bouterse then took a document and reached across putting it in front of me,
                    asking me whether I had ever seen it before. It was a copy of the letter that
                    had come through the mail slot. I admitted that I had seen it before. Major Horb
                    was looking extremely agitated and very nervous. Bouterse and the Foreign
                    Minister appeared quite calm. The dictator then asked me what I thought about
                    it. I expressed my view that it was a forgery and a provocation and I gave them
                    some of the more obvious reasons for my conclusions - I did not give them all of
                    our rationale. Horb was vastly relieved and turned to Bouterse and told him that
                    he agreed that it was a forgery and that he had had nothing to do with it. I
                    told the dictator that I thought the letter was a clear provocation and I
                    assumed that it had been concocted by people who were against good relationships
                    between the U.S. and Suriname and were trying to upset that relationship. I told
                    Bouterse that I dismissed the whole incident. He thanked me and said that he
                    would like to call a meeting of the diplomatic corps, which he wanted me to
                    attend, for noon. By this time, it was 10:30 or 10:45 in the morning. I returned
                    immediately to the Embassy and went to the station chief's office. I told him
                    exactly what had happened and expressed my puzzlement by these events. I asked
                    him whether he had any idea how Bouterse had gotten a hold of the letter. He
                    said that he didn't have any idea. We speculated a little bit on how events may
                    have transpired and how the letter may have fallen into Bouterse's or Horb's
                    hands. The station chief expressed total ignorance and total bewilderment and
                    gave me no advice on the meeting of the diplomatic corps.</p>
                <p>At 12:00 o'clock, I returned for the meeting of the assembled diplomatic corps.
                    Bouterse, Horb and the Foreign Minister were all there. Bouterse proceeded to
                    hand out copies of the document to everyone present; then went on to say that he
                    had called the meeting because everyone knew that the political situation in the
                    country was very fragile and that there was a lot of rumor mongering and
                    provocations going on. He said he wanted to commend the Ambassador of the United
                    States, who had received such a provocation, for coming forward and giving this
                    letter to the government. He noted that had been precisely the right thing to do
                    and hoped than anyone else who might be given such a document would be equally
                    forthcoming. I said nothing. As the meeting ended and we were walking out, I
                    turned to my French colleague and told him confidentially that we had never
                    given the letter to the Suriname government. I added that I had no idea where
                    the document came from, but that I would not be surprised if it had originated
                    with the government.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>I went back to the Embassy and the station chief's office. I reported what had
                    occurred and I proceeded to send a telegram - a fuller one than the brief one I
                    sent after the morning meeting - to Washington. About 2:30 in the afternoon, the
                    station chief came in to see me and said that he had given that letter to Horb
                    days previously. That was obviously the way Horb knew about it and could have
                    been, although not necessarily, how Bouterse found out about it. I noted that
                    during our morning meeting, he had denied knowing anything about events. He said
                    that he had told me that under instructions from his Washington headquarters
                    which had told the station chief that I was not to be told about the letter
                    having been given to Horb or that he had been in touch with Horb. I was to be
                    kept in the dark. I told him that I had just been walking through a mine-field
                    without knowledge of the facts. I had, on the spur of the moment, to decide what
                    to say to Bouterse when he confronted me with the document. I told the station
                    chief that I thought the whole situation was entirely unacceptable. I had been
                    totally blind-sided. I further added that fortunately, I had enough wit to
                    handle this thing properly, no thanks to him, the station chief or the Agency. I
                    told him that I would contact Washington immediately.</p>
                <p>So I sent a telegram to the Assistant Secretary, Tom Enders, explaining what had
                    occurred, that I had not been properly informed and that the decision not to
                    tell me had been approved by the Department of State. That last piece of
                    information came from the station chief. I requested that Enders tell me, by
                    return telegram, if the Department had agreed with the Agency that I was not to
                    be informed. I further added that if the information were correct, he would have
                    my immediate resignation. I got a return telegram within a couple of hours,
                    saying that the information I had was totally incorrect, that the Department had
                    never been told anything about the letter, it had never approved the idea of
                    keeping the Ambassador in the dark. I gave the station chief Enders' reply. He
                    said he didn't know what to say. In the meantime, another message was received
                    from the Agency, saying that it had never approved the idea of keeping me in the
                    dark. The station chief then alleged that it had been an oral arrangement, done
                    over secure phone and that he had been told that I was to be kept in the dark.
                    Obviously, someone was lying. Was it the station chief or his superior in
                    Washington? Or was it the State Department? Not clear. It was perfectly obvious
                    that this episode gave me grounds for firing the station chief and I could have
                    sent him packing within a week's time because he had clearly violated the most
                    fundamental relationship of loyalty and honesty that must prevail between an
                    Ambassador and his staff. I did not fire the station chief because he was, on
                    balance, an able officer. I had a very small staff. I relied on the station
                    chief as much as I relied on anybody within the entire Embassy in terms of
                    support and pursuit of U.S. policy in the country. Quite frankly, I would have
                    divested myself of a very important asset if I had sent him packing, which I
                    could have done.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>I cite this episode because it underscores a number of problems. First of all, of
                    course, is the importance of loyalty and confidence. Secondly, it points to the
                    reality of situations when you are abroad in a small Embassy, in a difficult
                    political setting, trying to conduct a relationship in pursuit of U.S.
                    interests. It sometimes becomes a luxury to stand on principle as I could have.
                    I was in a similar, although less serious, bind with respect to my Defense
                    Attache, who wasn't very smart and did some silly things - not dangerous like
                    what the station chief had done, but silly. I complained about this to the
                    Commanding General of the Defense Attache Corps when I called on him in
                    Washington. He asked me what I thought of the Defense Attache; so I told him
                    that I didn't think he was very good and gave some examples of how I reached
                    that conclusion. He said that he would pull him right out. I asked how long it
                    would take to replace him. The General said “Eighteen months.” That ended that
                    conversation. We had a number of ticklish things going on in Suriname and I had
                    to depend on that Defense Attache to take care of the SWAT team types who were
                    coming in, reconnoitering the country. I had to have the Attache in place to
                    backstop these special teams. I could not afford the luxury of getting rid of a
                    guy and taking a vacancy. These are the realities of what an Ambassador in a
                    small post is faced with. It is not like being in Bonn where you can fire
                    somebody because there are fifteen people standing behind the guy with the
                    senior ready to take over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned two matters on which I would like your
                        comments. You used the phrase “Country Team.” I'd like your views on that
                        concept. The other issue concerns the timing and phrasing of telegrams to
                        Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: On the first point concerning the “Country Team,” I believe in the
                    concept of a circle of senior advisors, each with his or her area of
                    responsibility - the Deputy Chief of mission, the Political Counselor, the
                    Economic Counselor, the CIA station chief, the Defense Attache, the chief of the
                    Consular Section, the Public Affairs Officer and others. For an episode of the
                    sort I described, I thought it was immediately imperative to involve the senior
                    Embassy officers and solicit their perspective on the situation to have them
                    come with some ideas of what was taking place and what we might do about it.
                    That is the whole point of having the country team. I felt that involving them
                    was important not only to get the benefit of their advice but also to inform
                    them about what was clearly a major development in our situation in the country.
                    As I described earlier, the station chief went off on his own and without
                    informing me, sent that initial telegram with the text of the letter.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>That had precisely the wrong effect, which brings us to the second point that you
                    raised. You should never send Washington a raw message about a developing
                    situation, without providing some degree of commentary about it. It may be
                    extremely brief and if it is complicated, you may just want to say “Our initial
                    reactions are... and a more detailed analysis will follow within the next twelve
                    to twenty-four hours.” Clearly this episode demonstrated the undesirability of a
                    raw, shoot-from-the hip message because it gets everybody needlessly excited.
                    They start jumping to conclusions which are usually ill founded. In this case,
                    Washington was wondering whether there was some kind of provocation that could
                    be quite serious, involving some move against the American Embassy or against
                    its staff. Ail of that was possible. But as I pointed out to Bouterse, the
                    forgery was rather ham-handed and it wasn't that difficult to detect the signs
                    of it being a forgery. There are other forged documents that are much more
                    sophisticated and therefore much more difficult to detect.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One other point about the telegram to Washington that
                        should be mentioned is that some times a wrong message leaks almost
                        immediately into the news media with horrendous effects.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: That is correct. As an epilogue to the story, I mention that shortly
                    after the “letter episode,” Bouterse imprisoned Horb in a small jail in downtown
                    Paramaribo, next to the Fort which was the military headquarters. Within one
                    month, Horb was dead allegedly a suicide - hanging by the string of his athletic
                    shorts. Nobody accepted that explanation. It seemed pretty clear that he had
                    been strangled to death - not suicide, but murder just like the other fifteen
                    that Bouterse had ordered sometime earlier. I might add that CIA had handled
                    that particular asset very poorly and his demise was in large measure because
                    the Agency had been stupid and had done something with and for Horb that even
                    Bouterse was smart enough to see had to had come from someone on the U.S. side.
                    Horb had been given a special trip to the United States, he had been presented a
                    couple of small ponies - he loved animals - which arrived by commercial charter.
                    Horb didn't have that kind of money; someone with an awful lot of money was
                    being very kind to Mr. Horb. If you live in a small country like Suriname, you
                    can figure out quickly who has the money for things like that. That was
                    stupid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lets' go to your next assignment.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: I left Suriname in 1984 and returned to Washington to do a management
                    study. The then Under Secretary for Management, Ron Spiers, asked me to make a
                    study of the relationships between CIA and the Department. I don't think this
                    was related to my recent experiences with that Agency, but a coincidence. What
                    had occurred was that in a routine inspection of the Bureau of Intelligence and
                    Research (INR), the Inspector General had commented that there appeared to be
                    some things that were not entirely right in the relationships abroad between the
                    two agencies. The IG was concerned about the use of “cover” abroad. I can't get
                    into detail on this issue because it is classified, but in effect I spent from
                    September 1984 to June-July 1985 working on this project which was a joint
                    project with the CIA. I always had good relations with my CIA colleagues which
                    stood me in good stead when I undertook this project because my reputation in
                    CIA was that I was a reasonable fellow who could work with the CIA without any
                    hang-ups—which cannot be said of all Foreign Service officers. This was a very
                    interesting project. The Agency was very cooperative and thought so highly of
                    the final report, which included 36 recommendations, that it had it printed as
                    an internal document and made it required reading for all their station and
                    deputy station chiefs. I was flattered that they thought of it as well as they
                    did. From that assignment, I went to the Inspection Corps as a Senior Inspector.
                    That assignment lasted for less than twenty-four hours because in the course of
                    the Summer, I had been approached by Jim Michel, the Deputy Assistant Secretary
                    for ARA to see whether I would be willing to take on the administration of an
                    appropriation of $ 27 million for humanitarian aid to the Nicaraguan resistance
                    movement—the Contras. I had declined to take that job on the grounds that I
                    didn't think I was qualified for it. It seemed to me that a more appropriate
                    person would have been someone with Central American experience, including
                    command of Spanish, and with experience in administering aid, which I had not
                    had. So I declined. I was asked once again by Mike Armacost, then the Under
                    Secretary for Political Affairs—an old friend. Mike called me in to ask me to do
                    it and I gave him the same reasons why I did not wish to do it. I then went to
                    Airlie House for a meeting of senior Inspectors of whom I was supposed to become
                    one. The IG went over the agenda for the coming year and the new Inspectors were
                    briefed on the process. While I was out there, I got a phone call about mid-day
                    from Armacost who repeated his views that I should take the assistance job
                    because I was just the right man for it. He said he understood my reservations,
                    but thought that I had other qualifications which would make me eminently suited
                    for it. He mentioned that the Secretary also thought that I was the right man. I
                    responded by saying that if the Secretary personally asked that I take the
                    assignment, I could not refuse. He said he would call back and within five
                    minutes he did in fact call back saying that I had an appointment with the
                    Secretary at 6 o'clock that evening. I returned to Washington and walked into
                    the Secretary's office at 6 o'clock. George Shultz showed his sense of humor
                    when he greeted me by saying :” Bob, I understand you have agreed to take the
                    job”. I said “Yes” and asked him what he expected. He gave me three major
                    points: the guidelines contained in the legislation on how the funds were to be
                    spent—he emphasized that I was to adhere to those guidelines and not to test the
                    limits of the law; he wanted the program administered efficiently and with
                    enthusiasm; thirdly, he wanted the maximum amount possible of the assistance
                    given to the intended recipients and the minimum amount spent on administration.
                    The reason he made the third point is because the newspapers carried a few weeks
                    earlier a story about a big fund-raising dinner in the private sector for aid to
                    the Contras. The story reported that the gross receipts from the dinner were
                    approximately $ 250,000 of which less than $25,000—more in the neighborhood of $
                    6,000—had gone to the Contras. The rest went to consultant fees—two guys got
                    $50,000 each—, dinner costs—food, drink, the hall—etc. The people who went to
                    the dinner forked out a lot of money, very little of which actually went to the
                    cause. I took on the job which was very interesting because Congress had
                    appropriated $ 27 million, but had also stipulated that neither Defense nor CIA
                    could have anything to do with administration of the funds. Congress was at that
                    time very unhappy with both Agencies on how they administered other Contra
                    programs. There had been considerable discussion among the various Executive
                    branch agencies after the passage of the legislation and Presidential approval
                    in early August 1985 on which agency might be able to administer this program.
                    AID refused to do so because they felt it would tarnish their image to be
                    associated with something that was so politically charged. George Shultz did not
                    want it in State Department because State was not an operating agency for
                    administering assistance. It went around and around until it was decided that
                    the only solution was to establish a new semi-autonomous agency which would be
                    under the political guidance of the Department. That is what was done and I was
                    given a Presidential appointment which did not require Senatorial confirmation.
                    It was up to me to create this new little agency. In light of Shultz' admonition
                    to spend as little as possible on administration, the obvious way to proceed was
                    to select people with appropriate experience and background who were already on
                    the federal payroll who could be seconded to me without reimbursement to their
                    agencies. This proposal was warmly received and that is what we did. My deputy
                    was from USIA—he had long experience in Central America and particularly in
                    Honduras. I finally got a commitment, after much haggling, out of AID to give me
                    three officers who had experience in administering assistance programs. Then I
                    got some people out of State Department. I put together a small staff of under
                    ten people. Besides myself, there were two State secretaries, a political
                    officer from the Department, there were three AID officers and one from USIA. We
                    set up shop in rather austere offices in a building in Rosslyn. There was no
                    precedent for administering aid like this. We were doing something totally new.
                    It was ill-advised but we had no choice because of the constraints placed upon
                    us by the Congress in the legislation. My first task was to talk to people who
                    had experience in assistance management looking for potential prototypes. I
                    found the closest parallels to what we were trying to do was in AID's Emergency
                    Relief Office and with the Department's Refugee Relief program, which were used
                    to fast actions. We had to take rapid action because the Contras by that time
                    had not had any US official assistance for over a year and were in dire need of
                    aid. We had to crank up very fast. The White House and the NSC and George Shultz
                    were very anxious that the program move ahead as fast as possible. I was on a
                    spot because speed in getting the program underway was one objective; the other
                    was that the program was to be administered in a way that accountability would
                    be preserved. I had to create processes that would channel these funds in an
                    efficient manner with the records kept appropriately, making sure that the
                    channels were viable and were reliable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was considerable scrutiny and criticism at the
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: There was indeed. This had been fiercely contested legislation and it
                    had some bitter opponents. Therefore, even after it had passed into law, there
                    were many members of Congress who would have preferred to derail the whole
                    program by putting road-blocks in front of the process for implementing the law.
                    I felt very unhappy about all of that because I believed that since it was the
                    law of the land, it was not appropriate for members of Congress—and there were a
                    couple of Representatives I can think of—to harass the proceeding. Mike Barnes
                    of Maryland was the principal opponent. He was the chairman of the Latin
                    American subcommittee of House Foreign Affairs Committee. Barnes had been
                    opposed to the legislation and even after it was passed he held hearings. Within
                    a couple of months of passage, we had an anonymous letter sent to the Inspector
                    General alleging financial irregularities in my operations and accusing us of
                    malfeasance. The IG immediately called me and told me he had the letter. I asked
                    him to send his inspectors over right away so that we could be watched every
                    minute. I was operating this program in clear daylight and wanted anyone who had
                    any questions to watch. I had also gone to the Intelligence Committees and asked
                    for their auditors to advise me on what procedures I should use to implement the
                    law. They declined to participate on the grounds that it would probably be
                    unconstitutional for the Legislative Branch to be telling the Executive how to
                    conduct its business. That I think was a bit of a cop-out, but I understood. The
                    next thing that happened, Barnes asked the General Accounting Office (GAO) to
                    get in the act and the FBI also got into the act. Within three months of
                    establishing this program, I had in my office representatives of the
                    Department's IG, of the GAO and of the FBI. Everything was open to them. They
                    saw everything. They were there for months and months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they help in setting up the system?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: No, they wouldn't play that game. That would have been nice. I would
                    have appreciated their advice. At the end of the program, no one was able to
                    come up with any significant assertion of malfeasance. There were a couple of
                    episodes where there were funds that were misused, but it was our organization
                    that discovered those, with the help of the CIA and we brought them to the
                    attention of GAO. The GAO in turn reported these to the Congress, as they are
                    obliged to do. The senior GAO official most closely involved with our program
                    was a Ms. McCabe. She was excellent, highly professional, entirely realistic.
                    The only difference that I have had with the GAO was on questions of theory. GAO
                    maintained that the accountability checks were inadequate for it to be able to
                    certify with certainty that the aid was reaching the intended recipients. My
                    response was that I agreed, that I understood the point, but that I was
                    operating under constraints, not of my own choosing, namely that this was an
                    overt program in the US, but we were in effect delivering covert aid in Central
                    America. This fact forced the aid to go through Honduras, which did not wish to
                    be seen cooperating with our effort to aid the Contras, because that was not
                    helpful to their own bilateral relationships with Nicaragua. They wanted to be
                    able to disavow any assistance, although the aid delivery was being assisted by
                    the Honduran military. This is now all in the public domain even though it was
                    no secret even then. It was this game of deniability that everyone was playing.
                    Another problem that arose concerned the location of my staff. I had expected to
                    put them in Honduras both at the airport and in the forward areas along the
                    border where the supplies were being delivered to the Contras. However, I was
                    not permitted to have my staff in Honduras. I was told the government of
                    Honduras did not want us there, but I have very good reasons to believe that it
                    was the US Ambassador-John Ferch—in the fall of 1985 who was the real block. He
                    was very much opposed to our program as was his DCM, Shep Lowman. They were
                    personally opposed to the program, so much so that a few weeks later, Elliott
                    Abrams, the then Assistant Secretary for Latin America, had to telephone Ferch
                    to tell him if he didn't support US policy toward Honduras, he would have to be
                    recalled. At that point, Ferch decided he would join the team. But until then,
                    he opposed our program because he felt it would be inimicable to US
                    relationships with Honduras. Of course, I was trying to carry out a policy fully
                    approved by State Department and Elliott Abrams, to whom I looked for political
                    guidance. I was trying to get the program off the ground, while being watched by
                    all the different agencies. When it was all over, there were only two cases
                    involving about $ 75,000—which we reclaimed in large part from the Contras in
                    cash because we felt that the expenditures were not in accord with the
                    legislation. Overall, then, the loss to Uncle Sam was in the $ 5,000-$10,000
                    range, which was very small. People have told me, after it was all over, that
                    they have never seen an aid program administered as efficiently as this was. We
                    had spent slightly over 1% of the principal for administrative expenses. The
                    normal percentage runs between 10% and 25%. We were considerably under the
                    average. That was in response to George Shultz' admonition to get the maximum
                    flow through to the intended recipients. We not only administered the program to
                    the best of our abilities under the constraints imposed on us, but I am
                    confident that that aid in fact did reach the intended recipients. We tried in
                    every way possible to check that, including audit of our in-country suppliers.
                    We procured items in the United States—boots, ponchos, web belts, raingear and
                    pharmaceuticals—and shipped them by air into Central America. Within Central
                    America, we procured food and other daily necessities—paper products, fuel oil,
                    some vehicles (Jeeps), boats, etc. One of the ways we were able to check whether
                    any material was being sold in the black market—that is people accepting the
                    material and then selling it in the black market for cash to buy weapons which
                    would have been misuse of the funds—was to monitor the market places in the
                    small towns where deliveries were being made. We were able to determine that our
                    material never entered the black market.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If you couldn't have people in the field, how did you
                        conduct the checks?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: We checked through the CIA, which had a sizeable operation in Honduras,
                    including a separate base that worked entirely on the Contra issue. CIA had its
                    agents in the field, right on the border. Under the legislation and with the
                    full understanding and agreement of the two intelligence oversight committees of
                    the Congress, CIA was able to provide surveillance and report back to us. We got
                    a steady stream of reports, eye witness accounts, on the delivery of the
                    supplies from the airfields in Honduras or El Salvador through the truck supply
                    system to the actual deliveries to the Contras. CIA people were reporting all
                    along the line at various points in the delivery system. That is not to say that
                    we had 100% coverage of the deliveries; we did not. But we had a significant
                    percentage and there were spot checks all along. We were pretty confident that
                    the reports were reliable. I want to make another observation. I was running a
                    program of $ 27 million, which in the federal budget, is a very small program.
                    Compare that with aid to Israel or Egypt. We were talking about peanuts. People
                    with experience in the aid business will tell you that there is a certain amount
                    of “spoilage or corruption” that is to be expected. I think that in retrospect
                    we looked very good. The other irony is that with all the scrutiny focused on
                    us, there were far worse abuses taking place in the Federal Government, such as
                    in HUD, Savings and Loans, etc. There you see malfeasance of dimensions that
                    absolutely dwarfed our program. Yet for political reasons everyone was fixated
                    on our program, thanks to the political opponents. One of the things that
                    motivated Mike Barnes was his desire to grandstand and grab headlines because he
                    was going to run for the Senate. In the spring of 1986, he was trying to build
                    up his public image by making a lot of headlines. I think that was part of his
                    motivation. In fact, he lost in the Democratic primary to Barbara Mikulski and
                    has passed into some degree of obscurity, at least for the moment. I have to say
                    that as a hard working civil servant, trying to discharge my responsibilities
                    under the law of the land, I took a very dim view of Congressmen trying to
                    derail what I was doing by putting obstacles in front of me. A lot of it was
                    pure harassment. There is another dimension of all of this that is noteworthy;
                    namely, the role of Oliver North. Oliver North, who subsequently achieved a lot
                    of notoriety, was the person to whom I was directed for information about the
                    Contras and the resistance movement in terms of their resources, etc. Elliott
                    Abrams and others in the Department directed me to North, a Marine Lieutenant
                    Colonel on the NSC staff. I was told that he had worked closely with Contras and
                    that I should call on him, which I did. I had known him slightly through a
                    conference that we had both attended when I was Ambassador in Suriname. The
                    conference had taken place in Panama. He is a very engaging person. He told me
                    one evening at the conference his world view. He said he thought that the
                    administration had an extraordinary opportunity to turn Communism back around
                    the world. This could be done in Central America, in the Caribbean and elsewhere
                    in the world. He thought that would be a great turning point in history. I
                    listened with some interest. I confess a degree of disbelief; it sounded a
                    trifle apocalyptic. That was my first encounter with Oliver North. A year later,
                    I went to talk to him as head of the Nicaraguan Humanitarian Assistance
                    Office—that is what my organization was called. I talked to him about the
                    Contras; he gave me a lot of information and some help; he mentioned to me a
                    private citizen whom he knew who had been working with the Contras by the name
                    of Robert Owen. Owen, in fact, called on me in September, 1985 when I was trying
                    to organize the staff for the new office. He came to volunteer his services;
                    that is to say he wanted to be employed. He had spent the summer in Central
                    America, working with a member of the Tom Dooley Foundation assessing the
                    medical problems and needs of the Nicaraguan resistance. They had written a
                    report which he gave me. He said that he knew the Contras, he knew Ollie North,
                    he was a true believer—by that he meant that he was a loyal follower of Ronald
                    Reagan—, he was a strong supporter of the policy and that he was the right guy
                    for me. I had some qualms about involving someone who was so clearly identified
                    with the Contra cause because although I was about to provide aid to the
                    Contras, I saw my operation as an arms-length, objective, government program. It
                    was not meant to be highly partisan, in my view. My second reservation was a
                    very practical one. I only wanted people already on the federal payroll who had
                    security clearances. Owen didn't have that. I explained that to him and told him
                    that I didn't have a place for him. In the course of those first six weeks
                    devoted to creating this new semi-autonomous agency, I was casting around for
                    ideas on how this might be done as well as to identify people who could join my
                    staff. I was discussing all these matters with the inter-agency group which was
                    a standing committee at the Assistant Secretary level, chaired by Assistant
                    Secretary for Latin American affairs, Elliott Abrams. The other representatives
                    on that group were officers from other agencies of equivalent rank, including
                    such people as Oliver North, representing the NSC politico-military section.
                    There was also another fellow representing the NSC political section. There was
                    someone from Defense, Joint Chiefs of Staff and the CIA and a few others. That
                    constituted a kind of steering committee which discussed policy and the
                    implementation of policy in the Latin American area. I met with that group
                    perhaps as much as twice a week in the initial stages to discuss with them how I
                    was approaching my task, what decisions I was making and to seek their guidance
                    on how to implement the legislation—what was permissible, what was not
                    permissible in terms of the kind of aid that could be given. The legislation
                    forbade anything having to do with armaments or guns or bullets or armed
                    vehicles, etc. It had to be “humanitarian”—food, clothing and the necessities of
                    daily living, pharmaceuticals, etc. In the initial discussions, I explained how
                    I intended to proceed. Ollie North took a very vigorous role in the discussions
                    of the committee. He was a very engaging character, but I thought he had the
                    temperament of a “naughty altar-boy”. He is very handsome in a boyish way with a
                    little lock of hair that falls engagingly across his forehead. He has a
                    wonderful grin. He has the classic all-American boy looks—trim, erect military
                    bearing, handsome, engaging, personable. He knows all that. He is an actor, he
                    knows how to use his appearance, his voice, his expressions, his eye-brows, his
                    grin. He can bring all of that to play and does it very effectively, as was
                    often shown during his testimony in Congressional hearings. I had reservations
                    about North, going back to that conversation I had with him on the beach of
                    Panama, which I described earlier. Also I felt that I had been put in charge of
                    this program and I believed that I should decide what it would be and how it
                    should be run. So I made certain assertions on how I wanted to do things. North
                    didn't take exception particularly but kept hammering on the urgency. He felt
                    that the material had to be moved rapidly. He thought the Contras were in very
                    tough shape and dying. He always wanted quicker action. I told him that I was as
                    anxious to get started as he was, but that it had to be done in an orderly
                    fashion because I was the one who was accountable and had to answer to the
                    Congress on how the program had been administered. I also was accountable to
                    George Shultz, the GAO, the FBI and the Inspector General. I refused to be
                    precipitous. There was a hell of a lot of heat being put on me to move in a
                    precipitous fashion. Ollie was pressing me very hard to take Rob Owen on my
                    staff. I explained to Ollie why I didn't want him. I felt that Owen was tainted
                    politically, because Owen was publicly identified with the right wing friends of
                    the Contras in the United States. I felt that my program had to be apolitical,
                    particularly if I was going to be able to defend it against the attacks from the
                    left. They were already coming from Mike Barnes. I certainly did not want to get
                    into bed right away with the right wing. So I didn't want Rob Owen for these
                    various reasons. My position finally forced a kind of a show-down meeting in
                    mid-October, 1985. It was a Saturday morning in Abrams' office and North had
                    been haranguing me on getting going and on Rob Owen. I had discussed the Owen
                    matter privately with Abrams and with Jim Michel, his principal deputy. They
                    understood my position, which I made very clear in the inter-agency meetings.
                    Finally, Abrams turned to me and suggested that I find a place for Owen. I had
                    become totally isolated with everyone, except me, feeling he should be employed
                    on my staff. They were all backing down in front of North. I had also received a
                    letter signed by all three of the Contras leaders —Calero, Cruz and
                    Robelo—asking me to hire Owen to work with them. I finally agreed, but I said
                    that I would only do so by making a grant to the foundation of which Owen was
                    the titular head. This was a one-man foundation called IDEA (Institute for
                    Democracy and Education). That grant would enable him to devote full time to
                    assisting the Contras and to act as a kind of liaison between the Contras and
                    me. He would work for them and I would specify the areas in which I wanted his
                    assistance. I wanted him to work especially on the medical program because he
                    had been involved in that before. I wanted him to expedite things, but he was
                    not working directly for me and was not on my staff. I also told the group that
                    I was in charge of the program and that it would be managed my way. If they
                    didn't agree with that, I asked them to tell me right then and there because
                    then I would resign. They all backed off because they knew I would resign. That
                    was the moment I drew the line on the sand and made it clear that I would not be
                    pushed on how I would administer the program. Ollie North backed off and said he
                    thought that I was wonderful in the job and that I had his full confidence. From
                    that moment on, I had no more problems with Ollie North. I did of course have
                    Owen, but I was able to fence him off to my satisfaction. He made a number of
                    trips to Central America from which he wrote reports which were reasonably
                    useful. He did some very useful things with respect to the medical program. But
                    he also, unbeknownst to me, was playing a double role, which became subsequently
                    public knowledge when he testified before the Congressional investigative
                    Committees. There he confessed that on the side, he was doing exactly what I
                    feared; namely he was working for Ollie North and the Contras and involved
                    himself in the private arms supply pipeline. There was nothing illegal about the
                    arms-to-the-Contras. It was just that my program could not have had anything to
                    do with arms. Although Owen was under contract to me full time, he involved
                    himself in the arms supply effort. He lamely excused himself before the
                    Congressional Committees, when asked about this dual role, by saying that the
                    arms work was done after five o'clock on his own time. The contract had
                    stipulated that he be full time and exclusively a contractor to my organization.
                    He had violated his contract. Then the Committee asked him what I would have
                    thought had I known of this dual role. Owen responded that I would have been
                    very disappointed, which would have been the least. The program continued and
                    the aid got there. There was very little cash; that was primarily used to buy
                    cordobas, the Nicaraguan currency. You could buy the cordobas at a huge discount
                    outside of Nicaragua because they were almost worthless due to the terrible
                    inflation. The only cash that we ever gave to the Contras were these cordobas
                    for use when they went into Nicaragua. Otherwise, everything else we gave was
                    in-kind assistance—food, pharmaceuticals, clothing, boots, ponchos, web belts,
                    canteens, etc. In essence, we had completed the disbursal of the available funds
                    by about July 1986. The legislation required that all the funds be committed in
                    the pipe-line by April 1, 1986. We did that. Forward contracts were written and
                    the actual supplies had cleared the pipeline by about August, 1986. By that
                    time, we were over the hump with all the investigations which had come to
                    little. In the meantime, a whole separate matter—the Iran-Contra scandal—was
                    beginning to bubble up. We were going out of business. By August, 1986 most of
                    the aid had been given. I spent the Fall of 1986 writing the final report
                    covering all of our activities. Two of my colleagues wrote parts of it, but it
                    was mostly mine. We outlined in detail all of our procedures, we discussed all
                    of the criticisms received, we appended a full accounting of every nickel, etc.
                    We had lots of invoices to back up our expenditures. That report was about
                    sixty-five pages long. It analyzed the experience in great detail. I wrote it
                    for the benefit of anyone who might find himself in similar circumstances in the
                    future. The report had great utility in part for unforeseen readers. Aid to the
                    Contras lapsed in April, 1986. It was cranked up again in Summer or Fall 1987
                    with a new program. This time it was under the auspices of AID, which is where
                    programs of this kind belong in any case. The fist thing the AID people in
                    charge of the new program did was to pull out my report so that they could build
                    on the past without having to reinvent the wheel. There were other problems
                    beyond the ones I have already mentioned. There were difficulties with the
                    procurement practices of Contras. We had inherited a pipeline system which I
                    used to a considerable extent although much of their procurement policy was
                    seat-of-the-pants which we of course couldn't use. There were some suppliers we
                    didn't use because we thought they were undependable. There were some other
                    problematic areas. They had to do with flights because we had to charter
                    aircraft and there were some allegations at one point that some of our flights
                    were involved in drug running. What happened was that we did charter private
                    flights from air charter companies, over which we had no control. We were simply
                    hiring a plane and a crew to fly our stuff from New Orleans to Tegucigalpa,
                    which then completed their obligation to us. Whatever else they did, we had no
                    knowledge of or control over. It therefore might have been entirely possible
                    that some of those private charter organizations could have been involved in
                    drug running, but never to the best of our knowledge, did anything that involved
                    us and they wouldn't have because we were moving goods from the United States to
                    Central America in the opposite direction from the drug flow. When the flights
                    returned to the US they were no longer under our charter. There were also some
                    questions about arms drops and we had consulted with the House and Senate
                    Intelligence Oversight Committees about whether we could be allowed to pay for
                    “mixed” loads. We got some guidelines from those Committees because they
                    recognized that if we were making air-drops in Nicaragua, you couldn't send in
                    more than one flight to a single destination and therefore if arms had to be
                    delivered, could they be put on board a flight that we had paid for? The
                    Intelligence Oversight Committees agreed that some limited amount, without
                    specifying how much—I decided unilaterally on 10%—would be permissible. So there
                    were two flights that actually did drop arms—two other were aborted—but it was
                    less than 10%, so that we stayed within the Congressional guidelines. (The arms
                    were not paid for by us, of course.) There was one episode in which there was an
                    unauthorized arms loading on one of our aircraft flying inside Central America
                    from Salvador to Honduras. That was against the rules and when we heard about
                    it, we refused to pay for the charter. That caused a bit of a problem, but we
                    overcame it by disavowing the flight and by refusing to pay the bill. It was
                    paid by the Contras from their own funds. The one other comment I want to make
                    about this experience is that I had the unique experience of creating a new
                    federal agency and disbanding it. It went out of existence when it had fulfilled
                    its mission. That is unusual in the federal government where most new agencies
                    go on forever. I cranked it up and cranked it down. Frankly, I am quite proud of
                    that. A lot of people said to me when I took the job that I was opening a can of
                    worms and couldn't understand why I wanted to participate in the Contras-aid
                    program. I thought it would be very challenging. Moreover, the Secretary of
                    State had asked me to do it and you don't say “No” to the Secretary. As Foreign
                    Service officers, we are to do the bidding of the President and the Secretary. I
                    feel very proud about having done that, under extremely difficult political
                    circumstances. We discharged the Congress' mandate efficiently. That was my last
                    assignment in the Foreign Service and I am very pleased in many ways to have
                    gone out on that note.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned Michael Barnes. Did you get fired at by
                        Jesse Helms, the Senator from North Carolina?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: We never heard much from Jesse Helms. We heard a lot from Congressman
                    Henry Hyde. He was strong proponent of the Contras. I was not involved in the
                    political battles, but Elliott Abrams was and he kept me out of those, quite
                    rightly. I almost never testified on the Hill, although I did testify before the
                    Intelligence Oversight Committees, because they wanted to know how it was coming
                    along and what I was doing. Incidentally, while I was catching flak, Senator
                    Durenberger, who was a co-chair of the Senate Committee, issued a press release
                    in June, 1986 strongly defending me and my program. He in effect said that the
                    flak was totally unfounded and that we were doing a magnificent job for which we
                    should be commended for what we were doing and the harassment should stop. That
                    was greatly appreciated. I never had any problem with the Oversight Committees.
                    It is a very different thing to testify in a closed session of the Intelligence
                    Oversight Committees because there the members are entirely professional,
                    serious, rational and business-like. It is when Congressmen meet in open session
                    that you get all the grandstanding and all the politicking and all the mugging
                    for the cameras and all that stuff. So it is a totally different environment
                    inside the Intelligence Committees. I never had any problems with those
                    Committees. The program was very political. The Contras had strong proponents of
                    which I am sure Jesse Helms was one, Henry Hyde was another. There were many
                    others. The Administration and Ronald Reagan and Poindexter were strong
                    proponents of the Contras. After all, the Administration was able to get aid
                    through the Congress on that occasion. There were other occasions when Congress
                    refused to grant assistance to the Contras.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Suriname, you were out of the Administration's focus in
                        Central America. So when you were brought in, although you were part of the
                        Latin American Bureau, you were not tainted. What was your impression of the
                        atmospherics, particularly around Elliott Abrams and other
                        personalities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: First of all, I admired Elliott Abrams. Not everyone liked Elliott. I
                    think he is very intelligent, very quick, very shrewd. His politics were more
                    partisan than mine—I am a centrist. But I respected his operating abilities.
                    Some people didn't like him because he had a sharp tongue and he sometimes had a
                    nasty air about him—a little bit vicious. That never particularly bothered me,
                    but then he was always very polite to me and even friendly. We got along just
                    fine. Jim Michel, Abrams' principal deputy, for whom I had great regard, had an
                    unparalleled experience with the Congress. He was very good at knowing how to
                    work with the Congress. Michel was a lawyer, having been in the Legal Advisor's
                    Office for many years. He was very quiet, very shrewd, savvy, thoughtful and
                    worked with Congress extremely effectively. They all liked him very much; they
                    like Michel in a ways that some people couldn't stand Elliott Abrams. In terms
                    of others, I had very high regard for Allen Fiers who was the CIA man in charge
                    of the whole Contras operation. Fiers unfortunately came a-cropper later on in
                    the Iran-Contras business. He must have testified in close session at some
                    length with the Investigating Committees. He was accused of doing some things
                    that were unknown to his immediate superiors. Fiers was forced into early
                    retirement. I had worked very closely with him because I could not have done my
                    job effectively without the assistance of the CIA for the oversight of the
                    delivery pipeline. Fiers was our principal link on an operational basis with
                    Central America and the Contras. Of course, I was in touch with the Contras in
                    Washington all the time. They had offices both in Washington and in Miami. So I
                    dealt with the Contras directly all the time. I thought Fiers was very
                    professional, very savvy, very operational. There was another fellow who got
                    fired from the Agency for doing things that were unauthorized. He was the chief
                    of the base I was using in Honduras. He once said to me that he was there
                    running the base to help the Contras. He said that he had been in Vietnam,
                    involved in the assistance to the Vietnamese Army. The way we “left our
                    Vietnamese friends behind” made an indelible impression on him. He said he would
                    never, never again be involved with supporting people that we would then turn
                    our backs on. He apparently did some things for the Contras which were
                    unauthorized and perhaps even contrary to official policy. He was therefore
                    sacked. He felt that on the one hand, we were promising to support the Contras
                    while on the other withdrawing aid to them. Of course, he was partially right
                    since our assistance was often on again, off again. He felt that it was
                    unconscionable to draw people in, then welsh on the commitment.I would further
                    say that if I were to fault the administration for any part of its Latin America
                    policies, it would be that they became so preoccupied with Central America that
                    they neglected other important US interests on the South American continent.
                    There was too much preoccupation with Central America to the detriment of other
                    more important issues in Latin America.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They also drew down a lot of good will by forcing Latin
                        American countries to support our efforts in Central America.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: That was true. We were using up a lot of good will from the Hondurans,
                    the Costa Ricans and perhaps others. I must however add that I don't think that
                    all Latin American countries covered themselves with glory. For example, the
                    Sandinistas came to power through the active assistance of the Costa Ricans and
                    the Colombians and the Venezuelans. Then when the Sandinistas had proven to be
                    fully as tyrannical as the Somozas had been, they refused to assist the
                    democratic forces, including the Contras. I am not saying that all Contras were
                    democrats. The Costa Ricans particularly like to posture as being very correct
                    and very democratic. In fact, they were at times very partisan when it served
                    their own interests. I never had much regard for Adolfo Calero. I thought he was
                    out of the classic Central American caudillo mold. Unfortunately, the Central
                    American countries historically have been ill served by a succession of
                    strong-men—the caudillos. It is very much ingrained in the political tradition
                    of Central America. You could even argue that that is what the Central American
                    people want and expect. Costa Rica is one of the few exceptions to that rule,
                    but elsewhere you have seen a succession of strong men. That is what Colero
                    would have been. He was not much of a democrat. Cruz was much more of a
                    democrat, but was rather weak-willed and rather indecisive. Robelo was smarter,
                    somewhat more of a democrat, but he too comes clearly out of the privileged
                    classes of Nicaragua. He was a little ambivalent in some of his attitudes. After
                    working with the Contras, from the top leadership to the lowest echelons, I have
                    the highest regard for the rank and file. I made two or three trips into Central
                    America to inspect the supply lines, the warehouses and the advance bases. I
                    came to have great regard for some of the people in the medical side—the doctors
                    and the orderlies—who were operating under extremely difficult conditions. These
                    doctors could have made a lot more money elsewhere, but they elected to work for
                    this cause because they believed in democracy in Nicaragua. They were doing a
                    wonderful job. There were a lot of others in the supply side who believed in
                    what they were doing and who were subjected to considerable personal privation
                    and discomfort. I had to admire their willingness to work under those conditions
                    for a cause. I did not have that high regard for the leadership which I thought
                    was in large measure rather self-serving. Some of their immediate assistants
                    were pretty good and some were clearly involved in self-interest. They were
                    living well and enjoying themselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came to the Contras issues rather late. Did you feel
                        you were essentially involved in a holding operation for a doomed
                        cause?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: At the time I went in to it, I did not think it was a doomed cause.
                    First of all, I would not have done it if I did not have at least a general
                    agreement with the policy. I was in general agreement with the Administration's
                    policy of trying to support a democratic resistance to the Sandinistas. I saw
                    the aid program being a factor in pursuit of that policy. I also felt that it
                    was a reasonable proposition. As I got into it deeper, I did feel that the
                    Contras leadership was a weak reed and that the whole operation was weak, if it
                    were to be the primary instrument for the restoration of democracy in Nicaragua.
                    I thought that the Administration was pinning its hopes much too heavily on the
                    Contras as being the instrument for the restoration of democracy. I didn't think
                    the Contras could hack it. The more I saw of them, both in terms of the
                    leadership's venality and the ineffectiveness of their military operations, the
                    less confident I became of the chances of success. In the long term, it was
                    doomed to failure. But I couldn't see or know that until I had been into the
                    operation for six to nine months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the other Foreign Service Officers? Were they
                        divided into true believers and skeptics on whether the Contras would
                        succeed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: Yes, it did divide people. I always had the impression that the Central
                    American Office had very mixed feelings about the humanitarian assistance and
                    the Contras themselves. I felt that Bill Walker, who was Abrams' deputy for
                    Central America, was very ambivalent on the subject. He was very careful to keep
                    a certain distance; he had to be involved, but I noticed that Walker and the
                    Central American Office director and staff, wanted to keep the Contras
                    assistance program at arms-length. They were always nice to me, polite and
                    friendly, but they were careful not to become too involved themselves. They
                    appeared to have reservations about it, intellectually, but they also thought it
                    was pretty high risk politically and they didn't want to get brushed with this
                    program if it might become detrimental to their careers. There seems to be an
                    increasing concern for careerism in the Department of State and among Foreign
                    Service Officers. Foreign Service Officers have been pushed into that. There is
                    a certain inclination among some to indulge in careerism. Increasingly, FSOs
                    have been pushed into being careerist—self seeking for personal
                    advancement—because there is less merit promotion at the top, there are fewer
                    jobs at the top because more and more go to political appointees. That makes the
                    competition increasingly tough and vigorous and in some cases, vicious, leading
                    inevitably to careerism at lower levels. So I always felt that there were
                    intellectual reservations, which are legitimate and genuine, but also other
                    factors at work. No one in the Department put up any barriers in my way. They
                    recognized it was the policy and they were going to discharge their
                    responsibilities. I worked with one middle-grade officer in the Central American
                    Office who was always very supportive who saw it as his professional
                    responsibility. But there were people senior to him in the same Office who were
                    much more aloof. The Nicaraguan desk officer never wanted to be involved. So
                    there was a mixed picture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Looking back on your multi-faceted career, what gave you
                        your greatest satisfaction?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>DUEMLING: That is hard to answer. We usually find professional challenges in
                    every place we are and therefore in terms of professional achievement, it is
                    possible to have a sense of success in different places and at different times.
                    I would point to my more senior positions toward the end of my career as being
                    ultimately the most satisfying. I am proud of what I was able to do with the
                    Contras assistance program because it was done under such trying and difficult
                    circumstances. That was an important achievement. I also enjoyed being
                    associated with the creation of the Multi-National Force for the Sinai because
                    that has proven to be a very lasting and successful peace-keeping effort. It was
                    again an opportunity to be creative because we had never done anything like that
                    before. Putting together that peace-keeping force outside the auspices of the
                    United Nations without precedent, was on the frontier of experience and
                    creative. It was great fun to go off on the negotiations with other governments
                    at a high level, achieving an objective. In both cases, we are talking about
                    tangibles—something happens that is clearly tangible, that you can achieve and
                    measure. Often, as we in the Foreign Service are painfully aware, what you
                    achieve is intangible and therefore difficult to measure and difficult to
                    stimulate a sense of achievement because you can't point to anything. The
                    “tangibleness” of those two assignments was particularly satisfying. However,
                    managing to successfully navigate the political rocks and shoals of two years as
                    Ambassador in Suriname, particularly with that extraordinary episode I described
                    earlier involving my disloyal station chief—that gave me a sense of achievement.
                    When I left, the government to my astonishment conferred upon me the highest
                    order that is available to a foreigner in the highest grade that had ever been
                    given. In Dutch, it is called Ere Ordre van de Palm Trager van de Grosse Lint,
                    or in English, “The Honorable Order of the Palm, Bearer of the Grand Sash”.
                    Under the Department's regulations, one has to ask permission to accept such
                    awards and it is done on the basis of “you keep it unless they object”. Since
                    they never objected, I have kept it. I wear it to this day. It has a little
                    rosette which goes into your lapel. It has a great star that you hang on your
                    left breast and it has a sash which goes around your neck and down your side,
                    with the medal dangling somewhere on your right left. When I am in white tie, I
                    am in full fig with this sash around my neck and the great star. It always
                    amuses me because I do actually wear a white tie from time to time—usually at
                    the National Gallery of Art when they are putting on a major dinner party with
                    the President in attendance. The Director of the Gallery—Carter Brown—, who
                    happens to be a good friend of mine, who has a number of decorations himself
                    from foreign governments, always says to me as he shakes my hand going through
                    the receiving line:” Bob, I never got one of those that has a lovely sash. I
                    envy you the sash”. If you are in to foreign decorations, every one recognizes
                    that a sash denotes a high order of rank within that particular chivalrous
                    order. People always want to know where I got that sash. They are always
                    surprised that it comes from a little country called Suriname. They gave it to
                    me because despite the very tense relationships between the US and Suriname,
                    they and I felt that I was able to conduct the relationship in as professional
                    and friendly a manner as possible given the circumstances. They appreciated that
                    I was always fully professional with them, particularly with the dictator. We
                    had a perfectly friendly relationship. It was never very warm, but it was
                    cordial and correct. I did enjoy some of my staff jobs, particularly working for
                    Bob Ingersoll, when he was Deputy Secretary and for Bill Bundy when he was
                    running the Asia Bureau at the time of Vietnam. I feel that at the end of it
                    all, I was very fortunate in the assignments I had. I never had a dull
                    assignment; I never had an assignment I disliked; I was never in a country that
                    I disliked; and I had some assignments, that from a purely personal point of
                    view, leaving aside professional considerations, were delightful. My first
                    assignment abroad, the three years in Rome as a bachelor in the early 1960s, was
                    absolutely wonderful. I had the time of my life. It left me with very warm
                    feeling towards Italy and the Italians. I can't say that my professional
                    achievements in Italy in those years were of particular distinction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would you say to a young person today who is
                        considering the Foreign Service as a career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DUEMLING: If he or she is seriously interested in the conduct—I stress the word
                    conduct— of foreign relations of the United States, then the Foreign Service is
                    the only real game in town. It is the number one area under the big tent. If the
                    person is more concerned with being a policy-maker in the foreign affairs area,
                    he or she will reach that goal faster by not coming in at the bottom of the
                    Foreign Service and working your way up. You can reach that goal by going into
                    the private sector—a bank or law firm—, mostly ingratiating yourself with a
                    political figure who may wish to have you in his administration and will appoint
                    you to be Assistant Secretary for Latin America Affairs. This may be a
                    precarious journey, but it may catapult you into a policy-making position. If
                    you are interested in policy rather than the daily fabric of the conduct of
                    foreign affairs relationships, then don't go into the Foreign Service. If you
                    are interested in the day-to-day application of policy and ultimately assisting
                    with the formulation of the policy, because you do get that opportunity, but
                    only in the mid-to-late parts of your career, then come into the Foreign
                    Service. Don't come into the Foreign Service if you are expecting something
                    else.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
