<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000533">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Robert B. Houston </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>ROBERT B. HOUSTON</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Horace G. Torbert </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 14, 1990</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mr. Houston, it is a great pleasure to have you here
                        today, I hope you won't be embarrassed by the fact that we have known each
                        other pretty well over recent years, but I would like to get your very
                        interesting career documented. Would you start by how you first became
                        interested in foreign affairs, either from your early education, late
                        education or by happenstance?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: I can certainly say we have known each other well. I can state in fact
                    you are the best boss I have ever had in the Foreign Service. That commercial
                    aside, my entry into the Foreign Service was accidental. I had been a radio
                    engineer at the Naval Research Laboratory in Washington, D.C. during the war.
                    When the war was over, I, who had spent the war years between Washington, D.C.
                    and the experimental base on Chesapeake Bay, decided that I wanted to travel. I
                    knew the Department of State had a telecommunications division so I went over to
                    talk to Francis Colt De Wolf, the head of the telecommunications division. We
                    had a nice meeting of an hour or so, but when it was over he said, “You know, we
                    have no openings, but the Foreign Service is hiring people. Why don't you go
                    over to the Walker Johnson Building and talk to them?”</p>
                <p>I had never really considered the Foreign Service before, but I did go over and
                    speak to the people over there. The Department in 1945 was desperately seeking
                    to rebuild its cadre. They were taking people with no oral examination into
                    something called the Foreign Service Auxiliary. I had interviews and went
                    through the necessary credentials proofing and so forth and was brought into the
                    Foreign Service class that met at the Lothrop mansion out on Connecticut Avenue
                    in October 1945. We graduated, I think, in November of 1945. Then the day came
                    to hand out assignments. When Mr. Perry Jester, who was the class monitor at the
                    time, came to my name, he smiled and said, “Oh, this is a delightful one. Mr.
                    Houston, you are going to Lagos.” At that point I hadn't the foggiest idea where
                    Lagos was. I had been convinced that I was going to be assigned to Rio de
                    Janeiro, and had even started studying Portuguese on my own. I was told that
                    until they could find me a ship to take me to Lagos I should go down and read
                    the files at the Bureau of African Affairs. It was then in the Old Executive
                    Office Building, just west of the White House, but it was then still called the
                    State-War-Navy Building.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't think it was a bureau at that time, it was
                        probably an office.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes, it was an office that consisted of two people, Henry Villard and
                    Joe Palmer. I was reading the files diligently until an emergency arose in the
                    Foreign Service. An officer had come down with malaria in Accra, and had to be
                    evacuated. So this created sufficient urgency for the Department to go to the
                    terrific expense of sending me by air to Accra. I spent Christmas eve at Roberts
                    Field in Liberia on my way to post. I arrived December 31, 1945 at my first post
                    in the Foreign Service, Accra, then the seat of the British Gold Coast colony.
                    We had established our first post there during the war because Accra was a
                    landing point for ferrying aircraft across the Atlantic. The route was Natal to
                    Ascension Island, then either to Liberia or the Gold Coast, and then across
                    Africa and up to Iran for transport into the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>Although most American forces had been evacuated by my time, a small detachment
                    was still in Accra selling off war surplus. The main raison d'etre for a post in
                    Accra was ceasing. The focus now was consular matters and watching the emergence
                    of independence movements. During my time in the Gold Coast the thinking was
                    that preparations for independence would last fifty years. In other words
                    sometime in the year 2000 the Gold Coast could aspire to independence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like the liberation of Eastern Europe in the past
                        year.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes, it came much faster. I had entered the Foreign Service not
                    necessarily to make it a lifetime career. So much of what I had studied at
                    Harvard in physics had been classified during the war. There were all sorts of
                    developments that had come out, the atom bomb, radar, computers, so I thought I
                    would get the travel bug out of my system and then go back and study physics
                    again. But three months after my arrival in the Gold Coast, because the new
                    Consul had medical problems, I ended up as the senior American representative at
                    what was then just a consulate but is now an embassy. I had three houses under
                    my control, four vehicles, a household staff of twenty. I sat on the right hand
                    side of the governor on every social occasion. For a young man of twenty-two
                    this was pretty heady stuff. So thoughts of going back and studying dry old
                    physics again tended to recede in the course of this first assignment.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>After I had been in charge there for about a year, the Department was finally
                    able to send out an experienced consul to take charge. My glory days were over,
                    but I still liked the Foreign Service. So much so that I applied for Arabic
                    specialization. I would hear more about this later at a most inconvenient time.
                    I would like to point out that I entered the Foreign Service before the Foreign
                    Service Act of 1946, under the Rogers Act. Many of the things that people take
                    for granted today did not exist at that time. There was no absolute guarantee
                    then of home leave. While there was an “April Fools Sheet” [the Post Preference
                    Report due in the Department each April 1st] which you could fill out, it really
                    did not mean a thing. Travel orders, in those days, I recall, stated it very
                    clearly: “These travel orders are not issued for your personal pleasure or
                    convenience.” The idea people have today of bargaining for where they would like
                    to go and arranging travel to suit themselves was not a part of the Foreign
                    Service in those days. On the other hand, some things were rather nice, too. We
                    got maybe one pouch a month, and if we received two telegrams in one day, that
                    was a busy day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They all had to be decoded on a one-time pad.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: That's right. If we needed money, we had a book of blank drafts drawn on
                    the Secretary of State and we could fill one out and take it down to the bank
                    and get as much money as we needed—an element of trust that seems extraordinary
                    today. We made out our own accounts and mailed them off once a month. Apparently
                    the system worked; I don't recall any cases of people absconding with the
                    Secretary of State's funds in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sometimes the books got a little messed up, but you made
                        it up out of your own pocket, I understand.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: This was very much a learning experience for me. Even though I had
                    majored in physics, I considered that I had had a fairly broad based education.
                    I do feel that I was up to the job that was required there, and decided to make
                    the Foreign Service a career. In December 1947, after two years in Accra, I was
                    ordered to Bremen, Germany. Those were still the days when one traveled by ship.
                    I spent twenty-six days on a ship coming up from Takoradi, the Gold Coast to
                    Amsterdam. It was not that the ships were so very slow in those days. This was a
                    combined freighter-passenger ship which anchored in a number of ports in West
                    Africa on the way to Europe. It also anchored in Le Havre for three days, during
                    which time I was in Paris. All this of course was while I was in travel
                    status.</p>
                <p>In many West African ports, it was necessary to anchor out in the roadstead. The
                    freight would be brought to the ship by lighters. Natives would come out in
                    outrigger canoes, one could bargain with them for a ride to shore. I was able to
                    go ashore in Monrovia, Liberia; Freetown, Sierra Leone; and Bathurst, Gambia en
                    route.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I had a few trips myself but I don't remember any
                        twenty-six day ones. Had you had any home leave?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: No, they were just getting used to the idea that Foreign Service
                    officers should be given regular home leave. I would not get home leave until
                    after I had been almost six months at my new post. On January 1, 1948 I took the
                    train from Amsterdam to Bremen, Germany. I thought all the time my assignment
                    was to Bremen, Germany. When I arrived in Bremen and met people there, I learned
                    that my destiny had been switched, again without consultation with me. I was
                    going to be the officer in charge of a Vice Consulate in Bremerhaven, Germany.
                    Bremerhaven in those days was quite active as far as American shipping was
                    concerned, being the port of embarkation for U.S. forces in Germany. There was
                    very little transportation by air then for either personnel or equipment, so
                    there were many vessels going in and out. The powers that be decided that a Vice
                    Consulate in Bremerhaven under the supervision of the Consul General in Bremen
                    was needed, primarily to handle shipping matters, but also because of the large
                    number of Americans residing in that city. The Vice Consulate would handle
                    consular matters, not the full range of consular matters, but primarily
                    applications for birth certificates and passport renewals. The Vice Consulate
                    would forward these to Bremen, where the experts could complete action on
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had no visa office?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: We had no visa office. The only consular service that we performed
                    totally in Bremerhaven were services to seamen and shipping. If there had been
                    some sort of heavy weather, or if a ship's captain for purely legal reasons
                    wanted to file a marine protest (which I learned about for the first time when I
                    got there), he would come in and swear to me that he had run into this unusual
                    weather. By doing this, if there was any damage to his ship or his cargo, he
                    could claim that it was due to the weather and not his seamanship. Also there
                    were a number of instances where seamen were problems. I can recall one instance
                    in which a MP convoy, escorted by four armed MPs, drove up with a man in
                    handcuffs. They took his handcuffs off outside and I was supposed to handle him
                    from then on. I also recall an instance, I think this occurred on January 1,
                    1950, in which a ship, which had been supposed to sail that morning, was delayed
                    because some of the crew decided to claim that it was unseaworthy. The
                    responsibility of the consul in those days was to investigate the seamen's
                    complaint. So on New Year's day I had to round up some friendly shipping experts
                    to go around, look at the complaints, and decide if they were unjustified or
                    not. The experts I had empaneled decided that the ship was as seaworthy as most
                    that came to the port, and that the seamen were just trying to prolong their
                    holiday by filing this complaint. The powers that consuls had, and may still
                    have, in such a case, include assessing costs on those who are guilty. In this
                    case I had to find that the seamen were at fault. I believe that the seamen's
                    pay was docked for the expense of the survey. This is a sample of what the Vice
                    Consulate was doing in those days.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>We also performed some political work. When I arrived in 1948, we were just
                    beginning to convince our military that the Germans were not our enemies any
                    more and were going to become allies. I think I played some small role in
                    getting the commander of the port of embarkation to pay a little more attention
                    to local German sensibilities. I believe I introduced the Oberbuergermeister of
                    Bremerhaven to the Army commander for the first time, the first social contact
                    between the Occupation Forces, as they were called, and the German political
                    authorities in Bremerhaven.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was something called “fraternization” which everyone
                        was opposed to in the military at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes. The reason for my going to Bremerhaven was that my predecessor had
                    been caught using the consular car to ferry cartons of cigarettes in a big
                    black-market deal. Black-marketing was a sore issue in our early period of
                    occupation of Germany, before we reached the status we now have.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As I recall it, cigarettes were not legal tender, but
                        illegal tender for all kinds of services. The locals often wanted to be paid
                        in cigarettes rather than cash.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: That is true. Before the so-called Wahrungs reform (the currency reform
                    of June 22, 1948), you could buy practically nothing with the old reichsmark.
                    Cigarettes were the kind of currency. While I did not engage in it, using
                    cigarettes for purchasing was practiced widely.</p>
                <p>I went on my home leave early in June 1948. I was actually out of Germany when
                    the currency reform took place. I attended the summer session at the University
                    of Colorado in Boulder that summer. When I came back in September of 1948, I was
                    amazed at what a change the introduction of a stable currency had made. The
                    German economy was beginning to take off. You could buy things with the new
                    currency.</p>
                <p>It was while I was on home leave, on the ship on the way home, that I met my
                    future wife. She came back to Europe so we could marry in Paris in January,
                    1949. To be married in Germany would have required my getting permission from
                    General Clay, the Military Governor of Germany in 1949. The military had set up
                    very complicated procedures to discourage GIs from getting married to frauleins.
                    I would have to comply with this very discouraging process, and it did not sound
                    very romantic. I decided that would be too much hassle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there legal complications in Paris? Or were they
                        relatively easy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: We had advice from an American lawyer in Paris as to how we could get
                    around the requirement that one party to a French marriage had to have resided
                    in France for at least thirty days. My passport showed I had been in France five
                    days, and my wife's passport showed she had been in France four days. But it was
                    easy enough with a carton of cigarettes to convince the concierge at our hotel
                    that she had actually been living there for thirty days. His certificate to this
                    effect was good enough for us to get married on. I don't necessarily recommend
                    this procedure to others, but I thought it was appropriate for those days. And
                    it has been a very successful marriage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your relation with the Consul General in Bremen
                        and did he have much influence on you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: The Consul General in Bremen in those days was Mr. Maurice Altaffer. He
                    was very conscious of the fact that the Vice Consulate in Bremerhaven was part
                    of his fiefdom. I went down to headquarters once a week, generally on Wednesday.
                    I would take down the passport applications, the birth certificate applications,
                    whatever, received during the preceding week and leave them there for experts to
                    process. I would confer with the experts on matters of interest. From time to
                    time, the Consul General would deign to see me. I must say that when on January
                    1, 1950 a ship's crew decided their ship was unseaworthy, and I chose to handle
                    the problem on New Year's Day using strictly Bremerhaven resources and not call
                    on the experts in Bremen, I got in a bit of hot water. I think the Bremen people
                    thought I was taking too much liberty with the long tether I was kept on. But it
                    turned out all right. During the time I was in Bremerhaven, I sometimes
                    questioned the utility of keeping the post. Only forty-two kilometers separated
                    the Vice Consulate and the Consulate General. When the Vice Consulate in
                    Bremerhaven was closed, it was found to be not all that necessary after all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you moved down to Vienna, where I first saw you. Was
                        that a routine transfer, or was it somewhat different? Sometimes how one is
                        moved about can be interesting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: No, I had spent three and a quarter years assigned to Bremerhaven. It
                    was time to leave. The Department gave me home leave and transfer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this time you were a full-fledged FSO?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: While I was still in Bremen, I took the Foreign Service exam. It was a
                    three day exam. I was very grateful in the fact that in those days, language
                    ability was deemed important. While I was somewhat shaky in some areas,
                    particularly in economics, I really clobbered the German part of the examination
                    and passed with a 77.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had been out by yourself dealing with Germans all
                        day.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: My German was very good. I had studied German in the university. I think
                    I got 97 in the German part and this was enough to bring my overall written
                    score up to 77. This was well above the passing level of 70, but I do think the
                    German part did a lot to raise my average. I was not sworn in as an FSO until
                    Vienna. I passed the oral exam during my home leave, between Bremerhaven and
                    Austria. The oral exam was given in the old Walker-Johnson building, now torn
                    down, which was where Personnel was. I remember that the chairman of my panel
                    was the author, Louis Halle. In those days, orals did not include in-basket
                    tests, or all those sorts of things they do today. A panel of three people
                    interviewed you. The panel had a chance to go over your file beforehand. I
                    assumed they were favorably disposed to my candidacy, as they asked me questions
                    that I could logically be supposed to know the answers to. I thought I did
                    pretty well, and before I left the building, Halle told me I had passed. By the
                    time I got to Vienna, the paperwork had gone through, and I was sworn in as a
                    proper FSO then.</p>
                <p>I was in what now would be called the consular cone, although they did not have
                    cones in those days. I had been assigned to two consulates and while I was now
                    in an embassy I was in the consular section of the embassy. I was specifically
                    officer in charge of the visa part of the consular section. The supervising
                    consul then was Bill Affeld, an officer I very much admired who did a lot to
                    steer me out of trouble in Vienna. Vienna was beginning, in those days, to be
                    part of the exodus route for refugees from Eastern Europe. A Refugee Relief
                    Program was established there, primarily, I guess, to get around what was seen
                    in Washington as the slow-moving pace of normal consular work. We performed a
                    full range of consular activities. Vienna was an exciting place to be in in
                    those days. The inner city of Vienna was still under Four- Power occupation,
                    with a different one of the Four Powers assuming control every month. There were
                    appropriate military ceremonies, bands, the hoisting and lowering of flags,
                    parades and so forth. Vienna was the center for spy activities in those days,
                    the Third Man film came out, and it was really an exciting place. Plus, Vienna
                    is one of the most charming cities, I think, to be assigned to. It was still
                    suffering from the collapse of the Hapsburg Empire, a city without a real
                    mission in those days. Being behind the Soviet lines, tourism had not really
                    developed. You could still get a seat at the opera for a dollar. I remember at
                    the Rathauskeller, run by a fellow with the name of Otto Kaserer. So his
                    initials were “OK” and one could get an “OK” steak dinner for one dollar, 26
                    schillings, which is what the dollar bought in those days. A delightful place to
                    be. Of course, don't try to go there today and try to get a dinner for a dollar.
                    We went back to Vienna several times since then, and we know how it has changed—
                    still a delightful city, however.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You stayed until the end of 1953.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: Before we left, I was reminded of some of the work I had done in
                    Bremerhaven regarding shipping. I was brought back to the U.S., at the expense
                    of the Justice Department, to appear as a witness at a trial in the Federal
                    Court House in Alexandria, Virginia. Some surplus merchant ships had been sold,
                    and the law required that these merchant ships be sold to American companies. It
                    was alleged in this trial that foreign companies hiding behind American dummies
                    has purchased some of these ships. It so happened that one of these allegedly
                    foreign-controlled ships put into Bremerhaven during my time and there had some
                    crew trouble. I had written what was called a despatch in those days reporting
                    the crew trouble. When the Justice Department was researching how to make a
                    case, they came across this despatch and decided that I would make a fine
                    witness to put on the stand. The Court House in Alexandria was not air
                    conditioned, and this trial was in July. The judge and jury, the Justice
                    Department feared, might have a tendency to doze off in the afternoon if the
                    testimony were dull. I was kept as their surprise witness to be used if it
                    looked like the judge was dozing. This was perhaps the only time that any of my
                    reporting work in the Foreign Service had any impact. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>Sure enough, I was put on the witness stand when they thought the judge was
                    dozing. The defense lawyer, as I recall, got up and said, “I object to all this
                    hearsay testimony”. I was able to beat him down, saying that I had been on the
                    ship, I had seen the ship's articles under which this foreign crew had been
                    signed on, etc. Later on the Justice people told me I had been a very valuable
                    witness. It does show the untold consequences of something you write, sometimes
                    it may mean something.</p>
                <p>We did leave Vienna in September 1953. Again, I must have been in the consular
                    cone, as I was to be the number two consular officer in our Consulate General in
                    Edinburgh. It was a two man post. I might note that Edinburgh was my fourth
                    Foreign Service post, and I was going to a slot that could be performed by
                    someone who was brand-new. The Consul General there was a very kindly man who
                    would have just loved to have a neophyte to educate. Edinburgh had never been on
                    my April Fool's wish list, but one did not think then of challenging an
                    assignment, you did what you were told.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>I drove my car from Vienna to Edinburgh, and the family flew out later for what
                    we thought would be a relatively long assignment. But it turned out not to be
                    nearly that long. It was a delightful place to be. I had Scottish ancestry. My
                    names are Robert Bruce and they treated me like one of them. My fondest memory,
                    I think, was of going to a celebration, at the ruined Arbroath Abbey, of the
                    anniversary of the declaration of Scottish independence. Afterwards, we all
                    repaired to a local restaurant for a proper banquet, with all the things
                    Scottish people eat and drink. Some of the speeches there were extremely fiery.
                    I thought that Scotland Yard could break in at any time and arrest the lot of us
                    for treason. This was not so far fetched. This was during the time the Stone of
                    Scone was still missing from Westminster Abbey, secreted somewhere in Scotland.
                    It turned out later our Public Affairs officer had unknowingly been the
                    custodian of the Stone of Scone for a period when Scotland Yard was looking for
                    it. Friends had foisted it on him unknowingly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He just had it in his basement or something?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: He had it in his basement, he was just storing a trunk for a friend. It
                    later turned out that the trunk had the Stone of Scone in it. We still have
                    Scottish friends from that period there, and exchange visits with them. The
                    place where we lived was a miserable Victorian house. It was advertised as
                    centrally heated because it had in a scullery a small one-pint coal burner that
                    heated a two-rail towel rack in the bathroom. This rack was the only “radiator”
                    in the house. We had fireplaces in every other room, which had been converted to
                    electric fires. The first time the guy came to read the meter, he said that we
                    must have been using electricity all the time. The next time, he found the meter
                    did not have enough capacity to keep track of all the electricity we were using
                    to keep warm. They had to put in their very largest meter. In December in our
                    hall, the temperature could get up to around 50 degrees with the heating we had.
                    But Edinburgh was a delightful place. We learned about chilblains, and eating
                    Scottish lamb. A Scottish dog bit me, but the National Health Service fixed it
                    for free. Our children got free orange juice. This was quite an experience for
                    us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In those days they had not yet discovered oil so Edinburgh
                        was not the great commercial place?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: The city had the Edinburgh festival so it was a great cultural center.
                    The city very much depended on coal, and bad coal at that. The center of the
                    city was black. Now they have gotten rid of the smoke, the city looks much
                    better.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>We had barely started our touring of Scotland when in the fall of 1954, orders
                    came transferring us to Bangkok, Thailand by way of home leave in the United
                    States. We took a ship out of Southampton to New York. A German friend from
                    Bremerhaven, who had immigrated to the United States, picked up our new car for
                    us from General Motors in New Jersey and met us at dockside in it. After going
                    through a briefing in Washington, we had driven to Kansas City, my hometown.
                    There, at Christmas time, my orders were changed again. Instead of going to
                    Thailand, we were to return to Washington after the holidays and learn Polish.
                    This perhaps reflected the fact that years ago, I had applied for Arabic
                    language training. Now they were finally getting around to giving me language
                    training, Polish. My wife and I had been looking forward to a tropical post.
                    Thailand with its palms seemed ideal. Much of our effects were on the high seas
                    between Edinburgh to Bangkok, but I persuaded my wife that this was an
                    opportunity not to be missed. Back we went to study Polish.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Service Institute in those days was in an apartment building which
                    had to be torn down later to make way for the new State Department building. I
                    had various instructors in Polish, and was really enjoying getting ready to go
                    to Poland. I was still in the consular cone, and I was to be the one man
                    consular section at the Embassy in Warsaw. This was before the Khrushchev thaw
                    had really affected Poland, although the very perceptive might have sensed it
                    coming. I went on ahead in October, 1955. My wife and three children came later,
                    staying in Berlin until our quarters could be prepared for us in Warsaw.</p>
                <p>This delay left me alone in Warsaw and prey to the UB, the Polish secret police.
                    I feel sure that the very attractive young girl who came into my office on the
                    first day I was there wanting to know if I could help her was a UB ploy. She
                    said her father in Poznan had thrown her out, that she had no place to live, and
                    couldn't I, the American consul, find some place for her? After consulting with
                    my predecessor, who was still there for overlap, I told her that the embassy had
                    no means of helping. I wonder if this was a UB effort to see if they could get
                    at a young married man in Warsaw without his wife. I thought about this again
                    when in 1961 an American FSO was compromised in Poland by a young Polish woman,
                    and convicted of passing on classified documents.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you start on consular work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: I spent about a year in Warsaw doing consular work. It was during this
                    period that it became clear that things were changing in Poland. No longer were
                    just a handful of old Poles trying to go to the United States. The floodgates
                    were opening. I had to try to convince, first the management of the post, and
                    then Washington, that a one-man consular shop was no longer adequate in Warsaw.
                    Before I left the post, I think the consular section had gotten up to four
                    officers.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>1956 was a very critical year in Europe. Most people only think of the events in
                    Hungary in 1956, but there was almost a war between Poland and the Soviet Union
                    in that year. It was the year of the riots in Poznan which led to divisions in
                    the Polish party. Nationalist Poles wanted to bring back Gromulka, who had been
                    imprisoned during the Stalinist crackdown, as party leader, but the old-line
                    Muscovite Poles were opposed to it. There was a very tense moment during the
                    party congress of that year. Khrushchev, Mikoyan and Bulganin flew in to try to
                    convince the Poles not to make Gromulka the head of the party. Even though the
                    Polish army was ostensibly commanded by a Moscow-leaning Pole, Rokosovski, the
                    Poles were able to muster enough military forces to start moving tanks around.
                    Khrushchev then backed off and decided not to intervene militarily to prevent
                    Gromulka from being made party chief.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is fascinating.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Well, I think it worth recalling one of the surprising events of the
                    time. In that near uprising, at a time when we thought Soviet tanks could cross
                    the Soviet-Polish frontier to put down this Polish rebelliousness, we sent our
                    military attach�s out to observe the frontier. The attach�s had a flat tire out
                    along the border. To the attach�s' surprise, the Polish secret police were
                    helpful, they changed the tire for them, and got them on their way as soon as
                    possible. This was a complete reversal of roles. They were the enemy usually.
                    This time they really wanted American military attach�s out observing the
                    border.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So there really was a feeling of independence there at
                        that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: I can recall the crowds of students marching through the streets of
                    Warsaw shouting, “Rokosovski do Moskvi! Rokosovski do Moskvi!” They wanted
                    Marshall Rokosovski to go back to Moscow; he was not Polish enough to have stood
                    up to the Russians in this instance. There was a period after Gromulka was in
                    power. The Russians had accepted this, not with the greatest of grace, but they
                    had accepted it. In a week, 4 or 5 ostensibly Polish generals were given medals
                    and sent off to Moscow. The Poles really cleaned house at this point. This house
                    cleaning made it possible for the Poles later on to play the leading role they
                    did in the breaking up of the Warsaw Pact. That, and of course the all-powerful
                    influence of the Catholic Church. Also the Poles had never eliminated the
                    peasantry. All these elements all played a role in giving Poland its independent
                    outlook. There are 35,000,000 or 40,000,000 Poles; none of the other Eastern
                    European nations are nearly so numerous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Polish Church has always fascinated me for they were
                        headed by a very skillful man during all of that time, or at least they
                        handled themselves very well during that period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes. The Poles are perhaps the most religious people in Europe.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Its all Catholic, no Protestants?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes. The Church throughout history had been identified with preserving
                    the Polish national spirit against Russians, and against other invaders. So the
                    Polish Church was uniquely positioned to play this role. Somehow the Polish
                    Communists decided they never wanted to tackle the Church head on the way they
                    had done in other countries. I think the abortive Polish uprising in 1956 was
                    one of the few instances in my career in the Foreign Service where I could have
                    been on the scene when history, I mean a big part of history, was being made.
                    Because of what happened later in Hungary, people tend to associate 1956 with
                    the Hungarian uprising. They often overlook how close it came to bloodshed in
                    Poland in that year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were some troubles in East Germany too, as I
                        recall.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: 1953 was the big year in East Germany</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, all of this time you were not doing consular
                        work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: After about a year, Art Wortzel came. He was supposed to go to Moscow,
                    but there was not a place for him there. So he was sent to Warsaw, took over the
                    consular section and this made it possible for me to go to what was one of the
                    more unusual jobs in an embassy. There was a joint British-American service to
                    translate the Polish press. The joint press translation service had some
                    commercial aspects to it. We tried to get money back to help meet expenses. We
                    sold subscriptions to this service to other embassies, to newspaper people, to
                    whoever would pay us money to meet some of the costs. That job was essentially
                    an early morning job. You had to get in early to get the press translated and
                    the bulletin out. This left your afternoons free, so the morning work was
                    combined with an afternoon job. This was to act as head of the German permit
                    office. West Germany was not recognized as a sovereign state then by Poland, or
                    by the other East European countries. Poland needed, as did the other countries,
                    to send certain people to West Germany, so the East European countries agreed to
                    allow Western allies to issue permits for local people who wanted to go to
                    Germany. We issued permits to Polish people going on visits or to ethnic Germans
                    being repatriated. Again, the job had unusual financial arrangements. My salary
                    continued to be paid by the U.S. taxpayer, but my staff of 15 or so Polish
                    nationals were all being paid by Bonn, as were the expenses of the office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The West Germans?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: The West Germans were paying all that. Of course all decisions were
                    being made in Bonn. Everything had to be referred to Bonn and I was simply the
                    front man.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were representing West German interests in
                        Poland.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: No negotiations were conducted by us on anything substantial, we were
                    limited to consular matters. Still this combined job of running a commercial
                    press translation service jointly with the British, and representing the Germans
                    in consular affairs there, made the job an unusual one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: About as unusual as you can think of. How big was the
                        embassy in Poland at this time? Had it been cut down to a skeleton staff as
                        we were in many other Eastern European countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes, it had a small staff. We had three people in the political section,
                    a one man consular section, we had a one man USIS section, we had an
                    agricultural attach� who had certain regional responsibilities, the ambassador
                    and DCM. On the military attach� side, the Army controlled the DAT function.
                    There was an assistant Army attach�, an Air Force attach� and a Navy man there.
                    We had the usual communicators. We did have a sizeable local staff, but the
                    Germans were paying part of them. We had our commercial earnings to pay the
                    locals working on press translations. We had a combined British-American school
                    staffed by wives, essentially. Our medical supplies were supplied by the United
                    States, and the British supplied the doctor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You probably had a fairly sizeable administrative group to
                        take care of all these disparate things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Well, we had an American administrative officer and a budget and fiscal
                    officer. One other interesting observation about our operation in Warsaw: the
                    owner of our Embassy building at that time was the Peoples' Republic of
                    Bulgaria. Between 1950 and 1960, we had no diplomatic relations with Bulgaria,
                    yet they were our landlords. The Swiss Embassy was nearby, and they represented
                    our interests with Bulgaria. Thus if we had any problems with our landlord we
                    would talk to the Swiss, who then would take up the problems with the
                    Bulgarians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were the ambassadors and DCMs when you were there and
                        did they leave any particular impression on you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: When I first arrived, Joseph E. Jacobs was our ambassador. He was, I
                    think, the most senior ambassador in the service at the time. He started, I
                    think, in 1912 as a language officer in China. He enjoyed the distinction, in my
                    eyes, of having headed our mission to Albania after the war, the only mission we
                    sent to that country. The mission had to leave when Albanian mistreatment in, I
                    think, 1948, became unbearable. Ambassador Jacobs was a very skeptical person.
                    He was, you might say, from Missouri. He was very distrustful of the Communists.
                    I think the Department in time felt that while he was a very good ambassador
                    when the Cold War was really cold, when things started to warm up, someone with
                    a different outlook was needed. We were fortunate to get as our ambassador then
                    Jake Beam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hardly a radical liberal (laughter). But a very
                        experienced, very intelligent man.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: One of the customers of the press translation service was the New York
                    Times correspondent, Sidney Gruson. I can't tell you that date, but in 1957 or
                    1958 he wrote the embassy was still in its bombshelter after the all-clear had
                    been sounded. Maybe as a result of this article, the Department decided that it
                    was time for a new ambassador to be sent out for a fresh approach. The DCM, when
                    I first arrived there, was Fred Exner. He was there for a while, then Willard
                    Barber came in. He was a Latin American expert. Warsaw was his first experience
                    in Europe in a Communist country. Before I left, there was another DCM change.
                    Frank Siscoe, an ex-FBI official, came in as DCM.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any final thoughts on Poland before we move on
                        to Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: No, Warsaw was a pleasant experience overall. I don't think I was
                    unusual in feeling a strong attachment to the Polish people, and how difficult
                    has been the role they have played in history. We actually wanted to stay in
                    Poland a little longer, but the Department was fearful, in those days, of
                    keeping people too long in hardship posts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Particularly Eastern European ones.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: So I was transferred to Washington in February, 1958. An officer who had
                    left the post before me had said, “Is there anything that you would like me to
                    try to line up for you in Washington?” This was Richard Earle Johnson. I said,
                    “Well, they are starting this exchange program under the Lacey-Zarubin Agreement
                    of February 1958.” Bill Lacey was the American negotiator and Ambassador Zarubin
                    was the Soviet negotiator. They signed this first exchange agreement between the
                    United States and the Soviet Union. There was a provision in the immigration law
                    banning the issuing of visas to Communists, so there were many new procedures to
                    work out while this went on. The agreement reflected a relaxation under
                    Khrushchev of tensions in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe. So the exchange
                    program was where I ended up in Washington in mid-1958.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your boss there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Bill Lacey was our spiritual mentor, he was listed as an advisor to the
                    Secretary. The actual bureaucracy running the program was placed in the Bureau
                    of Public Affairs. The particular office I was assigned to was called the Office
                    of East- West Contacts in the Bureau of Public Affairs—P. The head of the office
                    was Freddy Merrill.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was an Eastern European hand.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes, he and Bill Lacey were the same expansive type: “Don't bother me
                    too much with details, I'm a broad picture man.” But that was the sort of
                    vision, I think, needed for that kind of operation. Our office was set up in the
                    ground office of an apartment building at 1500 Massachusetts Avenue. We were
                    close to the Soviet embassy, and they would come around to see us frequently.
                    For someone who did not know much about bureaucracy in Washington, getting his
                    first taste of it in this assignment, was perhaps as good an assignment as
                    possible. We had to coordinate activities of the whole government vis-a-vis the
                    Soviet Union in respect to these exchanges. This meant that we dealt with many
                    different departments, and got a broad view of how those departments worked and
                    what their foibles were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find this at first to be pretty frustrating to be
                        in the bureaucracy after so many years of being relatively your own
                        boss?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes. One could not just write a message and expect to send it out.
                    Messages had to be coordinated everywhere, particularly in this sort of activity
                    where all sorts of agencies believed that they had an interest at stake. A
                    message had to be coordinated and rewritten. This was quite educational in that
                    regard. One of the things that I recall most clearly from this period was when
                    we brought over a delegation of Polish political leaders in the fall of '58.
                    Because I was just back from Poland and spoke Polish, I was tapped to be their
                    escort, to go across the country with them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was interesting and checked your language out
                        too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes. Also it was to give me the first opportunity to assess the premise
                    behind this program, namely that if we bring the Commies over and show them how
                    nice it is in the United States, they will go back home as different people. So,
                    this was my opportunity to see at first hand the immediate impact of America on
                    people brought up in alien cultures, who knew nothing about the United States,
                    and had been fed the Communist propaganda view of the United States all
                    along.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel that this premise was a solid one, did it
                        work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: I felt that indeed there is merit in the premise. True, they came here
                    under tight discipline. Bolislaw Jaschew, the head of the Polish delegation, was
                    a dyed-in-the-wool Communist, according to his biography. But even in his case,
                    I felt that we were making an impression. We had arrangements with Department of
                    State contractors in those days to line up meetings that would make this kind of
                    impact. I particularly remember we were booked into Garden City, Kansas because
                    also in the group were people representing the so-called Peasant Party of
                    Poland. The generosity and open-heartedness of the people of Garden City...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I must say that over the years they have built up a
                        tremendous corps of people all over this country who have given unstinting
                        help on these things, it is quite fascinating. What other problems did you
                        tackle?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: In the exchanges program there was a lot of paper shuffling,
                    particularly to get a waiver for every Communist to come in, the waiver of the
                    visa exclusion. Procedures had to be developed for that. We had to have liaison
                    with the security people to be sure that we were not taking Communist agents to
                    places where they could see the combination to Fort Knox, or that sort of thing.
                    But a big problem was also that we were running this on a shoestring. We were
                    depending on private enterprise wanting to conduct exchanges at their own
                    expense. In those days this was not too much of a problem. Many people
                    instinctively felt the exchanges were a good program to break down some of the
                    hostility, and they wanted to do their share. When, however, technical exchanges
                    were concerned, then questions of proprietary information and so forth would
                    come in. The Department of Commerce was concerned: “Was this a way to get around
                    our export licenses?”</p>
                <p>I would say that the biggest problem was simply how to get around the
                    bureaucracy. It was fascinating to get to meet so many of the people brought
                    over. I can recall entertaining Russian doctors, including some who had been
                    targeted by Stalin in his Jewish doctors' plot. They were in Washington on a
                    Mother's Day or some other holiday. Nobody else would take time away from
                    honoring their wife or mother to entertain these Russian doctors, so I persuaded
                    my wife to take them on. That turned out to be a good experience. The doctors
                    were all very nice, and were willing to talk about “the doctors' plot” and so
                    forth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were willing to talk about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes, Stalin was dead; Khrushchev was in power, and a new era had
                    arrived.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now this job lasted through the end of the Eisenhower
                        Administration. About the time Mr. Kennedy took office, or soon thereafter,
                        did the program change anyway after the change of administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: No, it still continued. After the breakdown of the Paris summit, after
                    the U-2 episode in May of 1960, things were perceived as being different, but
                    the change between the Eisenhower and Kennedy administrations did not mean much
                    for exchanges. I certainly do not recall any difference. I left the program in
                    the summer of '61, the Department giving me an academic year off. I would no
                    longer have to tell people I was a graduate of physics; after this year I was
                    able to say I had a master's in political science. I had made myself legitimate,
                    so to speak.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was out at Indiana, which in those days was the
                        school for Eastern Europe and also, somewhat, for Africa.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: They were known, in addition to their Soviet and Eastern European
                    studies program, for real politique studies. Africa, I'm not too sure about. I
                    was given a choice of either Columbia or Indiana when I was tapped for the
                    academic year. Since I don't like New York City, I had not the slightest
                    hesitation in opting for Indiana. We really enjoyed the year, not just myself
                    academically, but also the whole family. Bloomington was a nice community.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any outstanding highlights of that year or
                        contacts that you made?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Well, Bob Burns was the head of the Soviet and Eastern European
                    Institute at the time. He was an old RFB hand. I had as my advisor one of the
                    Czechoslovak Benes; he may have been a nephew of Jan Benes. We had on the
                    faculty at that time Robert C. Tucker, who later moved to Princeton. As it
                    turned out, we had both gone to the same high school in Kansas City. He had been
                    a few years ahead of me so I had not known him. Bob Tucker had been assigned to
                    the embassy in Moscow. He had married a Russian girl and ultimately was able to
                    bring her entire family over. We got to know his Russian-born wife well and
                    mamoush, the grandmother.</p>
                <p>And this all became so relevant for us when we were assigned to the Soviet Union
                    some 18 years later. At the time I was at Indiana, I wrote a thesis, based on my
                    Polish experience, on the German-Polish frontier. Today everyone accepts the
                    Oder-Neisse line. Back in 1961, the Line was not nearly an accepted boundary. I
                    assumed that I was going to be assigned from Bloomington to Belgrade where I
                    would run into Richard Earle Johnson again. He was then in Belgrade as a
                    political officer. But as so often happens in the Foreign Service, near the end
                    of my academic year, there was a PNG action [persona non grata], as a result of
                    which I was moved to Sofia. I was very disappointed at first. Belgrade was a
                    bigger post and Yugoslavia was not a hard-line Communist state, whereas Bulgaria
                    was one of the most rigid of the Warsaw Pact states. If people caught cold in
                    Moscow, Bulgarians would sneeze in Sofia, and that sort of thing. But Sofia
                    turned out to be a good assignment, we got there in July of 1962.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it still a legation then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: It was a legation. Our minister was Mrs. Eugenie Anderson, a big figure
                    on the Democratic National Committee from Minnesota, who had been Truman's
                    ambassador in Denmark. She was quite a savvy person, very much public affairs
                    oriented. She had been the supporter of Hubert Humphrey rather than John
                    Kennedy. If she had been the supporter of Kennedy she might have gotten an
                    embassy other than Sofia. She did have good relations with Averell Harriman,
                    another Democratic stalwart. Thanks to her connections with Averell Harriman, we
                    were able to get the Department to pay for leasing the famous Borovets villa,
                    which everyone who served in Bulgaria subsequently has profited from.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the Harriman connection, the money?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes. Funding is something we would not have gotten otherwise, without
                    the use of her political connections and Harriman's weight in getting that into
                    the budget. There are other posts in the world perhaps more deserving of a
                    recreation place than Sofia, but we got the money through Eugenie's good
                    connections. The previous minister, Eddie Page, had tried but without success. I
                    was Bulgaria during the Cuban missile crisis which started for real on October
                    22, 1962.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was in Budapest at the time, and I know that it was
                        quite an experience for us, how was it for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: The local reaction was one of great fear and caution. Our DCM, Charlie
                    Stephen, was out of the country at the time, so I was acting DCM. I don't think
                    the Bulgarians ever believed they were going to be the number one target. But we
                    came very close to nuclear war, and I am sure they realized how close it was. My
                    wife, our youngest daughter and I happened to be held at gunpoint for about
                    twenty minutes during the height of the crisis. I had taken the wife and child
                    out to show them what I thought was a quick and easy way to drive to Belgrade in
                    case the need arose. We were in a part of Sofia I had never been in before. The
                    place was not on the main road to Belgrade, and was not shaping up to what I
                    thought it should be. I stopped along the road and pulled out a map to see where
                    I was. Unbeknownst to me, the stretch of road where I had stopped was marked by
                    two no stopping signs separated by a couple of kilometers. Unless you happen to
                    see the beginning sign, you don't know the ban had started, and if you don't see
                    the ending sign, you don't know the ban had stopped. Where we stopped happened
                    to be along the road nearest to the main radar control site for the air defenses
                    of Sofia. The Bulgarians were sure I was there with nefarious purposes in mind.
                    They were out there holding us at gunpoint and interviewing me to see what my
                    story was. I showed them my map and told them I was trying to get the road to
                    Belgrade. They said, “No, you're not, you are out here in connection with your
                    friends.” I said, “No, I am out here only with my wife and daughter.” The secret
                    police were then trailing our military attach�s on their way at that moment to
                    observe the radar site, and there I was. Probably I went down as suspicious in
                    the books of the secret police at that time. I was officially the head of the
                    Embassy political section, but I was probably marked thereafter as somehow being
                    connected with spying operations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was right during the crisis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Right during the crisis.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had somewhat similar things in Budapest during those
                        days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Our being in the area was completely innocent. I did not know where the
                    main radar site was, I had not seen the no parking sign, and I was lost.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Didn't they name the chief villain in their favorite spy
                        movie after you later on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Later on, there was an incident when a spy, an undercover Bulgarian
                    allegedly recruited by the CIA, was caught. The Bulgarian security service was
                    trying to establish a link between this spy whom they had and the legation. They
                    captured the spy's radio transmitter and radio schedule. He was supposed to be
                    heard by a listening post in Greece if he had any serious information to impart.
                    The Bulgarians tried to use this radio communication link to set up a meeting
                    with the spy on the main street in Sofia, to be attended by someone in the
                    legation. Well as it came out later in some newspaper article, at the very hour
                    of the assigned meeting and on the street corner where this fellow was waiting
                    and was supposed to be picked up, I walked past him just as I did every evening
                    on my way home. Several other people in the legation who lived east of the
                    chancery went past that same corner too on that evening, it was the natural way
                    to go. Again their suspicions must have been aroused, “What was this guy Houston
                    up to?” The worst thing was that in press articles later, they did not describe
                    me by name. They just said that a short time after one legation officer went by,
                    smartly dressed, another legation staff member “in a cap and a crumpled
                    raincoat” came walking by, trying to disguise himself. Well, my raincoat was
                    crumpled and I did wear a cap, so I was sure they were talking about me. Later,
                    in talking about this with John Anderson, the husband of Minister Anderson, he
                    said, “You think that was you, I'm sure it was me.” So it is a matter of dispute
                    who the guy in the cap and the crumpled raincoat was whom Bulgarians thought was
                    trying to meet the alleged spy that evening.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was John Anderson living there all the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: He was an artist who became a Foreign Service dependent and adjusted to
                    this status quite well. The only other important incident in that first tour in
                    Bulgaria was the Kennedy assassination, November 23, 1963. Eugenie Anderson
                    wanted to have some sort of public commemoration. She was always very sensitive
                    to the public relations aspect. She arranged with the local Catholic Church to
                    have a memorial mass. She invited members of the Bulgarian government to come,
                    and the chiefs of diplomatic missions. The Protocol Office sent some low-ranking
                    officer, that was the only Bulgarian Government recognition of the Kennedy
                    death. They were very much atheists, and if they would go to any church, it
                    would not be a Catholic Church, but an Orthodox Church. The only Communist
                    ambassador to show up at the mass was the Romanian. He was a good Communist and
                    would not go inside the church door. He simply stood outside during the service
                    and made sure that we knew that he had come. In retrospect, this was the first
                    sign of Romanian deviation I can recall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was when it was just beginning. You got the usual two
                        year treatment and then back to what looks like something that you were
                        doing before.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: I came back from Sofia to the same organization I had left in 1961. It
                    was now in the Bureau of European Affairs. We had offices in the main State
                    Department building. Our DCM from Warsaw, Frank Siscoe, was now running it, and
                    ran it for quite a few years. I guess my assignment indicates that the
                    Department really did not know what to do with me. They certainly did not follow
                    their rotational policy very well with me. I had two tours in the cultural
                    exchanges business, just as I had two tours in Bulgaria and two with BEX. I
                    don't think many people have such double tours in the Foreign Service now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get along with learning three Slavic
                        languages? Did you get them confused?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: It is very difficult to distinguish between them. I must admit that
                    learning Bulgarian was facilitated by knowing Polish. During that summer in 1948
                    that I spent in Colorado, I studied Russian. That may have helped my Polish
                    later. Bulgarian is the easiest Slavic language, since the nouns and adjectives
                    don't decline. I got my test score in Bulgarian, I was 4+. Whereas my Russian
                    was only 3+ and Polish was 4 when I finished FSI.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any extensive report on your European exchange
                        job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: I think the exchanges assignments laid the groundwork for my later
                    appearance in Moscow as Counselor for Science and Technology. Normally you have
                    to do an apprenticeship in Soviet Affairs before you can get a Counselor rank in
                    Moscow. I think this is one factor that stood me in good stead when I finally
                    did go to Moscow.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>The job of Albanian/Bulgarian desk officer, which was just down the hall from the
                    Exchanges office, was useful to me later on. When Woodie White left that desk
                    officer job in the middle of 1966, I grabbed it. I was well qualified on the
                    basis of my time in Bulgaria, of course. The job gave me time to learn a little
                    more about Albania. I recalled my conversation with Ambassador Joe Jacobs in
                    Warsaw, and with his secretary there, who had also been with him in Albania.
                    Albania seemed like a quaint little country. Ultimately I hoped to be assigned
                    there. Now that I am retired there are signs that U.S.-Albanian relations might
                    be restored. Curtis Kamman is reported as having discussed this very subject
                    with the Albanian representative recently at the UN. I can't say that much went
                    on in Bulgaria or Albania when I was on the desk. I was called recently as a
                    possible witness at an espionage trial in New York of a Bulgarian trade
                    representative, because of conversations I as desk officer had had with
                    Bulgarian officials. I was never put on the stand. The U.S. and Bulgarians had
                    agreed that the Bulgarians could have a commercial office in New York. The
                    question arose as to whether persons assigned to that commercial office were
                    entitled to full diplomatic immunity or not. I had conversations during my time
                    on the desk with the DCM at the Bulgarian embassy on this very subject. But
                    other than that, I can't think of anything I did that will go down in the
                    history books. Certainly there was no movement to restore relations with Albania
                    at that time, relations were completely frozen.</p>
                <p>At the end of 1968, I was transferred briefly to Vancouver, Canada, ostensibly to
                    replace the number two man there. Although I outranked him, he arranged with the
                    Embassy in Ottawa to stay on, with me as his deputy. This was not satisfactory
                    to me; my assignment was shortly thereafter broken.</p>
                <p>I came back to Washington to work in something called the Substantive Information
                    Systems Staff. This was the Department's commitment at the time to try to
                    computerize its information handling, a very initial effort. We envisaged some
                    very wild blue yonder types of projects. Our boss was particularly keen on
                    having a system in which Department officers told the information managers the
                    kinds of information they were interested in. Thereafter, the distribution of
                    messages in the Department would be done by computer strictly according to those
                    profiles. If you did not get a message, it was because you did not ask for it in
                    your profile. As a Foreign Service Officer, I tried to add a little common sense
                    and Foreign Service background to what the wild blue yonder boys were dreaming.
                    I was never enamored with computer distribution of messages as much as
                    perfecting the retrieval process so that if you wanted a historical document,
                    you could get it quickly rather than search around, perhaps in vain, to find it.
                    I am afraid that all that came out of the effort was the introduction of the
                    TAGS system, or putting codes on all telegrams, airgrams and so forth which came
                    in, to aid in retrieving messages.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is hard to think at this time that the computer as such
                        did not exist, at least in the substantive parts of the Department, there
                        was certainly no Apples, Wangs.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: There was considerable resistance, I think, to the idea, and that is
                    why, perhaps, the project I worked on, which had such wild blue yonder ideas of
                    automatic distribution of messages according to user profiles, was never
                    adopted. The Department managers were willing to go along with introducing the
                    TAGS coding system. After all, the old-fashioned way was putting a file number
                    on a message and putting it in a folder. TAGS coding really was not that much
                    different.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I actually served myself on some kind of committee at that
                        time that met periodically and heard reports on the computer progress.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>We have come back to the great occasion when you and I got together to do
                    something.</p>
                <p>HOUSTON: This came about when Jack McSweeney, the first person to be elevated
                    from minister to Bulgaria to ambassador to Bulgaria, was looking for a new DCM.
                    Richard G. Johnson, who had been together with me, Richard E. Johnson and
                    Waldemar M. Johnson in Warsaw, was leaving as McSweeney's DCM in Sofia.
                    McSweeney, to whom I will always be grateful, remembered the assistance I as
                    desk officer gave him when he was first going out as minister to Bulgaria. I was
                    delighted. While I liked the computer job, I really did not feel it was vital,
                    and so I jumped at this chance to go back to Bulgaria. Richard G. Johnson had to
                    be back in the U.S. for graduation of a child at the beginning of June of 1970.
                    In May 1970 I went out for an overlap with him. Between the time Jack McSweeney
                    asked me to be his DCM and the time I got there, the Department had changed
                    their plans for Jack. He now was not to stay on long after I arrived. The
                    Department had Ambassador Horace G. Torbert in mind to go out to replace
                    McSweeney, but Ambassador Torbert was busy tending the shop in Congressional
                    Relations. It was not certain when he could be sprung. So just a few weeks after
                    my arrival in Sofia, I became charge. The charg�ship lasted until Ambassador
                    Torbert arrived in early October. This is the time when I most appreciated the
                    idea of being thoroughly prepared before going to a post. Having served two
                    years, 1962- 64, as head of the political section in Sofia and then two years as
                    Bulgarian desk officer, I had, perhaps for the first time, really adequate
                    preparation for my Foreign Service job. Language and everything.</p>
                <p>We did not have the problem of young children, this time, to educate. It was my
                    first DCMship, we had better living conditions. My second tour to Bulgaria, was
                    the most delightful, I think in retrospect, of all my Foreign Service
                    assignments. And particularly so because Ambassador Torbert, when he arrived,
                    proved to be a very fine boss.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [Laughter] We should strike that. [N.B.: The interviewer
                        is Ambassador Torbert] What kind of problems did you have? Communist
                        countries have a tendency to test people out fairly early when they think
                        they may be vulnerable. Did you have any problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: No. The whole time in Bulgaria was a very pleasant one. As I recall, you
                    arrived after the Plovdiv fair. I thus had to escort personally the Communist
                    Party boss, Todor Zhivkov, through the Plovdiv fair and explain things to him.
                    Things went well there. We had a few minor problems, but nothing like the test
                    of fire Eugenie Anderson was given on her first year of the Plovdiv fair. Then
                    the Bulgarians seized our fair brochure and were not going to allow us to
                    distribute it. She stood them down. Generally U.S.-Bulgarian relations at the
                    time were on the upswing, not very far up, but the direction was right. A man
                    now important in Bulgarian affairs, Prime Minister Andrey Lukanov, appeared as a
                    vice minister of foreign trade in those days, the first real new- thinking man
                    in the Bulgarian leadership.</p>
                <p>We had the beautiful dacha in the mountains to repair to. I just remember this
                    period as a very pleasant time. No Cuban missile crisis, no presidents
                    assassinated. True, we were frustrated in our long-standing wish to get out of
                    the chancery that we had in Sofia. The chancery was surrounded on all sides,
                    except the street side, by Bulgarian buildings, a security officer's nightmare.
                    It was also a fire trap. We made absolutely no progress on that front. I just
                    don't recall any particular problems, it all goes down as a rosy glow in my
                    memory.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you did a lot of good work there and one of the
                        things you did towards the end was to negotiate, finally, a consular
                        agreement. Do you want to talk about the history of that? It did not
                        revolutionize things, but it was the only agreement that was signed over
                        many years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Well, to say that we negotiated the consular agreement is an
                    exaggeration. A lawyer came out, an expert from LT (Treaty and Legal Division,
                    office of the Legal Advisor), who really did the negotiating. The agreement had
                    been under negotiation for a long time. Bulgaria fell in line on a consular
                    convention after other countries, including the Soviet Union, had negotiated an
                    agreement. The Bulgarian agreement did provide, at least on paper, assurance
                    that we would be promptly notified if American citizens got into trouble. We had
                    another agreement not so formal perhaps, to cooperate with the Bulgarians in
                    combating narcotics. Much of what was done under the agreement is classified,
                    but we did always consider the narcotics agreement a mark of how U.S.-Bulgarian
                    relations were improving. Later on, the assassination attempt against the Pope
                    occurred, and there were all sorts of charges of Bulgarian government agents
                    cooperating with Turkish drug smugglers, setting up Mohamad Agca, who was
                    responsible for the assassination attempt, etc. I could not help but think then
                    that maybe the cooperation between the United States and Bulgaria was really
                    designed, in Bulgarian eyes, to give Bulgarian security authorities a better
                    view of how much we knew about drug smuggling in and through Bulgaria. Then they
                    could devise better ways to smuggle drugs through Bulgaria without our knowing
                    it. But this is the way one becomes after years of service in Eastern Europe, I
                    suppose, suspicious of everything.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>One curious thing that came out when it was time for me to leave Bulgaria.
                    Ambassador Torbert had decided he wanted to retire, I believe, in January 1973.
                    I know you had some problems convincing the Department that it was your wish to
                    retire. You had to send in two letters of resignation before they would believe
                    it. In any case, the Department was not ready to name a new envoy when
                    Ambassador Torbert retired. Perhaps there was some struggle going on. Kissinger
                    may have been struggling with various career people as to who would take over
                    the embassy in Sofia. I was left as charge. It was clear that since I had
                    completed over three years there by May of 1973, I could not be left there. As
                    they did not have a new ambassador ready to be named, they simply named a new
                    charge. The new charge was Helene Batjer, an old Eastern European hand, who was
                    now, perhaps belatedly, being recognized as the valuable officer that she was.
                    But instead of having her designated as charge from Washington, as legally
                    should have been done, she was sent out with no special accreditation. I was
                    ordered to turn the embassy over to her two weeks after she arrived, and then
                    leave. So it fell to me as charge to inform the Bulgarian government that I was
                    leaving the embassy in the hands of Helene Batjer as charge. I think the Vienna
                    Convention prevents that sort of thing. In any case, the Bulgarians challenged
                    this. I think Bulgarian amour propre was offended by the idea that we were
                    leaving the important Sofia mission without an ambassador for an extended period
                    of time. Helene Batjer, I am told, ultimately had to be designated as charge
                    from Washington. Finally a new ambassador, Martin Herz, was sent out. This is a
                    technical point, and I must admit that I have not done a lot of research on it.
                    I do know that Helene Batjer's credentials were challenged because they came
                    from me rather than from Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the fascinating things that happened at that time
                        was the death of the Foreign Minister and the emergence of a new Foreign
                        Minister who became quite famous. I know that you made quite a study of it
                        and I wonder if you could tell about what we knew about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: I am not sure that anyone outside Bulgaria knows the truth. Bulgaria had
                    a very popular Foreign Minister, Ivan Bashev, at the time. A relatively young
                    man, and relatively more flexible than many in the Communist government at the
                    time. He was an athletic skier. Periodically he would go skiing on Mount
                    Vitosha. One time he disappeared in a snow storm not very far from a ski lodge
                    up there. The story put out was that he had gotten confused in this snow storm,
                    and froze to death up on the mountain. He was buried as a hero. Unofficially, it
                    was rumored that he was a man in trouble with the hardliners, and that he may
                    have been so driven into a corner by these hardliners. The rumor was that he
                    took his own life. That is theory number one. Theory number two, which is far
                    less accepted, is that he was done away with because he had become inconvenient
                    to the party boss. Zhivkov was overthrown in December '89, one of the last East
                    European hardliners to go. Subsequently he has been accused of all sorts of
                    nefarious deeds. Bashev's replacement was Peter Mladenov. Far from being a trim
                    and athletic figure like Bashev, Mladenov was a rotund man who became even more
                    rotund. In his role of Foreign Minister, he had to play the role of a liberal,
                    or quasi-liberal. He is now acting as a reform Communist, hoping that the
                    Bulgarian Communist Party in its new reform image will continue to play an
                    important role, although no longer a constitutionally guaranteed leading role,
                    in Bulgaria. The forthcoming elections will tell if he has been successful in
                    that regard. But cause of the death of Ivan Bashev under mysterious
                    circumstances in the storm on Mt. Vitosha, as far as I know, is still
                    unknown.</p>
                <p>When I left Bulgaria in September of 1973, I was told by Walt Stoessel that the
                    Department had something good in mind for me. They could not tell me just yet
                    what it would be, but in the meantime I would be assigned as an European expert
                    with the U.S. delegation to the Twenty-Eighth General Assembly meeting later in
                    September in New York. I never really thought highly of multi- lateral
                    diplomacy, having been brought up in bilateral diplomacy. I did profit,
                    educationally, from having this exposure to multi- lateral diplomacy as
                    practiced at the UN. My principal work assignment there was to lobby European
                    countries, usually the European neutrals, to support U.S. positions. And also to
                    report what they had to say. One of the more unusual things that I remember
                    doing was going out to Washington Heights to escort Henry Kissinger's parents to
                    the General Assembly session in which he made his first appearance as Secretary
                    of State. They were delightful people, and I was happy to do it. I was also
                    seated, at one time, in one of the U.S. seats on the floor behind Henry
                    Kissinger when the two German states were admitted as UN members. The two
                    Germanys had been blocked because the East did not want to recognize West
                    Germany and the West did not want to accept East Germany. But by 1973, an
                    agreement had been worked out that the two Germanys would be admitted as
                    sovereign states. I was behind Henry Kissinger when Willy Brandt got up to
                    deliver the speech for West Germany. Henry Kissinger put on earphones so he
                    could listen to him in English; I was proud that I could listen to him in German
                    without the earphones.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>Another interesting moment from that session: The U.S. and Soviet UN delegations
                    and permanent reps had a tradition that they would meet before a new session got
                    underway, to talk to each other and warn each other about anything they were
                    planning to bring up. The idea that we were trying to catch each other by
                    surprise had gone by the boards. As an European expert, I was present when Jacob
                    Malik came in to meet John Scali, who was the U.S. permanent representative.
                    This was an interesting session. By no means did they tell us all that they
                    eventually brought up in the session, but the Soviets went through the motions,
                    at least, of big power comity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is your view of the function of the UN General
                        Assembly and Council?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Well, I am glad you asked this question. The UN is a very extensive
                    operation. Fortunately it does have a Security Council where the really serious
                    war and peace issues are discussed. I say fortunately, because as we look at
                    Europe now, we wonder what is going to be the future security system in Europe.
                    NATO, which is premised on the West having a permanent enemy in the Warsaw Pact,
                    may have a limited future. What is going now is the Conference on Security and
                    Cooperation in Europe, CSCE. It operates on a basis even worse than the General
                    Assembly. CSCE operates on absolute consensus, as was so clearly illustrated in
                    the period leading up to the convening of the Helsinki Final Act of July and
                    August 1975. Then Malta for months prevented an agreement by holding out for
                    special provisions concerning the Mediterranean. Many people are suggesting that
                    NATO will have to go, that we will have to rely on the CSCE to preserve the
                    future security of Europe. If you think the rules for the General Assembly in
                    New York are bad, imagine a situation where Malta or Albania, which may join
                    shortly, will have a veto. How can you really trust the security of Europe to an
                    organization like that?</p>
                <p>Going back to the General Assembly of 1973, I met there my future ambassador in
                    Helsinki, Marc Austad, who was a U.S. public delegate to the General Assembly
                    that year. I also encountered the Finnish attitude towards neutrality for the
                    first time.</p>
                <p>What the Department had had in mind when they brought me home from Bulgaria was
                    to be the first DCM in East Berlin. Along with allowing East Germany to join the
                    UN, we were recognizing her and exchanging embassies. My assignment as DCM was
                    premised on the State Department candidate being named ambassador. He wasn't.
                    Instead, John Sherman Cooper was named ambassador. From his previous experience
                    in India, Cooper had his own candidate for DCM. As a consolation prize I was
                    sent to Helsinki as the DCM where there was an unexpected vacancy. Here again
                    Lady Luck smiled on me. There were many problems in East Berlin; not only the
                    problems of opening up a new post, but problems personality-wise. I really
                    enjoyed my three years plus in Finland.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>Eugenie Anderson had been my first political chief of mission in Bulgaria; in
                    Helsinki, I had two. The first one was John Krehbiel, who had been Nixon's
                    insurance man Southern California. After Nixon resigned in the summer of 1974
                    and Ford became President, John Krehbiel became vulnerable. One of Jerry Ford's
                    golfing partners, Mark Austad, was named to replace Nixon's insurance agent as
                    Ambassador in Helsinki.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there long with Krehbiel? Was he a satisfactory
                        ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes, we had roughly six months together. Fortunately, the bad news for
                    Ambassador Krehbiel reached him when I was in Majorca on vacation. Thus my face
                    was not associated with bringing him this bad news. Ambassador Krehbiel was a
                    delightful man. His attitude was, “Boys, if you need my help in anything, let me
                    know. I will be glad to do anything I can.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But don't bother me with details?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: He was content to leave most facets of the running of the embassy to the
                    professionals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you go see the Foreign Minister?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Maybe not the Foreign Minister, but I would certainly go in to see the
                    Director General of the Foreign Ministry. The Finns did not want to put the
                    ambassador on the spot, they would deal with us in other ways. Mark Austad, now
                    deceased, did not have this relaxed approach. He was very much public relations
                    minded. He was a very much hands-on sort of person, particularly in so far as
                    our USIS people were concerned. He even got to the point of creating a new U.S.
                    foreign policy towards Finland, irrespective of anyone else in the embassy or
                    Department of State. He determined that the United States should buy a
                    Finnish-made ice breaker in order to cement commercial relations between the
                    United States and Finland. In conducting this battle to get the U.S. to buy a
                    Finnish icebreaker, he made an enemy of the U.S. Coast Guard. He did have
                    certain allies in the Congressional delegations of the Great Lakes states,
                    because this icebreaker was designed to keep the Great Lakes open in the winter
                    time. This had never been done. Ambassador Austad was always able to get front
                    page headlines in the Finnish papers by announcing how progress towards the U.S.
                    purchase of an icebreaker in Finland to keep the Great Lakes open.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was the Coast Guard that would have to buy this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: The purchase would come out of the Coast Guard budget, and the Coast
                    Guard would have to operate it. However, the Coast Guard did not want it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they have any icebreakers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Nobody thought it made economic sense to keep the Great Lakes open in
                    the winter time. It was cheaper to have a lot of ore movers to move the ore
                    during all the non-ice months and stack the ore on the southern shore near the
                    steel plants than it would be to break ice all winter. In the current budget,
                    the Coast Guard is having another icebreaker foisted upon them, at the request
                    of Senator Stevens of Alaska, this time for use in Alaska. Again they are
                    resisting. The Coast Guard resistance then was two- fold: one, they did not want
                    the job of keeping the Great Lakes open. Two, if they were going to be given the
                    job, they wanted to have an icebreaker built in the United States. In any case,
                    the icebreaker campaign illustrated some of the problems the professionals in
                    the embassy in Helsinki had with Ambassador Austad. He was a strong personality,
                    very much hands-on, with his own ideas of what should be done with U.S.-Finnish
                    relations, and feeling no compunctions about making his own policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Austad speak Finnish?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: No. He really wanted the embassy in Norway because he was of Norwegian
                    descent, he had been a Mormon missionary in Norway and spoke Norwegian. Later,
                    he did get to be named ambassador to Norway. However, the person who was in
                    Norway at the time Nixon resigned had good credentials whereas Krehbiel as the
                    insurance agent for Nixon was vulnerable. Even though he wanted to be in Norway,
                    Mark Austad was a very hands-on ambassador in Finland. He cultivated very good
                    public relations. He is, perhaps, one of the very best known American
                    ambassadors to Finland in modern times. He got to be a buddy of President
                    Kekkonen. He arranged for President Kekkonen to come to the embassy for a sauna
                    with members of the staff. I had a sauna with President Kekkonen; once you have
                    a sauna with a Finn, you really have a friend.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>The really big thing that happened in Helsinki, the one time in my career when I
                    can say I was on the spot when history was being made, was the Final Act of
                    Helsinki in July and August 1975. President Ford and Henry Kissinger came for
                    the United States. Mark Austad really thought for a while he was going to have
                    the President as his house guest at the Residence. He was told to arrange a
                    presidential suite at the best hotel in town for Kissinger. As it turned out, of
                    course, the White House staff told the ambassador to move into a hotel.
                    Kissinger got the presidential suite, and the ambassador got sort of an ordinary
                    room. The embassy thereafter had two plaques. One was a plaque out in front
                    which said that, “In this room in 1949, the first talks were held between the
                    United States and the Soviet Union as part of SALT.” Austad put up another
                    plaque, in the dining room where President Ford had met with the leaders
                    bilaterally, Brezhnev, Tito and other people. Ambassador Austad's plaque there
                    read: “Mark Austad, Ambassador. This is the room where President Ford met his
                    counterparts at the CSCE Summit.” The next ambassador, Roz Ridgway, felt that
                    such a plaque was unprofessional. She didn't mind having a room identified as
                    the place where talks were held for SALT, but she did not think that Austad, who
                    did not live there at the time or really have anything to do with CSCE, should
                    have his name associated with the Helsinki Final Act.</p>
                <p>I can recall going to Finlandia Hall for this Final Act. I was standing in the
                    corridor once when I saw Todor Zhivkov just standing there, not doing anything.
                    So I approached him, I stuck out my hand and started to talk to him in
                    Bulgarian. He was chatting with me, asking how I knew Bulgarian, but I could see
                    his eyes were somewhere else. He was sort of in mid-sentence when the auditorium
                    door opened and Leonard Brezhnev came out. I was dead from then on. Zhivkov had
                    apparently arranged to meet Brezhnev for a corridor conversation. Others
                    attending were Pierre Trudeau, Marshal Tito. This is one time when I really felt
                    I was present when history was being made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a substantial support function for our embassy
                        and consulates in the Soviet Union, wasn't there? Did that create any
                        problems or was it a fairly routine administrative matter?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Helsinki support for the USSR posts worked normally, fairly easily. We
                    did have, I think, one person, in our mail room working on Moscow and Leningrad
                    APO mail; he was on the Moscow budget. The rest of our people working on this
                    support project were not covered, I think, by Moscow's budget. The support work
                    was done mostly by trusted Finnish personnel. It really was not a big burden.
                    Since my time, support has become much more of a burdensome matter. Because of
                    construction projects in the Soviet Union, many more bulky things have been
                    shipped through Finland. The latest plan to reconstruct the embassy in Moscow,
                    using large components fabricated in the United States, that is going to be a
                    very important task. Embassy Moscow, for morale reasons as much as anything,
                    would send non-professional couriers out once a week, and pay their expenses to
                    bring back the mail.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The old courier system.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: The old courier system. It perhaps could have been done in some other
                    fashion, but all people in Moscow appreciated the chance to spend a few days in
                    the freedom of Finland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any particular personality things? Anybody
                        PNGed as you remember, out of Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: I can't recall any such thing. The Finnish border was pretty well
                    guarded. Every now and then someone might make it across. Unofficially, I
                    understood that if a Finnish border guard would catch somebody escaping from the
                    Soviet Union, they would expel them as fast as they could to Sweden without
                    saying a word. The Finns really did not want to send people back to the Soviet
                    Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There is a bit of a transportation problem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: The Finns are very efficient. I am sure that if they have a policy, they
                    will find a way to accomplish it. One of the interesting things about
                    Soviet-Finnish relations is that the Finns don't want to forget the territory
                    formerly part of Finland which they had to cede to the Soviet Union after the
                    Winter War, in Karelia principally. In almost any Finnish cemetery you will find
                    a marker put up in memory of those graves left behind in Karelia. When the Finns
                    had to evacuate, they had to leave their dead behind. This stone is found in
                    every Finnish cemetery, so that those who left dead behind in Karelia they can
                    come and leave flowers at this particular stone. There are various organizations
                    for Finnish provinces who have celebrations, but no celebration is quite like
                    the Karelian celebration. There an effort is made to preserve the Karelian
                    culture, which may have some slight nuances that general Finnish culture does
                    not have. I have been to meetings of people from Karelia, or whose fathers or
                    mothers came from Karelia. Participants wear old Karelian costumes, do Karelian
                    dances, and sing Karelian songs. There is even a Karelian beer. Finns do like
                    their beer and other liquor. Karelian beer came out bearing a label of crossed
                    swords. One Soviet ambassador to Finland was foolish to say something about
                    this. He said this label was not very good of the Finns, who claiming good
                    relations with the Soviet Union, yet had a beer called Karelian beer bearing
                    very militaristic symbols on it. I am told that within a few months after the
                    Soviet ambassador made that remark, the producers could not keep up the demand
                    for Karelian beer; many Finns wanted to drink the beer just to show the Soviet
                    ambassador what they thought of his remark.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is your forecast and what is the situation in Karelia
                        now? Is there a large Finnish population there? Is there an independence
                        movement?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: No, I don't think there is much prospect of Karelia rejoining Finland.
                    The Finns are part of a language group to which many different small groups in
                    the Soviet Union belong. If anything, the Finns feel most kinship with the
                    Estonians, who are very, very closely related linguistically and culturally. I
                    think the Finns realize that the big power, Soviet Union, needs Karelia for the
                    protection of Leningrad. There is not much irredentism in Finland, but the fate
                    of Estonia is very much on Finnish minds at the moment. My experience in Finland
                    was, I think, good preparation for my next assignment, which was Moscow.</p>
                <p>When Roz Ridgway came to Helsinki in September, 1977, she had her own choice as
                    DCM. I stayed on for about two weeks, saw her present her credentials and make a
                    few calls. Then Sam Fry came in as my replacement and I left. I joined the Board
                    of Examiners for the Foreign Service. The assignment arose because when
                    Personnel knew of Roz's plans for a new DCM, they began casting about for a
                    place where I could go. I had seen a notice that the Consul General in
                    Thessaloniki was leaving. I called Washington Personnel and said, “I have been
                    in Bulgaria, I know a bit about Thessaloniki, what about naming me CG in
                    Thessaloniki?” Well it turned out that someone had already been tapped for that
                    job, Dan Zachary. He was a Greek speaker, and I wasn't. He was then head of the
                    economic cone on the Board of the Foreign Service Examiners so I sort of fell
                    into his vacancy. I took his place on the Board while he went off to
                    Thessaloniki.</p>
                <p>BEX was an interesting assignment. Of course, a BEX assignment does not lead
                    anywhere. So while I was doing examinations, I was looking for a place I could
                    go. I did not want to retire just yet. The thought occurred to me that I could
                    dust off my previous scientific credentials, my time in Soviet-American
                    exchanges, scientific exchanges, and perhaps become the next Science Counselor
                    in Moscow. There was considerable resistance on the part of the Soviet desk to
                    my idea. The Soviet experts do not like to see counselor-level jobs go to
                    persons who have not put in time at a lower level. However, with OES [Bureau of
                    Oceans, Environment and Science] beating down every non-science candidate that
                    EUR threw up, I was able to get this job. I took six months Russian language
                    training, from January to June 1979. Thanks to my previous Slavic exposure, I
                    got up to an evaluated 3 in Russian before going out. I made a sentimental
                    journey, which I recommend to everyone going to the USSR. I flew to Stockholm
                    and took a ferry to Helsinki overnight. If you can travel in June-July, the
                    ferry ride is absolutely lovely. I then went by train from Helsinki to Moscow. I
                    had a very pleasant lunch with Ambassador Ridgway and her DCM, Sam Fry, in
                    Helsinki on my way through.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>I took over as Science Counselor in Moscow in July, 1979. But five months after I
                    arrived, the Soviets invaded Afghanistan. President Carter, as one method of
                    retaliating, decided to stop all high level contacts under the exchange
                    programs. The programs were the principle raison d'etre, the principle source of
                    activity for the science office in Moscow. We found ourselves with not much to
                    do. The fall-off in exchange activity made it possible for me to engage in more
                    reporting on scientific topics. I also carved out a niche for myself reporting
                    on Soviet-Scandinavian relations, because of my service in Helsinki. I probably
                    stepped on the people in the political section a bit. The Science Section was
                    also given the job of controlling the embassy travel program. Travel is an
                    important part of a mission in a Communist country, particularly in the Soviet
                    Union where so much territory is off limits. You keep trying to get into places
                    where people have not been into before just to see what is going on there. The
                    travel program is normally run out of the political section. Since they had
                    plenty to do in 1980, and we didn't, we took over the travel program. This made
                    us become more involved in the political aspects of U.S.-Soviet relations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have plenty of funding for internal travel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: You never have enough money, but we had sufficient so that we could
                    spend some of it on lower priority targets, or on travel by people who were not
                    heads of sections. We could have spent more, surely, but Soviet secrecy not
                    funding was the big problem. Our getting involved in the travel program was
                    merely shifting the workload within the embassy, keeping track of travel, and
                    planning it. Before things got too bad after Afghanistan, I did make one trip
                    with one of our touring science delegations. This was a delegation of people
                    investigating Soviet practices in restoring strip-mined land. We went to
                    out-of-the-way places like the Siberian coal basins, Kemerovo, Karaganda, which
                    also had a coal mining operation, and Alma Ata, a charming town in the Central
                    Asian republic of Kazakhstan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These are very expensive tourist trips.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Traveling with this delegation exposed me to a typical Soviet attempt to
                    drink visitors under the table. I was not drunk under the table, not because I
                    am a good drinker, but because I had sense enough to go to bed early. The head
                    Soviet host claimed that he had an appointment and left before the drinking got
                    serious. So I used the same excuse and left. The next morning we had a difficult
                    time arousing one particular expert from the Bureau of Mines, who had stayed at
                    the party until the bitter end. The Soviet practice is this: they outnumber you,
                    as each person proposes a toast, the Soviets only drink to American toasts, not
                    theirs. Also their liquor is drunk, vodka. I don't know why we don't do a better
                    job briefing our exchange people so that they don't get caught the way one or
                    two of our group did.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I learned that during World War II with Soviet purchasing
                        missions.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: One of the first celebrations in Moscow after I arrived came when
                    Ambassador Toon dug the first spade of dirt for the new chancery in Moscow.
                    Since then, our construction of a new chancery has turned out to be a disastrous
                    project. We will have to demolish the new chancery at great expense and start
                    again. Andrey Gromyko gave Toon a farewell luncheon. V.V.Kuznetzov received the
                    credentials of our new ambassador, ex-IBM board chairman Tom Watson, in November
                    1979. Gromyko gave Watson a farewell luncheon early in 1981. I attended all
                    these functions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was Watson as ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Watson is a man who has had great interest in the Soviet Union since the
                    mid-30s. He is the man who also thought that if you spend 30 years in the
                    Foreign Service, you probably knew a great deal about diplomacy. So he relied
                    heavily on the advice of his staff, although he wanted to overcome what he
                    thought was an overdone anti-communism and skepticism of the Soviet Union on the
                    part of the professionals. He basically considered his mission, the reason why
                    he sought the job and took it, was to improve Soviet-U.S. relations sufficiently
                    so that there never would be a nuclear exchange between the two countries. I
                    must say the Soviets very badly timed their invasion of Afghanistan. Instead of
                    profiting from the departure of hard-line Mac Toon and the presence of a guy
                    willing to give them the benefit of the doubt, they went into Afghanistan. There
                    was nothing Watson could do to carry out his own desires at the time. I think
                    Afghanistan was a very great disappointment to Ambassador Watson, his desire to
                    head off the nuclear confrontation. He could do nothing, because of
                    circumstances. Later, I think he was the first foreigner to get permission to
                    fly a private airplane across Siberia. He had been a pilot on a mission which
                    flew from Alaska across Siberia to Moscow to open the Al-Sib route. The route
                    was used to fly aircraft to the Russian front from Great Falls Montana through
                    Alaska and across Siberia. He had been co-pilot of a plane flying back to the
                    United States from this mission to Moscow. The plane just barely made it back to
                    the town of Yakutsk in winter time when engine trouble developed. He was stuck
                    in Yakutsk for ten days in 1942 while they tried to fix the aircraft. I know
                    this story well. One of the things Watson wanted to do as ambassador was to go
                    back to Yakutsk with his wife to show her what that area was like. He and his
                    wife were good enough to ask my wife and me to accompany them on this trip. This
                    was the first time I had been on an ambassadorial trip, getting all the extra
                    attention that goes with that. Watson tried to meet some of the people whom he
                    had known in 1942 in Yakutsk, particularly the General who had been in charge of
                    the Soviet airlift at the time. There was still enough Soviet suspicion that
                    they did not produce that man. Watson did see a museum director whom he had
                    known 38 years before.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had IBM maintained an office in Moscow as they had in a
                        number of Eastern European countries during the cold war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: IBM had representation in Moscow when we were there, but I am not sure
                    about its history. There had been an IBM in Bulgaria for years, and one in
                    Hungary. I noticed the IBM office in Moscow got very busy when Watson was there.
                    When Olive Watson's IBM typewriter broke, the IBM people in Moscow wanted to
                    give her a brand new one, the latest. She insisted that they repair hers. They
                    had to fly a guy in from the IBM factory, I guess, to fix the old machine, but
                    they did just that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You talked about doing scientific reporting, how did you
                        do that, weren't you forbidden to talk to people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: No, I was not forbidden. The higher level people from the Government
                    agencies back here were not allowed to contact my people over there. The embassy
                    was never enjoined, even at the counselor level, from going out and talking to
                    anybody they could find who were willing to talk to us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of things were you able to report on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: I must admit that most of my reporting came from reading the scientific
                    literature we received at the Embassy, as well as from round-table meetings of
                    science counselors once a month. I picked up at these meetings what other
                    countries were doing in the science field who had not cut back because of
                    Afghanistan. Also there were ongoing U.S. projects. One in particular gave us
                    entry into a science research institute in Moscow, namely our cooperation with
                    the Magneto Hydro-dynamics Institute. The Soviets in science think nothing of
                    investing $50 million to build a full scale plant, whereas we are aghast at
                    spending so much on experimental projects. We prefer to test things on
                    computers, then try it on a small scale, and gradually work up before we invest
                    in a large way. The Soviets, on the other hand, lack some of our refined,
                    delicate instruments. So we found a happy marriage of Soviet willingness to
                    build a full scale plant to test the theory of magneto-hydro dynamic electric
                    generation, and our ability to supply components that they could not build. This
                    cooperation gave us unusual access into the particular institute doing this
                    work. Even though high level cooperation was cut off, we could still go to that
                    institute and find out what they were doing.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>Another example of reporting I did from Moscow: one summer while in Finland, my
                    wife and I spent a week near the Norwegian and Soviet borders at the Sub-Arctic
                    Research Station of the University of Turku. Our stay was primarily a vacation,
                    but I did look into various scientific activities under way. One thing I did was
                    visit the seismic station there. That station had two seismic detectors, one
                    Soviet and one American in keeping with the Finnish policy of neutrality.
                    Readings from the detectors were regularly sent to Moscow and Washington
                    respectively. Of course, the U.S. detector was much more sensitive than the
                    Soviet one, and the location close to the Soviet border was more important to
                    the U.S. than to the USSR. In any case, the Finn tending the detectors told me
                    that they had been picking up for some time signals indicating some sort of
                    drilling activity across the Soviet border. This all came back to me when I read
                    in Moscow a brief account of a Soviet project to drill the world's deepest hole
                    in the hard granites of the Kola Peninsula. I reported to Washington my
                    suspicion that signals the seismic station in Kevo, Finland had been picking up
                    for years came from the Soviet drilling project on the Kola Peninsula.</p>
                <p>Science and politics are very closely related in the Soviet Union. The USSR
                    Academy of Sciences plays a very important role in the USSR political system.
                    The Academy is automatically entitled to several seats in the Soviet parliament.
                    The President of the Academy of Sciences was always a member of the Central
                    Committee of the Communist Party. The supervision of the Academy of Sciences,
                    which covers not just the hard sciences as we know them, but also includes
                    fields like Party ideology and history. The Senior Party Secretary, Suslov in my
                    time, would supervise the Academy of Sciences, so there was a lot of politics in
                    the Academy. Andre Sakharov was a member of the Academy of Sciences. He was very
                    political, so there was a lot of interaction of politics and science in the
                    Soviet Academy. We had to be careful in dealing with the Academy of Sciences not
                    to tread too much on what the people in the political section were doing. The
                    political section maintained contact with Sakharov, for example.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We have our own bureaucracy. You must have had a
                        reasonably collegial atmosphere in the Embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: We had all those things which at the time of the Sergeant Lonetree trial
                    were portrayed as bad. We knew a KGB colonel worked in the Embassy personal
                    services section. We had New Years dances or Marine Balls at which Marines or
                    the ambassador would have his arms around the head KGB representative at the
                    Embassy. The relations of Russian and Americans at the Embassy were all very
                    collegial. Perhaps inexperienced Marines thought we did not care about security.
                    One time at Spaso House I remember in particular dancing with this KGB colonel,
                    to the American song “Rah, Rah, Rasputin, Lover of the Russian Queen”, a very
                    popular piece among the Russians at the time. [Laughter]</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>I viewed my assignment to Moscow as pretty much the end of my career. I think
                    that I had gotten into trouble in Finland by failing to ride herd on Ambassador
                    Austad. I felt I was not going to get any more good assignments. So when I came
                    home from Moscow, I went again to the Board of Examiners for a brief period. I
                    retired early in 1982 when the senior officer cap [the cap in salaries for
                    government workers which meant a higher pension calculation, based on the last
                    three years of salary] was raised. I thought I was very smart waiting that out.
                    I eased the shock of my retirement by taking a part time job in the Freedom of
                    Information work in the Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It must be interesting in a lot of ways, one you are using
                        your skill. Would you like to describe what you are doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: The job had its roots in the passage of the first Freedom of Information
                    Act in 1974. The Act laid obligations on government agencies to release
                    information unless it fell into certain categories. The burden of proof was
                    placed on the government to show why information cannot be released. At first
                    the Department tried to discharge these responsibilities by saddling the bureaus
                    with this task. This meant asking people who are competing for promotions and
                    trying to run relations with foreign countries also to engage in this other type
                    of work. That is not a congenial mix for most. Nobody wins a promotion by
                    releasing information, and you could very well run into problems with your
                    country by releasing that information. Furthermore, you could get the
                    Department's lawyers into lots of lawsuits by capriciously denying information
                    that had to be released under the law, as it is being interpreted.</p>
                <p>In 1979 the Department decided to set up an operation using retired Foreign
                    Service officers who were not bucking for promotion, who had the time to
                    consider requests free of the pressure of current events, who furthermore would
                    be around long enough to become experts. A great body of law exists that you
                    have to take into account in doing this work. When I retired early in 1982, the
                    Department was still building up the cadre of retired FSOs to do FOIA work. An
                    FSO had to be endorsed by various bureaus, there still being a vestige of bureau
                    control over the centralized operation. I guess each bureau has to give up a
                    certain amount of money each year for FOIA activities. I got the endorsement of
                    European Affairs, and OES [Bureau of Oceans, Environment and Science]. When a
                    case comes in, and it is decided which bureau the case belongs to, a reviewer
                    gets the case who has the endorsement from the particular bureau concerned. Over
                    time I have become a leading retired Soviet FOIA expert, even though I was in
                    Moscow only as Science Counselor and only for two years. I guess other Soviet
                    hands have found more lucrative ways than I have of putting their skills to work
                    after retirement. FOIA work is a way of avoiding cutting the final umbilical
                    cord that ties you to the State Department, plus one does come across some very
                    interesting cases from time to time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It keeps you abreast of history and to some degree,
                        current affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>HOUSTON: It really has posed before my eyes the problem of what to do about
                    publications like Foreign Relations of the United States which ostensibly
                    reflect everything important that has happened in U.S. relations in a particular
                    year. I know of some countries and years when the major things that happened
                    involved covert action. You cannot release covert action information at all. How
                    can we talk about what really happened, where covert action was involved?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It will be another generation at least and by that time
                        records may be gone, and the memory will certainly. You are still doing some
                        of the declassification?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This has been most interesting. You now have a son in the
                        Foreign Service so you have left an impression one generation down. Do you
                        have any reflections on whether it is still a good career, what changes
                        ought to be made in the professional Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HOUSTON: There have been several phases in the Foreign Service. One, the phase I
                    came in under, was the Rogers Act. Here people might go for seventeen years
                    without home leave, be forgotten in Tahiti for that period of time, go native.
                    At this time, there were some real horror stories. I think that clearly was
                    unfortunate. Maybe shortly after the 1946 Act was passed was the best time. The
                    Act brought benefits, and the problems had not arisen. Now, we have security
                    problems, a fortress mentality. The practice of negotiating assignments is a far
                    cry from the idea of the Foreign Service being a service. I am not sure we are
                    representing our country best when we worry so much about whether a particular
                    assignment is good for our careers instead of whether the job we are doing is
                    good for our country. So I have some questions about the Foreign Service as it
                    is today. As far as my son is concerned, he joined the Foreign Service on his
                    own; I did not recommend it to him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At least I apparently did not set a good enough example
                        because neither of my sons were taken to entering into the Foreign Service.
                        Thank you very much Bob.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
