<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001710">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Mr. Giles Kelly , 2011: a machine-readable
                    transcription.</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2012</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2012-06-24"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2012-06-24"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>GILES KELLY</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: December 2, 2010</p>
                <p>Copyright 2011 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right. Today is the 2nd of December, 2010 and this is
                        an interview with Giles Kelly, and it's G-I-L-E-S, and then K-E-L-L-Y. And
                        this is being done for the Association for the Diplomatic Studies and I'm
                        Charles Stuart Kennedy. And Giles, let's start. When and where were you
                        born?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I was born in Bronxville, New York, which is in Westchester County, a
                    suburb of New York City.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: 1921.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: OK. Tell me about your family in your father's side. What
                        do you know about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: My father was a graduate of University of Maine in electrical engineering
                    at the brink of World War I. He volunteered to go into the Navy as an officer
                    with a sort of 90-day training at the Naval Academy, and he served on the staff
                    of admirals as a radio officer. After the war he left the Navy and his main
                    hobby was amateur radio.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And do you know where the Kelly's come from? It sounds
                        Irish, but do you have any idea where they came from or?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. There's a place in Devon in England called Kelly. I've been there to
                    see if there is a connection with the John Kelly who settled in what is now
                    Newbury, Massachusetts in 1635. He came over on a ship called the Hector. We
                    think that he was one of the Kellys from Devon who was a second son. We've seen
                    the record and there was a second son named John Kelly. So that's the
                    connection, but we can not be absolutely certain. But I did ask the Kellys
                    living in England what they knew about their manor house in Kelly. They said,
                    “This manor house was listed in the doomsday book.” So those Kellys and perhaps
                    my Kellys go back to 1066.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, of the Kellys your great-grandfather, great-great
                        grand — what were they up to before your father ended up in Maine?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: They were mostly farmers in New England. Some of them were in the church.
                    My grandfather was a banker. I think a few of them were bankers. Nobody was
                    especially prominent or wealthy. There was a Kelly, an ancestor who was called
                    Yellowstone Kelly who went out west and became a well-known scout in Yellowstone
                    Park area. The Kellys fought in the Revolution. I recall my father was a member
                    of The Sons of the American Revolution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right. How about your mother? What's her
                        background?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: She was a New Yorker. She met my father here in Washington during or just
                    after I guess World War I.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: World War I.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes, She had gone to college out in Montana. I don't know whether she
                    finished or not, but I think that it was interrupted by the War and she came to
                    work for the Red Cross here in Washington. Her father was named Johnston with a
                    T, and they were Scottish.— that would be her grandfather, emigrated from
                    Scotland and married a German immigrant named Amelia Fiddler. My mother was one
                    of three children, the only girl and two brothers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right. Did you grow up in Bronxville as a kid? I mean
                        was this —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No. We moved a short distance away to New Rochelle. I think there was even
                    a year in between in Pelham. But I went to grammar school in New Rochelle, then
                    to junior high school, and then to the high school. But from the high school,
                    which was large, I transferred to a small private boarding school in Greenwich,
                    Connecticut, as a scholarship student. Something that my parents were eager to
                    have me do because I was showing some promise as an artist, and also that kind
                    of school, which was unusual in the '30s was coeducational,, although there were
                    some day students. And it was based on the philosophy of Dewey, the great
                    educator.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes, John Dewey from Columbia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. So- called the Progressive school idea.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah. Well, first place growing up in New Rochelle, what
                        was it like for a kid?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: They had fraternities in high school and it had a waterfront.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I want to go back before that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Before that it was —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Elementary school kind of.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. I remember one of my teachers who said — I'm trying to think of her
                    name— Ah, Miss Gallop. I remember her commanding; “Giles, march your boots up
                    here.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: (laughs)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I lived near the railroad tracks in a very modest house, but on the right
                    side of the railroad tracks. And we used to go into New York on the Boston and
                    Westchester Railway line, which was reduced to be the B&amp;W line, and then to
                    the Bump and Wiggle line.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: (laughs)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And there was that song, “45 Minutes From Broadway.” Which was about the
                    time it took us to get to Grand Central</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes, that was Cohan, wasn't it? George M. Cohan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “45 Minutes From Broadway.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Think of the difference it makes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>KELLY: (laughs) Anyway, we lived by those railroad tracks. They were out back.
                    including the New York and New Haven and Hartford line. So I used to love the
                    trains. I had a nice neighborhood. There was a girl in the next house whom I was
                    learning about girls from.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Uh-huh.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And a guy across the street was a bully. And we used to have a lot fun in
                    a sand lot which served as a playground for us. And we made roads and bridges
                    and tunnels there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you much of a reader?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: A reader. No. That doesn't mean I didn't read, but I —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, no, no.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I was not into books.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what about your artistic stuff? Did that come out
                        early?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean were you doing sketches?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cartoons, or what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I still have drawings that go back to those days of junior high school and
                    maybe even further back. Yes, I was always interested in drawing and did a lot
                    of drawing all my life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this sort of innate or were you getting any sort of
                        instruction or school or not? I mean before you went away to school.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Not any special instruction, just regular art classes that everybody
                    took.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: First place, where did your family fall politically?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: My father was a Republican and my mother a Democrat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: (laughs) So often the case.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I heard many debates as I was growing up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did Roosevelt play? Because Roosevelt were for him or
                        again' ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. My mother was very much for him. I think my father was not strongly
                    against him, but he certainly didn't think he was the right man for the job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was thinking of that cartoon, “Let's go down to the
                        Trans Lux and hiss at President Roosevelt.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In The New Yorker. Well, what about —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: By the way, The New Yorker was something that I grew up with. My parents,
                    especially my mother, read it. She was quite a liberal. And one of the nice
                    things when I got to this school in Connecticut called the Edgewood School, one
                    of my classmates was the daughter of Ray Irvin. Ray Irvin was the art director
                    of The New Yorker. He designed the original “Tilley” cover.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah, I always think of Peter Arno. The New Yorker had
                        wonderful cartoonists.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>How about religion? Was this important for your family?</p>
                <p>KELLY: Religion was not important, but it was something that was part of our
                    culture. I think my parents wanted me to go to different Sunday schools,
                    different churches. And I went to Christian Science, Episcopal, probably some
                    others that I can't really remember. But I throughout my life wanted to be
                    familiar with the Jewish faith. When I was in Khartoum I served as a Sidesman in
                    the Church of England. But I have never been a church person. I was only a
                    Sidesman there to further my professional connections.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah. Anyway, what was the name of this boarding
                        school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It was called The Edgewood School.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Edgewood School.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And it was on a lovely campus that had once been the Post Estate in
                    Greenwich, Connecticut. It's no longer there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was school like there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It had small classes, 12, 15 in a class maybe, boys and girls. And they
                    had interesting facilities such as a printing press, carpenter shop, and a Miss
                    Bentley that gave special exercises. She came once a week, or month or
                    something. We put on plays, Shakespeare, Gilbert and Sullivan. There was also a
                    studio for pottery. We played football and we had ice hockey. We had
                    inter-school hockey and football in which I participated. I lived in the boys
                    dorm, which was a bit of a walk to the main house and school building. It was an
                    open dorm, not rooms. And we had fairly rigid requirements to keep our stuff
                    neat, tidy and clean. I gave haircuts to some of the boys in order to earn a
                    quarter or a nickel or whatever it was in those days. We didn't go into town
                    much. We liked the campus. My parents could drive up from New Rochelle, probably
                    a three-quarter-hour drive in those days.</p>
                <p>The first time I was seriously interested in a girl was at Edgewood School.
                    Althea was an interesting person from Chicago who I was intrigued with. She was
                    fey, you might say. One crisis at the school and for me too, was after one
                    Christmas vacation she didn't return to school as expected. I, as a scholarship
                    student, worked on the switchboard. So I heard the principal talking with her
                    parents and saying where is she? And they said we took her to the station to
                    catch her train. And it became a cause celebe in Chicago. Where was this girl?
                    She came from a prominent and wealthy family there. So there was a mystery for
                    about a week or 10 days until she was found in Tulsa, Oklahoma, in a car with
                    three guys who she had met at a New Years Eve party —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: (laughs)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: — and they were heading “South of the Border.” Do you remember that
                    tune?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes, yes, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: They were going south of the border and to Hollywood. When she got back to
                    school she swore to me that she hadn't slept with any of these guys. I was
                    crestfallen, but still in love with her.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean the Depression was in its full swing during this
                        time you were in the school, weren't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Depression. Yes. My father was out of work, my mother was doing some
                    secretarial work for a well known scientist in New York. I'm trying to think of
                    his name now. Harold, Harold —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it'll come.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: So she was the breadwinner at times, and my dad was looking for jobs and
                    got one occasionally, sometimes it was installing a sound system in a theaters
                    or public address systems on ships. It was pick-up work. He worked for a time
                    for Western Electric, which was a big company.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the outside world — I'm trying to figure out, you
                        were at the school what years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Well, I, I graduated from high school in '39.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So did the outside world events, I mean Hitler and
                        Mussolini and all that, did that intrude — I mean was that very apparent to
                        you or was that far away?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It seemed far away. But interesting. War was in the news a good deal. I
                    was aware of it, but thinking it was not going to bother me—it was way over
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And I had a very good friends, interesting friends, at Edgewood because
                    only interesting people would go -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>KELLY: —to a place like that. I was doing art. That's why I was there, because I
                    was good at art. But I want to go back to one thing. In high school, New
                    Rochelle High School, when Amelia Earhart was lost in her flight around the
                    world, I was very interested in that. And I wrote a piece, an article, for a
                    contest that was held at the high school, and I won. It was about her last
                    flight— it was called I think “Pennies From Heaven,” But it was a make-up story
                    of what happened after she left the airport and flew across the Pacific.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It was sort of a dreamlike thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was specific.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. But that prize I think also helped me get a scholarship to
                    Edgewood.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, did you get any feel — I mean I'm trying to pick up
                        sociological things. I assume that there were no, now they call them
                        African-Americans — at the time we called them colored or black — in your
                        orbit at all.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No, they were at New Rochelle High School, but not the Edgewood School.
                    And I did not really have much chance to know them or be particularly interested
                    in them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about Jews? You know, there was quite a bit of
                        prejudice against Jews, but being in an artist-type school I think it would
                        be, you know, a considerable Jewish element there. How did that play in your
                        view?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: There was a Jewish presence, a good Jewish presence at Edgewood School,
                    more so than at the New Rochelle High School. And I was friends with and
                    attracted to Jewish people. In fact, my best friend at Edgewood was a Jew. There
                    were also, interestingly enough, even a communist on the faculty and a
                    socialist.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, at that time, I mean there were — we had the New
                        Deal and then the communists were a real presence at the time, labor
                        movements and all this. Did you find, I won't say attracted, but were you
                        aware of labor, of struggles in the period, or?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. Not involved, but aware. One of the things, Stu, if I may go on a bit
                    here was that there was a sort of laissez-faire attitude at this school, being
                    progressive, with a lot of permissiveness, and self-expression— all that sort of
                    thing. And by the time I graduated I felt it was too much. One of the things
                    that my family was dealing with was the depression,. What about college? Where
                    would we get the money? And where would Giles like to go?</p>
                <p>Well, two things. I had become very interested in boats. My father was interested
                    in boats. I got jobs in the summertime in New Rochelle being a launch driver for
                    one of the yacht clubs. I was also hired to be caretaker and skipper on a very
                    large sailboat with no motor. That was a big deal in those days for me to
                    handle. So I was thinking of being a sailor. I had this vision of maybe being an
                    officer on a cruise ship running down to South America. I'd have a nice white
                    uniform and all the girls would like that. Also, since I was a citizen of New
                    York State, going to the Merchant Marine academy would be cheap. So that's where
                    I went. There was one other influence: I was sort of fed up with the
                    laissez-faire life I wanted things to be more orderly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you know, when you look at it the '30s there was a
                        lot of experimenting around like the Dewey thing. I went to schools in — I
                        was —I was in junior high in California and I remember they didn't allow
                        homework. I mean this was one of the, you know, trying to make school more
                        interesting, something like — there was a lot of you might say foolishness,
                        but trying various things. Did you ever read the book Auntie Mame or see the
                        play?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because there was this thing where a young boy who there
                        was sent to a progressive school and he's yanked out because when he's found
                        all the little kids are out there waving their arms around calling
                        “spreading the sperm,” you know (laughs)?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: (laughs)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anyway, it's of that era. OK, you were at the — what's the
                        name of the — Kings —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No, New York State Maritime Academy Sometimes known as the Merchant Marine
                    Academy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Academy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And it was federally and state funded.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A little bit like the military VMI (Virginia Military
                        Institute) here in Virginia. You end up in the U.S. Military but its state
                        run.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, talk about — you were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: 1940 to 1942.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this is of course a red-hot period. When you went in
                        we were at peace. How did the academy strike you? What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It was located in the Bronx in a fort and we wore uniforms of course, and
                    we took naval courses, as well as merchant marine courses. We had a summer
                    cruise each year. I was seen as not the regular type guy there. I was still
                    pining for my intellectual and artistic friends at Edgewood School, and what I
                    was finding were people from not only New York, but other states, most of whom
                    were sort of rough diamonds, you might say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: So I didn't fit in too well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, the Merchant Marines is a different breed of cat. I
                        can speak of this as being a consular officer and having to deal with it
                        from time to time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Uh-huh.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how'd you do in the studies?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I did fairly well in the studies, not outstanding— wasn't the top of the
                    class, but probably in the upper-middle part. I had a bit of a knack, on
                    anything that had to do with seamanship. I did struggle with navigation though.
                    And I didn't have any problem with the Military. There was the usual humiliation
                    of plebes. We call them “mugs” there. And that is something you had to navigate
                    very carefully in dealing with the faculty and the upper class. It was important
                    among fellow students to be one of the guys.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, was there sort of developed the same spirit that you
                        got out of West Point Annapolis as far as class spirit and keeping in touch
                        and all that, or not, or?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I don't think it was nearly as cultivated or spontaneous there as it is in
                    those other academies. We were homogenous as a class vis-�-vie the other
                    classes, so there was class spirit. But the school is a very old maritime
                    school, the oldest in America. And so we were sort of led to believe that we
                    were very special if we were going to be Merchant Marine officers and some of
                    the best alumni have become famous captains or even naval admirals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there when the draft started and wartime
                        preparation. How did that affect you all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I was not subject to the draft because I was a naval reserve cadet and
                    midshipman. And I was there when we were attacked in some place called “Pearl
                    Harbor,” which we all thought was probably in the Philippines. We didn't quite
                    know where the hell Pearl Harbor was. But that changed everything of course. And
                    we knew that the very day it happened. It meant — well, let me put it this way.
                    Even Before Pearl Harbor due to war in Europe we did not cruise as was customary
                    to Europe on our summer cruises. In 1941 the cruise was only as far east as
                    Bermuda then down to the Caribbean. But the next year — gee, we just went down
                    the Atlantic Coast and saw some sunken tankers and hoped we weren't next. But
                    when December of 1941 happened it changed the pace, it changed the attitude</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, right after Pearl Harbor Hitler declared war on us.
                        We were having what was called for German U-boat commanders the “happy time”
                        or something. They were sinking ships off our coast. We hadn't even blacked
                        out, we didn't go for convoys. For Merchant Mariners this must have been a
                        traumatic period. What information were you getting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It was. However, there were very few of us out of a class of maybe 40 that
                    went into the Navy. So to answer your questions, most graduates didn't seem to
                    be inhibited from going to sea in the Merchant Marine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But weren't you get reports about the tremendous — I mean
                        it was a horrible period, tremendous loss of ships —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: — by German —</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>KELLY: As I say, as we went on a training ship down to Norfolk we saw wrecks, and
                    of course heard about them, and wondered if we were going to get blown up. Yes,
                    it was very evident. But I did not feel — nor do I think many of the students
                    wanted to quit going to sea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, no, I'm just saying that this had to have been
                        probably for the Merchant Marine a most traumatic period. All right, well
                        —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Let me add this point that the people in the Merchant Marine were getting
                    well paid and people like myself that went into the Navy were getting poorly
                    paid in comparison.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was the situation? Could you opt for the Navy
                        or how did this work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: If you had passed the naval courses that were part of the curriculum and
                    applied for a commission and for active duty, that was the route into the Navy.
                    A lot of guys didn't want to do that, they wanted to go to sea, make money, and
                    have a Merchant Marine career. I had turned away from it largely because I felt
                    that the people that were in the Merchant Marine that I met in the academy and
                    elsewhere professionally, were not the kind of people I particularly enjoyed. In
                    fact, in the yearbook of my class they said — they predicted that Giles would
                    become captain of Mrs. Astor's yacht (laughs). So you know how I was seen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah (laughs).</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: (laughs) Little did they know that in fact I would be captain of the
                    presidential yacht.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: (laughs) So how did this transition to the Navy work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Well, on graduation I had applied for a commission and active duty, which
                    I got but it took time. At that time my father was back in the Navy on active
                    duty. He first went back as a lieutenant commander, then a commander, and later
                    became a captain. I had to wait an uncomfortable time after graduation before
                    all the papers came through. I caught up with my father in Seattle and he swore
                    me in, which was nice. We got a picture of the two of us and I went off to
                    sea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's talk about your sea duty. What did you do and
                        where'd you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>KELLY: Well, the Navy knew I trained as a Merchant Marine officer. They have a
                    special designation for officers that come in to the Navy through the Merchant
                    Marine Academy. My designation indicated that I should be on some kind of a
                    cargo ship or passenger ship, and I was indeed assigned to a naval cargo ship.
                    It was one of the converted Liberty ships. My orders read to proceed from
                    Seattle to San Francisco and join the USS Carina, a new ship that was getting
                    ready to sail and being loaded. I got there before the captain and waited
                    around. I was not living on board the ship, but in quarters that were provided.
                    Other officers arrived. I was junior, at bottom of the list, I guess. Anyway, we
                    trained and took courses and finally took the ship to sea. She was loaded with
                    aviation gas and ammunition.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the name of the ship?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: The Carina, named after a star. She was an AK — AK was the Navy
                    designation for cargo ships. I've forgotten the number, AK-74 it was '42. I
                    remember we passed Christmas Island on Christmas Day, which was sort of nice. We
                    were on our way to Guadalcanal to bring fuel and ammunition to the troops
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And we traveled alone, no escort. We had a celebration on crossing the
                    equator, in the Naval tradition. We operated in a serious naval way, nothing
                    like “Mr. Roberts.” It was reasonable spit and polish. We did stop at the island
                    of Tonga, and that was exotic and fascinating. The natives lived in straw huts
                    and I ate my first breadfruit there, things they pull out of the ground like
                    yams.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know what you mean.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And I met a girl there, which was nice. She wanted me to stay and be her
                    boyfriend. She even took me to meet her family and we had sat on the floor and
                    had a meal together.</p>
                <p>KELLY: After I had to go back, she came to the ship with a little puppy as a
                    present. And the captain allowed me to have it on board as the ship's mascot. We
                    called the puppy Tonga.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you had a really involved cargo, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Very.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that nervous making?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. I was nervous. I was a coding officer and a communications officer.
                    My cabin was by the bridge. The captain was on one side and I was on the other
                    side. I got all the messages in code and had to unscramble them. And every night
                    I wondered if we were going to get blown up so I slept in my clothes. Yeah, I
                    was apprehensive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you sort of have to anchor at some distance from other
                        ships when you went to Tonga and other places?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No. We went immediately to Guadalcanal. And there's no harbor there; it's
                    just a beach. So we stood off the beach and unloaded into our own ship's boats
                    and on to floating docks brought out from the beach.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was happening at Guadalcanal when you were there? I
                        mean had the —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: The Jap ships were coming down the “slot” at night.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Still coming down?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Oh yes. And there were the air attacks. We usually left the beach and went
                    to a harbor at nearby Florida Island- surrounded by hills, hoping that we would
                    be hard to find because of the hills. We would retire each night and then go
                    back next day. But on one night we were called to general quarters at I guess
                    about 11:00. We soon heard on the radio that bogies are approaching on our
                    starboard side. We were all in our life jackets, with helmet on. My position was
                    on the bridges that time as a communications officer.</p>
                <p>And I heard — this is a little side story here of mine —When I heard that the
                    attacking bogies, were coming in on the starboard side, I was on the starboard
                    side of my ship, so I decided I'd go to the port side. Of course everything is
                    pitch dark, all lights out, and everybody tense and quiet. I started to cross
                    the bridge in a hurry, head down, earphones on. I must have got halfway across
                    the bridge when there was a tremendous explosion and I fell back on deck. Then
                    silence. A moment later I heard the captain's voice, “Who the hell was that?”
                    Apparently, the captain was rushing to the starboard side as I was going to port
                    side both with our heads down and we crashed into each other (smacks hands
                    together), our two helmets hit together— sounded just like an explosion. And we
                    were knocked to the floor. So he said, “Kelly, if you ever get in my way on this
                    bridge again you're going to be keel hauled.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Brig or?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Something like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, was there any particular attack at that time? You
                        know, to my mind the whole Guadalcanal experience is probably is well — not
                        many people are familiar with it. But you know, it was a fantastic air, land
                        and sea war where the two empires, the American and the Japanese could
                        hardly get at each other, but except at this one particular point.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: We were not of course a fighting ship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, no.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: We were more like a target ship. If they could it would help them isolate
                    our fighters on islands and they could stop our creeping back up north. So they
                    would bring down cruisers and aircraft carriers. To this front line. The Japs
                    were heading for Australia, we were heading for the Philippines, then to their
                    homeland. So they ran down the slot, with a group of ships. at night, shooting
                    up everything they could find, including us. We had fighting ships, battle
                    ships, and other war ships, to protect us. So while we were there important
                    naval engagements were going on around us. We listened in on our military
                    circuits. We also heard Tokyo Rose tell how we were being sunk. When we had
                    unloaded, we were not sent back to the United States which we had all thought
                    would happen. But, oh no, “you go down to an island further south, to Noumea,
                    and load supplies.” So we were doing a shuttle service for a while just back of
                    the front lines. And occasionally we would run into danger. We always zigzagged
                    in those waters because we were afraid of subs. And we were escorted
                    occasionally by a destroyer, sometimes one of the old destroyers from World War
                    I.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Four-stacker.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yeah, a four-stacker. And for me there was one unforgettable occasion. As
                    we were zigzagging with this destroyer at noon it was the time to change course.
                    I was on the bridge and ordered a course change to the right. Everything — clear
                    skies, everything was fine. I was thinking of submarines. And just as we turned
                    a string of bombs went off right down the track we had just left. I looked up
                    and there was a “Betty,” as we called the Jap bomber. Of course we went to our
                    battle stations and we fired off our five-inch anti-aircraft gun. The destroyer
                    didn't do anything. The Betty turned and left, — I guess he'd run out of bombs.
                    And so message from my annoyed captain to the captain of the destroyer saying,
                    “How come you didn't open fire?”</p>
                <p>The other captain came back with “Because we don't have any anti-aircraft
                    guns.”</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh God.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: But we did get damaged by a near bomb hit one night. It threw the shaft
                    out of alignment and damaged the bearings. We couldn't go our regular speed. So
                    we were sent down to Australia to go into dry dock and get fixed. And of course
                    we loved going to Australia and Sidney, seeing the girls.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yeah. Well, this almost been a favorite part.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Oh, it was—it was. For many reasons. First, we felt safe the first time
                    since December. Second, there were women.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how did it continue until — after you left Australia
                        what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: We went to a number of new places. We went to Norfolk Island, which is
                    between New Zealand and Australia. I was the only officer on the ship that went
                    ashore, because again, as communications officer some secret stuff had to be
                    taken ashore. You know, that was where some of the mutiny on the Bounty people
                    fled to. I made a sketch of the landing area. I sketched a lot during the war
                    and still have drawings. As we couldn't have cameras, I would sketch. We stayed
                    in New Zealand for quite a while and I got know quite a few people there and had
                    a wonderful visit. I can't remember quite where we went next. I think it was to
                    Ulithi Island. We were delivering cargo for troops again, but not the high test
                    gas and explosives so much as mail and all kind of stuff. After I'd been there a
                    year — I guess a year and a half — I was ordered home for leave and to a newly
                    constructed ship. The best way for me was by ship. We had some choices, to fly
                    or to go by ship. I sailed from Sydney aboard the U.S.S. West Point, which was
                    the former SS America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: America, yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: So I offered to be a bridge watch stander. So that was a good trip home, a
                    fast trip and I could take more luggage than I could have on a plane. My next
                    ship was fitting out at the Willamette Shipyard in Portland, Oregon. I had to
                    wait quite a while for her to be finished for going to sea and so I had a nice
                    time getting familiar with Portland and dating American women. And we put that
                    ship, an attack transport, in commission. She was a faster ship, and operated
                    frequently with other of ships of her class.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mm-hmm.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: — as an attack group. That captain was an old mustang, that is somebody
                    that came up “through the hawsepipe.” That is to say, he was a former enlisted
                    man. And was born and bred in the navy. I'd had some wonderful captains on the
                    other ship, two of them, but not this time. I became a lieutenant junior grade
                    and now I had a little seniority over ensigns on the ship. But I felt this
                    captain sort of had it in for me. It was the same kind of thing that I found in
                    the Merchant Marine Academy. He was rough and tough.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Uh-huh.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: But I had experience, both Merchant Marine experience and now naval — a
                    year and a half of naval experience — more than most of the other junior
                    officers. So I had a leg up, you might say. During our shakedown cruise, which
                    was off San Diego, an airplane went down, and all ships were alerted but we were
                    the nearest ship. So we were to make a rescue. That meant we had to put a boat
                    in the water to pick up survivors and the debris. I was the officer sent to make
                    the rescue. It worked out well. We saved two guys and the admiral gave us “a
                    well done”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then how did your naval career end?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Before it ended it was quite a few engagements.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, why don't we talk about them? I'd like to —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Well we operated now with other attack transports —and guarded by —
                    accompanied by destroyers and sometimes baby flattops.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: We were part of a task group and we were participated in the Philippines
                    and Okinawa landings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved in the Leyte operation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. Yes. And in the Lingayen Gulf Operation. There were two
                    PhilippineOps, one on the East Coast and one on the West Coast.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about Leyte? This is when, you know, the —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: That's when General MacArthur went ashore saying “I have returned.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I was thinking more of the big battle, you know, and
                        the —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Big battle. We were not there, but I've read about it recently. Glad we
                    missed it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I knew nothing about it at the time. It is fascinating to get the big
                    picture now because we were getting only the small picture, at the time. You
                    know, turn right, turn left to arrive at the certain point at a certain time and
                    discharge. I did get ashore in Okinawa during the battle. I did it too in the
                    Philippines, to talk with soldiers and make some sketches. Nice to get some mud
                    on my feet after being on a ship all the time. It was interesting. I did a whole
                    series of letters home that were kept, probably well over 100. Recently I've
                    edited those letters and put them into a book for my grandchildren. Not anything
                    published — just bound and edited. We learned Roosevelt died. Some of us were
                    sad and a lot of — most of us were sad, but a couple of officers said, “Glad
                    he's gone.”. When the Japanese gave up we learned about it while we were at sea
                    and there was huge applause and yelling. That was a very big day. Our ship was
                    then not an attack ship, but just a transporter. We were sent to Japan to pick
                    up materials to take to China were going to help the Chinese Nationalist fight
                    the Chinese communists.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mm-hmm.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: So excess war materials were loaded on our ship to be taken up the Yellow
                    Sea to Taku Bar, which is the closest you could get to Beijing in those days. We
                    unloaded materials there. Also we stopped at another place called Tsingtao and
                    there we were among the first Americans to arrive. There were still Japanese
                    military there. I had an interesting time there. I don't know whether I want to
                    bother telling you a little war story.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sure, as long as we're going this way, why don't we tell
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>KELLY: All right. We were the only ship in the harbor at the time. And we were
                    going to unload. I was at this point the executive officer on the ship, second
                    in command. So I took the ship's Jeep, and a Chinese speaking enlisted man with
                    me and two of my officers that I liked. We went off on a little tour of
                    Tsingtao, which was an old resort town, where they also make beer. You can get
                    Tsingtao beer here today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It used to be a German enclave.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It was. Very good! That's your history coming out. We drove out along the
                    sea front and where the nice houses were. I pulled up to one that had a circular
                    driveway. And I don't know why I stopped there, but a man came out, a white man,
                    perhaps a Russian Jew. And he was clapping and waving and saying, “Come on in,
                    come on in.” And so we did — the four of us. He took us in a side door and
                    explained most of his house had been turn into a cigarette factory by the
                    Japanese occupiers. So he was reduced to two rooms. He introduced his very
                    attractive Russian wife, a white Russian. I was always interested in beautiful
                    woman, particularly in those days. He served us some liquor and began to
                    complain about the Japanese officer who was living at the other end the house
                    without his permission.</p>
                <p>Emboldened by the drink, I said, “Well, we'll put an end to that right now.” So I
                    marched down the hall with my MP (Military Police) badge showing and my revolver
                    handy. With my cohorts and knocked on the door and gathered nobody was there. So
                    we opened the door, one way or another, I've forgotten how. We entered. I
                    noticed a lot of Japanese occupation money on the guy's desk. My cohorts decided
                    they would take some souvenirs, back to the ship. I didn't do that, but took a
                    handful of occupation money, for a souvenir. I then left a signed note demanding
                    that the occupant leave within 24 hours. On the way back to the ship I noticed a
                    small store that was selling silverware and stuff like that. I stopped and went
                    in and noticed a set of six silver Chinese cups that would be good for sherry or
                    something. The owner was happy to be paid with the occupation bills, which were
                    about to become worthless.</p>
                <p>I had promised the owner that I would come back the next day to make sure that
                    the Japanese guy had left. So when I drove up the next day in my Jeep there was
                    another Jeep there with two Marines in it. They asked “Sir are you the Lt. Kelly
                    that was here yesterday?”</p>
                <p>And I said, “Yes. What's the problem?</p>
                <p>“Well, sir the, the Marine Provost Marshall who's taking charge of security here
                    wants to see you, he has had a complaint of a robbery at this establishment and
                    he wanted to talk with you about it.”</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>I said, “It wouldn't be convenient for me to talk about it right now, but I will
                    see him a little later.” The Marines saluted smartly and drove off. I then went
                    back to the ship, called the guys that had been with me the day before. I said,
                    “Look, I've got to see the Marine Provost and it's going to be my word against
                    the Japanese word. I want you to get rid of everything that you took yesterday,
                    over the side.”</p>
                <p>So then I went to see the Provost. He was a stern guy and senior to me by a
                    couple of ranks. I denied theft and he ended up giving me a kind of a letter,
                    which I was to take to my captain for “appropriate action.” So when I took it to
                    the captain — this was now not the captain I disliked, but a new captain who I
                    did like — and I handed it to him. And he read it and said, “Giles, why didn't
                    you tell me you were going, I would have liked to meet these people.” And he
                    tore the letter up and threw it away. That was the end of it; except that years
                    later, I think The Saturday Evening Post or one of these magazines, had an
                    article about difficulties of occupation. And there was the story about how some
                    un-named naval officer had done just what I'd done.</p>
                <p>I was soon thinking of getting out of the Navy. The war was over. And I was
                    looking for something interesting to do. When we docked at Shanghai, another
                    officer and I were thinking about business — what about an export-import
                    business? Maybe get out of the Navy and get into business. So we talked with
                    Chinese, or expatriates that might be useful contacts in the future.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, the captain I liked was transferred and a four striper replaced him.
                    We hadn't had a four striper on board.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Full captain now?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes, a four striper, Naval Academy graduate. Came aboard. He had never
                    been captain of a big ship before. He had commanded a flotilla landing craft. He
                    didn't know what to do, which was a surprise to me. By that time I had advanced
                    to Lieutenant Commander and knew how to run the ship. The new captain relied on
                    me to show him the ropes. He was friendly, but I noticed he drank, which was a
                    real no-no. I'd never been up against that before. He would do stupid things
                    like call all officers together at midnight in his cabin and would be obviously
                    drunk. He would talk about how we weren't 100% with him, we weren't behind him,
                    and we were bad guys; he was a good guy. So the doctor didn't want to sail under
                    this man. When we got back to Hawaii we tried to get him fired. We went to see
                    the admiral. But the Navy sticks up for its senior officers and we were just
                    reservists. We were told we didn't have enough proof. My God, what proof could
                    we get? I put in for release from active duty. I got transfer orders when we got
                    back to the States. But I didn't leave the Navy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: (laughs) Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>KELLY: I had leave and got an appointment to a ship on the East Coast. On leave I
                    met the woman who was to be my wife. She was a Smith College graduate and had
                    been a camp counselor, and she was passing through Ipswich, Massachusetts where
                    my family lived. I thought she was really interesting. But she was going to
                    teach at the Putney School in Vermont You know Putney?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And I had orders as navigator for a large ship going to the Caribbean. The
                    ship was temporarily in Bayonne, New Jersey where I was supposed to meet her.
                    But that girl I liked lived in New Jersey. It was late summertime and I hoped
                    when I got to my new ship maybe I could meet up with her again, which I did. I
                    sailed with the ship but by the time we reached Norfolk I got my separation
                    orders. I went back to my family in Ipswich. And it is another story how I got
                    into Williams.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, we'll pick this up the next time. It'll be 1946 and
                        you've separated from the active Navy but you remained in the reserve,
                        didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes, I stayed in the Ready Reserve.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And we'll pick it up there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Today is the 17th of December, 2010 with Giles Kelly. Giles, we're 1946 and we
                    were just talking about having applied to Williams. Here you are, how old are
                    you?</p>
                <p>KELLY: 25.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: 25. You've already had your degree, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Oh no. One thing I had learned from my shipmates was I needed one. Most of
                    my fellow officers were college men. During those four years learned I needed to
                    go to a liberal arts college.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What'd you get from the Merchant Academy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>KELLY: I got a coast guard certificate making me eligible to be a second mate on
                    any ship, on any ocean, and probably a graduation certificate,. I've forgotten.
                    But the main thing was I got that Coast Guard certificate. That's what the
                    school was all about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you really felt you needed it, in order to get on in
                        the world, a college diploma. Was that —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I realized how much I was missing out and how much I needed to go to
                    college.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah, mm-hmm. All right. Well, could you describe Williams
                        in 1946?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Did I tell you how I got into Williams?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You told me that you came and they gave you a quick test
                        and —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: OK, then you know I got in sort of by luck.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Serendipity sort of thing. At that time Williams was male only. And I was
                    one of the many veterans there. They had veteran housing, left over from the war
                    years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah, I think there'd been an ROTC (Reserve Officers'
                        Training Corps) unit or something.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Since I was old enough, 25, to be sometimes mistaken for a young
                    instructor I didn't feel I fitted into the fraternity scene, so I joined the
                    Garfield Club, which was an eating club. I lived in one of the dormitories
                    during my first year as a freshman. And I had to take courses that summer to
                    make it into the sophomore class because I only got one semester credit for my
                    Merchant Marine Academy education. I don't know what to tell you particularly
                    about Williams at that time except it seemed isolated, but very beautiful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did any professor or any subjects particularly attract you
                        during the four years you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. I had decided that it was important to study economics and political
                    science. So I took the Political- Economy major But I was also interested in art
                    and music. I don't know of any other special interest at that time,</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Schuman one of your professors?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes, Frederick Schuman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was sort of a towering figure in the college-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Towering indeed. And there was a man who taught labor relations who liked
                    — tall and white haired — Robert Brooks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there when the McCarthy thing hit and Schuman was
                        one of the people named by Joseph McCarthy as a commie or something like
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No, I wasn't aware of that. I was in London then. But I was pleased to be
                    in academia. On weekends the Williams guys took off for Bennington and Smith and
                    other places to meet women</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And I did that sort of thing, started thinking it'd be nice to have a
                    girlfriend somewhere. I found out that that woman I liked was teaching at
                    Putney. Do you know Putney?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: So I looked her up in Vermont. And I migrated up there every once in a
                    while.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They had a school there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Putney School, and I saw her there. I went there on the weekends for some
                    square dances and romance. We dated and decided to get married. So after my
                    first year at Williams we lived in the veterans' housing. She had majored in
                    theater and was very popular on campus because there were never enough women
                    around, especially for the theater. She became an honorary member of Cap and
                    Bells.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>KELLY: I found that a bit distracting because I was hitting the books and she was
                    up there at the theater having a great time with the guys. They had late parties
                    and, you know, the camaraderie that comes with putting on a play. I was in one
                    Shakespeare play with her, but not very happily. We had a lot of fun with the
                    other married couples. I managed the Garfield Club, which brought in a little
                    more income beside the stipend that the government provided vets at that
                    time.</p>
                <p>I graduated in '49 and was about to have a baby. I got into Princeton's Woodrow
                    Wilson School on faculty recommendations. We had to find our own “digs” there
                    because there wasn't any veterans' housing available. We lived off campus in
                    something that was called Pigalee. Actually it was a little pig house that was
                    made over to for use of young students. We spent six months there before we got
                    veterans housing on campus. Two of our four children were born in Princeton</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you still interested in political economy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was just about the preeminent school for
                        international affairs at the time, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: The Master of Public Affairs degree was new. The first class was ''49 and
                    I was in the class of '51 which had 15 members. We had seminars rather than big
                    lectures. There were people like myself, veterans who had been to war, ex majors
                    and lieutenant commanders. Our class melded together rather nicely. We again
                    lived in government provided student housing with a stipend.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you looking at any particular area of the world? I
                        mean the Korean War was going on. Were you being caught up in the Korean
                        War?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Not in the slightest. I was keeping up with my reserve training annually,
                    or took correspondence courses, because I wanted to earn points towards military
                    retirement. But I saw my training as a sort of paid holiday for two weeks a year
                    The travel was interesting, and being an officer life was good. Aside from that
                    I was thinking of what to do after graduation. I hoped to go into the government
                    and contribute whatever I could to stopping war and making the world a better
                    place—that sort of thing. Like so many people at that age, I had stars in my
                    eyes and lots of ambition and hope for doing something significant.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So by the way, at Princeton did any professors
                        particularly strike you or influence you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: One, Professor Marvin Bernstein, I particularly admired, but I did not
                    became close to any one professor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now, again, trying to figure out how to tread, but I
                        remember when I was at Williams in 1950 I think four of my classmates ended
                        up being recruited by the CIA (Central Intelligence Agency). I filled out
                        one form, a huge form, for them and then I got caught up in the Korean War
                        and ended up in the Air Force.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Were you drafted?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I enlisted with the idea of becoming an officer but
                        ended up spending four years enlisted. I was kind of having fun. I was a
                        language specialist. I'd gone to the Army Language School. So at one point I
                        was off North Korea, where they just had that shooting stuff. We were
                        listening to Soviet Air Force. But I was also in Japan, Korea, and
                        Germany.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Did you get any good stuff listening?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Because actually in Korea we were — one of these
                        things — it's known but it's sort of forgotten that we were actually — the
                        U.S. Air Force was fighting the Soviet Air Force. I mean it was — there were
                        Soviet pilots and Soviet planes directed by Soviet ground controllers and so
                        we would listen and then if we would hear a flight of MIGs we would call up
                        the fighter control and say they're sending some MIGs up. And I just
                        remember one time we were shooting down the planes, practically 10 to one. I
                        think MIGs were a good but the Saber could take a lot more and our pilots
                        were more experienced. I remember listening one time to the ground
                        controller saying “attack the sabers.” And the pilot said, “Fuck your
                        mother,” (laughs). That was the highlight of my military career.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: (laughs) I love that. They're human too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah, yeah. Anyway, but this was a period when there was a
                        lot of attacks by McCarthy, but I think at the same time everybody was
                        feeling very patriotic and wanted to serve their country, well not
                        everybody, but certainly that was the spirit I think at the Ivy League
                        colleges.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>KELLY: I had another baby coming along when I got my degree, my third child. And
                    I was very concerned about earning a living. I'd done my war and I wasn't
                    thinking much about the Korean problem. When I had graduated I looked around
                    Washington for a job that would at least give me pay equivalent to what I had
                    made as a lieutenant commander. That was my benchmark. And the best deal was
                    with the CIA because they didn't seem to be bound by the personnel system.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: So I went with the CIA not knowing what was there for me, what they would
                    want me to do. I found it was a very informal attractive collection of people,
                    many from the Ivy League and well heeled.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was, as they used to say, it was very much a white shoe
                        place. I mean this was — people went to college used to wear white buck
                        shoes. But I don't — I mean there was a very aggressive campaign by the CIA
                        and Williams. I'm sure this is duplicated in all the other Ivy League. It
                        was somewhat similar to the way the British had worked with their Oxford and
                        Cambridge and all, except we were catching up. So this was the beginning of
                        the organization.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. I went in without knowing much about the organization. And at that
                    time it was housed in temporary two-story office buildings that lined the
                    reflecting pool with 12-foot fences around it. I found people who were very
                    compatible and very interesting, both men and women. We were far enough away
                    from downtown Washington so that with no restaurants around most of us
                    brown-bagged our lunches. Often in the summertime with our bare feet in the pool
                    and our brown bag along side, we would have a social lunch.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: — which was very pleasant. The other thing is we were learning trade
                    craft, how to shadow people, how to open locks, communicate, and all the kind of
                    things that you have to know to be an operator. First I heard that I was going
                    to Reykjav�k, Iceland. I also found myself in the operations section, secret
                    operations that is, not so much in intelligence gathering, but in running secret
                    operations. I had some connections in the CIA, not very high, but up there. It
                    was awesome to discover who was there. Some bosses were OSS alumni and a couple
                    of them were, surprisingly, from the theaters in New York. One officer was
                    married to the very glamorous Gertrude Lawrence. I was impressed to work with
                    people who had jumped out of airplanes behind the German lines, and others who
                    were big in show business.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It really was.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Oh yes. And then to be learning dirty tricks and the spy craft on top of
                    that, honestly it was exciting. As I look back on it it was one of the most
                    glamorous parts of my life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did you do this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Nine years. When I was new in Washington my third daughter was born. Soon
                    after my assignment was changed to London. I don't know why, but suddenly I was
                    going to London to work on joint operations with British Intelligence. So after
                    my third daughter was born, my family and I sailed “minimum first class” on the
                    SS United States to Southampton, England.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the United States was the biggest and the fastest at
                        the time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. And incidentally one of my classmates from the Merchant Marine
                    Academy was Staff Captain (executive officer) on board.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Uh-huh.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Due to having three children we got a pretty nice suite. I think I made
                    four crossings altogether because we came back on home leave and returned on the
                    SS United States. In London, we were very fortunate. My wife and I each had some
                    connections with Americans and British people there. They steered us toward
                    living in Hampstead, which is a little north of the center of London and on the
                    metro system.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>We were very fortunate in renting The Watch House, an ancient building of four
                    stories counting the basement. It was on high ground in Hampstead looking out
                    over the city, but could rarely be seen because of the smoke and fog of those
                    days. With it came a walled garden, a studio, and a greenhouse. It was in a very
                    picturesque part of London — narrow roads. You couldn't get two cars past each
                    other, in places, lots of cobblestones, a quaint little Catholic church nearby,
                    a famous graveyard. I rented the house from a film director named McQuitty. He
                    became a friend. We were in a community of artists and writers and theater
                    people. My wife got to know our neighbors while I was working at the embassy.
                    And again, life seemed glamorous because on the one hand we met people of the
                    art world. On the other hand we came to know British intelligence officers,
                    diplomats, and Foreign Office officials. And, lo and behold, we met another
                    couple that almost mirrored us. They were very important to us. He was a member
                    of Parliament. She was an attractive Scottish wife. And they, like us, had three
                    girls and one boy. He was ex Royal Navy and both of us were in government. They
                    lived nearby us and we had a lot of fun together. Our kids were all more or less
                    same age, and played together. We showed them how to play Kick the Can and they
                    taught us Scottish dancing. They had a boat and we all went sailing on the
                    Solent. Good stuff. At that time there was the problem over the Suez Canal. The
                    British were very angry with our government, but not with us personally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah, this was 1956.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. And I sort of had to defend our government among my British friends.
                    The US was definitely frowned at, at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Eisenhower essentially pulled the plug on the French
                        and the British.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Right. But it didn't disturb our liaison.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let me ask you about that, because just prior to
                        this Suez thing one of the things I've heard was that all communications
                        with the British shut down. Did you experience that or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No not on my circuit. They might have in the front office, so to speak,
                    But the intelligence work and liaison continued in my office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, were you aware of what was — I mean this is — the
                        British and the French had to put together an expeditionary force, which was
                        not easy for them at that time. Were you picking up?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>KELLY: Well no, not in the liaison circuit that I was on. We were Cold Warriors
                    dealing with the Cold War and not with the Egyptians. And I don't think I was
                    bothered or cared what was going on in the so-called front office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then did you find that the aftermath of the Suez
                        crisis, that this put a crimp in your work or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No, because as I say, we were working on entirely different problems—how
                    we could prevent strategic supplies getting to the Soviet Union; how to counter
                    their efforts to shape public opinion or to recruit young people, or
                    propagandize. I was mostly working with interesting and colorful people. People
                    that had experiences like our former OSS people had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you run across Ian Fleming at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You know, in a way, particularly during World War II, the
                        British special operations people or just the general intelligence community
                        had put together an awful lot of rather fancy things about deception and all
                        that. And there seem to be a proclivity to enjoy special operations and all
                        that, and I think we picked up some of that. Did you find that there was a
                        certain relish on a part of the British in getting involved in this sort of
                        thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. They had their department of dirty tricks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then how long were you in London?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: From '52 to '57. It was a good for me to be there. I think I was doing
                    well in the CIA. My boss was not very popular with the rest of his crew, but he
                    liked me and I felt that I had a good career ahead.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: After my five years there it was time to move on. But in Washington I
                    didn't feel my future looked as bright as I had thought earlier. They wanted me
                    to go to Florida to get ready for the operation in Cuba.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bay of Pigs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: The Bay of Pigs. But I didn't want to go to Florida and I didn't speak
                    Spanish and I thought Cuba thing was not my meat. So I, turned it down and felt
                    rather let down in Washington after the high life of London.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And also I was having the problem that so many of us in the CIA were
                    having, of hiding our true employment. People asked “What do you do?” Well, I
                    work for the State Department, or I work for the Department of Defense, and it's
                    all a lie. I didn't feel comfortable doing it and then getting into the funny
                    situation when friends said, I'll give you a ride to work and they'd drop me at
                    the State Department where I would be half a mile from my real office. I had to
                    pretend too much. And another thing was when one of my daughters said, “Daddy,
                    why can't I come to your office? Mr. McGee's daughter went to his office but you
                    never invite me to yours.” About then I realize it was not the kind of life that
                    I wanted to continue to live, It was not the real me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And I had had enough contact with the Foreign Service in London to realize
                    that that's where I should be. So I applied. I was interviewed, and took an oral
                    exam. I didn't have to take a written exam. I guess they were short of economic
                    officers, so I got through the orals OK.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You remember any of the questions that were asked of
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I remember one that amused me. They said since you've got a naval
                    background, if you had a ship in the Great Lakes and you wanted to take it to
                    Florida how would you do that? So I gave a sequence of waterways and places that
                    I would pass. What they wanted was something off the top of my head that I
                    hadn't prepared for, but knew. I guess to see what kind of a presentation I
                    could give. Anyway, I passed. I came home one night after more interviews at the
                    State Department and said, “Get ready to pack we're going to Sudan.”</p>
                <p>“What? Where's Sudan?” After my wife looked it up, she said, “How could you do
                    this to our family with small children? Are you nuts? You are asking too much of
                    us.”</p>
                <p>But when I mentioned another family going out there that we knew, that made a
                    difference. It was the family of a Smith grad my wife knew. They were going to
                    Sudan at the same time as we were.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Uh-huh.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: The father was there as a second secretary. I had known him in the agency
                    where actually he was quite senior to me. And I was first secretary, which
                    seemed a funny irony to me. Anyway, that helped my wife over this hurdle because
                    they too had several children.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mm-hmm.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And so we went by ship to Rome then flew from Rome down to Khartoum on
                    what was then known as the BOAC (the British airline). BOAC we soon learned
                    actually stood for “Better On A Camel.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: (laughs)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Anyway, planes flew in and out there in the evenings because the hot air
                    at midday was not good for takeoffs and landings. The air was too thin. We
                    landed there in 1960—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were there from 1960 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: To '64. We stayed at the Grand Hotel first as our quarters were not quite
                    ready. The hotel was right next to the zoo and had big old fans going around and
                    safragies in their jellabiya and head scarves. It seemed right out of Hemingway.
                    We could hear the animal sounds at night and the Blue Nile ran at the edge of
                    the property. I felt I was in a film set.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The kids must have been fascinated.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Oh, they thought it was great. My wife still had her doubts. But I must
                    tell you four years later she was in tears on leaving.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: We got into a house enclosed by a wall and had an embassy driver on call
                    for several of us, not exclusively mine. The ambassador was named Moose,
                    M-O-O-S-E.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Old and very much an Arabic hand.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: James Moose. One of the first things I remember he said when we met was,
                    “Giles, I find it hard to believe these Sudanese are Arabs because they're so
                    nice and so calm.” That was his 1960 evaluation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The British — I mean the Sudanese Civil Service, were
                        still at that time the top civil service of the British Empire. The Sudanese
                        had a great reputation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It was only about four years after the Sudanese had got independence. It
                    was in '56 when they got theirs, and we were talking in 1960.</p>
                <p>I took over as head of the economic and commercial section of the embassy. I
                    didn't know much about my home office as I'd not worked in the State Department
                    for long, and felt quite unfamiliar with it at that point. But there I was in
                    the field working for it. I had to learn the requirements and write the required
                    reports. I loved the new responsibility I had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I had to deal with the (laughs) with the AID people, (Agency for
                    International Development) who outnumbered us in the embassy. And at the country
                    team meetings, where all the heads of departments met with the ambassador, I
                    found myself sometimes at odds with the AID people. They had lots of money and
                    more people and more projects than I felt was appropriate. I tried to keep an
                    overview of the country, which is as you may know is the largest in Africa. It
                    took a while to get familiar and comfortable in my assignment but I grew
                    critical of AID for trying to do too much. More than Sudan could absorb. Maybe I
                    should leave it at that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I do want to cover your impressions and what was
                        going on in Sudan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Well, let me put this to you. It was a benevolent dictatorship under
                    General Abboud. The Sudanese had not yet entirely found themselves as a new
                    state. Their biggest problem was over sharing the waters of the Nile for
                    agricultural purposes with Egypt. In the Sudan political parties were not
                    permitted at that time. Our political officers sometimes leaned on me for leads
                    because of my economic and commercial contacts. Sudanese would hardly ever visit
                    a political officer in our embassy, but some felt free to see me about economic
                    and commercial matters. Thus I sometimes picked up information about politics
                    along with economics and commercial matters. I felt pretty happy with my role
                    there. As you know, the political officers often thought they were “top dog” at
                    an embassy. It was nice to come to some meetings with political information they
                    didn't have.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: (laughs)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: The Sudanese were not by nature business people. Therefore a lot of the
                    expatriates in Khartoum were really running the businesses. At the time, the
                    Sudanese were sort of second and third echelon people learning to run the
                    business. The Sudanese were by nature nomads and camel drivers and farmers. But
                    there were exceptions. I became a member of Rotary and got to know as many
                    business people as I could. I also needed to get out of town and put together a
                    little expedition that included my family and a USAID family. We made up a
                    caravan of a truck and two Jeeps (with off-road tires) to explore the western
                    part of the Sudan, places like El-Obeid, Kadugli, Umm Ruwaba, Dilling, El Duiem,
                    and Bara. That trip report for the Department also appeared, (edited) in The New
                    York Times (April 19. 1964). I made a point of flying down (no roads) to Juba
                    and Yei. Juba is the major southern city near the Congo border where the White
                    Nile runs through swamps. It's marshy there. At my time, oil had not yet been
                    discovered in the South. The main industry when I was there was raising tobacco,
                    tea, and coffee. British, Greeks and Italians were running the plantations.
                    Christian missionaries were present.</p>
                <p>Most of the agricultural commerce of sorghum and sugar was centered around
                    Khartoum. USAID were introducing and helping the Sudanese to grow wheat. Wheat
                    would have a market in India, which at that time was suffering from food
                    shortages. I became interested in trying to promote it. I did the preparations
                    for a U.S. PL (Public Law) 480 Agreement. The new ambassador, Ambassador
                    Rountree, signed it. The AID mission was still trying to do too much. The
                    Sudanese were always willing to say yes to more chicken farms or such a things
                    as movie equipment, even though they didn't know what to do with it all.</p>
                <p>There were no paved roads out of Khartoum at that time, so it seemed much like
                    living on an island. However, there was a primitive railroad system. But a paved
                    road was needed between Port Sudan and Khartoum. We were developing roads in the
                    Sudan. It was so interesting that both the Chinese and the Russians were also
                    present in Khartoum at that time (1964).</p>
                <p>At one point there was a incident in my home that I shall not forget: One night
                    my wife woke me and said, “Somebody's in our room.” We then were sleeping on the
                    ground floor and the children were on the second floor. Sure enough, I saw a guy
                    going through our closets. I didn't wear much at night, and I think I must have
                    been near naked when I jumped out of bed with no weapons, but I could make a
                    pretty loud noise. So I shouted and yelled and waved my arms. The thief fled and
                    I followed him. He found the front door locked so he headed upstairs, which was
                    the way he must have come in. But that got me excited because that's where my
                    children slept. I chased him up the stairs still yelling. He went out on a porch
                    and jumped over the railing and disappeared. It was pretty scary.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes. Well, was the division between the north Islamic
                        side and the southern area which was Animist and Christian? One was black
                        and one was Arabic. This is a pretty pronounced division, isn't it, in
                        Sudan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes indeed, it was. And there were practically no Arabs down there. And
                    there was a feeling at the time that they had to bring some of the blacks up as
                    at least tokens in the government as administrators. That was so that
                    southerners were represented in the administration. There wasn't a strong
                    feeling for rebellion that I was aware of in the early '60s. That was to come
                    later. There were, however, a few rebellious people causing trouble who were
                    locked up, but no widespread movement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there tribal conflict in those days?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Not that I knew of.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How stood Islam in those days? I mean was it aggressive or
                        was it just sort of all pervasive, or what? I mean the enforcement of
                        Islamic rules and that sort?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Stu, I did not feel that there was any pressure. In Khartoum, of course,
                    we heard calls to prayer, but there was no vigilante, no religious police that I
                    new about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because I was a little earlier in Dhahran we had religious
                        police in Khobar and all.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: None of that. None of that. It all seemed very peaceful and a little
                    backward, but slowly emerging. And as I say, it was a benevolent
                    dictatorship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how about Nasserism? I know around that time in the
                        souk you would find jokes with Nasserists pictures on them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: The only issue with the Egyptians was Egyptian economic pressure. They
                    wanted to control as much commerce as possible. I think Egyptians felt that if
                    there was any kind of a political vacuum created due to the exit of the British,
                    that Sudan would be under their sphere of influence—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you mentioned Lebanese. The Lebanese in so much of
                        Africa are sort of the mercantile —</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>KELLY: True in the Sudan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: — group, sort of like the in other places the Chinese and
                        the Jews. Were these sort of the economic people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes, they were the exporters of Sudan's long staple cotton, which was a
                    major export. But the Sudanese generally were not commercially minded. So the
                    Lebanese had filled in for years. They weren't newcomers; the Lebanese and
                    British simply continued running what they had always been running.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And they took Sudanese in as understudies and put their name on their door
                    so it looked like a Sudanese operation. There were also businesses in the Sudan
                    run by French, Germans, English and Scots.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mm-hmm.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: — Also Italians, mostly doing import and export.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now looking at the Sudan, where did the stuff get —
                        how did it get out of there? Did it go to Port Sudan or —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Port Sudan was the major export port— I can't know of anything other than
                    Port Sudan and Egypt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a railroad going ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: There was no railway into Egypt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really? I thought when Kitchener came down he'd build a
                        railway all the way down.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It wasn't there when I was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, maybe he didn't.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>KELLY: The railroad ran down to - Wadi Halfa—that was the railhead. Then freight
                    went by boat to the Nasser Dam, then by railway to Cairo or Alexandria. I made
                    that kind of trip once to Cairo.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Nasser Dam while you were there —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It was being worked on and it was a problem. What could be done about the
                    flooding of Abu Simbel when the dam backs up the Nile? There was the idea of
                    building a cofferdam around it. But in the end they raised up Abu Simbel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get to mess around in boats on the Nile?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Oh yes. For me it was sort of a heaven because of a very active sailing
                    club on the Blue Nile. The club's headquarters were on Lord Kitchener's gun
                    boat, the Melik, which was used at the battle of Omdurman. In fact several
                    gunboats fought there, but the Melik was the only one that was still there. It
                    was on the Blue Nile and became the clubhouse for the Blue Nile Sailing Club. So
                    I owned one of the British sloops made out of sheet metal, not wood because wood
                    would be torn apart by the extreme dryness. From a distance they looked like
                    ordinary wooden boats because they were painted bright colors. I had one; they
                    were all named after animals. Mine was Mongoose. I sailed a good deal and once
                    won the “Ambassador's Cup.” But there was one guy, a Greek, and there were a lot
                    of Greeks in the Sudan, one guy named Magliveras and his wife I could seldom
                    beat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: (laughs) Speaking of Greeks, one of the things I learned,
                        I served in Athens for four years. And I was informed and I saw that the top
                        belly dancers of Egypt came out of Alexandria, but they were Greek. And I
                        was wondering did you have good belly dancing in Khartoum?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes we had attractive Greeks who came up to Khartoum from Alexandria on
                    business. We partied with them. In fact, we did a lot of partying because when
                    you live on an “island” like Khartoum, you had to make your own entertainment.
                    We partied at the large houses that the Greeks, Lebanese and British owned along
                    the Blue Nile. We did not play on the White Nile because of the Bilharzia
                    worms.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bilharzia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: There was no Bilharzia problem in the Blue Nile. So we could water ski and
                    sail and enjoyed all kinds of water sports there. And that's where the best
                    expatriate homes were.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the Sudanese officials, because as an
                        economic person you — statistics were your lifeblood and all that. How did
                        you find that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Not very sharp, but pleasant and polite. Things got done on Sudanese
                    timetables, which means slowly. They didn't seem to get enthusiastic about
                    projects. But they moved along slowly and were very pleasant. We had a problem
                    socializing with them because of women. They seemed uncomfortable at parties
                    because we were with our wives. They never brought their wives. We didn't even
                    meet their wives.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And so socializing was rather limited and stilted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mm-hmm. The head of it was —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: General Abboud.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Abboud. What was your impression of his rule?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I've said benevolent. How he dealt with the Sudanese themselves was hard
                    to tell because there was so little public information available except through
                    Sudanese I might meet. I think there was not much complaining about the
                    government. But I did hear of heavy-handed repressions of the Muslim
                    Brotherhood. Some of the university students were objecting to Abboud's rule.
                    But it wasn't serious. Nobody was in the streets, nobody was shooting. There was
                    repression, but — it didn't seem to be inciting rebellion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Something — again, I'm going back to the time I was there,
                        '58 to '60 and in Saudi Arabia — something that kept being thrown in our
                        face in Saudi Arabia was our relations with Israel. Did that come up
                        much?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No, not at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't a cause.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>KELLY: It was not a problem that I recall. In the paper—an English paper, there
                    was no sign of it. I didn't read Arabic and there were no radio programs in
                    English. Most everybody of consequence spoke English, thanks to the British.
                    Word of mouth or The Sudan Daily provided us with local news and opinions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the things that I've heard from people who've
                        served farther south in Africa, particularly in Tanzania, other — Nigeria,
                        those places, was sort of the unfortunate hand of the leaders who went
                        through the London School of Economics. You know, they'd be into socialism
                        and all that sort of stuff. I suppose we call it left wing, but did that
                        permeate in the Sudan or they were doing their own thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Well, you know there was some of that in the Mahdi family, who were
                    religious leaders there down through history.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Religious to the former Mahdi of Omdurman and all that
                        sort of stuff.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Right. But the Mahdi leader who I met had been educated in England and the
                    United States. And I think they were waiting for the day that democracy would
                    come to the Sudan, but they were not — as far as I could tell — in combat with
                    the regime. I did know them socially and the Mahdi I knew was probably in his
                    late 30s and a very attractive guy. He had several wives. One of them — Sarah —
                    was educated in America and became friendly with my wife. My wife volunteered at
                    the UN (United Nations) Mission there. She and Sarah talked about liberating
                    women and bringing them into the 20th century. But as I say, there were no rabid
                    movements I knew about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there much spilling over from Ethiopia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: There were some refugees from — Eritreans. Eritrea hadn't got its
                    independence at that time and was still part of Ethiopia. But a number of
                    Eritreans did work that the Sudanese would not do, especially domestic women's
                    work. We had an Eritrean mother's helper or nanny. You couldn't get a Sudanese
                    woman for that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: OK, you left there in '65?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: In '65. Not long after Kennedy was shot.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah. How did that go? I mean, you know, in many places it
                        really hit a lot of people you wouldn't think would have been affected.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. And that includes the Sudanese. I don't know how much was — formality
                    of coming to our embassy with regrets, but I thought a lot was heartfelt, and
                    they shared the shock that we Americans felt. I think it was beyond doing the
                    polite thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah, I was in Yugoslavia at the time and all the flags
                        were half-mast and I mean there was a tremendous sympathy. I think it was
                        really a generational thing. Here was a young, attractive man where most of
                        the countries were run by rather —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Well, he represented hope for a better world. The hope that I think was
                    shared around the world that this attractive young man was going to somehow
                    bring better times to the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's hard to, you know, today to — for people to
                        understand. I mean this was a worldwide event.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: He was a world symbol — of a good future.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah. OK, well Giles this is probably a good place to stop
                        and we'll pick this up the next time. You let the Sudan in '65 and
                        whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I want to say one thing more. The sailing and tennis there were important
                    to me in that remote country. I played tennis at the Sudan Club. But the Sudan
                    Club didn't have any Sudanese members. It was a British club that had continued
                    after independence. It was the spot where all the British expatriates and
                    diplomats would retreat from the Sudanese scene, to drink and play games and
                    celebrate English customs and holidays. So I played tennis there regularly. Hard
                    courts would not work in the Sudan because the reflection of the heat would be
                    overwhelming, so they had grass courts. And they had to have a number of them so
                    that there would be some soaked, some drying out, and a few ready for play. They
                    were in constant rotation.. And to play in that kind of weather you had to be
                    well watered — I mean, you personally. They served a drink called a “lamoon”,
                    which was made out of a combination of lemons and limes sweetened and iced. I
                    well remember how good a big pitcher of it looked being brought to the court by
                    a safragi with the ice tinkling in the pitcher. It was a perfect refresher for
                    that dry climate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sort of replication of the old colonial life to a certain
                        extent.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>KELLY: It was. It was an extension of it. These guys came out in their turbans
                    and, and did their thing just as they had done I suppose when Kitchener was
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah. OK, well where'd you go in '65?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Back to Washington by way of England where I stopped to see old friends
                    there, then back to the Department. I was asked what I'd like to do and I said,
                    “Look, I know so little about the Department, left in such a hurry, that I'd
                    like a job in the Department now rather than another overseas assignment. I
                    thought the best place for me to get to know the place would be in the Bureau of
                    Public Affairs</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: OK, so we'll pick this up in '65 when you're Bureau of
                        Public Affairs. This is with Giles Kelly on the 17th of December and we'll
                        put it at the end here. So we'll pick this up the next time, but you want to
                        —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Wait. I should mention the Yale Law School graduate who was out there at
                    the time to help the Sudanese write their constitution. Also, in 1962 I was
                    promoted to the rank of captain in the Naval Reserve while there and I did my
                    naval duty, so to speak, with the US fleet in the Persian Gulf.</p>
                <p>Also, my wife had a serious health problem that affected me and my career quite a
                    bit. Also, I sat next to Kim Philby, the Russian spy, at a lunch for him at the
                    British Embassy</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The spy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: The spy. At that time he was working, I believe, for the Manchester
                    Guardian. I also chatted up a friendly Russian diplomat posted there. I should
                    mention that the Chinese were building a residence right next to ours.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you say Chinese you're talking about the Mainland
                        Chinese.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Mainland Chinese. And there were two big US projects that were being
                    undertaken while I was there. One was making the film called “Khartoum” and the
                    other was building a Hilton Hotel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Charlton Heston, Laurence Olivier.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>KELLY: Yes, but I didn't deal with them. I dealt with a fellow named Blumstein,
                    who wanted to produce the film “Khartoum. This was my professional work. —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah, yeah, yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And also for my country I found myself at a little Sudanese nightclub
                    called Elite Corner dancing with the head of Sudan Airways. That was Sudanese
                    “high life.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: OK, well we'll pick this up the next time around.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes —Where I left off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I got it. OK. Today is the 3rd of January, and I wish
                        everybody a happy new year. It's the first interview of 2011. This is with
                        Giles Kelly. Giles, we left you, you're leaving Sudan. But something I'd
                        like to — you put an addition on about your life in Sudan. And it strikes
                        me, for a political officer that you're able to circulate — I mean it's
                        basically a pretty small community, and you talked about playing tennis and
                        all this. I would say this would be a great place — I'm not putting in sort
                        of the secret intelligence, but a good way to find out what's going on
                        because it's small enough, particularly in those days, that you really could
                        get a pretty good idea of who's doing what to whom and all that sort of
                        stuff.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. Since I had been in intelligence I was sort of tuned in to who in
                    Sudan is CIA and who is British Secret Service, and what concerns they might
                    have about the Chinese or the Russians there. That wasn't my job but I could
                    guess what the CIA station chief was worried about, which made life more
                    interesting for me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the equivalent of — what do they call it, the Islamic
                        Brotherhood or, you know, this radical movement in Egypt — was that
                        reflected down there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No, not at the time. It might have been at the university; I wasn't
                    acquainted with that. I was covering economics and commerce. Even in the country
                    team meetings I don't recall that a political officer talked much about the
                    Brotherhood or about any radical movements in higher education at that time
                    there. But later that is where it all came to a head and spilled out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was sort of the lower half of the Sudan — which as of I
                        don't know the next few days I guess they're going to have an election down
                        there — but was there anything like an independence movement or any thought
                        of it or anything like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>KELLY: I traveled down there and, again, I wasn't looking at the political side.
                    I was interested in what was being produced and what the economic and commercial
                    outlook was. But I would say, Stu, that there was no movement for an independent
                    state. There was a good deal of resentment toward the Arabs in the north for not
                    giving them opportunities or their fair share of living in the country. That is
                    to say, they were not given jobs, they were not given facilities, road building,
                    schools, libraries that were being enjoyed in the north. So there was a feeling
                    of discontent from the standpoint of what was — they felt was their right as a
                    member of the Sudan nation. But nothing then about a separate state.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, were you picking up anything from Christian
                        missionaries who were — obviously Christian memories don't get anywhere in
                        Islamic area, but in the south where it was mainly Animist and Christian,
                        were they at all a factor, the missionaries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. And what I've just said I picked up more from the missionaries than I
                    did from talking to the natives, because many of the natives did not speak much
                    English and didn't care to talk particularly with me. But I was talking with the
                    local officials who were indigenous and a few of the missionaries. That's where
                    I heard of inequality treatment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah. It's sort of a racial thing too. The north was
                        Semitic and the south was Nubian, or whatever you want to call it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Absolutely. They were either Christian or Animist.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: OK. Well, then you left the Sudan when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: In 1964. I headed back home, stopping in London to see old friends and
                    have a little rest. I had a feeling at that time, since I had been almost
                    immediately sent to the Sudan when I joined the Foreign Service that I needed to
                    get familiar with the State Department. So I said I would like to have a tour in
                    the Department and I thought it'd be great to be in the Bureau of Public Affairs
                    because that would provide wide contacts in the Department. So that became my
                    assignment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: OK, you were in the Bureau of Public Affairs from when to
                        when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: From early '64 to'70. But I did have a break. In '68 I was recalled by the
                    Navy for active duty.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mm-hmm.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: At State I was head of Conferences and Speaking Arrangements. At one of
                    our foreign affairs conferences at the Department for top officers in the
                    Executive Branch, there were several admirals, I let them know I was pleased
                    they came, and that I was a captain of the Naval Reserve. I said I thought that
                    the Navy and the State Department were natural brothers in arms, so to speak
                    wherever we met in the world. Later I was asked: “Would you like to come back on
                    active duty?” I said, only if I can get leave from the State Department. I
                    didn't want to go permanently back in to military service. This was during
                    Vietnam and they said that my skills as a public affairs officer were
                    needed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mm-hmm.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: So I was ordered to Norfolk to the headquarters of NATO (North Atlantic
                    Treaty Organization) there. It was a joint naval headquarters for our navy and
                    for NATO Navy. I served on the admiral's staff. I dined in the admiral's mess
                    for lunches, and hobnobbed with several of the foreign admirals. It was a
                    wonderful experience including promoting support for NATO in this country and
                    accompanying the admiral abroad in his private plane. It was an interesting job.
                    I had a staff three officers and about 15 men.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long were you doing that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Just for one year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: OK, well let's go back to the time when you came back in
                        '64? When you were in Bureau of Public Affairs. Who was the head of Public
                        Affairs at that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: The assistant secretary for public affairs? I cannot recall. There was a
                    wonderful black woman who was deputy assistant of public affairs and my pal. I
                    really liked and admired her a lot. She's now passed on —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's see, there's James Greenfield and —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Greenfield. That's who.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, they don't have it here (in a book)—</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>KELLY: She was a lovely tall black woman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, when you went off to the Navy was when we really
                        started beefing up our presence in Vietnam. This must have been — Vietnam
                        must have pretty well dominated what you were doing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It did. Rusk was secretary at the time and as chief of speaking
                    arrangements I made arrangements for some of his speaking trips and sometimes
                    accompanied him. It was exactly what I wanted to do, to get to know the
                    Secretary of State, and see how State worked within our own country when looking
                    for support for the foreign policy, and to promote understanding of the Foreign
                    Service, which was then lacking in my view.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well first place, what was your impression of Dean Rusk
                        and how he handled things from your contact with him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I wasn't on his staff so all I knew was from traveling with him, flying in
                    a special airplane with him or at a hotel with him or while waiting to do a
                    speaking arrangement. I can only tell you about one sort of example.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's what I like.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I made a speaking arrangement for him in Chicago. I think it's called the
                    economic or executive council. I accompanied him to the hall where he was to
                    speak. The arrangement he wanted was, instead of taking questions from the floor
                    after his speech, he wanted the questions written on a piece of paper and sent
                    up. I was to receive the questions and sort them to avoid duplicates, edit them
                    and give them some priority. I then handed them over to Rusk. After it was all
                    over he turned to me as he was leaving and said, “Kelly, come with me.” I didn't
                    like his tone and I feared he was upset with me about the job I did. We got into
                    the elevator to his special suite, the VIP suite. He still didn't say anything
                    to me. in the elevator</p>
                <p>I thought, “This is bad.”</p>
                <p>I followed him into the suite. He sat down in a big chair and asked the waiter
                    for a bourbon and water, his usual drink. He said, “Kelly, what'll you
                    have?”</p>
                <p>“A Coke would be just fine, sir.” I said in a thin voice. He then took a long
                    swig and he looked at me. I thought here it comes, I'm fired! There was a moment
                    of silence. Then...</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>“Kelly, tell me how do you think I did tonight?” Wow! I realized here was a
                    lonely man. I was the only person he could talk with. His wife wasn't around. He
                    just wanted to unwind and perhaps get some encouragement from me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And that made me feel important for a moment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It really does show the problem of — I mean this is a time
                        of terrible stress. I mean he had eight years of one of our most wrenching
                        times. I mean right now we're going through a difficult time with a couple
                        of wars going on, but we've had three or four different secretaries of
                        state. And here was a guy that took it all.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And the country was divided and —The Domino Theory, remember that?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yeah. Well, did you find that the questions were
                        basically hostile?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Quite often. There were demonstrations. There were signs. He'd get out of
                    the car and there'd be a group of students and young people with anti war signs.
                    That's because of the advance publicity that he was going to come to speak. So
                    yes, there was a lot of hostility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, when you're sorting out the questions did you — I
                        mean if somebody says, “We think your policy stinks,” or something like
                        that, would you — I mean did you — were you sorting it out for decorum or
                        were you sorting it out so they didn't duplicate, or what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Primarily to pick questions I felt were interesting and to sort out
                    duplicates or questions on different subjects. So that's where I thought maybe
                    I'd gone wrong, that I'd give him questions that he'd rather not answer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you know, as one gets into this thing sometimes it's
                        better to answer questions straight on. I mean they're difficult, but it's —
                        you come out better in the long run. How was he as a person that had to
                        handle questions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Well, I thought he did well. I mean I thought gee, some of these questions
                    are tough, how the hell would I answer them? And then I — he was smooth and he,
                    he could draw on history and on his own connections within the administration so
                    that he would be pretty convincing, I thought. I was convinced that the domino
                    effect was what we were dealing with.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Even today when one looks at it, I don't discount the
                        domino thing. I mean I think that we might have had a completely different
                        situation in Indonesia if we hadn't been there, because I think Sukarno
                        would have taken it down the path of full cooperation with the communists
                        and maybe into the communist camps and that would have taken an awful lot of
                        manipulating and pressure and everything else for us for years to come,
                        years afterwards. I mean one can argue this, but I don't think it's
                        something can be discounted.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Certainly not. Thank goodness it didn't happen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah. Well, then also Rusk's background is being basically
                        a poor southern boy and not sort of an elite looking down your nose at
                        people, I think gave him much more credibility than if we'd had somebody who
                        was out of the prep school and — Yeah, that society. I mean he was —
                        basically poor dirt farmer stock.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: But he was a scholar. And I think that he almost was like a professor
                    sometimes talking with the students.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: He lectured, but I don't know that people trusted him, that he was that
                    convincing. I think that he didn't really turn many minds on these trips.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I doubt if any. Did you pick up the other, almost his twin
                        on the other side, George Ball? And George Ball was sort of kept on as the
                        discipline disagreer or something. I don't know, but you know what I —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I didn't pick up on that, Stu. I didn't know George Ball. I didn't work
                    with him. He was a big man and — but I haven't got any comment really.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right. Well look, did you get involved — I talked to
                        many people. Thank God I never got involved in it, but we were sending
                        Foreign Service officers out as sort of young lieutenants going over the top
                        in the trenches to talk to all sorts of groups where they were getting
                        mauled by the particularly students and all. Did you get involved in that
                        program?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>KELLY: No, the lectures that I arranged didn't seem to have that problem For
                    instance, I'd arrange for a Foreign Service officer to talk to visiting 4H kids
                    in Washington. They'd want somebody from the seventh floor to talk to them.
                    You'd never get any difficulty, demonstrations or arguments from them. They were
                    all very polite. And especially the groups that came into the department. I
                    hosted or arranged more talks in the department than I sent people out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You've always alluded to, but how did you feel about the
                        Vietnam War and our commitment there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I was with the administration 100%. I was appalled at the street reactions
                    and the over-the-top kind of treatment of government representatives by the
                    young people in colleges. I didn't share their view at all. I was very
                    comfortable with the administration and what they were doing. Now of course I
                    look back on that and think, oh boy, I must have been blind.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, one can reopen that wound again and again and look
                        at it. I think with age one can be a little more sympathetic on both
                        sides.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Well, you know, I fought in one war and I was afraid the next would be
                    against communists. I thought they were powerful. They were taking over parts of
                    the world. And I thought they had to be stopped but I didn't see how to hell to
                    stop them if not by war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I subscribed to that. Well, then in your year with NATO
                        were you picking up sort of rifts within NATO over Vietnam? I mean other
                        countries, you know, they were all technically with us but —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Well, no, I did not — Of course it was not NATO's business to consider the
                    war in Vietnam. The main question was, are our allies prepared to deal with the
                    Soviet Union. The discussions, the attitude and the interests is what we focused
                    on. You might hear occasionally of resources being put into Vietnam. There was a
                    war going on there, but at NATO we were focusing on Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a period, I think, when the Soviet Union had
                        developed a Blue Water Navy, as they say. I mean, they put a tremendous
                        amount of investment into building up their — navy. How did we view it at
                        the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>KELLY: We were reacting in kind, or at least we were strengthening our naval
                    forces and we were coordinating with other NATO member naval forces. That was
                    what I was interested in. At NATO Norfolk we organized joint maneuvers with
                    treaty member forces. We'd have one in the Atlantic and then one in the
                    Mediterranean. And we would react when Russian submarines or Russian forces
                    showed off their abilities.</p>
                <p>It was a time when I thought NATO was doing very well in getting everybody to
                    cooperate, that is, have the same type of equipment and procedures. NATO would
                    have naval exercises with maybe six different nations and sometimes more. Ships
                    would exercise together and communicate in English. We were consolidating
                    resources, realizing that the Soviets were strengthening theirs. It was “Cold
                    War” thinking.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any impression of the relative abilities of
                        the various navies in NATO or?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Of course some were better than others, but the British and US were the
                    leaders The Dutch and the Danish were very smart. NATO standards were being
                    upgraded continually. That was an objective that we discussed in our conferences
                    and directives.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, did Sixth Fleet in the Mediterranean, is that out of
                        your area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No. in fact, I visited the NATO naval headquarters at Naples. The admiral
                    was commander of your Sixth Fleet and the NATO forces in the Mediterranean. So
                    he was double hatted there. NATO ran exercises in the Mediterranean just as in
                    the North Atlantic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I would think things in the Mediterranean were
                        probably based on within the first six hours you know who was going — I mean
                        things would happen very quickly there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: —Going to happen in Turkey and the strait? We would try to bottle up the
                    Russia Black Sea Fleet by closing the strait.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any feel for the Greek-Turkish
                        confrontation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No, just what I read in the paper. At NATO headquarters the Greeks and the
                    Turks seemed to get along fine. We were all staff under the Secretary General at
                    NATO headquarters and I didn't feel there was any animosity there between those
                    two. I had friends from both of those countries I would lunch with them or go on
                    trips with them and saw no animosity at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, in 1970 you left sort of the State Department and
                        NATO business and where'd you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I came back to the Department after my one-year of NATO duty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: And personnel said well, you're a NATO expert now so we have a job for you
                    in Brussels on the International Staff. I then joined the Bureau of European
                    Affairs and prepared for Belgium.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mm-hmm.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: That happened in 1970.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you did that was from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: '70 to'74.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your responsibility?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: As a civilian I continued in public affairs including coordination of NATO
                    public affairs in all the NATO countries. That included providing broadcasts,
                    films, publications and speaking teams. Also, because of my military background,
                    I was assigned to work with military public affairs officers of the various air
                    forces, navies, and armies. I have one photo of about 20 female officers from
                    all the NATO countries who work in public affairs. All in distinct uniforms. It
                    was scary. I was doing double duty in PR on the military side and on the
                    civilian side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were our ambassadors with NATO around that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Rumsfeld. I knew Rumsfeld, though I was not on his staff. I was at times
                    invited to his home.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, some say he was a strong manager perhaps a mild way
                        to describe how he dealt with his staff.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>KELLY: Yes, At that time he was thought of as “the boy wonder.” Not much likedat
                    NATO headquarters. He was abrasive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But when you had him this was before he had gained this—
                        How was he at your time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: You see I didn't work under him. I was getting impressions from his staff
                    that he was hard nosed, a strong man who irritated a lot of people. His DCM
                    (deputy chief of mission) was very nice, very well liked. He was the opposite of
                    Rumsfeld. He became a career minister. I take it Rummy was much the same kind of
                    person when he was secretary of defense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there during the Soviet's SS-20 challenge within
                        the intermediate rocket?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think it came a little later anyway. What were your main
                        issues that you had to deal with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It was the fact that all of us at NATO headquarters felt that we didn't
                    have a strong public constituency. I was trying to sell NATO, trying to
                    encourage each country to sell NATO to its citizens, so more resources could be
                    committed to the alliance in men, arms, and money. And how do we do that? By
                    publications, films and speakers. I used to take teams of four speakers, each
                    from a different country, and do a “dog and pony show” in the US going from one
                    city to another. On such a team I would typically have a Frenchman, a Norwegian,
                    and a Greek, all spoke English well and could speak about NATO to a college or
                    foreign affairs audiences.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mm-hmm.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Often we'd get a write-up in a newspaper with a photo saying what NATO is
                    about and how important it is. Then I could feel “Mission was accomplished.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, did you find at that time, particularly in Germany
                        and France, within the university audiences a pretty strong support for
                        NATO?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>KELLY: I wouldn't say strong support. I would say, young people, didn't feel it
                    was so important. And we were trying to indicate how important NATO was in the
                    Cold War situation. I think that talking with groups of older people was easier,
                    they were more concerned with international affairs and military affairs, and
                    were thus supportive of NATO. But it was more difficult at universities and with
                    young people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, we were getting farther and farther away from World
                        War II and the immediate — and the Soviet occupation of so much of
                        Europe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: On the whole, we had good audiences and good reaction in the United
                    States. It made a difference having foreigners talk to them. Americans don't
                    often have a Frenchman and a Norwegian talk to a college groups or to a world
                    affairs group. It increased interest. To me it was very rewarding to go around
                    the country with my teams and raise interest in NATO. Each team member had a
                    certain aspect of NATO to speak on. Besides the work, we had fun as a group on
                    and offstage. Onstage they could be sometimes very entertaining.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you did this what, for four years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes. Up to '74</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: After four years, the question was what to do next. By that time I had
                    spent 24 years as some sort of government official, and unless something
                    interesting came up, I felt retirement at the relatively young at age 53 had
                    great possibilities. I could do what I pleased, or do nothing, knowing I would
                    have a modest income for the rest of my life.So I retired.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After you retired you got very much involved in the
                        Antarctic, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I went to the Antarctic. But that was well before I retired. It was in the
                    late '60s. It was one of those two weeks of active training duty in the Navy. I
                    asked a couple of Princeton friends at the Pentagon “Can you fix me up with a
                    couple of weeks of good training duty?” And they came up with escort duty to
                    Antarctic for a group of foreign officers. That was interesting duty. I even
                    wrote a “Post Report” about it for the Foreign Service Journal. OK, after
                    retirement I first ran a sailing school and worked for the Smithsonian taking
                    foreign visitors, Norwegians, Lebanese, around the United States. They were
                    dancers and musician performers. I had a two-man staff and we went “on the road”
                    to cities as planned by the Smithsonian. There was a divorce at that time.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>Also, I had some GI (Government Issue) left-over college credits so I signed up
                    at American University for a course in art, writing, and television. And while I
                    was at AU I noticed a ridiculous course in canoeing, so I thought, why not
                    sailing? I went to the head of the physical education department to suggest I
                    teach a course in sailing. I think having a master's degree helped. Anyway, they
                    appointed me an adjunct professor. I taught sailing, seamanship, and navigation
                    a couple of years. During summers and winter vacations I took students down to
                    the Caribbean to cruise on chartered sailboats. Being with college kids on
                    sailboats in the Caribbean Virgin islands was great fun.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah, great. Did you run across sort of the overindulgent
                        party life that I understand — I mean not the college kids, but the wealthy
                        have with their boats sometimes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Not really. I knew that this was about the best cruising area in the
                    world, around the British and U.S. Virgin Islands. So when I started teaching —
                    these kids that had enough money would say that they could pitch in to charter
                    one, two, or three boats and sail among those islands. So it wasn't necessarily
                    an upper crust thing with everyone pitching in. But I got a free ride. And we
                    had some great times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's been documented elsewhere, but I wonder if you could
                        talk about you and the Sequoia bit.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Yes I wrote a book about the Sequoia. It all started while I was teaching
                    at AU. One of my students was a caretaker on this famous boat that had been
                    bought by a trust and brought back to Washington from Florida where it had been
                    decaying. The idea was that they would raise funds to restore her and return her
                    to the government as a gift to the American people. But they didn't have a full
                    time captain for her. They would hire some qualified local guy for a trip to
                    Alexandria or to Mount Vernon. Then he was off the boat. So they were looking
                    for someone to take care of the boat full time. The student caretaker suggested
                    they talk to me. So they interviewed me and I was hired. But the boat was in
                    poor condition.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's a Sequoia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: A giant tree.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You might explain what the background of the boat
                        was.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>KELLY: Well, the Sequoia was privately built in 1925 for a wealthy Philadelphia
                    family. They were more or less competing with other rich families at that time
                    to have the best yacht down in Palm Beach during the winter. The Sequoia was for
                    that purpose. But after a year or so they decided the Sequoia was not big or
                    grand enough, so they sold her. The Sequoia went through several hands — but
                    when the depression occurred she was bought by the government to be used as a
                    patrol boat in the Chesapeake to catch rum runners. Looking like an expensive
                    yacht they'd try to sell liquor to her, but they'd get arrested. She was owned
                    by the Department of Commerce at that point and was also used to enforce labor
                    laws in the fishing industry.</p>
                <p>At that time Hoover was in office and his presidential yacht was out of service.
                    So he requisitioned the Sequoia. As a fisherman, he thought she was good for
                    fishing. He also used her to travel to the Virginia Capes for an anniversary of
                    first English arrival at the Virginia Capes. He liked her so much that he also
                    sent her down to Charleston where he picked her up for fishing in Florida. So he
                    was the first president to use her. He was followed by seven other presidents to
                    use her. That would be Roosevelt and —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Truman.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Truman, Eisenhower, Nixon, Johnson and the last president was Ford. Ford
                    took his whole cabinet for a cruise, which gave the Secret Service fits. They
                    didn't want all of them in one boat.</p>
                <p>When the trust brought her back to Washington. They expected to fix her up for
                    presidents to use. They wanted me to oversee her restoration. Their idea was to
                    send her around the country so people could see her and perhaps chip in to help
                    with their idea of returning her as a gift of the American people. They offered
                    cruises on the Potomac for $5,000 to Mount Vernon. Then they also decided for me
                    to take her on a 6,000-mile voyage along the waterways of America as far as
                    Texas. then up the Mississippi and through the Great Lakes.</p>
                <p>I did that. It was a very interesting challenge and fun to see how much people
                    appreciated the Presidential Yacht. Some were in awe of her history which could
                    be appreciated through the photos on board and our talk about her. And after I'd
                    done that cruise and overseen a two million dollar restoration program, they
                    wanted to send her on another trip up the Mississippi. I wasn't interested in
                    doing it again. I contended there is little money up the Mississippi, instead
                    take her along the East Coast where the money is. The Trust persisted. I
                    resigned. A man I'd trained became the new captain for the trip. Not much money
                    was raised. The Trust went bankrupt trying to keep the boat going. Congressional
                    support faded. I was disappointed. She was laid up in 1989. In the year 2000 she
                    was bought from the shipyard by a private person and again brought back to
                    Washington this time to be put into commercial use. She's here now and in good
                    shape.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would think that this would be a little difficult to
                        navigate. You know, I read Mark Twain's Mississippi book, but also I mean
                        it's a very powerful river and changing topography the whole time. Was it
                        difficult?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: It was, and I am pleased you recognize the difficulties. One of the things
                    that helped was meeting a pilot in New Orleans. I contemplated going up the
                    Mississippi in May, which meant that there was a lot of debris coming down as
                    the ice and winter waters were flowing down. I also had received a notice from
                    the army engineer that they were going to close one of the locks I had to pass
                    through. They were going to close it in June. And I thought, my God, I could get
                    all the way up to this lock and it would be closed and all I could do was turn
                    around and come back down. And I would be working against about a four or
                    five-knot current. And the Sequoia only does 10 knots at best.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've, you know, looked at the Mississippi I remember at
                        St. Louis and boy oh boy, I mean that — that's powerful.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: Well, this pilot, was officially a river pilot for only between New
                    Orleans and the Delta. But he knew the upper river too. So I took him and his
                    wife aboard as guests. He showed me how to run the back currents. and make time,
                    as the Mississippi runs there are whirlpools and short cuts to take.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: He showed me how to avoid the strongest currents. In fact, we got a little
                    push upstream at times. I was helped by him as far up as Memphis. Then another
                    nice thing happened. At Vicksburg I met the big sternwheeler Mississippi
                    Queen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Something like that, or the Robert E. Lee? Those names
                        spring —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I was invited to have lunch with the captains and I mentioned I was
                    apprehensive of going on to St. Louis because of debris in the river. The
                    captain of the Queen said, you can follow me. “We do about eight knots. You
                    follow right behind us and we'll clear the way for you.” So that's what we did
                    as far as St. Louis. From there we went up the Illinois River, which wasn't a
                    problem until we got to a railroad bridge that I couldn't get under and didn't
                    open. So I had get a derrick to take off our smoke stack, mast and the awnings
                    on the upper deck so we could squeeze under, then put it all back t again on the
                    other side of the bridge.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: We sailed into Chicago one noon. The bridges were raised for the Sequoia
                    escorted by police boats. When we docked, the mayor came aboard and oh, it was
                    big stuff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, and then you went back down the Mississippi.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: No. We went through the Great Lakes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Saint Lawrence Seaway or?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: — Through the Welland locks that join Lake Erie with Lake Ontario. Then we
                    exited at Oswego, New York and joined up with the Erie Canal. That took us to
                    Albany and the Hudson. We stopped at West Point. The commandant came aboard. In
                    turn, I was invited to review the troops. We went on to New York Bay and down
                    the Atlantic Coast, along the Atlantic, and into the Delaware Bay, then into the
                    Chesapeake Bay and back home. Mayor Barry and a band were on the dock to
                    celebrate our arrival back in Washington after six months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh boy. Well, as a retired FSO (Foreign Service Officer)
                        it's kind of hard to top that, but what have you been doing since?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I left the yacht in 1988. I enjoyed my wedding in '84. Ann was with me on
                    the long trip as photographer and purser. The Trust had expected to produce a
                    book on the Sequoia. However, after I left and the Sequoia fell again on hard
                    times, the trust lost interest in the book. But we had photos, so we decided to
                    write the book and find a publisher. We did a year of research, checking with
                    presidential libraries and newspapers for history and old photos. I organized,
                    with the help of Sequoia's new owner, a reunion of some of Sequoia's old navy
                    alumni. We got them aboard the Sequoia and heard their stories about the yacht
                    which we to put into the book.</p>
                <p>After the book was published we did as most retirees do, we traveled. I had an
                    advantage: as military retirees do, I could fly on military planes when space
                    was available. Thus we flew at times at no cost.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well Giles, I think this is a good place to stop. I want
                        to thank you very much. We appreciate this.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KELLY: I appreciate your interest and your help in bring up these memories.</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
