<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000042">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Milton Barall </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>MILTON BARALL</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: April 10, 1990</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wonder if you could give me a little about your
                        background, kind of where did you come from?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I was born on Madison Avenue, so I don't have to say what city. Lived the
                    first thirty years of my life in New York. I'm a graduate of City College, from
                    which I got a bachelor's degree and a master's degree.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In what subject?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Romance languages and education. I went, the day after I graduated, to
                    France, as a graduate student, and really learned the language that I hadn't
                    learned adequately in college. And then I came back and took the teaching exam
                    and taught French and Spanish in high school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the dates of this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: The bachelor's degree was January '32. I went to the University of
                    Grenoble (France) for six months and got a certificate which contributed toward
                    a master's degree. That was in June of '32, and in June of '33, I had a master's
                    degree in education. I took the teaching exam, which was very difficult at that
                    time, and passed it high enough to be appointed immediately. And that was an
                    achievement in the Depression years. While teaching, I also took a Ph.D. at New
                    York University. I had the doctorate almost completed when the war started, and
                    then I was off in the Army for almost five years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in the Army?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>BARALL: I had been a Reserve officer at City College. Although we had lots of
                    protesters against the ROTC, it was the largest voluntary ROTC in the country at
                    the time. So I graduated with the potentiality for a commission. I had to wait
                    until I grew up and became twenty-one and got my commission as a second
                    lieutenant. I stayed in the Reserves.</p>
                <p>By the time the war came along I was a captain, and I was called to active duty.
                    I was an infantry officer. As was typical, I was supposed to be called to active
                    duty with the 77th Division, but instead I was called individually and sent down
                    to Puerto Rico to serve in the Army Air Corps. On Pearl Harbor day, I was
                    commanding a squadron. After six months, the need for people who could read and
                    write, in the Air Corps was so great that I was made executive officer of the
                    entire base, Boringven Field, which was very important in the war. It was the
                    first stop overseas on the route to build up Northern Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, this was the famous route that went down to
                        Brazil and then over to Dakar and then across that way.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: That's right, we were the first step. First overseas flight for a lot of
                    those pilots. We shepherded them. We had one guide and 50 planes following him.
                    And they were scared. We had a fleet of crash boats to go fish them out of the
                    drink if they went down. They thought that the B-26, for example, couldn't fly
                    on one engine. It could. But they were scared.</p>
                <p>After awhile, the war moved on. After the invasion of southern Europe, I was
                    transferred to Europe in a very interesting assignment, at the SHAEF (Supreme HQ
                    Allied Expeditionary Forces) Mission to France. This was the Anglo-American
                    military- diplomatic headquarters group that was working with General de Gaulle
                    and his government-in-exile. We had the capability of sending people into France
                    to find information for us. When de Gaulle moved to Paris, we moved to
                    Paris.</p>
                <p>My job was working on displaced persons, French and other civilians captured by
                    Germans and used as forced labor—or volunteers who worked in Germany. We
                    finished that part of it and I was sent on into the military government in
                    Germany. But by that time, I had been overseas almost all of the war, so, when
                    they started sending people home, I was one of the first to go.</p>
                <p>I kept my interest in the Army, and I'm a retired colonel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you really had quite a dose, the equivalent to Foreign
                        Service type work in your military time, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>BARALL: Yes, even in Puerto Rico. Everybody important coming or going to Europe
                    had to come through there. For example, General Giraud, who was co-president
                    with de Gaulle. We got a message from the president, whom he was invited to call
                    on: “Hold this guy for three days, the President's not ready for him yet.” So I
                    spent three days looking after him, all in French. That was an interesting
                    experience, because he was a very senior general and co-president. When we got
                    to France, I went and looked him up in Clermont-Ferrand where he lives, just to
                    renew the acquaintance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What brought you into the Foreign Service, and how did you
                        get into it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: A friend of mine told me that the Manpower Act had come into being. I had
                    not heard about it directly or read about it. It occurred to me that that would
                    be a very nice change from teaching. It's the kind of program that was
                    successful only at that particular juncture, where you had a lot of people who
                    had returned from the war, or from wartime jobs which were phasing out, and were
                    free to change their careers.</p>
                <p>I had always thought about being a diplomat, in the '30s, but there was no
                    opportunity. No exams were given. If an exam was given, your chances of passing
                    it were zilch. If you passed it, your chance of being appointed was zilch. So I
                    fulfilled a youthful ambition. I entered the service very late; at age 37. Of 6
                    classes, I was at the bottom of Class Five.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you came in when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: In 1948.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any training before you went out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Just a little bit, a six-weeks training course at the Foreign Service
                    Institute, or whatever it was called at that time.</p>
                <p>But we were all honored because General Marshall, as Secretary of State, came to
                    swear our class in. And he said something wise that I'll never forget. You
                    gentlemen are all diplomats now, and you have diplomatic immunity. I want you to
                    behave yourselves. If you commit any crimes, I'm going to waive your diplomatic
                    immunity.</p>
                <p>I thought that was exactly the right thing to say.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Here you were, you'd been around, you're an older person
                        and all, what was your impression of the bulk of the people coming into the
                        Foreign Service classes in 1948, and of the State Department and all
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, the training class I was in was largely people like myself, older
                    and with other experience, although some of them had been in the State
                    Department and just transferred to the Foreign Service this way. John Steeves,
                    for example, who became Director General of the Foreign Service. A lot of us had
                    military backgrounds. Two of them were graduates of Annapolis, and West Point.
                    They quit their military careers to go into the Foreign Service. So I felt quite
                    at home with those fellows.</p>
                <p>But then, when I was assigned to my first post, I discovered I was about ten
                    years behind the average. That seemed unfair to me, because entry class into the
                    Foreign Service was based on your civilian salary. I had gone back, very
                    briefly, to teaching, which was not a very well-paid profession. But I had
                    already been a lieutenant colonel in the Army, and that was fairly senior. So I
                    said to myself: “Well, this is a highly competitive system; how are those young
                    kids going to compete with me?” Turned out right, because I went from Class Five
                    to One in twelve years and caught up to people of my age.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's very good. Boy! Well, now, your first post, I have
                        you being in Santiago from 1948 to '50. What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I was administrative officer there. I was pleased to be a section chief,
                    as a low-ranking Class Five officer. I thought it was an excellent way to start
                    in the Foreign Service, because if you're going to learn what an embassy does,
                    being the administrative officer is a very good way to do it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also, this was playing to your skills, too, wasn't
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Yes, that was easy for me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find, say, military administration and State
                        Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: It's a little different. That was the time when you could write your own
                    vouchers and things like that in the Foreign Service. I had been an expert in
                    squadron administration in the Air Corps. Also, I was made Executive Officer of
                    the airbase without being a flying officer, but that was because I could read
                    regulations; see that they were followed precisely, and check up on people. I
                    enjoyed the administrative assignment in the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Chile when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Chile was a great country at that time. It had an elected president, who
                    happened to be a very decent man, middle-of-the-road, nice wife who was selected
                    internationally as “Mother of the World.” They changed the government by
                    elections. Chile was one of the few countries of Latin America that was
                    considered to be a real democracy. I think the democracy lasted all of thirty
                    years. That was a good record at the time, compared with the overthrows in other
                    countries.</p>
                <p>So that was a good time, and we had a real good democrat, Claude G. Bowers, as
                    the ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He'd been there a long time, hadn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Yes. With his service as Ambassador to Spain, followed by Chile, he was
                    able to retire, the same as a Foreign Service Officer, with over 20 years of
                    service.</p>
                <p>After my assignment to Chile, when I was desk officer, I heard that the head of
                    the FBI, J. Edgar Hoover, thought that Bowers was too much of a liberal, and he
                    tried to have President Truman fire him. I understand the memo went back to
                    Hoover saying: “Mr. Bowers will remain as ambassador to Chile as long as Mr.
                    Bowers desires. H.S.T!”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Claude Bowers, if I recall, has written several
                        books, hasn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Yes, he was a major American historian.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A very well-known figure. Well, what was your impression
                        of how he dealt with the Chileans and the embassy and all this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I had a very funny experience due to my military training. I had been at
                    the Embassy about a week when a message came from the Secretary of State saying
                    that the Ambassador's locally employed social secretary was the wife of a
                    Japanese collaborator, and she was to be fired immediately. As administrative
                    officer, I was in charge of personnel and could hire and fire local employees.
                    So, I obeyed the orders signed SECSTATE and fired her!</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>Soon, I was called into the officer of Ambassador Bowers, who said to me, “Young
                    man, I want you to know I am the Ambassador, not you!” Later, he explained that
                    an Ambassador who was a friend of the President (as he was) didn't have to
                    follow orders from the Secretary and sometimes had other alternatives.</p>
                <p>But he never held it against me. We became very good friends. He used to call on
                    me to do some translating for him. He deliberately didn't try to speak Spanish.
                    He said, “I'm a lousy linguist. I can understand a lot. I don't want to speak
                    it. I don't want to appear to be foolish.” And he would occasionally tell me,
                    “You don't have to translate this, I understand what they're saying.”</p>
                <p>And after I became Chile desk officer and officer in charge of Chile, Peru, and
                    Bolivia, we had a lot of correspondence. At that time the “Official Informal
                    Letter” was a means of regular correspondence between the Department and our
                    embassies. The desk officer used them to give the Ambassador advance information
                    on problems being discussed and to transmit the mood of Washington.</p>
                <p>With respect to Chileans, he was not a “hands-on” Ambassador. He didn't want to
                    do everything in the embassy. He allowed Eddie Trueblood, a career officer and a
                    competent DCM (Deputy Chief of Mission), to run the meetings and to keep the
                    embassy moving, which I think is the way that a political ambassador ought to
                    work. I think they all have good career deputies. I was in that job twice, and I
                    felt honored that I was selected to serve with political ambassadors.</p>
                <p>In Chile, Ambassador Bowers knew the important people. And though he was not a
                    Catholic and sometimes made fun of Catholics, he was a good friend of the
                    Cardinal, a natural-born leader and a very important figure in Chile. He got
                    along well with President Gonzalez Videla, of Chile. He also got along well with
                    ex-presidents, whom he knew, regardless of their political coloration. In turn,
                    he was highly regarded and the people of Chile considered him a friend.</p>
                <p>You must remember, Claude Bowers was a very experienced politician. He was editor
                    of the old New York World, a very good paper in its day. And in that job, he got
                    to know Franklin Roosevelt quite well. He was at two conventions. At one, he
                    made the keynote address for Roosevelt, and at the other, he made the nominating
                    address.</p>
                <p>He was not interested in economics, nor interested in my sideline reporting on
                    the Antarctic. I didn't want to be typed exclusively as an administrative
                    officer, so I asked Eddie Trueblood to give me some kind of reporting
                    responsibilities. So he gave me Antarctic, with all its overlapping chains,
                    saying: “Nobody's in charge of that, so you do all the reporting on it.” And I
                    did.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I can't help but remark that, I think while he was a
                        professor at Harvard, Henry Kissinger is reported to have said, “South
                        America is a dagger pointed at the heart of Antarctica,” showing how people
                        regarded South America. What was our interest at the time that you were
                        reporting on Antarctica?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, we were just interested. The United States has never set forth a
                    claim, though we and the Russians both go back to 1820 and were the first two
                    nations that did any real exploring in the area. There's a sea named for the
                    Russian explorer, and the United States has legitimate claims to much of the
                    area. Though we don't have a claim, we have bases there, and if we did set forth
                    a claim, we would overlap with the Chileans, the Argentines, the British and a
                    number of other countries. My interest at that time was just reporting on the
                    activity. Both Chile and Argentina were very active in trying to push their
                    claims, and even arguing with each other about who controlled what. That
                    argument is still going on, although they have recently settled ownership of
                    three islands near Cape Horn. For me, it was just a matter of keeping in touch
                    and reporting anything that was happening, if anything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you found Chile at that time, with a pro... democracy,
                        quite open and easy to get to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Yes, yes, the legislature and elections and cabinet members, all
                    relatively honest and open and aboveboard.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now, you came back to Washington from 1950 to '54,
                        where you were, what, the desk officer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I was desk officer to start with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For Chile.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Yes. They had six countries then, in what was called West Coast Affairs,
                    and I soon became Maury Bernbaum's deputy for those six countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Maurice Bernbaum.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>BARALL: Yes, he's on the list of officers you interviewed. After a while it was
                    decided to split the six countries and give him the three northern countries and
                    give me the three southern countries. I had Chile, Peru, and Bolivia, as an
                    officer-in-charge. I was acting officer-in-charge, because I didn't have enough
                    rank to carry this job. They gave me a little differential in pay. The heady
                    part of the job was authority to send outgoing telegrams to three embassies
                    without reference to higher authority. The telegrams ended with the typed name
                    “Acheson” but I was authorized to initial them and send them out. I was still in
                    Class IV of six classes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're talking about the '50 to '54 period. Of course, we
                        were very much absorbed in what was happening to the development of NATO,
                        the Korean War, all this. And these were three countries which were about as
                        far as you can get, in a way, from the United States, in the Latin American
                        sphere.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Geographically they're far away. Not economically and politically.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right, well then what was our interest down there, as
                        you saw it at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: In Chile, we had economic interests, because the biggest copper mine in
                    the world was in the hands of an American company, Anaconda. Kennecott was also
                    there. Chile was, and is, a major copper producer in the world. And those
                    companies were in talking to us all the time. They didn't want to be
                    nationalized, and they didn't want to be taxed out of business. There were
                    always issues like that.</p>
                <p>We wanted Chile on our side because, even though it's a small country of maybe
                    ten million (sic) people, it has a lot of influence and is frequently grouped
                    among the leaders. Like Argentina, it has a lot of well-educated people, and
                    thus had influence in Latin America. For example, there is not much leadership
                    coming out of Ecuador or Bolivia, that is, with respect to other countries. But
                    Chile produces people who talk up and exercise leadership. So we wanted them to
                    be on our side.</p>
                <p>We had no interest in nitrate, which was the principal product of Chile up until
                    World War I, when it tried to monopolize the world market. The Germans invented
                    a synthetic, and that was the end of that. Chile has the biggest natural
                    deposits of nitrate in the world, used for gun power and as a fertilizer, that
                    Chile tried to have us recognize as superior to the synthetic product. So Chile
                    tried to keep us from helping to build plants that would produce nitrogen
                    chemically, because they thought we were interfering with their natural market.
                    They still had some natural market for nitrate as a fertilizer, not as gunpowder
                    any more. This was an issue they would raise regularly with us. Every time we
                    made an Export-Import Bank loan, for example, for someone to produce nitrogen to
                    be used as a fertilizer, we'd get a complaint from the Chileans.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how would we deal with that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: We'd tell them that we have interests, too, and you can't just bend for
                    everything. But we did on some things. For example, when there was a glut of
                    copper on the market, the Chileans and the copper companies both came to us in a
                    joint effort and asked the United States if we would buy copper for the US
                    stockpile. Well, the stockpile happened to be full, and it was a difficult
                    problem for us. But because we had these friendly feelings toward Chile, we took
                    steps and got authority to negotiate with them. Working with the Department of
                    Interior and getting Congressional approval (because Congress has to approve
                    overfilling the stockpile), we got all the approvals necessary to help buy more
                    than was needed for the stockpile and to overfill it. This was after a long and
                    difficult negotiation. When we subsequently sold off some copper from the
                    stockpile we received complaints that we were forcing down the international
                    price of copper. Anyway, the US made lots of money buying copper in a distressed
                    market and selling off the surplus when demand and prices were high.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this one of these things where at the end of this you
                        sort of looked at the Chileans and said: Now you owe us one?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, we felt that way at the time. And they were very grateful, both the
                    copper companies and the Chilean government. They were on the same negotiating
                    team, and the United States government was on the other. They were very grateful
                    to us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you know, one of the things that is said again and
                        again, and particularly this is for historians, we're looking very much at
                        the role of American economic interests, and here you have, say, major
                        copper companies which are American-owned. How did they deal with you? I
                        mean, how influential were the copper companies?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Oh, the chairman of the board would come into my office and say: “Call me
                    by my first name.” They wanted to know me. They had a suite at the Hay-Adams and
                    a couple of elegant gentlemen whose job was to entertain you and tell you what
                    the copper company interests were. They were full-time public relations
                    employees, and when the chairman of the board came to town, he really wanted to
                    know the desk officer. It was an amazing experience for a junior officer.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>I also had an interesting role in this negotiation, because I acted as secretary
                    of the US committee, which included some high-ranking people. But nobody seemed
                    to be in charge of it. I would write up the minutes and circulate them, and
                    arrange committee meetings or sessions with the special Chilean negotiating
                    team. Yet nobody seemed to be able to decide the time had come for us to go
                    ahead. I believe I settled the issue with a few phone calls and memos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you're saying that the chairman of the board would
                        come and see you and all. In the first place, what was the situation at the
                        time? Were there any sort of restrictions on you, or were people saying:
                        Now, watch it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: If there were restrictions, no one ever told me what they were. As a
                    matter of fact, I was surprised at how much leeway I had as a desk officer, and
                    this is something that I think doesn't exist any more. But a desk officer at
                    that time was one man and one secretary, or one man and half a secretary, and
                    you did everything. You did political work, you wrote the national intelligence
                    estimates and policy papers, handled economic negotiations, kept the Assistant
                    Secretary informed, met frequently with Chileans who considered you the
                    principal contact in the US government, etc. You could initiate actions or kill
                    them off. You were the focal point for all actions concerning your country, and
                    people listened to you.</p>
                <p>As a matter of fact, the Assistant Secretary...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Eddie Miller, a man who knew Latin America very well. I think he was born
                    or lived many years in Cuba, spoke Spanish beautifully, had been a vice
                    president in Dulles's law firm in New York. He was interested in Latin America,
                    and he got interested in Chile. He would drop in and sit on my desk sometimes
                    and say, “Mike, tell me all about this.” I would say, “Well, Mr. Miller...” He'd
                    say, “Call me Eddie.” This was like a captain in the Army talking with a
                    four-star general—call me Eddie, let your hair down and talk—and this astonished
                    me. I'm sure that that doesn't happen now. I think desk officers in the
                    department now perhaps have never met with the assistant secretaries. In my day,
                    it was possible to do all of this work because you were alone on the job and
                    your bosses were few and very busy. No, with expanded staffs, I believe there
                    are too many people getting into the act and it must be very difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think so many people have been routed in between. They
                        sort of over-staff things.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: At that time, when I was an officer in charge, my superiors were one
                    office director, one Deputy Assistant Secretary, and one Assistant Secretary.
                    You didn't have all those other guys in between. And you didn't need so many
                    clearances.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, not to belabor it, but to go back because of the
                        interest. How did you see the role of these copper companies, that this was
                        beneficial to both, that this was a good deal for the United States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Oh, absolutely. I thought it was beneficial to both. And I thought it was
                    part of my job to protect American industry. It's so easy for a foreign
                    government to set up special taxes, especially since the industry is virtually
                    controlled by foreign companies. You're not going to lose any votes domestically
                    if you give them a different tax schedule, for example. I thought it was
                    certainly clearly in the interest of both companies, because we were starting to
                    run out of copper. I don't think we produce much copper at all now—if any. The
                    major companies have gone out of business producing here. Eventually Chile did
                    nationalize, but apparently they worked out a deal that was satisfactory to the
                    companies. That would be one of our responsibilities, to try to make sure that
                    they are given national treatment, that they are not treated worse than
                    national...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we have any leverage? What was the tool?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: The United States always has leverage. They wanted Ex-Im Bank loans, they
                    wanted access to markets, they wanted exports to the United States. One of our
                    sayings was: Well, if they're being difficult, you put a slower man on the
                    desk.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As these issues would come up, could you go over and talk
                        within what was then a much smaller department, to sort of get this
                        together?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I had a lot to do with the economic area, which is perhaps one of the
                    reasons I ended up in economics. I got good training in international economics
                    in the jobs I had. Some of it came from discussing common problems with officers
                    in the Bureau of Economic Affairs or the Department of Commerce. I could not
                    only talk with other people in the Department, but I could also talk with the
                    Chilean government, through the ambassador, Felix Nieto del R�o. He had been
                    foreign minister. He was a man of prestige, carried some weight in the
                    diplomatic community, and would listen to me. Sometimes he would drop in at the
                    office, which was rather unusual. Normally Ambassadors would see the Assistant
                    Secretary or the Deputy Assistant Secretary or the office director. But we
                    became quite friendly, the ambassador and I, and he would invite me to lunch and
                    talk things over at the embassy. Since he was an influential man with his own
                    government, that was another way to send clear messages to the Chilean
                    government.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>But nobody ever told me what to say, or checked on what I said. It was assumed
                    that I knew what the policies were and that I was transmitting them. As far as I
                    know, I was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what about the other two parts of this? In the first
                        place, Bolivia. What was our interest in Bolivia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: We had sort of the same kind of deal in Bolivia. But before that, there
                    was a real fundamental revolution in Bolivia, in 1952. A man named Paz
                    Estenssoro, who was living in exile in Argentina, was elected president. Siles
                    Zuazo, the man who ran the revolution within the country became the vice
                    president and subsequently, President.</p>
                <p>But we had a problem of recognition. One of the problems was the Congress (this
                    was the McCarthy era), and a question of whether you could recognize a country
                    that was in the hands of a really revolutionary, labor-oriented government which
                    disarmed the military and gave the weapons to the labor unions. It looked like
                    mob rule to this country.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, we had a visit from a Bolivian named Pati�o. Pati�o was one of the
                    big-three tin mine owners. The tin mines were owned by foreigners who feared
                    expropriation by the new government. Pati�o, with a group of people, came to my
                    office and said, “If you people recognize Bolivia, we're going to denounce you
                    to the McCarthy Committee.” That was a real threat.</p>
                <p>And it was a double threat, because Eddie Miller, the Assistant Secretary, had
                    received a letter from Paz Estenssoro personally, and in that letter, Paz said,
                    “I am a Marxist, but you can trust me.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This, at that particular time, was...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Eddie Miller said: You know, if we recognize this government, and
                    somebody produces a copy of this letter, then we could be in trouble.</p>
                <p>But we cogitated over it, and wondered, and decided that we'd take a look at the
                    people and see what they do. And after awhile I went to Eddie Miller and said,
                    “For once, let's bet on the people. Let's recognize them.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Ok.” And we recognized.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>BARALL: Yes. Even Sullivan and Cromwell, which was not known as a very democratic
                    law firm, at least at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was the New York law firm which Secretary Dulles came
                        from. Well, now, this is very interesting. How did you feel? I mean, the
                        McCarthy period was going on and all of a sudden you had this thing. Did you
                        do anything to clear it with Congress, or to explain what we were doing or
                        anything like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I myself didn't. I assume that Eddie Miller had to do that kind of thing.
                    He set the wheels in motion. We have a congressional relations bureau, as you
                    know, and those are the guys who get saddled with the problem of softening up
                    the Congress. I didn't have to do that, because once the Assistant Secretary
                    made up his mind, he set the wheels in motion. If things went wrong, he would
                    take the heat. I thought he was courageous and that he did the right thing in
                    spite of McCarthy's slanted hearings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a feeling when this went on that at any
                        moment you were going to be sitting before Senator McCarthy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Somehow I wasn't scared at all. I had the feeling until many years later
                    that one had to believe the Department's statements that it wanted aggressive
                    officers who gave their honest opinion, and they would not be penalized for it.
                    And it's true, I was not penalized for it—but neither did it reach McCarthy! As
                    I said before, I would not bear the brunt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you looked at this change in the Bolivian government,
                        what were you looking for that would sort of help make up your mind?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, you know, you've got classic things like: Are they in charge of the
                    country? Are they willing to live up to their international obligations? And
                    they gave us those assurances. We didn't do this lightly. It wasn't a matter of
                    days, it was a matter of months that we fiddled around.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was our embassy? Were they watching? How were they
                        looking at it and what were they reporting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I think they were reporting that they had access to Paz Estenssoro, and
                    that they could talk with him and he seemed to be a reasonable man. But I don't
                    recall specifically that they ever made a recommendation about whether we should
                    or should not recognize.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we have any American economic interests in
                        Bolivia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: We had an interest to having access to tin, because that's something we
                    don't produce. Regardless of the ownership of the tin mines, a lot of the tin
                    came to the United States. Bolivia is a very important mining country. It's got
                    other mines, too, including uranium. And I think we were interested in
                    maintaining good relations with them. Later on, at the request of the Bolivian
                    government, we negotiated and finally bought its tin for our over-stocked
                    stockpile. As was true for Chile, we could not avoid making a large profit when
                    we sold off the surplus at a time of shortage, and therefore, high prices. Still
                    later we supported creation of a mechanism to establish floor and ceiling
                    prices, internationally, for tin.</p>
                <p>Bolivia is one of the poorest countries in Latin America. Those who live up in
                    the Altiplano are great big barrel-chested people, and the ones who live down on
                    the plains are skinny little people, because of the oxygen. The capital is
                    something like 12,000 feet high. We were interested in Bolivia as a country that
                    we thought we ought to be helping in some way because it was so backward. It's a
                    very Indian country, full of illiterates. But the minerals that it contains were
                    of interest to us. At that time there was no drug problem, so we weren't worried
                    about coca, although the people there produced and chewed coca to keep the pangs
                    of hunger under control. It is hard to think of a time when Bolivia had good
                    government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again, we're trying to recreate the past. How did we feel
                        about the “Soviet menace” at that time? I mean, here was a man who is an
                        avowed Marxist and all that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, I think at that time the Soviets weren't really all that active.
                    This was way pre-Cuba. They had their own problems in the post-war world: the
                    Berlin Wall, and how do you get along in four-power control over things? So our
                    problems with the Soviet Union were related to Europe at that time. They were
                    not all that active in Latin America. We did have a Soviet scare in Guatemala in
                    1954, but that's about the first real one that I can remember when we were
                    afraid that the Soviets would move in. Well, they weren't really trying.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Here is something that is often overlooked. Everybody
                        zeroes in on the Eisenhower period in Guatemala, and yet you had something
                        that certainly could have been called the same thing in a way, although it
                        was home-grown, but it could have been played up. I mean, here was a man who
                        was an avowed Marxist—whatever that means.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Oh, that's right. If McCarthy had that kind of information, he could have
                    blown it up into a major incident.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But everybody looked at it, they knew what they were
                        dealing with, and took it and went ahead and...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: We took the risk, and there was no repercussion. Not McCarthy or any
                    other. There wasn't any Jesse Helms at the time — fortunately.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jesse Helms being an extremely conservative senator from
                        North Carolina (we're talking about the 1980s, 1990s), who plays some of the
                        same critical role that other people, including Senator McCarthy, did in the
                        earlier period. Well, you had a triumvirate. Now, the third one, Peru. What
                        was the situation there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Peru was relatively quiet. I think we had one of those nice quiet
                    dictatorships where nothing happened. We had occasional problems with American
                    tuna fishers down there, fishing in waters that the Peruvians claimed were
                    theirs. But these were minor incidents, and I think they've been going on
                    forever. We also had a long-standing problem of American-owned oil lands. But
                    Peru was easy for me. Most of the problems were handled by the desk officer. I
                    didn't have to do much there. But Bolivia was a real job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I'm sure. Very interesting. Well, in 1954 you were
                        assigned to Haiti as the deputy chief of mission, and you served there until
                        1956.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Right, I was a Class Four officer and a second secretary. I think they
                    peeked at the promotion list, because they sent me down as a first secretary.
                    About two months after I was there, the promotion list came out and then I was a
                    Class Three officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Class Three at that time was about the equivalent to
                        colonel.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: That's right. There were no deputy chiefs of mission below Class Three,
                    so this was a really very early promotion in jobs. Not necessarily in
                    salary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get the job?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>BARALL: I didn't ask for it. I had been in Washington for four years, which was a
                    long time, and it was time for me to go abroad again. They were considering me
                    for a variety of jobs. I had developed a lot of what they recognized as
                    political competence as a desk officer there, and as an officer in charge, and I
                    knew the senior people. Inter-American Affairs was a bureau where we all knew
                    each other, at that time. It's so big now that I don't think they can know each
                    other. I didn't think I was in line to be a DCM anywhere, because I was still
                    junior in rank. But I was fluent in French and, apparently, had demonstrated the
                    ability to deal with a variety of problems. And maybe someone up there liked
                    me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The ambassador there was Roy Tasco Davis, who was a
                        non-career ambassador. What was his background, and how did he use you, and
                        how did he deal with the relationship?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: In about 1920, he won Missouri for the Republicans. As a reward, he was
                    made, at that time, Minister to Costa Rica and another country in Central
                    America. And apparently he was very good at it, at that time. He was sort of a
                    homespun philosopher, a Will Rogers type. He had been, for some years, a college
                    president. Not a great college, but a college president. And he was an
                    attractive man at that time—at a time when we had no major problems in Latin
                    America. He got along well with people, and I understand that he spoke
                    Spanish.</p>
                <p>When the Republicans came back into power with Eisenhower, they wanted to reward
                    this man, a good Republican. So, as a retread, in the 1950s, he's brought back
                    and sent to the wrong country at the wrong time. He didn't know any French at
                    all, and that was the official language of the country, though most of the
                    people spoke only Creole. Ambassador Davis had good common sense, was
                    gentlemanly, if not courtly, and was wise in public relations. But he was a fish
                    out of water in Haiti.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The language was Creole.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Ten percent of the people speak French and the rest speak Creole, and
                    most of them are illiterate. And I don't know how you're going to make people
                    literate in any language if they don't have a written language and they're
                    illiterate anyway. That's another point.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Davis rarely told me what to do though I tried to keep him informed of
                    what was happening on a daily basis. He was interested in knowing the important
                    people because he was a politician. He knew the president. But he never
                    questioned the motives or actions of the president.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>Paul Magloire was president at that time. He had taken power through a military
                    junta. But he was then the sole survivor of that junta. For Haiti, he was a
                    pretty good president. The people would say: We're accustomed to presidents who
                    steal, but they must leave something for the people. And he was smart enough to
                    leave something for the people.</p>
                <p>So Davis wanted to know the president and members of the cabinet and whatnot. But
                    he did not try to talk about anything serious with them, like issues that might
                    arise between the two governments. He was in favor of supporting and aiding the
                    Haitian people, and that was one of his Will Rogers ways of being popular. He
                    sought popularity, and he was popular, because the people knew him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, here you are, the deputy chief of mission. Here is a
                        man not only with political clout but also an older man, a man whom you
                        could respect in other things, at the wrong place, wrong time and all. How
                        did you deal with this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, he wasn't difficult to deal with, because he didn't have an awful
                    lot of interest in what was happening, in the kinds of things that we report. I
                    wrote the whole Weeka, for example, with no input from the Ambassador and only
                    occasional paragraphs from the economic section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A Weeka being a weekly report.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: A weekly report that was then a major reporting instrument, from every
                    embassy, of what happened in the past week. We covered political, economic, and
                    everything else. I occasionally asked our economic man whether he had any
                    information, but otherwise I wrote the whole thing myself. And I would send it
                    in through the ambassador. Almost invariably he just initialed it and sent it
                    on. In other words, I gave him an opportunity to check or change or do anything
                    he wished, but he didn't seem to be interested in controlling what I would
                    consider normal embassy activities, which were left to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were American interests there, from your perspective,
                        during the '54 to '56 period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, it's an impoverished country, and everybody wanted to help the poor
                    people. How you help them I don't know. We had a very big AID program. We had
                    about half a dozen people in the embassy, and we had an AID mission of 36.
                    Curiously enough, one of the people who worked for that AID mission was Papa Doc
                    Duvalier, who was a legitimate MD and a public health physician. We used him in
                    that capacity as a public health technician.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>By the time I arrived in Haiti he had gone into exile because he had political
                    ambitions. But the chief of the AID program, and a lot of other people who knew
                    him, believed he should be president, because all he wanted to do was help the
                    poor black people who were undernourished and ill.</p>
                <p>The political problem in Haiti is the constant struggle between the blacks and
                    the mulattos for control. There is an aphorism (which probably comes from Africa
                    because you can hear the same aphorism in Brazil) that says: “A rich black is a
                    mulatto, and a poor mulatto is a black.” Color was the important issue in Haiti.
                    A Frenchman wrote a book about the 79 different shades of color found in
                    Haiti.</p>
                <p>I had a wonderful cook, who was not literate, but she spoke English very well
                    because she'd been cook for American families for about 30 years. She would ask
                    who was at the party last night, and I'd tell her, and she'd say, “Well, I never
                    heard of him. Is he a black man or is he my color?” I thought she was black.</p>
                <p>But the Haitians themselves were interested in graduating people, how they fit
                    with respect to color.</p>
                <p>The US was interested in improving the lot of poor Haitians though the government
                    was not. We also looked after American interests in the major sugar refinery and
                    in sisal plantations. The US also financed a large multi-purpose dam in the
                    Artibonite.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During the Henry Christophe period, or
                        Toussaint-L'Ouverture, I think, the United States helped put down a revolt
                        of mulattos against the blacks who were in control at that time. This was in
                        the 1800 period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, it was after Toussaint-L'Ouverture. I think you're talking about
                    the time of independence, when they started with two separate parts of Haiti.
                    One was run by a mulatto general named Petion, , the other was run by
                    Christophe, a black. And that was around 1804, when they became independent.</p>
                <p>We did have some small business investments and we wanted them to keep going
                    because they provided jobs. The big problem in Haiti was class, and we didn't
                    know how to cope with that.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>We had occupied the country for 19 years. A man named Herres was still there. He
                    was a sergeant in the Marines. His job was supervising the bank, and he learned
                    so much about it that he was paid by the Haitian government to keep on working
                    in the bank. He tried to keep them honest, but they had a mechanism that made it
                    impossible. They had, and they still have today, something called non-fiscal
                    receipts. This was money received from taxes on common things like salt and
                    matches, that went into a separate account controlled by the President. They
                    never were fiscalized, were never put into the accounts, or the budget, or
                    received by the state as revenues. It was available to the president. Some of it
                    went into his personal account, and some into other things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How much control did we have?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: At that time we had no control. The occupation had ended with Roosevelt,
                    in 1934, with his Good Neighbor Policy. We had some controls because we could
                    raise or lower the amount of aid that we were giving them. And some of that aid
                    was very important. The big dam financed by the US Export-Import Bank was
                    supposed to create lots of agricultural land, hydroelectric power, irrigation,
                    water in homes. We were putting a lot of money into loans and some grants. We
                    were also an important factor in road repair and things like that. Because of
                    the climate and the rainfall in Haiti, maintaining a road is almost
                    impossible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How could we use this leverage? What were we trying to use
                        it for?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, we couldn't use it to interfere in internal affairs and tell them
                    to stop stealing. I don't think anybody could have done that. We could have a
                    little bit of influence with the president or with the secretary of commerce or
                    others. But our problems were not major.</p>
                <p>The only fairly large American investment was in the sugar business. The company
                    had land, and they planted it with sugar cane. Then they processed the sugar
                    cane and made sugar and exported it to the US. We rarely had any problems
                    because the head of the sugar company had been there for 30 years, was respected
                    and he knew all the politicians. And whatever he did, pay them off or whatever,
                    he was a good enough public relations man that he almost never came to the
                    embassy for help. He always wanted to know us, of course, in case he needed real
                    help. But in the two years I was there, we were not called upon. He took care of
                    things himself and was a major employer of labor—mostly with few skills.</p>
                <p>We wanted Haiti to be a democracy. The last thing we did, before ending the
                    occupation, was run perhaps the only honest election in that. And a good
                    president was elected.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>But after the US forces left, things just disappeared. We had a very good
                    agricultural experimental station and a very good hospital. Shortly after we
                    left, the hospital was looted, the equipment taken out. At the agricultural
                    research station, whatever equipment they had was taken, food was taken, or
                    whatever they were producing. Experiments were abandoned and they went virtually
                    out of business. They tried later to reestablish the agricultural experimental
                    station under the Haitian government, but it never became important.</p>
                <p>I had a very funny experience in Haiti. I don't know, whether history would have
                    been different if I hadn't been transferred to the National War College. I told
                    Ambassador Roy Tasco Davis that he really ought to try to do something with
                    Magloire, who was a popular president compared to most others. He was not all
                    that brutal. He got his share of the loot, but he was relatively decent compared
                    with others who have run Haiti.</p>
                <p>I suggested to the Ambassador that we have a little visit with the president and
                    see if we can't convince him to run an honest election on the grounds that if he
                    did so, he would go down as a great man in the history book of Haiti. He could
                    be the President who established Haiti as a democracy forever. (At that time the
                    president served a 6-year term and could not succeed himself.)</p>
                <p>Davis was against that. He didn't think it was proper for the US to influence the
                    government. I nagged at him for awhile, and finally he said all right, he'd go.
                    We made the appointment. We went to the palace. And since he didn't speak
                    French, I did the speaking for him. Magloire spoke a little bit of English but
                    not well. The President and all the cabinet, of course spoke French. So I made
                    the pitch and translated for the Ambassador what I was saying, so that he
                    followed the whole thing.</p>
                <p>Magloire finally said, “I will do that.”</p>
                <p>I said, “What a wonderful promise. You will never be sorry, Mr. President.”</p>
                <p>Soon thereafter I was transferred to the National War College. I think I would
                    have stayed on happily in Haiti for a few more years. But I wasn't going to give
                    up the National War College, because I was at the upper limit of the age when
                    you could be admitted. I think, 46 was the maximum age at that time, and I was
                    45. I wanted to go to the National War College.</p>
                <p>After I was transferred, I think both the President and the Ambassador forgot
                    that little meeting, or didn't pay any attention to it. Roy Tasco Davis didn't
                    really want the President to step down. He thought he was running the place
                    pretty well, even if he didn't seem to have great devotion to democracy.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>But an election was held about a year after that. Magloire was unable to keep
                    himself in power. And in that election, it was Duvalier who was elected
                    president. When he showed his real hand, he was not very much interested in
                    helping the poor blacks but in exploiting them, it was too late to do anything.
                    He knew the techniques for maintaining control.</p>
                <p>One other thing. We had a visit from Vice President Nixon. He went to the
                    Dominican Republic and Haiti. I flew to the Dominican Republic as the advance
                    man, and briefed him on the short flight from that country to Haiti. Then I
                    translated for him on a national hookup, which was about four stations. Arrival
                    statements and so forth. The Foreign Minister and the Vice President both had
                    statements, so I translated both ways, simultaneously. I also did a whispering
                    translation for the Vice President when he met the President. I was kneeling
                    behind and telling him what was said.</p>
                <p>After the call on the President, the director of Middle American Affairs, and the
                    Assistant Secretary of State, drew me aside and asked; “What about Roy Tasco
                    Davis. We've been hearing some stories about him. Should we replace him?” That's
                    a hell of a thing to ask of a DCM.</p>
                <p>My answer was, “Well, I don't know, he's got some problems, but he's pretty
                    popular here. He doesn't cause any major trouble. I think I can handle him.
                    Leave him here.” They took that advice.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then, you went to the War College from '56 to '57.
                        And then you went to, you might say, the big leagues, or the bigger leagues.
                        You went to Madrid as economic counselor, where you served from 1957 to
                        1960. It seems like a logical assignment. Did it please you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, I got interested in politics in the 1930s because of the Spanish
                    Civil War, which was a big, big issue in New York City, with the Herald Tribune
                    on one side and The New York Times on the other side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which side did you take at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, I think I read the Herald Tribune, but I was on the Republican
                    side. That is, I could not be in favor of Franco. Franco had been so damned by
                    Herbert Matthews, and other people writing in The New York Times, that he was
                    considered to be a terrible ogre.</p>
                <p>When you graduate from the National War College an officer comes over from the
                    personnel department and says, “Well, here, we're going to talk about what your
                    next assignment is, and we're going to give you some choice. And here are the
                    four jobs that are open.” One of them would carry the rank of minister, as US
                    representative to UNESCO.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>I said, “Well, that sounds good.”</p>
                <p>But the answer was, “You don't really want that job!”</p>
                <p>I went through all those three jobs that I thought they were offering me, and
                    he'd say, “Well, that's not a good job for you. A good job for you is
                    Spain.”</p>
                <p>I said, “I've never been an economist.”</p>
                <p>He said, “There's an awful lot of economics in your political reporting, so we
                    know you can do it.”</p>
                <p>Well, I had had some government economic experience in Latin America. We didn't
                    have major political problems with the countries that I was dealing with, there
                    was a lot of economic activity. So they finally said, “That's the job for
                    you.”</p>
                <p>It was an interesting job, because it combined being the embassy's Economic
                    Counselor with being the Deputy Director of the AID mission. And that put me in
                    the position of coordinating and controlling the two activities.</p>
                <p>The Director of the AID mission was a political appointee, a classmate of
                    Ambassador John Davis Lodge at Harvard. He was a theatrical producer, president
                    of the National Theater, had been married to Gertrude Lawrence. He was there as
                    a friend of the Ambassador and as a good PR man. He wasn't terribly interested
                    in running a mission, though he followed events, was interested in knowing the
                    key government officials, and in general, helping to make the mission
                    successful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It doesn't sound like a very good, professional AID
                        person, somebody who's in the arts.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: He was there to satisfy an Ambassador who had a lot of political clout.
                    Lodge and Nixon had been junior first-time members of the House together; they
                    were the founding members of the Chowder and Marching Society.</p>
                <p>I want to say this. Lodge had a lot of critics, too, but he was the right man,
                    right time, right place in Spain at that time. Because Spain was run by Franco
                    and a handful of people, a lot of them aristocrats, with whom John Davis Lodge
                    felt quite comfortable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was, of course, the Franco regime. It was
                        well-established, and he was at the height of his powers, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>BARALL: Yes. And he had, curiously enough, a cabinet that was full of
                    technocrats, people who were not political. I was informed that Franco didn't
                    interfere with them. They were said to be all Opus Dei, or the principal ones at
                    least were said to be Opus Dei. We evidently didn't know much about it, and we
                    still don't know much about Opus Dei.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain what Opus Dei is. It's a work of God,
                        isn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Opus Dei is supposed to be an organization of sincere, good, practicing
                    Catholics, who believe that you do God's work out in the world in a regular
                    suit, not with a reverse collar. They were very competent technocrats. But it
                    was hard to know some of them well and our reporting on them, in the files, was
                    sometimes inaccurate.</p>
                <p>For example, I had read about the Minister of Commerce, an important man there
                    because he controlled the exchange rate and could favor certain imports or
                    exports. Before I met him for the first time, I read in the files that he was
                    abstemious, very sober, didn't smoke and was perhaps the head man of the Opus
                    Dei. The first time I met him, at a luncheon, he had two martinis and he smoked
                    almost incessantly. Because the AID Mission allocated some 200 million dollars
                    per year as economic assistance to Spain, in part for the use of very important
                    air bases, I dealt fairly often with Cabinet members such as the Minister of
                    Finance, Commerce, and my counterparts in the Foreign Office.</p>
                <p>(It was a big secret that we had nuclear weapons on our B-52s. But after one of
                    them dropped into the ocean, much after my time we couldn't keep it secret.) So
                    our AID program wasn't just eleemosynary, we were getting quid pro quo. We had
                    the airbases, one of them just right outside of Madrid. And we were building a
                    major naval base on the Mediterranean, at Rota.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's the name of the airbase?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Torrejon, near Madrid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We want to come back to the bases, but first let's talk a
                        little about the relationship in the embassy. Did you find it difficult
                        running the AID mission? I mean, you had a putative boss who was more a
                        sidekick of the Ambassador.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: And he had the rank of Minister.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And he had the rank of Minister, which I guess was the
                        real reason why he was given the job, wasn't it, because he wanted to have a
                        high rank? And particularly in those days, the AID man in a major country
                        was often a rival to the ambassador. In this case I don't know so much if it
                        was.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: There had been a lot of rivalry, actually, in many countries, at the time
                    of the Marshall Plan. Because sometimes those in charge of aid were not
                    subordinate to the Ambassador, and could just go about their business. Some,
                    like Harriman, could report directly to the President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know, I was in Greece and heard rumblings about what had
                        happened early on there. How did you find that this worked? There was an
                        awful lot of administration responsibility. Was this difficult in that
                        scenario?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: No, it wasn't difficult at all. It was clear, first of all, that I was in
                    charge of all economic reporting, and nobody ever tried to interfere with that.
                    So I had the economic side of the embassy all to myself. I was the Economic
                    Counselor. Nobody else supervised me in that job except, theoretically, the DCM
                    and the Ambassador. On the AID side, I think Richard Aldrich and I really became
                    good friends. Once again, as I had done with Roy Tasco Davis, anything I sent in
                    on the AID side went through him. I never bypassed him, but he allowed me a lot
                    of leeway. I worked with the program officer and the other people in the AID
                    Mission, regularly. And I was very pleased to supervise the work of the AID
                    staff and work on the budget and the allocations of funds because that gave me
                    access to a lot of people. It also helped my economic reporting.</p>
                <p>The economic and aid programs were major interests in Spain when, under Franco,
                    there was little or no political activity. So I felt I had a key assignment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I found this. I had served as consul general at a number
                        of posts, and often people would come to me because I was dishing out visas
                        for their relatives. They were far more interested in that than just talking
                        to somebody on the political side.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: So I really had no problems. It worked out very well, and I got into a
                    big negotiation, a three-way negotiation. I think I did my best work for the US
                    government in Spain.</p>
                <p>Lodge was interested in big issues. He wanted to get Spain out of isolation and
                    into the world, to be part of Europe. He wanted to get them into NATO. And he
                    wanted them to start being economically competitive, stop running things out of
                    ministries and whatnot and get some competitive enterprise. And I think that was
                    exactly the right kind of position for the US ambassador to take.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>It's difficult under someone like Franco because he controlled everything. But I
                    didn't have any evidence that the ministers on the economic side—minister of
                    finance, minister of economy, minister of commerce—had to go to Franco with
                    everything. They seemed to have lots of leeway, so long as it was not anything
                    that Franco was interested in, and they were doing good things for the
                    economy.</p>
                <p>This idea of having Spain as part of Europe led to talk about a three-way deal
                    between the government of Spain, the International Monetary Fund, and the United
                    States government, in which Spain would modernize its economy and they would get
                    a standby loan from both the United States and the International Monetary Fund.
                    The key action was going to be the devaluation of the peseta.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Peseta being the national currency.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: The assistant director for Europe of the International Monetary Fund came
                    regularly to Spain, and he would talk to officials. He would drop in on the
                    embassy and tell me what he'd heard; I'd tell him what I knew about the thinking
                    in the Spanish government.</p>
                <p>Eventually we got to the point where the Minister of Commerce told me privately:
                    “I am going to devalue. And I'm going to deny it until the day I do it.” Which
                    is exactly the right policy, because people can make an awful lot of money, as
                    you know, on currency exchange if they know it's going to be devalued.</p>
                <p>I was so scared of that information that I telephoned it in from a public booth
                    out in the street. I didn't want anybody in the embassy to know that, even the
                    Ambassador, who was not strong in economics and might have revealed it
                    inadvertently. The Ambassador knew everybody important, spoke Spanish fluently,
                    was very attractive, gave great parties. But I didn't think that he could
                    exercise the restraint necessary not to tell his relatives or friends. I also
                    respected the secrecy of the information the Minister of Commerce had
                    provided.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, boy. Oh, boy. Well, who did you let know?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: John Leddy in the office of Under Secretary for Economic Affairs Dillon.
                    I had met Dillon. He and Senator Fulbright visited Spain to look around. They
                    wanted to play golf, so I borrowed some golf clubs. They took off their coats
                    and ties, they were wearing suspenders and regular clothes. I scrounged some
                    shoes and we went out and played golf. And that was a great time to talk about
                    economics.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>I developed a most great admiration for Dillon, a non-career man who had been
                    Ambassador to France. He had great insight about international affairs in part
                    from his family's famous vineyard in France. He asked direct questions, and he
                    knew what he was talking about. He evidently developed some respect for me
                    through our post-golf talk. We were playing informally and had a beer
                    afterwards. It was a wonderful chance to talk. I had never sat and talked at
                    length with an Under Secretary before.</p>
                <p>I think it also ruined my career, because when he went back and they were looking
                    for an economist to help with what became Kennedy's Alliance for Progress. Mike
                    Barall was the guy...</p>
                <p>This is a digression. John Jova was then a personnel man with Loy Henderson. He
                    wrote to me and said I was to be transferred to the Department as Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary for Latin America, the first one on the economic side. You
                    can fight it, he said, but it's been approved by Dillon; Tom Mann, who was
                    Assistant Secretary; and a skillful and respected Director General of the
                    Foreign Service, Loy Henderson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But to go back to this. Here is something where you've got
                        something very hot. I mean really hot. In other words, the beginning of wars
                        and all, this is interesting. But the actual news that the country is going
                        to devalue, I mean people can made big bucks, or big pesetas on this. Can
                        you even tell your people at the embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: No one. I told no one, not my wife or anybody.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why would he tell you this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Because he knew I was talking for the United States in this particular
                    problem of trying to work out the three-way deal with the United States, the
                    International Monetary Fund, and the government of Spain.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a minor thing, but how would you tell Dillon over
                        the open line?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, I didn't tell Dillon, I told John Leddy. There was no evidence of
                    censorship. It was a public booth out in the street. They had gone to get John
                    to answer. I'm sure I talked around it. I could write, you know,
                    official-informal or something like that. John Leddy had been there, he knew
                    what the deal was, and he talked with the assistant director for Europe of the
                    IMF, just as I did. I knew that he would tell the Assistant Director of the IMF,
                    and Dillon but probably no one else.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, here you've got a man that you felt was doing the
                        right thing, and took an interest in politics in the country, and was trying
                        to get Spain into NATO and the Common Market and all this...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: And into the economic mainstream. The Common Market hadn't...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right, it was before the Common Market. What was
                        the attitude of the other officers towards Franco? I mean, here was a regime
                        that really, for most Americans, kind of smelled. It was the last remaining
                        major country that had a Fascist regime. We had military interests there and
                        all, but still it was sort of a noxious regime in the eyes... What was the
                        attitude and the feeling of the officers, the Americans that you worked with
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: The Spanish Civil War ended in 1939, and I'm talking about the period
                    1957 to 1960. Time had worn much of the animosity, and there were no acts of
                    brutality that you could see, no acts of government oppression. I think the
                    people in the embassy generally accepted, some may even have been favorable
                    towards Franco. You don't have any problems with a guy like that in charge.</p>
                <p>To give you an example, one of the terrible public relations problems the embassy
                    had was all the GIs, all the airmen and whatnot, stationed in the Madrid area.
                    And, of course, as they do everywhere, they would occasionally get drunk and
                    they would drive cars. They had cars when the Spaniards didn't have cars, and
                    there was a lot of jealousy about that. But they also might hit a pregnant woman
                    and kill her, or cause her to lose her child or something.</p>
                <p>And even though there was censorship of the press, sometimes that would be put in
                    the press. It depended on whether they wanted to slug us that day or not. There
                    was a Minister of Information who decided.</p>
                <p>We wanted to have good relations, and we sometimes were able to avoid the
                    unpleasant publicity. We tried to keep the United States from being pilloried
                    unnecessarily in the press. Some Americans found it quite convenient to deal
                    with a government that could control such publicity.</p>
                <p>We did have a big military mission there, headed by a lieutenant general, and a
                    military aid program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we feel at this time that if Franco left, that God
                        knows what would happen and maybe the Marxists might take over? How did we
                        feel about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>BARALL: I think it was clear that the Marxists were totally disorganized and
                    demoralized, and that they didn't appear to be a threat. We followed that kind
                    of thing casually, even in the AID program. My responsibilities included
                    supervision of labor reporting. Some of the people our labor man talked with
                    might have been labeled radicals or Marxists or whatnot, but they had no real
                    influence, even if they did some work of organizing people, as a labor union
                    does. So long as they were acting as a labor union, they didn't have much
                    authority or power because the government could squash it anytime it wanted to.
                    But we had some contact with people like that, and they would tell us
                    things.</p>
                <p>But, as I say, you didn't see or feel police brutality. There was almost no crime
                    because the people knew that crime was going to be dealt with severely. And the
                    Spanish people appeared to be very honest and trustworthy. It was easy to become
                    fond of Spaniards working with you, or servants, who were devoted and
                    dependable. Much more competent than the equivalent in Latin America.</p>
                <p>I think one of the big gaps we had was the lack of information. With censorship
                    of the press, you had a Catholic press which would tell you everything about
                    what was happening in Catholicism, but it didn't tell you much about what was
                    happening elsewhere in the world. So you'd get the Herald Tribune, the English
                    edition, flown down regularly. But it was very difficult to get information
                    about what was happening in Spain, because that didn't appear in the papers.</p>
                <p>As a matter of fact, I had a particular problem. When they convinced me finally
                    that this was the job for me, I said, “Well, I think I can handle economics, but
                    finance, that's a special field, and I'm no expert on that.”</p>
                <p>The personnel man said, “Don't worry at all. Two men in the AID program—one a
                    former professor of money and banking, Ph.D., and the other a professor of
                    finance, Ph.D.—will give you all the information you need.”</p>
                <p>Well, that proved to be all about as wrong as could be. Spain did not have a
                    press that revealed anything and there were no journals or magazines telling you
                    what's going on and publishing statistics and all that. So you had to go out and
                    talk to people—if you could get someone to talk to you. These professors
                    couldn't speak Spanish, and I could. So I ended up doing the financial reporting
                    myself.</p>
                <p>I got to know the head of the Bank of Spain quite well. Bought him a lunch about
                    every two weeks at The Jockey, the best restaurant in town, in my view. We had a
                    martini and a nice luncheon with wine, and we talked. He told me about what was
                    going on, and I would report back information faithfully to the department so
                    everybody could know about it.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>John Lodge was no great economist. He would go around in the regular staff
                    meetings and ask the staff what's going on. He might argue if he didn't like
                    what you said or even subject you to ridicule. I tried to keep him and the staff
                    informed. But sometimes I had to resort to a spiel of economic mumbo jumbo. He
                    stopped calling on me.</p>
                <p>But he gave the DCM, Park Armstrong, a terrible time. I arrived in Spain about a
                    week before Armstrong. And when I called on Lodge, he was steaming because he
                    was reading an article from The New York Times which listed political
                    Ambassadors who were unable to speak the language of the country. It said John
                    Lodge was in Spain and he knew no Spanish. That was all wrong. Lodge was
                    absolutely right. He was almost bilingual in Spanish, he told jokes, he spoke
                    colloquially, and he could make a wonderful speech in Spanish. So that was very
                    unfair.</p>
                <p>But Lodge also said, “Furthermore, I've been put through the paces by the former
                    DCM. This is Park Armstrong's first post. I am more experienced than he. I'm
                    going to run the embassy.”</p>
                <p>Ambassador Lodge, with his fluency in Spanish, knew what was going on. He talked
                    to people, and picked up a lot of inside information that was, of course never
                    published. Armstrong, who didn't speak Spanish, couldn't keep up with him and,
                    in fact, the Ambassador ran the staff meetings and the embassy. But it should be
                    the work of a DCM to coordinate staff reporting and work and this fell by the
                    wayside.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just to give an idea of how the thing worked, what
                        happened to Armstrong after?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, he had a nervous breakdown while there. At least, he was
                    hospitalized for awhile and nobody knew exactly what it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, your next assignment then, you went back to
                        Washington where you were to spend a considerable amount of time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: No, at that time I spent only two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, two years. And you were deputy assistant secretary for
                        economic affairs from '60 to '62.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Until 1960 there was only one Deputy Assistant Secretary. I was the first
                    of the multiples. Les Mallory, the other deputy was about to leave when I
                    arrived.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>The assignment was due to Under Secretary Douglas Dillon and his recognition of
                    the fact that there were lots of stirrings in Latin America. The president of
                    Brazil had written a paper, that he called “Operation Pan-America,” that
                    recommended a vast assistance program. They were already in the process of
                    creating the Inter-American Development Bank. And Dillon personally carried
                    through the creation of and the signing of something called the Act of Bogota,
                    in 1960, with Latin Americans, where the United States pledged for the first
                    time $500 million (this was real money at the time) for economic assistance to
                    Latin America.</p>
                <p>This was a year before the Alliance for Progress. But it was a sort of precursor,
                    in response to all the complaints from Latin America about aid. “You had the
                    Marshall Plan. You're helping everybody else. What are you doing for Latin
                    America?”</p>
                <p>And so Dillon got that through, $500 million. We took $6 million for AID
                    administration and personnel, but $494 million of that was given to the
                    Inter-American Development Bank; the first money they had. It created the Social
                    Progress Trust Fund, giving the bank a very important sum of money that they
                    could use for social purposes in Latin America.</p>
                <p>In my new job I was dealing with the bank. It happened that Felipe Herrera was
                    the first bank's first president, a Chilean. He was one of the negotiators on
                    the old copper deal. We were friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the effectiveness of this
                        Inter- American Bank?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, this was a big hurdle that we had to cross, because everybody felt
                    that the Latin Americans wouldn't run the bank on a technical basis, with some
                    administration. It was believed it would resort to cronyism, and, as everyone
                    knew (it was thought) Latins don't know how to run a bank. But it had to have a
                    Latin American president because it was a Latin American bank.</p>
                <p>We had helped write the charter so that there was an American executive vice
                    president, because we were far and away the largest contributor, as we are in
                    everything else. Even though we are a minority contributor, we seem to be the
                    largest single contributor for all international organizations.</p>
                <p>The first executive director was Braden Upton, who had been Assistant Secretary
                    of the Treasury for International Affairs. He knew money and banking. And he
                    knew some Spanish, because he visited Latin America, and was serious about
                    learning Spanish. His wife spoke Spanish too. Very attractive people.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>But they weren't able to keep up with a young, vigorous and clever man like
                    Felipe Herrera, who had been head of the Central Bank in Chile, and knew about
                    Latin America and its politics, and knew how to maneuver.</p>
                <p>So he reduced the importance of the US executive vice president considerably from
                    what we would have preferred. We would have liked to see somebody who had a sort
                    of equal power. But Felipe Herrera was strong, powerful and competent. He made
                    the bank a real Latin American institution. And successors have been pretty well
                    selected—a former finance minister of Mexico, for example, and people like that.
                    The presidents have been competent and, though the staff may be too large (as in
                    the State Department) the bank has been successful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So your impression was that: Ok, we're not quite getting
                        it the way we thought it, but the final outcome is where we want it to
                        be.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: That's right. And in large part because some outstanding people have been
                    selected. The present man, who's named Iglesias, is highly regarded by the US He
                    is a Uruguayan. A very competent, outstanding man who has made great efforts to
                    improve the economic condition of Latin America, and somebody in whom we had a
                    great deal of confidence. When you get a man like that in as head of the bank,
                    he's going to run it competently.</p>
                <p>In general, the bank exceeded our expectations. That doesn't mean that there
                    isn't a little bit of hanky panky, in friendship and so forth. And maybe not all
                    loans are wise. But not all loans made by the World Bank or the Export-Import
                    Bank or the US Savings and Loans are all so good either.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there in the ARA bureau, Latin American bureau,
                        from '60 to '62, so you were there during the Kennedy administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Right, they inherited me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did this work? I think the change of administration,
                        particularly when two parties are changing jobs, can be very indicative of
                        how things work. How did you see this at ARA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Worked disastrously for me. Up until this time I felt that I had been
                    selected for this job as a technician, not somebody with political clout and not
                    somebody who's going to try to do anything to satisfy domestic political needs,
                    needs of the White House. Good leaders like General Marshall would tell us: “We
                    want your honest advice. Don't you worry about the politics in the United
                    States. That's for us to worry about. We want your honest views.”</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>The Kennedy administration was my first exposure to the obverse of that.
                    Everything was politics; and building up the family and the president.</p>
                <p>Let's take the Alliance for Progress. I was at the White House when the Alliance
                    for Progress was announced. The term “Alliance for Progress” had been created by
                    Richard Goodwin, a brilliant Harvard lawyer, who had been an “advance man” in
                    the Kennedy campaign. But when he came to Washington, the first I heard his name
                    was from the press, which asked, “Do you know anything about a guy named Richard
                    Goodwin?”</p>
                <p>I said, “No. Why?”</p>
                <p>“He called us and asked the press to recommend some good books on Latin America
                    because that's what he was in charge of in the White House!” (Richard Goodwin
                    was a PR man who dealt with the press. He read 83 magazines a week and tried to
                    read all the newspapers, talk to all the reporters.) He saidhe had coined the
                    term “Alliance for Progress” during the campaign and had some idea that this was
                    going to be Kennedy's first big foreign policy effort, like Roosevelt's Good
                    Neighbor Policy. It would rival that.</p>
                <p>But how do you fill the gap between reading some good books on Latin America and
                    being in charge of it? For him, the gap seemed to be nothing. You know, you just
                    read some books and you know all about it.</p>
                <p>Well, he tried to run Latin America from the White House. Example: after I'd
                    heard his name, some few days later I get a call: “This is Richard Goodwin in
                    the White House.”</p>
                <p>“All right.”</p>
                <p>“The President would like to know all about the following problem.”</p>
                <p>Well, if the President wants to know, he's got a right to know, so you provide
                    the desired information to Goodwin.</p>
                <p>A few days after that I get another call: “This is Richard Goodwin in the White
                    House. The President has considered what you said, and he wants you to do the
                    following...”</p>
                <p>Then I had my first falling out with the Kennedy administration. I said to
                    myself, “I cannot do that.” I had unanswered questions and doubts.</p>
                <p>Did Goodwin understand what I said? Did he talk to the President in fact? Did the
                    President tell him something?</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>What I told Goodwin was that I was only a Deputy Assistant Secretary. I have a
                    boss who's called the Assistant Secretary, and he has a boss called the
                    Secretary. I would be exceeding my authority, and would be cutting out two major
                    bosses if I were dealing directly with the White House. I could not take that
                    kind of responsibility. Well, this was frustrating for Goodwin, but I could not
                    accept elimination of two echelons of power in the Department.</p>
                <p>I had another falling out with the Kennedy White House. I was at the March 13,
                    1961, speech in the East Room of the White House when the President announced
                    his Alliance for Progress. Among other things, he said he expected all
                    Ambassadors to be interested in this program. He was also going to appoint
                    outstanding AID mission directors, and he would expect them to be just as
                    competent and just as good and well-qualified as the Ambassador.</p>
                <p>Soon, I received, for approval, the name of the first mission director that they
                    were going to appoint to Ecuador. It happened to be somebody I had known in
                    Chile. He ran a little dry cleaning establishment, played basketball excellently
                    but had never been in an important job, nor made much money. He had little
                    understanding of international economics or its problems, which one would have
                    to know as an AID mission director. He was a great athlete, I knew that. I tried
                    to veto the nomination on the grounds that he was a fine man, but not qualified
                    to carry out the program that President Kennedy set forth in his speech on the
                    Alliance of Progress.</p>
                <p>A few days after that, I got a telephone call: “This is Ralph Dungan in the White
                    House.” (Ralph Dungan was then appointments secretary for President Kennedy.) He
                    said, “What's the ideology, pal? What's the matter with our man for
                    Ecuador?”</p>
                <p>I said, “No ideology. This is just someone whom I happen to know. And I think the
                    President wants better people, of top quality. This is a major program, and I
                    know that this man is not qualified for the job. That's from my own personal
                    experience.” That made an enemy of Dungan. The nomination was sent forward and
                    my approval was never sought again.</p>
                <p>I later discovered (and this was my own fault) that this man had played football
                    at Harvard with Joe Kennedy, who was killed in World War II, and was supposed to
                    be made president by his father, Joseph Kennedy.</p>
                <p>But to pin it on me for “ideology,” and consider me against the President because
                    I exercised my right to give an honest opinion, was unfair. This wasn't hearsay.
                    I knew what I was talking about and that nominee proved to be the worst Mission
                    Director in Latin America. Let me be fair by saying there were also some
                    outstanding Mission Directors, like Walter Howe, in Chile, who went on to be
                    Ambassador to that country.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>So I had two major enemies early on. To the extent that they permitted, I was
                    able to do my job, the economic and AID job in the Department. We had a lot of
                    international meetings for which I would see that the briefing papers were
                    prepared. I had no problems in dealing with the EX-IM BANK and other US
                    institutions encompassed in the Alliance.</p>
                <p>About a year later Goodwin was sent over to State as a Deputy Assistant Secretary
                    in ARA, in the political slot. He lasted only a month. He wanted to do his usual
                    PR work. I understand Ed Martin, who was the Assistant Secretary at that time,
                    just got rid of him. Nothing more was heard about Richard Goodwin, but he came
                    back to help President Johnson in some speech writing.</p>
                <p>As I said, he's a brilliant man, but in my view an evil man, an untrustworthy
                    man. I could not deal with him; I will accept that as a weakness on my part. But
                    I had to believe that I could express my own opinion and that I would not be
                    penalized for it in the Department of State, because that's what I was hired to
                    do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what about the Assistant Secretaries for Latin
                        American affairs? I must say, looking over this, over a fairly consistent
                        period of time, it seemed to be almost a revolving door. I mean, people were
                        in and out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: That's very true. Tom Mann was the Assistant Secretary at the time of
                    Kennedy's inauguration. I had the greatest respect for Tom Mann. We had worked
                    together before. Everybody thought Tom was first rate, very competent. But they
                    got him out because he wouldn't talk to anybody like Goodwin. He was “kicked
                    upstairs” to Mexico as Ambassador.</p>
                <p>Then we had a big gap. Wimberly Coerr, who was the political deputy, and I, as
                    the economic deputy, held ARA together for six months or so. They were looking
                    all over for somebody to be assistant secretary. But if you've got people like
                    Goodwin and Dungan running things in the White House, nobody wanted the job.</p>
                <p>Finally, Adlai Stevenson was on a trip around South America, talking about the
                    Alliance for Progress. He ran into Bob Woodward, who was ambassador to Chile,
                    and soon sent a telegram to the President saying, “I have found your man for
                    Latin America.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just Ambassador to Chile. He'd just been there for a very
                        short time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>BARALL: I had seen Bob up in Washington before he went down. I said, “Get out of
                    town as fast as you can. They're looking for an Assistant Secretary.” He had
                    been a Deputy Assistant Secretary years ago, and he would have been a natural
                    for the job. He went down to Chile thinking he had avoided it. When Time
                    magazine ran the story on his eventual appointment, they captioned it: “Number
                    Twenty-Two.” Twenty-one people had turned it down before he took the job. But
                    Bob Woodward didn't last very long, either. And I was mixed up in that, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then he went to Spain.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Yes, but I was mixed up in that, too. Here was another problem with the
                    White House.</p>
                <p>Brazil expropriated a power plant. There is something called the noon briefing in
                    the State Department. Somebody has to prepare remarks for a spokesman to tell
                    the press. We knew that someone was going to ask a question such as: “How do you
                    feel about the expropriation of an American-owned power plant?” Not US
                    government, but private, American-owned. I think it was the American Foreign
                    Power plant that had been expropriated.</p>
                <p>So I prepared a statement for Bob Woodward. It said, “We recognize the right of
                    every government to expropriate, subject to prompt, adequate, and effective
                    compensation. And the government of Brazil has promised prompt, adequate, and
                    effective compensation in this case. We cannot be against it. But what have you
                    done to help yourself if you've used existing resources to buy out something
                    that already exists? Would you not be better off under the Alliance for Progress
                    if you use your money to create something new?”</p>
                <p>I told Bob Woodward, as I handed him the suggested remarks, “This is dynamite.
                    Consider it very carefully. This can make waves.”</p>
                <p>He read it, after the warning, and said, “I'll make it, very prudently.”</p>
                <p>The statement was made at noon. At 2:00 P.M. Woodward got a call from the
                    President himself: “Who authorized that statement?”</p>
                <p>He said, “I did.”</p>
                <p>“It's not what I want from the Alliance for Progress.”</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>Evidently we wanted the Alliance for Progress, from the White House, to be Big
                    Brother, donating and giving. There was so much talk about how much money we're
                    going to give them and very little talk about what they have to do by way of
                    self-help efforts to make the application of money useful and effective. Soon
                    thereafter Woodward's transfer as Ambassador to Spain was announced. Then Ed
                    Martin was moved from Assistant Secretary for Economic Affairs to Assistant
                    Secretary for Latin America.</p>
                <p>At that time, Secretary of State Dean Rusk had sent my name over to the White
                    House to be Ambassador to either Venezuela or Uruguay. It went to Dungan and
                    Goodwin, the two Latin American “experts” over there, who refused to forward the
                    nomination to the President. I was told by the Under Secretary for
                    Administration, a competent political appointee, that the Secretary didn't
                    accept this. He didn't accept the idea that two men on the President's staff
                    could veto a recommendation of the Secretary of State, believing that only the
                    President himself should do that. The Under Secretary said Rusk went over to the
                    White House and had a big discussion about this issue. And he lost!</p>
                <p>I reacted strongly to this information. I was close to fifty years old, and had
                    almost 20 years of service, so I could exercise my option for early retirement.
                    I had a standing invitation from a corporation that if I ever wanted to make a
                    change, think of them. I contacted the company to see if their offer was still
                    in effect. I retired from the government at that time. I signed a 2-year
                    contract to serve as a vice-president of the international company, in
                    Switzerland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What type of work were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I was vice president for AMF International, which manufactured automatic
                    machinery of various kinds, including turnkey factories that make tobacco
                    products, or bread, with hardly any personnel. I had two happy years, with much
                    higher pay.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did they get you back in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: After the Kennedy assassination, Tom Mann was called back by President
                    Johnson to be Assistant Secretary again. I wrote to Tom and said, “The men and
                    issues in foreign affairs are more important. If you want me to come back, I
                    will.” He checked it out. There is a provision in the Foreign Service Act where
                    the Secretary of State, without approval of Congress, can recall a retired
                    Foreign Service Officer.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>I was recalled and again assigned to ARA, working on inter-American affairs. They
                    were then creating something called CIAP, the Inter-American Committee on the
                    Alliance for Progress, which was supposed to give the Alliance direction and
                    make sure that everything was done right. Walt Rostow was our first
                    representative. He was also head of the Policy Planning Council. To help him do
                    both jobs, I became his deputy on CIAP. This was only at the organizing stage. I
                    went through the organization and establishment of our part of the committee,
                    went to its meetings and helped Rostow as well as I could.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is May 22, 1990. This is the second interview with
                        Milton Barall concerning his career. We last left off where he was dealing
                        with the Alliance for Progress and the OAS from 1964 to 1967. What was the
                        name of the organization that was dealing with this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: There was, in the charter of Punta del Este, a group called “The Nine
                    Wise Men.” They were presumed to be able to judge a country's development plan.
                    And if they approved it, presumably lending institutions and other
                    organizations, including the United States government, would be willing to
                    provide funds in support of the judgment of these nine wise men. They certainly
                    did not command the attention that was expected of them. Institutions,
                    especially lending institutions with their own boards and their own loan
                    officers, tend to make up their own minds. So that didn't work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were these so-called wise men coming from?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, they were sort of part-time employees of the Organization of
                    American States. They were generally professors, most of them, and mostly Latin
                    Americans. A few of them were political figures in Latin America. But no one
                    outstanding. They were hired on a contractual basis, but I don't know whether
                    they were given a yearly stipend or were paid only for the times that they
                    worked. They were not all in the Organization of American States, some of them
                    had offices there.</p>
                <p>When that mechanism didn't work, the Organization of American States and the
                    United States government created an organization that would have greater
                    authority and be more meaningful in the process of judging and approving a
                    country's development plan. CIAP (that's the Spanish acronym for the
                    Inter-American Committee on the Alliance for Progress), was designed to be
                    prestigious enough to command respect and run the Alliance.</p>
                <p>The first US representative to that organization was Walt W. Rostow, an
                    internationally known economist who was certainly of the stature that would tend
                    to give credence to the findings of such a group of men. Walt Rostow had been
                    the head of the National Security Council. At the time he was given this job as
                    an additional duty, he was also head of the State Department's Policy Planning
                    Council.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>I had just come back from retirement, and they assigned me as Walt Rostow's
                    deputy, I suppose because of all my experience in Latin America. He had another
                    deputy for the Planning Council. Each of us had an office next to Rostow to help
                    him with his dual responsibilities.</p>
                <p>The Latin-American members of CIAP were of equal caliber. They were, for example,
                    Rodrigo Gomez, head of the Central Bank of Mexico, or Luis Escober, former
                    Minister of Economy of Chile, people well-known in Latin America. If anybody
                    could have given credence to the findings of a Latin American group as a whole,
                    that was it. The chairman of CIAP was Carlos Sanz de Santamaria, former mayor of
                    Bogot�, Colombia, former Ambassador to the United States, former Foreign
                    Minister of Colombia. A man of stature. People listened to him.</p>
                <p>The most important mechanism through which this group operated was called the
                    country review. It was run at the Organization of American States, in its
                    Washington offices, which provided the principal staff. The other participants
                    were the international community in Washington interested in Latin America. The
                    AID (or the ICA or whatever name it had at the time), the US aid agency, was an
                    important participant at each of the country reviews. The International Monetary
                    Fund was there, the World Bank, the Inter- American Development Bank, and there
                    were some observers from other countries and institutions.</p>
                <p>There was a fairly good, searching inquiry into the development plans of the
                    country under consideration, which was generally represented by the Minister of
                    Economy, the Minister of Planning if they had one, sometimes the head of the
                    Central Bank, but someone in a position of authority. And if it didn't produce
                    any other results, at least it led to a concentrated study of where the country
                    was and where it ought to be going in the economic and social development
                    process. It was a good exercise even if it didn't entirely bring the results
                    that were anticipated.</p>
                <p>Walt Rostow was not the only member of CIAP who had another job, almost all of
                    the others did too. Carlos Sanz de Santamaria would preside over the country
                    review and there would always be at least one other member. Although
                    hypothetically there were not supposed to be substitutes for the principals on
                    the council, I was allowed as an exception, because they knew Walt Rostow was
                    busy, to sit in on most of these reviews instead of him. The country review took
                    almost a whole week.</p>
                <p>As a matter of fact, the late Walter Sedwitz (then Assistant Secretary OAS) and I
                    had dreamt up this mechanism in earlier years and tried to use it, but it wasn't
                    successful and didn't have the high-level participation it gained when it came
                    under CIAP auspices. CIAP had clout because of the quality of its members.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>However, because each of the lending institutions had its own deciders and
                    policies (and the United States government was not different from, let's say,
                    the International Monetary Fund), the United States might make a poorly planned
                    loan, because of political needs, or because we felt that that particular
                    government needed shoring up—the alternative being even worse. And in the case
                    of the lending institutions, they had their own priorities and their own boards
                    of governors or directors, and they had to come to their own conclusions. So, if
                    you got a good send-off from the country review and the people sitting around
                    the table, that didn't necessarily bring you the result of all the money you
                    wanted. Self-help was more of a factor than it had been but no single
                    organization can make decisions for governments and independent
                    institutions.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, as I said, there was some use to it because it tended to
                    concentrate the country's plans and thoughts, and it provided a place where a
                    dialogue could take place. Unfortunately it's customary in the inter-American
                    system, that nobody ever really gets criticized, nobody says a bad plan is a bad
                    plan, and you should be doing this, that, or the other thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is this almost endemic to anything in the..., the system
                        is sort of non-confrontational?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: That's right. And that's the reason that you don't get Latin American
                    problems solved in the Organization of American States. They will not take on
                    each other. They may occasionally take on the United States and criticize us,
                    but they tend not to criticize each other. Sometimes they say, privately, “We're
                    on your side.” But back home, “We have political problems!” My answer to that
                    is: We've got the same problem, you know. We really think you said the right
                    thing, but the people in our Congress, don't like that at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The State Department has been using Congress for probably
                        at least two centuries, as far as saying: Well, you know, it's not our
                        fault, it's Congress's fault that we don't get this. Well now, a couple of
                        things. How focused was Walter Rostow on this? How did he manage, and how
                        effective was he in his role?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Given the limited participation in time-consuming things like the country
                    review, which lasted a whole week, by the way, and people sat for a couple of
                    days in advance doing the paper-work, Walt didn't have the possibility of doing
                    it at that time. But as an economic historian, he did know a lot about economic
                    development, and without knowing the details of the country or its development
                    program, he could talk knowledgeably about the overall picture, the overall
                    measures that countries ought to be taking in order to move the development
                    program forward.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>One of the things he kept talking about much of the time was what he called the
                    “national market.” That is, instead of just exporting goods, develop a market
                    right within your own country and let the people get the benefits from your own
                    production. And that went not just for a country national market, he was also in
                    favor, for the same reason, of any kind of economic integration with respect to
                    common markets, or common external tariffs, or free trade areas, anything of
                    that nature. The Latins agreed with him but they did very little about it! He
                    argued that the Latin American countries were isolated from each other and that
                    therefore they all were export-oriented. They were facing toward the United
                    States or Europe or other markets and not dealing with each other. So that if
                    you wanted to manufacture something that needed a market, there wasn't a ready
                    market in Latin America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the lending institutions?. These were, what,
                        mainly American and European banks?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: The principal ones were a) the Inter-American Development Bank, which was
                    created just before the Alliance for Progress under the Eisenhower
                    administration. It came into existence in 1960, just before Kennedy was elected.
                    It became an important mechanism in the system because it was, for the first
                    time, a Latin American-directed international bank. We put in the most capital
                    (as we do in almost all institutions), but the president of the bank was a Latin
                    American, and the heads of departments were primarily Latin American. In other
                    words, we did not run it. And it was going to play an increasingly important
                    role in making loans to countries of Latin America.</p>
                <p>The others were b) the International Monetary Fund, which used to have a very
                    important role. I don't know whether it's changing now; they may be swapping
                    places with the World Bank. But it had the role of trying to advise countries on
                    how to straighten out their economic problems. And they dared to give advice.
                    Not public advice, not anything critical that they would say openly, but they
                    were fairly frank with the government because they negotiated what they called
                    standby loans, that is loans to a country to help it reform its economic system
                    and pursue fiscal and monetary reforms that those countries were supposed to
                    bring about. So they were a very important institution.</p>
                <p>And c) the World Bank was very important because it had much money, even at that
                    time. It started with $30 billion dollars, and it's up to, I think, $120 billion
                    of loan money now. So that's a very important institution. It was also able to
                    make soft loans in terms of interest payment, fifty-year payout and things like
                    that. But it was project oriented rather than just seeking reform. And, of
                    course d) there was the US AID program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they going in different, I mean, were you and the
                        inter-...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>BARALL: It's not just inter-American, because the International Monetary Fund and
                    the World Bank are world institutions. And, of course, the US has wide
                    interests.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a feeling you were going in different
                        directions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: No, I don't think so, they were complementary rather than competitive.
                    Each had an Assistant Secretary. The Fund, for example, had an Assistant
                    Secretary for Latin America, a Chilean. And the World Bank had someone, a Vice
                    President I think he was called, in charge of Latin America. I would make it my
                    business to know them, when I was in a position of responsibility working on
                    Latin America, and they would want to know the United States government because
                    they wanted to swap information.</p>
                <p>I sought out the Fund Assistant Secretary, who was an old friend. We talked very
                    frankly and confidentially about what the Fund's policies were and what the US
                    policies were and how could we coordinate them to get the best improvement in
                    the economic performance of the country under discussion.</p>
                <p>And it was almost the same thing with the Bank. Krieger Vasena, an Argentine, was
                    the Vice President for Latin America. He was a former Minister of Economy. I
                    knew him, and we used to talk almost as frankly as with the International
                    Monetary Fund.</p>
                <p>The International Monetary Fund was key, because it was in charge of overall
                    economic reforms. If a country was not acceptable to the IMF it would probably
                    be turned down for any loan. The World Bank would be talking about a project
                    loan, and therefore we had to decide whether we should vote in favor of building
                    a road or a dam or a power plant. But it wasn't as key to the overall process as
                    the International Monetary Fund, where we were talking about economic reform and
                    doing a better job for the country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any countries that were particular problems in
                        the period you were dealing with them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, this was really still in the '60s, and all of Latin America was
                    feeling left out. They felt that Alliance for Progress aid was tapering off
                    without serious change, whereas the Marshall Plan was fine Europe and they were
                    all thriving and doing well; and that we had never had any major program for
                    Latin America. Of course the post-war problems of Europe and the structural
                    problems of Latin America were not at all the same!</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>Nevertheless the US did have, in the Alliance for Progress, a major aid program.
                    If it did not achieve its overblown objectives it was mostly due to lack of
                    self-help! Dillon also became a key actor in the Kennedy administration. He was
                    made Secretary of the Treasury, and the Treasury has an important voice in any
                    meeting that's going to dish out the money (and they should have). The Treasury
                    representatives were always a very important part of any US delegations, not
                    only in the country reviews, but also in meetings of the Inter-American Economic
                    and Social Council, which was a part of the Organization of American States; the
                    Economic Commission for Latin America, a U.N. organization which became the
                    model for similar UN Commissions in Africa and the Far East.</p>
                <p>The Economic Commission for Latin America was run by a Latin American, a man
                    named Raoul Prebisch, a former head of the Central Bank of Argentina and a man
                    who gave much of the complaining attitude to Latin America. He considered Latin
                    America to be throttled by the United States. They were exporting raw-materials
                    to the United States whereas we had a mercantile mentality that didn't allow
                    them to develop manufacturing for export.</p>
                <p>Prebisch had come to the conclusion, in the '50s, that if you were going to deal
                    with the problem of unemployment in Latin America, you had to get heavily into
                    manufacturing. In the long run, he probably was wrong in giving Latin America an
                    excuse rather than pushing vigorously for economic integration and wide markets
                    in Latin America.</p>
                <p>I think Walt Rostow's idea of manufacturing for your own market was very good for
                    Latin America, creating a situation where the economics of scale would permit
                    you to buy and sell within the Latin American context. Prebisch also supported
                    manufacturing but called it “import substitution” which is more limited and
                    restrictive. Also, you save foreign exchange through import substitution whereas
                    vigorous programs could be much better earners of foreign exchange.</p>
                <p>Prebisch called and led the first inter-American meeting that excluded the US in
                    Alta Gracia, Argentina, in 1963. Collectively, but guided by Prebisch, they
                    developed a list of demands on the US and other industrial countries. In 1964,
                    Prebisch, with the rank of Under Secretary in the UN, created UNCTAD, which
                    stands for the United Nations Commission on Trade and Development. That got most
                    of the developing countries of the world to join regardless of affiliation. That
                    is, they could be oriented toward the Communists, or so-called non-aligned, or
                    with the West, but they all reached agreements about what should be done for
                    them.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>For example, they reached an agreement that the United States and all
                    industrialized countries should contribute one percent of GNP to the development
                    of other countries. But when they put the figures down, they discovered that was
                    a very large sum of money and not attainable. Then they changed the number to
                    seven-tenths of one percent. And you still hear that figure quoted when they
                    talk about how much assistance is being provided by countries. The United
                    States, specifically, is criticized for never reaching that seven-tenths of one
                    percent. For us, that would mean something like $3 billion a year, which is
                    probably double our current aid budget.</p>
                <p>So all of these things were going on, and CIAP was part of it. But it could not
                    be a directing organization because it only met a couple of times a year. It
                    would meet in Washington or in Mexico or someplace in Latin America. And there
                    was some good high-level talk and advice to the Inter-American Economic and
                    Social Council about what should be done. But there was no follow-up on the part
                    of CIAP and no enforcement of self-help, as foreseen in the Alliance for
                    Progress.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was during the Johnson administration. Did you get
                        any feel for how committed the administration was, or were they just sort of
                        tied up with Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I can tell you that President Johnson, personally, was very much
                    committed. I was at a meeting at the White House with all the members of CIAP.
                    The President talked off the cuff for about an hour and a half, without any
                    notes. No one else there but just the members of the CIAP and he.</p>
                <p>He said that the Alliance for Progress was a very serious program for him, and
                    that he didn't think it should last only ten years, which was the target of the
                    Kennedy administration. They made a promise that for ten years we would provide
                    at least a billion dollars a year, in support of matching funds of a billion
                    dollars a year from Latin America, for economic and social development. The
                    President said, “I pledge to you now that there is no end to this, no calendar
                    end to the program.”</p>
                <p>He also had a summit meeting with the presidents of Latin America, where he
                    wanted to do something big about the Alliance for Progress. But the Congress was
                    in no mood to appropriate funds. This was around '66 or '67, and it was probably
                    part of Johnson's plan for re-election, before he had made up his mind to
                    withdraw.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>The President had sent Linc Gordon and Sol Linowitz around South America in 1966
                    to see if the prospects for a summit were good. Sol Linowitz had, by then,
                    replaced Walt Rostow as the member of CIAP. But Sol Linowitz was also Ambassador
                    to the Organization of American States, which was his full-time job, and the
                    CIAP was decidedly part-time for him. I was inherited by him as his deputy; sat
                    in the chair for him, and did pretty much the same as I did for Walt Rostow,
                    including supervision of the preparation of US economic-policy papers for all
                    the inter-American meetings.</p>
                <p>I accompanied Sol Linowitz for the first part of the trip. In Uruguay, we talked
                    to the new president-elect, a man who died shortly thereafter, and his foreign
                    minister-designate, it happened that there was a meeting of foreign ministers
                    about another thing (I think it was economic integration), and we were invited
                    to meet with all the foreign ministers.</p>
                <p>The message I heard, in Spanish, was clearly: If you're going to have a summit
                    meeting, it has to be very well-prepared in advance. You have to have everything
                    agreed to. There has to be funding. There has to be organization. And I sensed
                    that the ministers were negative. Other people put a different interpretation on
                    what they heard.</p>
                <p>Sol Linowitz then split off and went up the west coast. I joined Linc Gordon, in
                    going to Argentina, where we met with the Foreign Minister and the President
                    Ongania. Then we went to Brazil, where Linc Gordon, who had been Ambassador
                    there, knew Marshal Castelo Branco, who was President. We had about three and a
                    half hours in his office, just the three of us, talking about economic
                    development, mostly in Portuguese, and about a possible summit.</p>
                <p>I heard the same message as in Uruguay. In both cases, I drafted telegrams about
                    what was said. The Foreign Minister was not present in Brazil, just the marshal
                    himself. I heard the same negative: If you're going to have a summit meeting,
                    there has to be something already agreed to in advance that you're going to be
                    able to announce as a result.</p>
                <p>Then the two teams joined forces and met in Venezuela. Gordon and Linowitz called
                    on the President but I was not included. After we returned home, Linowitz and
                    Gordon were invited by the president to come to the White House to tell him what
                    the results were. I don't know whether they were playing politics. Perhaps
                    because they knew the president was very anxious to have this meeting for his
                    domestic political purposes. They reported that Latin-American leaders wanted
                    such a meeting!</p>
                <p>It was held. It was a dismal failure. We had looked at Punta del Este as a
                    possible site, because, off-season, you can put up a lot of people, and
                    presidents are accompanied by a big entourage. It was held there. But hardly
                    anybody knows about it, since nothing happened. It was not carefully prepared in
                    advance. There were no agreements. We had nothing to agree about. We had nothing
                    to offer.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is one of the lessons that we have to relearn each
                        time, that summit meetings are only good if you want to enforce what has
                        already been agreed to.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: That was clear to me. And it was clear to all the leaders of Latin
                    America that I talked to, the Foreign Ministers and Presidents. But I was not
                    asked to advise the US President. And God knows what I'd have said if I were
                    sitting alone in the office with the President. You know he wants this. Am I the
                    guy...?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: President Johnson was a pretty overpowering person.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: He was a towering and overpowering man. And conversation with him was
                    largely a monologue. So I don't know what I would have done if I'd been in the
                    office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On this period, I wonder if you could comment on two
                        things. One, the effect of our intervention in the Dominican Republic. And
                        the other one, somewhat akin but not completely, the role of Cuba in our
                        thinking and how it played.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Cuba represented a threat the same way Nicaragua was built-up by
                    President Reagan as a tremendous threat: They're going to march up there and
                    conquer all of Central America, next they'll take Mexico, and then they're at
                    the borders of the United States. This was the tiny country of Nicaragua with
                    three and a half million people or so. Cuba is a little bigger, and it's got ten
                    million people, but the threat was not military. The Cubans, acting as
                    surrogates for the USSR, were trying to win supporters of the centrally-planned
                    economy.</p>
                <p>At that time, people in Latin America had the capability of threatening us by
                    saying: “Well, you know, if we can't make it your way, we'll jump into the arms
                    of the Communists.” I think George Kennan gave the right answer to that a long
                    time ago. If you get faced with that question, the answer is: “Go jump,” because
                    nobody really wanted to undertake that kind of system. The Cubans were dominated
                    by a Communist, so they ended up with a one-man dictatorship the same as in
                    Africa, where many of the countries are socialistically or communistically
                    oriented. And this is a great mechanism for somebody who wants to exercise full
                    power all by himself. Theoretically he is the government. That's the Communist
                    way of doing things.</p>
                <p>But the Dominican Republic was another deal. I was in on that partly, because I
                    was sent down as part of a delegation a couple of times to look things over. For
                    a time there was chaos in the Dominican Republic. The troops were finally sent
                    in under the fig-leaf of a Brazilian commander and under the aegis of the
                    OAS.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: American troops.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: They weren't all American troops. Because Castelo Branco had been
                    commander of a Brazilian brigade, in World War II, in Italy (this is how he and
                    Vernon Walters got to be great friends), the Brazilians provided the
                    commander-in-chief. Technically, on the books, it was an OAS operation, with a
                    Brazilian military commander, and the greatest number of troops, some 23,000
                    being American.</p>
                <p>But to give the OAS credit, Jos� Mora, then secretary general of the OAS, went
                    down there himself. He acted very sensibly and wisely and helped things get to
                    normal. I give Jos� Mora, whom everybody considered a relatively mild and
                    ineffective Secretary General, a lot of credit for acting like vigorously and
                    constructively. He did it by himself, without sitting around and getting
                    approval from the Council of the OAS, because it probably would have been
                    denied.</p>
                <p>That intervention worked out well. It's one of the few that you can justify,
                    because it came after Trujillo, a terrible dictator was overthrown and the
                    people had no way of governing themselves. So Caudillos were maneuvering and
                    fighting to take over the country after Bosch was thrown out.</p>
                <p>Balaguer became sort of a perennial president (And this is going on right now,
                    another election between the two. Nobody knows who's going to win, or who has
                    won, or how you count the ballots.) But Balaguer had been one of Trujillo's
                    puppets. Trujillo had installed him as president. Nobody was de facto chief of
                    state except Trujillo. But Balaguer or Trujillo's brother or somebody was
                    nominally chief of state. Balaguer was a much more sensible man. He knew much
                    more about government.</p>
                <p>At that time, Bosch was anathema to the United States because he was a very
                    left-wing, probably unbalanced man. At least that's how we looked upon him. He
                    was not a sane left winger. Unpredictable, and certainly would have been awful
                    for the Dominican Republic if he had become president.</p>
                <p>But Balaguer was elected president, and he did lead that country to a sort of
                    democratic process. He's been President almost all the time since then. But he
                    did lead the country to elections. When he was defeated, he stepped down, and
                    then ran again and was elected. At least they have a democratic change of
                    government that's not done by fiat, nor do you have the same leader
                    eternally.</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>The Dominicans, a quite backward and underdeveloped people, have been trying to
                    do things by way of economic development. Mind you, you start on the Island of
                    Hispaniola with Haiti and the Dominican Republic always the two most
                    impoverished and backward countries. Haiti at one time was even considered ahead
                    of the Dominican Republic, because the people had nothing there except what the
                    dictator allowed to flow to them. The Dominican Republic has much better land.
                    Haiti is full of mountainous, non-producing land, and the Dominican Republic can
                    produce much, much more—sometimes with illegal Haitian labor.</p>
                <p>The Dominicans have been doing something serious. They're still far from out of
                    the woods, but I think that intervention paid off. Haiti is still wallowing in
                    uncertainty and bad, self-appointed governments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then this was not a major setback as far as your dealings
                        with the other Latin American countries at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: To the extent that there was a cover of the OAS leadership and a
                    Brazilian commander they couldn't blame just the United States. They could blame
                    the United States because we did provide most of the troops. But it was not a
                    Bay of Pigs fiasco. We had enough troops, and just the idea of a battleship
                    offshore was enough to calm people and to keep a lot of two-bit revolutionaries
                    from trying to get into the act.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now, moving from this. You spent about two years
                        dealing with Caribbean Studies from 1967 to 1969. What were the issues that
                        you were dealing with? How was this set up in your organization, and what
                        were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I got called in by Covey Oliver, the Assistant Secretary. He said, the US
                    wanted a policy study for the Caribbean. In the '60s there were already four
                    major countries that had become independent from Great Britain but there were
                    also associated states, and colonies. The British Caribbean was in a state of
                    change after the failure of the islands to get together in the Federation of the
                    West Indies.</p>
                <p>The associated states were somewhat in the same situation as Puerto Rico. That
                    is, they had self-government up to a point, but Great Britain was in charge of
                    foreign affairs and defense, as is true for the US in Puerto Rico. They complain
                    that they're subject to some of the laws of the United States, but in Puerto
                    Rico we collect excise taxes on the rum they ship to the US and we send the
                    money back to Puerto Rico. It's their money. They're not subject to the US
                    income tax.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>And they are self-governing. The British Islands, like Puerto Rico had the
                    capability to move on into independence, and the British island have since. They
                    are countries of over 100,000 people, with very limited economic resources and
                    very limited manpower resources. I was not given any prescription. I was told by
                    Covey Oliver, “Take a year and look around the Caribbean and tell us what we
                    ought to do.” That was the end of my instructions. I was given the personal rank
                    of Ambassador to facilitate high-level meetings in the Caribbean.</p>
                <p>It was a great, great job because I was left alone and I wrote a one-man report,
                    without a committee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your conclusions? What were you reporting
                        back?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I didn't build up any staff, by the way. I had one staff assistant and
                    one very competent secretary, and I had some money where I could hire outside
                    consultants.</p>
                <p>I had a little help from the outside. And I had help from other US government
                    institutions. The Department of Agriculture write a paper on agriculture in the
                    Caribbean, and the Commerce Department wrote about trade in the Caribbean. And I
                    used all of their statements or papers as annexes to the paper that I finally
                    wrote. I had eleven annexes, two from outside consultants and nine from agencies
                    in the United States government.</p>
                <p>One consultant wrote one on education (we didn't have a Department of Education
                    at that time). I also got the Bell Company to write a paper, with some maps and
                    whatnot, on the communications system of the Caribbean and how they were
                    connected with each other, if at all.</p>
                <p>Even in Latin America, until not so long ago, you could not talk from one country
                    to another except by using the United States as a relay station. One of the
                    problems in the Caribbean; was the inability to communicate with each other.</p>
                <p>Inevitably was they had to get together and do something, because a country of
                    100,000 people is not an economically viable organization. As a matter of fact,
                    if you take the whole Caribbean together, even if you include the biggest
                    island, Cuba, which is not part of it at all now, you still haven't got an
                    awfully big thing.</p>
                <p>They trade with each other in little boats called schooners. There are no
                    container ships, because you haven't got that kind of volume. Maybe for bulk
                    exports you could have container ships, but they've got to have return
                    cargo.</p>
                <p>So the problem was: What sorts of policies ought the United States adopt?</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>I recommended, I think it was obvious, that we support political and economic
                    cooperation among them. Certainly the common market or free trade area, whatever
                    would facilitate trade with each other without economic barriers.</p>
                <p>And they have done quite well. As well as they can. If your principal export is
                    bauxite, as in the case of Jamaica, there's no way you can ship bauxite anywhere
                    in the Caribbean. I mean, it's got to go to a country with hydroelectric power
                    or other form of cheap power. There are a couple of mainland countries, Suriname
                    and Guyana, that happen to have very good and cheap water power. I met with a
                    Dutchman named Van Blommestein who thought that water was a tremendous resource.
                    He showed Suriname how to create hydroelectric power to produce alumina from
                    bauxite, the first step toward aluminum. With aluminum you may be using
                    one-thousandth of the ore that you originally shipped. With alumina, it may be
                    ten percent of the ore that you're shipping. And the value increases enormously.
                    Perhaps as an independent country, now, they are making aluminum. I haven't been
                    to Guyana since then, and that's almost twenty-five years ago, but if they were
                    properly governed they should have the same capability.</p>
                <p>I recommended things like a Caribbean police force, and I think that was one of
                    the recommendations that they adopted. I was in Antigua once when there were
                    demonstrations and a threat to violence near a big depot of gasoline. We were
                    afraid that someone would torch that and blow up the whole island or kill
                    everybody on it. It's not easy to evacuate all the people on an island. The
                    question I could not answer to myself was whether, if the government, the
                    premier, wanted to put down the uprising, would his 200 man police force start
                    shooting and clubbing their brothers, the demonstrators?</p>
                <p>So I recommended that there be a Caribbean police force. If five countries or
                    islands get together, each one contributes a fifth of the troops, who receive
                    professional training that goes on all year round. Then they could be available
                    to serve for public order in any of the 5 countries. It could be even larger
                    than a 5-country force.</p>
                <p>I also pointed out that color is a perennial problem all over the Caribbean and
                    racism was going to be a continuing political issue in the area.</p>
                <p>I had a section called “Subversion through Corruption.” And this was related to
                    the gamblers and the drug dealers who, as we see in Colombia now, are people
                    capable of being terrorists, or subverting a whole country, or making it
                    impossible to even hold a presidential election because they murder the
                    candidates.</p>
                <p>There were also US administrative recommendations for lands moving out of
                    European control into independence. They became part of ARA and members of the
                    OAS. The report was 457 pages, and I can't tell you all the things in there.
                    Twenty-three pages of recommendations alone.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>Not through my efforts, but I think the Caribbean, the English-speaking lands, at
                    least, had a very good background and training for self-government, which began
                    a long time ago. Political parties grew out of the labor unions, and the leaders
                    of those labor unions became the heads of state.</p>
                <p>They had responsible people, well-educated. Some of them had the “been to”
                    syndrome. They had been to the law schools in London, and other excellent
                    universities, but they came back. Like the prime minister of Barbados, who had
                    been a flyer in World War II, a London law school graduate, a man of very high
                    character and standing. And Doc Williams, who lived in Trinidad and Tobago, but
                    says he didn't know he was black until he came up to the US as a professor at
                    Howard University. Then he discovered it and started to hate Americans because
                    they treated him like a black. (At that time Washington, D.C. was still a
                    segregated city with discrimination against blacks.)</p>
                <p>There were movements in the Caribbean. Ras Tafari, was Haile Selassie's
                    precoronation name. He visited Jamaica in the 1930s and was treated as a
                    God.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was that sort of native movement which was
                        based...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: They're called Rastafarians now, in Jamaica, and they have braided, oily
                    hair. Some of them look like crazy people, and some of them act crazy. And they
                    did kill a few Americans now and then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, they do smoke something called “bang,” I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Ganja.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which is a hemp, or something like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: That was a very interesting assignment, and I enjoyed it very much. I was
                    received by all the heads of state and the prime ministers of the islands that
                    were going to be independent. And I was very much impressed by the words.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>I also went to the French area, but they are overseas provinces of France, under
                    the Minister of Interior of France, and I don't think they want to change or
                    become independent. In Guadeloupe there is a movement for independence, that is
                    Communist-led. Not in Martinique. They get so many benefits, because these
                    overseas departments get all the same help that any department of France gets.
                    But there are restrictions, too. If they want carrots, they've got to import
                    them from France. Their education and everything else is under the French
                    system. So they were not an important part of the study and I made no
                    recommendations.</p>
                <p>I excluded Cuba deliberately, because that probably is worth a study of its own.
                    And anyway I had no access to them. Any recommendations would be meaningless.
                    Even today, a recommendation would be meaningless.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From 1969 to 1971 you became Deputy Chief of Mission in
                        Argentina. How did that job come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Well, John Lodge had a healthy skepticism about career people. He had
                    been to Spain, where I had served with him. He wanted to have people he knew and
                    he felt were trustworthy and wouldn't be disloyal to him. So when he was named
                    Ambassador to Argentina, he asked me if I would go with him. I was at a loose
                    end at that time and still had two years to go before I faced compulsory
                    retirement at age 60. Fortunately this stupid law has been amended to allow
                    service at least till age 65.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's changed, but that was how the rules were in those
                        days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: That was the law. Not just the rules, it was the law, and you couldn't do
                    anything about it.</p>
                <p>I liked Buenos Aires, it's a great big city. And it's no insult to be Deputy
                    Chief of Mission in a Class One post. So I went along with him, and we worked
                    out to be a pretty good team.</p>
                <p>I thought he was a great Ambassador in Spain, because he had no problems working
                    with Franco. Lodge was a born aristocrat, and in Spain he fit in beautifully. He
                    pushed to get Spain into NATO and to break down isolation and become part of
                    Europe and the economic world.</p>
                <p>In Argentina, we were in a democratic country, even though they had three
                    military dictators in a row, as presidents. Still, it was a democratic country.
                    The press was totally open, and you could say anything you wanted in the press.
                    And the universities were allowed to teach freely and to expose students to all
                    views. Many of the teachers and students leaned toward socialism. Peronism, a
                    continuing and leading political movement, was named for a dreadful dictator who
                    disseminated populist, unworkable ideas and nationalized much of the
                    economy.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>At the time I was there, they had not yet started “the disappeared.” You know,
                    the people who disappeared and were sometimes dropped into the ocean out of a
                    plane or a helicopter. This began as a reaction to left wing terrorism by
                    “Montoneros” and other organizations while I was still there.</p>
                <p>I was told by our CIA man, who was very competent, that at first, the government
                    didn't know about it. The Montoneros (who were like the Tupamaros, the
                    revolutionaries in Uruguay) were assassinating people at that time. They had
                    assassinated former President Aramburu, who was very popular. But he had helped
                    in overthrowing Peron so there was some resentment against him.</p>
                <p>Some of the sergeants in the police and the army got together and decided to
                    reply in kind, to kill those Peronists who are killing the military and other
                    leaders. Our CIA man said he thought the President and the government did not
                    really know about this. But, awhile the government became aware and even though
                    it was not proclaimed policy, at least it was tacitly permitted.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Lodge was in a difficult position in dealing with these problems. We
                    worked as a team. He was a marvelous linguist. He could deliver a speech
                    beautifully, he had been an actor, and, like President Reagan, he worked very
                    successfully with 3 x 5 cards. The PAO and I programmed him to visit all the
                    provinces. The people of the provinces and the governors were very happy. They'd
                    never seen an American Ambassador. He visited them and was treated royally. A
                    very attractive man, he gave speeches and shook hands and the people had
                    parties.</p>
                <p>And that left me to run the day-to-day embassy back home. We were a good team. I
                    used to say: “One show horse, one work horse.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were America's major issues with Argentina at the
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: We had no really great issues with them. We were friendly. We wanted, of
                    course, to see a democratic government, but it was not our business to tell
                    them, and we didn't deliver that message.</p>
                <p>We were sort of allies in looking askance at the Allende administration in Chile.
                    And the Foreign Minister, de Pablo Pardo, had been Argentina's Ambassador to
                    Chile. He asked for a special liaison with the US Embassy, where we could
                    discuss the problems of Chile and exchange information, but not acting together.
                    He named an Under Secretary, and I was named for the embassy. We met a couple of
                    times but I also met quietly, occasionally with the Foreign Minister, who had
                    been a professor of international affairs. Before he was named, I sought him out
                    as an “eminence gris” at the Foreign Office. We used to lunch together and
                    discuss foreign affairs. I was the only one in the embassy who knew him
                    then.</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>My source of information was that CIA man, who went over to Chile regularly to
                    get information, and also (in a legal way) to bring back money at a free rate of
                    exchange. This was with the permission and the knowledge of the Argentine
                    government.</p>
                <p>This man, who subsequently became head of the CIA in Vietnam, and was really one
                    of their most effective operators in the world, was dependable and of absolute
                    reliability. In Argentina a Braniff airplane had been taken over by some cuckoo
                    with a gun. Our CIA man, at the risk of his life, went onto that plane and
                    talked the man into surrender.</p>
                <p>One of the things he told me after a visit to Chile was that the US had nothing
                    to do with efforts to overthrow Allende.” We had, certainly, an input. We tried
                    to keep his opponent from being defeated, by contributing money. But the
                    congressional investigation showed something like a total of four to eight
                    million dollars. You can't buy a Chilean election for that kind of money—they're
                    much more expensive.</p>
                <p>So we didn't win the election. I think the Chileans lost it themselves because
                    Frei, who was the president, and the Christian Democrats didn't put up a good
                    candidate. They put up a man named Radomiro Tomic, who was wild-eyed and maybe
                    to the left of Allende. It seemed to me that the people of Chile came to the
                    conclusion that “if we're going to have a Communist, let's get a real one, not
                    someone who's masquerading as a Christian Democrat.” And so Allende won the
                    election in spite of our efforts.</p>
                <p>I am thoroughly convinced, that we did not overthrow him and did not murder him.
                    I think, in harmony with conventional wisdom, that he did, in fact, commit
                    suicide.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you're looking at it. You're an economist. Why is
                        it, here is Argentina, which is not, maybe it's the wrong term, but not
                        stuck with a large indigenous Indian population which has its own problems
                        and all. I mean, here...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: It's the best educated country. Argentina and Uruguay, far and away the
                    best educated countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean, wonderful country resources and everything else.
                        Was it working then? I'm talking about economically at that point.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I'll give you a facetious answer first. The Argentines tell the same
                    story about themselves as the Swiss. They say: “God gave us this wonderful
                    country, all this capability, with mountains and lakes and rivers and arable
                    land and whatnot. And to even up the score, he put the Argentines here.”</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>They don't get along with each other, although they're mostly of European
                    background. At the beginning of the 19th Century, there was a great wave of
                    immigration from Italy and Spain. And there were a lot of people who came with
                    some Socialist notions. This led eventually to something called Peronism. And
                    Peronism is the reason why they are not able to be economically or politically
                    sound. Peron nationalized to put his people on the public payroll.</p>
                <p>Peron became Minister of Labor in 1945 and then parleyed that up into becoming
                    the President of the country. He called his followers the Shirtless Ones, and he
                    wanted to put a shirt on their back by putting them on the government payroll.
                    So that you've got in the railroads about six times as many employees as you
                    need to run them. Peron very stupidly paid a lot of money to buy the railroads
                    from the English, whereas he could have got them for nothing if he had just put
                    a little pressure on them, because they were losing money due to government
                    regulations and pressure. Then he proceeded to exaggerated government.</p>
                <p>They took over steel plants and power plants and a lot of things. A
                    state-controlled economy. So that leads to black market operations. It leads to
                    currency being sent abroad. It leads to lack of initiative. Now they still have
                    a lot of wonderful farmers, and they produce agricultural commodities for
                    export. But by double invoicing or whatnot, they don't let the money come back
                    into the country, in most cases.</p>
                <p>I was there just last February. A friend of mine, a banker, arranged a special
                    lunch with the head of the stock exchange, a general, a big businessman, a
                    leading economist, etc. in the boardroom of his bank. I said I had read in the
                    papers, in the United States, that the rate of inflation was currently five
                    thousand percent per year. I asked if that were possible, how can a country live
                    with that?</p>
                <p>After consultation he replied that it was probably more like eight to ten
                    thousand percent. The funny thing is that the present President, Menem, is a
                    Peronist. He was elected by the Peronistas. Yet he is trying very hard to do
                    everything the opposite way, to get rid of government controls, to cut the
                    public payrolls, and to run the country properly. Whether he makes it or not is
                    very dicey. It's like Gorbachev really. You know, somebody from the inside
                    trying to change the system, and it's a very, very difficult thing to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now, at the time (we're talking about '69 to '71),
                        what was the relationship between our military and the Argentinean
                        military?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>BARALL: Very good. We had a military assistance program there, a MAG, led by a
                    brigadier general who was on very good terms with the military in power in
                    Argentina. He was not really, technically, part of the embassy, but we gave him
                    an office because we wanted to know what he was doing. He submitted willingly to
                    direction from the Ambassador or me. He considered himself part of our staff as
                    well as head of the MAG. He was a very good, competent officer, and he wanted to
                    be on the team. We were providing a little military assistance and a little
                    training, that's about all. We didn't have a big military staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've always wondered about these large military
                        establishments, or what seem like large military establishments, in Latin
                        America.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Are you talking about the US military establishments?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I'm talking about right within a country, the military
                        being so important and taking over, when they don't seem to fight each other
                        very much. Are these necessary? Was our aid sort of perpetuating this
                        over-emphasis on the military at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: Aid's a funny thing, you know. You have many purposes. The United States
                    never has an opportunity to have a clear-cut decision. You can look at today's
                    newspapers and you see that the President has to balance one thing against
                    another all the time in making a policy. China and the students' rioting happen
                    to be mixed up with most favored nation treatment and other matters. Really,
                    you'd have difficulty making a policy decision on one of them alone, and when
                    you get them both thrown together, they're very complicated.</p>
                <p>So you may have to help some of the countries of Latin America even if you
                    disapprove of some of the government's actions, or the government itself. We had
                    diplomatic relations with Allende!. Also, it was always one of the objectives of
                    the United States to standardize US equipment in Latin America, so that if they
                    ever joined us in a war, we could help them arm their troops because they would
                    know about our weapons.</p>
                <p>Refusal to help also had its consequences. In Peru, we once turned them down for
                    military assistance. They wanted to buy sophisticated planes from the United
                    States, but we said no, as a matter of principle. So they went and bought the
                    Mystere from France. So it's not just a nice moralistic decision that you have
                    to make. The question is: What's good for the United States? when you consider
                    all of the problems that have to be considered.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you didn't feel that what we were doing in Argentina
                        at the time was inordinate.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>BARALL: We were not helping them a great deal. We had an economic aid program,
                    which had been cut down and was eliminated after awhile. So our assistance to
                    them was not very great, no. In any event, it is not wise to disregard the
                    military in Latin America. One reason they are frequently the government is that
                    the army is generally the only institution of national scope.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, looking back on this. You left the Foreign Service
                        in 1971. If a young person were to come to you and ask how you feel about
                        joining the Foreign Service today, how would you reply to that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: I would say I think it is a much less attractive Service than it was in
                    my day, because it is too big. For example, when I was a desk officer, I felt I
                    had a great deal of authority as a very junior officer. I think people now don't
                    get any of the responsible positions until they're very, very senior.</p>
                <p>And we're so highly politicized. I mean, you've got mostly political Ambassadors.
                    What is it, seventy-five percent now are political? And the scrambler telephone
                    may make embassies less important, because Washington can ask for reports on
                    current problems and issue orders by telephone!</p>
                <p>A lot of senior career officers don't have fulfilling careers. They seem to be
                    picking the same people over and over again. They go from one important
                    assignment to another one. And you end up with Larry Eagleburger being the
                    Deputy Secretary. He's one of the dependable guys. Maybe it's like Lodge's view:
                    If you find a Foreign Service Officer you can trust, lean on him. Because some
                    of them are not considered trustworthy by politicos. But you probably know, from
                    your own experience, that once they work at an embassy, they discover that
                    Foreign Service Officers are decent people, very well trained and competent and
                    trying to do what's good for the United States. Some political appointees become
                    great admirers of career people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It takes three or four years of any administration. We're
                        still going through the suspicious years in the Bush administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARALL: But I would continue my statement by saying: Still, the men and the
                    issues and the things you do are very, very interesting. If you are able to pass
                    the exam, and are willing to stick it out, you will have a very interesting
                    life. It will never be dull. As I said at a farewell party before I retired, “If
                    the government hadn't paid me to do this job, I would have paid it. My great
                    complaint was that I was retired too early, just as I was beginning to
                    understand the conduct of diplomacy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I want to thank you very much. I really appreciate
                        this. This was fascinating.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
