<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001043">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Ivan Selin</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>UNDER SECRETARY IVAN SELIN</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Thomas Stern </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 29, 1991</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mr. Under Secretary, you had some acquaintance with the
                        Department of State when you were appointed in 1989. What did you expect to
                        find?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SELIN: I found pretty much what I expected. I had had a lot of experience with
                    State, having been in the national security establishment since 1965. My company
                    had done some work with State, consulting on systems work. I had worked
                    personally on a numbers of projects at State. I knew the personnel area fairly
                    well; I had some knowledge of the Foreign Service; I had some idea of the state
                    of the Department's financial management and information systems.</p>
                <p>I did find myself charged with the responsibility for refugee programs, which was
                    a brand new field for me. Therefore, the only two areas that were big surprises
                    to me when I came on board was the Refugee Program, because I had never thought
                    about it, and Consular Affairs, which was much different from what I had
                    envisaged. I knew that the Department's financial management system was in
                    terrible shape. State had nothing like a financial planning system; did not
                    really know where its resources were going and that even its financial
                    operations had a lot of holes in them, although the Department had taken some
                    strong actions to try to fix up the process.</p>
                <p>I thought I understood the personnel system, but it turned out to be more complex
                    and less well managed than I had anticipated, although still within the
                    framework that I had expected. On information systems, I knew that there had
                    been terrible internecine warfare between the financial management offices and
                    the information systems people. The information systems people and the
                    communicators were quite different and didn't get along very well with other
                    offices. In the foreign buildings area, I found pretty much what I expected.
                    There had been some very clever short-term management, but no real long term
                    plan or long term resource allocation plan. The security situation was pretty
                    much what I expected: good management of an effort to move from a minimum
                    security situation to a high security posture in a very brief period of time.
                    There was some over-shooting of targets, but Bob Lamb had done an extraordinary
                    job. I knew that there would be a lot of re-calibration that would have to be
                    done, but that was not a major issue.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>I had no understanding of consular affairs. I thought it was pretty mechanical;
                    you would turn out so many passports and issue so many visas and that was it. In
                    fact, it turned out that consular affairs is a very subtle set of processes. I
                    had no understanding of what was involved in emergency evacuation and more
                    generally what was required to support American citizens abroad. The refugee
                    programs were much worst than I thought, but on the other hand, much easier to
                    fix than I had expected once I got involved. We had some very good policy people
                    who had never considered the issue of resources; once I had pointed that out, it
                    was possible to make a lot progress in a very short period of time.</p>
                <p>The one thing that was clear was that the higher echelons of the Department had
                    not paid any serious attention to management. There had been so many festering
                    issues that could have been settled had only some senior officials said that
                    this was the way the issue would be settled and if someone didn't like, he or
                    she could retire. There were a lot of difficult and subtle issues, but they were
                    greatly outnumbered by the many easy issues that just required some discipline
                    at some level. They could have been decided a long time ago and then the senior
                    officials could have moved on to the next problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To what do you attribute this lack of interest in
                        management at the top of the Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SELIN: I can sympathize with the situation, but can't explain it historically.
                    The Department of State is the most extreme federal agency I have ever seen in
                    one sense: it had always felt that policy could be made without regard to
                    resources. It felt that policy was done on a grand level and that resources
                    would somehow follow. If it had a little more money, it would live a little
                    better; if there was less money, it would live a little less well. But the
                    amount of resources would never affect its ability to conduct policy. That
                    attitude created certain idiosyncrasies; the previous Secretary of State was
                    very interested in personnel policies, but it was not because he felt that this
                    would enable him to improve the conduct of foreign policy, but just because he
                    empathized with people and tried to make the Department a more humane place to
                    work. At least, that is my impression.</p>
                <p>There was never any feeling at the Secretary or Deputy Secretary level of the
                    Department that good management meant better foreign policy. Therefore it was
                    viewed more as just a hobby or idiosyncrasy, as opposed to a matter of survival.
                    It wasn't that the Secretary or his Deputy weren't interested in management
                    topics, but from the evidence available, I guess that there was no comprehensive
                    understanding of the significance of resource management for a rather small, but
                    very complex Department. There seemed not to have been an understanding that if
                    you didn't set resource priorities consistent with foreign policy objectives,
                    that those objectives could not be achieved. So a number of very nasty issues
                    were left festering.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>There is a second guess I would make: management issues are not like policy
                    issues. Policy issues require that the decision-maker listen to all views; he or
                    she has to make an extra effort to elicit people's opinions. Those who are going
                    to carry out the policy should be heard; it is therefore very important to build
                    consensus and to communicate even if it takes a little longer. That is vitally
                    important for the conduct of foreign policy. When it comes to resource
                    management, the same process becomes an excuse for delay. In many cases, it
                    doesn't make much difference what decision is made; the important point is to
                    make a decision and then move on. The enormous committee structure and
                    consultations are fine for policy making, but it leads to a structure in which
                    management decisions are not made and even if once made, there is no structure
                    to carry them out. Committees are fine for reviewing all aspects of policy, but
                    in management you need to put some one in charge. There is always the tendency
                    for an individual to avoid responsibility or at least not to confront a policy
                    issue, which is fair because policy is everybody's decision, but in the
                    execution of projects, someone has to be on the line. If the project turns out
                    well, the manager has done well and should be rewarded; if it turns out badly,
                    he or she have been a failure and should be punished. There was very little of
                    that attitude in the Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That management philosophy assumes that the Secretary and
                        Deputy Secretary will give the Under Secretary for Management their full
                        support. Was that your situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SELIN: As a start, I had unusual qualifications for this job in the combination
                    of my business and management experiences and my personal knowledge of a number
                    of elements of foreign policy. I assumed from the beginning that the Secretary
                    did not want to spend a lot of time on management issues, but that he was making
                    a significant investment because he knew that he was employing a person whom he
                    felt was qualified for the position and one whose reputation was that he was not
                    satisfied with half-way solutions. A person with such a background was bound to
                    raise some difficulties and problems. I took it the job on willingly, making it
                    quite clear to both the Secretary and the Deputy Secretary before accepting that
                    I was interested in reform and in recasting the management processes and not
                    just being at the helm of the ship for two or three years just to get it from
                    here to there. They took me on knowing my goals. I haven't needed a lot of
                    support from them, but when required, I have gotten it.</p>
                <p>They are obviously driven by two inconsistent considerations: one, they want me
                    to do a wonderful job and leave the place in much better shape than I found it;
                    second, they don't want to invest too much time in knowing what I am doing.
                    Their idea of supporting me is not to second-guess me and occasionally going to
                    bat for me if necessary, but not being deeply involved. I was in effect employed
                    to be “The Vice-Secretary for Management” to act on their behalf most of the
                    time, although there were some inconsistencies in this philosophy.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is an interesting comment because a number of your
                        predecessors are on record with statements that sometimes the substantive
                        officers of the Foreign Service would “run around” them to the Secretary and
                        get their management decisions over-ruled.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SELIN: That happened very rarely to me although there were occasions when I would
                    have liked to be involved in the decision-making process, but didn't know that a
                    particular issue was being reviewed. These issues were not ones that usually
                    considered as “management issues”, but were policy issues that had a management
                    content or were issues in my area which however were not management issues, such
                    as refugee programs. The Refugee Bureau is as much a policy office as it is a
                    management one; the reason why I was given the responsibility was because there
                    were considerable amounts of money being spent on that program without a policy
                    statement having been written that was consistent with available resources. So
                    my stewardship was focused on guiding a program so that it stayed within
                    available resources as well as improving its management.</p>
                <p>In consular affairs, one would think that is a straight management function—how
                    many people does it take to issue how many visas—but in fact, at the edges of
                    the management issues, there are other questions. I am the manager of emergency
                    evacuations and security for American personnel overseas, which becomes an
                    integral part of the policy process. A lot of the decisions in these areas have
                    to be made quickly. By statute, the Department's crisis manager is the Under
                    Secretary for Political Affairs. Some decisions have been made which were more
                    or less “political” decisions in which I would like to have been involved,
                    either because they had an important management aspect or because they involved
                    consular affairs or refugee programs. These instances were relatively few. The
                    Secretary, the Deputy Secretary and especially the Under Secretary for Political
                    Affairs have bent over backwards to get my views on issues which strictly
                    speaking were not in my province and therefore not required. On management
                    issues, they wanted to make sure that the policy input was considered, but the
                    final judgement was mine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would like to pursue the relationship of policy
                        development to resource availabilities because this problem has been endemic
                        in the Department. What were you able to do to bring these two processes
                        together?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>SELIN: One of my biggest disappointments is that, although I was reasonably
                    effective in the management of the Department resources, I have had very little
                    influence on the use of over-all foreign affairs resources, except as they might
                    impinge on the management of the State Department. I have had a fair amount of
                    influence on the integration of programs overseas and therefore on non-State
                    resources used overseas. We did that through the enhancement of Ambassadorial
                    authority and my insistence that Embassies be viewed as single units, but here
                    in Washington, the Department does not have the same authority that a Chief of
                    Mission has overseas. So on major foreign policy resource issues, if they did
                    not involve the Department's own resources, I have little influence and that has
                    been my biggest disappointment.</p>
                <p>Concerning the Department's own resources, the Deputy Secretary is the resource
                    manager of the “International Affairs” budget account. He has become an absolute
                    zealot about not approving programs—assistance, public information, etc.—unless
                    the resources were available, in State or in another agency. The needed
                    resources had to be available somewhere. I can't take full credit for this
                    approach; the budget exigencies have done a lot to force this approach. My chief
                    financial officer and myself have been able to create an environment in which
                    the information about resource availability is made available to the
                    decision-maker. We have forced overseas budget decisions to be tied to programs;
                    we were not satisfied with the old approach of cutting a person here or there.
                    We looked at budget questions programmatically, determining the program
                    consequences of resource reductions. We have established a budget process that
                    may not be tied to policy, but is tied to programs. In other words, the budget
                    may not be tied to the rejuvenation of Eastern Europe. but is tied to the
                    ability to conduct a private sector assistance program in Poland. We have made
                    sure that people's attention has been drawn to the fact that it takes resources
                    to operate programs of that kind and that they be reviewed from that aspect
                    before the normal personnel and overseas operations decisions were looked
                    at.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you run into much resistance from the Foreign Service
                        to your concept of linking policy and resources?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SELIN: No. My view is, at least at the conceptual level, the Foreign Service was
                    just waiting for someone to come in to manage the resources, including the
                    personnel system of the Foreign Service itself. The enormous uncertainties, the
                    roller coaster with the many lean years, the continuing indecision which moved
                    personnel policies back and forth, made the Service very discontented. Having
                    said that, I must admit that a lot of the habits of the Foreign Service are
                    inimical to the kind of management that I viewed as required. When faced with
                    the costs of this kind of management, maybe some of its enthusiasm may have
                    waned.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>For example, the entire Foreign Service performance and evaluation system is
                    based on individual performance. The officer with the best performance is
                    promoted. I tried very hard, with only moderate success, to try to recognize
                    units—the best Embassy, the most successful political section, etc.—as opposed
                    to individual solo performances. That is not in the culture of the Foreign
                    Service; it is not truly a Service; there is no “rushing in” to take over
                    someone else's position in case of need. The Service consists of people much
                    more oriented to a strict division of labor with each person knowing what he or
                    she is doing, trying to do the best job possible. The Service's willingness to
                    accept such things as unpleasant living environments is very positive; there
                    isn't much whining about issues of that kind; on the contrary there are many
                    more examples of people willing to do what is asked of them and only
                    subsequently negotiating for better positions and conditions. But the whole
                    culture of the Foreign Service is oriented toward individual, not team,
                    recognition. If you can generalize about a group consisting of about 4,900
                    generalists and 3,300 specialists, you would have to say that the Service
                    accepts the idea that discipline is a “good thing”, that management is a “good
                    thing”, leadership is a “good thing” and that State Department could be a lot
                    more effective and efficient with more of these “good things”. But on a
                    day-to-day basis, the exercise of the “good things” might well arouse some
                    hesitation among Foreign Service individuals who might wonder whether the
                    perceived sacrifice that they might be called upon to make is really
                    necessary.</p>
                <p>In summary, I think that the Foreign Service has been desperate for strong
                    leadership as long as it is participatory leadership, which provides the Foreign
                    Service, individually and collectively, an opportunity to participate in some of
                    the major decisions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me divert for a moment to the macromanagement question
                        of the international activities. Are you satisfied that the U.S. Government
                        as a whole has a reasonably good idea of what the role the Department of
                        State is supposed to play?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SELIN: I don't think so. There is one view with which I have no sympathy at all
                    which proposed that the State Department be to foreign affairs what the Justice
                    Department is to legal matters. That is to say, that regardless of the issue,
                    all representation, all negotiations, all diplomacy with other nations should be
                    conducted by State Department officials. The idea that a very complicated
                    environmental treaty or a very complicated trade agreement should be negotiated
                    exclusively by the State Department is ridiculous. To be sure, the Department
                    has a role to play. It should provide the policy consistency and the bulk of the
                    overseas services, —e.g. administrative support, security, American citizens
                    services—which are most efficiently provided by a monopoly instead of separate
                    agencies.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>But the content of negotiations, of diplomacy and of reporting has become so
                    specialized and so technical, that the foreign affairs core functions—State,
                    AID, USIA, CIA, the Agriculture Service—are now left to form the “warp and woof”
                    of the fabric of overseas operations—that is the framework and the continuity of
                    overseas service. A number of professional services with overseas representation
                    —which may or may not have a continuing body of experts who serve overseas—have
                    grown in the last fifteen years. The Foreign Agriculture Service does have a
                    professional corps which spends most of its career overseas; the Foreign
                    Commercial Service does not—they are in and out. A lot of other parts of
                    Agriculture, or the Defense Department, or EPA, for example, have not
                    established professional overseas organizations. These institutions believe that
                    people can do one or two tours overseas and then return to driving tanks or
                    doing environmental analysis in the U.S. I don't think that is very effective.
                    Whereas the State Department doesn't and shouldn't have a monopoly on
                    negotiating and reporting, those organizations that should participate, need to
                    make a greater investment in having a professional overseas service which would
                    permit them to have more qualified to handle their overseas operations. I refer
                    here to such skills as languages, an understanding of what an Embassy is,
                    culture knowledge, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Does that thought suggest that you would like to the
                        Foreign Service Act applied to all personnel assigned overseas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SELIN: If I really had my choice, I would prefer to see two things: first) a
                    major reorganization of the foreign affairs agencies—something comparable to the
                    Defense Department reorganization of 1958—which would replace State Department
                    with a Department of Foreign Affairs which would encompass the present State
                    Department, AID, USIA, ACDA and probably the Foreign Commercial Service. I would
                    exclude the Foreign Agriculture Service, which would make the plan somewhat
                    inconsistent, but the Department of Foreign Affairs would have no relative
                    advantage to offer FAS. The organizations in the new Department of Foreign
                    Affairs would be under the line control of the Secretary of State, much as the
                    military departments, the unified commands and the specified commands are under
                    the Secretary of Defense.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>My second objective would be the establishment of a single Foreign Service so
                    that whenever an individual was assigned to an overseas position, he or she
                    would be seconded to that Service and not any longer be the employee of the
                    agency that he or she just left. That agency would reimburse the Service for the
                    cost of the employee; there would be a single set of benefits applicable to all
                    American personnel assigned overseas; there would be single set of training
                    programs. Most of the officers would be seconded for more than one assignment so
                    that those going overseas would be subject to the overseas training policy, etc.
                    This would certainly be applicable all of the “main-line” agencies; that is,
                    those that have more than a handful of personnel overseas. The unified approach
                    would not apply to, for example, a Naval Medical Research unit which might be
                    engaged in research on tropical medicine, which may have to be done in Panama or
                    Indonesia, but are clearly not part of a global system. I would distinguish
                    between people who carrying out technical activities which may be primarily
                    extension of domestic programs, but happen to incidentally take place overseas
                    and those which are an integral part of the U.S. Government overseas programs.
                    In the latter group, I would include the personnel of the Federal Aviation
                    Agency, the Department of Transportation and the Justice Department. They are
                    serving in overseas assignments and are part of the U.S. Government overseas
                    programs. They are under de facto or de jure authority of an Ambassador and
                    should be treated in terms of status and compensation like a Foreign Service
                    employee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you see the foreign policy consequences being of
                        our present disparate personnel systems?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SELIN: The fact is that the Ambassador is held responsible for all activities at
                    his or her post. We have taken steps which to any rational person might look
                    rather trivial, but having been on the firing line for a couple of years, are to
                    me rather consequential. They were all intended to enhance the Ambassador's
                    authority. I believe that on a day-to-day operational basis and in the policy
                    determination area, an Embassy's problems are relatively minor. The more acute
                    problems are related to inefficiencies. Resources are so tight that we really
                    can't afford to have Minister-Counselors for three-four persons organizations.
                    We can't afford to have separate agricultural or commercial sections or in some
                    cases even political sections in smaller Embassies. Those instances are a
                    deplorable waste of resources. Given that funds are so scarce, we could utilize
                    the scarce resources in better ways than in the overhead costs that these small
                    sections incur. Having said all that, I don't think that a case can be made that
                    these small sections undermine each other; it is just that we could have more
                    people assigned abroad if we didn't have to support some of unnecessary overhead
                    costs which are devoted to independent organizations, with the resulting
                    consequences of over-ranked officers with representational housing and other
                    expenses. These situations arise from the attitudes of their Washington parent
                    organizations.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What impact has modern technology—e.g. communications—had
                        on the way the Department conducts its operations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SELIN: Of all the new technologies, communications is probably the one that the
                    Department has absorbed the best.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What effect has the print and the visual media, with its
                        greatly improved communication systems, had on the conduct of, foreign
                        affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SELIN: I don't think that either State or CIA has caught up to that new
                    phenomenon. Clearly, the Department does much too much political reporting. We
                    have political reporting requirements that must have been set twenty or thirty
                    years ago. These reports permit INR and others to write an analysis of how a
                    particular party in Country X will do in the next election. I don't think that
                    either the field report or the Washington analysis adds much to policy
                    development and furthermore, much of the information sent by the field is
                    probably already available from good journalists. It is pretty clear that the
                    Department's reporting is not really focused on what is not available from the
                    press or other sources which are already available to Washington offices. It
                    should be concentrating on information not available which will supplement media
                    reports. CIA is worse; overt information should only be collected to fill
                    informational holes not available from non-governmental sources. At the same
                    time, I am not very sympathetic to the criticism that we only deal with the
                    elites and don't take “the pulse” of the common people. It is probably much too
                    much the other way; we deal with all kinds of people who have little
                    influence—people with whom contacts are just not worth the effort.</p>
                <p>In general, I don't think that the U.S. Government's reporting has caught up with
                    the major expansion of information now available from other sources such as the
                    media.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During some of my interviews, I have encountered a
                        confusion between “management” and “administration”, particularly among
                        Foreign Service officers. Have you had to face that problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SELIN: Not really. In my definition, administration is a matter of taking the
                    tools you are given and operate with them as efficiently as you can. Management
                    is basically a matter of asking: “What are we trying to do and what tools are
                    required to accomplish it?”. If you don't have the necessary tools, then you
                    construct new ones.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>The Foreign Service has understood this difference. I have done as much as I can
                    to broadcast the difference and I think that has had some effect. In my view,
                    the Under Secretary for Management doesn't have to be a Foreign Service
                    administrative officer. There are of course administrative tools that we work
                    with, but we work with people, with leadership, with project management, with
                    trying to bring the tools to support the policy. Management means leading
                    organizations and concern for people.</p>
                <p>I think the Foreign Service is beginning to understand that. The understanding is
                    increasing rapidly because you can't become an Ambassador until you know how to
                    manage. Of course, if you look at some of the choices that have been made, we
                    made not have been completely consistent with that policy, but we try. We are
                    certainly trying harder than was the case in the past.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Does the fact that the Department has to manage two
                        disparate personnel system inhibit efficiency?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SELIN: We have four separate personnel systems. I find the problems between
                    specialists and generalists more taxing and much more troublesome than managing
                    different personnel systems. I have had a very simple idea of what the Foreign
                    Service is: it is a Service for people who serve overseas. The jobs the Foreign
                    Service fills in Washington should be chosen essentially to make the Foreign
                    Service officer more effective when he or she is serving abroad. I don't really
                    care whether we have two or twenty Assistant Secretaries or other senior
                    positions who are Foreign Service officers. There are a lot of Foreign Service
                    officers who can make major contributions in a Washington position; there are a
                    lot Civil Service officers who can do the same. The key objective must be to
                    keep the Foreign Service officer overseas most of the time because that is why
                    they joined the Foreign Service in the first place. We have invested a lot of
                    resources to train those officers for overseas service and that gives them a
                    relative advantage. They can have a role in formulating foreign policy and in
                    pushing paper in Washington, but they do not have a unique advantage over Civil
                    Service officers in those roles. If you accept that point of view, then a lot of
                    the conflict between the Foreign and Civil Services disappear. We have been
                    insistent to the point of being absolute fanatics that an officer not spend more
                    than five consecutive years in Washington—preferably fewer—and that he or she
                    spend at least two-thirds of their career overseas. We started recasting the
                    diplomatic security service to insure that its members spend more time overseas
                    and less in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One final question. You raised the subject of generalist
                        versus specialist. Could you expand on your views on this subject?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>SELIN: The problem is that the Department has never had a personnel policy for
                    specialists. It has never defined what a specialist is—is it a secretary or a
                    physician or something else. We haven't made much progress on this question. We
                    started to try to define those issues that are essentially “guild” issues which
                    apply to all specialists and those issues that apply specifically to one
                    specialty or another. Every specialty, including secretaries—which is probably
                    the most populous specialty—did not have a decent job ladder, didn't have any
                    kind of consistent training concept. We haven't made much progress, as I said
                    earlier, but we have extended job ladders by introducing more consistent rules
                    for advancement. We have made some progress in identifying what training is
                    required. We have not done as well in identifying those traits which are common
                    to all specialties as compared to determining what specialties the Department
                    needs and how to make each of them useful.</p>
                <p>There is a lot to be learned from the military system in this regard; it has
                    commissioned and non-commissioned personnel and also warrant officers, who are a
                    kind of commissioned specialist. A warrant officer is a high ranking specialist
                    who however is not being trained to assume generalist responsibilities. A
                    warrant officer carries out his or her duties at a very high level of
                    proficiency with high compensation, but does not generate inefficiencies by
                    being placed in a training program designed to prepare an employee for
                    unpredictable assignments. Commissioned officers are essentially generalists who
                    have specializations; they are all being trained to be general officers. It is
                    true that some know more about armor, some about engineering, some about
                    artillery, but they still need to know about combined arms strategies and
                    tactics. The Department has done too little of that; the military is less
                    specialized than the Department of State. The military, if it wants someone to
                    fly helicopters for twenty years, employs a warrant officer and not a pilot.
                    Pilots do a lot of other things; they have to prepared to run the Air Force and
                    not just fly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At this point. I would like to thank you very much for
                        giving us time for this very interesting interview. Many thanks.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
