<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000622">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Jeane Jordan Kirkpatrick </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Women Ambassadors Series</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR JEANE JORDAN KIRKPATRICK</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Ann Miller Morin </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 28, 1987</p>
                <p>Copyright Ann Miller Morin (used with permission)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you perceive as the principal goal of your
                        mission when you went to the U.N.?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Oh, to represent the United States in the United Nations, which is
                    more controversial than it sounds. I learned rather quickly, because when I said
                    that in response to questions, it was often suggested to me that the job of the
                    U.S. permanent representative to the United Nations was more appropriately
                    conceived as representing the United Nations to the United States. I stuck
                    rather staunchly to my own conception, which happened also to be the
                    president's.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a nice distinction. Were you given any special
                        training by the State Department before you went?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: No. I wasn't given any. I was given some briefings. I did spend
                    quite a bit of time actually with staff, for example, in the Bureau of IO
                    (Bureau of International Organizations). And I did some talking on my own
                    initiative to former U.N. permanent representatives. And I spent a day in New
                    York with Don McHenry [US permanent representative to the U.N., 1979-81], who
                    was very helpful, and with Bill Den Heuvel and the team of ambassadors who were
                    with the mission then. I wouldn't say I was given any special training by the
                    department, but where I asked for briefings, I got them. Okay?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Now there is a difference. There is, as you know, a
                        course for ambassadors, but you did not take it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: No, I didn't even know that until this minute.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did not know that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a course mainly for bilateral ambassadors, but Jean
                        Gerard [US ambassador to UNESCO, 1981 - 1985] took it, for example.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Did she really? I didn't even know there was one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think there should be one before people go to
                        multi-lateral places?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I don't know. I don't think the department's much good on
                    multilateral diplomacy. And, quite frankly, unless they know more than I think
                    they generally show evidence of, I'm not sure it would be very helpful. Now,
                    having said that, I do believe that it would have been very useful to have some
                    training—a course, a short course—on what might be called the sort of routine
                    functions of running a mission. That, I think, could have been helpful. I really
                    think that the FSI [training], for example, and most of the training in the
                    department on multi-lateral diplomacy is quite poor. I think it ought to be
                    improved; could be improved and, I hope will be improved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. You're not the first to have said that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I'm sure. No, I think there ought to be a cone on multi-lateral
                    diplomacy, in fact. A formal recommendation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's quite distinct, isn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: It's very different; it's really very different.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Even the way you proceed is totally different.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: It's very different, really. I think that there are some aspects of
                    running a mission that clearly are in common among all heads of mission; and it
                    would have been useful, sure, to have that—to have a short course on that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, which you could have done in a couple of weeks or
                        so.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Or even a week, as a matter of fact, would have been helpful.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, did you believe that your gender would be an asset or
                        a liability? You were the first woman.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: It might. I had no notion what a shock my gender would be. Let me
                    tell you how much the first woman I was. I was not only the first woman to head
                    the U.S. Mission to the United Nations. I was the first woman to ever represent
                    a major power at the U.N. I was the first woman to ever represent a western
                    government at the United Nations. Western—broadly interpreted, that means a
                    European government; Eastern Europe or Western Europe. There had only been about
                    three or four women to head missions at the United Nations before I got there.
                    There had been a Guyanese, there had been a Sri Lankan, Mrs. Bandaranaike headed
                    their mission briefly. There had been a Liberian; that's about all. Such a big
                    shock.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there none from South America?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: No, I don't think so. I didn't really know the extent to which the
                    diplomatic corps of the world and the diplomatic profession are an exclusive
                    male preserve. I also was the first woman—think about this: I was the first
                    woman to sit in the National Security Council on a regular basis, much less in
                    what I sat in, which was the inner circle of the NSPG (National Security
                    Planning Group), of which I was a member of in a, not ex-officio, but personal
                    capacity. I didn't think there'd ever been a woman in those councils on a
                    regular basis at the table.</p>
                <p>There are a few women who have made their way into the background; not even many
                    of those, though. So I think my appointment was a big shock to my colleagues at
                    the United Nations. It was a bigger shock than I realized it was going to be. I
                    hadn't thought much about it before I accepted, quite frankly. I had grown
                    accustomed to being the only woman in a lot of rooms that I was in. I was the
                    first woman on the Rank and Tenure Committee at the University, the first woman
                    to be a Senior Scholar here at the American Enterprise Institute. But even so, I
                    didn't think much about it; I didn't give much thought to it. And it turned out
                    to be a bigger shock to my colleagues than I'd dreamed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. It rocked the world.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: It rocked them. I think that's fair to say; it rocked them. I mean,
                    it would have been strange enough for a woman—for any western country to send a
                    woman; but for the United States to send a woman. By the way, when I said, not
                    only was there no woman head of mission, there weren't any women, you know, as
                    ambassadors. The Soviets have 11 ambassadors; not one is a woman. The United
                    States had five ambassadors; well, there was one woman ambassador there, Joan
                    Spiro. But there are very, very few senior women around the U.N. system, in any
                    role whatsoever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How are they perceived at the U.N.—these other women who
                        are in the background?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: After my appointment, two other women were appointed by western
                    nations. The Belgians appointed Edmonde DeVer as permanent representative, where
                    she has performed extremely well, let me say; and today admits to more
                    consciousness about being a woman in that role than she would admit when she got
                    there. She's undergone a little consciousness-raising herself, so's she's a
                    little franker about it. She's a career officer, very highly regarded. The Swiss
                    appointed a woman to head their mission. Now they're observers, but still they
                    participate quite a lot. Nobody believes that those women would have been
                    appointed if I hadn't been appointed. But, by the way, I left, Edmonde is
                    leaving this week, the Swiss has already left. Once again, there is no woman at
                    the top of any western mission. I don't know whether we made any permanent
                    impact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I'm sure it will be easier for the next one who will
                        eventually go.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Eventually.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they were perceived as—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: As competent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As competent. I guess you took most of the flak.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Well, they came about, oh, a year-and-a-half to two years after I
                    was there. I think the shock was past then. But I have no doubt that my
                    appointment and survival of those first two years, which was very tough, in fact
                    opened doors for women in career foreign service positions in those two
                    countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm sure it did, because not only did you survive, but you
                        survived a lot longer than many men.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: That's right. I stayed longer than anybody since Adlai
                    Stevenson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And were perceived as successful. Now did events prove
                        that your gender was a plus or a minus?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I don't know. You know, in the beginning, I think it was definitely
                    a minus. I have no doubt that it was. That's an extremely complicated,
                    difficult, frustrating job, which is the big reason that the turnover is so
                    rapid in it. Don McHenry said to me, for example, that I had to be ready to be
                    criticized for not being adequately accessible. “Because,” he said, “no matter
                    how much time you spend with representatives of all of the other countries
                    represented here, it will never be as much as people think you should.” You're
                    dealing with 159 countries, and it's enormously complicated and difficult. They
                    all want to see the Permanent Representative. If they're an ambassador, they
                    want to see the Permanent Representative, in spite of the fact that you've got
                    five other ambassadors there who are very competent. The demands are fantastic.
                    So it's a very difficult job for anybody.</p>
                <p>I think there was also quite a lot of deep scepticism and concern about the
                    Reagan administration. That was also a problem, I think. In the beginning,
                    nobody knew what kind of people Reagan appointees were going to be. And on top
                    of it, I was a woman. I think it was a problem—it just made me a little more
                    strange than I already would have been as a Reagan appointee, or as a political
                    appointee, because probably 80% of the U.N. perm reps are career officers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Eighty percent are career officers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Well, I don't know. Seventy-five percent. It's a high percentage. By
                    the way, most of the ones who aren't are academics, which is kind of
                    interesting; professors of constitutional law and so forth. I think with some of
                    the Europeans, the Asians, at least as much as the Africans and the Arabs, I
                    sensed some sort of sex-related reticences—static, I would say. I think they
                    just regarded me as a very odd creature. Now, since nobody ever gave me any
                    training in how to be an ambassador, maybe I was a pretty odd creature.
                    (Laughter) This was maybe a little true, though I was, of course, very serious
                    from the very beginning, and I worked prodigiously. And I did something else
                    that most of Americans haven't done, namely, I spoke a couple of languages well
                    enough to do business in them, which is very important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: French is one?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: French and Spanish. Those are two very useful languages at the U.N.
                    It is very useful at the U.N. to speak other languages, to be able to really
                    function in them. I am told that I was the first U.S. perm rep who could
                    actually function in other languages. Now, of course, Dick Walters [US permanent
                    representative to the U.N., 1985-89] functions in nine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: But that helped. Once I established myself, demonstrated to my
                    colleagues that I was serious and I did my work, and that I was business-like, I
                    think in fact that I probably profited as much from being a woman as I had ever
                    suffered. I do believe that there are whole cultures in which men, like
                    ambassadors and foreign ministers, and even heads of state, may find it a little
                    easier to deal with a woman than with another man. I think in macho cultures,
                    like both Latin and Arab—and somebody said African—they're much less likely to
                    regard a woman as a competitor. And I think women are generally, including me,
                    trained to be good listeners. I did an awful lot of listening and a lot of
                    seeking of advice, and my colleagues liked that. So I think that I probably had
                    some advantages overall, once I got over the original sort of shock of being a
                    woman in there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that you could “get away” with saying things
                        directly to a man that another man couldn't say?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Millicent Fenwick [US ambassador to the UN Food and
                        Agriculture Organization, 1983-86] has reported that from her job. She said,
                        “I can say the most outrageous things, and because I'm a woman they accept
                        this.” And I wondered if that would hold true with the U.N., or maybe
                        they're more sensitive there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: There's an interesting culture at the U.N.; it's an interesting mix
                    of informality and highly stylized diplomatic communication. Everybody's on a
                    first-name basis almost immediately; and I mean everybody, except the
                    Vietnamese, the Khmer Rouge, the PLO, the people we don't speak to at all. My
                    Soviet colleague and I were on a first-name basis from within the first two or
                    three weeks I was there. On the other hand, everybody is very polite, and
                    relatively formal; I mean, formal in the conduct of business in a context of
                    informal salutations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's curious.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: It's an interesting mix. That's observed by almost everybody. I
                    think I adapted, frankly, my own style of communication to that of my colleagues
                    that I observed around me, especially the British, the French and the Dutch.
                    When I was with Latins, I talked like the Latins talk to each other—as “the
                    ambassadors,” you know. I didn't associate with anybody but ambassadors; of
                    course, there are so many ambassadors at the U.N. I don't think I said many
                    outrageous things. I will say this: maybe I was more outrageous than I realized.
                    I developed very quickly a reputation for extraordinary and often shocking
                    candor. Now, I never thought of myself as particularly candid. Nobody ever
                    called me particularly candid before I went to the U.N., so I think I must have
                    been speaking in a way that made me seem shockingly frank.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it one of your desires, ambitions, goals when you went
                        there to elevate the status of the United States at the UN, where we have
                        been kicked around for so long?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I don't think it was one of my desires when I went there, but it
                    rapidly became my principal goal. (Laughter) When I fully realized our condition
                    there, then it became an almost obsessive goal, frankly. Not just to elevate the
                    status either; but to secure decent treatment for the United States. I always
                    said that my goal for the U.S. at the U.N. was that we should be treated with as
                    much fundamental respect and consideration as any small third world country,
                    which we were not. And we probably still are not. I didn't deliberately say
                    shocking things. When I was shocking I think it was largely inadvertent.</p>
                <p>I do agree with Millicent Fenwick about one thing, though. I think women tend to
                    communicate more directly than men. I know Millicent thinks this because I've
                    heard her say it with a little laugh. When I was trying to be as formal and
                    diplomatic as I possibly could, I was probably being more direct than most of my
                    colleagues. Americans would tend to be more direct, anyway.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you began your duty, what was your perception of the
                        career diplomats and of the State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: You know, I never thought about the State Department, to tell you
                    the truth, before I went in. I worked for the State Department once. My first
                    job ever was in the State Department and he (pointing to her husband) was my
                    boss. He was not my teacher, but he was my boss. I decided, after one year's
                    experience, that I didn't want to work at the State Department, but my problem
                    was not with the State Department, it was with big bureaucracies. I simply
                    thought I didn't want to work in a big organization. That was my only personal
                    reflection.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>I thought that the State Department had done an absolutely miserable job in
                    Central America, if I may say so. I thought that because I started following
                    U.S. policy toward Central America, particularly both El Salvador and Nicaragua,
                    in about 1978, and I followed it unusually closely. I read all the hearings. I
                    became convinced this part of the world was terribly important to us
                    strategically, and the decisions we were making there were terribly important to
                    us. I did very close analysis of predictions. When I say a “bad job,” a “lousy
                    job,” I mean to say that the predictions that were made turned out to be not
                    true; and all those standard kinds of objective criteria about the adequacy of
                    analysis. So I guess I had a poor opinion of the group. But I mainly attributed
                    it to the Carter Administration, frankly, rather than the Foreign Service. I
                    didn't have any generalizations about the Foreign Service. I developed some
                    views about what I took to be some biases—policy biases—in the Foreign Service
                    rather early on, especially concerning the Middle East. And I think I discerned
                    those famous State Department Arabists rather early on. I became aware of this
                    because we were continually dealing with attacks on Israel at the United
                    Nations. It was the first issue I dealt with, and then obsessively through time,
                    we were dealing with complaints against Israel. I also was dealing with the IO
                    Bureau and the Secretary of State.</p>
                <p>One of the crazy things about the job of perm rep is that you have to operate on
                    many different levels. Any perm rep has to, in fact. I found that the NEA Bureau
                    was, in those days, out of step with the administration; by which I mean the
                    secretary of state, with whom they should have been in step, and the national
                    security advisor, and the president, and me. It was difficult; it was much
                    harder than it should have been to get support and staffing to implement
                    decisions made by the heads of government—the U.S. government. That's sort of
                    the first, of what might be called “opinion” about the Foreign Service, and it
                    wasn't about the Foreign Service; it was about a particular group of Foreign
                    Service officers located in a particular place in the department. But when I
                    came in, I didn't really have any views about the State Department. I mean, I
                    assumed they were competent professionals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before you had Ambassador Sherman, you had somebody else
                        with whom you just did not click. But that was a personality thing, wasn't
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I hope so. It didn't have anything to do with Foreign Service, I
                    don't think. It may have had something to do with sex roles. I chose him, by the
                    way. I take responsibility. But the problem was one which, I am told, the women
                    political ambassadors have rather more frequently than others. And the problem
                    was basically—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The DCM syndrome?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: The DCM syndrome. He literally proposed to me the first week that I
                    went to New York, that in order to learn something about the way the U.N. system
                    works, perhaps I would like to take a trip around the world, observing missions
                    and all that. He assumed I was not going to be interested in the running of the
                    mission; he assumed I was not going to be interested in policy, he assumed I
                    wasn't going to be interested in administration, and he assumed that it was
                    going to be his job to do it all. And I felt very strongly that he
                    systematically, not only cut me out, but cut me out and simultaneously took
                    charge of the mission and the relationships in Washington and the process, in a
                    way that was going to be incompatible with my functioning. I hate letting people
                    go, firing people; I really hate it. In my life, generally, I hate it. I keep
                    people a long time because I hate it so much, and I have fired very few people.
                    He was the only person I ever let go at the U.N. the whole time I was there, out
                    of a lot of people. But I concluded, and all the other [US] ambassadors up there
                    concluded, by the way, that we were not going to be able to function without
                    getting rid of him. And so, feeling a real sense of personal failure about
                    having chosen the wrong person, I went to Joan Clark [director general of the
                    Foreign Service]. Or maybe I told Al Haig first. But very early on, I went to
                    Joan Clark and told her my problem; I confessed my problem, and said basically I
                    wanted some help about getting rid of him. I understand Anne Armstrong [US
                    ambassador to Britain, 1976-77] has had a very similar experience in
                    Britain.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, she did with Ron Spiers [deputy chief of mission,
                        American Embassy, London] until they finally sat down and talked it out. And
                        then it was all right. But they were on the point of positively blowing up.
                        The one who had—well, there are several. Ruth Farkas [US ambassador to
                        Luxembourg, 1973-76] had bad trouble.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Yes, I heard that, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Anne Cox Chambers [US ambassador to Belgium 1977-81]
                        had a very bad time. As you say, it happens.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: And Geri Joseph [US ambassador to the Netherlands, 1978-81], I
                    think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have not interviewed Geri Joseph. I'll be interested in
                        that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: She's very good; she did a super job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But that is definitely a theme that runs through this.
                        It's an arrogance in a certain age Foreign Service officer.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Would he have treated a man as he treated me? I'm not sure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't think so; no. I don't think so. But a political
                        man might have been given a rough time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Uh-hmm, uh-hmm.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But never as bad as the women are; I don't think. And I
                        have talked to a couple of hundred people on this subject. But it seems to
                        be a certain generation, and thank goodness it's not the entire
                        generation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: That's great. I'm happy to hear that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that man, perhaps, in his 50s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, there you are. It's the “old” Foreign Service, and
                        it runs right through.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Very smart, very competent guy. I told him, when I told him that I
                    was going to let him go, request his transfer, I told him I didn't want to
                    destroy him; I didn't want to destroy his career. I believed he would, in fact,
                    do well for the United States as an ambassador some place else. And I felt that.
                    And he did as a matter of fact. But not with me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, of course, there is a question of personality.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I don't think it was personality. I don't think we had a problem in
                    personality. I think, actually, we were sort of the people who would have
                    enjoyed each other as dinner partners, you know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it was a matter of his attitude, really, more than
                        anything else?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: It really was. It was really a work-related attitude.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What I don't understand is how these men, and it happens
                        over and over, can be so stupid, when they don't have the strong cards in
                        their hands.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: That's right. You'd think they'd be a little more cautious.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, wouldn't you? Especially when it's their
                        career.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: He was totally surprised, by the way, by my decision.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he really? Had no idea that you—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Totally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did you keep him? I did not know that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Two months maybe. I made the decision early.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I presume you hadn't know him very well, just had no
                        idea.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: No, I had not. I had not. I had decided myself that I wanted to get
                    a Foreign Service officer as a deputy because I had no experience in the State
                    Department, and I just thought it would make sense to do that. But I didn't do
                    it after I let him go, by the way. I didn't do it again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's when you took Adelman [senior political analyst,
                        Stanford Research Institute, Arlington, Va.]?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I took Adelman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And he was somebody you had known?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Yes, though I hadn't known him well. But I had known him somewhat.
                    And I decided I didn't want a Foreign Service officer there. I was so stung and
                    so burned by that experience, quite frankly. I was determined to try to take
                    charge of this job and to try to do it, and I didn't want somebody else—I feared
                    that a Foreign Service officer in that job—. It's a potentially very influential
                    job, and I just didn't want somebody else trying to use the job to take over. By
                    the way, I love Bill Sherman, of course.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Isn't he nice?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: With Bill Sherman, we were able to do some very good things
                    vis-�-vis the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I know you got them some—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: We got them some housing allowances, which had become very
                    controversial, but it was very important to do. And we did a lot of sort of
                    upgrading. We did a lot of support—we inaugurated a lot of support services,
                    which enabled us to upgrade the quality of the Foreign Service also. I learned
                    some things about staffing in the Foreign Service at the U.N. I don't know if
                    you know this, but I learned, for example, that it was considered one of the
                    least desirable posts in the system. And that it was a dumping ground. And I
                    established a rule which—I established it for myself—that nobody could come to
                    the U.S. Mission—nobody could be assigned to the U.S. Mission unless I had
                    personally interviewed them and okayed them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which made them feel selected.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which is psychologically very good. Had you interviewed
                        this other gentleman before?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Yes, I had. I interviewed him; I had lunch with him; I talked to my
                    friends about him; I talked to mutual friends about him. I did all the things
                    that one should have done. He had, moreover, the kinds of skills that I
                    particularly respect. He was very carefully chosen; I had given it a lot of
                    thought. And so all of the reasons—you notice the first thing I said to you was,
                    “I chose him myself.” (Laughter) You know, I was devastated by the mistake I
                    made, but I had to face the fact that I had made a real mistake. And I think I
                    was dead right in making the decision of cutting very early on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, in Steering the Elephant [Rector, Robert &amp;
                        Sanera, Michael, editors, Steering the Elephant: How Washington Works, New
                        York: Universe Books, 1987.], this book about managing—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Oh, yes, right, Steering the Elephant.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You list six different steps to take—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Do I? I don't even remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, actually, you do. And I notice one of them—the first
                        thing you say is to “select your key players, who have professional
                        knowledge, who are professionals.” And then you talk about “mastering the
                        problems,” “digging in yourself,” and “having control of things.” And then
                        “selecting good career staff.” Now, am I right in inferring from that that
                        you would not put career people in any of the top slots?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: No, that's not right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is not so?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right. Let's go into that then. When you went into
                        this business, how much opportunity did you have to choose your own people?
                        How much of a free hand were you given?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I had a lot. I had very good support from the White House. Now, I
                    didn't have a completely free hand. There was a kind of mystique, which—Dave
                    Stockman [director, Office of Budget and Management] described it in his book,
                    and I'm describing it in mine, too, of the administration in the very early
                    days. Our most serious charge was that we were not to be taken over by the
                    bureaucracy. This was really taken very seriously in the cabinet
                    indoctrinations. I didn't go to any State Department indoctrinations, but I sure
                    went to cabinet indoctrinations, and this was all taken very seriously. I took
                    it sort of seriously, because we were told to, you know. That's what we were all
                    supposed to be doing. We had some ideas, all of us, in the early days about some
                    policy goals we really were very serious about accomplishing.</p>
                <p>Nothing about this, however, prevented me from choosing a foreign service officer
                    as my number one deputy, which is the best proof that I didn't mean I wouldn't
                    go to a professional for that. I would. Except, that having made the mistake I
                    made with him, I was simply scared to go back there twice. I didn't have the
                    self-confidence, quite frankly. I would have a lot more self-confidence today.
                    And I had a lot more self-confidence by the time I left. That was really a
                    pretty traumatic experience for me.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it must have been. To have this huge job and all it
                        involves, totally different from things you've done before, and not know the
                        rules of the game, so to speak; and then to have this happen. I don't know
                        how you survived it. (Laughter)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Well, you know, I don't know how I survived those first months
                    either. And I've thought about that. I've said it to Kirk a good many times. And
                    as I'm writing the book, I'm sort of reliving certain of those experiences. And,
                    quite frankly, I'm a little surprised that I survived that first six months
                    because there was so much I didn't know, and so many ways to go wrong. And I was
                    taking several of them, I think. So many pitfalls that I wasn't even aware
                    of.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With everybody taking potshots at you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How far down were you able to go in selecting staff? You
                        selected the other four ambassadors, I presume?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Yes and no. I mean, remember that I was a Democrat, and so I was
                    regarded with a lot of suspicion, actually, by, for example, the “kitchen
                    cabinet.” They wanted me definitely to take some long-time Republican with me to
                    the U.N., and I chose Chuck Lichtenstein [assistant to the president, Nixon
                    White House; deputy counsel, Ford WhitHouse], who happens to be an old friend of
                    ours as well as a long-time Republican. And there was this great sigh of relief,
                    when I proposed Lichtenstein, from the White House group in the “kitchen
                    cabinet,” because they think “good old Chuck,” because he had been in the
                    Goldwater campaign and all those things. And so I had to take somebody like
                    that, and Chuck fit that dandily. I wanted myself,—I had some views about area
                    competence, area culture and language competence. I feel very deeply that that
                    is one of our great strengths as a nation—our pluralism—and that we ought to
                    utilize it. I had also talked to Don McHenry and I'd studied where we were, and
                    it was clear to me—and Don agreed, by the way—that there was a big opportunity
                    with Latin America. And so I thought about Jos� Sorzano [political scientist,
                    Georgetown University]. Basically, I came to him out of a theory about what we
                    needed. I tried to get Ted Briggs, just to give you another example of having
                    attempted to get professionals—to bring in professionals at the top. The only
                    reason I didn't get Ted Briggs is that he turned me down for reasons that seemed
                    sensible to him, because he was offered a deputy assistant job in the department
                    about the same time. And I understood perfectly. But I wanted somebody like
                    that. I didn't get Ted Briggs; I did get Jos�, who was very sophisticated and
                    good. Who else did I have? I don't even remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, eventually, you had Sherman.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was for running the nuts and bolts, wasn't he? Sort of
                        an admin. counselor?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: No, he was a lot more than that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he more than that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Sure. He was an Asia specialist, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I know that, but I meant how you used him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I used him as an Asia specialist. Every one of our ambassadors had
                    major area responsibilities. It was terribly important to us, and this is
                    something I would like to teach the department about multi-lateral diplomacy and
                    staffing for it. It made a big difference in our effectiveness to have at the
                    ambassadorial level somebody who was genuinely expert in every major area of the
                    world, and at home in the language and culture. Every one of them had assigned,
                    as a serious part of their assignment, the development of close personal
                    relations with people from their region, and following those regional problems,
                    in addition to whatever functional responsibilities they had in the mission.
                    Bill Sherman was our Asia specialist and did a lot with regard to all of the
                    U.S. Mission's activities concerning Asia, and then had the political [work]. I
                    mean, we'd function like ward heelers, too. When it came time to try to round up
                    votes, then Bill worked the Asian constituency. But he regularly followed those
                    issues and cultivated those people. He was not just a “nuts and bolts” man, by
                    any means. He supervised the administrative counselor, and he knew how the
                    bureaucracy worked. He's the man who did that, and he kept that all oiled.
                    That's not a “nuts and bolts” job either; that's something more subtle in a
                    complicated mission like we had, with complicated relations with the department.
                    That's a lot more demanding, and a heck of a job, I think, frankly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, yes, and also the U.N. is different than any other
                        mission because you have to worry about things like parking tickets. I mean,
                        you have the whole weight of all those 158 other missions.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Sure. Now we put Liechtenstein in; that's host country relations.
                    Are we going to be able to get the Mexican ambassador out of jail if he's
                    punched New York cop? Which happened.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now, did you take an area of Europe or something for
                        yourself? Or did you sort of keep the team running?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I took the Security Council, and I took the special relations with
                    the ambassadors in the Security Council, plus running the mission. But I was the
                    only one who didn't have a geographical area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this division of expertise, division of
                        responsibilities, enable you to concentrate on the substantive issues? You
                        didn't have to worry much about the actual running of the mission?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I would say that—I had a very good team, let me say. And I tried
                    very hard to allocate functions and responsibilities so that everybody was very
                    clear about what they should do, and what they were responsible for. I had a lot
                    of confidence in them. And so it is a fact that I delegated a lot. At any given
                    time, however, I stayed in touch with everybody.</p>
                <p>I stayed in touch whenever there were problems. We had particular problems
                    regarding particular areas of operation. Obviously, I was in touch with those. I
                    stayed in touch from time to time with everything, but I did a lot of delegating
                    and I had confidence that the people who were in charge were doing it right. And
                    they did, by and large. When I developed a concern about whether something was
                    going right, then I focused very intensively on it until I became convinced that
                    it was fixed, it was on track.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, but don't you think one of the reasons this worked so
                        well is exactly what you did? You held them responsible.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I sure did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And if people know what they're responsible for—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I did, I did. I think that's terribly important; I think that's
                    terribly, terribly important. You know, sometimes it was asserted that I was
                    inaccessible by my own mission. And sometimes I was inaccessible, because I
                    spent quite a bit of time traveling back and forth to Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know you did, being in the cabinet.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: And also because there are simply so many meetings, and especially
                    the NSPG. The big thing that I participated in was the NSPG, which is really
                    where it's been at in the Reagan administration and foreign policy. And much of
                    the time, it met relatively frequently. This was absolutely essential, I think,
                    for our effective functioning. I really believe that my direct contacts in the
                    top levels of the administration were absolutely essential to our effective
                    functioning in New York. I don't think that it can work the other way, either.
                    It's just too complicated bureaucratically and you get too involved with too
                    many departments. You can't function simply through the departmental structure,
                    through the geographical bureaus and IO, because it's at too low a level. I
                    realized, like lightning striking me at a certain moment, what had happened to
                    Jimmy Carter and Don McHenry in that famous resolution, which Carter said cost
                    him the election. You remember?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: And Carter and Vance both sort of accused Don McHenry of having
                    somehow misled them. There was a moment when I had been there, I don't know, two
                    or three—six weeks maybe—when I realized what had happened on that. I understood
                    that what had happened was that Don was dealing with the bureau, and the bureau
                    was basically out of touch with Vance and Carter. And what everybody was saying
                    was true. I mean, there was a disconnect. There are a number of potentially
                    quite delicate—politically delicate—issues for any president, any secretary of
                    state. Delicate to the United States, with a lot of maybe different departmental
                    perspectives in which the bureau and the assistant secretary may not really be
                    wholly informed, or wholly in touch and wholly reflective. And if you can't plug
                    in at the top, then you're in very bad shape. You're operating in a very
                    high-visibility role all the time to have that sort of thing happen. I believe
                    something probably happened with Andy Young [US permanent representative to the
                    U.N., 1977-79] and the PLO, if I may say so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, it sounds like it, doesn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: But to keep those channels open takes time, and it meant doing a lot
                    of delegating. I think I had strong people and I think they stayed in very close
                    touch. I also had very good counselors—my political counselor, ECOSOC counselor,
                    resource management counselor. We had first class people in those jobs. And so I
                    think it worked.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the impact on your ability to get things done
                        from the fact that you were in the cabinet as well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I think it was very important. What it did was give me access
                    through those channels; that's what it did. It gave me access to authoritative
                    decisions from the top level.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>You know the U.N. is unique in the fact that it confronts us and other countries
                    with continuous decisions. We have to make choices; they have to be public; you
                    have to vote “yes” or “no.” You can't fuzz the issue because you have to act. We
                    don't control this context in which we must act.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: It's terribly important to be able to get it right. And to be able
                    to get it right, it is often necessary to be able to go right to the top, and
                    make really certain that you understand what the president and the secretary of
                    state want out of this negotiation—and what they don't want. You just can't
                    afford to run the risks of misunderstanding on some of the subtle and delicate
                    issues, where we're about to have to take a very highly public position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you see any minuses out of being in the cabinet and
                        the very fact that it took up so much of your time? You had to commute, for
                        example.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Yes, sure, but I don't think that they're as important as the
                    pluses. By the way, there's one other very important plus for the U.S.
                    Government and for the functioning at the U.N., and that is that it gives one
                    access to the ministers and even heads of states of other member states, and
                    that's very important since there is a constant stream of ministerial level
                    visitors to the U.N., and heads of states visitors. If you're a member of the
                    cabinet, then you meet them—you develop relationships with them. You can call on
                    those when you need their support. It makes a big difference for their
                    ambassadors to know that you're on good terms with their foreign minister or
                    even their head of state, and that you can call them if necessary. That's very
                    useful in getting votes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I can see that would be.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I think it's also a useful listening— I think it enhances the value
                    of the permanent representative as a listening post for the U.S. Government
                    because it multiplies the number of ears that can give input on high-level views
                    with foreign visitors. So I think it was very valuable. I think it is personally
                    very tiring. And it was personally very tiring.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It must be. Did you commute by plane?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Yes. Eastern Shuttle. I didn't “commute”, you know.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you must have come back quite often.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I think I probably—I made at least two round trips a week. Sometimes
                    I made three.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd call that “commuting.” [Laughs]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: But they were very irregular. All of the principal bodies in which I
                    participated met irregularly—Security Council, NSPG, cabinet—they all met
                    irregularly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, sure. Well, what about the social circuit? You have a
                        150 plus countries and that many national days. What did you do? How did you
                        tackle that part of it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I didn't go to most of the national days. I didn't because I just
                    couldn't. I went to a few—just a few. I did a very great deal of socializing.
                    The best way I know to tell you how much socializing I did is to tell you that
                    the nature of my relationships were such that when I was leaving, for the last
                    two months I was there, I went to a dinner in my honor every night. And the last
                    month I was there, I went to a luncheon and a dinner in my honor. And I left a
                    good many people without, you know, having turned down their urgings to let them
                    have a dinner in my honor, because I didn't have time. It's just another way of
                    saying that I became very deeply and thoroughly involved in the U.N. social
                    circuit. But I never really got very much involved in the national days because
                    I couldn't do it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you see that those were covered?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I saw that they were covered. They were always covered at the level
                    of counselor or above—minister counselor or above. It's very important, by the
                    way, for the United States to have multiple ambassadors at the U.N., too. The
                    ambassadors who were responsible for the area were also responsible for the
                    national days for that area. So Bill Sherman would cover all the Asian ones and
                    Jose would cover the Latin ones.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And that would come to be the expected thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Exactly. Precisely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Otherwise, you'd totally wear yourself out, I would
                        think.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: That's right. So we would have at least an ambassador and usually a
                    counselor, and often then a political officer. We were very well covered at
                    national days, but I didn't do much of the covering. I did very few receptions,
                    frankly, except when there was a big one in honor of a head of state or
                    something. Then I did those.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mostly dinner parties?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Mostly dinner parties. I did lots and lots and lots of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where you could discuss things.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Right; exactly. Dinners and lunches.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where you could actually sit and discuss things.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Lunches are very big for Security Council business. I've still not
                    lost the weight I gained there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, you had no party backing. You've already said that
                        the “kitchen cabinet” eyed you with a little bit of dismay.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Uh-hmm.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you get your clout? Was it from the fact that
                        you were the in-house intellectual? Or was it because you knew the
                        President, and he had picked you? You were a woman and a Democrat.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: That's right. Well, I didn't have any clout that I didn't build
                    after I was appointed. Let's put it that way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you built it after you were appointed.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I had to have some, I guess, to be appointed. The President
                    appointed me to his Senior Foreign Policy Advisory Group after he was elected
                    and before he was inaugurated. That was headed by Gerald Ford, you may recall. I
                    was, in fact, the only member of that who wasn't either a senator or a previous
                    cabinet member.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is that so? This was the transition—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Yes, this was transition staff. Ronald Reagan and I sort of hit it
                    off; that's the best way I know how to put that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, there's nothing like that, apparently.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: That's right. And Bill Casey [director of the CIA] and I were also
                    good friends. We hit it off too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you known him before?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: No, never. Met him the same day I met Ronald Reagan. As a matter of
                    fact, I met Ronald Reagan, Ed Meese [counselor to the President] and Bill Casey
                    the same day. We did; you remember that? In 1980 was when I met them all. I
                    think, frankly, I knew more about some issues than the other people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Well, he obviously had confidence in you, which would
                        be an important thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: And I knew Dick Allen [Richard Allen, national security advisor,
                    1981-82], too. I did know Dick Allen. I didn't know Judge Clark [William P.
                    Clark, Judge, deputy secretary of state, national security advisor] until he was
                    appointed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the problems that you had? You had successes,
                        too, but, if you don't mind, let's discuss the problems for awhile. It
                        turned out to be one of your great successes, when Israel bombed the
                        Iraqis.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Well, until Alexander Haig made snide comments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Would you run over that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Which aspect of it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The aspect of how did you decide what actions to take?
                        Whom did you consult?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Oh gosh, I was in absolutely continuous contact with Walt Stoessel
                    [Walter Stoessel, Jr., deputy secretary of state], who was acting secretary of
                    state. And Dick Allen. And I was in intermittent contact with Ed Meese and the
                    president. But I was in touch with Walt Stoessel and Dick Allen two or three
                    times a day. I mean, every time there was a question, I was in touch with them.
                    I had a conversation with the president in advance of my first meeting with
                    Hammadi [Sa'dun Hammadi, Iraqi foreign minister], in which he made very clear
                    what he hoped I could get, and there was perfect agreement.</p>
                <p>This was a big, shocking traumatic experience for me too. My life was very
                    traumatic in those days, and things were happening to me I couldn't dream would
                    happen to anybody. There was perfect understanding between the president and Ed
                    Meese, who in those days was involved with all the issues, and Dick Allen, and
                    Walt Stoessel, about what they wanted, and my job, I thought, was to try to do
                    my very best to get it, and Al Haig was out in the Pacific.</p>
                <p>I stayed in very close touch with them. Every time a new possibility developed, I
                    was in touch with them, and I finally achieved exactly what they wanted. The
                    president couldn't have been more pleased and Walt couldn't have been more
                    pleased. I must say, it never occurred to me that Alexander Haig wouldn't be
                    pleased. We had tried to stay in touch with Haig, too, but we couldn't stay in
                    touch with Haig because the telephone connection was so bad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With the time changes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Well, no. It was telephone connections more than anything. He was in
                    Beijing and then, eventually, in Manila. We just had terrible connections and
                    the whole issue had sort of developed after he was gone and we were under very
                    heavy time pressures, and so we just had to proceed.</p>
                <p>I was totally shocked when the stories appeared in the Wall Street Journal and
                    the New York Times, saying Haig's aides said that Kirkpatrick hadn't followed
                    instructions. First he said I'd done unauthorized things and then he said he did
                    it, really. That I shouldn't have gotten that agreement but that he really got
                    it. Neither of which was true. I did what I was supposed to and I did follow
                    instructions and he didn't do it.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>As a matter of fact, this is an interesting thing; this is a sex thing, I think.
                    Hammadi—the Iraqi Foreign Minister, who is thought around the U.N. to be one of
                    the meanest, sourest people any place—I think this is a man for whom being a
                    woman probably helped me. I think he was a little nicer with me than his
                    reputation led me to believe that he was with anybody. And I was probably a
                    little nicer to him than an American male diplomat might have been, including
                    little things like writing him the letter when the elevator fell and offering
                    him various kinds of reassurances about the president's views. I was in a
                    position to do that, by the way; that helped too.</p>
                <p>He had real dislike for Haig—Hammadi did, and he expressed that several times in
                    the course of those negotiations. And then the last day, when we had finished—we
                    had got an agreement; it had actually already been announced by Brian Urquhart
                    [under secretary general of the UN]. I had a lot of witnesses to all of this—and
                    about ten minutes later, Alexander Haig called Hammadi, feeling that he could,
                    perhaps, help out in closing the deal. And Hammadi didn't even tell him that we
                    had reached an agreement. He didn't tell him anything because he didn't like
                    Alexander Haig. He just didn't respond to anything that Haig said to him,
                    basically. This left Haig with the impression that the situation wasn't closed
                    and, therefore, when he heard that there was an agreement, he thought he had
                    done it. But anyway, it was very bad.</p>
                <p>I learned from journalists on the plane, much to my shock, that Alexander
                    Haig—well, that it was Rick Burt and whoever was press counselor in those days,
                    Haig's spokesman; I've forgotten his name. Anyway, Haig had asked them to put
                    the story out that appeared in the New York Times and the Wall Street Journal.
                    And it was a fabrication. The president called me in France. (I left the day
                    this happened.) The president called me to tell me how badly he felt about it
                    and how pleased he was with my performance. And Haig called me, too, to
                    apologize and say he had nothing to do with it. He would get to the bottom of it
                    and somebody would pay. This was all lies. That was sort of an incredible
                    experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It must have been. You must have wondered if you were
                        through the looking glass.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I did. I really did. Thank God, I'd had a lot of witnesses to all
                    aspects of it. There were a lot of people involved, including Walt Stoessel, who
                    I think is an extremely honorable man. When I said to Alexander Haig that Walt
                    knew that I'd been in constant touch, he said, “Well, I've lost confidence in
                    Walt Stoessel, too, out of this whole affair”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He sounds like a little boy, doesn't he? Stamping his
                        foot.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I am told that Alexander Haig said to a friend of mine, who is a
                    good witness—he'd never met me; he had been appointed secretary of state and I
                    had already been appointed U.N. perm rep—and he said to him, “I don't know how
                    anybody expects that I will work with that bitch.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, talk about bad judgment! You don't say things like
                        that. Now, what about Argentina and the Falkland Islands? Did that happen
                        because they thought we would back them against the British? What do you
                        think is the background of that Argentinian episode?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I don't know what they thought. We'll never know what they thought
                    for sure. The fact is, of course, that it never occurred to anybody in the whole
                    US Government or the British Government that the Argentinians would dream of
                    doing such a thing. When I went to Argentina, I went with a big brief, and I was
                    supposed to tell them, and I did tell them, how we would never understand if
                    they used force to settle the Beagle Channel dispute. Roger Fontaine and I had
                    lunch with the Argentine ambassador, visiting somebody not long before the
                    Falklands issue. They had made some sort of move on the Beagle Channel—and we
                    made a big point to communicate the fact that our government would never
                    understand if they used force on the Beagle Channel.</p>
                <p>Nobody ever mentioned the Falkland Islands, because in the extremes of our minds
                    it never occurred to anybody that they would do such a thing. By the way, Peter
                    Carrington [Lord Carrington, British foreign secretary] says the same thing
                    about himself and the British. And the fact is that it was so inconceivable to
                    us, that we didn't even hear what later we clearly recognized, in hindsight, had
                    been sort of clues. We missed them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. You missed the clues.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: We missed the clues because it seemed so inconceivable. Who knows
                    what the Argentinians thought? They had no reason to believe that the United
                    States would in any way condone such an action. No reason at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, not against the British.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I can't conceive of why they would imagine that we would take a less
                    serious attitude toward the Falklands than toward the Beagle Channel, which we
                    talked to them a lot about. Unless they thought that our omission was
                    significant, which is an interesting question.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Or the fact that you didn't pick up on the clues,
                        which you didn't recognize as clues.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: That's right. But it came, you know, as a total shock. It was a
                    shock to Tom Enders [Thomas Enders, assistant secretary, Bureau of
                    Inter-American Affairs] and it was a shock to me. It was a shock to Peter
                    Carrington; it was a shock to everybody. The disagreement between Haig and me
                    was actually not even really about the Falklands.</p>
                <p>By that time, Alexander Haig really didn't like me at all, and I don't even know
                    why, frankly. I don't know why he disliked me as much as he did. Except that a
                    friend said that he had been powerfully prejudiced against me before he'd even
                    met me. There was a kind of disagreement between us, but, no more disagreement
                    than there was between Cap Weinberger [Caspar Weinberger, secretary of defense]
                    and I, who have been fast, good colleagues.</p>
                <p>My position on the Falklands was that we ought to remain neutral. I very strongly
                    supported Haig's mediation efforts. I carefully avoided any contact with the
                    Argentinians of an informal sort from the time of the beginning of those
                    mediation efforts until the end of them, and I never had any contact at all,
                    except sort of the minimal necessary to do with the Security Council business at
                    the U.N. And I had lots of people with me. I had learned a few basic
                    self-protective practices by that time. That did not prevent Haig from spreading
                    some sort of rumor that I was somehow sabotaging his negotiations. He says in
                    his book that he heard this from the British. That's a very odd thing. But then,
                    who knows?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And who knows whom he means by “the British”? Well,
                        obviously, he was trying to get you out. And you outlasted him by a good
                        long time, didn't you? Which is a delightful thing for women.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: No, there was a steady stream of unpleasant leaks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Little picks at you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Well, and some very harsh ones.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I know, the newspapers, especially, had a lot of fun
                        with that. Would you say that your personal relationship with Ronald Reagan
                        could be compared to the one Clare Boothe Luce [Clare Boothe Luce was U.S.
                        ambassador to Italy at the time of the settlement of the Trieste issue in
                        1954] had with Eisenhower, when she was able to go to him at the time she
                        was trying to settle the Trieste matter, and bring things to his attention
                        so that he could then sort of push things in motion? Did you have that much
                        access?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I had access to the president when I wanted.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did? Whenever you wanted?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Yes, I mean, if I wanted to see the president, I could call up and
                    get an appointment with the president. If I wanted a half an hour, one-on-one, I
                    could get half an hour one-on-one. I could call and say, “I'd like to see the
                    president; I'm going to need half an hour, and I would like to see him
                    one-on-one.” I could do that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't think people ever forgave Haig for what he did
                        previously, when he said, “I am in charge,” but he wasn't in charge.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: That's right. But that was his fantasy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He didn't know the order of succession.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: What he did was share with the whole public his fantasy, his private
                    fantasy. But he acted like that all the time, and it got on the president's
                    nerves. There's no doubt about it. And that's what brought his downfall; it
                    wasn't anybody else. He brought his downfall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Your relationship with the representatives from the
                        major countries—Japan, NATO, ANZUS and so forth, you had close
                        relationships?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Well, the Security Council was a very important center of our
                    life—that's my life. My relationships with the Security Council were
                    particularly close—the Security Council ambassadors. I worked most closely of
                    all with the British and the French throughout my time there, but I also had
                    good relations—reasonably good relations actually—even with the Chinese. And
                    eventually, I developed a reasonably cordial relationship with the Soviet
                    ambassador; not a close one, but a cordial one. He had a luncheon in my honor
                    when I left, for example; invited all the NATO and the ANZUS ambassadors, which
                    was nice. Nobody had done that for a U.S. ambassador in many years—in living
                    memory—at the U.N. I went to their national day reception, by the way. That's
                    the kind of exception I made, after we had permission to do it. In the
                    beginning, we were banned, of course, because of Afghanistan. I'm trying to
                    think who else I was particularly close to. Oh, several of the Latins; the
                    Central Americans, the Costa Rican ambassador, for example; the Honduran, the El
                    Salvadoran, the Ecuadoran ambassador was kind of a good man. One of the
                    Colombian ambassadors I was very close to. Some of the Asians we worked very
                    closely with, and I came to be on really quite personal terms with the Thai and
                    the Singaporean and the Malaysian. You know, those kinds of people. I was never
                    particularly close to the Japanese. I don't mean that I had a strained relation,
                    but I just wasn't particularly close. Bill Sherman was, however. That's very
                    important that you know this, very important that Bill was. Actually, I was very
                    close to the Dutch and the Belgians. Of all the other NATO ambassadors, besides
                    the British and the French, I was probably closest to the Dutch and the
                    Belgians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I recently met a gentleman from Mauritania, Amadou Ould
                        Abdallah [Mauritanian permanent representative to the UN].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Oh, yes, of course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And he just thinks you are absolutely marvelous.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Yes, yes, yes. He's a good man.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He thought you were terrific.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Well, I had some friends among the Africans, too. I've helped
                    promote some foreign ministers in Africa today, so to speak. They were permanent
                    representatives whom we developed particularly good relations with and helped
                    them in Washington, and helped them win promotions at home, as a matter of fact.
                    The current Secretary General of the OAU and former Foreign Minister of Niger,
                    Amarou, was a very good friend of mine. The Senegalese, Foreign Minister Niasse,
                    and Sarr�, who's their perm rep in New York, is a very good friend of mine. The
                    Togolese—by the way, these were also Security Council members. The Zairian
                    Security Council member became a good friend of mine. I was able to work with
                    the francophone Africans especially because of being comfortable in French.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which they take as a great compliment, don't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Yes, right, and since most of them are not comfortable in English,
                    this is very important. French is more important, by far, for dealing with the
                    francophone Africans than to dealing with French and the Belgians, most of whom
                    speak English. What time is it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's almost five o'clock.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Oh, okay. Ask one more question.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Last question: How do you regard the U.N. now that you
                        have been there? How do you regard its effectiveness in the world, and its
                        usefulness?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: It's very ineffective.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Necessity for it, perhaps, is the word I wanted to
                        use.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: It's ineffective in relationship to its central responsibility,
                    which is peaceful resolution of conflict, and peace-keeping and peace-making.
                    Some of the independent agencies of the U.N. are quite effective—UNC, HCR,
                    UNICEF, WHO—some of those agencies, I think, do very good work. But generally
                    speaking, the U.N. is quite ineffective. It is a seriously bloated, overblown,
                    international bureaucracy with a lot of the worst aspects of many national
                    bureaucracies combined. The budget is basically out of control and so is
                    personnel.</p>
                <p>There are a lot of nice people there, whom I enjoyed knowing and working with,
                    and whom I really not only respect, but like. I think the U.N. is basically
                    negative in its effects on the United States and our role in the world. I think
                    its impact on us, our values, our friends, is largely negative. [This was during
                    the cold war. - J.K.]</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>We can, with maximum energy and intelligence and effort, control those negative
                    effects and minimize them. But it's a colossal effort just to keep major damage
                    from being done to us. Nonetheless, I don't advocate U.S. withdrawal from the
                    U.N., because I think it's too important to many small, poor, third-world
                    countries. I don't think it's objectively important to them, but it's
                    subjectively. They think it's important. It's important because they think it's
                    important, you know?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sure.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: It's important for them to have some kind of place they can meet
                    each other and meet representatives of the major countries and get some kind of
                    hearing for their concerns, and have some kind of feeling that they have open
                    channels.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A place to blow off steam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I strenuously object to the notion that the U.N. is a place to let
                    off steam. I call that the “Turkish bath” conception of the United Nations, and
                    I don't think we ought to tolerate becoming the target of cathartic exercises by
                    third world countries. And I don't think that's necessary to their purposes,
                    either. I think what's most important to the third-world countries is that there
                    be a place—literally an arena—in which they can meet people. A lot of arenas,
                    you know, in which different kinds of problems are discussed and in which they
                    can speak. It's not necessarily blowing off steam, but get a hearing—just get a
                    hearing. Oh, I think it would be a terrible shock to the sensibilities of almost
                    everybody if we were to withdraw from the U.N., so I don't think we should, but,
                    on the other hand, I don't think we should underestimate the damage that's done
                    to our values, interests, and principles, and friends in the U.N., and that we
                    need, therefore, to be very energetic and realistic about defending ourselves,
                    and helping that body focus on more constructive enterprises.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Well, you certainly did it by writing them letters
                        and saying, “Why did you vote this way?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Just once.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just the once?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Just once.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Has it not been done again?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: I don't think so. I did that in my first year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again, that's the accountability idea.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: Well, that's right. It's also the direct contact. I did some
                    equivalents to writing letters. I did, for example, mention by name countries
                    who spoke against us in the Nicaraguan debate, whom we had good reason to expect
                    better behavior from. So I expressed explicitly our disappointment at the
                    comments of Pakistan, Senegal, Sri Lanka, or China.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And where did you do this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIRKPATRICK: In the U.N. Security Council on the record. I only did it once
                    because I never had to do it again. Because not one of the countries that I
                    mentioned ever again entered a complaint against the United States with that
                    kind of language. It was very shocking. I mean, there were real shock
                    tactics.</p>
                <p>I didn't do it harshly. I just expressed our disappointment and surprise that
                    Pakistan would say something like this about the United States in this context,
                    or that China would engage in this kind of hyperbole, or make this kind of
                    mistake. I took about five countries with whom we were closely associated. I
                    didn't make a big point of them. I did it in one small piece of the speech. But
                    it produced a lot of shock, and they didn't do it again.</p>
                <p>Now, I mean, that's not too destructive a way of communicating that we really
                    care and that there will be consequences. That we really do hold people
                    responsible for what they say about us in official places on the record. I'm not
                    sorry I did that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I shouldn't think so. Well, thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
