<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000512">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Roger Hilsman </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Service, Lyndon Baines Johnson
                    Library</p>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>ROGER HILSMAN</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Paige E. Mulhollan</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 15, 1969</p>
                <p>Q: Let's begin by identifying you, Sir. You're Roger Hilsman, and your last
                    official position with the government was as assistant secretary of state for
                    Far Eastern Affairs which you held until of 1964. Is that correct?</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: No, March 15th. I actually resigned earlier than that, but the President
                    asked me to stay till March 15th while he got a replacement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you had been director of the INR [Intelligence and
                        Research]from the beginning of the Kennedy Administration until 1963?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you served about a year in the Far East post.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Just a little over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you know Mr. Johnson at all prior to the time you came
                        intthe Kennedy Administration? Had you ever had any contact?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: I had had some indirect contact with him when he was on Capitol Hill. I
                    was chief of the Foreign Affairs Division of the Legislative Reference Service,
                    and then I was deputy director of the Service. And though I didn't know him
                    personally, I had done some things with some of his staff.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>It was funny about this, because William S. White, you know, Bill White, was a
                    great friend of the President's. And he's a great friend of mine. Bill White
                    always thought we two would really hit it off. White arranged a real small
                    dinner party early in the Kennedy Administration. It was Bill and his wife, my
                    wife and myself, Jim Rowe and Lady Bird and the Vice President. The whole
                    purpose of this dinner was to get his two good friends together. We talked about
                    Texas and not much else except Texas. You see, my grandfather, my family comes
                    from Texas - both sides.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That should have been a plus.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, except I have no accent. My father was an armofficer, and although
                    I was born in Texas, we lived all over the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like Eisenhower's birthplace was Texas.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, that's right. And the President didn't know my grandfather. My
                    grandfather had been chief justice of the Criminal Court of Appeals in Texas.
                    His portrait hangs in the Capitol at Austin. In fact, I have two relatives whose
                    portraits hang in the Capitol.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But Johnson didn't know him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Didn't know him. And I was amazed at that. Didn't know him and didn't
                    know of him. Of course, I should have phrased that more carefully: didn't know
                    of him because, after all, he died in 1923. I would have thought that he would
                    have known of him anyway, but he didn't. But it's funny about that evening,
                    because my memory of it is that it was inconsequential. We never talked about
                    anything substantive or anything else. But after I resigned and was a critic,
                    friends in the press tell me that Johnson tells a story about that evening that
                    I just don't remember anything remotely like. I know it didn't happen the way he
                    told it. Although he does these things, you know. That is, he sees it
                    differently. Let me tell you the way it came back to me was that at the dinner
                    we got to talking about Vietnam or the military or something like this. And we
                    disagreed. I was supposed to have said, “Mr. Vice President, you're full of
                    shit,” or something to this effect.</p>
                <p>Well, A., as a West Pointer Army officer, I couldn't do anything like that. I'm
                    just incapable of it. But knowing Mr. Johnson, I could well visualize, with his
                    personality, that if you have said, “I just don't agree; you're just wrong,”
                    that that would be the functional equivalent of saying, “You're full of
                    shit.”</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>I think that what must have happened - which also happens with him, as you know,
                    frequently - is that in meetings about Vietnam, there were disagreements and
                    that he transferred those in his mind. In other words, I don't think he was
                    deliberately manufacturing anything. But I think he was confusing it later,
                    much, much later, with NSC meetings or other meetings when he was vice president
                    and there were disagreements. You know, just transposing it into the other
                    scene. But that's when I first really [met him]; the first intimate
                    occasion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had he been to Vietnam? Was this after his Vietnam trip
                        that year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: It must have been, must have been.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So he was knowledgeable about it? I mean he had some
                        knowledgabout it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: But my point is I am absolutely certain we didn't discuss Vietnam that
                    night.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right. Did you talk to him about his trip at any time
                        subsequently?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: No, there are a couple of funny things about my early relationship with
                    the Vice President. They really are kind of misses. Because it is perfectly true
                    what White said, that there were things in both of our backgrounds that would
                    have made it logical for us to have hit it off. I mean, just things like I know
                    Texas. My father and Johnson are very similar personalities. Dad grew up not a
                    couple of hundred miles from where Johnson was born and grew up. And they're
                    very much the same. In fact, I'm often struck that Johnson is eleven years older
                    than I am, but he is really of my father's generation. He's that kind of a
                    Texan, you see. My only point thus being that I, unlike, say, some of the
                    Kennedy people, understood this personality. I had known very intimately my
                    father and people like this, and so, therefore, I could have adjusted. And I
                    admired him.</p>
                <p>But there were just a couple of just kind of misses. For example, I went out to
                    Vietnam, and after having talked with R. K. G. Thompson, came back with some
                    ideas that lumped under the strategic hamlet program thing which had some
                    promises of winning. Of course, one of the issues was that I was always
                    convinced after that trip - I had been a guerrilla leader in World War II and
                    taking these two experiences, I became convinced that it could be won, but not
                    by conventional military means. It had to be done by adopting tactics of the
                    guerrilla by arming the villagers, the strategic hamlet type program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your book is a very clear enunciation of that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, on that. Well, one of the other things that happened that was kind
                    of funny was that when I got back, I talked to the President at great length,
                    and the President-</p>
                <p>Q: Wait a minute, you talked to Mr. Kennedy now?</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Kennedy, yes. Talked to Kennedy at great length about this with Max
                    Taylor. Kennedy said, “I want you to go around and see Bobby and several other
                    people and give them this briefing.”</p>
                <p>And he named the Vice President. So I set up an appointment to give him a full
                    briefing on this whole new concept. And it was just one of those damned things.
                    I arrived at his office, and there was some sort of political crisis going on in
                    Texas. He was all tensed up; the telephone would ring every two minutes. He'd
                    come over and sit down and say, “Okay. Go ahead.” Then two minutes later he'd
                    jump up and call a secretary and say something like that and then come and say,
                    “Now, what were you saying?” And then the telephone would ring.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've had some interviews like that on this project.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: It was just a total flop, you know. I think that right there, if it had
                    worked out so that I could have had an hour with him, he would have understood
                    better the nature of the problem [Vietnam] when he did become president. Well,
                    there were a series of episodes like this where it just sailed by.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>Then, when I was director of INR, I got to thinking about him and tried to
                    arrange to give him an intelligence briefing on a regular basis. Somehow this
                    news was never picked up. Then on several NSC meetings, he used to sit next to
                    me, and we would whisper back and forth about what was going on. But then, after
                    I got to be assistant secretary, it really . . you know, the struggle over the
                    whole Buddhist crisis with the military and NSC. Everybody was split. The CIA
                    split down the middle about how to handle the Buddhist crisis. And the military
                    wanted to go on with Diem and, of course, the political situation. I think the
                    then-Vice President Johnson, having met Diem and liked him, and the famous quote
                    about the Churchill of Asia. Of course, that was true about a lot of us. I knew
                    Diem and liked him, too. But being, by this time, assistant secretary and being
                    very intimately concerned with the political side of the question, why, I, went
                    along with [W. Averell] Harriman and [Dean] Rusk and the others in the State
                    Department became increasingly convinced that we couldn't sit still. We had to
                    say something, had to do something. And I think that there were a couple of NSC
                    meetings where Johnson's sympathies were with the military and with Diem. I
                    think that probably was the period in which he disagreed with what I was saying.
                    I don't recall any episode where he became an advocate and I disagreed with him.
                    But I can recall lots of meetings where he sat silently as McNamara and I
                    fought, or the JCS and I fought, and so on and so forth. And I had the feeling
                    that his sympathies lay with the other side. But I really think that there is an
                    enormous tragedy here that somehow - I'm speaking from hindsight now and I'm
                    speaking on the assumption that it turns out that those of us who thought
                    bombing would not work, that those of us who thought that American troops would
                    merely drive - you know no matter how many Viet Cong you killed that the use of
                    troops foreign to Vietnam would drive the peasants into the arms of the
                    communists. I'm assuming that that now turns out to have been correct. And my
                    feeling was that the time that Mr. Johnson could have been influenced was no
                    later than 1962.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In other words, long before he became President.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A full year before.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: My impression is that when he became President his mind was made up, and
                    that people like Harriman and myself were just simply going to be out of it:
                    Harriman put on a shelf, you know, Harriman couldn't be fired, you couldn't fire
                    Harriman, but put on a shelf, taken out of it. Of course, Harriman was an old
                    man and had the patience and also had the wisdom to know that he would have to
                    be the one to be sent to the negotiations when they came. He had the patience to
                    wait. And because of the high esteem in which he was held by the Soviets, [he]
                    knew that he gotten to be land would be] indispensable when the negotiations
                    came and that LBJ would have to come to him.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>But I have the impression that when Johnson became president, his mind had been
                    made up that the people he was going to listen to were the guys with the
                    military hard line and that he was not going to listen to any others. I don't
                    say that he had determined on escalating. I don't think he did. I think that
                    that first year he wished very much that there would be a victory on the same
                    terms as JFK's policy. But I do think that he had made up his mind not to listen
                    to the guys who argued that it was a political problem and not a military
                    problem and that if there was a crisis that he would listen to the military
                    advice.</p>
                <p>Q: How much was he in on the Kennedy Administration consideration of the problem?
                    You mentioned his being in the meetings, but was it any more than that or was he
                    in on the really important meetings even?</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: I don't know. I'm sure that you could find this out. But mimpression was
                    that he had a standing invitation to all NSC meetings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, there were not always the important ones, I
                        suppose?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, I think they were pretty important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, important in this sense: that when you've got a divided government,
                    when the military and the CIA and the State Department are divided about these
                    matters, then any president has got to go through a certain amount of motions of
                    maintaining some unity. Because, you know, if somebody resigns in a public blast
                    that these decisions were made without proper consultation, why, that's hard on
                    any president. So my feeling is that maybe Bobby and Jack had some private
                    conversations that were very crucial. But nevertheless, both in the Cuban
                    Missile Crisis and in the whole Vietnam business, my impression was that the
                    importance of keeping the government together was so great that those NSC
                    meeting were very important.</p>
                <p>Now, I think that the Vice President didn't come to all of them. And I don't know
                    about the invitation; my impression was he had a standing invitation. Again, you
                    know, maybe we should have pushed hard, maybe I should have pushed harder when I
                    was director of Intelligence to give him a regular briefing. I tried several
                    times, but he didn't pick it up. Of course, the Vice President has always got
                    these problems, you know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, that's inherent in the office, I suppose.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: Inherent in the office, that's right.</p>
                <p>Q: You go into this in some extent in the book. I take it that what you say is
                    that at the time Johnson became President, the die had not been cast. In other
                    words, he could have - it would have been possible to have adopted the course of
                    action that you were recommending at that time. It was not already set. Is that
                    a fair understanding of it?</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, now look, nobody can prove anything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Because these are matters of judgement. I'll tell you what I thought at
                    the time. That is, I remember, after the Diem coup, John McCone and I having a
                    talk about this. And I remember saying that all that this had done was give us a
                    second chance and that we now had to press very hard. I wrote a memo, as I
                    described in the book, following the Diem coup, urging that certain steps be
                    done. Now, I don't know, and nobody knows, whether it was too late, whether the
                    strategic hamlet program would have worked if it had been pursued energetically.
                    Nobody knows. I clung to that hope, and I clung to that hope for a long time, as
                    my public statements will reveal.</p>
                <p>Even as late as 1966, I probably still thought there was a chance. And
                    increasingly, I became more and more pessimistic and visited Vietnam in late
                    summer of 1967, and came back. This was the period where the optimism was very
                    high before the Tet Offensive, but I have been around the race course many
                    times. I came back admitting that there had been a lot of military progress, but
                    even more deeply pessimistic about whether this was going to be relevant. By
                    that time I began to have real doubts - in the fall of 1967 - whether it was too
                    late for anything. Now let me say one other thing though. In late 1964, early
                    1965, came the crisis of morale. Now, I tell you quite frankly at the time and
                    now, I have doubts about whether it was really a crisis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You have doubts about the degree of deterioration in
                        SoutVietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: That's right. In order words, I think that in late 1964, 1965 - I'm not
                    nailing my colors to the mast on it, I only say that I have real doubts as to
                    whether it wasn't a temporary thing. I don't think necessarily, I really don't
                    in my heart believe that a collapse would have followed. I think there was still
                    time for an energetic strategic hamlet program in 1965. But let us assume that I
                    am wrong on that. Let us assume that there was a crisis. My feeling is that it's
                    very difficult to change an ongoing policy in the absence of some climax, some
                    crisis.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>What I mean by that is that if you say, “Let's go to Paris. Let's go to Geneva
                    and negotiate Vietnam.” Bob Kennedy said this once, in November before the Diem
                    coup. And somebody said, “Well, let's play it out along this line a little while
                    longer. We've got time.” It isn't that. So my point is-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fifteen minutes more.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You have the “fifteen-minutes-more” theory.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes. Well, that's right. But the point here is that I define a crisis
                    for these purposes as when both the hawks and the doves agree that doing what
                    you're doing isn't going to work and that you must go big. Now in that kind of
                    circumstance, then a president finally is free, you see; he's finally free to
                    make a bold change. Now whether or not there really was a collapse of morale in
                    South Vietnam in late 1964 and early 1965, all agreed that there was. All the
                    Washington people did, both the hawks and the doves. Now at that point, Mr.
                    Johnson could have gone to Geneva as easily as he escalated the war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's the freedom that you were talking about.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: That's the freedom and he was perfectly free to negotiate. My feeling
                    was that there was his great mistake, because I think, quite frankly, that we'd
                    have gotten maybe more out of those negotiations of 1965 than we'll get out of
                    these. And the reason is because the North Vietnamese had never experienced the
                    bombing, never experienced five hundred thousand Americans, and they would have
                    been fearful of it. They would have been under the threat. The threat is always
                    worse than the actuality. They might have been more willing to negotiate under
                    those circumstances than they are now. Now they've had the bombing, and they've
                    survived it. Now they have had five hundred thousand Americans, and they've
                    taken their measure, and they know they can cope. That means I think we would
                    have been better off negotiating.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was anybody advising him to get out in 1964? HILSMAN: I
                        left in March, 1964, so I don't know about that period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Q: But even during the period before you left, was there any counsel at all?
                    Later on all of his critics at least would say we should have withdrawn. Was
                    anybody ever saying that inside?</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: No, no. I don't think so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that's important too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: That's very important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That there wasn't any advice of this given.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes. When I put in my memo when I left - my sort of political testament
                    - the thesis of this memo was: Don't bomb the North; it won't work; it will be
                    interpreted as an act of desperation, and it will force you into premature
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, you mentioned that. Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: That's March, 1964, because Walt Rostow and the others were already
                    putting pressure on the President to bomb the North. Now, my point about that
                    was that it would be interpreted as an act of desperation, an admission that
                    everything failed in the South, and that it would not work. But it would start
                    the neutralist hares running both among our allies and at home.</p>
                <p>So I was advising, at that time...now that was in the absence of crisis.</p>
                <p>Q: Right.</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: I don't know what advice he was getting in late 1964 or early 1965. My
                    advice, if I had been there, would have been to ride it, you know, to again try
                    the strategic hamlet program. But I certainly would have advised against bombing
                    the North. Now, if riding it, and it turned out there was a real crisis, a real
                    collapse in morale, why, then I would have thought that you had to negotiate.
                    Because, you see, I always thought that you never really had the option of
                    introducing American troops, that even if the American troops won the battle,
                    you'd simply just have to occupy the country for the rest of time. The minute
                    you turned your back, it would go down the drain because of the use of American
                    troops. My analogy always was that if the President of the United States at the
                    time of the Watts riots had called on Prime Minister Saito to send five hundred
                    thousand Japanese over here, we'd have all been on the barricades.</p>
                <p>Q: Right, right. In your book, one of the time periods in which you don't go into
                    a great deal of detail is the period from Mr. Johnson taking over until your
                    departure. And yet, you say you felt sure during that time his basic decision
                    had been made and so on. Were there specific-?</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: Oh, no. I didn't mean and didn't really say, I don'believe, that his
                    basic decision had been made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's probably unfair the way I put it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, that implies that he had already decided to bomb thNorth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: NO, no.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: I don't think he had. I don't think he decided to bomb the North until
                    late 1964 or early 1965. Really, what I was driving towards is: Were there any
                    events during that period that, in the light of the later events, seem to you to
                    have been critical? In other words, were there decisions made then in that sixty
                    day period or thereabouts that turned out subsequently to have been
                    important?</p>
                <p>Well, not in a policy sense. There were several things that happened that made me
                    convinced that my usefulness was at an end and that Johnson's mind had been made
                    up. By that, I meant that he had made up his mind that he wasn't going to accept
                    or negotiate anything less than a victory and that he would do whatever he
                    could. How, I tried to clear up this confusion in the paper edition of the
                    book.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why, I haven't even seen the paper edition. I read the
                        othegreat big book twice.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: In the paper edition, I tried to clear this up. Now the reason it became
                    confused was not, I contend, what I said, but what the New Left said. You see,
                    the New Left review the book and use it, I might say, with complete lack of
                    scholarship, misquoting me, quoting me out of context. Well, you know how they
                    do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: That John McDermott testimony.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's the most famous one, I guess, in the reviews.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, that review took quotes from me and I. F. Stone and mixed them all
                    up. And you couldn't tell who was I. F. Stone and who was me.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was quite a juxtaposition, you and I. F. Stone.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, I agree. But anyway, I tried to clear this up in a footnote to the
                    paperback edition. I wanted to rewrite the chapter, but the production things
                    that have to be done for photographs - that was all I could do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Now, let me read this to you. “After the publication of the first
                    edition of this book, it was pointed out to me that the above passage could be
                    misinterpreted to mean that President Johnson had made the decision to escalate
                    the war before the 1964 election campaign, when he so effectively countered
                    Senator Goldwater's advocacy involving the North with the statement that we did
                    not want our American boys to do the fighting for Asian boys. I do not know what
                    occurred after my departure in March, 1964.” And I suggest then that James
                    Thomson's article might be helpful to those readers that want to know.</p>
                <p>“I do know that no such decision had been made by the time that I departed. I
                    also believe that President Johnson sincerely, even desperately, wanted to make
                    the existing policy work. My misgivings were not based on knowledge of any
                    specific decision, but were of a different order. First and probably foremost in
                    my mind was the obvious fact that the advocates of a 'political approach' in
                    whom the President had reposed confidence, meaning Kennedy, did not enjoy the
                    confidence of President Johnson. That is, that he did not repose the same
                    confidence in Harriman, Forrestal, and myself.” And [George] Ball, I might say.
                    “While those who advocated a more 'military' approach, did. Second, there were a
                    number of things, not decisive in themselves, but suggestive. Suggestive, I
                    interpolate, of my growing conviction that he had made up his mind to accept
                    nothing less than a victory.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: No matter what the cost, you see. “Not decisive in themselves, but
                    suggestive.” His oft repeated remark that this is the only war we've got. That
                    to me was terribly significant. Whereas Kennedy kept saying, “It isn't a war;
                    it's a political struggle with military aspects,” you see. But it had become a
                    war, right? It had become a war; “it's the only war we've got.”</p>
                <p>“His appointment of a committee to prepare a list of possible targets in case the
                    decision to bomb the North became necessary.” Now that to me was overwhelming,
                    you see. Was this pressure from the military to go ahead and make this
                    contingency plan that resulted in that?</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>No, it actually went the other way around. Shortly after Kennedy was killed, guys
                    like Rostow started pushing for bombing the North, et cetera. And McNamara was
                    again all gung-ho. McNamara's whole history in this thing was, anytime there's
                    any crisis, starting off with a military type answer, buying whatever the JCS
                    were recommending - coming in and very aggressive and dynamic in an NSC meeting
                    and steamrollering opposition. The other side, Harriman and myself, et cetera,
                    arguing against it. The compromise always was that McNamara would go out to
                    Vietnam, which, of course, I hated too because it kept adding to the American
                    prestige. But then what happened is: Almost every time McNamara would go out
                    gung-ho and come back agreeing with us over and over and over again. I used to
                    say that the guy is one of the brightest guys I ever met, but he's not a wise
                    man. His instincts were all wrong, but his intelligence eventually conquered his
                    instincts. But anyway, that's what happened in this case. They went out
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the Christmas 1963 visit?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: That's right. And the issue here was “Boy, we've got to do something
                    about those infiltration routes; we've got go invade Laos, or bomb Laos, or bomb
                    the North. And McNamara goes out and comes back and says, “I do not recommend
                    bombing it at this time. But I do recommend getting ready for it.” He's setting
                    up a committee to look over the targets. Well, there was no real battle, in the
                    sense that you can't really fight-Q: A contingency planning.</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: A contingency planning, right. So there was not a battle. Then he set
                    this up, and the only concession to our side of the thing was they made chairman
                    of the committee, Bill Sullivan, who was, of course, Harriman's prot�g�e and a
                    guy in whom we had confidence and in whom McNamara had confidence. He was a
                    bridge type, that is, he was acceptable to both sides. That was the only
                    concession to us, but it seemed to me that this was clear. Was that all that
                    that committee was supposed to do originally? To locate targets?</p>
                <p>Originally. Then it was later transformed into a Vietnam task force.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was just before you left?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, that's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the background of deciding to do that? Was it
                        importanto the problem or something specific?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, I interpreted it as meaning one more move in disarming the
                    political people, the guys who were advocating the political approach. In other
                    words, one more move in getting us, disarming us, and muting us, spiking our
                    guns. So I interpreted it as a political move to ease us out of positions of
                    influence.</p>
                <p>Q: That's an important question. George Ball, for example in his book talks about
                    the necessity for continuing the policy pretty much as we are, because of, among
                    other things, the fact that the military people are so in favor of doing so. Can
                    the State Department not stand against that type of pressure - the
                    intensification of the pressure to take a military action?</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, it depends on how the State Department does it. Now, as I think
                    comes out in my book, I felt that, well, let's put it this way: So long as
                    Kennedy lived, we were okay. Except that we ended up making more concessions,
                    i.e. McNamara's continuously visiting Vietnam, which was bad. It elevated the
                    problem; it increased the American commitment publicly and all this. I talked
                    around this in the book, but, in fact on one of those visits of McNamara's, it
                    was decided that he would go, and we had opposed it. I was sufficiently upset
                    that I followed Kennedy into the Oval Office and protested again. With some
                    impatience, as it he were dealing with some unruly child, which he was at the
                    moment, he said, “Look, Roger. I know that. I know that it's costly and bad to
                    send McNamara out there. But the only way that we can keep the JCS on board is
                    to keep McNamara on board, and the only way we can keep McNamara on board is to
                    let him go see for himself. Now that's the price we have to pay.” Now, I think
                    that Kennedy had to make more concessions than were wise to the military because
                    Rusk did not stand up as much as he should have - as I think he should have.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The key, then, becomes the Secretary of State.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: That's right. In other words, I think that as I say in the book I can't
                    blame McNamara for pushing his department's view as vigorously as possible. But
                    I certainly can blame Rusk for not pushing his view, or our view. And always
                    over and over again, it ends up with Harriman and Hilsman arguing against
                    McNamara and the JCS and McCone. And that's not quite an equal contest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, it doesn't sound like it. (Laughter)</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: It would have been much better if it would have been Rusk, Harriman,
                    Forrestal, and me versus McNamara and Joint Chiefs, et cetera. But so long as
                    Kennedy is alive, you see, then we have Bob Kennedy on our side and we have the
                    President on our side.Now, once Kennedy's dead, with Johnson actually being more
                    sympathetic to the military side, then we are finished. But I think Johnson's
                    mistake again - of course, this goes to his personality - is that he has a hard
                    time having people around who will disagree. He doesn't accept this and, I tell
                    you, I think it's a mistake. I think that the kind of personality like
                    Roosevelt's that not only permits, but it delights in opposition all around
                    him-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Builds the tensions in, even.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, that is a better way for a president. At least you're less likely
                    to make huge mistakes that way. But Johnson has a tendency to build in around
                    him sycophants. He does. Now George Ball attempted to play the role [of
                    dissident], but as James Thomas points out, he ends up being the tame dove.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right, the house dove.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: The house dove, and then it isn't really serioudisagreement, it's-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Pro forma.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Pro forma disagreement. Well, to answer your question, I really think
                    that there's always these oppositions. There are always hawks and doves or
                    'hards' and 'softs;' there's always this around you as President. Let's put it
                    this way, Kennedy by and large, on Vietnam, followed the political line and
                    maneuvered around the hard liners, compromised, made concessions, et cetera. Or
                    in, say, Laos, which is an even better example, he followed the softer line and
                    maneuvered around the other ones. Johnson, on Vietnam, followed the hard line
                    and maneuvered around the 'softs'.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a very well put comparison.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Now, the point is if his Vietnam policy had worked he would have come
                    home free, but in fact it turned out that the doves were just as dangerous to
                    Johnson as the hawks were on Laos to Kennedy. In the end, the doves brought
                    Johnson down.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: So the point I'm trying to make is only that both kinds of pressures
                    exist. Now, if you can end the problem and get - let's say Kennedy's great
                    fortune was that, by and large, the Laos agreement, though no raging success,
                    was no failure either. There Souvanna Phouma sits, still prime minister of Laos;
                    it did not go down the drain overnight, or anything like that. And that killed
                    the hard line opposition. They occasionally squeak about it a little bit, but it
                    isn't in the headlines, you see. So it worked, by and large or, at least, it
                    wasn't a success, but it wasn't a failure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't a failure.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: And that silences the opposition. In poor Mr. Johnson's case, it didn't
                    work. It got worse, and worse, and worse. And more and more people moved over in
                    opposition.</p>
                <p>Q: Right, do you answer the other New Left criticisms in the paperback versions
                    of your book? I'm handicapped not having read that edition. The general
                    criticism they make - I think all of them, Howard Zinn and McDermott, and the
                    whole bunch that have reviewed it - was that really the political side that you
                    describe as being a part of it, you and Harriman and Forrestal and the rest, is
                    really just a kind of a sophisticated militarism that leads to the same place.
                    What do they call it, crisis managers?</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, yes, that stuff. Well, basically, I don't attempt to [answer this
                    criticism]. I have a saying which is: Never wrestle with a pig; you both get
                    dirty, and the pig likes it. So I don't ever attempt to deal with these people.
                    They're impossible. Basically that review was not a review of the book. The
                    first third of that McDermott review was an attack on Lyndon Johnson which,
                    using selected quotes from my book, mixing them up with other quotes and also
                    the selected quotes were taken out of context, making me appear to say something
                    I did not say; i.e., they were trying to charge that my book showed that Johnson
                    had decided to bomb the North before the 1964 election. And my book did not say
                    that; quite the opposite.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: So that was just straight-out lying and propagandizing. The latter
                    two-thirds of the review was an attack on the American social system, but not a
                    review of my book - just using me as an example. And basically it was the same
                    line that Bolsheviks take towards the Social Democrats. If you recall, they
                    said, “Hilsman is a crisis manager and one of the best of his breed.” Then it
                    went on to say that “you liberals think that Hilsman is a good guy because he
                    fought the generals on Vietnam and all of this stuff. But in fact, he's worse
                    than [General] Curt LeMay. The reason that he is worse than Curt LeMay is that
                    if Hilsman and people like him refused to participate in the American
                    government, it would collapse. Since they participate, they make it work, and
                    therefore they make Curt LeMay possible. Therefore, they are worse than Curt
                    LeMay.” You see, it's the Bolshevik reasoning, and it's not worthy of a
                    reply.</p>
                <p>Q: The only other arm of their criticism is, I think, criticism which is always a
                    problem when someone leaves public life. Why, if you disagreed with what was
                    going on, didn't you do something that might have contributed to changing it, or
                    make a public statement?</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, I probably should have answered that one, because, in fact, I'm
                    clean on this. I left office on March 15th and within two weeks I gave a speech.
                    The trouble is that if they had bothered to research it, it would go against
                    their case. I gave a speech in which I warned against the temptation of
                    over-militarizing the war and over-Americanizing the war. Those were my two tag
                    lines that I gave the speech. But I put it in terms of the temptation. What I
                    was saying, of course - and it's perfectly clear in the speech - is that there
                    are people in government who want to bomb the North and want to send American
                    troops, i.e., over-militarize, i.e., over-Americanize. And I warned against this
                    and said it wouldn't work. Now, I gave that speech within two weeks after
                    leaving office. Now, it did not hit the front page of the New York Times. You
                    know, warning against a temptation of something that hasn't happened is not a
                    big headline, and I wasn't that big a public figure. So I think you will find on
                    about page twenty in the New York Times and maybe three or four inches, but it's
                    there. So that charge, in fact, was false.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is one that's worth answering, though, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: I think so, but it's too late now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, they wouldn't listen, now, anyway.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: They're not worth very much, I don't think.</p>
                <p>Q: The occasion of you leaving brought forward all kinds of different stories
                    about the causes and so on. How do you view it? Did you look upon it as being
                    pushed out, being told to leave?</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, I always regarded this as a kind of red herring, because it really
                    is a chicken-and-egg thing in the sense that technically I resigned, but if I
                    had delayed two or three weeks, Mr. Johnson would have moved me to some other
                    job. I don't think there's any question of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's no such thing as firing under a President, really,
                        osomebody at that level, is there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, not especially when - I mean, you could fire a guif, like Mr.
                    Fortas, he accepted a bribe or something.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, yes, right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: But when it's a disagreement over policy, no. I'll tell you the story as
                    I know it, and I don't know what was going on in the White House or anything
                    else. But in January, I was scheduled to visit Australia. This was six weeks
                    after the President was assassinated. We got on an airplane, and we rode to San
                    Francisco, and that's five hours. Then we spent the night with my parents; then
                    we rode to Honolulu; and that's four and a half hours. I think I went out and
                    spent a morning with CINCPAC. Then it was a Saturday and a Sunday, and we laid
                    on the beach in Waikiki. And then we got on an airplane and rode eight hours to
                    Fiji, or something like that. But to make a long story short as we circled
                    Sydney Airport, I said to my wife, “I must resign.” And she said, “I thought you
                    had been awfully quiet.” Well, I had been quiet and what I had been doing was
                    reviewing in my own mind all of these things, that is, the forming of the
                    bombing committee, the impossibility of little things. You know I think it would
                    have been wise for Johnson, even if he had made up his mind that our side was
                    wrong, at some stage to have called me over and closed the door, just the two of
                    us, and said, “Okay, Roger, I disagree with what you're saying, but I want to
                    give you a chance to make your case without the Secretary of Defense and the
                    Joint Chiefs looking over your shoulder. Now tell me what your case is.” But he
                    hadn't done that, you see. [There were] things like, “It's the only war we've
                    got,” all these little things that I mentioned in the book. I reviewed those,
                    and I came to a conclusion that within a very short time I would either be
                    totally discredited, that is, that there would be a fight, and it would be a
                    nasty thing, and everything I said thereafter would be sour grapes, or more
                    likely, that he would do to me what he did to [John A.] Gronouski or to Ed
                    Martin - that is, that all of a sudden I would be called up one day, and very
                    soon, and told, “Look, I want you to be Ambassador to the Philippines.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Which is the precedent for it, Chip [Charles E.] Bohlen,you know, in the
                    Eisenhower Administration was sent to the Philippines.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sure.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: In other words, not fired, but just shifted or what he dito Harriman,
                    which was to put him on the shelf.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, there were other people to whom that ultimately
                        happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Oh, sure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Other Kennedy people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Sure, that's right. Well, Harriman and . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ralph Dungan ended up as ambassador to Chile, I
                        guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Chile; Gronouski to Poland. Sure. In other words, that, I thought, was
                    what was going to happen. And then I thought very seriously about whether I
                    wanted to do this or not. I've always argued that I did not want to be a career
                    foreign service officer. I think it's a mistake for a Presidential appointee to
                    shift over that way. I think it's not fair to the Foreign Service and so on and
                    so forth. I had an academic career and, if I was going to get on with it, I
                    ought to get on with it. And finally, if I was right about the way things were
                    going to go, I wanted to be in the position to be an outside critic. So I came
                    back and went to Harriman and said, “I'm going to resign.” Harriman argued with
                    me, and argued. Finally he said, “Well, at least go and give the President a
                    chance to respond before you just do it.” And I said, “Averell, if I do that, I
                    will be fired before I can get the resignation typed out.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: “I would prefer to resign and not do it.” Well, Averell said,”Well, if
                    anybody tries to do that, they'll have to reckon with me, because I will take
                    the responsibility.” Well, in fact, I called Mac up and told him I wanted an
                    appointment, and it was perfectly clear to him what I wanted to talk about. I
                    went out and wrote my resignation out in longhand, and waited for Mac's call.
                    And sure enough this did set things in motion. Before I could see Mac, Ball
                    called me up and I went up to see Ball. Ball said, “We want you to go be
                    ambassador to the Philippines,” and I handed him my resignation at the same
                    time. At the same time. Then they did really put considerable pressure on me to
                    go to the Philippines as ambassador. And of course, this is where Johnson is
                    such a clever guy. You know, he really is one of the brightest men you'll ever
                    meet.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: As you probably know, his IQ is way up there. But, you see, I had grown
                    up in the Philippines. He knew that, too. And he knew that, too. He'd found that
                    out, and [it was] very much the Gronouski bit, you know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, only Gronouski had never been to Poland, I
                        think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, I know, but a guy of Polish descent to be aambassador to Poland is
                    a kind of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: But, you see, I had grown up in the Philippines. It's a number one post,
                    it's got a residence up in Baguio and a residence down in Manila. It's a very
                    appealing thing, and it was particularly appealing to me. So that's the way it
                    went, from my point of view. In other words, I would recapitulate and say that
                    there was clearly a policy difference; it was no question that I was going to
                    leave. Whether I left because I wanted to resign or whether I left because I was
                    shifted to Manila seems to me be irrelevant. The point of the matter is that
                    there was a disagreement, and it could not have gone on. And it seems to me to
                    be a storm in a tea cup whether-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which came first.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, which came first. Because, it was perfectly clear we couldn't go
                    on, that I disagreed so fundamentally with the way they were going that I would
                    not have any utility, that he was so determined, it seemed to me, to go in this
                    direction, that either I would become a prostitute or he would have a guy in the
                    key post that disagreed with the policy to implement it. Now, you couldn't do
                    that. So I had to leave. The only issue was whether I left by going to Manila as
                    Ambassador or whether I went outside. And, of course, the fact that I chose to
                    go outside and to be a critic is that much of the tension and bitterness came
                    after all of this, came when I became a public critic.</p>
                <p>Q: You were talking about the New Left critics or of people who have reviewed
                    you. The right wing said at the time you left - Human Events or somebody - that
                    your telephone had been tapped in the State Department and all sorts of things.
                    Is there anything to these allegations at all?</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: I think that's a lot of nonsense. You know, that's just nuts. They
                    generally are, but I give you a chance to deny all the accounts that came out.
                    Was there quite a lot of anti-Johnson talk around town by this time among the
                    Kennedy people? Public talk? Georgetown cocktail circuit talk? This type of
                    thing? Well, I don't know. Of course, there is always this stuff just like
                    there's talk about the Kennedy family and all of this stuff. There's always
                    things like that - the political wits.</p>
                <p>But my own feeling about this is that the first few weeks before I went to
                    Australia, and I remember at the time of the funeral, the way Johnson was moving
                    and the importance of him getting hold really touched me. I remember up in the
                    State Department at the time of the reception when we were bringing foreign
                    heads of states in. I was there with a couple of foreign heads of state. As one
                    of them said goodbye, before the next one came up to him, I said to Johnson with
                    tears in my eyes, because it was an emotional time, but I was feeling very
                    identified with the problems he had and everything else, “I just want you to
                    know that” - I think I even said as a Texan or something like that - “I think
                    you're doing great and I'm with you a hundred per cent.” And that was another
                    occasion where it just didn't - [we] sailed by each other, and so on.</p>
                <p>I'll tell you frankly, those first few weeks, before I went to Australia I kept
                    saying to Mike [Forrestal], “We've got to reach Johnson, that is, we've got to
                    get a chance to sit down and talk to him, really just us, and really tell him
                    what's the background and all of this stuff. We've got to reach him.” And Mike
                    got very pessimistic very quickly. And he was in the White House at first.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sure.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: He got very pessimistic very quickly. And he said, “You'll never do it.”
                    And I said, “Oh, yes, we will.” And I began and I called Bill White up and tried
                    to somehow reach the President through Bill White. I tried to think of friends
                    of mine on Capitol Hill, senators, that might do it. It was only when I sat down
                    on that airplane and reviewed it that I realized how hopeless it was, that I
                    began to be convinced that there was just no longer any point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where is Mike Forrestal? He's one of the people we can't
                        locate.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: He's here in town. Shearman and Sterling.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He's with Shearman and Sterling.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, right here in town.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, good. We had to get our addresses through the White
                        House,and they've lost track of him somehow.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, it's 20 Exchange Place in New York City. Shearman,S-H-E-A-R M-A-N
                    and Sterling, P. O. 98500.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: I see him all the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good, because we do really want to talk to him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: No, I'll tell you, my own feeling is that my departure was directly
                    concerned with Vietnam, absolutely centered upon Vietnam. And of course, I
                    suppose - you know, I never was one of the jet set or this business. My father
                    was an army officer and I'm not in this eastern seaboard-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Establishment?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: No, I certainly am not. I'm not of the Mac Bundy group and so on and so
                    forth. So there was never any of that, as far as I was concerned at least, in my
                    relations to Johnson. It was strictly policy as far as I was concerned. And I
                    think that the restatement of it is that it became very clear that his viewing
                    of it and mine were diametrically opposed. It was perfectly obvious that I
                    couldn't stay from his point of view and from my point of view. I couldn't stay
                    and try to carry out a policy that I didn't agree with, and he couldn't have a
                    man in a key position who disagreed with the policy he wanted followed. So it
                    was perfectly clear I had to go. And I think these issues of personal attention
                    and all this stuff are pretty much afterwards, that is, the gossipy sort of
                    thing afterwards that come up. I remember somebody came up to me a year or so
                    later, and again, that's always the key. It's after the public quarrel begins,
                    and this really begins in September of 1965 when I testified before Ted
                    Kennedy's Subcommittee on Refugees, which was probably unfortunate that it was a
                    Kennedy subcommittee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: But nevertheless, that was the only opportunity I had. But when I came
                    out and said, “The bombing is a mistake; it should have never been done,” that
                    was September of 1965. It had been going on for nine months. I kept quiet after
                    the bombing started. And I think all the tension and bitterness stems from after
                    the point, you see. For example, it was after that that somebody had told me
                    some story about my having a tiff with Lady Bird at a party. That's absolutely
                    absurd. I have never been to a party with Lady Bird except the Bill White party.
                    So, you know, you get all this crap, which seems to me to be crap.</p>
                <p>Q: What kind of things did Mr. Johnson and his White House people do to a critic
                    such as yourself? You've mentioned a couple of stories that he gave to the
                    press. Were there other things, other reactions that came back to you after you
                    became an open critic and particularly after the book came out?</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, as far as Johnson is concerned, the only thing that has ever come
                    back to me was this sort of thing that you've heard about on background with the
                    press. I mean, I've heard stories of what he said about Mac Bundy, about Bill
                    Moyers in backgrounders and so on and so forth which I dismiss. There have been
                    two or three episodes that friends of mine in the press have said that he said.
                    One was this story I've already told you.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right, right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Which I have no doubt he said. I don't think he was fabricating it. I
                    think he was mixing up disagreement and so on and so forth.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By the time he told it, he believed it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, by the time he told it, he believed it. But there have been a
                    couple of things like that and things like his just making disparaging remarks
                    of “Certainly glad we got rid of Hilsman,” or things like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Nothing concrete in the way of retribution.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: No, nothing that I know of. My income tax has been audited every year,
                    but I don't think that has anything to do with it. (Laughter) That can happen to
                    anybody. Mr. Rusk, I think, is not as big a man as Mr. Johnson and he has said
                    some things. I remember it was reported in the press that in a background
                    session with the Washington Post and New York Times people that he has said that
                    he fired me. And my response to that publicly and privately is that I doubt very
                    much if he said it that way. Because, first of all, it isn't true. And second of
                    all, I would think he was a bigger man than that. But I do think that Rusk is
                    probably - well, for example, I wrote Rusk a letter very similar to that letter,
                    and he did not answer, but Mr. Johnson did, as you see.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a significant difference, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: I think it's a significant difference. Of course Rusk's view of
                    government is such a peculiar one - that of secrecy, excessive secrecy. I really
                    think that Rusk feels that the American people don't have a right to know what
                    goes on in their government and that he really thinks that anybody who writes a
                    book is making a mistake.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Although, presumably, he's preparing something for
                        publication ohis own right now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Probably his speeches. {Laughter)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: But you know, most of the reviewers who didn't have an ideological ax to
                    grind, i.e., the ones that were neither on the right nor the left thought that I
                    really kind of leaned over backwards to be fair to Rusk, and I certainly didn't
                    have anything in it like Schlesinger did about being a Buddha or something like
                    that. I actually have a lot of admiration for Rusk, but I make no bones of the
                    fact that I think that he did not serve Kennedy well, in the sense that he did
                    not present the case for the political side vigorously, that he tended to sit
                    there, you know.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>Q: The only other issue in which you mention Johnson in the book is in regard to
                    Indonesia. Did he ever give an explanation to you as to his refusal to sign the
                    determination required by the Broomfield amendment?</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, I must confess that. It's funny about that. There were really three
                    substantive issues, you know, at the time that we overlapped - the hundred days
                    or whatever it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The hundred days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: The hundred days. One of them was China policy, and this ivery-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was something moving there at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Oh, you bet you; you bet your boots. See, what had happened was this was
                    my open door speech and this is very interesting. I hope this gets into the
                    record. Just to review the bidding, Kennedy had tried to do something about
                    China policy in 1961-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: - by recognizing them and by going on with the rest of it. And just came
                    a cropper on Capitol Hill. So that ended that. Then one thing led to another,
                    you know. In 1962 there was the crisis over Quemoy-Matsu and the buildup and so
                    on. Then in 1962, the Cuban Missile Crisis. Then there was - it's in the book -
                    the “year of the tiger” business where Chiang kept trying to land people on the
                    mainland, guerrillas and so on. But the fall of 1963 came around, and we looked
                    around the world, and things looked pretty good. The Cuban Missile Crisis has
                    passed; Test Ban Treaty is signed; things are quiet; you know, pretty good. And
                    the time had come to do something about China, and this was kind of decided. The
                    opportunity came with an invitation to me to give a speech in San Francisco. So
                    we really prepared a very careful speech. And this was to be sort of the policy
                    of the second Kennedy Administration, you know, that we were going to get it
                    going before the election. And the key phrase in that speech, just to try to
                    prove the point that it was a fundamental change, was that Dulles' speech said
                    that Communism on the mainland is a passing phase-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: - and out of that assumption flows a policy of hostility, rigidity,
                    isolating China. Well, in my speech the key phrase is: here there's been all
                    this turmoil, but there is no evidence that the communist regime is in any
                    danger, that is, it's here to stay. And that out of that flows what is called
                    the open door speech - “we will match you step by step.” Now, Kennedy was killed
                    before I gave the speech, and then the question was: Do I give it anyway? I
                    sounded out the White House on this one, and [there was] no objection. So I
                    decided to take the bull by the horns and go ahead and do it. I suppose in my
                    mind [I said], “We might as well smoke out Johnson on this one,” because this
                    was very early in the first couple of weeks. But I took the speech up to Rusk,
                    told him what was in it, and said, “Do you want to read it? There's going to be
                    some flap about it.” And when he said, “No, I'll let you do your own thing,” I
                    gave the speech, and there were big headlines and everything else. Interestingly
                    enough, [there was] very little kickback from Capitol Hill. The China lobby
                    eventually did attack the speech, but was very slow about it. But nothing much
                    from Capitol Hill. [There was] some favorable editorial comment around the
                    country, very good, even in anti-State Department papers. And generally the way
                    it goes was, you know, they're common sense people. Here we've been doing this
                    for so many years, and it hadn't worked. Well, let's try something different. So
                    the old sting of the China lobby was out. Well, after a couple of weeks to see
                    what the flak was, I called up Walter Jenkins and Tom Hughes. Tom had known him;
                    I didn't know him; but Tom Hughes called up Walter Jenkins and said, “Roger
                    Hilsman would like to have lunch with you and like to find out how the President
                    felt.” Now that already gives you a measure of this. I couldn't call the White
                    House and say, “Can I see the President? I want to talk to him about this China
                    speech.” I had to go through devious ways, you know. But anyway, Walter Jenkins
                    was warned that we really wanted to see what LBJ felt. We also wanted to talk
                    about the upcoming election. Because Tom and I, both being political animals,
                    were thinking about what the White House had in mind and how we might give
                    speeches and so forth for the 1964 election. But, anyway, we asked Walter
                    Jenkins to sound the President out on it. He came back and said, “On the whole,
                    very good. The President thought this was pretty good.” And that was
                    encouraging. Now I did not - I would never have recommended implementing the
                    speech. If Kennedy had been alive, I had on my desk recommendations to lift
                    travel bans on Americans, reexamine the question of trade restrictions, invite
                    them to the disarmament talks, and recognize Mongolia. Those would have been the
                    first moves. But I never even forwarded those to the White House, because you
                    see, my feeling would be that you don't want any grand initiatives in foreign
                    policy in the period when the new President has got to get his hands on the
                    reins. The time to do that would have been after the 1964 election, you see. So
                    I was happy. It even went so far that it was either the summer of 1965 or the
                    summer of 1966, but I think the summer of 1965, before my public attack on the
                    bombing, I got a call from the White House staff, and then President Johnson had
                    made a speech on China policy that was very similar in content to mine. You
                    know, it was an olive branch. The White House staff called me and said, “Well,
                    we thought somebody from the White House ought to call you today, because the
                    President has made a speech that carries out your ideas.” Further, some of them
                    said, “Why, we even just pulled the press briefing for your speech out of the
                    file and used it over again.” My point being that there was no disagreement
                    about this that I am aware of, that he was sympathetic to my views on China
                    policy.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The other two issues were Vietnam and Indonesia. I
                        think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: -and I thought at the time and I think today, that his handling of
                    Indonesia was bad. And again, it was the same thing; it was listening to
                    military side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was the military, and not Congress, in this case?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, all right, it was Congress. You are probably right.You're probably
                    right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was kind of driving at the idea of whether or not he
                        leaned oCongress pretty hard there at the first.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes, that's right. You're probably right. But anyway, I thought it was a
                    mistake. He sided too heavily with the British. Of course, it was linked to
                    Vietnam. He wanted British support on Vietnam, you see. And the truth of the
                    matter is that this one he lucked out on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like you said: If you win, your opponents are
                        disarmed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: That's right, but I would say that the truth of the matter is that he
                    lucked out, not because of anything he did or the Americans did. What happened
                    here was that the other side made a mistake. And I think that truth of the
                    matter is that not only did our policy not contribute to the victory in the coup
                    of 1965, but actually hurt our friends - our policy did. It weakened our side.
                    And I think that if the Communists hadn't made the mistake of attempting a coup
                    prematurely and [had] let it go and gained strength, which our policy was really
                    weakening our friends and strengthening the Communists, I think. So I disagreed
                    with Mr. Johnson on this one.</p>
                <p>And here again, you know, he put the responsibility in the hands of McNamara, and
                    that's not where it belonged. It was bad, and that was another element, another
                    element in my feeling that he was just not going to listen to the
                    Harriman-Forrestal-Hilsman-Ball group.</p>
                <p>Q: I don't want to cut you off. You're very generous with your time. Are there
                    any other subjects on which you had dealings or knowledge of Mr. Johnson that
                    you think should be mentioned here?</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: No. There's one funny story. And that is that once in here, I have
                    forgotten the exact date, but by this time I think that the policy disagreements
                    were clear. But I took over to the White House - it must have been - [Harold]
                    Holt, the later prime minister. He wasn't a prime minister at the time. But I
                    think it was that it was an Australian. And as Assistant Secretary, I took him
                    over to see Johnson - just the three of us. And in the kind of the banter that
                    takes place in the beginning, Holt, I'm sure it was, said something about having
                    just been to Texas. And Mr. Johnson said, “Well, that is more than Roger can
                    say.” And I got my back up, you know, because he had forgotten that I was a
                    Texan. As I recall the episode, it was a little flip, fresh, but I said
                    something about, “Mr. Johnson, you've forgotten I'm a Texan. Why, I have two of
                    my relatives portraits hanging in the state house of Austin.” And I didn't say,
                    but you know the thought, “which is more than you could say.” (Laughter)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right, right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: But I didn't say it.</p>
                <p>Q: You saw him in some very trying times there at the beginning, but you did see
                    him fairly close. What kind of personal diplomat was he during those three
                    months?</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Dealing with foreigners?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Oh, I think very good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some of these critics have traced a lot of our later
                        trouble witDe Gaulle, for example, to the funeral meeting and so on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, I was not present there. I was not present there. But this guy is
                    a highly intelligent person, and he's canny, and when he wants to be, he can be
                    charming and sensitive; there's no question of that. He can be awfully cruel
                    when he wants to be to people, and there's a streak of this in him, too. One
                    thing I do remember and notice now that I think about it. I hadn't thought of
                    this, but it's true of everybody and it probably doesn't have too much
                    significance. When I first became assistant secretary and had to deal with
                    foreign ambassadors, you're not quite sure of yourself at first. I can remember
                    my looking past the ambassador, finishing something that it had been decided
                    that I would say, and looking over to the desk officer for reassurance, you
                    know. And I noticed that Johnson did this with me. That the first two or three
                    chiefs of state that I brought in, he would make his pitch, and then he would
                    look at me for reassurance.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it works all up and down the line, right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Sure it does. I noticed that, but I wouldn't put too much significance
                    on it in the sense that some people might say that this is another instance of
                    his real insecurities [of] which, of course, he has many.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: But I don't think so, because I think this is a natural thing that
                    happens to anybody who is thrown into that kind of situation where you suddenly
                    have to play a new role. Well, I don't know. You have nothing else?</p>
                <p>Q: No, I don't want to keep you from delving into areas that you think are
                    important. But you've been very generous with your time. And if you can't think
                    of anything to add now, perhaps you can add it to the transcript or
                    something.</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, he is an extraordinary personality. You know, he's a big man, in
                    the sense that his successes are big and his failures are big.</p>
                <p>Q: That's true. You might add, incidentally, what we were talking about before
                    the recording started, that the breach between you and Mr. Johnson has, at least
                    apparently according to the documents on your wall, been now healed by an
                    exchange of very friendly letters in January and March of 1969.</p>
                <p>HILSMAN: That's right, but I don't know that it would be wise to say that the
                    breach has healed. I think that people like Walt Rostow who are going to be very
                    busy-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are very busy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: [They] are very busy trying to justify the decisions and rationalize
                    them, that that's not going to heal, in that sense. And in the sense that I
                    think that some major mistakes were made. And I think that some of them were
                    unnecessary mistakes. I think some of them go back to Johnson's personality, in
                    that his inability to tolerate opposition around him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The sycophancy that you mentioned earlier.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>HILSMAN: Well, that's where his insecurity comes in. I always used to say after I
                    got to know him fairly well, after this period that there were only two possible
                    relations with Johnson. One was the Jack Valenti relationship; you know, a total
                    adulation. And the other one was that you had to be a senator. Now, what I meant
                    by that was that you had to have independent political power. Then you could
                    have a relationship with Johnson. But where it's perfectly true that where, with
                    Kennedy, see, I had nothing except expertise. I mean, I had no constituency; I
                    couldn't go out and muster opposition. I'm in a better position to now than I
                    was then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: You see, because I've gotten to be known because of the criticizing of
                    the Vietnam War. But [then] I had no constituency. Yet with Kennedy, I could
                    feel as free to stand up and argue with the Joint Chiefs of Staffs as the next
                    man, you see. But not so with Johnson; not so with Johnson. It just seemed to be
                    very difficult to have a relationship with him, unless you either had
                    independent power or were willing to be a Jack Valenti.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's an important distinction.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, thank you very much again. Sooner or later we'll get
                        transcript of this back to you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HILSMAN: Okay.</p>
                <p>End of Interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
