<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000369">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Herbert A. Fierst </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>HERBERT A. FIERST</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: July 16, 1996</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: First, I wonder if you could tell me when and where you
                        were born and something about your parents.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: Well, believe it or not, I was born the day that World War I, not World
                    War II, started - July 29, 1914. I was born in New York City. My father was an
                    immigrant who came to this country at the age of 16, in the year 1900, from what
                    is now known as Lithuania, then part of Russia. He was a youngster of 16, an
                    ardent Jew who was about to be drafted into the Czarist Army and managed to
                    escape in a kind of spectacular way, and came penniless to the United States and
                    then founded a boys' clothing manufacturing company. My mother was born in
                    Montreal, and was the daughter of an Orthodox rabbi. They were married in 1913,
                    the year before I was born.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In a way, this is the classical story, isn't it? Did you
                        get much feeling from your father about Russia and the situation there,
                        particularly for the Jewish community? Did he talk much about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: Not when I was a youngster, but when I got interested later on it was a
                    subject that fascinated me and really influenced me in a number of
                    directions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would you say it influenced you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>FIERST: Well, he was, long before he came to the States, at the age of 13, an
                    early Zionist - he ran a library of Zionist literature before he emigrated. He
                    later became treasurer of the Zionist Organization of America and we had a
                    succession of impressive visitors to our house. We used to live in Mount Vernon,
                    Westchester County, New York, and there was an active Jewish community there.
                    And then he realized his great ambition, which turned out to be mine, too -
                    bringing me, together with the rest of the family to Jerusalem to celebrate my
                    Bar Mitzvah at the age of 13. That was the year that Lindbergh flew the
                    Atlantic. There was no commercial aviation - it took us two weeks to get there
                    by ship and rail and car. I was the first American boy to celebrate his Bar
                    Mitzvah in Jerusalem. So I say that this was an early exposure in a very
                    exciting, emotional way, to Zionism.</p>
                <p>I just might interpolate now that when I was about that age I was in an
                    oratorical contest at my synagogue. I won it with a very emotional peroration -
                    that someday, I said this roughly in about 1927, Palestine would be a haven of
                    refuge for hundreds of thousands of oppressed Jews around the world. My father
                    afterwards took me aside and said that he was very proud of me, but I should
                    learn not to exaggerate - not hundreds of thousands he cautioned! So that's the
                    atmosphere that I was raised in as a youngster.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now tell us about your schooling - your education.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: I went to a conventional grade school in Mount Vernon, and ended up that
                    educational system at public high school. It was then called Mount Vernon High
                    School, and later became A.B. Davis High School. Then I went to Harvard College,
                    entered in 1931 and graduated in 1935. That really ties back to the question you
                    asked me about my father. To him, this was a dream come true, that his son
                    should be attending Harvard College. When he came to visit me there, along with
                    my mother, he took so seriously the kind of inscriptions that were on the arches
                    of the buildings we passed through every day and really didn't notice - such as
                    “Enter and Grow in Wisdom,” or something like that. He was very much of an
                    idealist. I have to say that really influenced me.</p>
                <p>I look back with a great deal of affection at my four years at Harvard. I had a
                    scholarship, but also a job of 15 to 18 hours a week, the whole four years that
                    I was there. Most of the time, two of the four years, I did work that did not
                    relate to my subsequent career, as it turned out. I was in the Harvard College
                    Astronomical Observatory. One year I was in the Boston State House on some
                    research project related to government.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>I had a great experience during my senior year that affected my attitude toward
                    foreign affairs, really for the rest of my life. We had to do a thesis in the
                    honors program. I was majoring, or concentrating as they called it then, in
                    Government. In 1934 there had been a general strike on the San Francisco
                    waterfront, led by Harry Bridges, an Australian longshoreman, a crypto
                    communist, a very dynamic fellow. Somehow or other, I got interested in the
                    subject of the general strike as a method of averting war. It became the subject
                    of my thesis. The socialist movements around the world had developed the notion
                    that the workers were cannon fodder of the capitalists and if war was declared
                    or initiated, all they had to do was strike and they could not be subjected to
                    the brutal treatment of WWI, when they were killed by the hundreds of thousands
                    and millions. I started looking into the subject, as I recall, from an objective
                    and neutral point of view. However, as I analyzed it in the context of world
                    affairs at the time, I reached the conclusion that it was a terrible idea
                    because the only areas in which a general strike could be effective were in the
                    democracies. The threats to world peace came from fascist, Nazi fascist,
                    countries and from the Soviet Union, which would not allow a general strike to
                    be organized.</p>
                <p>This now, in retrospect, seems such an obvious conclusion, but at the time it was
                    not. There were so many well meaning liberals and radicals who thought that the
                    thing to do was to curtail world armaments and that would solve a lot of the
                    problems. Unfortunately, they influenced primarily the democracies, not the
                    threats to peace. The Government Department thought very well of my thesis and
                    my work, and I graduated summa cum laude.</p>
                <p>More important than that, a few weeks before graduation I was awarded a Sheldon
                    Traveling Fellowship, which provided the munificent sum, in those days, of $1500
                    for a year's travel abroad. The only conditions attached to it were not to get
                    married during that year and not to stay in any one place and study, but to
                    broaden yourself by traveling. A wonderful, wonderful fellowship! I had already
                    been admitted to Yale Law School at that point, and was intending to go to law
                    school and become a lawyer. So I changed my plans altogether and spent a
                    fascinating year abroad traveling in 15 countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was what year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: This was from July, 1935 to June 1936.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, boy. That was a really...things were still open,
                        but...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: Yes, I had some hair raising experiences, say, in Nazi Germany, which I
                    won't go into here. This is a long-winded answer to your question about
                    college.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the things I'd like to get - coming from your
                        background - liberal, idealistic, New York Jewish, immigrant, and then going
                        to Harvard - what was your impression, during these times, of the Soviet
                        Union, that you were getting from the family, neighbors, and then at
                        Harvard? Were there differences?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: I don't remember the neighbors. There were some pro-Soviet people that
                    were idealistic and thought that the USSR was going to change the world for the
                    better. I have to say, while I think of it, I had a very lucky experience in the
                    Soviet Union on this trip. Through a series of coincidences and introductions, I
                    had a letter of introduction from Otto Tolischus, who was the New York Times
                    correspondent in Berlin, to Walter Duranty, the New York Times correspondent in
                    Moscow, who was regarded at the time as a great reporter. Later he wrote a
                    famous book, I Write as I Please. The reason it was lucky for me was lucky that
                    when I went to Moscow and I went to his office, he was either out of the city or
                    out of the country. His secretary introduced me to somebody else. I'm afraid
                    that if I had met Duranty I would have fallen under his influence. In
                    retrospect, from what I know, he did some terrible pro-Soviet things, concealing
                    the extent of the famine among the peasants and so on. Whether this was
                    deliberate or not I don't know, but as I look back over the accidents of my life
                    and the coincidences, a number of times I've said to myself - I wonder if I
                    would have come out of the Soviet Union with a different, pro-Soviet view if I
                    had been under the influence of Walter Duranty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was very easy - it is difficult today to go back and
                        reconstruct, I think, for those who haven't experienced it. From what I
                        gathered, a lot of Americans went to the Soviet Union to visit, and they
                        were looking for good. This was supposed to be the “new man”, the “new
                        world”, and all that. What was your impression of the Soviet Union? What did
                        you come away with?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>FIERST: Mind you, I was there, as it turned out, during the initial period of the
                    purges, which I didn't know about at the time. Instead of meeting Walter
                    Duranty, I had met through his secretary, a young man named John Hazard, who was
                    there on a fellowship to study Soviet jurisprudence - the first American to do
                    that. He took me under his wing, a little bit. He took me to see a Soviet
                    municipal court in action. I had no inkling at the time, and I doubt that he did
                    too, that the purge trials were beginning. They had not been publicized. I had
                    the impression, which was reflected in letters that I wrote after I got out, or
                    in a diary, that American visitors, and world visitors were taken in by what
                    they saw through the eyes of an inexperienced visitor, because they were gushing
                    all over when they came looking for uplifting things. I use a very simple
                    example - it comes back to me now - of when I was a youngster of 21 at the time.
                    It was January of 1936, the middle of winter that I was in Moscow, and I was
                    probably the only American tourist in the whole country. As a result of this,
                    though, (I was traveling third class, and was supposed to go with tourists in a
                    bus for sightseeing), I was taken around in a limousine by myself with an
                    Intourist guide and I remember she took me to a candy factory. I had never
                    visited a candy factory in the United States. [Most American tourists didn't
                    visit candy factories or any other factories, and they get impressed by
                    machinery if they visit factories abroad.] But I was appalled by the way that
                    these women, whose noses were dripping with colds, were wiping them off with
                    their hands without having gloves, then handling the chocolates. It had a
                    superficial impression of efficiency, but was really very primitive and even
                    health threatening.</p>
                <p>I did have one fascinating experience with a young Soviet engineer, who was a
                    relative of somebody from my hometown. He was in his late 20's, as I remember.
                    He had been an engineer on the Dneeprestoy Dam which a lot of American engineers
                    had worked on. He had picked up real vernacular, fluent English. He came to my
                    hotel room where we talked and we did a little walking together for seven solid
                    hours, he was just spewing forth some of the conditions that he had met in the
                    USSR. He wasn't bitterly complaining, but very realistic and not very
                    complimentary. So I did not emerge as a starry eyed apologist for the Soviet
                    Union. I might have been tempted, as I mentioned before, if I had come under the
                    influence of Walter Duranty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While we're doing this, could we touch the other base,
                        what did you cull out - here you were, of Jewish stock, coming into Nazi
                        Germany just when it was really cranking up towards its hate. How did it
                        strike you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>FIERST: I had a very unusual experience - it almost embarrasses me in retrospect
                    to tell you how it started. I was in Brussels, attending the World's Fair. I had
                    no intention of going to Nazi Germany, although I had been invited there by the
                    father of a then 12 year old boy my parents had taken into our house. He was on
                    the first boatload of Jewish refugee children coming to the United States in
                    1934. But, well, we are about to have the Olympics here - this was half a year
                    before the famous 1936 Berlin Olympics - the Nazis were supposed to be on their
                    somewhat better behavior. There was much talk of a boycott of Nazi Germany which
                    I was prepared to observe. I can laugh now about why I changed my mind, but I
                    didn't at the time. In visiting the Brussels World's Fair, somehow or other I
                    got duped by three confidence men and they deprived me of practically all the
                    money I had at the time. Another increment of my Fellowship money was due in a
                    couple of months. So I decided that I would take advantage of the invitation
                    that had been extended to me. I wouldn't really be violating the boycott, since
                    I didn't have any money left (I had a little), and I would be staying in Berlin
                    with this Jewish family. So that's what I did.</p>
                <p>I can't resist telling you about the fantastic opportunity I had that,
                    unfortunately, I was not able to take advantage of, to assassinate Hitler. I
                    wouldn't be here, but it also would have changed the course of history!</p>
                <p>I am a great believer at this stage of my life in serendipity. Things happen as
                    you go along, and sometimes you can influence the course of events and sometimes
                    you can't. In this particular case, after I had been in Berlin, living with this
                    family for a little while, I did have the sense of the world closing in on the
                    Jews but not of anything really dramatic.I wrote to Ferdinand Kuhn, who was then
                    the New York Times correspondent in London. I had a letter of introduction to
                    him from our mutual high school history teacher, which I had not used as yet. I
                    said, “I am going to see you when I came to London, but would you please
                    introduce me to the New York Times correspondent in Berlin.” So, by return mail
                    he sent me a letter of introduction to Otto Tolischus, whose articles I had read
                    avidly in the Times and I thought he was a terrific reporter.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>When I went to see him and explained to him my circumstances - how do I go about
                    finding out what's really happening here - he took me in hand and gave me a good
                    many practical suggestions, which I followed. I should explain, for the benefit
                    of those who may be reading this, that in those days I had quite a bit of hair
                    and it was quite blonde. I have a German sounding name. So, while I made no
                    effort to conceal or restrict my activities because I was Jewish, I also didn't
                    go about mentioning it one way or another. I met quite a few Nazis, many of whom
                    looked very non-Aryan but they assumed that I was of “Aryan” extraction. Anyway,
                    I'll just tell you this one incident to give you the flavor of how exciting this
                    trip was. He said to me (Otto Tolischus) “Do you have a document or certificate
                    from Harvard that has a seal on it?” And I said “Yes, as a matter of fact I have
                    and I don't know what to do with it.” He said, “Well, do just what I say - go to
                    the Propaganda Ministry - do you speak any German?” I said, “Pretty well.” and
                    he said “Well, don't speak a word of German, and just hold out this certificate
                    with the seal on it and say that you want to see Herr Vogt.” I said, “Who's he?”
                    and he said, “He's in charge of propaganda to the United States. Just be very
                    innocent, just say you're a student from an American college and you want to
                    find out the real truth about Germany. See what he says.”</p>
                <p>I followed instructions. We are so used to being screened for security nowadays
                    that we assume that happened way back then. But, to the best of my recollection
                    there was nothing like a metal detector to go through or a body search. I just
                    walked in and followed instructions, and said that I wanted to see Herr Vogt.
                    They looked a little puzzled and I had to wait quite a while. Then I was taken
                    up one or two flights of stairs, as I recall, where there was this enormous
                    office. A tough looking man looked up from his desk very quizzically - he didn't
                    know who in the world I was. I went through the routine of “finding out the
                    truth about Germany” and he took me for a sucker. He started telling me how
                    Roosevelt was surrounded by Jews and so on and so forth. In the middle of his
                    talk, there was a kind of a fanfare outside. I hadn't known it, but the
                    Propaganda Ministry was right opposite the Reich Chancellory and he beckoned to
                    me and said, “That's our Fuhrer coming out of the Reich Chancellory, if you want
                    to see him.” He went to the window, and opened the window, and there was Hitler
                    coming in his car, just as a visiting dignitary would come from Blair House into
                    the White House. He was in an open roadster and he was sitting next to the
                    driver in the front seat with three men, probably security people, behind them.
                    But here I was, looking right down on him! And it wasn't somebody who whizzed
                    right by - he had to make a right angle turn, and there I was right at that
                    point almost directly above him.</p>
                <p>I can't resist telling you that some months ago, my 12 year old grandson in
                    Massachusetts called me at 7:00 in the morning. Apparently his parents had given
                    him some version of this and he had to do something for school, and he said,
                    “Did you really see Hitler, grandpa?” And I said “Yes, matter of fact I had a
                    chance to knock him off but I didn't have a weapon.” So he said, “What
                    happened?” I tried to describe this to him, and he said, “What about a
                    flowerpot?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bright kid!</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>FIERST: It never occurred to me, but what would have happened if I had seized a
                    flowerpot and used it appropriately? Anyway, it was a fascinating year, as you
                    can tell.</p>
                <p>You probably heard about Harold Laski, of the London School of Economics. He was
                    quite a radical at the time, and kept up a correspondence with a lot of
                    Americans, especially Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes. He did, by a conversation,
                    change the course of my early career. I had a letter of introduction to him from
                    my tutor, the Chairman of the Government Department at Harvard, Professor
                    William Yandell Elliott. I sought Laski out in London and at that time I wanted
                    to be useful to the world, to further the labor movement, and I guess I was
                    quite an idealist, though I did have the sense by the time I was almost finished
                    with this year's travel that the world was really going to collapse. I told him
                    that I had been admitted to Yale Law School and that I had intended to go there
                    before I left on this trip. However, I had seen so many fascinating things that
                    were important to write about, that I was considering changing to be a
                    journalist. He talked me out of it. He said that's really not a career, but if
                    you learn a profession, like the law profession, you can be much more useful.
                    Maybe I would have reached that conclusion myself anyway. I had already been
                    admitted to the Columbia School of Journalism, as I recall, when I was so
                    fascinated by the many things I was seeing, but I decided to go into law school
                    after all. That's a rather long-winded version for what you asked me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, it's a period that we'd like to capture, I think it's
                        a very important one - one of those formative times, how people reacted. In
                        law school, you went to Yale, for what was - three years? What did you
                        specialize in, any particular, or was it some sort of general law?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: It was general law. I was very interested in civil liberties, and I
                    promoted a special course in civil liberties, to be given by Harry Shulman, who
                    was then a professor concentrating mostly on torts. We tried to arrange a kind
                    of a practical laboratory where Yale law students would be confronted with
                    specific civil liberty situations. I am talking now mostly about those involved
                    in the labor unions. It was the era of the sit down strikes and the attempts to
                    break up unions and the formative years of the National Labor Relations Board.
                    One summer I was a volunteer with the New York City Civil Liberties Committee
                    and was kicked out of Jersey City which was in the domain of “Boss” Hague, Mayor
                    Hague.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>One of my classmates subsequently became a well-known professor of copyright law,
                    and I recently saw him at our 55th Yale Law School reunion. I was reminiscing
                    with him and I said, “You know, in my professional legal career I've been
                    spending most of my time lately on copyright law, and I never took a course at
                    the time in law school, in copyright law, and I've wondered why.” He said, “It
                    wasn't given then.” So it was a totally new field for us, and again exemplifies
                    what I mentioned earlier about serendipity. I'm not going to go into my
                    professional career as a lawyer, but the kind of work that I did a lot of and am
                    now doing quite a lot of, developed out of a series of coincidences, tracking
                    back in a totally different context to two people that I met at the State
                    Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about your connection - you graduated from law
                        school in what, about 1939, in which all hell is getting ready to - broke
                        loose - in Europe. Just to sort of move on until we get to the State
                        Department, anyway, foreign affairs field, because it may not have been
                        immediately the State Department, what did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: I'd say that if I had known you then, and if you had made a bet with me
                    whether I would ever end up in the State Department, I would have given you odds
                    of a thousand to one, or a hundred thousand to one, that I would never end up in
                    the State Department. It was never my ambition, and it had never really occurred
                    to me. When I graduated from law school in June, 1939 and took the Bar Exam in
                    New York and was admitted to the Bar, I practiced fairly briefly with a New York
                    law firm that was known as Parker and Duryee. One of the partners was appointed
                    Moreland Act Commissioner, as they called it then, by the Governor of New York
                    to make a study of quasi-judicial action of administrative agencies. He asked
                    for me to be released temporarily to be on his staff.I've got to mention one
                    person who was in that law firm as a partner that, through serendipity, I'll
                    skip ahead, if you don't mind, greatly influenced the course of my future
                    career. This was a man named Robert Finley, one of the senior partners in the
                    firm. I worked with him on one case that had nothing to do with civil liberties
                    or labor law, and one day he approached me and said that the war in Europe was
                    liable to expand and might have an impact on the United States. He had become a
                    Captain in the New York State Guard, which drilled, I think, a couple of times a
                    week in an armory off Park Avenue. He wanted to know whether I would be willing
                    to join and get practice in marching and drilling and shooting. I have to say
                    that I was very much of an interventionist by then and thought that it was
                    inevitable that we would get involved, so I took him up on his invitation. We
                    used to drill fairly elementary stuff, but something that I had not known
                    before.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>This became an important event in my career in early 1944. I was already in the
                    Army, had entered as a Private, and I had become a Second Lieutenant, trained in
                    anti-aircraft artillery. Through a series of coincidences, I had ended up in
                    military government. We were being trained, along with British military
                    government officers, to follow the troops after D-Day. We were in a place about
                    50 miles west of London called Shrivenham. We were kept busy, because we didn't
                    know when D-Day was going to come, by taking long marches which were really
                    quite delightful, if one might call it that at that period in the English
                    countryside. One day I was coming back from one of these marches. As we
                    approached our campsite, we were given the order to come in looking like a well
                    drilled group. The British and the Americans were interspersed and we had
                    different styles of marching, and I was on the outside file. We were, I am sure,
                    looking ridiculous, and out of the corner of my eye who do I see but Major Bob
                    Finley! He burst out laughing when he saw me - after all, he had trained me and
                    the New York Guard to do much better than that. That night he came to my
                    barracks. He looked me up, he hadn't known that I was there, and I hadn't known
                    that he was there. He said he was working in Supreme Headquarters, Allied
                    Expeditionary Force (SHAEF), in what was called the Legal Functional Unit. He
                    was in charge of it, and his responsibility was to draft proclamations and
                    orders to be posted when troops arrived in a conquered village or area. Of
                    course, there had to be different ones for France and for Nazi - for Germany, if
                    it reached that far, and for Austria. He said he had one assistant, and needed
                    another one, and would I be willing, if he could arrange it, to do that? Of
                    course, I jumped at the opportunity. If it hadn't been for that, that's why I
                    went into this long detail, after D-Day, I probably would have been a military
                    government officer someplace in Europe, and I strongly doubt that I would have
                    ever come to the State Department.</p>
                <p>That led to another series of coincidences. (I think I'm dragging this out too
                    long, but I think it's worth pointing out how one's career gets affected by
                    these serendipitous events.) At the time of the Battle of the Bulge, I was still
                    in England. The day after Christmas (which is known as Boxing Day in England), I
                    came to the office - half of us were on duty on Christmas and half on Boxing
                    Day. The sergeant said that a cable had come in for me, maybe he wasn't supposed
                    to show it to me but he would, and this was that I should be sent back to the
                    States right away. They were looking for somebody with my qualifications in the
                    office of the Chief of Staff in the Pentagon, in a new division which had been
                    set up, called the Civil Affairs Division. I hadn't the faintest idea how this
                    had come about, and when my commanding officer received this the following day
                    he was furious, thinking that I had manipulated, maneuvered it somehow, but it
                    turned out again to have been coincidence. A Lieutenant Colonel who had been
                    Dean of the Buffalo Law School had followed a cousin of mine who had previously
                    been Dean. I had come to know him in Shrivenham, and he had been called back to
                    the Pentagon. This man's name was Mark DeWolf Howe, who later turned out to be
                    the biographer of Oliver Wendell Holmes Jr. When he got back to the Pentagon,
                    one division in the new Civil Affairs Division, the Planning Division, had four
                    full Colonels in it and they wanted a junior officer with all kinds of special
                    experiences. He felt that I had these qualifications, so they sent an order to
                    bring me back immediately. When I finally reported for duty in the Pentagon, by
                    that time there had been a reorganization and I was put in another division, and
                    so on.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>Through a long process of administrative changes and coincidences, I became very
                    close to Major General John Hilldring, who was the Director of the Civil Affairs
                    Division in the Pentagon - that's a story in itself - but later, when he was
                    asked to come over to the State Department, asked by Secretary of State James
                    (Jimmy) Byrnes to be Assistant Secretary, a new position, for Occupied Areas -
                    Germany, Austria, Japan, and Korea - he brought with him about 8 or 10 of us,
                    who had been about to be civilianized and go back to our normal professional
                    lives. That's how I would have lost my bet with you, if you'd made one, because
                    I found myself in the State Department as Special Assistant to Assistant
                    Secretary of State Hilldring. This was in March, 1946.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was General Hilldring's background?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: His background is extremely important. Again, another example of
                    serendipity. He had intended initially to be a journalist, and had gone to the
                    Columbia School of Journalism. Then World War I broke out, and he ended up in
                    the armed forces, had military service abroad and decided to make a regular
                    career in the Army, in the lean days between WWI and WWII, lean from the point
                    of view of the Army. He was a Captain, I believe, at the time the New Deal set
                    up the CCC (Civilian Conservation Corps). Military officers were put in charge
                    of various districts. It so happened that he was put in charge of one district
                    and the district next to him had in charge a Major named George C. Marshall.
                    They became very close friends. The years went by, and during WWII, General
                    Hilldring had become a Major General commanding an infantry division that was
                    about to be deployed in the Pacific.</p>
                <p>I think it was in San Francisco that they were given their final medical
                    examinations. They found that there was something wrong with General Hilldring's
                    heart, and they wanted to retire him on the spot for disability. As the story
                    goes, General Hilldring, in characteristic fashion, picked up the phone and
                    called General Marshall who was, by this time, Chief of Staff in the Pentagon
                    and said, “I realize that I can't serve you overseas in this condition, don't
                    you have a place for me in Washington, where I can further the war effort?”
                    Marshall brought him back to Washington, and he was first put in charge of
                    relations with Congress. Then when this new division was set up in Washington,
                    the Civil Affairs Division, known as G-5, he was made the first Director of
                    it.</p>
                <p>He was a formidable character. He had a booming voice - most people on his staff
                    and most people he came into contact with were in awe of him, of doing anything
                    that would run afoul of him. He was a brilliant fellow, spoke and wrote
                    extremely well.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>I want to interpolate at this point an incident which brought me to his personal
                    attention and greatly affected my life and career after that. This was still
                    back in the Pentagon, in the spring of 1945. I had been assigned to what was
                    called the Economics and Supply Branch of the Civil Affairs Division, and I was
                    something of a jack-of-all-trades where I was supposed to cover maybe 15 or 20
                    subjects by reviewing a tremendous flow of highly classified material that was
                    coming in from the war in Europe, our troops in Europe. As a result of the
                    Jewish background and sensitivity that I covered at the start of this talk, I
                    was particularly sensitized to any material about the liberation of the
                    concentration camps. As of that time, the Army was coming in for some criticism
                    by journalists and by some American Jewish leaders and organizations, some of
                    whom had guilty consciences about not having pressed hard enough during the war
                    for more specific action on behalf of refugees or for bombing concentration
                    camps, and so on. Anyway, out of this mass of Top Secret material that was
                    flowing across my desk, one day I came across a bulky report classified Top
                    Secret, why I don't know, of the liberation of one of the concentration camps.
                    There was so much human interest in there about the GIs, falling all over
                    themselves, doing whatever they could to help the survivors, sometimes literally
                    killing them with kindness by giving them their rich chocolate bars which they
                    shouldn't have done, and so on. I am citing this as an example not only of
                    coincidence, but also of the personal interactions on policy in those days.
                    Things happened very quickly, and we were all very intimate with each other.</p>
                <p>I went in, I recall, with this material to Ernest Gross, who was a Major at the
                    time and who later became Legal Advisor of the State Department - he had come
                    over with us from the Pentagon. Later he was Deputy US Representative to the
                    General Assembly of the United Nations.</p>
                <p>I said, “Ernie, take a look at this - it is so different from the accounts
                    appearing in the press - it puts the Army in such a good light.” He said that
                    Colonel Davis would be very interested in this. Colonel James C. Davis, (I think
                    it's a “C”) a prominent lawyer from Cleveland, was in charge of this Economics
                    and Supply Branch, and he said, “Get up a memo right away from me (Gross) to
                    Colonel Davis. But he wants everything boiled down to no more than two pages.”
                    How could I do that? All this valuable material compressed into two pages! Under
                    pressure, I put it into two pages.</p>
                <p>Colonel Davis called me in right away, and said something to the effect that
                    “...this is terrific, we ought to get this to the attention of General Hilldring
                    right away!” Up to this point I had gone to staff meetings, but had never
                    actually had a personal relationship with the General. And he said, “Drop
                    everything, get it in memo from me (Davis) to Hilldring, but he wants everything
                    in no more than one page.” How can I do that? Do it! So, I got it down to one
                    page.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>I learned later how Hilldring had reacted. He was a man of direct action, he
                    always had a clean desk, and he believed in finding somebody whom he could
                    trust, no matter what his rank, working with him and relying on him. He asked
                    who had written the memo, “Who is this fellow, Fierst. Get him in here right
                    away. Get this into a memo from me to Gen. Marshall”, who was then Chief of
                    Staff and a world figure, and he said, that “...he wants everything on half a
                    page!” So I got it down to half a page, and I still remember how excited I was
                    when Hilldring, sometime later, not long afterwards, came - he used to sort of
                    waddle like a duck - into my little office and threw this memo on my desk
                    triumphantly. In the upper right hand corner were the initials GCM. The memo had
                    registered with Gen. Marshall. The important thing for my subsequent career was
                    that from that moment on, I was Gen. Hilldring's displaced persons expert,
                    particularly on the problems of Jewish displaced persons. He knew that I was
                    Jewish. If he didn't know then, he found out in due course. We had a very close
                    and important relationship for a long time afterwards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, we're in the State Department. What were the years
                        you were in the State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: From roughly the middle of May, 1946 to around December, 1955.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you arrived there, what was the impression of Jimmy
                        Byrnes, particularly in his relationship to this foreign occupation type
                        work that you were doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: I have to say that the only time I had a personal contact with Jimmy
                    Byrnes was when he announced his retirement and he had a reception where we just
                    filed by and he shook our hands. I never had any personal direct contact with
                    him. But it came back to me that the reason that some of us were brought over to
                    the State Department was that he had considerable contempt for what he called
                    the “striped pants boys”. I remember Gen. Hilldring describing how Byrnes had
                    asked him to come over when Hilldring was still Director of the Civil Affairs
                    Division in the Pentagon. Byrnes said, “We've got these four major conquered
                    countries on our hands, Germany, Austria, Japan and Korea”. Italy was not in
                    that category. “What are we going to do, we have to run them, but I can't rely
                    on these foreign service people to do that, they can't do anything practical. So
                    I need somebody like you who'll be in charge, and bring over whatever staff
                    you'll need.” That's how Hilldring broke the news to some of us that he wanted
                    us to come over to the State Department with him and be on his staff. I really
                    look back on those days with considerable amusement because for a while, I still
                    had my Captain's uniform, didn't have any civilian clothes, and was regarded
                    along with others on General Hilldring's staff as sort of a military mafia!</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>This might be interesting to people who look back on that historical period:
                    Everything was so intimate in those days - in terms of personnel, lines of
                    authority. As I recall, there were maybe four or five Assistant Secretaries of
                    State. I don't think that the Middle East had an Assistant Secretary of State
                    until afterwards. Loy Henderson was Director of the Near East Division. This was
                    important because Hilldring, through his own direct contacts, would go right to
                    the top. He would often assume jurisdiction over officers in the department who
                    were not in the direct line of command.</p>
                <p>I'll give you one example which is kind of exciting and illustrates this point.
                    One day, my office mate, who was in charge of press relations and who had also
                    come over from the Pentagon, flipped a clipping onto my desk and said, “Why
                    don't you do something about this?” This was because I was generally in charge
                    of refugees and displaced persons on Hilldring's staff. This was a newspaper
                    account of 48 Estonian refugees who had come across the Atlantic in two open
                    boats, and landed in Florida. They didn't want to be sent back to their native
                    country which was under the domination then of the USSR. They were not Jewish,
                    had nothing to do with concentration camps, or anything like that. But it did,
                    in my mind, have something to do with the spat we were in with the British, who
                    were refusing to allow Jewish displaced persons to go to Palestine and were
                    blockading the coast of Palestine. This was really just a humanitarian
                    situation. They were going to be sent back. They had no visas, therefore they
                    were to be sent back. I immediately went to see David Niles, one of President
                    Truman's three or four assistants. He was also in what we used to call the “Old
                    State Department Building”. I had gotten to know him quite well, in connection
                    with the Holocaust situation and Jewish displaced persons. I showed him the
                    clipping and said, the President ought to do something about this. He said,
                    “Well, it just so happens that the President is having his weekly press
                    conference just this afternoon. Give me a statement and I'll see if I can have
                    him deliver it.” It was the easiest thing to draft, although it was very heady
                    stuff. “...These are the kind of people that made America and I am directing the
                    State Department to find a way of keeping them here.”</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>So sure enough, the President issued the statement at his press conference that
                    afternoon, and Dave Niles asked me, “... where do we go from here?” I said
                    “Well, have the President send it over to the Secretary and tell him to do it.”
                    So, it went over to Dean Acheson, who bucked it down to General Hilldring, who
                    bucked it down to me. I drafted a memo, as I recall, from General Hilldring to
                    George Haering, who was the Director of the Visa Division. The Visa Division was
                    really a kingdom in itself, and had really close connections with the
                    Immigration Service, Justice Department and with the Hill. As I recall, I had
                    Hilldring bucking it to George Haering saying, “... Here is a statement the
                    President made, and sent it over for execution, so find a way of doing this and
                    report back to me.” Again, this was a blurred chain of command. But just to
                    finish up on this little anecdote - Haering, sometime later, produced a mammoth
                    memorandum, giving all the technical reasons why it was not possible to do this
                    - that the quota was only a hundred a year, I think it was, and it was already
                    over-subscribed and these people didn't have visas. Hilldring summoned Haering
                    to his office. He wanted one-on-one, but he called me in afterwards with great
                    gusto and described what took place. It still stands out in my memory, I must
                    say with some relish! Hilldring said, “Mr. Haering how much do you get paid in
                    your position?” Haering drew himself up and proudly said, “$10,000 per year,”
                    which was the top government salary at that time. Hilldring said to Haering,
                    “Well, when the taxpayers of this country pay you that tremendous sum, they
                    expect you to bring some imagination and skill to your job. When the President
                    of the United States announces to the world that he is directing the State
                    Department to find a way of keeping these people here, he doesn't expect you to
                    come back and say there are all kinds of technical reasons why that can't be
                    done. So find a way of doing it, and do it!” And it was eventually done. That
                    was the way some things were done in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me, before we move to the occupied thing, what was
                        your impression of how we, the government, State Department, and of course
                        the military was heavily involved, faced up to the problems of the
                        Holocaust, of the aftermath of the Holocaust, we're talking about '46, '47
                        and so.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>FIERST: Well, I'll tell you, it came about to a large extent in the form of a
                    battle with Ernest Bevin, Foreign Minister of Great Britain, on admitting Jewish
                    refugees to Palestine. Bevin had agreed, or maybe initiated the idea, to have a
                    12 man Anglo-American committee on Palestine appointed - six British and six
                    Americans. They were to look into, hold hearings, do whatever they wanted. They
                    were to look into the overall problem of Palestine, in the context of what had
                    happened in the Holocaust. He was reported to have told the British members that
                    he would agree to put into effect anything that they could unanimously agree
                    upon. He was very confident that there couldn't be unanimous agreement. The
                    Anglo-American Committee made a tour of the displaced persons camps,
                    particularly the Jewish displaced persons camps, held hearings there and then
                    secluded themselves to write their report. Meanwhile, survivors of the
                    Holocaust, who were not actually being taken into our displaced persons camps as
                    our armies advanced, were following various routes into our zones of occupation
                    in Germany and Austria. Part of it was pretty clearly improvised and organized.
                    What might happen, for example, would be that some Polish-Jewish survivors had
                    survived by reason of having gotten to the USSR before the Nazi armies
                    incarcerated or exterminated other Jews. They wanted to come back to their
                    former places of residences, in say, Poland and found when they got there that
                    for one reason or another they weren't welcome. They would be encouraged, and
                    sometimes organized surreptitiously, to continue on to Germany and Austria. And
                    they were pouring into our displaced persons camps. We in the US zones were much
                    more sympathetic than the British zones or the French zones and there was a
                    dilemma that developed as far as the American-Jewish community was concerned and
                    the American military. The conditions in the displaced persons camps began to
                    deteriorate because these hapless people were pouring in, sometimes 1,000 per
                    day, and overwhelming the Army, which regarded its major responsibility as the
                    military government of Germany to root out the Nazis and to rehabilitate the
                    German economy. They really had not been trained for this kind of humanitarian
                    work. Generally, of course, the GIs and the officers who served their country
                    overseas wanted to be demobilized as quickly as possible and come back to
                    civilian life.</p>
                <p>Both in the Pentagon before I transferred to the State Department and later in
                    the State Department, considerable pressure was brought by our theater
                    commanders, particularly by General McNarney in Germany, to close the borders to
                    future entrants. They wanted to say, “Okay, we've reached the saturation point,
                    we just can't take any more in.” They were all coming in except for those who
                    were following a clandestine route out through Italy and were intercepted by the
                    British and taken to Cyprus. Except for those, the pressure was building up in
                    the displaced persons camps and the zones of occupation. The Anglo-American
                    Committee was very conscious of this. To the consternation of Ernest Bevin, they
                    came out with a unanimous recommendation to transport 100,000 Jewish displaced
                    persons immediately out of the DP camps and to admit them to Palestine. There
                    was a lot of struggling byplay back and forth in the Pentagon and in the State
                    Department as to how much pressure could be placed upon the British - should be
                    placed upon them. Bevin was absolutely adamant, though, and made some unsavory
                    remarks about President Truman catering to the Jewish vote. Basically, it was a
                    nasty situation.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think one should put into context - Bevin had the
                        problem which exists today, they had a mandate on Palestine. There were
                        Arabs there who weren't going to look upon this very kindly. The British
                        were caught betwixt and between a hard place.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: It was a nasty situation, and it was the major difference between our
                    staunch ally - two staunch allies - the British and ourselves. Just the other
                    day there were some moving stories in the New York Times and Washington Post and
                    elsewhere about the 50th anniversary of the pogrom that took place on July 8,
                    1946 in Kielce, Poland, where 48 or 49 Polish Jews who had returned from eastern
                    Europe to their former homes in Kielce, were brutally murdered by the Polish
                    population. This was a particularly poignant memory to me, because, and I might
                    just go into this a little bit in detail to give you an indication of how
                    sensitive the whole subject was at that time and how we worked with it. In March
                    of 1946, when General Hilldring and others were already over at the State
                    Department, the War Department was receiving recommendations, urgent requests,
                    of the field commanders in Germany in particular, to have authority to close the
                    borders to any further entrants. I came up with the suggestion to General
                    Hilldring that we have an off-the-record conference with Jewish leaders in the
                    United States to get them to understand the difficulty of accommodating still
                    more under these conditions, and asking for their help in stemming the flow, to
                    the extent that they had any control over the situation. I remember General
                    Hilldring telling me that he had taken this up with Dean Acheson. Acheson had
                    been very skeptical that we could get Jewish leaders to agree on anything among
                    themselves, but it was worth a try. So Hilldring said to me “...All right, set
                    up the meeting.” This is one of the examples that came to mind when you asked me
                    earlier in this interview about my early background. I was very familiar through
                    my upbringing as to who some of the key Jewish leaders were in the United
                    States. We got them together in about the middle of March, 1946, and the War
                    Department, actually Secretary of War Bob Patterson, came over. I did a briefing
                    paper which I delivered to Secretary Patterson's house the night before. I also
                    did a briefing paper for General Hilldring and Dean Acheson. Acheson started
                    this meeting and then somebody came in and said the President wanted him to come
                    over to the White House right away about something else. So he left General
                    Hilldring in charge.</p>
                <p>The Jewish leaders were very understanding of the situation and, without making
                    specific commitments, they said they would do the best they could to stem the
                    flow and they would be appreciative in their public statements of efforts that
                    would be made to accommodate the occupants of the displaced persons camp under
                    these terrible conditions.</p>
                <p>Whatever they did seemed to work, because for a while there was less pressure
                    from our military commanders to do something about it. But then came this
                    terrible pogrom in Kielce and the flow started up again in a few days after
                    that. Today is July 15th, it must be the 50th anniversary today or within a few
                    days.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>We had another meeting with the Jewish leaders and outlined the situation to
                    them. I remember that Colonel Buster came over from the Pentagon along with
                    Secretary Patterson. Colonel Buster had a huge map of Europe and he had marked
                    on it quite accurately, according to my own sources, either then or later, the
                    routes that were being taken by the survivors to get into these displaced
                    persons camps.</p>
                <p>One of the Jewish leaders in particular, Jacob Blaustein, knew Secretary
                    Patterson personally. Patterson was a very decent human being and gave the
                    impression of being sort of embarrassed at having to come and take the
                    hardheaded position that we just can't take care of any more. Mr. Blaustein was
                    a tough business man in his private life, I think he was Vice President of the
                    American Jewish Committee at the time. He was not known as a very emotional
                    person, but he made a very emotional plea to Secretary Patterson that this was a
                    remnant of the Jewish people after this terrible event, “...and it's very
                    difficult, we know, to impose upon the American Armed Forces, etc. etc., please,
                    for history's sake do whatever you can.” It did produce humanitarian results. It
                    was a very fascinating period of American and Jewish history.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To follow through on the problem of the exodus, going to
                        particularly the Cyprus thing, to have this mixed commission, making it were
                        at loggerheads with the British over what to do - how did that work itself
                        out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: It worked itself out, I guess, in the special session of the General
                    Assembly on Palestine. We were very much at loggerheads with the British. There
                    was another commission, I have been referring earlier to the Anglo-American
                    Committee on Palestine, which was British and American. But when Britain threw
                    up its hands really and dumped the Palestine problem, as it was known, into the
                    United Nations and said “We're leaving, you take over, we're getting out.” The
                    UN appointed a committee, I think it was called UNSCOP, United Nation's Special
                    Committee on Palestine. They made a recommendation for partition of various
                    areas in Palestine so that Jerusalem would be internationalized and part of the
                    area would be a Jewish state and part would be an Arab state. Ben Gurion, along
                    with Chaim Weizman, top Zionist leaders, recommended to the Jews involved in the
                    situation that they accept the partition plan even though it did not give anyone
                    nearly everything they wanted. The Arabs opposed it and 6 or 7 Arab countries
                    initiated an attack against the nascent country of Israel. That is a long
                    detailed story itself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Going back to the occupation thing, let's take what I
                        assume is probably the shortest one of all of the various countries from
                        what I've heard from other sources, the role of your office in State
                        Department dealing with this foreign power, i.e. General Douglas MacArthur
                        in Japan. That must have been a battle royal the whole time, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>FIERST: It was, but I have to plead not so much loss of memory, but absence of
                    involvement, in that particular part of the world, Japan. Korea, I got involved
                    in in a different context - not in the occupation of Korea. But by the time of
                    the invasion of June 25, 1950, the Office of Occupied Areas that I had been
                    placed in, had ceased to exist and I had been transferred to, at first it was
                    called UNA, United Nations Affairs, and then IO, International Organization
                    Affairs. General Hilldring and his successors had long since left the State
                    Department, and I was an assistant to Jack Hickerson, who was Assistant
                    Secretary for United Nations Affairs.</p>
                <p>I still remember vividly Sunday afternoon, June 25th. We had some out of town
                    visitors we were showing around, but I wanted to drop in to the State Department
                    to see if by chance I was needed on account of this invasion of South Korea and
                    I bumped into Jack Hickerson in the lobby of the New State Department. He had
                    just come back from a conference at the White House and said that I wasn't
                    needed that afternoon. I mentioned earlier in this interview the importance of
                    personal contacts and I had mentioned Ernest Gross, never thinking you'd get
                    around to the subject of Korea, but by this time, Ernie Gross was deputy to
                    Warren Austin at the UN. When a special meeting of the Security Council had to
                    be called to get authorization for resistance to the invasion, I remember that
                    Ernie's daughter had had a slumber party going on at the time and that the
                    telephone rang in the wee hours of the morning and he had to grope through
                    slumbering girls to get this order to call an immediate session of the Security
                    Council to resist the invasion.</p>
                <p>You had mentioned over the telephone the other day that you'd been in Japan. In
                    the early days when I was in General Hilldring's office, he had a Deputy
                    Administrative Officer, or maybe the Administrative Officer himself, Charles
                    Kades, we called him Chuck. He was a Colonel. He left to be on General
                    MacArthur's staff in Tokyo, and I read somewhere recently that he was largely
                    responsible for the drastic and new, democratic constitution of Japan, that he
                    drafted it in a short period of time. But I have to say that this was outside of
                    my own area of responsibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your area of responsibility was with Germany and
                        Austria?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: Germany and Austria when it came to occupied areas. When I got into
                    United Nations Affairs, it was a wholly different range.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's stick to the occupied areas first. What was the
                        state of the occupation in 1946 - Germany first, what were the plans, and
                        what were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>FIERST: As I have indicated earlier, my main area of concentration was on the
                    displaced persons problem, which was enough of a headache. Part of that, which I
                    didn't get to but it's relevant here, I think, is that General Hilldring saw
                    very clearly that part of the solution of the displaced persons' problem was to
                    make exceptions in American immigration law, and admit a fair proportion, I'm
                    not talking about only about Jewish displaced persons into the United States.
                    And so we worked with an organization, an ad hoc organization which did succeed
                    in getting legislation passed in 1948.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Displaced Persons Act, displaced persons - what we now
                        term as refugees, but that was the term for the first...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: General Hilldring, I might mention this to you, as it gives you a certain
                    flavor of what he was like, was to appear before a joint session of the Senate
                    Immigration Committee and the Senate Foreign Relations Committee. Senator
                    Vandenberg was chairing the meeting - he was Chairman of the Senate Foreign
                    Relations Committee. Senator Revercomb of West Virginia was Chairman of the
                    Senate Immigration Committee and was very anti-immigration. In preparation for
                    that appearance, General Hilldring said to me that he wanted to be able to prove
                    that by setting up and supporting the International Refugee Organization as the
                    successor to UNRRA, United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Agency, we would be
                    saving money. This is the language that they understand on the Hill, he said. He
                    directed me to find out from whatever sources I could how much it was costing
                    the US Army per refugee or displaced person, and how much it could be done by an
                    international organization such as IRO or UNRRA. I had a terrible time, it's not
                    really my field, in getting a figure, and Hilldring said, “Look, do the best you
                    can, but whatever we say will be accepted.” He then made a dramatic appearance
                    before this packed joint session. So many of my “do-gooder” friends were
                    attending, representing various organizations, both Jewish and non-Jewish. They
                    were filled with the humanitarian aspect, motivation, about what they were
                    doing. I could practically hear them gasp when General Hilldring pounded the
                    table and said, “This is costing too much - we've got to find a way to do it
                    more cheaply!” and he said, “I believe that these unfortunate people, many of
                    whom are barefooted, should be given shoes, but they don't have to be given GI
                    shoes that at that time cost $3. They can be given some cheap European shoes,
                    but we can't do that. If the US Army handles it, it will have to meet its high
                    standards of care. So, he said, let's turn them over to an international
                    organization, which will assume responsibility, thus costing us less. When the
                    Chairman invited questions, there were none - not even from the hostile Senator
                    Revencomb. Whereupon Senator Vandenberg said: “Well, General, I guess you slayed
                    them!” That really taught me a lesson, which General Hilldring had learned a
                    long time before in his relations with Congress, that you have to make a case in
                    their terms, and he was great at doing that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did it work out while you were...how long were you
                        dealing with displaced persons?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>FIERST: I would say roughly until about 1949.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How had the situation changed by the time that you
                        left?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: It had changed vastly. One area that I have not mentioned that was
                    extremely sensitive was the issue of forcible repatriation. We had a terrible
                    time with the Soviet Russians, who accused us of brainwashing Ukrainian, Baltic,
                    and Russian displaced persons, and they wanted us to transport them whether they
                    wanted to come back to the USSR or not. There were some ugly incidents where, in
                    the early stages, they were loaded onto trains at the point of bayonets and then
                    we had to change that policy. I had a hand in drafting some speeches for Eleanor
                    Roosevelt when she was our Representative at the General Assembly, and replying
                    to Andrey Vishinsky, the Soviet prosecutor in the purge trials and their Deputy
                    Foreign Minister who represented them at the UN. They took a very hard line.
                    “...These are our citizens, you're keeping them from coming back, deliver them
                    to us...it's simply a transportation problem.” They accused us of all kinds of
                    insidious activities to avoid forcibly repatriating those Soviet DPs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you aware that many of these people who were going
                        back would end up by being in very difficult circumstances, vis a vis the
                        Soviet authorities once they got back, up to and including being purged and
                        killed. Did we know that then, were we naive, or how did we feel about this
                        at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: I think we were naive at the time of Yalta. I don't profess to be an
                    expert in that, but generally speaking, we were accused, not by the Russians,
                    but by some American liberals, of having sold the Soviet displaced persons down
                    the river at Yalta. And again, I am not an expert. If I had the time and the
                    expertise I would look into those records, but my own impression, which may or
                    may not be accurate, is, that at the time of Yalta, it never really dawned on us
                    that hundreds of thousands of Soviet displaced persons wouldn't want to go back
                    as soon as they could. It was really, from our point of view, a logistical
                    problem. Transportation was so disrupted throughout Europe as a result of the
                    war, and the Russians wanted to have some kind of priority given to their people
                    to return - I mean, this is the way I think we viewed it. I had no direct
                    responsibility for anything that had to do with Yalta, but I was aware, later
                    on, of the US Government being on the receiving end of criticism from some
                    Americans that FDR had not taken into consideration what would happen to the
                    people who came back to the USSR.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With your responsibility for the displaced persons, were
                        you there when the Displaced Persons Act got in, and sort of international
                        committees took over much of the responsibility?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>FIERST: I was, and it was a very exciting time. I remember being asked to
                    participate as a Representative of the Department in two different arrivals in
                    the United States, one in Boston - I think it was the first ship coming over
                    with displaced persons - and the other in New Orleans, the first one that came
                    in to the South. For the one that came into the South, on that occasion, I
                    remember, there was a special military plane that took us down. There were
                    representatives from the Senate and House Immigration Committees. The Mayor of
                    New Orleans had a reception and gave us all keys to the city. It was really a
                    very heartwarming affair. And similarly in Boston.</p>
                <p>I think that in spite of all the turmoil here we can look back with satisfaction
                    on what was accomplished. We changed the atmosphere. It is not really realized
                    nowadays how vehemently anti-immigration sentiment was in the United States at
                    that time - including, especially, the American labor movement. I remember
                    vividly accompanying General Hilldring to a meeting of the US Delegation to the
                    General Assembly, when he was to make a presentation on the necessity of having
                    an international refuge organization set up. I remember there was Senator
                    Vandenberg there, and John Foster Dulles, Adlai Stevenson, and Congressman Sol
                    Bloom, who was the Chairman of the House Foreign Affairs Committee.</p>
                <p>Hilldring made a very poignant presentation to the US Delegation about the plight
                    of the refugees, and it was not just the Jewish ones - all of them. We had
                    finished all of the logistical aspects of returning those who wanted to be
                    returned or helping them to resettle in Australia or Canada or wherever it was.
                    But he said that we have to set up this international refugee organization, and
                    we have to take the leadership in doing it. We have to find places in other
                    countries around the world, but let's face it, we have to initiate some
                    legislation in our own country - take our fair share in the United States. At
                    this point this American Congressman, Sol Bloom, who was very sympathetic
                    because of his being Jewish, said, “Look, General, you don't seem to be familiar
                    with the atmosphere on the Hill. If you even try to get any immigration
                    legislation on behalf of displaced persons, you're going to end up with
                    legislation that will bar all immigration to the United States. So I would
                    advise you to let well enough alone.” Hilldring wouldn't accept that, but I've
                    often thought of that as a vivid example reflecting the atmosphere. The American
                    Legion was against it. The general feeling was, and I think I'm oversimplifying
                    it, twofold: one, all the millions and millions of servicemen coming back from
                    abroad are going to be looking for jobs; and the other was, there are going to
                    be a lot of radicals among these immigrants and how can we control them? The
                    best thing is not to let anybody in. And this was quite a very prevalent
                    attitude.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now you moved over to United Nations' Affairs. What was
                        your job with United Nations' Affairs? This was 1949, you say.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>FIERST: It's hard to define bureaucratically. Generally speaking, we wanted to
                    generate and preserve an atmosphere of support for the United Nations. There
                    were still a lot of isolationist attitudes in the United States. At the time we
                    had, as I recall, a pretty good working relationship with Trygve Lie, who was
                    Secretary General of the United Nations. On the other hand, there were some
                    embarrassing incidents, where some Americans with extreme left-leaning
                    backgrounds had gotten employment at the United Nations as international civil
                    servants, and this led to an involvement with Roy Cohn and Senator Joe McCarthy.
                    Roy Cohn at that the time was in his early '20s and was at the US Attorney's
                    Office in New York making a big fuss. There was an uneasiness throughout the
                    country about the Soviet Union, well justified, about the time of the Rosenberg
                    execution (Ethel and Julius Rosenberg). My job, really, was the public relations
                    aspect of it: To explain the United Nations to the American People - not
                    verbally, but through literature, some of which came under my supervision - sort
                    of putting out fires that were occurring. On a more constructive level, and this
                    ties into the invasion of the Republic of Korea in June, 1950, we tried very
                    hard, and I think we succeeded, in internationalizing the resistance to the
                    invasion. We tried to get as many foreign countries as possible to contribute at
                    least token military support forces so that we could say that it was not just
                    the United States resisting, it was the United Nations against North Korea, and
                    later China. There were a lot of fires that had to be put out at one stage. The
                    UN forces were falsely accused of waging germ warfare, remember that? So we had
                    to put that fire out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you deal with that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: I don't really remember. It was a big crisis at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, well it was just one of those accusations that I guess
                        we kept going out and saying, “We're not doing it!” which we weren't. Well,
                        what about...did you ever, during this time, this is 1949 on, this is the
                        height of the McCarthy period. Did you run afoul of McCarthy at all, or that
                        thing there, were you....</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: That's a very low key question for a very high key answer. I had the
                    dubious distinction of having been Senator McCarthy's Case Number One in the
                    State Department. Just to personalize it, going back now to when Senator
                    McCarthy made his subsequently famous (nobody paid too much attention at the
                    time) speech at Wheeling, West Virginia - he accused the State Department of
                    having 205 communists.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “He says, “I have here a list in my hand...”"</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>FIERST: Yes. And then at the time Jack Peurifoy was Under Secretary for
                    Administration in the State Department. His office was on the same floor as ours
                    in New State, or whatever we called it at the time. I knew him quite well. He
                    exuded confidence that if they gave McCarthy enough rope he would hang himself.
                    He and the administration grossly underestimated McCarthy's ability to
                    manipulate the media. The media were generally anti-McCarthy, but they couldn't
                    help covering the news when he called a press conference, and reporting it. I
                    remember vividly when the administration decided to challenge McCarthy on the
                    floor of the Senate, and they said “...what are you talking about, cite chapter
                    and verse.” The morning press reported that Senator McCarthy had given 81 case
                    histories in a long speech before the Senate, but without mentioning names. That
                    morning, I remember picking up the Congressional Record, which was delivered to
                    my office every morning. I was primarily following displaced persons legislation
                    and related legislation. I saw this long speech by Senator McCarthy and I
                    remember being curious as to whether I would recognize anyone. It never dawned
                    on me that I might be one of the 81! I got no further than Case #1, which was
                    unmistakably me, he didn't mention any names - just gave the case summary, that
                    he was talking about a Special Assistant to a General was an Assistant Secretary
                    of State, and so on. He threw in there as fact what had been a number of
                    allegations that had been subsequently investigated and disposed of.</p>
                <p>Let me just interrupt myself and take a few steps back. When the notorious 80th
                    Congress had come under Republican control, they conducted an investigation of
                    the State Department. The State Department had made available to the 80th
                    Congress Committee all of its personnel files and they had (I didn't pay any
                    attention to these personnel matters in those days) surprisingly, given the
                    State Department a clean bill of health. But there were in these files many case
                    histories. Unbeknownst to me, mine was one of them. I forget the number of my
                    file - they didn't use names. I think it was 51 or 52. They had a master list,
                    which was correlated to the case numbers, and in my case there were three
                    individuals with whom I had dealt who warranted investigation. They
                    investigated, and they found that there was nothing to any of the allegations
                    bearing on security.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>I might just mention one of them as an example of what the atmosphere was in
                    those days. This might sound self-serving, or self laudatory, but it helps fix
                    the date in my mind. Just before we were leaving the Pentagon to come over to
                    the State Department in early March 1946, a Major came into my office, a heavily
                    decorated Major, who had rows and rows of ribbons, and combat stars on them. He
                    didn't have an appointment, but introduced himself as Henry Collins. He said
                    that he'd just gotten back from overseas and he'd been part of the occupation
                    force in Germany. He'd come across a lot of displaced persons in his work and
                    felt very sympathetic to them. He understood we handled this problem and he'd
                    like to work with us. I was interrupted at this point, somebody reminding me
                    that we had a staff meeting, a special meeting with General Hilldring. So I
                    said, “Can you remain here until we finish this staff meeting?” He said he
                    could, and it turned out that, unbeknownst to me, this was a staff meeting in my
                    honor, and Gen. Hilldring awarded me the Legion of Merit. He pinned this
                    ostentatious looking medal on me, and I remember a feeling of embarrassment
                    walking back to my office. I had not been in combat, and here I had this
                    dazzling medal on to resume my talk with this Major. I explained to him that a
                    number of us were going over to the State Department very shortly, as we were
                    being civilianized, with Gen. Hilldring, in this new office. If he was still
                    interested, and if we were short of personnel, I would look into adding him to
                    our staff. He went into a long bureaucratic history about how he had been
                    working for one department and had been on loan to Senator Kilgore's
                    Investigating Committee and had gone into the Army. So it wasn't a brush-off by
                    me, but it was, I didn't know what the situation would be - “get in touch with
                    me if you're still interested.” He did come around to see me when I was in the
                    State Department. He was then in civilian clothes. He said he could get an
                    arrangement with his agency, to get them - some well-known agency - which agency
                    had lent him to Senator Kilgore's committee - he could get them to lend him for
                    three months to the State Department. So he wouldn't be on our payroll, and
                    would not fill a personnel slot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a government agency?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>FIERST: Yes, it was a US government agency something like the Reconstruction
                    Finance Corporation. We were absolutely overwhelmed at the time. This seemed
                    like a godsend. Here was this guy experienced in displaced persons, and was
                    interested in them, and so on. I wasn't a personnel person, so I took it up with
                    General Hilldring and he said “...sure, if we can get him for free, do whatever
                    is necessary.” So I asked him to draft the kind of letter that he would want
                    from us to his agency to lend him to the State Department for three months, as I
                    recall. But then, my drafting initials appeared on the letter rather than his
                    when I sent it forward for General Hilldring, I think it was, to sign. I am
                    going into this detail to show how it started. He came to work for us, and he
                    wasn't really very good. When it came time to renew the three month period, we
                    decided that we had had enough. Lo and behold, at some stage thereafter, there
                    were these hearings where Elizabeth Bentley appeared before the House
                    Un-American Affairs Committee, and she identified this Henry Collins as the head
                    of one of the communist cells in the 1930's. Meetings had been held at his house
                    and so on. This had never come up, there was no reason for it to come up, in our
                    conversations, or in the kind of work that he had done.</p>
                <p>He was one of the three. In McCarthy's summary, instead of saying “...it was
                    alleged that...” it was as though this Number One had manipulated the
                    bureaucracy to bring this communist in to the State Department. After reading
                    this Congressional Record statement, I went to see Jack Peurifoy, and he said
                    that “...we have no security problem with you at all.” I had Top Secret
                    clearance all the time.</p>
                <p>So I did lead, I have to say, kind of a charmed existence, in that McCarthy never
                    released, at least at that stage, my name, or the names of the others, but he
                    went on in his presentation to the Senate to say that these were all terrible
                    people, radicals, brought in to the State Department, etc. etc. But the worst
                    was what he called “The Big Conspiracy, by the Big Three - Numbers One, Two and
                    81”. Number Two, as it turned out, was John Carter Vincent, whom I had met maybe
                    once or twice when he was coming into General Hilldring's office. I really had
                    nothing to do with the Far East in those days, or ever, other than I would go to
                    assist displaced persons in a special area. Number 81, I learned, was a woman
                    whom I don't think I had ever met, or even heard of, named Esther Brunauer. She
                    had something to do with USIA.</p>
                <p>I was saved for quite a while as far as publicity was concerned because McCarthy
                    kept on jumping from one thing to another. When he'd be challenged, somebody
                    would feed him some information and he would focus on that.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>I do have to recount this, to show you what the atmosphere was like. It was not a
                    very pleasant time to live through. Jack Peurifoy had asked me if I would mind
                    meeting, on an off the record basis, or not for attribution basis, anyway, with
                    Stuart Alsop, who was a very prominent columnist at the time. He wanted to write
                    a column about The Big Three, with the understanding that he wouldn't mention
                    their names. So I had lunch with Stuart Alsop, and he wrote an excellent column
                    afterward. I have to say that, as I recall, only one of my friends came close to
                    recognizing me. But it was all a bunch of nonsense. As a result of that, I
                    wouldn't say I had a friendship with Stuart Alsop, but it prepared me for a
                    telephone call I got from him one day, saying, “I am up at the Hill now, and
                    Senator McCarthy has just announced that he's holding a press conference
                    tomorrow at 10:00 o'clock, where he is going to announce the name of the top
                    Soviet espionage agent in the United States, who is still in the State
                    Department.” So he said, “Do you have any idea who that might be?” I hadn't the
                    faintest idea. (I should have mentioned earlier all the atmosphere about Alger
                    Hiss and so on.) He said, “I hate to have to tell you this, but the word around
                    here is that it is probably going to be you!”</p>
                <p>So I hung around the news ticker the following day in the State Department, as
                    McCarthy had his press conference. Lo and behold, he came up with the name that,
                    in my ignorance, I had never heard of before, Owen Lattimore. Poor Owen
                    Lattimore, he really went through a really grueling period as a result. A few
                    years later, just to complete this aspect of it, some mutual friends, some
                    friends of ours in Baltimore, called up and invited us to dinner. They said, the
                    only other guests we will have will be our other dear friends, the Owen
                    Lattimores. By this time, he had been exonerated after weathering a terrible
                    ordeal. This was a small house, and the women were in the kitchen, the host was
                    mixing drinks and here I was sitting on a sofa next to Owen Lattimore. I said,
                    “I know that you are wondering who in the world am I, and I have to tell you
                    that, when I first heard your name, I must admit that I hadn't heard of you
                    before, but I was glad it was somebody other than myself!”</p>
                <p>So that's the way things went in those days. It was very exciting to be in the
                    government, but also there were some very tense times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that Under Secretary of State John Foster
                        Dulles, going through these times, did you feel a lack of support at
                        all?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>FIERST: Definitely, and I'll tell you of one other incident that comes to mind.
                    Shortly after Dulles took over as Secretary, there was an Assistant Secretary
                    for Congressional Relations who was brought in. He was a member of Congress, a
                    Republican, I don't remember his name...later he became Republican National
                    Committee Chairman. I had not met him. I came back from lunch one day and I had
                    a phone call from this man, whom I had not met before. He said, “Can you come
                    right to my office?” At that point, McCarthy was riding high in the country and
                    he said, “Senator McCarthy wants you up there right away, before his committee.”
                    So I went in to see this man, and he very matter-of-factly said, “Go to such and
                    such a room, and we will get a car for you.” I said, “Now, wait a minute, what's
                    this all about? I have been in the Department X number of years and have never
                    had less than Top Secret clearance. I'm entitled to know under what
                    circumstances I'm being called up there. Is this an executive session, or a
                    public session?” McCarthy was having public sessions on TV. The Assistant
                    Secretary was very nice, but seemed a little embarrassed, and said, “That's a
                    fair question, I'll try to find out.” He asked his secretary to get the name of
                    a new assistant who was liaison with the Senate Government Operations Committee
                    - Jack Leahy. He called him out of the hearing and Leahy said, “McCarthy is
                    looking into the activities of the USIA.” The head of the group that puts out
                    literature was testifying about a pamphlet they had put out about the United
                    Nations and the American role in the United Nations. McCarthy asked him who had
                    reviewed his material, and under whose auspices he did this, and he mentioned my
                    name. McCarthy said, “Oh yes, he's a bad egg, get him up here right away!”</p>
                <p>I dropped everything, and went up. Luckily, I had been given the option of having
                    my security hearing under the old administration or under the new one. It was
                    due to be in a few weeks. The significance is that I had reviewed my past
                    history in preparation. A lot of these things that get blurred in your memory
                    were quite fresh in my mind as a result of my preparation. I'll give you one
                    example. When I was sworn in, before McCarthy - it was an executive session - I
                    remember saying to myself on the way up there, “...just don't be provocative
                    here, but show McCarthy you would not be a good witness to put on national
                    television.” There was one American diplomat who had more or less defected to
                    the Chinese communists at the time. I have forgotten his name. McCarthy, sitting
                    up on the raised platform as Chairman, looking down, said to me at the
                    beginning, “Tell us about your relationship with this particular person...”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it Fields, or something like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>FIERST: No, Fields was in Eastern Europe. So I said, “I don't know him, never met
                    him, never talked to him.” McCarthy said, “How come you used him as a reference
                    in your application to the State Department?” Now, if I had been on national
                    television and had been confronted that way without advance preparation, I would
                    have said that I don't remember why I did that if I did. But I knew for a fact
                    that I had not, because I had reviewed all that. So I just categorically denied
                    it, and he casually went on to something else. He had just been making it up.
                    That's the way he operated. So I ended up, about an hour and a quarter later, at
                    this executive session hearing, and nothing ever came of it afterwards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You weren't looking bad, so he didn't want to...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIERST: He didn't want to put me on national television. It was really a terrible
                    period to have gone through, because the atmosphere was such that decent people
                    were intimidated. I remember, for example, this was before the incident I just
                    mentioned, on a Friday afternoon, I had been called in by Arch Jean, who was in
                    charge of personnel for the State Department. He said, “I am calling in those
                    who are prominent on McCarthy's list. We have complete confidence in you, but
                    there is this hearing the Senate committee is going to have on Monday, when
                    McCarthy is going to be presenting his case. As you know, you're Number One, so
                    it is logical you'd be the first one that he'd come to. We're going to take a
                    strong position in defense of all those on the list, because we have checked
                    them all out, but we're advising each one to get his own lawyer.” So I called up
                    a prominent lawyer in New York, Goldthwaite Dorr, who had worked for the
                    Secretary of War, Stimson, a long time ago, but also had been brought in to
                    handle some displaced persons aspects on the Hill. He recommended that I get in
                    touch with a man I had worked with on displaced persons legislation, Senator
                    John Sherman Cooper, of Kentucky, who had just been defeated and was going with
                    a prominent law firm in Washington.</p>
                <p>So I got in touch with him immediately and he had me meet him in a hotel near
                    Union Station, and listened very sympathetically. He said, “I am just new in
                    this firm, (it was a quite prominent law firm in Washington), and I would like
                    really to be your lawyer, but I have to check it out with my new partners. So
                    let's meet tomorrow, a Sunday, at a particular time at the same place. When I
                    met with him he was so apologetic, mumbling and embarrassed. He said he had
                    taken it up with his partners. They felt that it was really too controversial
                    for him to represent somebody who had been attacked by McCarthy. But he said,
                    “I've written out something for you that I recommend that you say when, as and
                    if McCarthy attacks you publicly. I'll be glad to meet with you informally, just
                    to give you advice.” I took one look at his draft, it was on a yellow lined
                    paper and he had worked it over and over, and it epitomizes the difficulty that
                    people like us were in. What he had drafted was almost word for word the
                    statement that Alger Hiss had made, over and over and over, “I am not now, nor
                    have ever been in the Communist Party. I am a loyal American, etc...” This is
                    why I have not had a very high regard for what Alger Hiss did. Intrinsically,
                    what he did was bad, but also it poisoned the atmosphere.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It really did, I've always had this feeling about Alger
                        Hiss. He, to use an old term, he let down our side, you might say. He really
                        - he lied. And he lied at a time which discounted an awful lot of very good
                        people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I'm just trying to figure out, is there anything else you think we should cover
                    in this period?</p>
                <p>FIERST: I think I've rambled around quite a bit without any advance preparation.
                    I'm not sure if I've covered the areas you had in mind...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Part of Oral History is to catch the atmospherics. And
                        it's not just obviously the McCarthy thing, but dealing with the displaced
                        persons' time and getting ready for things at the end of the war, with the
                        United Nations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Just one last thing, then, on the United Nations. What was sort of the biggest
                    problem you had selling, you might say, as you saw to the American people about
                    the United Nations?</p>
                <p>FIERST: The biggest problem, I suppose, selling to the Congress, was the inflated
                    bureaucracy of the United Nations. The Secretary General, whoever he was,
                    whether it was Trygve Lie or Dag Hammarskjold, or his successors, is always
                    under enormous pressure from other countries to have their nationals on the
                    staff both from the point of view of influencing policy, that was certainly the
                    case on the Soviet side, and from the point of view of having good jobs. So
                    there were these enormous budgets that were projected, of which the United
                    States had to shoulder a major share, and that really poisoned the atmosphere.
                    There was a constant ideological and strategic struggle, as you know, during the
                    time of the Cold War. Sometimes it was hotter than cold in the Soviet Union. I
                    think that there developed a genuine skepticism on the good part of the American
                    public that we were losing control to third world countries that didn't
                    understand what our own security interests were. There was a lot to that. There
                    was a lot of well intentioned international liberalism about the colonies that
                    used to be in Africa, for example, being emancipated from the kind of
                    colonialism that they had been subjected to. So many of them turned out to be
                    terrible disappointments that it affected the confidence the American public had
                    in the United Nations. Anyway, they were very interesting times.</p>
                <p>In conclusion: I feel that I have just scratched the surface of my varied
                    experiences in the State Department so many long years ago. Hopefully, at least
                    I have given you a bit of the flavor of professional life in those times and
                    those places.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
