<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000333">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="interview">Interview with Horace Y. Edwards </title>
<title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
<name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for education and scholarship.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or greater.</p>
</editorialDecl>


</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
<body>
<div>
<p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History Project Information Series</p>
<p>HORACE Y. (TEX) EDWARDS</p>
<p>Interviewed by:  G. Lewis Schmidt </p>
<p>Initial interview date:  November 20, 1989</p>
<p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  This is Lew Schmidt interviewing Tex Edwards in his home in the Van Ness Apartments in Washington, DC.  The date is the 20th of November, 1989.  Tex, I'm going to ask you to start out by giving us a brief background of where you came from, what your education was, if you had experience before you came into the service, into USIA, briefly what that was, and then how it was that you came about to get started in the USIA or its predecessor agencies.  Then we'll take each one of your assignments in succession, I'd like you to discuss what you did there and, as I told you before we started, there are certain things I'd like you to cover in connection with each of your assignments.  So why don't you start out with your background.</hi>
</p>
<p>Education</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Fine, Lew.  I was born and reared in Texas.  I took my first college degree from the University of East Texas in the small town of Commerce, later did graduate work at the University of Colorado and the University of Pennsylvania.  When the war came along after Pearl Harbor, I volunteered both for the Army and for the Navy, but was turned down by both because I had been crippled for a number of years, but I thought I was doing well enough to enter.</p>
<p>Military Service in Germany</p>
<p>So since I was turned down I went into defense work for North American Aviation where I was a template inspector.  And then the following year both the Army and the Navy classified me as 1A.  So I went into the Army and then went very soon to Germany and was in the Combat Engineers.  I was one of the first to throw a Bailey bridge across the Ruhr River in Germany.  I happened to be the only one in the whole outfit that could do it without a book.</p>
<p>1948:  From Military Government to Department of State'sEducation and Cultural Relations Division at HICOG</p>
<pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
<p>When the war was over I went into the Office of Military Government.  Then representatives the State Department came by and asked if I'd like to take the Foreign Service exams and I did.  In the meantime, I had married, and when I got home my wife asked how I did on the exams.  And I said, “Oh, I'm sure I failed.” It was the most difficult exam I'd ever taken in my life, but as it turned out I hadn't failed.  I actually passed and I was in the — I believe it was called Education and Cultural Relations Division of the Department of State at the time.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you take this exam in Germany?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I took the exam in Germany and then got the results of the exam in a couple of weeks.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I see.  Were you still in the Army at that point?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, I was in the Office of Military Government at the time.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was this during the HICOG period?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Well, Lew, as you know, the Office of Military Government, or MilGov as we said, was the Office of Mil Gov (US zone of occupation), which we quickly called OMGUS.  OMGUS was replaced by HICOG and I, like many others, painlessly moved from the one to the other.  I was asked to go into Military Government before the war was over since we were already occupying part of Germany.  But I didn't want to leave my outfit at the time and said that I might consider it when the war was over.  The day after the war was over they came back to me and asked would you go into OMGUS now and I did.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were you in the Corps — were you an engineer by training in college?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, I was a mathematician.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Oh, at least you had some building experience.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Probably, at least a little in carpentry.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Well, let's get now to the point where you were in this educational and cultural part of the HICOG.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  You probably know this division was broken off so to speak from the Department of State, and many, perhaps even most of us, who were doing this type of work in the Department of State then went into USIA, which took over this responsibility.  USIA was formed at least partially by this branch of the Department of State, the Education and Cultural Relations Division.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What time was this?  When you went into the Department of State initially, what year was that?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  In '48.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  '48.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  So at that time it had just become legislatively authorized in the State Department.  It was actually USIE at that time which was the United States Information and Education Program.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, I believe so.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That's what you were in.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I'm not sure of the exact title but I think that is correct.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What were your objectives at that time in the program in Germany?  What was the kind of work that you did?</hi>
</p>
<p>The Massive Educational Exchange Program:Germans to US</p>
<pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  We had started the educational exchanges program which became a very large program under Ralph Burns who had been head of the Department of Education at Dartmouth in Hanover, New Hampshire.  We sent everyone from high school teenagers to important leaders from Germany to the United States for various periods of time.  The students went for a year.  The program included high school students and university students, of course, and then leaders in almost every walk of life, everything from public health to political leaders, professors and civil administration people.  We sent thousands actually.  We sent so many at one time that we had to charter ships from Holland to send them and to bring them back.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Now, when you were sending students I gather the majority of whom as you say went for at least an academic year.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you send those in large numbers?  And how was it handled in the United States?  Who was doing the backup for you in the US to get them located in appropriate schools?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  There were various organizations.  We worked with the Department of State and through it with the Institute of International Education, the Missouri Synod of the Lutheran Church, with the National Catholic Welfare Association and many other exchange organizations in the United States.  But our primary contacts were with the Department of State which worked with all these organizations.  The latter, in turn, had established contacts with schools all over the United States, and the students were placed very readily, all of them.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Probably would be more difficult today to get them placed.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh, I think so.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  In those numbers.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh, yes.  I think so.  Americans everywhere were very generous, very willing to help.  And it turned out to be very effective.  We had an evaluation program and we were convinced that it was a very good program at the time, exceedingly good program.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You really could see the results of their educational and cultural exposure.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh, yes.</p>
<pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  To the United States.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh, yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did they then go back to German universities when they returned and complete their education in Germany?  Or did you get a pretty good spread throughout the country of these people who had gone and then who may have returned?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  We had a fairly good spread of the people who wanted to return to the United States, but this did not become a serious problem.  We had selection committees set up all over Germany, made up of Germans and the American from the exchanges program.  Sometimes some other important American was on the committee, but the committees were primarily composed of Germans in positions of leadership, not just in the educational field but also in politics and in city administration.  When the people came back, we didn't have to encourage them to talk about their stay in the United States.  They were almost invariably eager to talk about it, to tell the rest of the Germans about it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you ever encounter any adverse reactions from some of the students?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Occasionally.  Yes, occasionally we did.  There were one or two cases that were unfortunate and I think probably it was due to a misunderstanding on both sides where the youngsters, the high school students were — they thought, being used as free labor on some of the farms, but it was a very unusual thing.  But the vast majority, I would say 98 or 99 percent of the high school exchange program was very successful.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were all the high school students placed in American homes?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, all in American homes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How about the university students?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  University students also were placed in American homes.  The university students offered a different problem.  They had to sign a statement saying they would come home after being over here for one year, but they weren't always ready to go back home.  In some instances they could get an extension for another year, and very frequently when they got back to Germany they couldn't wait.  They did everything within their power to come back to the United States.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Of course, Germany was in still pretty much of a shambles at that time.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh, yes.  The currency reform wasn't until July of 1948 and even after that it took the Germans quite a while to get back to where they had a viable home life.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Times have changed slightly.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, I should think they have.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you have anything to do with the Amerika Hauser?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.  Yes, of course.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That came under your jurisdiction.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Also.  Yes.  I was involved with the Amerika Haus both in Bremen and in Hamburg where it was under my supervision.  Then we left Hamburg and were transferred to Bonn where I became Deputy Chief of the Exchanges Program for Germany and that was enough to keep one busy.  You didn't have time to become involved in anything else.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  At what stage did the German exchange program begin to phase down a little bit?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I was in Germany for ten years — I left Germany towards the end of 1954 and the number of exchangees per year had been reduced considerably by that time.  It continued but then I lost contact with it.  Even the last few months that I was in Germany I wasn't involved with the exchanges program because I was asked to take over from Tom Tuch to take charge of the first international exhibit on peaceful uses of atomic energy in Geneva.  This was in '54.  So I left the exchanges program a few months actually before I left Germany.  But it had decreased considerably by that time.  I don't know what it's doing, whether it's still going on today or not.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I suppose it's going on but in a greatly reduced size.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I should think so.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Initially, there were two or three different levels in the program though as there were then, both high school and university as well as leader grants.  Nowadays, high school exchanges are mainly outside the Agency.  The collegiate level was and is still within the agency, as is the leader type of Exchange.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  In the Amerika Haus program what did you do in that connection?  What were you running?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  May I make one statement before that?  Speaking about the numbers that were sent over to the United States, they tried in various places to form groups of those people who had been in the United States and they found that it was very difficult because that was about the only thing that they had in common, that they had been in the United States.  The high school students and the leaders and the politicians had very little in common other than that.  But there got to be so many who had been in the United States that in joking there was a saying going around that we ought to have a club of “those who have not been in the United States.”</p>
<p>Nature and Value of Amerika Hauser Program in Germany</p>
<p>Well, the Amerika Haus was, I suppose, primarily founded we said for the teaching of the English language, but also to bring in all sorts of programs about the United States, to bring in speakers and to have exhibits about the United States; things to give a favorable impression of life in the United States, what we do, what we did, and to help counteract perhaps some of the unfavorable information that had been disseminated about the United States over there.</p>
<p>They had governing committees, some of which were made up almost entirely of Americans.  If we are going to say “Amerika Haus” then correctly we should use the German plural “Amerika Hauser” also.  If my memory served me, we always used the German words.  Some of the Amerika Hauser were controlled almost completely by the Germans, and as a matter of fact later were turned over to the Germans themselves to run and eventually finance.  They had libraries but not extensive ones like some of our regular libraries abroad such as the one in Mexico for example where we had a real library.  They were places to go to gain information about the United States in almost every aspect of life, whether it was politics, the fine arts, American homes or business in the United States.  The works were usually carefully selected.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  To what extent did you find the Germans using the libraries, especially in the early days?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  In the early days they used them a lot because so many of their libraries had either been destroyed or else they had been carried off for safekeeping and also the German libraries were so full of Nazi propaganda and so out of date that they were of little value.  I heard that some valuable books were taken into salt mines in Germany just like a lot of the fine art works to protect them from the bombs.  And in the early days even though our libraries weren't very good, they certainly had information about the United States that was never available in any of the German libraries.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did most of the Germans and even the young people read English?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh, a great many of them.  Oh, yes.  A great many of them.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That's rather interesting.  There must have been pretty extensive instruction of English in the schools.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  There was.  We were surprised at the number of high school students who came in, 15 years old, who spoke very good English.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  On the matter of speakers, did you find the Germans were responding pretty extensively to your lecture programs, seminar programs?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, they were.  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were you using essentially Germans?  Or were you using a lot of Americans who were brought over on exchange arrangements?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  We used both, but we felt the Germans themselves, and I suppose this is a natural reaction, were more likely to be completely believed about everything that they said to their fellow countrymen than were the American speakers.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were you able to use those who had been exchangees to the United States extensively in the program?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, we did.  We used them a lot.  They were always not just willing, but eager to talk, and we used them a great deal.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  To what extent would you say that German professors went to the United States on these exchange programs and then were sent back to their own universities?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  They had no trouble getting back into their own universities.  The problem was that we had to agree on how much time would be considered worthwhile and at the beginning we wanted them to stay longer than the German professors could stay.  They couldn't stay three months in the United States for example.  They just couldn't do it.  So we didn't get a great many German professors in the beginning.  We had to shorten the period of time we expected them to stay, but then I knew of no cases where they had any problem coming back into their own universities after they got back.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  At a later date did you reach a point where you could send them on total sabbatical or one year exchange?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I can't remember many of those.  We did have Americans coming over sometimes for one year exchange.  We had a few, yes.  We had a few Germans I know who came to the United States for a year, but the problem in each case was a financial problem.  The German universities did not have the money to pay their professors when they were absent and even if they had had the money the salaries which they were getting in Germany in those days would not have been sufficient to keep them going in the United States.  Today, I don't know.  It might be a different thing.  American salaries might not keep the Americans going over there.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  So you were in Germany then for a total of about ten years.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Is there anything else you would like to say about the German program before we go on to the next assignment?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I don't believe so, no.  You'll probably have a lot of people talking about the exchanges program, how it worked.</p>
<p>The Visiting American Leaders Program</p>
<pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
<p>I think I would like to touch upon one more aspect of the program.  In the beginning of that part of the program which brought American experts or leaders to Germany, the Department of State almost invariably did an excellent job of sending us good people in the fields in which they were requested.  But as word spread in the United States that this was a pretty good deal — a free trip to Europe plus extra money — the Department began to get political pressure from congressmen and administration officials who wanted to use the program to pay off political debts.  The Department and in turn we in the field were caught trying to make the best of a bad deal.  I cite an example; tragic if you were involved, comical if you weren't.</p>
<p>A Startling Anecdote:One Unfortunate “Leader” Performance</p>
<p>Mildred Allport was our Women's Affairs Officer.  The wisdom of choosing that sort of title, and especially in Germany in those days, lends itself to debate.  However, Mildred was an intelligent and energetic woman, always impeccably dressed, who entertained well and knew her way around.  One day Mildred received a telegram saying that Mrs. Logan, of the Massachusetts Logan Airport family, would arrive at Frankfurt by train on such and such a day and, in essence, do something with her for two weeks.  The Department had failed to say that Mrs. Logan dearly loved her alcohol, was, in fact, an alcoholic.</p>
<p>The train arrived and Mildred waited until all passengers appeared to be off the train, but saw no sign of Mrs. Logan.  I don't know what German porters use today for moving luggage, but in those days they used large, flat carts about five or six feet long upon which they could stack a great amount of luggage.  Mildred said she was about to leave the train station as a porter pulled up with a cart loaded with luggage and a well-dressed woman lying flat on her back — sprawled is a better word — atop it all.  Mrs. Logan.</p>
<p>A few days later Mrs. Logan was scheduled to speak at the Amerika Haus in Hamburg; her subject: “American Women in Politics.” Hamburg was the largest city in West Germany and, along with Bremen, possibly the most progressive and international in outlook, due in part, probably, to their many years as members of the Hanseatic League.  It was easy, therefore, to fill the Amerika Haus with interested, educated German women.  Mildred and Mrs. Logan were seated at a library table, meaning that the audience had a full view of the feet and legs.  I noticed that Mrs. Logan had on lovely high-heeled shoes and a dress too short for the occasion.  I also noticed that she had had one too many drinks before she arrived.  Mildred arose, showing no outward sign of worry or misgivings and told how Mrs. Logan had been active in politics, particularly in campaigns and said, “And now I am pleased to present to you Mrs. Logan who will speak to you about women in politics in America.”</p>
<pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
<p>Mrs. Logan had been sitting there apparently in a daze.  A wisp of hair had fallen down over one eye.  She blew at it once out of the corner of her mouth and then ignored it.  When Mildred said she was now on stage she came to life.  Her ankles suddenly had no bones and collapsed, turning her feet on the sides with the shoe heels toward each other.  This may have been what pulled her legs farther apart.  She leaned forward, placing one elbow on the table and chin in hand she said, “Girls, it's a rat race!”</p>
<p>1954:  The Atoms For Peace Exhibit</p>
<p>I next took over the direction of our atomic energy exhibit from Tom Tuch when he was, I believe, going back to the States.  I took it first on practice runs in Dusseldorf and then Vienna getting ready for the big exhibit in Geneva at the time of the First International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy.  We had let the Germans build the exhibit for us with materials coming from the United States.  We had some excellent Germans working for us and I picked up some more wonderful workers in Vienna, all of whom were either physicists or advanced students of physics.  So, by the time we got to Geneva we had a superb, well-trained staff and an excellent exhibit.  There were many exhibits there, some from the largest commercial firms in the United States and Europe.  But there was no exhibit better and I don't believe any as good as the USIA exhibit, and it made my job so much more rewarding to have such a well trained and enthusiastic staff.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I think that was probably one of our two or three prime exhibits around the world.  Tom, of course, Tom Tuch when he went back from Germany to the States for a year or so was in the exhibit program in a small group in the agency.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  He sort of managed this thing on a worldwide basis.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  He came out and spent about two or three months with us in the summer and early fall of 1955 when we were preparing to put on the Atoms For Peace exhibit in Tokyo.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Where it was an absolute smash.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  Was it?  Yes, I can believe it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Subsequently it toured all over Japan — 15 different cities.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Well, it was certainly a tremendous success in Geneva.  We had more visitors to our exhibit than any in this tremendous exhibit hall in Geneva.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was it subsequently put on in Germany?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  It began in Germany, in 1954.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I see, first.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, Tom had it in Germany.  I don't know how many places.  And then I had it in Germany only at Hamburg and Dusseldorf and then in Vienna.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Then you took it from Vienna —</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, from Vienna to Geneva.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Essentially the same exhibit.  I suppose you kept getting some additions or changes as you went along.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Right, a few.  And they were all important practice runs for the really big show in Geneva, and by that time we were well prepared for it.  All the people were really very well prepared.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Of course, it was a new thing at that time.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh, they were all excited.  Everyone was excited about it.  I learned physics terminology in German that I didn't even know in English.  I had to go look and see what it meant in English.  Some of the terminology was new in both languages.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  When you left Germany did you come back to the States for assignment in Rome?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  No.  Do you remember how they used to pass out all these forms regularly at the end of the year or every two or three years about what would you like your next assignment to be?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Yes.</hi>
</p>
<p>1955:  Assignment to Mexico</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I always put down Mexico.  For years I put down Mexico, Mexico, Mexico.  I just thought I'll never get to Mexico but I'll just keep putting it down anyway.  Then I got notice I was transferred to Mexico.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Directly from Germany?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  From Germany.  Well, we came to the States for home leave only and then went to Mexico.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  So that's where I first met you down there.  Was Jack McDermott the PAO?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Jack McDermott was the PAO?  No, he wasn't the PAO when I got there.  It was Andy Anderson.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Oh, yes.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  You remember him?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I know Andy.  I knew him.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Fine, fine person.  He was wonderful.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And he was replaced by McDermott.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  By McDermott, right.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And Earl Wilson was the Deputy.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  Right, that's right.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And you were what, the Cultural Attach�?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I was the Deputy Cultural Attach�.  We had five Cultural Officers</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Jake Canter?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, Allen Hayden was Cultural Attach� when I went there, then Jake Canter.  But then we had five Cultural Affairs Officers in Mexico City including Mauda Sandvig, Director of the large Benjamin Franklin Library, an excellent library.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Yes, I know.  They had one of the largest in the world.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, and at exam time the university students, Mexican university students, couldn't all find chairs, so they sat all over the floor.  You had to walk carefully and step over bodies, but literally.  I would go in there in the evening during university exam times and you had to step over bodies all through the library.  The desire to work seemed contagious.  I think they enjoyed it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  The students were using your library as a cram course.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  The library, yes, they were.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How about their command of English?  Were most of your books by that time in Spanish?  Or were there large numbers in English?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, most of them were in English.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  They had enough English so they could make use of them.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  At least they could read them, yes.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What would you think was your single greatest success in the cultural field in Mexico?  Was there any highlight of your tour there that you think is particularly outstanding?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I got to be very close to a lot of the people in the art world and in the education world in Mexico.  And in the education world I'd like to say I placed particular emphasis on archeology because there it is so important.  Archeology and anthropology were so important in Mexico then and are perhaps even more so today.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Yes, perhaps even more so now.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, and Mexico certainly has the best archeological museum that I have ever seen.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That was pretty badly damaged, I understand, during the quake in '85.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Not so badly.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Someone told me it was quite badly damaged.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, I just saw it about three weeks ago.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Oh, I heard it's been well restored.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, it has and additions have been added since the last time I saw it which was about six years ago, but I still have contacts after all these years.  We left Mexico at the end of 1960 and I still have contacts in the education and art world in Mexico today, and those two fields are more important to the average Mexican citizen than they are to the average American, much more important to them.</p>
<p>Attitude of Mexicans Towards Americans:1950s and Today</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What did you sense among the Mexicans about their attitude toward the United States?  I think in later times it's become rather — I won't say vitriolic, but it's at least acrid on occasion.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  It was on occasion then also, but I think not so much as it is now.  But they have a contradictory view about the United States actually.  I would say it's almost a love/hate relationship.  They admire the United States in so many ways and yet they feel that the United States has always looked down upon them, that it has never treated Mexico as an equal as it has so many other nations in the world.  Mexico is an extremely proud nation.  They are overly proud sometimes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And they're overly sensitive too.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, they're very, very sensitive about Mexico, extremely sensitive about Mexico and are very much aware of some of the uncomplimentary jokes or sayings in the United States about their country.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  There is of course a terrible divergence between the highly wealthy and the poor in Mexico.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Extremely.</p>
<p>The Class Separations In Mexico</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How do you feel to the extent the Mexicans had a middle class at the time you were there and the extent to which — well, let me rephrase my question.  This is a triple headed question.  Did the middle class really have a great deal to say in the higher reaches of the art and archeological world, the educational world and the business and governmental world?  And what was the relationship between the very poor, the middle class and the extremely wealthy in Mexico?  Was it just a complete separation, any mix at all, standoff?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, there's a complete separation between the very poor and the wealthy, even between the upper middle class and the very poor.  The latter were used as the servant class, never even considered to be those with whom they would have social intercourse.  A great deal of that is true today.  The middle class had a lot of influence in the field of education and a lot of influence in the cultural field.  I would say the middle class was very important in the field of anthropology and archeology.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How about the arts and the performing arts?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  And very important in the arts and the performing arts, very important in that field.  They did not have the same influence in government.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I suppose from what you say then that it was quite possible for perhaps not the extremely poverty stricken people but nevertheless the lower middle class to be upwardly mobile and in those fields in which the upper middle class was rather prominent it was possible to come from lower levels and achieve a degree of fame.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, there was a possibility there for upward mobility, but more limited than it is in the United States.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was there any noticeable effort by those who had it made already to put a few obstacles in the way of those who were upwardly mobile?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Well, I would say perhaps no more so than here.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Always looking out for your own.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, looking out for your own interests first.  Yes, very much so.  In Mexico, though, the upper class and the upper middle class fed on the humor of the lower class.  It's the lower class of Mexico that has the most delightful and fantastic, imaginative sense of humor that I've ever encountered, and it always comes from the bottom up.  It percolates to the top.  The upper classes feed upon it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was there any possibility at all that the lower classes would ascend to higher levels in Mexico?  Did any of them make it?  Or was that a very rare occasion?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, some of them make it.  After all, you had some presidents who came from the lower class in Mexico.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And then became the upper class.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Right, and then became the upper class.  Oh, the possibility is definitely there, but I'd say it's not as common a theme as it is in the United States.  Your class divisions are sharper there than they are here.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was it possible to — I guess what I'm asking is were your efforts in Mexico designed primarily to present the United States in a favorable way and to exchange people with the United States so as to add to the Mexican experience in that area?  Or did you have other thematic informational approaches which would not necessarily have been your bailiwick but another element of USIA?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Well, we soft peddled what was important to us and tried to do it without being blatant about it.  Mexico has not been really a democratic nation.  It has been a more or less authoritarian democracy.</p>
<p>The Change in the Power of Mexico's NationalRevolutionary Party (PRI)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Democratic authoritarian.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Or democratic authoritarian because of the National Revolutionary Party.  The PRI, as it's called, has always been and is still the party that decides who's going to be president of Mexico.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  It may be changing.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  The last election seems to have changed that considerably, but they always spoke of who's going to be the next president as a “tapado,” the one who's covered up.  So you always knew who was going to be the next president of Mexico as soon as the PRI mentioned his name, you knew he was going to be the next president.  That, I think, is no longer true and I would say by the time Salinas has finished his term, I believe the PRI will not be able to say decidedly who is going to be the next president of Mexico before the votes come in.</p>
<p>The Mexican Political Left Wing is InfluentialBut Should Never Be Considered Communist</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was there a substantial left wing political element in Mexico in your time?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I think their force, their power, was greater than their numbers.  I don't think the numbers were great, but they had a noticeable voice in all of things.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  In this last election I note that the left wing candidate, whose name escapes me at the moment, polled a very high percentage in the vote.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, those are not, however, real communists.  You may be talking about Cuatehmoc.  Those who are leftists I think we should keep in mind they are not necessarily communists.  Many of them are not communists at all.  So we can't equate leftism in Mexico with communism.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  There's been too much attempt to do that in the United States.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, of course.  Yes, yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Well, how long were you in Mexico then?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Six years.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Six years?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, going around with the ambassador helping him sing “Cielito Linda.”</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  One of your ambassadors while you were there was Bob Hill.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, he is the one who loved “Cielito Linda.”</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  He was always running for Congress while he was Ambassador to Mexico.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Right.  He entered the bull ring also while he was in Mexico.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  He what?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  He entered the bull ring.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  He did?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  He got into skin diving when he was ambassador to one of the Central American countries.  I've forgotten which one.  Either El Salvador or Costa Rica.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Costa Rica I believe.  Yes, I believe it was Costa Rica.  I heard about that.</p>
<p>Mexico in the 1950s Was a Delightful Post.Today, Air Pollution Has Degraded Mexico City</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  So, do you have anything else you want to say about Mexico now before we go on?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Nothing except that I thoroughly enjoyed my six years in Mexico.  We enjoyed it.  My wife and my children all got into just everything, you know.  We got into the life of the country.  I loved the variety of civilizations that you have in Mexico and I thoroughly loved my tour there.  Mexico City has changed completely.  I used to go to the office every morning.  The first thing I did was go and look out the window and I could see those two lovely mountains, Papocatepetl and Ixtacihuatl.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Now you can't see the buildings across the street.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Now you can't see very much and they say it's been years since they've been able to see the mountains.  While I was in Mexico just recently it came out in one of the principal newspapers that Mexico City is now the most polluted city in the world.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That's what I understand.  It's supposed to have about 18 million people.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  The closest they can come is between 18 and 20 million.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Which I guess makes it the largest city in the world.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I don't know of any city that's larger, no.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  People tell me, I haven't been there since 1972, and I understand the smog is just terrible.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  It has grown unbelievably.  A friend of mine and I wanted to see a beautiful church out in the little village of Tepotzotlan to the northwest of Mexico City.  The church is a superb example of Churrigueresque architecture and has the most beautiful chapel that I probably have ever seen.  This used to be a nice drive out through the country.  Now you drive out of Mexico City on the super highways and as far as you can see up the hillsides on either side of the highway all the trees have been cut down and for miles and miles all one can see are little houses, little shacks right up against each other with no space, nothing, just shack after shack after shack.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  No running water and no sanitary facilities.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  It's very sad.  Pollution is also in the rivers and none of the streams are safe, not only not for drinking, they're not even safe to bathe in or to wade in.  That's very sad.  It was such a lovely place.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And where did you go from Mexico?</hi>
</p>
<p>1960:  A Washington Tour. Then to Uruguay as PAO</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I came back to the United States for my first and only tour in the Agency as Cultural Officer for Latin America, after which I went to Montevideo, Uruguay as PAO.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were you there during the Tupamaros troubles?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I was there when it started and I saw what was coming on and could have stayed for another tour but my children at that time were big enough that they sort of worried me.  One of them was just about ready for college and they were so completely Uruguayan that I was afraid that they would get involved, since some of their companions were involved.  So I said no thank you.  I wanted to leave.  I had a chance to go to Spain.  So I left after three years down there.  But the tour in Uruguay was wonderful.  People there were so open, unlike so many other cultures.  More like the Americans than any place where I've ever served.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  They have been a pretty democratic country I think.  Did you observe that they were falling into a dictatorship?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  It's entire history had been democratic.  It's the only place in South America that had never had anything except a democratic government.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did they fall into more or less autocratic and authoritarian ways in order to combat the terrorism?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  They made the mistake of turning over to the Army the responsibility of combating the terrorism.  The Army grew stronger and stronger and decided it liked what it had.  It liked the power and so it kept it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I really didn't follow Montevideo very much after I left my concern with Latin America, how long did the Army control things there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Well, I was already in Spain when the coup took place.  Let's see, I went to Spain at the end of '67 and I suppose the Army took over the following year, if my memory serves me right, and it lasted until about a little over a year ago.  So you might say 20 years, roughly 20 years, and the Army is still in control even though they recently permitted elections.  They had elections with the understanding that a civilian government could not do anything to try to judge any of the people in the Army who had been responsible for all of the deaths and the kidnappings.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  As in Argentina.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Right, except that the Argentines, you see, did do something about theirs.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  The most recent president has pardoned them all.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, that's right.  But Uruguay is still under control of the Army.  They can never do anything, take any action against them at all.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What kind of a program were you running in Uruguay?</hi>
</p>
<p>Uruguay's High Educational and Developmental LevelPermitted USIS Efforts to be Productive</p>
<pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  We had a large force of locals working for us.  The Uruguayans are a very highly educated people.  They have a high level of medicine, high level of public health.  It's not one of the places where you go and say, where can we drink the water?  Here, any place you drink it, anywhere in the world you go in Uruguay.  We had some very good employees there.We had excellent contacts with all the information services in Uruguay, and Uruguay had more newspapers per capita and more radio stations per capita and TV stations than any nation in the world.  And we had excellent contact with all of those, very good working relationships with them.  The co-director of one of the important newspapers there became a very good friend of mine and later became president of Uruguay.  He was also a good friend of two or three other people in USIA there at the time.</p>
<p>USIS Originated Uruguay's Equivalent of the Former American Huntley/Brinkley Show —
A Great Success</p>
<p>One of the best programs we had in the information field there was the program that was modeled more or less on the old Huntley/Brinkley show here in the United States.  This was on TV, and Frank Chiancone was the Press Officer at the time.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Could you spell that name?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  C-H-I-A-N-C-O-N-E.  Frank got two of the best known announcers in Uruguay to be on this news program.  They were very good and it soon became the most popular news program in Uruguay.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were these people who had previously been personalities in television?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh, yes, these were people who had already been stars, one of whom had been our regular employee for a long time, and the other one was on contract and Frank put the two of them together on this well-planned program.  It was a great success.</p>
<p>The Meeting of Western Hemisphere Presidents atPunta del Este — Lyndon Johnson's Green Grass</p>
<p>The other occasion, probably the most important single incident during my tour there was the meeting of the presidents of the western hemisphere at Punta del Este with Lyndon Johnson coming down.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How did Lyndon perform by the way?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Beautifully, beautifully.</p>
<pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That's one of the occasions when he did.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, he turned on the charm for the other presidents.  In preparing for the conference some funny things happened.  For example, we were told that President Johnson liked green grass and it was winter-time down there you see.  It was held along in July, I believe.  I don't remember the date, but it was winter-time in South America.  So the Ambassador told the Agricultural Attach�, okay, you find us some, you know, plant some grass.  Be sure we have some green grass on the lawn down there.  But the Attach� said he couldn't plant green grass down there at this time and have it ready for the meeting.  So the Ambassador said, “Well, you know what they said.  The President wants green grass.” So the Attach� found a wealthy Argentine family that had a lawn that stayed green all winter long and he bought the lawn from them.  He bought the lawn had it cut in strips, rolled it up, and took it over and put it on the lawn of the house where Lyndon Johnson would be staying.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Lasted long enough for the conference.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  It lasted long enough for the conference.  It may have lasted even longer than that, I don't know.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What Lyndon wants, Lyndon gets.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  What Lyndon wants, Lyndon gets.  And they also said, We understand that Lady Bird likes Dove soap.  Okay, will you see to it that we have Dove soap there?  Well, is Mrs. Johnson going to come down with him?  We don't know, but we can't wait until the last moment to find out.  We want Dove soap.  So sure enough we had a whole case of Dove soap brought down there and Mrs. Johnson didn't appear.  Things like that, you know, went on.</p>
<p>We stayed up all night long at the end of the conference because we had made the mistake of preparing for our President a book with photos of the people there and things that were said and pictures of all the conference and it was covered with cowhide, not just the hide but with the hair on it.  This particular one I think was brown with white spots on it, very pretty, and we made that for our ambassador to give to President Johnson.  USIA made it.  Well, the Ambassador liked it so well we had to stay up all night long and prepare them for the presidents of all the other countries represented there.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I went through something like that too.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  We were so sorry we had made one in the first place.  First of all, we had stayed up late every night.  You know how it is when you have something like that where the newspeople from all over the world are there and you certainly would stay up for LBJ.  And so you don't get any sleep.  But that night we didn't even pretend to go to sleep.  We worked all day long, all night long, all day the next day.  And we didn't get paid for it.  I didn't expect it for the Americans, but the Ambassador wouldn't let us pay overtime to the Uruguayans.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  But did you produce the books?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  We produced the books.  We produced the books.  But nobody, not even the locals could get any overtime for it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  No, I know.  The White House never pays for anything if they can avoid it.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No.  We could have paid the Uruguayans from our own funds but the Ambassador wouldn't let us.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Your allotment in those days was probably pretty small anyway.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Well, it was pretty small but we had enough to pay, but he wouldn't let us.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Who was your predecessor?  Was that by any chance Hal Urist?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, Graves, Lem Graves.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  So your predecessor was Lem Graves.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.  I got there about three or four days before he left.  He was very helpful.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Yes, he was a very nice man.  He subsequently died of cancer.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, I know.  We moved into the house that he had lived in.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  There was an Ed Purcell who served down there.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  Ed had also just left before I got there.  I knew him but he had left.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  He had a succession of children.  So that finally when he left I think he had either 11 or 12.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Thirteen.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Thirteen!</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I believe so, but I'm not sure.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Well, do you have other comments that you want to make about the Uruguayan experience?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, I don't think so except that it was such a delightful experience for all of us.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you have pretty good connections with the University there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  The university was a little bit difficult.  I had good connections with some of the people at the university.  But there was quite a leftist group in the university in Uruguay at that time.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Quite prevalent in Latin America.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I was going to ask did you find any antipathy due to the leftist influence in the country?  Did you find an antipathy towards America there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, none.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You didn't.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Not even among the leftists?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, we never encountered anything unpleasant at all while we were there.</p>
<p>Late 1977 — Barcelona, Spain</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Well, then you went to Spain from there.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Right.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You went to Barcelona.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Barcelona, right.  I went to Barcelona at the end of 1967 and had a very difficult time finding housing there because although Spain was having economic problems at the time, housing as such was in short supply.  And to find the kind of home that one would want a PAO to have where he can do some entertaining was almost impossible.  The prices were so far above agency allowances that it was absolutely out of the question.  So we stayed in a hotel for three months trying to find a place to live in Barcelona.  And I finally sent a message to the agency saying, look, to live within our allowance we will have to move at least 15 miles out into the country to find a decent house but I certainly would not be able to do any entertaining at all.  It would be difficult to participate in the events that take place within the city.  Or else if I find one in the city the Agency's going to have to pay for it.  And bless their hearts, they came right back with a telegram and said “Get a place in the city.  The Agency will pay for it.”</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Well, that's unusual.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, I wouldn't have dared do it except that at the end of three months I was absolutely desperate.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you find a nice place?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, it was very nice.  We had a nice apartment.  A house was beyond thinking about.  There were houses for rent, but they were beyond the pale in those days, in '67.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  The Caudillo [Francisco Franco] still was alive at that time.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh, yes.  Oh, yes.  Very much so.</p>
<pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
<p>In Franco Spain USIS Programs Were Limited Except In The Binational Center, Where Spanish Government Did Not Interfere</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What kind of a program could you put on in a country that was as strictly controlled as Spain?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  You had to be very, very careful.  There was little that you could say about a democratic form of government or political parties or anything like that, very little you could say.  I finally had a good relationship with the principal newspaper in Barcelona, La Vanguardia, which was actually at that time the most important newspaper in all of Spain.  And we did get some material in there that obliquely talked about elections and this sort of thing.  But you couldn't get a program on to TV or the radio.  We did, however, have good programs in the binational center.  And Barcelona had the largest binational center in Europe and it may well still be.  We had a very good board of directors composed primarily of Spaniards, but we had two good Americans on the board and some Spaniards that were very well known.  I mean, very well known not just in Barcelona but one or two internationally.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What kind of programs could you put on?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  At the binational center we could put on anything we wanted to because it was considered “American territory.” We had lecturers.  We had exhibits of all forms, and some good entertainment programs.  We had a big building, not just one floor, but a seven-story building in Barcelona.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You used the whole building?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  We used all the building except a couple of floors which were used by the Phillips-Andover-Exeter program abroad.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were you ever watched carefully by Franco police?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I don't think so.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  At your centers.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, no.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  They weren't worried that you were going to do something that was out of line.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, the police were interested in watching the programs.  That's true.  We had a program of Hawaiian dancers there one year and we had to hire the police to keep the crowds away.  After the first night word spread about them, and there were people lined up all the way around the block.  We had to have police protection to keep the people out, to keep them from just jamming the building.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  There are limits to the number of performances in the evening a Hawaiian dance group can put on.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, I know.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How long did they stay?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  They were only there for three nights and the first night it was packed and they had to have tickets.  It was free but you had to have a ticket.  Well, the second and third night people came who didn't have ticket because they couldn't get them and they'd heard about them, how good they were.  There had been a couple of photos in the newspaper the next day.  And probably a thousand came without tickets and wanted to go in and see them anyway.  It was pretty awful.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  So you had to turn them away?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh, we had to turn a lot of them away, the police did, yes.  It was almost a mob scene.  It was a frightening experience.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you ever have programs in the center with lectures dealing with controversial subjects?  Or did you stick pretty close to something you knew would be within the limits of what the government would permit?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  We really had no problem with that.  I don't remember any problem at all with anything except this particular program where the crowds wanted in so badly that it became a frightening thing and we had to call up and they sent a lot of police to help protect us.  But we had no problems with our lectures, or with our exhibits, none.  But we did practice some discretion.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You used American teachers to some extent?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh yes.  It was the only Binational Center program that I knew of where every teacher had a degree in teaching of English as a foreign language.  They were all Americans.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What was the enrollment basically would you say?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  The last I heard we had an enrollment there of a little over 2,000.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Not just a continuing enrollment.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I'm talking about a constant enrollment.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were your teachers native speakers, native Americans?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh, yes.  They were native Americans.  Now, we had some programs in other parts of Spain where the teachers were not all native Americans, but in the Binational Center in Barcelona the teachers were all native Americans with degrees in the teaching of English as a foreign language.</p>
<p>1969:  New Ambassador Transfers Edwards fromBarcelona to Madrid as Country CAO</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How long were you in Barcelona?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I was in Barcelona for two years and then Bob Hill, Robert C. Hill became our Ambassador.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Who was that?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Bob Hill.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Oh, Bob Hill.  That's right.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  He did move to Spain, didn't he?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, and dragged me kicking and screaming to Madrid.  Well, not that I didn't like Madrid but I had become so fond of Barcelona by that time that I didn't really want to leave.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I'm interested because Bob Hill didn't like Jake Canter.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  When you were in Mexico, Jake was Cultural Affairs Officer, and Hill was Ambassador.  And it fell to me to tell Jake that he had to move because the Ambassador didn't want him.  It was a terribly embarrassing experience.  Jake went from there to be CAO in Spain.  That must have been in the late ''50s, probably around '58 or '59, couldn't have been later than '59 because I went to the War College at that time.  Wasn't he in Spain as CAO when you were there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No.  Jake was in Mexico as CAO for a while and after he was removed to Spain, he was followed by Dulaney Terret.  Ambassador Hill couldn't stand either of them.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  It would have been ironic if Bob Hill had come there to find Jake as CAO again.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  In Madrid.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Yes, I mean in Madrid.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  We got off a little on the Bob Hill versus Jake Canter bit, but what was your position when you were called up from Barcelona to go to Madrid?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  I went to Madrid as CAO.  It was very nice but Madrid was a little bit more difficult to make contacts than Barcelona was.  But I'd also had the problem in Madrid that my wife had just died and two of my children were still with me and we had to find a place to live in Madrid.  But the people were so very, very nice in helping us.  For example, we'd stop at an apartment house, a large apartment house, and one for example, I remember the doorman there said, “Well, no, we don't have a thing here.  But there is a very nice building down in the next block and you tell the doorman” — and then he said, “No.  Don't.  I'll go with you.” And so he accompanied us all the way down the block and introduced us to the doorman at the next place.  You would have insulted him had you offered him a tip.  It was that sort of niceness in those days that was so attractive about the Spaniards.</p>
<p>Edwards Gains Help of Ambassador Hill in Preventing A Spanish Government Rigged Trial of Students That Would Have Had World Wide Repercussions</p>
<p>My stay in Madrid was rather uneventful.  I remember one thing; there were some University student problems, some student unrest.  I did meet with some of the students in Madrid a few times and found out about some of the protests that might have been planned and so on.  The Spanish government at the time was planning to arrest and bring to trial some students, four students, who the Government claimed had been responsible for the death of a Spanish guard.  I think, but I'm not sure, that it was one of the guards in one of the provinces.  I don't know how the person was killed, but they had no evidence whatsoever that these students had been responsible.  The Franco Government just wanted someone to punish.</p>
<p>I went to Ambassador Hill, Bob Hill, because he was going to the States the next day.  I called him at night and said, “I have to see you before you leave in the morning.” And he said, “All right.  Come over right now.” So I went over and said, “I know what is being planned.  You know that these four students are going to be arrested by the Spanish government and tried, and of course convicted.  You will have access to people in the United States, both the Spanish Embassy and the American authorities.  You will know, they will know, how this will all appear in the papers of the United States and every paper in the United States and Europe will carry it.  There is going to be a tremendous protest meeting in Spain.  There's going to be students marching all over Spain in every university in this country if the Spanish government goes through with all of this and you may be able to put a stop to it because you have very close contact with the people now who are influential in the Spanish government.” I said, “I haven't said a word to anybody else about this.” And he said, “Well, thank you very much.”</p>
<pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
<p>I knew that he had very close contacts with pro-Franco people.  So sure enough it didn't happen.  And he came back from the States in about three or four days and at a big meeting of every American in the Embassy.  He said something to the effect that there are things that go on here that you may not know about, but there are important things that — and he mentioned my name, for example, something that Tex and I know about that the rest of you don't.  So there are a lot of things that go on and that's all he said about it.  But he had stopped it.  He had stopped what surely would have been a tragic confrontation between students and Franco forces.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Well, I think that can be a great achievement on your record?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Well, it was because it stopped a lot of young people, I know, a lot of young people from being seriously hurt and many surely killed in Spain.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Oh, yes.  When they put on those protests under the Franco regime their lives were in danger, even the lives of family and friends.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I knew professors who were taken out of their classes for no known reason and taken out into the country where they could not be in contact with even a telephone.  They weren't put to death the ones that I knew of, but they were completely isolated.  Their families didn't know where they were and some of them were gone for as long as six or eight or nine months at a time and the families didn't know whether they were dead or alive.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  No.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  And this was evidently for just something that they may have said in a classroom.  My son had a very good friend named Carlos who wasn't even in protest, he was getting out of class at the University of Barcelona, was walking through just a crowd of young students who had gathered on the sidewalk.  Carlos was just trying to get through them, and Spanish guards came up on horses, rode right through them, and beat him over the head until he was unconscious.  He was in the hospital for about two weeks and then they put him in confinement and never told him, never told his family what the charges were.  He was as innocent as you or I.  He was just trying to get through a crowd to get home.  It ruined his life.  They kept him for two years with no charges.  He was a recluse for over two years and then entered training to become a priest.  So I know that what Ambassador Hill did could have saved untold suffering in Spain.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I'm sure!</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  To say nothing of the four young men who were to be tried who, for all anyone knew, were innocent.  They had just picked out some people to be tried for the thing.  Other than that there weren't too many things that were of special mention in Madrid.  It was a difficult period.  And of course, very soon after I left Franco died and it was all over with.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You left in what year now?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I left late in '71.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Where did you go then?</hi>
</p>
<p>1971:  Back to Washington Until 1974 Retirement</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  I came back to the Agency in '71 and then stayed there until I retired.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You retired when?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  At the end of '74.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What did you have to do in the interim?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Well, one year at the Kennedy Center and then went back and worked with the program sending American speakers abroad, I can't quite remember what we called it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  It may have changed its name two or three times.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  The leaders program.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  It's now the IV program, I believe, the International Visitor Program.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  But it's had several other designations.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes.  Well, I worked with that program until I retired.  I lost the sight of one eye at that time.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Oh?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, they never knew what it was.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And you never regained it.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  No, I went to every doctor in Washington, everyone that they recommended and then they sent me to the Johns Hopkins Eye Clinic.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did it go out like that or did it just gradually degenerate?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  It just went out like that.  I was sitting there in the office with Leon Picon, my boss, and suddenly the upper quarter, I would say, of the right lens of my glasses turned black.  The window was open and I thought, well, something has blown in on my glasses.  I took my glasses off and looked at them and I couldn't see anything on them.  I put them back on.  That spot was still there.  So I got up and went to the washroom and washed my glasses.  The spot was still there.  And I went back to my desk and in a few minutes the lower quarter turned black so that at that time half of the lens, just as if you had drawn a straight line, half of the lens was black.  By that time it was about time for the office to close.  But I did pick up the telephone and called this agency that recommends doctors and ask for a good ophthalmologist.  And they said, “We can't recommend one but we'll give you the names of three that we think are good that are near your office.” So I went the next morning to see one of the ophthalmologists and he thought I might have a disease called histoplasmosis which is caused by dust from dry pigeon dung that you inhale, and then it gets into your lungs and eventually can get into your eyes and is incurable.  But he sent blood samples to Atlanta, the Institute for Tropical Diseases and they came back and said it wasn't histoplasmosis but they didn't know what it was.  So that is when we started trying to find out what it was but never found out.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  For heavens sake.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, Johns Hopkins took thousands of photos and all sorts of information and sent it all over the world including back to Spain, but never found out what it was.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  For heavens sake.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  The Mayo Clinic had had one case that looked like it about ten years before, but they never found out what it was.  So I don't know what it is.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Well, do you have any overall statements you'd like to make about the Agency, any thoughts you have on how you enjoyed your career?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Oh, a lot of thoughts.  I won't have time for all of them, but a lot of thoughts.  I think that as far as I am concerned, just I alone am concerned, I don't think I could have possibly been in any kind of work that I could have enjoyed more than I did working for the United States Information Agency.  That doesn't mean that I didn't have moments of frustration and moments of unhappiness, perhaps, but I can't imagine there being any career that you don't have moments like that and I had had other careers.  I'd worked for the public in more ways than one and those problems come wherever you are.  But taking it as a whole I liked it very, very much.  I think it can be difficult for the children if they stay away a long time.  It's difficult for them to adapt and feel that they are completely American.  It takes a long time after they get back into the United States.  We perhaps know, you and I, I'm sure, know families whose children did not adapt and who will never feel at home here.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Really gone off the deep end.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Right, and have lived abroad so long that they will never be Americans.  This did not happen to mine.  I think mine now have finally become completely American.  I think they feel completely integrated, but it took some time.  And the first thing they did, one after the other, the first thing they did after they finished college in the United States was go back to the country which they thought was their choice.  The first one came home and said don't go back.  It's not the same.  The second one went back anyway.  Then the second one came home and said to the third, don't go back.  It's not the same.  But the third one went back anyway and stayed for three years before he decided to come home.  But they're all over it now.  They're all Americans, I think and hope.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Which country did they choose?</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Uruguay.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Uruguay.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
<p>EDWARDS:  Yes, Uruguay.  Of course, in the meantime Uruguay had gone through this awful thing of the military coup and many of their friends were no longer there.  The families of their friends were no longer there.  Had that not been the case, I don't know.  I may have lost some of my kids to Uruguay because the Uruguayans were so easy to get to know.  They were so wonderful with the children.  They took the whole families and you were invited to a Uruguayan affair and told to bring the children.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Yes.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  And they loved it.  So other than that I have nothing to say except that I was delighted to serve in the United States Information Agency.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Well, on that note I think we'll close and I thank you very much for your time, Tex.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Well, you're welcome.  I'm glad to do it.  I'm glad to talk about it.  We have edited a few things.  I'm sure you understand that.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I know.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  But that's probably advisable.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Perhaps.  In any event, if you think of anything that goes on afterwards, that you should have included or anything you want to cut out, please feel free to do it.</hi>
</p>
<p>EDWARDS:  Thank you.</p>
<p>End of interview</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>