<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000404">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Robert L. Funseth </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>ROBERT L. FUNSETH</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: June 13, 1994</p>
                <p>Copyright 2002 ADST</p>
                <p>[Note: This interview was not edited by Mr. Funseth.]</p>
                <p>Q: Today is June 13, 1994. This is an interview with Robert L. Funseth. My name
                    is Charles Stuart Kennedy, and it's being done on behalf of the Association for
                    Diplomatic Studies and Training. Bob, I note you were born in 1926 in Minnesota.
                    Give me something about your family background and then about you and your
                    education.</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: I was born in International Falls, Minnesota. I suppose that was
                    prescient. As a matter of fact, I was born there and then reared in Western New
                    York, near the Canadian border, so I spent a lot of time along that
                    international border. My father - Funseth, that is a Norwegian name. My
                    grandparents emigrated from Northern Sweden, a province called Upland, which is
                    a Norwegian-speaking province. They were among the original settlers of what
                    became known as Roo, Minnesota. They were homesteaders. Homesteaded west of
                    town; cleared the land and started that community. My grandfather, Karl Funseth,
                    he and his friends built the first church in that town. It's still there. And I
                    visited there, and that's where my father was born. It's an unusual name. It
                    dates back to about the 12th, 13th Century, when there was a plague in Norway in
                    a place called Noomendahl, which is a North/South valley west of Oslo.
                    Apparently my ancestors came on an abandoned farm. People had all died, and they
                    occupied it. They called it “Oondercepter, a place that we found.” It's still
                    there. Funseth is a place called Funseth Farm, etc. My great grandfather went up
                    north as a young man when that was opened to forestry. My mother's family are
                    French. They emigrated from the area around La Rochelle in the time of the
                    French immigration to French Canada.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Huguenots.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>FUNSETH: They were Catholics from the La Rochelle area in the 1620s, and settled
                    near Quebec on a farm. They lived there right up to the 19th Century when my
                    grandfather, at the time of the Industrial Revolution, came down into New
                    England and worked. Then he went west to St. Paul when it was just a crossroads
                    village, met my grandmother. He was a cabinetmaker. But in order to be
                    self-sufficient, he homesteaded and also bought a place and was one of the
                    original settlers of Woro, Minnesota, which is on Lake of the Woods. Interesting
                    place in the history between us and Canada because there is something called the
                    Northwest Angle in Lake of the Woods. They made a mistake when they drew the
                    line and discovered here was this piece of land in the Lake of the Woods.</p>
                <p>Anyway, he cut down the trees just like my Dad's father, started a log cabin and
                    farm and cleared it off. It's still there; still in the family. The Funseth farm
                    is no longer in the family. But all the buildings that he built are still there.
                    An interesting part of this man, who was more a cabinetmaker than a farmer, the
                    Gebo farmhouse - my grandmother had been raised in a convent, city girl really;
                    never lived in the wilderness - she played the organ. So she had an organ in
                    their house outside of Woro. There were no churches in Woro, so all the
                    itinerant preachers would come to their house and give services because she had
                    an organ. Well, my grandfather one day announced, according to my Uncle Ed, that
                    he was tired of celebrating mass in the living room of his house and couldn't
                    get his friends, unlike the Scandinavians who all got together and helped build,
                    so he built the first Catholic Church in Northern Minnesota by himself, with my
                    Uncle Ed. Chopped the trees down. Had 'em lumbered. Built a white church with a
                    steeple on it. That's sort of the background.</p>
                <p>These farms didn't support a large family. My father went to work in
                    International Falls, where I was born, and then came to Buffalo to work. I was
                    raised outside of Buffalo in a little place called Ebenezer, New York. Ebenezer
                    was founded by the present inhabitants of Amanathe Amana Society in Iowa - that
                    makes home freezers. They were a religious group. Ebenezer is from the Book of
                    Samuel. It says, “I place my rock here. This is my strength and I called it
                    Ebenezer.” That's sort of the family background. I was reared in this little
                    village which was outside of Buffalo, part of a Township of West Seneca.
                    Occupied by Seneca Indians. A very famous Seneca Indian leader lived there,
                    called Red Jacket, who we signed treaties with. Another famous one—Joseph
                    Brandt—also was from that area.</p>
                <p>In fact, the land that our family owned was in the title search when my father
                    died the family we had bought it from it had been a farm, they had bought it
                    from the Ebenezer Society when they moved to Amana, and the previous owner, the
                    Ebenezer Society, had been the Seneca Indians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where'd you go to school? Did you go to the local high
                        school?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>FUNSETH: Ebenezer High School. There were 18 in my graduating class in 1943. From
                    the kindergarten to the 12th grade, we were all in the same building. A very
                    good school. In those war years, the Navy, planning for a long, long war in the
                    Pacific, started what was called the B-12 Program. I was successful in that exam
                    and I was sent to B-12 training at Hobart College. I went there until '44, left
                    there, was commissioned, joined the Pacific Fleet, and then came back to Hobart
                    after the war and finished my education.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in the Pacific Fleet?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: I was on the USS Sturgess, a troop transport. I'd been trained in a new
                    specialty in the Navy, which was just then introduced to the fleet, called a
                    Combat Information Center, CIC Office of Communications. Obviously, we weren't a
                    line ship, so I was the Communications Officer—navigation, radar, signals. I was
                    16 when I passed the exam. I'd just turned 17 when I went into the Navy. I
                    remember when I was in Midshipman School, they held up my commission because
                    they said they didn't want to commission an 18year-old officer. So when I turned
                    19, then I was commissioned. Until I learned that George Bush had been
                    commissioned at 18, I thought I was the youngest officer. But he was, so I was
                    one of the youngest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of courses were you taking at Hobart?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, Hobart, a good liberal arts college. As a Navy Cadet, there had
                    been an emphasis on math and science and engineering. When I went back, I was an
                    Economics major, but I took English and Political Science and Sociology, and had
                    a good, solid education. It's a very good school.</p>
                <p>I graduated from Hobart in '48; wanted to be a writer. Ran out of money. Out in
                    California, my first job was on the Desert Barnacle out in the California desert
                    near the Salt and Safe. The New York Times says it's all the news that's fit to
                    print. Our motto was “The Most Low Down Paper on Earth, published every week of
                    the year 275 feet below sea level.”</p>
                <p>After the Desert Barnacle, I moved on to a paper in Anaheim, California called
                    the Anaheim Gazette, which was then a weekly. While I was there, it went daily
                    became managing editor of that paper and an Associated Press correspondent for
                    Orange County.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>A President of Hobart College made the first visit ever to the West Coast, and it
                    prompted me to go to a dinner in his honor in Los Angeles. I'd been getting
                    restless on the Gazette and wanted to be an editorial writer of foreign affairs.
                    His coming out caused me to come up with the idea of returning to Hobart as a
                    graduate student in diplomatic history. I was their first graduate student.
                    There was some consternation among the faculty about even admitting me, I
                    learned subsequently. So I went back to Hobart and earned a Masters in
                    Diplomatic History and while I was there, with the encouragement of my mentor, a
                    wonderful Professor of Diplomatic History called Leonard Lawson, applied and was
                    accepted to the School of Advanced International Studies (SAIS) in
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why diplomatic history?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Because I was interested in international relations. I wanted to report
                    on international affairs. When I came to Washington, I still wanted to return to
                    journalism. But then, after I got here and I'd been in summer school at Cornell
                    for two summers, I was torn between becoming a college professor or returning to
                    writing. At SAIS there were several senior foreign service officers teaching.
                    They kept encouraging me—urging me—to apply for the Foreign Service. The
                    clincher was, “You solve your dilemma because the Foreign Service is a neat
                    compromise between being a college professor and being a writer.” I'll always
                    remember one of these officers—I think it was Norman Burns—who told me that when
                    you write in the Foreign Service, you're writing for a much more important
                    audience than you would be as a reporter working for a paper, because the
                    secretary of state and the president of the United States are going to be
                    reading what you're writing! So I took the exam and I was successful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came in in 1953?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, there was a hiatus, if you remember. Those of us who took the '52
                    exam, (Eisenhower came in and Dulles—was the whole McCarthy era.) there was a
                    suspension of promotions and of taking in new officers. So I originally started
                    working in the Marshall Plan agency which then was known as the Mutual Security
                    Agency. Then went into the U.S. Information Agency when it was first
                    established. I still hadn't taken my oral examination. No one off of that
                    register had been given an oral exam during that hiatus. I went to Tabriz to
                    open up an information and cultural program in Azerbaijan and Kurdestan
                    [provinces], having taken my oral before I went out and passed it. I'll always
                    remember, it was the last day before I left and I had been the first candidate
                    they'd allowed to give an exam to.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>The reason I was able to get it is I went tPersonnel and said I'd been cleared to
                    be a Vice Consul in Tabriz. Why can't I take my orals? They offered me an
                    immediate appointment. I told them I felt I had a moral commitment to open this
                    program in Tabriz which had been asked for by the Shah of Iran and by Ambassador
                    Loy Henderson. So I went to Tabriz for two years. Then, when I came back from
                    Tabriz - I went out as a Foreign Service Staff Officer under USIS - I came back
                    and received my FSO Commission in '56.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you went out there in early '54?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Early '54. I went to Tehran first and spent most of the summer there
                    working on projects. That was good because I got to know Tehran. Had an
                    opportunity, with the encouragement of the office, to get around Iran. I went to
                    Isfahan and Shiraz by bus. Went by Chevy Van out to Mashed, where a friend of
                    mine, Bruce Laingan, had been assigned as Consul. And then I went to Tabriz. I
                    want to add what the real opportunity was that I had the occasion to meet Loy
                    Henderson, who was my first Ambassador. I must say, at least for my generation,
                    to have Loy Henderson as your first Ambassador: he looked like an Ambassador, he
                    talked like an Ambassador, and was considered certainly Mister Foreign
                    Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't know if he was considered that yet...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, he was certainly well respected in NEA for his work of putting
                    together in NEA the Truman Doctrine. And to go to his staff meetings, it was a
                    real thrill for me to sit and listen to him talk about what the issues were.
                    When I went to Tabriz, he visited us in Tabriz for several days. So, it was
                    very, very interesting. It was an interesting embassy. William Rountree was the
                    Deputy Chief of Mission. There were some junior officers who have remained my
                    friends. Maybe there was something about a first post special memories about
                    that first assignment: Bruce Laingan, Grant Mauser, Chris Chapman were at the
                    embassy and friends in the U.S. Information Service. David Knoll went to Mashed
                    and opened an information and cultural program there.</p>
                <p>My recollection, the real priority, was of Azerbaijan and Kurdestan. I
                    subsequently had occasion in '76 to meet the Shah for the first time. He even
                    remembered, he claimed of asking for this program—because it was just shortly
                    after Mossadegh and the Soviet Union was strongly supportive of the Tuda Party
                    in Iran. Azerbaijan, you may remember, and Kurdestan had been set up as puppet
                    republics by Stalin. They speak a different dialect from Iran. They speak
                    Azerbaijani Turkish. So there was always a separatist feeling there and there
                    was a strong Tuda underground party. It was conducting propaganda and a hostile
                    campaign against the Shah and against the United States. So he asked Loy
                    Henderson to open a discreet information and cultural program to counter that in
                    Azerbaijan. That's how I was assigned there.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>Q: What was the situation while you were in Iran? I mean, you were a junior
                    officer, you're kind of a fly on the wall in absorbing things. How did we view
                    the Shah and his government and the situation at that time?</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, in 1954, the Shah was a symbol of reform in Iran. It was shortly
                    after Mossadegh. The Russians were still very active there. We were then
                    embarking on what became after Korea, then surpassed Korea, as the largest Point
                    Four Technical Assistance Program in the world. I've always regretted that
                    someone hasn't written a story of that period because that program (ironically
                    it may have contributed to the counterrevolution), but at the time it certainly
                    made a lot of sense and this was a period when we really thought we could create
                    a network of countries and governments that were becoming increasingly
                    democratic. A Point Four Program introduced agricultural extension in Iran,
                    public health, modern public education across the board. It was a very good
                    program and it was situated out in the provinces. So when I went to Azerbaijan
                    and Kurdestan, what we were trying to demonstrate was that the United States was
                    supporting this modernization effort of the Iranian government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you went to Tabriz, Tabriz covered both Kurdestan
                        anAzerbaijan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: And Azerbaijan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was our post like at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, Tabriz, first of all, Azerbaijan was the largest and most
                    important province of Iran because it's located up in the Northwest corner. It's
                    fertile. It supplied a lot of grain and fruit. From the Turkish conquest of
                    Tamberlane, it still spoke a Turkish dialect and in the 19th Century and earlier
                    the Crown Prince was always resident there because there was always concern
                    about it. We established a consulate there before World War II or in that period
                    to protect the American missionaries. American missionaries established a
                    Presbyterian mission there in the 19th Century. It was a mission initially to
                    the Nestorians, the Assyrian, Aramaic speaking people, who go back to the early
                    schism in the church over doctrine. A patriarch named Nestorious was sent there.
                    So they had these missionaries and we established a consulate to protect
                    them.</p>
                <p>Then there were periods when it was closed between World Wars I and II. Then the
                    post was reopened there during the war as a listening post.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>There is a very interesting story about the Tabriz Consulate that I used to use
                    when I was recruiting. There was a Junior Vice Consul there named Bob Rossow.
                    The issue of Azerbaijan is the first item on the Security Council agenda, and is
                    still on it. It's never been taken off. The Russians had agreed to withdraw
                    their troops after the war. So the Iranians registered a complaint with the
                    Security Council. Vishinsky [USSR Foreign Minister] denied that the Russians
                    were not withdrawing. Well, here's this Vice Consul sending in messages on a
                    one-time pad on a Morse Code telegraph system from Tabriz to Tehran and then to
                    Lake Success where Secretary of State Burns is getting these messages that the
                    Russians not only weren't withdrawing, but in fact they were advancing! Based on
                    that one Foreign Service Officer's report, and over the protestations of our
                    allies who didn't want to get into a major confrontation with the Russians,
                    Burns, on behalf of the United States, pressed the Russians very hard.</p>
                <p>Suddenly they started withdrawing their troops. They didn't want a confrontation
                    with us. So it was very much a listening post. It was in an old compound
                    adjoining the American hospital. The building was in a former stable, a mud-type
                    building. I lived in the last relic of the former great days of Tabriz. Tabriz
                    had been visited by Marco Polo. There was a huge building called the Arc; and I
                    lived in a house that was near that arc and learned after I'd moved into it that
                    it had been the first American Consulate in Tabriz. We had this compound with a
                    gate and a wall around it, and we had three Vice Consuls and a Consul. The first
                    Consul I served under was Norman Hanna. The second was Robert Greeson, both Near
                    East hands at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your main job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: That was what was fun about the job. I sort of was sent up there and
                    they said, “Do it.” “Do what?” “Well, do what you think needs to be done.” Some
                    of it, it was obvious to me, like putting press releases in a Persian language
                    newspaper in which most of the population was illiterate, wouldn't get you very
                    far. I did a lot of things. I was invited to teach English at the University of
                    Tabriz, which ironically was founded by the Russians as part of their separatist
                    movement. I went into the College of Arts and Sciences and discovered that most
                    of the students were studying English, but there weren't any native speakers.
                    But I didn't want to be just sort of a native speaker like we have at FSI. So I
                    got the idea, I said, “I'll teach, but let me teach a course in American
                    Studies.” That resulted, I learned that was probably the first course in
                    American Studies ever taught in an Iranian university.</p>
                <p>We did a lot of audio-visual. We placed 16mm projectors in theaters all over
                    Azerbaijan and Kurdestan and had newsreel-type films; U.S. information films
                    that were shown. We gave them the projector free and the film free. We developed
                    a wall newspaper which was a huge, sort of enlarged poster that came out every
                    week with photographs of what we were doing to help modernize Iran.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>Instead of opening a library that someone could throw a brick through, I opened
                    an American corner in the Tabriz public library and in the University of Tabriz
                    Library and gave them books, encyclopedia, dictionaries, reference books,
                    periodicals. To succeed me, we sent a young Iranian professor to the United
                    States to study American Studies, to come back and teach. Also, I identified and
                    sent the first Kurd who'd ever come to America under our Leader Grant
                    Program.</p>
                <p>I felt it was a very rewarding experience and it was quite different assignments.
                    I literally taught; I had hundreds of young students I had taught in the
                    university. I had a class for high school English teachers. So I had a lot of
                    friends and it was a very interesting period.</p>
                <p>I traveled. I wasn't married then, and I had a car and driver and an Iranian
                    assistant and traveled all over those two provinces. Went into villages where I
                    was the first American that they'd ever seen. I remember I went into the ancient
                    capital of Iran called Ardiviel, a very holy city. In that building in the
                    mayor's office, there were two pictures, one of the Shah and one of Abraham
                    Lincoln. I don't know where he'd gotten that latter one. Not from me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression dealing with the local
                        governmenofficials,?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Obviously, they were all loyal to the Shah or they wouldn't be there.
                    Most of them were friendly, but I also was sensitive to their own feelings. They
                    tend to be xenophobic. It's an isolated part of the country. They're a very
                    proud people. We had to be careful that even though we were playing a very
                    dominant role, to be sensitive to their feelings of pride. One thing that was
                    interesting - and I remember when Khomeini came in and I'd remembered at the
                    time - the one group of people that we never succeeded in having contact with
                    were the mullahs. They just were not reachable by us. They didn't want to have
                    contact with us. We would, on national days or feast days, meet one or two
                    religious leaders in the city. But by and large, we did not have contact with
                    them. They did not want to have contact with us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that time, was there a feeling that one had to be very
                        carefuabout religion?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: You had to be very sensitive about it. The religious issue out in the
                    provinces was very sensitive. You had to be very careful about photographing.
                    They had in the Shiite faith, as practiced in Iran, developed rituals and
                    traditions. One of them, called Mooharan, is sort of a period of penance, like
                    Lent in the Christian faith. But it can become very bloody and a period of
                    fanaticism. You had to be very careful about that. There was a curfew in effect.
                    There was a Russian Trade Minister ostensibly in Tabriz at the time. No
                    foreigner was allowed to leave the city without permission. Every time you left
                    the area of Tabriz, you had to get special permission from the Governor General
                    wherever you went. Always received it. They were sensitive about the border
                    areas. We were 40 miles from the Iron Curtain.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the view of the people you talked to, both
                        officials anthe private, of the Soviets?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: I don't every recall meeting anyone who said they were pro-Soviet or
                    pro- Pishi Bari, who was the name of the leader. There was certainly a
                    provincial pride as Azerbaijanis. I remember the Director of Provincial
                    Education was an Azerbaijani. The government in Tehran was gradually bringing in
                    more Azerbaijanis into positions of responsibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: I think they were sensitive to that, but I think the main thing was
                    people—the whole idea of getting an education. The Shah had followed his
                    father's practice of liberalization of women. They didn't have to wear the veil
                    anymore, although many did. This was an issue that brought a lot of criticism of
                    the Shah and opposition from the conservatives and from the mullahs.</p>
                <p>Iran was then in a transition. There was land distribution going on. I'll always
                    remember when I first came to Tehran, the former colonial British Club had been
                    taken over by the Iranians, and it was called the Tehran Club. I remember the
                    first or second week I was in Tehran, someone introduced me to an Iranian who
                    said, “Oh yes, his family owned 100 villages in Azerbaijan.” That was a concept
                    I hadn't realized, that you still had a feudal society. If not legally owned.
                    They “owned” the land. But these people were almost indentured. They lived as
                    sharecroppers. As I recall, there were four divisions of the crop: Twenty-five
                    percent for the land, twenty-five percent for the water, I think; twenty-five
                    percent for tools and twenty-five percent for labor. So most of these people
                    would stay in the same village for generations. Centuries perhaps. But they got
                    a limited amount. With modernization and land distribution, we supported that
                    effort to get people their own land and to get them productive and
                    self-sufficient.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any feelings about the CIA, at that time was
                        “messinaround”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: There have been lots of accounts published since then about the whole
                    role of the CIA, and we certainly had an intelligence presence in Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we have listening posts in that area or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: I'm sure we had an intelligence presence in Azerbaijan.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about corruption? Was this a problem for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: I never encountered it, but there is what we call corruption, I've
                    learned in a lot of societies is sort of accepted depending on to what extent it
                    is carried out. But there certainly was corruption in Iran. I didn't personally
                    observe it, but I'm sure it was going on. There's always concern when you have a
                    big aid program, but this wasn't that apparent out in the provinces because
                    there wouldn't be much money going out there.</p>
                <p>I think, if you look back on that period, this was before we had some of the
                    tension between the Shah and the United States at the end of his reign. In that
                    period, we had enabled him to come back. We were a strong supporter of his
                    modernization policies and I think if you go back in the reporting at the time
                    by the press, I think most of the press reported favorably of what he was trying
                    to achieve. There was always a debate, I suppose, within the government, had we
                    made the correct assessment in not supporting Mossadegh? To return to that
                    period, Mossadegh was not an easy person to negotiate with. And a very hard
                    person to assess as to where he was really heading.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the modernization? Was it making many
                        inroads?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: You saw it all over! First of all, you saw young women were able to go
                    to college. They were able to enter into professions. You saw new schools being
                    built. They were small schools; in fact our provincial education adviser was a
                    black educator from Virginia. His experience had been with rural black schools
                    in Virginia, so what he was trying to do was not build something that was
                    unrealistic, but taking what they had and making a curriculum that made more
                    sense.</p>
                <p>Public health. We introduced public health. Public health clinics, pre-natal
                    care. The infant mortality rate in Iran was amazing. In that period, we
                    succeeded in vaccinating the population against smallpox. I remember when I was
                    there, there was an epidemic of smallpox which, even in the 1950s, was
                    unusual.</p>
                <p>But we succeeded in addressing that and in agricultural extension. There was a
                    lot. Transportation. Infrastructure. All kinds of things that our aid program
                    did. The modernization of the armed forces of Iran at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in 1956?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And came back to Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in Washington? How long were you
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, when I came back from Tabriz, I had to make this decision whether
                    I was going to resign from USIS. And I must say they made it very difficult for
                    me to leave. There were a couple of great opportunities; one opening a new
                    information and cultural program in Aleppo, I remember, or going to Cairo. As a
                    Foreign Service Staff Officer, I'd gone from an eight to a four in rank. But I
                    decided that if I was going to follow this career of foreign affairs, then I
                    ought to go into the Foreign Service. So I made that decision and entered the
                    Foreign Service in the fall of '56.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go abroad right away?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, I was at FSI [the Foreign Service Institute] and was put in French
                    language training. During this period, through mutual friends, I met my wife who
                    was one of Loy Henderson's secretaries in the Department. He was then the deputy
                    undersecretary for Management. We were married, and my first post was as junior
                    political officer in Beirut, Lebanon.</p>
                <p>Q: You arrived in Beirut in '57. Things picked up shortly thereafter. What was
                    the situation?</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, I was there from 1957 through '59. This was in the aftermath of
                    the Suez War. The promulgation of the Eisenhower Doctrine, with its acceptance
                    by Lebanon. Embraced by Lebanon, which was the only country that did. The
                    President of Lebanon was Camille Chamoun. The Foreign Minister was Charles
                    Malik, who had been President of the United Nations General Assembly, and was a
                    renowned statesman.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>Lebanon was then living up to its reputation as the Switzerland of the Middle
                    East. But there were ominous signs because even as I arrived, there was an
                    election campaign going on and Nasser was very strong in Cairo and was making an
                    appeal to Arabs, including in Lebanon and in Syria. The whole history of Lebanon
                    and Syria and how it had been carved out in the French mandate was still an
                    issue. Then Chamoun was making indications that he would serve a second term and
                    have the constitution amended as an independent republic. It had only become
                    independent at the end of World War II. One of the provisions in the
                    constitution was a one-term President. This issue divided the Lebanese. There
                    were people that were certainly not pro-Nasser who did not favor Chamoun
                    succeeding himself. Nasser was reportedly supporting people who were opposed to
                    Chamoun. There were people in Lebanon who, I suppose, some internationalist
                    wanted to go so far as to become even much closer to Nasser. During this period,
                    you had the United Arab Republic created in which Syria became part of Cairo.
                    And some of which you're seeing played out in the Syrian relationship with
                    Lebanon now. It was certainly apparent at that time.</p>
                <p>Q: I find that the role of a political officer is often misunderstood. AJunior
                    Political Officer in Lebanon, which obviously was at an interesting political
                    time. How did you go about your work? I mean, who told you what to do and how
                    did you go about doing it?</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, basically it's what my mentors at the School of Advanced
                    International Studies said it was. The Ambassador is reporting on political
                    developments at his level and the Deputy Chief of Mission—we had a two-person
                    political section, sometimes it was three, augmented with an officer—you report
                    on the political developments in Lebanon as they related to our own interests.
                    Very similar to my training as a newspaperman. You were a reporter, and that
                    basically was the way I operated. Established a broad range of contacts in all
                    of the political factions, both pro-Chamoun and anti-Chamoun, to find out really
                    what was going on. Here's a political officer's dream post because the Lebanese
                    are so accessible and like to talk. So basically I reported on those issues of
                    personalities that we were interested in.</p>
                <p>Q: At that time, was there much of . . . (I'm not sure how to describe it.) the
                    Shiite, the poor Arabs. Did they have much or were they kind of off to one
                    side?</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, the Shiites as a political force have come in recent times, it
                    wasn't that apparent. But it was a communal society in which I remember the
                    leader, There was one who was pro-Chamoun who was the speaker of the Parliament.
                    Then one who was probably anti-Chamoun, General Chehab came in became speaker of
                    the Parliament. So we had contacts in the Shiites. The Sunni community was
                    divided, reflecting a history of the Sunni community in Beirut which dated back
                    to the Ottoman times. Then the Sunnis in the north that had really been brought
                    more close to Syria. The Colomi family was very active in that.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Then you had the Maronites who were the dominant Christian community. The largest
                    Christian minority were the Greek Orthodox. You had the political parties sort
                    of reflecting these religious groupings. Then there was an interesting new party
                    just starting. Its leader in Lebanon was Jumblatt, who was also in the feudal
                    tradition, leader of the Druze. Here you had this Druze feudal leader who was
                    ideologically trying to be a social democrat and attracted a lot of young people
                    - Greek Orthodox - it was trying to be a secular party but very Arab
                    nationalist. The movement was just then starting, and wasn't that strong in
                    neighboring countries, but it was beginning. Nasser was a member. It was cutting
                    across the political spectrum. So you had people identified primarily with their
                    religious confessional group and then by village. But then you had this other
                    crossing.</p>
                <p>Beirut was also interesting because of the American University of Beirut with its
                    American connections. You had the French tradition, especially among the
                    Maronites. The French University, St. Joseph, had a monopoly on training the
                    lawyers. If you wanted to go into a political life, you primarily were a lawyer.
                    You had a free press there. A very active intellectual community. On the
                    surface, it was a very young country. It had been enlarged when it became
                    independent. It demonstrated, even the following year during the first Lebanese
                    civil war and then subsequently, how fragile this union was.</p>
                <p>Q: Among the officers what was the view towards Nasser at the time?</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, after all, it was the Eisenhower Administration. Eisenhower had
                    just been reelected and had opposed the Anglo-French-Israeli war. I think we
                    were still trying to reach an accommodation of some kind with Nasser. But here
                    in Lebanon was a government that was committed to democracy, to western values
                    and ideals and wanted and asked for our support. Then Nasser supported to
                    elements that we thought were inimical to our interests emerged. That influenced
                    our attitudes at least towards the Nasser elements in Lebanon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Donald Heath was your ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Donald Heath was the ambassador when I arrived there.Before the war
                    began in '58, Robert McClintock arrived as ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Donald Heath like as ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, I never got to know him very well. He'd come from Vietnam. For me,
                    as still a junior officer, he was certainly a very pleasant man to be around. He
                    always wore a white suit, I remember. I think he, perhaps from his Vietnam
                    experience, and this is just an hypothesis on my part, I'm not sure it's
                    correct, but I think he'd sort of been involved with the U.S. support of Diem in
                    Saigon and he found a strong man and courageous leader like Chamoun and you
                    supported him. But he wasn't there even a year before McClintock arrived. Then
                    you had this contested election in which Chamoun had a narrow minority. But the
                    issue of the expiration of his term was coming in 1958. And there was an
                    incident—an assassination—and you had the Muslims starting to close off their
                    border, and then you had the murder of the Iraqi king.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: July 14, 1958.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Yes. I remember that very well because there was a curfew and I had a
                    political assistant, a Lebanese, who worked for me who used to just monitor the
                    radio at home. He picked up this report from Baghdad that the king had been
                    murdered. He called me on the phone and told me what had happened. I really had
                    to debate, because there was a curfew, but anyway I got in my car and didn't get
                    stopped by any Lebanese police and made it to the embassy. I woke up Ambassador
                    McClintock, and we sent a “Flash” [top priority telegram] into the Department
                    that we had picked up this report. Q: Let's talk about how this played out,
                    because that really started things off out there.</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: I think that leading up to this there was a division in reporting. There
                    were elements, especially in the intelligence community, that were reporting
                    from their sources that Nasser was supporting elements in Lebanon that were
                    opposed to our interests. Nasser was supported by the Soviet Union, so there was
                    a big power play. In the Political section, I was reporting that the issue was
                    Chamoun's desire to seek reelection, which was the real issue, and that there
                    were people - Lebanese nationalists, I can think of several prominent people -
                    who were opposed to his seeking reelection because they believed it would be too
                    disruptive to the compact that held them all together. After the coup, there was
                    a great period of uncertainty in the Middle East. No one knew what was going to
                    happen. The Muslim quarter of Beirut, called the Basta, erupted that night and
                    Chamoun invoked the Eisenhower Doctrine and asked for help. The President
                    agreed.</p>
                <p>I'll always remember that before that time I lived in an area in the center of
                    town. Being a junior officer, I couldn't afford to live up in the high rent
                    district around the Chancery, luckily because we lived in an old quarter of
                    Beirut near where the President lived. Not until after we moved in it was the
                    old Jewish Quarter that dated back to the 17th Century when the Sephardic Jews
                    were expelled from Spain. We lived in that Quarter, and I remember the first
                    thing that happened was that I evacuated my wife from that apartment and brought
                    her to a hotel near the Embassy.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>A lot of the dependents left. The fleet was off-shore and it was to land at noon
                    the next day. I remember that morning I was called up. We all met early in the
                    morning and the ambassador announced that the U.S. Marines from the Sixth Fleet
                    were going to land at noon, and that his wife, the DCM's wife, and the wife of
                    the CIA Station Chief had left on the 6:00 flight that morning. They never
                    invoked mandatory evacuation but it was alert one, two, three. I guess it was
                    two, but strongly urged. I remember a lot of dependents left on a cruise ship
                    that was in port.</p>
                <p>I had just been married. My wife and I didn't want to be separated. I went to the
                    Ambassador and said, “It isn't a mandatory evacuation.” And he said, “That's
                    right.” So Marilyn stayed. She was one of three wives who stayed behind.</p>
                <p>Anyway, it was a very tense period. The Marines came in and did land. They
                    secured the airport. There was a debate about Jordan and it was finally decided
                    the British would go into Jordan, which they did. After the Marines secured the
                    airport, the next day they were going to move in from the airport which is south
                    of the city, up the road along the Mediterranean and into the city to the port
                    and secure that road so the ships could come in. It was probably one of the most
                    exciting, intense days of my life. Remember, Radio Moscow was putting out that
                    this was going to be World War III. We were in the eye of the storm, there were
                    headlines around the world. Khrushchev was-</p>
                <p>Q: I was in Rostenur, Saudi Arabia, at the time. We kept looking out the window.
                    We knew about the landing. We couldn't tell anybody. Everybody was waiting for
                    the mob to arise.</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: There have been documents released that I've recently seen that the King
                    oSaudi Arabia's pleas to Eisenhower strongly influenced the decision. He was
                    urging him to do this.</p>
                <p>Anyway, it became a very tense period because General Chehab, the Commander of
                    the Lebanese Army, had remained aloof from all of this. The patriarch was not
                    pro-Chamoun. No one knew which way the Army was going to go. Going back, one of
                    the problems was communication. The Embassy was unable to communicate with the
                    Sixth Fleet that we could see. We had to go through Washington to get to the
                    Sixth Fleet, to the landing Commander. All the ambassadors were coming in to see
                    the American ambassador before they sent telegrams back. I was sort of at the
                    residence with McClintock ushering people in. I'll always remember the French
                    ambassador, who had an apartment overlooking the beach, and remembering the
                    French, as I recall, were three days late going into Port Said. He was talking
                    to me before he went in to see McClintock. He said, “I was standing on my
                    balcony watching and when the first raft touched on the beach, my second hand
                    hit twelve o'clock.”</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>Apparently, that was a real effort for him because those Marines had been aboard
                    those ships for a long, long time and they were headed back to Greece, and they
                    had to turn around and they weren't all that sure they weren't landing in a
                    hostile environment until they saw young boys selling 7-Up and Coca Cola.</p>
                <p>That was the morning when I evacuated my wife and I remember McClintock swearing
                    everyone to secrecy in the room. You can't tell your spouse or anybody what's
                    going to happen. Of course, the Sixth Fleet had already been in with mine
                    sweepers and everything. I said, “Well, Mr. Ambassador, obviously we'll keep the
                    confidence, but I want you to know that they're selling boat rides from the St.
                    George Hotel out to the landing area. 'Come see the American Marines in action.'
                    The curious are going out to see it.”</p>
                <p>Anyway, it was a very tense day when they landed. There were no hostile fire. We
                    did lose a pilot, I remember. His plane burned out and crashed in the hills over
                    Beirut. It was a very tense period because we didn't know what was going to
                    happen next. The Commander of the Marine Force was a brigadier general named
                    Wade. I'd been at the Embassy all night. Very early in the morning the
                    ambassador's secretary called me. We had then since moved from the old Chancery
                    on rue Clemency down to this converted apartment house right on the beach which
                    was where we were located when it was blown up. My office, being the junior
                    political officer, was in the kitchen of that apartment. The ambassador had sort
                    of a penthouse apartment overlooking the bay. Came in the room and there was
                    this brigadier general standing there on one foot. Very nervous. I don't know
                    who else was in the room. McClintock says, “Bob, this is General Wade.” I
                    noticed he had empty holsters. I learned when he arrived at the chancery, a
                    corporal disarmed him. Wouldn't let him come up with it.</p>
                <p>Anyway, McClintock said, “The Marines are going to move in from the airport
                    today. I can't reach General Chehab. We have reports that the Lebanese Army is
                    deployed against the Marines.” He was very excited. He said something like,
                    “Bob, you get the hell out there and prevent a war until I find Chehab!” I had
                    Blanche call down to the motor pool and get a car and then, because I didn't
                    speak Arabic (I spoke French) and most of the people in the Lebanese Army spoke
                    French, (there was an Arabic language school in Beirut at the time), I called
                    down to one of the language officers who just died this past week, Slater Black.
                    (I think he participated in this.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I have his interview.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Anyway, I called down. Slater was in a special operation. I said,
                    “Slater, meet me in the lobby.” We didn't have cue cards in the motor pool.
                    Wouldn't you know, the car that came up was the old Plymouth that had a weak
                    battery and no springs. In this car we get with the general in the back. Slater
                    and I are sitting in the front seat and off we go on the way to the airport.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>Well, I had remembered my own reconnoitering that there was a UN compound on the
                    way out to the airport and that I had seen the armor of the Lebanese army, which
                    I think was three or four light tanks on semis, had been parked there the day
                    before. So I said, “Let's swing by there.” Sure enough, the tanks weren't on the
                    flatbeds. So we continued down the road and there was a circle there with the
                    road that goes to the beach and there's a tank. There's a back road from the
                    airport which the general didn't know about. We didn't know whether his unit was
                    coming up the main road from the airport or taking this back road. So we stopped
                    there and I remember Slater and I crawled up on the guy and asked whether we
                    could come up. This Lebanese sergeant spoke English and I introduced myself. I
                    said, “You know, the American marines landed yesterday.” He said, “Yes.” We
                    talked a little bit. I tried to get some contact point. My recollection is that
                    he had an aunt in Toledo. I said, “You know, the marines were invited in by your
                    government. They're just going to be driving down the road here to secure the
                    fort. What are your orders when this column comes down the road?” He said, “I'll
                    ask my second lieutenant who's up above here listening in on our conversation.”
                    By that time, the general was really getting nervous. He's sticking his head out
                    the window. So I said, “Well, look, when this marine column comes down the road,
                    remember your aunt in Toledo!” So we continued down the airport road and there's
                    four Lebanese tank guns zeroing in. You go around a circle and you head towards
                    the airport—a double highway.</p>
                <p>Off to the left, there was a sort of an athletic camp for the Lebanese army and
                    in the trees there I saw a Lebanese infantry company digging trenches.
                    Meanwhile, the American reporters of the International Press were following me
                    all over town. When they saw me leave the Embassy, they jumped into a taxi and
                    followed us out. So as we come up over the rise on this divided highway, there
                    comes the rumbling marine amphibious group. So it bounced over and stopped.
                    General Wade gets out. There was a Colonel. His name begins with an H. All
                    black-faced. I think a military attache was there. We started to talk.</p>
                <p>Then I realized a couple of things. One, this marine amphibious group didn't have
                    all that much ammunition. Indeed, four Lebanese tanks were a problem for them. A
                    Lebanese infantry company was also a problem. It wasn't a sure thing. Moreover,
                    they didn't want to open fire anyway. But it was a very, very tense situation.
                    And then the Lebanese air force started flying above us. At that point—it's a
                    long time ago—Slater went off someplace and the attach� left. I was sort of
                    there alone. I remember telling General Wade that these reporters could hear
                    what we were saying. So they called up a squad of marine riflemen; young kids
                    with guns. I remember they pushed the press back and they said, “Make like birds
                    and fly away!”</p>
                <p>So they made this circle. Oh, before I left the ambassador's office, when I went
                    out the door, he said, “One thing. If you get that column moving before I get
                    back out there, remember that we want . . . a tank and some men up to the
                    residence to guard that compound.” We weren't guarding the chancery, but we were
                    guarding his residence. I was wondering what that was about.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>So then—and this may be a little off—but the incidents are right. The sequence.
                    At this point a Lebanese officer arrives on the scene from General Chehab. So we
                    talked back and forth. I think even Admiral Holloway comes out at this point.
                    Anyway, he finally said he could agree and we plotted the road by which the
                    column would go. It would hug the coastline, even though there were some
                    difficult places for tanks to get through all along the Cornish into the city.
                    Not go through the center of the city. We finally worked that out, and that was
                    agreeable.</p>
                <p>Then I had this dilemma. Should I tell him that we're going to peel off some
                    vehicles to go to the residence or should I not say anything? I decided I'd
                    better. Good lesson in the principle of diplomacy because I didn't
                    know—supposing we'd peeled them off and we didn't have an understanding. We had
                    reports that the Lebanese army were coming out between us and I didn't know
                    where they were. So I was really agonizing over it. I finally said, “Major, oh
                    by the way, when the column goes to the left towards the St. George Hotel, we're
                    going to peel off a couple of vehicles and there are going to be a few marines
                    who are going to be at our old compound on rue Clemency to guard the residence.”
                    He said, “That's not within my authority. My authority was...” And he was a good
                    military officer. He was told to agree to a certain route. He said, “We're going
                    to have to check that out.” We started moving anyway with that issue unresolved.
                    The Military Attach� - Colonel Haad was his name - said, “We're going to get
                    moving.” I don't even know if the general was there. “Who the hell knows this
                    route? This isn't the route we're supposed to take. Can you lead us in?” I said,
                    “Yes.” All these marines are in flack suits. And I'm in a seersucker suit. I
                    thought, “Well, I'm going to crawl into the lead armored vehicle.”</p>
                <p>All of a sudden, the jeep comes up. Here's a 17, 18 year-old kid driving the jeep
                    in a flack suit, a marine photographer sitting in the back seat and me in a
                    seersucker suit. And Colonel Haad and they all get back into their armored
                    vehicles and close the hatches down.</p>
                <p>At that point, Stu, I thought to myself, “Funseth, you're supposed to be a smart
                    fellow. What in the world are you doing, sitting in the lead vehicle, coming
                    over the hill, facing a Lebanese Arab infantry company?” At that point, what had
                    been sort of not a serious war, became a very serious war to me. And off we go.
                    At that point, Ambassador McClintock arrives with Holloway and more exchange and
                    we then stop at this physical education camp where these troops are. And there
                    in what had been the little room of—a pretty big room—whoever ran that little
                    training facility, was General Chehab at the desk, chain smoking cigarettes and
                    I even think maybe the guy's bed was in there. Here we are: Admiral
                    Holloway,</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Commander of the Sixth Fleet.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>FUNSETH: I think the Sixth Fleet Commander. No, he was that Admiral in London who
                    had been made Supreme Allied Commander, or something, over the Navy, and
                    everybody. General Wade and there may have been another admiral, McClintock and
                    me and Chehab. He's on the phone and obviously there was a very tense situation.
                    The additional Lebanese troops had come in in that beach area between us and the
                    airport.</p>
                <p>Chehab wasn't quite sure what was going to happen. He was trying to work out some
                    peaceful entry. The marine general was getting increasingly concerned that it
                    was going to become more and more difficult. So at one point, he just whispered
                    in my ear, “Tell the Ambassador that I want to move.” So I told the ambassador.
                    I'm not absolutely sure of this, but McClintock and I were whispering and either
                    I came up with the idea or he did, or we both did, “Why don't you invite Chehab
                    to ride with you and then the Lebanese soldiers will see their commander is
                    leading.” So he put it to Chehab. Chehab was really perspiring and he agreed. So
                    they get into the ambassador's old Cadillac with flags flying. They're the lead
                    car. Then behind them, I guess, was the marine general in that beat-up old
                    Plymouth with no shock absorbers, and then me in the jeep, and then the armored
                    column behind us.</p>
                <p>As we get up by the beach area, it all stops. I ran up and McClintock said,
                    expletive deleted, “There's a problem in the back now and the General and I are
                    going to have to go back and make sure the Lebanese troops are obeying his
                    order. Lead 'em in and I'll catch up with you.” Then I remember asking him,
                    “What about the group that's supposed to go to the Embassy?” The General said,
                    “You take the first three units and lead them to the chancery and the driver
                    will take me with the rest of them .” So we split. I remember leading the
                    marines down the main street outside AUB [the American University of Beirut].
                    Everyone's applauding. We pull up in front of the old chancery. Well, there was
                    a person who lived in—and you may have known him—Colonel William Eddy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Vice President of Tapline.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A very famous Arabist.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: President of my alma mater, Hobart College. He mounted the whole
                    intelligence operation in North Africa. Born in Beirut. His father had been a
                    missionary. He lived in an apartment house overlooking the old chancery on Rue
                    Clemency. If you remember, that was a high-rise. He and David Dodge sent a
                    letter to President Eisenhower opposing the landing of the troops or U.S.
                    intervention if it was there to support violating the constitution of General
                    Chehab in office. But he's a Marine from World War I. He was the first U.S.
                    Minister to the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He translated for Roosevelt.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: At Bitter Lake Conference, yes. But his commission as U.S. Minister—to
                    show you what kind of Marine he was—although he's a professor of English,
                    President Roosevelt said, “Colonel William Eddy, U.S. Marine Corps retired.”
                    Anyway, as we pulled in, what had happened as we had arbitrarily taken these
                    three vehicles was I'd split up a Marine Company. When we finally stopped in
                    front of that chancery, I was confronted with a very angry young Marine Office,
                    either a Lieutenant or a Captain, who had lost half of his company. He was
                    furious! Really steaming! I looked up and there was Colonel Eddy and Mary
                    looking down at us.</p>
                <p>So I told him what it was. By then, I began to wonder about this action and
                    wondered if it might not have something to do with President Chamoun's house
                    that was another half mile down the street. Anyway, I told this young
                    Lieutenant, “In your Marine Corps orientation, did you ever hear of Colonel
                    William Eddy, U.S. Marine Corps? He's a much-decorated Marine Officer from World
                    War I.” I briefly outlined his career. And I said, “He's a real loyal Marine.
                    You know what would really gladden his heart? Why don't you ask your platoon to
                    salute him?” That was a great idea! So they lined up all the Marines to present
                    arms and saluted William Eddy. Eddy was so delighted he almost fell off the
                    balcony!</p>
                <p>How much more time do we have?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why don't we finish up Lebanon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: It became more interesting. Eisenhower was President, had gotten enough
                    that there was some division in the embassy between the intelligence community
                    and the political reporting from the Embassy. [It also was evident] that there
                    was some disagreement in the embassy about supporting Chamoun. It was our
                    contention, as I've said earlier, that the real issue in Lebanon was Chamoun
                    seeking reelection.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the intelligence community seeing this as a
                        Nasser, comSoviet-right thinking.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Yes, and of course there was Nasser money coming in there. It wasn't
                    benign. I mean, the prime minister was. . . they attempted to assassinate him.
                    He was evacuated out. He may have lived the rest of his life in exile in Turkey.
                    It was very tense.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>There was a lot of bloodshed! There was common knowledge that Nasser was putting
                    money and arms in there. It was coming across the border. There had been UN
                    security. A UN Observers' group had been put in there before the landing and
                    they had established posts. It was a constructive lesson on depending on the UN
                    because during the daylight they were watching everything, but then the stuff
                    had come in at night. Arms were coming in there. It was a very tense
                    situation!</p>
                <p>I've always felt that President Eisenhower made the right decision for the wrong
                    reason. His instincts on it were correct, but not for the reason presented.
                    Although you didn't know what was going to happen after that letter. Anyway, so
                    he sends Murphy out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Robert Murphy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Robert Murphy comes out. I'll always remember it because I was used to
                    this sort of cryptic messages that I had sent. Murphy came out and McClintock
                    went out to meet him. We all knew that there was this split. He made the first
                    jet flight to the Middle East. The Air Force flew him out in a tanker or
                    something, a jet, and he flew non-stop from Dover to Beirut Airport. I remember
                    we couldn't get him out of the air because they didn't have anything to do
                    it.</p>
                <p>I'll relate the following incident chronologically, but I didn't learn about it
                    until I was back in Washington the following year. Colonel Eddy told me.</p>
                <p>Murphy was in North Africa, and Murphy and Eddy became friends during the North
                    African campaign, so they knew one another. Eddy told me that Murphy came to see
                    him and said, “Bill, I understand you're opposed to our landing.” Eddy never
                    told me while I was there. It will show you how discreet and correct he is. He
                    said, “Bob, these troops are in here to jam Chamoun down the throat of the
                    Lebanese people. You're damn right I'm opposed to it. But if we're coming in
                    here to uphold the Lebanese constitution and the Republic of Lebanon, then I'd
                    support it.” Then he said, “Bob, just follow your instincts as a good Political
                    Officer and get all the facts before you make up your mind. Talk to the
                    opposition. Find out.”</p>
                <p>So, that then explains what then happened the next morning. Now, Murphy is
                    meeting with the country team. I don't want this to sound self-serving. I'm
                    going to make this as accurate as I can, but this is what happened. Apparently,
                    I learned, Murphy is sitting there and he's in a white suit. He may have already
                    spoken to Chamoun. At this point, as visitor, he wanted to talk to the
                    opposition. So he asked who in the country team. We had the ambassador, the DCM,
                    the station chief, the chief of the political section there. Did they personally
                    know the opposition? They didn't. Murphy said, “Well, who in the Embassy does
                    know the opposition?” McClintock said, “Well, I have a Junior Political Officer
                    who has maintained contact with the opposition.” So he said, “Send him up.”</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>I get this call, again from Blanche, the same secretary who told me to come up a
                    couple of days earlier. She said, “Get up here right away!” So I ran up and came
                    into this office and there is Murphy. I'm not awestruck, but I can tell you I'm
                    not relaxed! Here's the great Robert Murphy! He knows. He said, “You know, I've
                    reached a point in my visit where I thought it might be interesting to talk to
                    the opposition. I understand you know some of the opposition.” He already had
                    decided this. He said, “Who would you suggest I talk to first?” I said, “Well,
                    there are three Sunnis: Abdul Leafi, Saab Salaam, and Rashid Karami are three
                    people that you need to talk to.” He said, “Can you arrange to have those
                    appointments set up?” I said, “Yes, I think I can.” And I did.</p>
                <p>Apparently, the next day he asked for another opposition leader and no one in the
                    country team knew. It became an uncomfortable joke, and he said, “Well, I
                    suppose Bob knows that person.” So, my brief moment of glory. Each day I would
                    go up and set up another appointment for him with Kamal Jumblatt, Rashid Karami,
                    Abdul Leafi, Sami So.</p>
                <p>Then Murphy went to Cairo. My recollection is that when he went to see Nasser,
                    Nasser kept him cooling his heels for several hours. But Murphy refused to take
                    umbrage at that. He just stuck it out.</p>
                <p>[Back in Beirut] he came around to what had been the political section, which was
                    largely me. My position was that we should support the Lebanese constitution and
                    Chamoun. There are other people who have written memoirs about this incident of
                    how we had flip- flopped on our policy.</p>
                <p>The Parliament then met later in the summer and Bud Ramzar, who had then come out
                    as Chief of the Political Section, and I went to witness this election of
                    Chehab. The whole city was cordoned off. We had to walk the last half a mile. My
                    wife, of course, knows where I am. When the ballot reached where he had been
                    named president, the Army started shooting. It sounded like the whole civil war
                    had started over again. I remember coming back to the chancery. The new
                    government came in and all of my contacts: Karami was prime minister, Raymond
                    Eddy was in, Kamal Jumblatt, Philippe Takla as foreign minister. All of these
                    people came in.</p>
                <p>Ambassador McClintock—I don't know if he ever knew them, knew them by
                    reputation—he was relatively short, very dapper, had a grey moustache, and very
                    self-confident. Anyway, I came into his office and he said, “Well, Bob, you're
                    such an expert with the opposition. Let's exchange contact lists.” So a lot of
                    the people that I had developed contacts with, then became the ambassador's, the
                    DCM's. Then I had the opposition!</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>But out of all this there was one [overall] experience. You know, the Arabs as a
                    people remember, if not friends, people who've been loyal to them. When I left
                    Lebanon (it never happened to me again in my Foreign Service career) these
                    opposition people that I didn't have [social] contact with had a dinner in my
                    honor, [given by the foreign minister]. And other ministers.</p>
                <p>When I came back to Washington, I was assigned to UN Political Affairs. That
                    fall, Rashid Karami, as prime minister came to and addressed the General
                    Assembly. Eisenhower invited him down [to Washington] to meet with him here.
                    That's when the planes landed right at National Airport. They came down
                    commercially. I went around to the Lebanese Desk and didn't expect to be
                    included. Karami was coming to the Department, and I would at least like to be
                    in the Lobby and say hello to him. I was made to understand, “Look, you're not
                    involved in this anymore.” So, I didn't press it.</p>
                <p>That night - we were living in an apartment in Fairlington - I get a phone call
                    from the Lebanese Desk Officer. His superiors had ruled that I shouldn't be
                    included. He said, “Are you free for lunch tomorrow?” I said, “Why?” He said,
                    “You won't believe it! The plane lands. The Chief of Protocol is standing there.
                    Some Assistant Secretary is there. Rashid Karami gets off the plane and starts
                    looking. Comes down to the bottom of the ramp. Shakes hands with the Chief of
                    Protocol. 'Where's Bob Funseth?' I can't believe he isn't here to welcome me to
                    Washington!” Oh, boy! So I was included. Karami personally included me in every
                    event that he was involved in. I think he was letting people know that there was
                    someone at least in that Embassy who listened to him and he had confidence in
                    reporting their position, and he wanted us to know he appreciated that.</p>
                <p>Q: One of the things I've found interesting in these interviews is often how—it's
                    not repeated in such dramatic terms, but—an embassy tends to get so absorbed
                    with the government they end up by throwing the opposition to a junior officer,
                    or maybe if it's a labor type government, maybe the Labor Attach�. Then a new
                    government comes in and the embassy power structure is sort of helpless because
                    they haven't done this.</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: First of all, it was so tense between Chamoun and the opposition. And
                    believe me, not all of the opposition were favorable to our interests. It was
                    very emotional, and I think that probably McClintock hadn't been there that long
                    to develop contact, but I think they were respectful. The fact that McClintock
                    tolerated my extensive contacts with the opposition. My telegrams were
                    reported—whatever I wrote went in. I guess the Embassy was covered. I take your
                    point, and it's something you have to be careful about, but we did have contact
                    at least with one political officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I note in looking in the Biographic Register that you got
                        commendation for your work in getting the Marines in. What did you get?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, first of all, I was part of a small group of officers who the NC
                    (?) got a Distinguished Honor Award for that whole operation. Then from General
                    Paul Adams, Commander of the 82nd Airborne: I was one of several Foreign Service
                    officers who were given citations by him personally when he left. That was in
                    recognition for, as they said at the time, my courage and diplomatic skill in
                    getting them into Beirut without a shot being fired, and then my subsequent role
                    as Political Adviser.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you work as a political adviser, sort of an
                        intermediatobetween the military and...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, General Adams I don't think was four stars, but he certainly was
                    three stars. I never briefed him personally, but his G-2 [intelligence officer],
                    who was a full colonel, saw me every morning and I briefed him fully. That
                    briefing was provided General Adams. There wasn't one incident between our
                    troops and the Lebanese. [Our military] had absolute rigid control.</p>
                <p>The 82nd Airborne was camped where Marc Anthony's Roman Legions had camped near
                    the airport in an olive grove. The owner of that grove filed for an indemnity
                    just as his ancestors had done against the Roman soldiers for cutting down a
                    tree or something. I remember when they had their first liberty in Beirut that
                    Adams personally rode—sort of a Patten-like figure—with pearl pistols. He rode
                    around in an armed jeep with a machine gun. Any guy who behaved in the slightest
                    way that wasn't correct was shipped out. I remember we had the UN observers,
                    Odbol General, there was Gala Plaza from Equador, and there was a man from
                    Pakistan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Odbol was from Norway, wasn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: He was Norwegian. They were the UN Observer group. Well, when our troops
                    first arrived and then the 82nd Airborne Division came in, we decided we'd have
                    a reception at the Ambassador's house to introduce UNIGIL to Adams and his
                    staff. The city was sort of cordoned off, so you didn't want the general getting
                    lost. I remember I was in front of the embassy and the general had had this new
                    sedan flown in. Randy Higgs was the DCM and the General was there in the front.
                    Randy said, “Bob, you'd better get in the car and make sure he gets [seated
                    correctly].” So I jump in the car and [the general] sort of freezes. I quickly
                    introduce myself.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>I don't know if you've ever been in that old Lebanese house which was a
                    residence. There was a little patio and there's the three UN people and some
                    other people and in strides this general - a paratrooper with his boots and his
                    two guns. He comes walking in and Ambassador McClintock calls me and says, “Bob,
                    you think you can disarm the General?” So I walked over to the general:
                    “General, you think you'd be more comfortable if you checked your sidearms with
                    me?” He sort of hesitated for a moment and then he took off his two six-guns and
                    handed them to me. I put them in the ambassador's bedroom.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Q: Today is the eighth of July, 1994. Bob, the last time I had you leaving
                    Lebanon. Would you give me your appraisal at the time, and in subsequent years,
                    the common feeling within the Foreign Service, and the professionals, about the
                    effectiveness of this landing in Lebanon?</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: A couple of observations. I think I might expand it into the UN also
                    because that was my first experience with the UN Observer operation.I think, as
                    we discussed in the last meeting, President Eisenhower made the right decision
                    probably for the wrong reasons. The effect of that landing, which was very
                    successful and a credit to the United States, resulted in a period of truce, at
                    least in the history of Lebanon. It also gave the Lebanese time to regather and
                    reunify themselves as a nation. Unfortunately, that didn't happen. There are a
                    couple of factors. One, I think, looking back at it — and I never served in
                    Lebanon again but I maintain an interest in it — is that when King Hussein of
                    Jordan expelled the Palestinians, the PLO {Palestine Liberation Army], a lot of
                    them came into Lebanon. I think that was more than that fragile political
                    structure could digest. That led to other developments.</p>
                <p>A lot of other outside players—Israel became very much involved in the internal
                    political situation in Lebanon. For its own reasons, Israel got involved with
                    the Phalange Christians. A guy I knew very well, Pierre Jamaille, and his sons,
                    his successors. So, I think at the time, it was the correct move. I think also,
                    in retrospect, that it was realized we're not in a position to do that anymore.
                    We had massive resources. We were a world power and we were prepared to exercise
                    that power.</p>
                <p>I think the other thing is that the military operation—you can't fine tune it.
                    There are too many different people involved. No matter what we were recording,
                    by the time it filtered down to the G-2 of the landing party, I don't think they
                    had a clear idea of all the facts on what to expect. Certainly, when a larger
                    force came in, from my own experience in briefing General Paul Adams, he had a
                    very imperfect sense of what was the reality. But they quickly adjusted to it,
                    and I thought acted very responsively, and [consequently], I think, made a
                    powerful impression on the Lebanese. The troops were well disciplined,
                    attractive young Americans. They fanned out in the perimeter around Beirut,
                    including the overlooking mountains.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>I remember after things had settled down, my wife and I drove up the mountains to
                    have lunch. It was quite a sight driving up the road and the Sixth Fleet
                    anchored down there below. We went into this hotel and there were Lebanese
                    families with their daughters and they were chaperoning a little social event
                    that Sunday afternoon, with GI's and Marines who weren't on duty, dancing, and
                    having a good time. First of all, the troops were very well behaved, very well
                    disciplined. They made a powerful impression on the Lebanese.</p>
                <p>[The landing] permitted the [Lebanese] to regroup and exercise their
                    constitution. The elected General Chehab. I think that that period then probably
                    was reasonably tranquil. Unfortunately, they just couldn't escape their own
                    history. Many of the people that I knew rather well at that time, Camille
                    Chamoun, and others—Kamal Jumblatt—those political leaders hung on in protecting
                    their own clans and their own groups, and they never came together again. Then,
                    in recent years, you had Syria reintroduce itself. Syria was a factor even then
                    because through the United Arab Republics and the Syrian infiltration, the whole
                    [Syrian influence and] effect in Northern Lebanon.</p>
                <p>I was thinking about it. It is a very interesting thing for me because I went
                    from Beirut to the UN up there where this was being played out in the UN
                    Security Council. Lebanon, a very small country, had a very unusual Foreign
                    Minister, world class, in Charles Malik. He represented Lebanon before the
                    Security Council. Dag Hammarskjold was then Secretary General. The UN sent out
                    this observer group, UNIGIL. They followed conventional UN military procedures.
                    They'd establish places. But everyone knew the infiltration was still taking
                    place at night on back roads. But that wasn't reporting. So the impression you
                    get from reading the UNIGIL reports, and what was being reported in the United
                    Nations, in fact what was happening on the ground, there was a disconnect in
                    reality. It pointed out to me—I learned a lesson at that time—you have to be
                    very careful in how much you can depend on a UN operation. First of all, you
                    don't have that much control over it; secondly, it's imperfect. You may hope
                    it's going to expose, as Lebanon did, infiltration, but it didn't. So it's very
                    much a political instrument.</p>
                <p>It was exciting times. I remember Hammarskjold coming to Beirut. Then, of course,
                    we landed with the UN there present when we came in and then after we left.
                    Those are my thoughts.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>I think I also mentioned a Marine Amphibious Landing Group come over the beach
                    and then they were followed by the 82nd Airborne, and hour after hour for days
                    planes landed, and they're taking up positions. But I remember, as I think I
                    recounted in the last interview, wanting to negotiate a Status of Forces
                    agreement and this lawyer telling me that the Air Force had 10,000 people on the
                    way into Turkey. If you could be up in the sky, you'd see airplanes nose to tail
                    across from the Mediterranean back onto the Atlantic Coast. Again, that
                    demonstrates for us as Foreign Service, when you bring the military in, you
                    don't have complete control. It's the whole problem with communication that I
                    pointed out in the last meeting. There was a possibility of a serious mishap on
                    the beach, which I recounted in the last meeting which I participated in, to
                    some extent, in preventing that from happening, but I might not have been
                    successful. Whereas, when they landed the day before, we at the Embassy had no
                    way of communicating with this Amphibious Force that was over the horizon.
                    General Chehab was proposing sort of a peaceful entry into the port, and not
                    what could be perceived by some factions in Lebanon as a hostile landing on the
                    beach. Indeed, the Army perceived it as that.</p>
                <p>So this whole problem of communications is something we're still working on. I
                    remember participating in exercises with the Atlantic Command and I can't
                    remember if I mentioned it to you, but the Marine officer who was in charge of
                    the Marine Guards in the Middle East subsequently was the Colonel in charge of
                    the landing party in the Dominican Republic. They exercised, tried to learn from
                    the lessons of the Beirut experience and they still had the same communication
                    problem. The embassy couldn't communicate with the landing force. It came
                    through Washington and through command, so there's still that communication
                    problem.</p>
                <p>I thought I might just recount [the following] for the record. I was thinking of
                    some of the names of the people, personalities that I had occasion to meet. Not
                    all of them. Camille Chamoun, certainly. General Chehab. Abdel Osay Iran, who
                    was the leader of the Shiites and speaker of the Lebanese Parliament. Sir John
                    Philby, a teacher at AUB. I remember a fascinating afternoon in which, for three
                    hours, he recounted how he had just been an archeologist and was sent out during
                    World War One to find the Saud family. Did I mention that?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>FUNSETH: Here's this legendary character. We had lunch at the American University
                    Club. He recounts this story that I've got written down someplace. He was called
                    to the Foreign Office of Intelligence and they told him that this guy by the
                    name of Lawrence was the branch of the family of the Hashemite people. But there
                    was another Arab in the Arabian Peninsula, the Saudi clan over in the East and
                    they wanted him to get in touch with them to see what he was doing in this whole
                    period of World War One. They told him there was a plane out in the airfield.
                    The pilot would fly him. He remembers stopping in a book store and getting a
                    bunch of road maps. He gets in this airplane. Open cockpit. I guess the pilot's
                    in the front cockpit. He's got this road map and they're flying from England to
                    France, stopping every few hours to refuel, and following these maps, and makes
                    his way into the Arabian Peninsula into Eastern Arabia and finds old Ibn Saud,
                    and that's how he established contact with him.</p>
                <p>Did I mention Charles Malik, who was a fascinating person, coming from a little
                    village of Huteron [Batroun??] near Tripoli, a Greek Orthodox? I went to school
                    with a cousin, but he regarded himself as a nephew, Ilie Salem, at the School of
                    Advanced International Studies. I came to know that family and the village he
                    came from. Ilie Salem subsequently became Foreign Minister of Lebanon. Then
                    there was the Muslim leader, Sami Sol, and Afilie Afie Comoge Jumblatt,
                    fascinating guy, who had this bifurcated persona in that he was the founder of
                    this bi-Socialist Party in Lebanon and yet he was the heir of the Jumblatt clan
                    which was one of two ruling clans of the Druze in Southern Lebanon. Here this
                    guy was this feudal lord on the one hand and this Social Democrat on the other
                    hand and lived in this ancestral home which was the Jumblatt castle. Then when
                    the civil war broke out, he became a feudal lord again and not a Socialist. I
                    remember I was sent down there by McClintock and established contact with him
                    after our troops had landed. It was out of Beaugest. I'd been there on my way to
                    Iran. I met a Lebanese student who took me to see Jumblatt and told me about the
                    party, about the forming of this Blat party.</p>
                <p>In this period I arrived again back at this place and they'd blown out the
                    bridges. I remember having to cross on sort of a log and there was a sentry with
                    Druze ammunition belts. They knew I was coming. I came out with my embassy car,
                    which came so far. Then I had to walk up to the castle. They captured a French
                    armored car.</p>
                <p>Kamal Jumblatt, a Druze—they are kind of mystics and get involved in Chinese and
                    Confucius, I think—knew me; actually, we knew one another very well. I was one
                    of the few foreign homes he'd come to. So, I had lunch with him. He formed the
                    Independent Druze Republic, he said with a smile. “There's my armored division;
                    here's my Minister of Defense.” He was introducing me to all these guys as
                    cabinet ministers. He had a colleague, Semarge Delani, then I mentioned Rashid
                    Karami from Tripoli, and Philip Takla. There was a whole cast of these
                    characters. I think what was so interesting for me as a junior political officer
                    was that I represented the American embassy. On the other hand, they're very
                    open people. Very open society. Very friendly. Not very rank conscious. So if
                    you established some sort of intellectual relationship, you had it</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>The guy I left out, who was very important, was Raymond Eddy, whose father had
                    been President of Lebanon. There were two Eddy brothers—Raymond and Pierre.
                    Raymond was head of the party and was a very close contact of mine. He, among
                    others, argued persuasively that the issue was not communist influence in
                    Lebanon at that time, but President Chamoun's efforts to amend the constitution.
                    Now to Chamoun's defense, I'll give them all the benefit of the doubt. I think
                    Chamoun loved Lebanon and he thought he was protecting, in the first instance,
                    the Maronites, and the soul of Lebanon. That was the whole issue. For Malik it
                    was very much religion, tied up with nationalism. To protect that which goes
                    back centuries, this Christian foothold in the Eastern Mediterranean.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find this society very open?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: You were in Saudi Arabia at this time?</p>
                <p>Q: I was in Saudi Arabia. There was a whole different thing. I mean, we didn't
                    have those contacts. The Saudis were a whole different breed of cat. Were there
                    wheels within wheels within wheels in this Lebanese society? I mean, was it
                    difficult to tell what was really happening?</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: No, I don't think so. In fact, it probably spoiled me for the rest of my
                    Foreign Service career as a political officer because it was so open and you had
                    to discipline yourself and prioritized, because you didn't have enough time to
                    talk to all the who were available to talk to.</p>
                <p>There was a lot of intrigue going on at this time. I mean, this was, after all,
                    1956, the Eisenhower Doctrine, Nasser, and the Russians had a huge mission
                    there. Intelligence officers all over the place. I remember there was a guy from
                    the Russian Embassy, who was obviously assigned to me. I'm pretty sure he was
                    KGB (Soviet Intelligence). We maintained contact. We'd see one another. Try to
                    find out what the other side was thinking. He then surfaced as a Pravda or
                    Investia correspondent when we landed. We've always known there was a close
                    intelligence connection. I was getting from the FBIS (the U.S. Foreign
                    Broadcasting Information Service). Here was a byline from this guy that the
                    Marines landed, rolled into town; I'd led them; there were people throwing
                    flowers and cheering. I mean, there was absolutely no hostility. But Tass was
                    reporting, “The Marines landed today into a hostile environment. The tanks
                    rolled over children in the streets.”</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>This guy came to see me and I read the article to him. I said, “Where does this
                    BS come from?” without saying BS. It didn't bother him. He said, “All I was
                    reporting was what the Cairo press was saying.” I said, “Well, you oughta [ought
                    to] hear yourself!” Anyway, I think you really could understand it. Obviously, I
                    felt I understood it as well as you could as an outside observer and as a
                    student of the Middle East.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you went to the USUN. You were there from</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: I had fallen in love with the Mediterranean and the Middle East, but
                    Beirut really spoiled me. So, on April Fool's Day, the first one after I was in
                    Beirut, I discussed it with my wife and put in that I just wanted to spend the
                    rest of my career in the Mediterranean covering the former Roman Empire within
                    site of the Med. I wanted to go, I thought, to Tunis and Morocco; a good place
                    to go from Beirut. Unbeknownst to me, my reporting had come to the attention of
                    Joe Sisco in [the State Department's] UN Affairs. I didn't know Joe Sisco. He
                    was Deputy Office Director in UNP [United Nations/Political Affairs] in IO
                    [International Organizations; got me, and I was assigned as the Officer in
                    Charge of Relations with the new IAEA [International Atomic Energy and Outer
                    Space].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was something for which you were well qualified.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: It was not something I was terribly interested in, I can tell you. I
                    came into UNP. That would have been '59, '60, '61; a two-year tour. It turned
                    out I didn't say too long in UNP. We were in the old New State. The annex was
                    built while we were there. The head of IO was Francis Wilcox. This was the end
                    of the Eisenhower [Administration]. Henry Cabot Lodge was in New York, but we
                    never saw him when he was in Washington because he never came into the State
                    Department as far as I know. He stayed at the Metropolitan Club and was in the
                    White House. He emphasized his Cabinet rank and had nothing to do with the State
                    Department. I mention this because I want to share an amusing story about how we
                    handled when Adlai Stevenson came in. I think Woody Walner was Wilcox's Deputy.
                    Bill Cargo, who was not far from me in Arlington, was the Director of UN
                    Political Affairs. Sisco was the Deputy. There were some interesting people.
                    Virginia Hartley, I remember, who was I think, a lawyer. But she'd been
                    President at San Francisco.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>In 1959, there were some people who'd been involved in the creation of the UN
                    thing and probably were involved with Koslovski and Cordell Hull, something I'd
                    examined in my graduate thesis. Elizabeth Brown was the officer in charge of the
                    Political side. Bill Buffam was with her. I remember I shared an office with
                    Steve Palmer and the other two officers were Mike Millem and Bob Oakley. We were
                    UN Political. There were a couple of things that I remember. No one would forget
                    meeting Henry Cabot Lodge, who reigned at the U.S. Mission [to the United
                    Nations in New York]. Anyone who has met him will not forget it. Hammarskjold,
                    of course, was Secretary General. In that period, John Foster Dulles became ill
                    and Christian Herter became Secretary of State. Just think of the Department and
                    its stratification and S/S [Staff Secretariat], the Secretary, and clearances
                    that existed when you retired and when I retired.</p>
                <p>Then this story. I can't remember what the issue was because there were two
                    issues I covered in that two year period. One was Africa and the whole
                    peacekeeping operation in the Congo and the other was Southeast Asia. I'll
                    mention each of those briefly. One night, I had drafted a cable for the
                    Secretary's signature on the green form that you type and had gotten it all
                    cleared. I was up front with Sisco and Wilcox and somebody. Remember the old
                    Lobby on 21st Street. They said, “The Secretary's getting ready to leave his
                    office. Take your cable down and wait for him in the lobby and get him to sign
                    it.” So, I'm an FSO-7, so I took the elevator down and waited. It was sort of
                    like, I guess someone earlier might have felt when he saw Franklin D. Roosevelt.
                    I didn't realize that Mr. Herter was crippled with arthritis. Out of this
                    private elevator comes Mr. Herter. Well, he had two canes. Very difficult. He
                    walked over to the desk; there were no guards in those days. No one was there as
                    far as I can remember. It was 7:00 or 8:00 in the evening. He said, “Oh, you're
                    Mr. Funseth in UNP. You have something for me?” I said, “Yes, sir.” He took it
                    over to the little receptionist's desk. No one was there. Read the cable. Asked
                    me a question or two about it, signed it, and said. “Very good. Good night.”</p>
                <p>Which leads into “what if?” I think Hammarskjold took the initiative, but at that
                    time in Southeast Asia in North Vietnam the Pathet Lao occupied two provinces in
                    the northeastern sector of Laos. That was all. I remember there was a King then
                    and he had a brother who was the Red Prince. Anyway, Hammarskjold got this idea
                    that you establish a [perimeter ?] in Southeast Asia, put a fence up literally,
                    around these two provinces from what divided north and south Vietnam. He had a
                    UN Observer Force there. Behind that barrier, you have something called the UN
                    Mekong River Development Program.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>The thought of working in UN Affairs was that regardless of your rank you were
                    given things to do. I was officer-in-charge of this thing and drafted the
                    letters for Herter, back to Hammarskjold. I remember this was right leading up
                    to the elections in '60, I guess. It really came through down through the years.
                    At one time, we had a meeting with the French and the British to discuss this.
                    This isn't completely fair, but the one thing I remember about the meeting was
                    the British were primarily exploiting any British commercial opportunities and
                    any such scheme so that British firms. This guy was talking about Bailey
                    Bridges. All the Frenchman was interested in was to protect the primacy of the
                    French language. Anyway, I often remember, “what if”, because it got lost in the
                    elections and then, if you remember, Laos became very important under
                    Kennedy.</p>
                <p>Then we'd moved into the new building and President Kennedy used to have his
                    press conference in our auditorium, had a big map of Laos. Then he very quickly
                    decided that he didn't—maybe a lesson for our subsequent Presidents—that our
                    vital interests weren't involved in Laos and he lost interest in it.</p>
                <p>The assistant secretary or deputy assistant secretary was GrahaParsons, I
                    think?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jeff Parsons.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Jeff Parsons. He was very much involved in Laos. I'll always remember
                    the story that Kennedy introduced him to the Swedish foreign minister and said,
                    “Mr. Prime Minister, I want to present to you a very distinguished American
                    diplomat, Ambassador Parsons, who is the greatest living expert in the world on
                    Laos. Therefore, I am sending him to Stockholm as the next U.S. Ambassador.” So
                    Laos went off the screen. But what Hammarskjold had in mind was intriguing.
                    Nothing ever happened to it.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>The other big thing I was involved in, which again was another example. Almost
                    every chapter of my Foreign Service career I had some involvement with the
                    American military. This was in the Congo in that whole period with the eastern
                    Congo seceding, Katanga, and all that thing. Hammarskjold was subsequently
                    killed in that upset. What happened, and I've been reminded of it under present
                    peacekeeping operations. I guess if I had more time, I'd write a letter to the
                    editor, but it wouldn't do any good anyway. But we seem to have forgotten in UN
                    peacekeeping that at the very beginning, we didn't provide ground troops. We
                    provided logistical support. We did the airlift and we airlifted men and
                    supplies into the Congo. I was the principal contact with the Defense
                    Department. That was my assignment and I was dealing with military officers much
                    more senior to me in rank—Colonels and Captains, even Generals and Admirals. We
                    developed a relationship over the telephone. They kept inviting me over. I
                    remember Sisco and Cargo saying, “If you go over, and they see how junior you
                    are, you're going to blow it. Your credibility.” They kept holding me off. So
                    finally, when it was all over, I came over and we had a lunch in the flag
                    office. They probably figured out what it was. I think they were a little
                    surprised at my rank. But I'll tell you the thing I learned. We used to have
                    some pretty frank exchanges. They took me into a room. It was the Joint Chiefs
                    with all their tape recordings, in which they recorded every phone conversation
                    they'd had with me. They had a record of everything we in the Department said.
                    But, again, it was, as I look back on it, first of all you had a relationship
                    with them and you had to be responsive to them and they did provide it, but we
                    weren't involved in providing ground troops. We provided the logistical
                    support.</p>
                <p>I want to tell you a story about Adlai Stevenson. The election happened. Harlan
                    Cleveland was succeeding Francis Wilcox. Then Adlai Stevenson, like Lodge, got
                    the consolation prize. He wanted to be Secretary of State. Very similar to
                    Lodge. He was made UN Rep. With Cabinet rank. I remember sitting in the front
                    office. It's the same suite of offices that we originally went into. Who has
                    pride of authorship? We all participated in it. Anyway, you know how these
                    assistant secretary offices are. You have the assistant secretary and it's
                    paneled. Then as you get further away where the staff sits, until you get to the
                    end of the suite, it isn't carpeted. So they got this idea that the last office
                    in the whole suite that was also sort of at the end, they extended a corridor
                    carpet down to that office, made it really fancy. I'll always remember because I
                    was in the welcoming party. I think I went down to the lobby and brought
                    Governor Stevenson up, and I really admired him. Brought him up—jovial and
                    cheerful—we'd orchestrated the whole thing. At the end of the meeting, Harlan
                    Cleveland says, “Governor, I want to show you your office when you're in
                    Washington.” He walks him down this new stretch of carpet down to the end of the
                    suite, and there was this office. Stevenson looked around and said, “Very nice!”
                    So whenever he came to Washington, he always sat in that office. But it promoted
                    a much closer relationship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Henry Cabot Lodge. They said he reigned rather than . How
                        dipeople at IO when you were there, what did they feel about him?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>FUNSETH: Remember again, this is the '50s. There were books then being written,
                    “The other State Department.” The issue wasn't resolved after all; it came very
                    much to the head under Jeanne Kirkpatrick. “The Other State Department.” I mean,
                    the bristling in New York; that they got instructions from the State Department
                    to carry out. PermRep [permanent representative] up there calling the White
                    House directly, or alleging that he had. You never know whom he's actually
                    spoken to. Then they say, “Well, the President doesn't want to do this, or the
                    White House doesn't want to do that.” So I think it's more, going back to the
                    origins of it, the whole idea of taking instructions. People who are associated
                    with the UN, they had a different attitude at the UN in the '50s and subsequent
                    years, that it could do more things. People wanting to sublimate our bilateral
                    interests. So there was this tension that's still there, but was much more so
                    then.</p>
                <p>I really felt that I appreciated the limitations of the United Nations from my
                    Lebanese experience. But that wasn't the sentiment in IO when I arrived. There
                    used to be an annual circular telegram; you may remember. It went to all posts.
                    Long airgram. Twenty pages. It listed every agenda item for the upcoming General
                    Assembly. Every embassy was instructed to go in and get their government to
                    support the United States on all of these issues. It was drafted with the State
                    Department in mind. I remember when I came in the first fall. I arrived in
                    September and this thing was under discussion. I said, “Do you have any idea how
                    this instruction is carried out? I carried out that instruction in Lebanon. The
                    Bureau of International Organization Affairs in the Lebanese Foreign Ministry
                    consisted of two people. I'll never forget this was one of the first
                    instructions I carried out as political officer. My first assignment. I made an
                    appointment with this official and went to the Lebanese Foreign Ministry. It was
                    sort of in a converted billet. Found my way, knocked on the door and the guy
                    said 'Come in.' I couldn't find the person because there were piles of UN
                    reports that were coming in. Imagine if all the UN reports in any given year
                    were put in one room. In the middle of this skyscraper was this one Lebanese. I
                    said, 'I've come in to discuss this instruction.' He was the one who had to
                    carry it out.” Charles Malik was not there, but a personality equivalent to that
                    explained to me, “I'm not going to tell Hajim Bey in New York how to vote.” We
                    didn't really grasp how much independence a PermRep has in New York. Never mind
                    the politics of it, just the technical how do you carry out an instruction?” A
                    one man bureau in Beirut or dozens of other countries can't keep track of every
                    agenda item in all six committees.</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>Q: There are two things I'd like to put in here. Two of my interviews. One was, I
                    think, in Upper Volta or something, where our ambassador went in to ask support
                    on something dealing with whale fishing. The Foreign Minister said, “Well, we'll
                    certainly support you, but tell me, what is a whale?” Another one was going to
                    get Chad to keep the Soviets from overflying to Cuba. They assured us they
                    would, but where was Cuba? These things just aren't on their agenda. Someone can
                    come to us with the same problem that we wouldn't know. Almost not the futility,
                    but the resources that were tied up in trying to get UN votes. Did they ever get
                    a realistic view of how the people in the field did it? Or was this something
                    that they did and they were so bound up that they thought everybody was
                    expending all their capital, our embassies, in order to get the UN votes on</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: We still do. I mean, that's what diplomacy is all about. Hopefully, you
                    have to balance some of that out. In subsequent years, I was a member of the
                    delegation and I remember spending a day in the Secretariat Building—the General
                    Assembly—I'd been there all day. Crossing over [to the U.S. delegation offices]
                    to write my telegrams at 8:00 at night, I realized, as I'd come out of the
                    building and was walking across, that for some time I'd began to feel that this
                    was the world. An underworld.</p>
                <p>Overall, I really think the UN has served our interests and we've been a
                    responsible leader in it. It is useful. I mean, that's never been a question in
                    my mind. It's not to have exaggerated expectations. We still have. And we sort
                    of refer to it as if it's an independent body of some kind. We don't realize
                    it's just an organization of state. It's easy to forget—the UN this, the UN
                    that. It's sort of like saying, “The Foreign Service.” As if there's something
                    really a corporal body of the Foreign Service. There isn't. People like to say,
                    “Why doesn't the Foreign Service do this or that?” There's no Foreign Service to
                    act that way. We're a collection of individuals. The UN is sort of like that.
                    Now, with variations. It does have a Secretary General who can presume to speak
                    on its behalf, so it does have an independent voice. But we certainly did have
                    expectations of the UN that weren't realized. We had to adjust accordingly. And
                    we did!</p>
                <p>Q: What about the Congo business during this first great effort of the UN? How
                    did we view what was happening in the Congo? Were we seeing this in East/West
                    terms? I'm talking about in IO.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>FUNSETH: I honestly can't remember. I don't think the Russians really started
                    playing a strong hand in Africa until much later, in Angola, for example. They
                    didn't have airlift capabilities. I can remember one point, and it wasn't then,
                    it was some years later, maybe even in the '60s. The Soviets didn't have
                    experience in a big airlift far from their country. They tried one once and ran
                    into a little trouble, and called the whole thing off. It took them some years
                    before they gained the confidence of being able to operate an extended air arm.
                    My own recollection, and I haven't gone back and read the history of it, and
                    these are many years ago, almost forty. My recollection is that this was more
                    associated with the issue of colonialism rather than the issue of the East/West
                    and the creation of independent states in Africa and members of the United
                    Nations, and helping these new states develop and become democracies. I think
                    that was the issue in the '50s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again, while you were there, did you get any impression
                        about throle of Arab countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: This was again right after Suez. The whole UNRA. I was the UNRA Desk
                    Officer also. A lot of U.S. support for UNRA. I mean, UNRA was then stationed in
                    Lebanon—the headquarters—and America was the head of UNRA. Henry Labouisse,
                    remember that name? Just think back how things have changed. UNRA isn't even in
                    Lebanon. It's in Vienna. Very few, or no American staffers are safe to go into
                    Lebanon. So how UNRA has changed. The borders of Israel are different. This was
                    before the war in the '60s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there and you didn't get back to your
                        beloveMediterranean.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Never. Never. Then there was a personnel system just about that point in
                    time I was in UNP and my recollection is that Personnel came up with a new
                    requirement that in order to get promoted to almost anything you had to have
                    experience in all cones [skill area, such as political, consular etc.]. I'd been
                    a political officer, I'd had information experience, but I hadn't had consular
                    experience. So I was told in Personnel that before I could go back into a
                    political job, I'd have to be a consular officer. So I wound up being assigned
                    to Bordeaux for that reason.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from '61 to '64.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: I originally went out on a two-year tour to be a vice consul in Bordeaux
                    and then be transferred to Paris as a political Officer. While I was in
                    Bordeaux, they changed the tour. I think a few weeks before I went on home
                    leave, in order to save money, the Department ruled that I wasn't eligible for
                    home leave until after the third year. So I stayed another year in Bordeaux,
                    lost out on a transfer to Paris, and then subsequently was stationed in the
                    department.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in Bordeaux?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, in Bordeaux, originally when I arrived there, it was a four-person
                    post: principal officer, deputy principal officer, a vice consul in charge of
                    sort of the citizenship side, and a vice consul in charge of the visa side. I
                    was that number three. The number two position got abolished in some sort of an
                    economy way and again, as always happens, the function to be abolished—the
                    deputy job was the reporting officer. Well, the principal officer said to me,
                    “You're going to do the reporting and do what you've been doing.” So I did and,
                    as it turned out in that period, each of the principal officers left the Service
                    after one year. So I was in charge of the post for extended periods. I had three
                    principal officers in three years. It was '61, '62, '63, '64.</p>
                <p>So I basically, became the deputy soon after arriving, and had so many changes in
                    the principal officer slot, was acting for a long time. So I really was in
                    charge of the consulate. Interesting post. One of several that lays claim to
                    being the oldest post in the Foreign Service. Dates back to the Continental
                    Congress. Indeed, the first consul was wealthy, came from a prosperous [family],
                    was a ship agent from Georgetown and had enough money to build a very handsome
                    building called the Fenwick House, which was the offices of the French line.
                    Pretty much since then we've had a post. It was closed during World War II.</p>
                <p>Kennedy was President; one of the most popular American Presidents since Thomas
                    Jefferson in France. He and Mrs. Kennedy made a big impression on the French
                    people. DeGaulle had come back to power. The mayor of Bordeaux was a speaker of
                    the French parliament—a distinguished French political leader by the name of
                    Jacques Chaban- Delmas, who'd been in the French Underground, had been mayor of
                    Paris during the occupation. The story o“Is Paris Burning?” is tied in with this
                    guy, a real hero.</p>
                <p>Our consular district was south of the Loire river, the whole southwest of France
                    including the Basque country to Toulouse, that whole area. We had some American
                    military installations in the area. Bordeaux was an important port. When I
                    arrived, General Gavin was the Ambassador. He was succeeded was Charles Bowen.
                    Cecil Lyon was the Minister under both while I was there.</p>
                <p>It was personally interesting for me. I visited La Rochelle, where my ancestors
                    came from, on my mother's side, who had emigrated to Quebec in the 17th Century.
                    At least my grandmother's family were Huguenots. I read recently that in order
                    for a Huguenot to get an exit permit, they had to convert to Catholicism. In my
                    mother's family, they were Catholics, but probably both of them were Huguenot
                    families who were leaving the area, and they emigrated to French Canada in 1628,
                    I think.</p>
                <p>I learned a couple of things. I am again reminded of the role a Foreign Service
                    local plays. It was something I commented on in my retirement.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They're called Foreign Service nationals employees
                        now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Right. In Tabriz, for example, there was a man there named Mohammed Ali
                    Asouf, who was hired when the post was opened during World War I, and every time
                    we closed it he'd take the seals home and the consular files. Then, when we
                    reopened, he'd come back. I never felt that we were really fair to them as
                    employers. Then in Bordeaux, we had this man; his name was Robert Artisian. He
                    has since died. He had worked for us for many, many years; was our senior
                    commercial employee. I remember the department of Commerce thought he was the
                    best one in the world; he generated more export opportunities. But, again,
                    during the occupation he had taken the seals home and classified papers under
                    great personal risk, buried them under his house, and then when we reopened. He
                    said that after the War, he hadn't heard anything. He finally got a letter and
                    he thought it might be a thank you. It was a letter to inform him that the years
                    when the consulate was closed would be subtracted from his years of service for
                    purposes of retirement. I helped, among others, to get him an honor award to
                    recognize his great service during that period.</p>
                <p>Another thing I remember, we had a lot of locals [foreign service nationals] who
                    were on sort of temporary [hire]. I converted all of them to permanent
                    employees. Another thing I first learned that I didn't really grasp the full
                    meaning of until recent years. The first inkling I had—I'm talking about the
                    French occupation then. I was walking with Artisian near the square in front of
                    the opera house and, not using the acronym, but the full words, Artisian points
                    to this prominent Bordelais and says, “That son-of-a-bitch was in the SS during
                    the occupation!” I remember talking to him about it and got the impression that
                    an amount of collaboration and going along was quite prevalent in Bordeaux and
                    there weren't that many people in the Underground. There were people in the
                    Underground. Another time I was with Artisian and he pointed out a little old
                    French lady carrying her baguette of bread going home and he said, “You see that
                    woman? I always had at least one and sometimes three downed American pilots in
                    the basement of her house. She was part of the Underground spiriting American
                    pilots out through Spain.” That was the first sort of eye-opener I had. The
                    extent of cooperation with the Nazis was more than I realized.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's still an issue in France. It's almost one they
                        don't...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>FUNSETH: Sure, they're now addressing it! It was a factor. I remember the deputy
                    of Bordeaux was the sort of super [Gestapo ?] in several provinces. He had a
                    deputy who was a very senior officer, and a talented, attractive guy. If you've
                    ever met any of the French civil servants in the prefectural service of the
                    ministry of Interior. They're absolutely top flight and comparable to the
                    Foreign Service. Competitive, it's considered a real plum. But this guy had been
                    associated with the Vichy regime. So he was capped. He wasn't going to go any
                    higher than he had.</p>
                <p>There were a couple of things, a lot of things in Bordeaux, but of course there
                    are a lot of things you really remember. I remember DeGaulle running for
                    reelection, meeting Chaban-Delmas. I remember when I was acting principal
                    officer, DeGaulle made this gesture to Germany. It was the first big effort for
                    sort of a Franco/German Entente. He invited Adenauer on a state visit to France,
                    the first German Chancellor. There were mixed feelings in France. He wanted him
                    to go outside of Paris. There was no place that was eager to have this German
                    Chancellor, although it was nothing against Adenauer. But again, it was '61,
                    '62, '63. Chaban offered Bordeaux. It was quite interesting, the lead up to
                    Adenauer's arrival. There was a big debate in Bordeaux. I remember going up to,
                    there was sort of an International Club coming out of the EEC, I suspect. I
                    remember this big debate about welcoming Adenauer to Bordeaux. I'll always
                    remember this young French professor stood up and said, “I can't join in any
                    welcome as a Frenchman to a German chancellor coming to Bordeaux. But I can
                    welcome him as a European welcoming another European.”</p>
                <p>I remember Artisian telling me he was coming to work and the bus driver—you can
                    just see this bus coming down this narrow street and the German flags on all the
                    flagposts because this was the road out of town to Modesque's residence where
                    Adenauer was going—is shouting to everybody and nobody: “Every time I see one of
                    these flags, I want to drive my bus into the lampposts and knock the goddamn
                    thing down!” And Adenauer arrived. As acting principal officer, I had the honor
                    of meeting him. I was presented to Adenauer and I realized it was a historic
                    occasion, this arrival of an unknown.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>Another thing that I'll always remember about Bordeaux. Well, a couple of things.
                    I arrived there in September, and November 11 is a big day. (France doesn't
                    celebrate World War II. They celebrate World War I.) There's a suburb right
                    outside of Bordeaux called Tolerance anI was told by the principal officer that
                    Tolerance always laid a wreath and flowers on the remaining graves of the
                    Americans from World War One, and the American Consulate was represented, since
                    1918, in this ceremony every year. I was a new arrival, so I would have the
                    honor of representing the United States of America. The reason I had the honor
                    was it usually was a cold and rainy day. I remember going to Tolerance - a
                    little city hall - and we marched through the streets. Cold, drenching rain. We
                    laid a wreath on the American grave, then on the French, and then went back to
                    the city hall, the auditorium. There was a French liqueur, Perneau, or something
                    like that. One of the highlights of the day was it was all you could drink and
                    all the veterans, and I gave my first speech in French. I remember it was a good
                    speech. Talked about how we're still bound together, the fight for freedom, and
                    all that. The mayor of Tolerance was the town doctor. He got up and gave a
                    speech in response to what I said and said he didn't disagree with what I said,
                    but, “We must also remember the sacrifices.” He remembered, I think it was his
                    father. But the railroad station was on the other side of the river in Bordeaux.
                    They hadn't built a bridge across it. He said, “I remember seeing my uncle going
                    off to Verdun and he never came back.” I think he was the one who said there was
                    a village between Bordeaux and Toulouse. There's a monument. “Every man over 18
                    was killed at Verdun.” It was interesting. First, he was right; remember the
                    sacrifice. But it was also illuminating. Here was this man who had not fought in
                    World War One, but probably in World War Two, and they were defeated in World
                    War Two, but they hadn't forgotten Verdun.</p>
                <p>But it also demonstrated to me within a month or two after I arrived there, that
                    there was great affection and admiration in that area towards the United States.
                    On the Fourth of July, spontaneously, not organized, I remember going down—I'd
                    heard about it but no one had really said anything—driving down to hoist a large
                    American flag in front of the consulate on the fourth of July. American flags
                    all over Bordeaux! Ordinary people had faded flags; banks had flags! We were the
                    only foreign flag flown over the city hall at Bordeaux on our National Day! Huge
                    American flag flying over the city. It was affection and admiration and real
                    genuine feelings towards the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were the American soldiers doing there? This was close
                        to thtime when basically DeGaulle . . .</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>FUNSETH: Very well. Yes, but that was not a popular decision in France.I suppose
                    one of the things I'll remember forever was when I was in Bordeaux, Kennedy was
                    assassinated. You'd probably never forget it no matter where you were, but here
                    I was in Bordeaux, the American consulate. I remember someone called and I
                    turned on the radio and got the news and went down to the consulate. Thought I
                    oughta be there. You know, the good old Foreign Service regulations tell you
                    what to do when the President dies! Anyway, we were in a lovely old building.
                    There are a lot of these in Bordeaux. Built in the 17th and 18th centuries by
                    people associated with shipping - handsome residences - in which the business
                    would sort of be on the first floor and the negotiation or whatever would be
                    upstairs. Well, this building that we were in, the Barkley's Bank building,
                    occupied the ground floor. We were on the premi�re �tage, which had been the
                    living quarters, then on the second floor the bank manager had his apartment.
                    The office I had was registered as 17th Century—a beautiful room! Anyway, I went
                    down there, and as I'm going up the landing, I meet the manager of the bank.
                    Tears in his eyes! Throws his arms around me. Then I remember on Thursday or
                    Friday, it seems to me, I read in the regulations: the black crepe you're
                    supposed to fly on the front. I sent an employee down. All of our employees were
                    in various degrees of emotion. But I remember, I think it was Christianne
                    Lumatay, I sent to the department store to find some black crepe. She came back
                    and told me that when the salesgirl recognized she was from the Consulate, she
                    opened her eyes and said, “Pour le Pr�sident?” Christianne said, “Yes.” And the
                    girl, tears flowing down her cheeks as she measured out the crepe, in memory of
                    Kennedy. We had a line of people that never ended signing the book—all walks of
                    life. We decided to have a memorial mass at the time of the mass that was taking
                    place here in Washington. The consul general decided he wanted it in the
                    cathedral. So I went over and saw the Archbishop. There's another church in
                    Bordeaux that's a very special church. He thought it ought to be there, and he
                    was afraid the cathedral which seated thousands of people—I think it was to be
                    at five o'clock—that people wouldn't be able to come. Because of work and going
                    home; it was an awkward time. We wanted it at the exact time it was taking place
                    here. So he was afraid it wouldn't be full and this would be mistakenly seen as
                    somehow lack of respect or affection which wasn't the case. Anyway, we decided
                    to have it at the cathedral which, incidentally, is the site where Eleanor of
                    Aquitaine was married, across from Jacques Chaban-Delmas' H�tel de Ville. If
                    you've ever been in France, the veterans' organizations, I remember they called
                    up and said they wanted to be there and wanted to form a guard of honor and
                    would we review them? So, we drove over, my wife and the consulate general and
                    the other consuls and their wives and we went to the city hall first and there
                    were some of the guys I'd seen in Tolerance all lined up; most of them from
                    World War One. Then we walked over to the Cathedral. It's 300 years old and it's
                    sort of settled several feet below. I don't know where they found the flag
                    because we provided one. All of our flags were borrowed and indeed I provided
                    the flag that had flown in front of our consulate to put over the coffin that
                    they had, as they do in Europe, for the person to be remembered. They had this
                    huge American flag in the entrance and as we walked into it, you could hear this
                    music being played on this organ—like a hymn. At first, I didn't recognize it. I
                    mean it was familiar, but it was the Star Spangled Banner played by the organist
                    like a hymn. The Cathedral was packed. They had this huge flag for a king, to
                    cover the coffin and a 10 foot candelabra and seated next to it. You just felt
                    that Kennedy's body was there. And then that night there was a rural parish
                    outside of town and they were going to have a memorial service at 8:00 in the
                    evening. The priest called and asked if someone from the Consulate would go. I
                    went out. It was as magnificent as the one in the cathedral. Yet here it was
                    just a rural parish with farmers coming in, and it was packed for Kennedy.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>Q: It's really very difficult in these days to duplicate this. Kennedy was under
                    the new generation. A new hope for everybody. I mean, as realists in the Foreign
                    Service, I've always been sort of amazed. I was in Belgrade at the time and we
                    had a memorial service at the Catholic cathedral, which was small. It was packed
                    with communist officials. The first time many of them had ever been in church
                    except when they were baptized. Did troops cause a problem for you, or not? I
                    mean, American troops.</p>
                <p>FUNSETH: We had no incidents. We took care of their citizenship needs. We had no
                    problems with American military. They were still there when I left. It was the
                    supply line. One of the largest ammunition dumps in Europe was south of
                    Bordeaux. They all come through the port of Bordeaux. It was a logistic
                    lifeline. Then in La Rochelle there was a port.</p>
                <p>The other thing I hadn't—I just thought of it—reminding me, I was a Naval officer
                    in World War II. But in both Bordeaux and in La Rochelle were [these bunkers]. I
                    tell you, they really looked ominous when you see them. These huge concrete
                    things. You can't destroy them. They're built so powerfully. I don't know what
                    they do with them in Bordeaux. In La Rochelle they use them as an underground
                    boat marina. But I mean there's just something stealth-like about them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the communist party? Is it very strong in
                        Bordeaux?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: It was strong in Bordeaux. That's a good question, Stu, because I
                    remember this big election I covered. I was the only foreign consul that
                    certainly did it. But, also having been a newspaper reporter, I suppose, I went
                    to all the rallies. They had big rallies and DeGaulle's Party, and the radical
                    socialists, and the socialist's home . And I went to the communist's. It was an
                    open meeting. Very interesting. They were all held in the auditorium in the city
                    hall. Public auditorium. And the communist, I think, was the last one. You know,
                    you'd go in, and it was decorated with the party flags all over the place. And
                    then, whoever they were supporting—DeGaulle or whomever else. But for the
                    communists, they'd taken down the French Flag and the communist flag was flying
                    over. A different group of people. It sort of reminded me of a volunteer fire
                    department. They had the auxiliary. It was very much of a social thing. Husbands
                    and wives and children and the junior auxiliary. “We have to raise money because
                    we don't have the money that the bourgeoisie and the capitalists do”, I mean the
                    jargon was all different. But there wasn't much talked about Vive La France. It
                    was mostly vive the people. There was a lot of talk of Marxist/Leninism. You
                    know, that famous head of the French Communist party for decades was still head
                    of it.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>I'll always remember at the end of the rally when they were talking about how we
                    need money so our candidates can compete against the capitalists. There were
                    four very attractive young French girls from the Communist Youth League who were
                    collecting the money. They had a hammer and sickle flag and people were giving
                    their money to the Communist party. The communists controlled the labor unions.
                    CGT, the docks and the shipyards. The Marcel Darceau Aviation plant, where
                    DeGaulle was building his nuclear strike force, the “force that flopped”, was
                    CGT dominated. They never were a significant voice. The Bordeaux area was pretty
                    strong DeGaullist and radical Socialist.</p>
                <p>I have to remark on the difference between General Gavin and Charles Bohlen as
                    ambassador. There was a wine-tasting competition, une tasse de vin, or whatever,
                    at this wine drinking fraternity. It was a trade promotion. At the time of the
                    harvest, they dressed in robes. Like honorary degrees at a distinguished
                    college, people try to bring in distinguished people. Huge luncheons or dinners
                    at a chateaux, 400 people, fantastic wine. When Gavin came down—it was the first
                    year I was there. They give you this glass of wine and you smell it and you're
                    supposed to guess what it is, and unless you give the right answer you cannot
                    become a commandant of the vignerons. But it's all part of a joke. I mean, the
                    guy whispers in your ear what it is and you go through the motions and smell it,
                    and then you say what year it is and what the chateaux is. I remember an unnamed
                    person in Paris called me and said General Gavin's schedule was down to the
                    minute. You know, the ambassador arrives one minute, everything minute by
                    minute. Well, the head of the ceremonies was the owner of the Chateaux Gloria,
                    which was then not marketed in the United States. I remember encouraging him to
                    market it because it's across the street from Beshville. It's a darn good wine,
                    but it doesn't sell for the same price. His name was Henri Martet. He also owned
                    the Bordeaux football team. Anyway, I remember telling the Embassy, “You know, I
                    haven't been here very long but . . . I mean, I have no idea. Tell him not to
                    worry about it! When he gets here, we'll tell him. We probably won't decide
                    until that day.” Well, that wasn't good enough for General Gavin. I was so
                    embarrassed. Finally, we bugged them and bugged them and Martet told us what
                    wine it would be and what year, and we conveyed that and the visit was a great
                    success.</p>
                <p>Then Bohlen came. Totally relaxed, you know. The question never came up. I sort
                    of told him to stay loose on it and then, I think it was the chateaux where he
                    was staying. (I think Joan Kennedy was there at the same time). Anyway, he was
                    great. We gave him a background of the chateaux. He was fluent in French. He
                    stood up and went through the whole thing. Swirled the glass around, bouquet and
                    the name of the chateau, and the whole works.</p>
                <p>Q: I take it the whole time there, there weren't any major issues that the
                    embassy was particularly concerned about in Bordeaux, that they were pressing
                    you on?</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>FUNSETH: Well, you know, yes, it was the whole period of DeGaulle, this business
                    of Adenauer coming down was a big event. But we were primarily a consulate
                    promoting trade and commerce, protecting American citizens, and issuing visas.
                    We did weekly political reports on developments in Southwest France, which
                    covered quite an area. Basque separatism. I remember we reported on it when the
                    French still didn't recognize they had a problem with the Basques! And they did.
                    We reported on that, the DeGaulle thing, Adenauer, there were elections in that
                    period. Trade promotion. We were a very good post on trade promotion,
                    protection. We had a lot of American citizens living in the area. I remember the
                    University of California established a junior year abroad at the University of
                    Bordeaux. Very impressive! They had a lot of resources. It was a very
                    interesting</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sounds like you had a good, solid . . .</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Three years. It was a real great, and I've always been very partial on
                    these constituent posts. I remember there was an election there and, because we
                    were closer to what was going on—I can't remember what the outcome was—read all
                    the local papers. We subscribed to every newspaper in the province, primarily
                    probably for trade opportunities, but also just doing your job so you understood
                    what's going on. And absorbing all that. I remember I called the election much
                    closer than the embassy did. We just knew more of what was going on. In Europe
                    you have prominent political figures come back home. I mean Marcel Foureaux, the
                    head of the Socialist Party, was Mayor of a nearby town. Each of these mayors
                    were important political personalities in Paris and they came home a lot. We had
                    more access to Chaban-Delmas than people in Paris did. I thought, in our area,
                    and I'm sure the other consulates did, we certainly promoted trade. We had a
                    good cultural and information program and represented the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll stop at this point now and next time we'll pick up
                        when yoleft Bordeaux.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FUNSETH: Then I became Portuguese Desk Officer in Iberian Affairs anhad an
                    extended period in the Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Alright. Fine. We'll pick that up then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>[interview not completed]</p>
                <p>[end of interview]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
