<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000638">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Ruth Enslie Kotula </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Program Foreign Service Spouse Series</p>
                <p>RUTH ENSLIE KOTULA</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Kristie Miller</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: March 9, 1990</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is Kristie Miller, on March 9, 1990, interviewing
                        Ruth Enslie Kotula at her home for the Foreign Service Oral History.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Actually, even before the post maybe you could talk a bit about your pre-Foreign
                    Service work experience if any.</p>
                <p>KOTULA: After graduating from Fairleigh-Dickinson I taught for — well, I was
                    teaching for l-l/2 years before I went into the Foreign Service, or married a
                    Foreign Service person. He was at his first post, Cairo, Egypt when we married,
                    though not when we met; he went there in April 1966. I had known him for a
                    little more than a year before. At that particular time, we were talking about
                    getting married, but then he was accepted in the Service, at the very lowest
                    staff position that there was, which put him on two years probation; they
                    wouldn't have accepted him had we been married.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was his position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: The earlier designation was FS Staff l4 but they changed it to FSS l0. He
                    was the Pouch Clerk in Cairo, so they wouldn't have accepted him if he were
                    married; that's what we were told. Kirk wanted to go into the Foreign Service,
                    he had been going to school part-time — I met him right after he got out of the
                    Marine Corps. He'd served about three years overseas as Marine Guard at
                    different Embassies, in Tokyo, Kuala Lumpur (Malaysia), and Phnom Penh
                    (Cambodia). When he got out I was finishing college, and he had started
                    attending Fairleigh-Dickinson College at night.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then he went into the Foreign Service, and was in about
                        eight months before you married.Once he was in, that restriction was
                        lifted?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, my parents were in the process of moving from New Jersey to
                    California and there was a possibility that I could move with them, although I
                    was out on my own, with my own apartment, and teaching full-time in an
                    elementary school of the Chester public school system. So it was either a
                    decision as to whether I wanted to go to California, but Kirk and I were in, so
                    I decided to go visit him, in December 1966.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you didn't really plan to get married when you went out
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: No, we had no pre-plans because I thought that two-year probation would
                    be in effect. And indeed, it kind of was, because I went to Egypt, he asked me
                    to marry him, we were married there about three days after I arrived. I had
                    taken a few days off from school and was in Cairo for about three weeks. I had
                    to come back to finish up my teaching contract. That's what I wanted to do,
                    because there were no pre-plans of any kind.</p>
                <p>So we were married. I ended up paying my way back to the States, and I also paid
                    my way back from overseas even though at that point I'd been married for six
                    months. I was due back in Cairo on June 23, 1967. (both laugh) That was a good
                    entry into the Foreign Service because he was [evacuated] during the Six-Day War
                    in '67 and was sent temporarily to Athens, and I met him there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened to the restriction? Why were you allowed to
                        get married?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, the personnel person in Cairo looked it up in the regulations and
                    said, “Well, there isn't any regulation about her if you marry here.” But I
                    wouldn't be picked up as a dependent until the next post. Or, if I had opted to
                    stay in Cairo —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they weren't going to pay your way back for your
                        teaching.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: No. They wouldn't pay my way to Cairo, the second go-round. And I came
                    out tAthens on my own also.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do after that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: (with sigh and laughter) You never had to be the wife of the Mail Clerk!
                    (Interviewer laughs)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what was his next assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>KOTULA: I do remember a humorous thing. Kirk had told me a lot of stories about
                    the Foreign Service. He knew that there were difficulties, for instance, for
                    women.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were aware of that before you were married.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I was somewhat aware of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kinds of things did he choose to tell you? What did
                        he find important?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: (after pausing to reflect)That it wasn't always easy, that there were
                    pressures to do certain things for women to support their husbands as far as
                    their career goes.And I remember one thing that was going on in Cairo at the
                    time. It was about a 300-person post at that time, one of the biggest posts
                    before the '67 War. I was there for less than three weeks, but this was what a
                    lot of the women were upset about: there was a junior FSO's wife there who was
                    very highly trained in nursing and psychological counsel background. She had a
                    Ph.D. and this, that and the other thing. Well, she had taken over [many
                    duties], work in a children's home in Cairo, and the work received a lot of
                    recognition for her paramedic [abilitiates], which received a reward, and it
                    ended up that she had done all the work. And when the award was announced,
                    everybody thought Margie was going to get it. It was given to the ambassador's
                    wife, whom nobody had ever seen on the project. (she laughs heartily) I had
                    arrived right after that happened, and I think every woman who talked to me
                    said, [in angry tone of voice] “This is what happens in the Foreign Service!”
                    This is the thing I found current, that ran for a number of years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which is?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Doing [something for nothing], you do a certain amount of work, you do a
                    lot of work in some areas, and there is no credit for it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Either from the host government or from the American?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Or from the American community within the embassy, you know, the people
                    that you work with. And I think that's probably the hardest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So this woman, Marjorie, never even got recognition, say,
                        from the ambassador or the ambassador's wife for the work she had done?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>KOTULA: Oh, no, no.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you found that that kind of thing was the hardest to
                        accept.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I think it was. And this was in '66, and for the first few years. It was
                    changed in 1972. I was on my husband's Efficiency Report and I was written up as
                    doing whatever I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, in a way, that was recognition -</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: That was recognition, and you know that's the part I thought, “Well,
                    gosh, this is kind of antiquated and this is unfair.” But I also felt a sense of
                    pride that I did get the recognition from that. And I've talked to a number of
                    other women and much as they, some women, didn't like having to do these things,
                    there was also a sense of pride that at least you did get that recognition.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And when the '72 directive abolished that, because there
                        was nothing to replace it —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Again, I talked with a number of other women, I think at first there was
                    a sense of relief. That now we could say “no.” And yet there was that nagging
                    undercurrent, that feeling that how was this going to work. (she laughs
                    suddenly) And indeed, as years went by, nothing changed except that there was no
                    recognition.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You still had to do the work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: You still had to do the work, and that made it worse, that made it — I
                    think that really compounded it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Since there was no legal obligation to do the work, why
                        did we have to do the work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, I think we felt — I know I did, and I know a number of other women
                    I talked to felt — I don't think this is a particularly simple subject. There
                    were a number of things. These are just feelings of my own but also the
                    information gathered from other women. I know I myself felt a high sense of
                    “this is what you do, this is the right thing to do, this is to support your
                    husband's career, and this was part of my role in life.” There is a very strong
                    sense of obligation.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel a sense of obligation only to him or also to
                        the Foreign Service? Did you feel that you were a part of the Foreign
                        Service as a spouse?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes, that was part of it.I don't know whether that was the stronger thing
                    in my case, but that certainly was part of it. There was a feeling and I had a
                    feeling that we were representing our government. That's the way it was and you
                    wanted to do the best job that you could. I guess that's what happens from your
                    having lived through the [John F.] Kennedy years!That was the feeling. This was
                    in '66 and that was still the feeling. A lot of women had that feeling, I
                    think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When your husband was then sent to Athens, what happened
                        after that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, it was interestin(she laughs) because they said I was expected in
                    Cairo on June 23. What happened was, when he was assigned to Athens temporarily,
                    anybody at that point who hadn't been overseas for l8 months — he had been for
                    l4 months by then — was put in a safe-haven place and waiting for direct
                    assignment.And you didn't know how long it was going to be until they found a
                    post for you. He was put to work in the embassy there, and we wanted to know
                    immediately, well, what do I do?</p>
                <p>He was told by the embassy kind of informally, “ Well, since you'rassigned here
                    temporarily, it would be better not to have your wife join you at this point.
                    Wait until you get the new assignment.” I had my own tourist passport, since I
                    was paying my way, so I was very upset by that. I flashed back a telegram, which
                    I still remember to this day that went to the embassy in Athens when I'd
                    received Kirk's correspondence on the matter. I saiGOVERNMENT WON'T STOP THIS
                    TOURIST ARRIVIN(she breaks up with laughter) and giving the flight number and
                    the day. And that was it, I just arrived.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they didn't pay for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: No, well, that's why I felt — they weren't paying for anything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had a non-person status.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: That's exactly what I had. That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Great. So then what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>KOTULA: I think we ended up being there for a month or a little more. Then we got
                    direct assignment to Ankara, Turkey. And at that point they picked me up, I got
                    a Diplomatic passport and a ticket. But in the meantime they wouldn't pick up
                    any personal property, household effects or clothing or anything like that. I
                    had mailed a lot of things to Cairo. Fortunately, the boxes got there and Kirk
                    just never unpacked them. So eventually, six months later, when they finally
                    cleared things out of Cairo, our stuff arrived pretty much okay still packed in
                    the original boxes I had mailed to the APO. I had to pay for mailing other
                    things, too. The stuff going from Cairo to Ankara was covered.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, finally, there you were in Ankara, a full-fledged
                        Foreign Service spouse, what was Kirk's job there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: That's when he went into communications.He became a national
                    communicator.I'll never forget this — he had no training in the equipment,
                    because he was Athens when they assigned that slot and of course I think they
                    asked him if he'd had any sort of training whatsoever and he said, “A little.”
                    But I remember him going in the first day on duty and he didn't know how to turn
                    on the machine! (laughing uproariously) It was, like, he felt mortified. Anyway,
                    he received his training there, on the job, on the spot so to speak.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Ankara for-?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Our direct assignment was for a year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your first post. How was your role there? How did you fit
                        in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, because of the way I came in. In one way it was exciting and in
                    another way I kind of felt like a non-person too still, because I had none of
                    the Foreign Service orientation, for instance. And there wasn't really anything
                    at post. Years later there was the Family Liaison Office, but I remember no real
                    welcoming. I think I recall going to one luncheon that the Admin Counselor's
                    wife gave in her home. All the junior women ended up moving her furniture around
                    every day. (laughter) That was the old Foreign Service, you see! I'll never
                    forget that. You were invited there one time in the year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to paint or pursue your-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I did, that's what I did do. I spent that year painting, and indeed I had
                    a one-person show at the Bi-National Center, and I also gave lectures with
                    slides on contemporary American art history. So I did have that.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You've spoken to me in the past about your feeling that
                        the wives of junior staff people were discriminated against to a certain
                        degree. Did you feel that in Ankara or was that later?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, I'm probably going to be talking a lot about opposites, because
                    there are so many opposites all the way through that I was aware of, that I was
                    always dealing with. And in dealing with opposites, being a very junior person I
                    definitely had the feeling that I did get a lot of praise and approval,
                    especially from the older women who'd been in the Foreign Service longer.
                    Because anything I did — well, the painting, or if I did anything with the
                    different women's groups and being thmost junior woman at the post, anything
                    that I did, or entertaining, was “wonderful.” Because looking at Kirk and what
                    his position was, it was completely non-threatening; and since he was the most
                    junior person in the embassy pretty much for the first few years at several
                    posts, I was no threat to them whatsoever. So for anything that I did I got a
                    lot of praise and a lot of approval.</p>
                <p>But then there was also this feeling on the other side, tha(she gropes for words)
                    — well, I was completely non-threatening.My husband didn't amount to —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel condescended to? Patronized a little
                        bit?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “Look at what she can do!”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: (Laughing) Exactly! So it was always a kind of message with two
                    opposites.I think that message persisted all the way through. As my husband's
                    role changed and he moved up in the FSO corps — he came into the “Mustang
                    Program” in '73 and eventually ended up with consul general, at the last post.
                    So it was a steady move upward. But that message didn't really change-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Even when he was consul general?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: No. Then what happened was, it reversed itself, I think.No matter what I
                    did — because then I did an awful lot of entertaining and women's club things
                    which I did because I felt very strongly were supporting his career, then it was
                    never enough. What happened later on was you didn't get any praise, or very
                    little, and as a matter of fact you got criticism.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of criticism? What kinds of things did people
                        say?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: It was more of a subtle. It's hard to put into words. There was an
                    undercurrent of jealousy. If you did things very well, which made me pleased
                    with myself. I sometimes got the feeling that it was a threat. It was very
                    threatening to some other women.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That they thought you were setting a standard they might
                        not be willing to match?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes. And it wasn't just me doing this. I'd look around and a number of
                    other women that I talked to had these same feelings throughout the year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Once their husbands rose to a position of some
                        significance in the embassy hierarchy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel that because you were college-educated that
                        their thinking of you was as being of your husband's rank? Again, not
                        thinking of you as a person, really, in your own right; that you were just
                        sort of an adjunct to your husband? Your rank was his right or your status
                        was his status regardless of your own achievements?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Early on I think obviously my education and background and achievements
                    were very much appreciated or commented on or noticed. But as Kirk went up in
                    the hierarchy, then my personal accomplishments — meaning my painting, I wasn't
                    really teaching as years went by but I was a professional artist doing a number
                    of exhibits and whatever — although I received some praise and recognition for
                    that, certainly a lot of recognition in a way — it was kind of a two-edged
                    sword. Again. And then much more tied to what Kirk's position was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Almost that it was inappropriate for you to do that kind
                        of thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: There was that feeling at times, yes. Or perhaps you shouldn't be after
                    selling your paintings! (hearty laugh) But this is what I do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's very interesting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes. I mean, selling is demeaning.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Almost as the feeling that if your husband can support
                        you, you don't have to support yourself.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Right. And then the other feeling was — I obviously had my studio in the
                    houses we lived in, so I worked in the home painting on a regular schedule. So I
                    wasn't visible as going to a place to work like some other wives as more and
                    more jobs were opening up for women part-time of what have you in the embassy; I
                    wasn't physically seen as working. What I got more and more at times was, when I
                    would say, “No, I'm painting for an exhibit and I cannot do this, I'd like to
                    but I really can't” or sometimes I wouldn't say “I would like to,” I'd say, “I
                    can't, this is more important to me.” There was an underlying current of “well,
                    you can change your schedule around and do whatever you want, you don't have a
                    real job.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you get this more from Kirk's superiors? Or from
                        people who were under him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I only got this from women.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of the superior officers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That they wanted you to help them with their agenda and
                        they didn't accept that you had another role.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: It was a number of women at the post, not always the superiors, sometimes
                    there would be some very junior women who'd put forth the same feeling.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it wasn't just a status thing, it was just that nobody
                        really considered that you had a real job even though it was pretty visible
                        by —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: It wasn't just me because through the number of posts that I had I saw
                    other people who were artists and other women who were writers or what have you
                    and they [had] very similar feelings. A number of times I thought, “Well, my
                    gosh, why do I have to feel guilty about saying no?” But that's what I ended up
                    feeling. I thought for a number of years off and on, well, maybe it's just me.
                    But, again, I talked to a number of other women, because this as I say really
                    bothered me from time to time. And that feeling was definitely there.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>Nobody was completely honest about it. (after a laugh) That's the thing that I'm
                    trying to get at: the dishonesty about what's really happening; what's really
                    going on after what people are saying or acting like is going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's the party line here? What's the ostensible thing
                        that everybody is saying? That you don't have to work any more because of
                        the '72 directive?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Everybody is saying that you don't have to work any more, and if you say
                    you don't want to do something, that's perfectly fine, you don't have to, in
                    fact we encourage you to be your own person.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's the reality?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: The reality is exactly the opposite. And it can be so much the opposite
                    that I think it can be a pure nightmare. (she laughs again)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Give me an example.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, you can be ostracized. The posts that I've had some of them quite
                    difficult, hardship posts in very isolated areas of the world. There was
                    Antananarivo, Madagascar; there was Dhahran, Saudi Arabia: that was like getting
                    off the plane and stepping into the l3th century.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes! They are very small, isolated posts.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I've not had a large post. I've had very small, isolated posts, and less
                    than half were even what you'd call medium-sized posts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So in these small, isolated posts you tended to feel the
                        pressure even more?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, yes and no. At a really small post, where it was really bad, a lot
                    of time what would happen is you got things that — people pulled together more,
                    and so what you think would be absolutely awful situations sometimes were better
                    to deal with. People pulled together and helped one another more. But you didn't
                    seem to have anything in the middle. It was either really, really good with a
                    group of people, people getting together personality-wise and being able to work
                    together and play together — when you get to small posts like this, you had to
                    have that ability because you worked and associated with the same people all the
                    time; which could be a nightmare if you didn't get along with them.And then on
                    the other hand you had people that you couldn't get along with. So there wasn't
                    much in the middle at a small post.</p>
                <p>Now at a medium-sized post, I experienced more difficulty at medium-sized
                    posts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kinds of difficulty?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: There seemed to be more expectations. Well, okay, at small posts, if you
                    pulled together, there was more of a family spirit, I suppose, so there was more
                    recognition of what you did. At a medium post, that kind of fell by the
                    wayside.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And yet you still had a lot of work to do. You had
                        representation-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Representational work of one kind or another whether or not your husband
                    was in a representational function or job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember that when you were in Dhahran, where your
                        husband was a communicator, you were one of the most helpful people for me,
                        when I arrived. You were the one who took me to meet the General's wife at
                        the military post-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Gee, I forgot about that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was very grateful, because it was my first post, my
                        first real post, the first post where anyone had done any of the welcoming
                        activities, and you took a major part in it, because there was no — not only
                        did the consul general not have a wife, but the DCM didn't have a wife
                        either! You really took the lead. You were kind of filling in the gap.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>KOTULA: You've brought up another interesting point. In a number of my posts this
                    was a recurrent pattern and I don't know whether it became more or less the
                    same. You just mentioned Dhahran, and that was an earlier post, but what I saw
                    was —especially in a small post: Asuncion was one when we were there. There were
                    three officers without wives in the top level of the embassy. So there was a
                    bigger proportion representing the embassy in the women's clubs or different
                    things that the embassy women wanted to sponsor. And also in the mid-level wives
                    to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And that was sometimes you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: For a number of years that was me. Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And again, you were having to do these
                        high-representational-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I wasn't the only one. There are a huge number of women out there that
                    are in that category in the Foreign Service. They don't receive the full
                    recognition for that. A lot of times, if it's representational functions,
                    neither they nor their husbands are receiving money for it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you cope with that? Did you have to use your own
                        outside income?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Oh-h-h-h, in some of the entertaining that we did, yes, we did have to do
                    that. Or you just decided you didn't want to do it and then sometimes you felt
                    guilt(laughing) about that because-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because you would have to dip into your own money.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a very good point. And you say that's not
                        uncommon.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: No, that's the sort of thing that's very common.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And yet if you don't do it, what makes you feel guilty, or
                        who makes you feel guilty if you're not doing it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, it's not just your husband's entertaining, it can be sponsoring — a
                    lot of what I did was opening my home up for women's clubs' groups or special
                    interest groups in women's clubs, or what have you. And of course everybody
                    would volunteer to help with a number of things, but it was stil— it was more
                    difficult to do. For instance, if I were in a large enough house I would have
                    meetings that would be 50, 60, 70 women. It's not like I had a staff. Oh, here
                    it is: the difference for that may not be monetary — well, it was, because if
                    the DCM's wife, for instance, they have a staff to provide all the help and the
                    work that goes along with that. And when a mid-level staff wife does it, there
                    isn't a staff, and we pay for a maid and do the work. And although other women
                    help it's not exactly the same.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that's a very good point.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: And the same thing with representational entertaining in relation to your
                    husband's job, when we always gave a number of parties when it was felt it was
                    needed; especially when it was Costa Rica. I had one maid. We paid for it but we
                    were getting anywhere from 50 to l00 people-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But he was the consul general, right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: He made consul general. And, okay, we could hire bartenders or this or
                    that but it was still a tremendous amount of work that had to be done. We had a
                    representational allowance there but there was no way it began to cover... You
                    couldn't afford to hire somebody and still be paid for the food! (she laughs)
                    That's the way it is.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How do you think Americans rated in Costa Rica as far as
                        representation was concerned?Did you feel that you entertained as much as
                        other posts did, or did you have to entertain more, or were you not able to
                        entertain as much as you thought you should?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I think we entertained a lot more there, because of its location.The
                    ambassador, because of the location and time in the location there, that was one
                    of the huge strains that was put on him. All-l-l-l of the visiting Congressmen
                    because of the location... What was happening in Nicaragua, what was happening
                    in Panama and because that was the meaty place to visit, I think there must have
                    been every Congressman and everybody in Washington you could think of with a
                    plausible reason to go down and see the “war zone.” And the embassy had to
                    provide — oh, it was such a strain those years we were there.As a matter of
                    fact, directives went around toward the end of that, after Gramm-Rudman went
                    into effect, where “we don't have money to do this.” And at times there would be
                    “Would anybody volunteer to house Congressman So-and-So?”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because Gramm-Rudman affected their travel-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Right. It affected their travel and their per diem, and therefore we were
                    asked if we could do it out of our pockets and the kindness of our hearts and
                    our patriotic duty is really what it- (laughing heartily)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You've mentioned before-KOTULA: Well, at Dhahran it was a
                        similar thing. At Dhahran there were no hotels, no place that anybody could
                        stay, whether they were technicians coming in or visiting whatever. So there
                        we were all so happy to see another American or somebody else who didn't
                        live on the compound and that we didn't work and eat and sleep wit(breaks
                        down laughing) that we a lot of times very gladly put up anybody that came
                        off an airplane and brought us outside news and was different to talk to.
                        Well, it was the same sort of thing: we had to do it, sort of.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But it must have been a terrific strain in Costa
                        Rica.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: It was. The time we were in Costa Rica was a tremendous amount of stress.
                    Everybody in that post was under an extreme amount of stress.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were some of the things that made it so
                        stressful?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: There was the policy that was going on at the time... We were there in
                    '84 and left in January '89; under three different ambassadors, with extremely
                    different personalities.The embassy tripled in size during those years.It was a
                    strain to provide services because of all the visiting dignitaries and what have
                    you. There would be at any given time three or four or five or six each week.
                    They would come in and want services and what have you. This was just a normal
                    week there, it was unbelievable. And it went on month after month after
                    month.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then when Gramm-Rudman came in, how did that affect the
                        embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, back and forth there was less money to do things internally in the
                    embassy and still provide the services that everybody felt needed to be done
                    when anybody visited. This is not uncommon, it happens periodically throughout
                    the Foreign Service, but when you get in a money crunch and you have visitors
                    come through post, everybody works. It isn't just the wives. I mean, wives
                    shuffle around wives of visiting persons, keep them happy on shopping tours and
                    this that and the other. And there's only a certain amount of money. So it was
                    happening at the same time with Gramm-Rudman with all the money cutbacks,
                    personnel cutbacks; personnel shortages showing up. Especially in the
                    administrative and consular.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your husband being consul general, how did that affect
                        him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: More strain. He didn't know when one American left in a section whether
                    there would be — maybe there would only a two-week gap between assignments and
                    sometimes there were overlaps — the person leaving and the new person arriving
                    would arrive a few days or a week ahead to kind of get orientated, et cetera. By
                    the last summer of '89 the gaps — what was coming out of the Department was
                    “it's not unreasonable to expect” — and this kept changing, but first of all
                    “it's not unreasonable to expect gaps of a month or six weeks.” And then they'd
                    say — but overseas we were really experiencing double that. And then the
                    directive came out saying “it's not unreasonable to experience three or four
                    months.”</p>
                <p>The two hardest sections hit were administrative and consular. But all the
                    sections began experiencing that. A big reason why administrative and consular —
                    especially consular — was hit is because they cut back intake of new Foreign
                    Service officers in half with Gramm- Rudman. And of course in some important
                    ways Personnel systems supplement consular work, so that that was a shortage
                    there in big part. Another thing was happening too — TDY money was less and
                    less, and TDY positions' money went for when you needed fill-in for Political
                    people but there was no money for covering TDY people for administrative and
                    consular.A whole combination of things, some that I'm not even-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that impact the families that were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Oh! The stress level just went up and up and up and up. As the political
                    situation — well, in San Jose, for instance, that's the third largest American
                    community of retirees living outside the U.S. of any place in the world. Because
                    of our policy, there's a lot of anti-American feeling. Among retired Americans
                    there, a lot of anti-Government feeling. A lot of them were very much against
                    the Nicaraguan policy that we were carrying on at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you had heat from them?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>KOTULA: We had distrust. That doesn't make it all black-and-white either, because
                    a number of retired Americans in Costa Rica were there for various and sundry
                    reasons, like some of them for tax evasio(she laughs) so you had that, too. And
                    then you add on the political situation at the time-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find it hard to make contacts in the American
                        community? Did they tend to be distrustful of Foreign Service people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes. Angry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And with the stresses being brought on, how did that
                        affect morale at the embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Morale was terrible. (laughing) Sure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do for social life? Did you socialize with
                        them, or did you make friends outside of the American community?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I made a number of friends outside of the American community. Being there
                    that long and being active in the outside community, which I really was, through
                    my art and also women's groups. There were three or four women's clubs there, in
                    different varieties. And partly because of my art, too, because I would give
                    talks on different aspects of art. I just thought that was what I should do,
                    too, as representin[trailing off]. But the big thing was distrust, I think.
                    There was that double-edged feeling.</p>
                <p>You're being treated very nice because you are part of the American embassy; and
                    the strongest feeling that you got, the reaction just under the surface, of
                    complete distrust.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You've talked to me in the past about some personal
                        problems that you had in your post at Antananarivo. Do you want to talk
                        about that a little bit?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes. I had a series of deaths in my family. Five deaths in five years. I
                    was an only child. When I went overseas I had both sets of grandparents and my
                    parents were still living.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>When we were in Ankara, Turkey I lost my grandparents on my father's side, within
                    six months of each other. While we were in Saudi Arabia my mother committed
                    suicide. A year later, my maternal grandmother, whom I was very close to, died.
                    And I had an episode where I, because I hadn't done a proper grieving, I was
                    halfway around the world, very isolated, that probably added to the feeling.
                    Anyway, I attempted suicide. I was medically evacuated. Well, actually went out
                    — we left on our own and went back slowly through Africa, I wasn't put on a
                    plane in a straitjacket. (she laughs) But the reality of it was the assignment
                    was broken and so it was the Office of Medical Services which brought me the
                    funds and I went into psychotherapy for close to 18 months, here in Washington.
                    So I had first-hand experience of what the Office of Medical Services does for
                    one with problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And how would you rate what they did?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: That was in '72. The one thing that I think they probably do well is that
                    it's not a stigma. There are lot of personal problems in the Foreign Service and
                    they're very open and it doesn't seem to be a stigma. You have problems, they
                    deal with them and it's over with. And as long as you're deemed okay you go back
                    overseas. It doesn't impact — it certainly didn't then, and it doesn't now,
                    obviously. I think they've become even more open in the last few years.</p>
                <p>So that's a positive. Medically, financially, once you're deemed to have a
                    problem, I think they really go all out to give you the proper help and
                    assistance that you need. The difference between then and what I've just gone
                    through is that there's little concept of helping the whole family, for
                    instance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: It was just Kirk and me at the time. I would think that if that would
                    have happened — now, if somebody has a, for instance, a suicide attempt within a
                    family, it's urged that the whole family get counseling. This is the difference
                    between the approach, the psychiatry, too. So I think the Foreign Service has
                    moved along quite well with that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you want to talk about what you've gone through
                        recently?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, what I've gone through recently is quite like a nightmare.
                    (laughing) In the process of getting divorced from my husband, he's had problems
                    of alcoholism. The Department of State has paid for this and treatment for this
                    and that. My daughter had a suicide attempt and a possible problem with alcohol
                    addiction and depression. She's fifteen.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you feel that their problems were exacerbated by the
                        strains in Costa Rica, where you were living at the time these things
                        arose?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: The problems my husband was having? (after a pause) Yes, without a doubt.
                    I can go back to the time when Gramm-Rudman kicked in. There was a time there
                    when my husband was in the newspaper practically every day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of stuff were they writing about him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Things related to Irangate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why was he involved?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: He was involved with some minor characters. Well, you might say involved
                    but I'd put that in quotes. But the question mark, he wasn't really — there were
                    a group of kind of soldier of fortune people arrested, a French, British and
                    American arrested up on the northern border of Nicaragua; two were Americans.
                    And, of course, he being the consul general had to deal with these two Americans
                    in jail. He was their spokesman.</p>
                <p>There was that involvement that put him in the newspaper. And then there was
                    another character who came into the consulate for consular services who was one
                    of the minor characters bu(she laughs) a major character in Costa Rica. That put
                    my husband in the newspaper every day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So there it is in the newspaper, taking the heat every day
                        for the political situation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Taking the heat for that. And we had several threats — against him
                    personally and several occasions of bomb threats to the house. So you had that
                    and there was constant security. Whether it was made up or real, who knows? It
                    was a tremendous pressure at times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were short-staffed in the Consular Section because
                        of Gramm-Rudman effect. So these three different factors rain on him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Exactly. Part of it has to do with an old problem that's gone on in the
                    Foreign Service for a long time. The last — and this creates a tremendous amount
                    of pressure for people working in the field — when you get into problem areas,
                    o— how can I say it? — the lack of support from Washington, or the lack of felt
                    support from Washington, you don't perceive any support from Washington, whether
                    it's —</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's like the ether: maybe it's there but you don't see
                        it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: That's right. And I think — it wasn't just the fact that my husband was
                    in the papers every day or every week or what have you, in the daily papers in
                    Costa Rica; these went on wire services across the States. But this was in the
                    middle of Irangate and had to do with Iran and he was being interrogated by all
                    different groups coming down from Washington from Congress, FBI, the whole
                    embassy was. Of course, Irangate became public knowledge. That was around
                    Thanksgiving of '87. Anyway, you lefa number of people, it wasn't just my
                    husband, the stress was tremendous in the embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you feel Washington should have done?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I don't know. I don't know whether there's an answer for it, except that
                    the people working there, and it wasn't just my husband, the whole top echelon
                    in the embassy was under a tremendous amount of stress. And the effect of stress
                    did some pretty awful things to some of those people.He was not the only one
                    affected by it by any means. And there wasn't any recognition of this, or help,
                    preventive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like, nobody was sent out to counsel these people or try
                        to — do you think that might have helped?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: The only thing that came out was - of course, the Regional Medical
                    Psychiatrist came through every three or four months, but then when Gramm-Rudman
                    kicked in he was with us for less.He would be there for two or three days and
                    would give little brown bag luncheons on, you know, how to handle your
                    stress.</p>
                <p>I think there's a big need in the Foreign Service for wives. I think the stress
                    at some of these posts, and not just at San Jose but it's absolutely tremendous.
                    I mean, I thought way back early on in the Foreign Service it does — stress can
                    do crazy things to people, make them so whacko, and yet there's no — I didn't
                    get the wives' orientation when I came into the Foreign Service, I did get it
                    when Kirk went into the Officer Corps in '73 and I went to the wives' seminar
                    and some other courses that the Foreign Service Institute offered wives at that
                    time. And yet I had seen up to that point I had certainly seen some extremely
                    stressful situations on posts. When we were in Cair— I had been there only three
                    weeks when that post was under tremendous surveillance. I mean, in Cairo during
                    the '67 War everything was bugged. You couldn't have conversations any place but
                    in your cars or out in the desert, perhaps. Running your car was the only way
                    you could trust your car!</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>In Athens after evacuation the people got together. They'd been in Athens
                    probably three weeks by the time I got there, and they'd still be sitting in
                    little Greek restaurants up in the plaka and whispering, you know? Because they
                    used to whisper in Cairo. Somebody in the group would say, “Why are they
                    whispering?” (both laugh) And they would use funny words for different things,
                    you know, they had a whole code in the way they used to — and then
                    they'[imitating nervous laugh] “Why then, we don't have to do that any more.”
                    The Foreign Service Inspector Corps had come through Cairo at that time and said
                    that they saw more surveillance of the people in Cairo than they'd seen in the
                    Iron Curtain countries that they'd been in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just getting PNG'd must have been stressful. Getting
                        evacuated must be stressful. And even though all this had happened before
                        you took orientation —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: This is the history of the Service. I mean, this has been happening since
                    the very beginning of the Foreign Service. And yet there was no way of dealing —
                    I mean, I didn't even know what stress was. And neither did anybody else there,
                    I don't think. I mean, you never talked about stress, there was never anything
                    on “Stress.” In Antananarivo, Madagascar, I thinprobably one of the things that
                    led to that, probably added to my feelings of isolation there, is that my
                    husband and I arrived in Madagascar after half the embassy had been PNG'd, so we
                    were very much in disfavor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why were they PNG'd?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: That's another whole long story, I'd have to check my facts. And even
                    though we were only there ten months, we were there during the overthrow, the
                    coup started by the Malagasy students. We lived right behind the embassy, about
                    six blocks from downtown; and I can remember one Saturday morning sitting in my
                    living room hearing the machine guns firing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, what is the classic way that the Foreign Service deals
                        with stress?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: You just stiff upper lip and “that's the way it is.” There's this dualism
                    again. You know, “this is the way it is” and a number of people in the Service
                    say, “Oh, this is exciting, this is why I joined the Foreign Service, this is
                    where it's at, this is where the action's happening.” But there is an opposite
                    side. They don't deal with the real terror and how frightening a lot of this is.
                    How can you say... there's a stuffed feelin(she laughs) — I'm out there waving
                    the flag, I'm showing the best there is of our country, and you're not “allowed”
                    to have feelings of being scared to hell, you're not allowed to own the negative
                    parts of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And nobody gives you any help in interpreting them and
                        working through them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: They give you help fixing you up after yo(laughing) fall to pieces, but-
                    (she trails off in laughter).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you feel that perhaps something should be done in
                        wives' training courses or other training courses-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I think that would be an excellent place to [discuss] a lot of this. Now,
                    I think since the establishment of the FLO office, the Family Liaison Office has
                    been moving into some of this but so slowly that it'— I think, at least in my
                    conception, everyone in Honduras that helped kind of make a space in the embassy
                    for [help during this] period; now there's someone in pay positions but that
                    wamy understanding of one of the purposes of the Family Liaison Office, you
                    know, to kind of keep an eye on what the problems are and help in different
                    areas where help was needed and organize that help and bring to Washington's
                    attention the problems going on.</p>
                <p>There is a vehicle there, that's one vehicle that more could be made of. There's
                    a huge need for wives and families to have more orientation about — I mean, the
                    State Department put us through the terrorism thing. Well, that doesn't handle
                    the stress, for me, of being under — how can I say it — they prepare you to be
                    aware of being mugged or kidnapped or sho(she laughs) but that's different from
                    being psychologically prepared for living this day to day to day. I think a lot
                    more could be done and should be done. Every place that I've lived overseas,
                    I've lived behind bars on windows. I've lived in places that were high-crime,
                    except in Dhahran, Saudi Arabia. I had bars on my windows because I lived above
                    the consulate but nobody else did because there was no theft there. All the
                    other places I've lived it's always been a constant. You couldn't leave your
                    house alone, you couldn't do this, you couldn't do that, there was always the
                    threat of being broken into, robberies. And there were security problems from
                    time to time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was another source of stress?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes, that was always another source of stress for me. But I was used to
                    this. That's one of the things about life overseas, one of the things that I
                    haven't liked about the Service at all. You know, you're just expected to lived
                    this way, it “goes along with the territory.” When I came back to the States in
                    1980, that's the way it always was and that's the way I felt about it.We were
                    here for four years. When we went out, the one thing that both my husband and I
                    were struck with, that really bothered both of us a lot, I went overseas
                    thinkin“well, I have to stack the bars behind the windows and I don't like
                    this.” And I verbalized this as “something that I'm going to have to work out
                    and maybe if I'm vocal about i(she laughs) I'll feel better.”Before we went to
                    San Jose in '84, I went to a couple of the newest terrorist things they were
                    giving, thinking, “Oh, boy.” My husband and I knew people personally that ended
                    up in Iran during that problem and were some of the hostages there; so I knew
                    it's a very real thing. But we went back overseas and it was really oppressive
                    to both of us in those four years, the security.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you think maybe they should do more in helping you
                        deal with that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes. Because I can remember both Chris and I talking to a lot of people
                    at post ohow [they] had been treated and there was a huge difference in four
                    years. And yet we'd always lived under [constant] security.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you felt it got significantly worse in that four-year
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Maybe it's paranoia. I'm just throwing the word out there but it's part
                    of the feeling that I got. The threat's there but the threat of the threat
                    became almost a paranoia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because of the Iran situation-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Because of a number of things that were going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At what point did you have your child?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, after going to Egypt, and Ankara, then Dhahran and Antananarivo, I
                    had Kerstin when I was assigned back here to Washington. She was born in
                    '73.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you had several posts without children, and then you
                        had had —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Several what you'd call really pretty hard hardship posts.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you like to talk some about what it's like having a
                        child overseas? Some of the advantages and disadvantages?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I think having a young child is really good. I think there are a lot of
                    advantages to it. The disadvantage all the way through is that you're cut off
                    from your family. That's the disadvantage in bringing up children overseas.If
                    you're overseas for three years at a time, and come back to the States for three
                    years, it's somewhat different. My experience for most of the 23 years was
                    overseas. Basically I only had two State-side assignments — well, three because
                    I was here the ten months my husband was in [Vietnam] — I don't know whether
                    that count(she laughs).That's difficult. The good part of what happens overseas
                    is you make yourself surrogate family relationships. I think that's a good
                    thing, a needed thing, because you are isolated from your family. The children
                    grow up and don't see their grandparents very often, they don't have that
                    feeling of family. That's hard for children. When you get to school age
                    overseas, then you get a few more problems, depending on where you are, because
                    you don't always have the best education. I think enough has been documented on
                    tha(she laughs), but “that's the way it is.” And especially in developing or
                    third-world countries, whatever one's terminology, it's a problem. You just
                    don't get consistent enough education for your children. You can't get that
                    because there isn't an available pool of teachers qualified to teach, and
                    especially not at a salary of $4,000 to $5,000 a year, which a lot of these
                    teachers are still paid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is that anything you think anything can be done about? Or
                        do you think that's like the bars on the windows —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: The bars on the windows. “That's the way it is.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think people are aware of that before they have
                        children and responsibilities? Or do you think it would matter? Or is it
                        just a tradeoff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I think it's a tradeoff, that most people accept. I don't know what the
                    solution to that is.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is there anything you'd like to see the Department doing
                        to support families with children? Anything you think they could do along
                        those lines?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>KOTULA: I think they have made some really good improvements, as much as they can
                    along those lines. They have become more liberal about education away from post,
                    and visitation things back and forth; that helps. Perhaps there could be more
                    things, I haven't done much thinking along that line.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned that your daughter had some problems with
                        alcohol at the time that you were in Costa Rica. What do you think was
                        behind that? Was it something specific to the Foreign Service, and how was
                        it dealt with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Alcohol is a big problem in the Foreign Service, I think. (laughing more
                    heartily than ever)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just for children? Or for everybody?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Everybody.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And why is it a particular problem in the Foreign
                        Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Well, okay, I've mentioned the amount of stress that people can be under.
                    At times, extreme stress. I can go down the list of all the posts I've been to.
                    At times, depending on what was going on, there have been times when — there's
                    always more stress living overseas than there is in the States, that's the way
                    it is, and especially for wives and families.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why is it especially for wives and families?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Because the wives have to — they do this horrendous moving and
                    reestablishing themselves, and there's no way to get around that but it's like
                    you leave everything you have from one post to another or established. If you
                    have anything personal of your own, you leave your friends, but if you have a
                    career, that's a big area. If it's not in the embassy, if you're not part of a
                    tandem couple, then there are problems there, too — continuing making your
                    career, going post to post with your husband that can carry your career upward
                    instead of parallel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But if people like you have a completely independent
                        career, then you have to uproot all that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>KOTULA: I have to uproot all that. Throughout the Foreign Service I've had
                    hundreds of people say, “Oh, it's so wonderful you have such a portable career.”
                    Yes; that is true. However, that is another complete flip side of the coin — the
                    fact that I have to reestablish a market every time I move. And in the number of
                    times I've moved, that gets extremely tiresome and difficult to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You're not just painting, you're selling your
                        paintings.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I'm selling my paintings. I can paint all day, but at one point, if I
                    have a “career”, that means she makes money with it, and you sell. And it takes
                    a year to establish a market. In essence that's what I've found, whether I'm
                    overseas or here- (end of tape)</p>
                <p>Well, for instance, I can see there have to be all kinds of creative ways that a
                    monetary award can be given to women for the work done. It doesn't necessarily
                    have to be a huge salary. One of the big problems is retirements, retirement
                    credits. You can earn Social Security credit and have your separate retirement.
                    There could be some creative thinking along that line, there certainly could be
                    some jobs where maybe the salary wouldn't be greater, there might not be any
                    salary, but I think money could be paid to reach the minimum amount of Social
                    Security credit for that year. Or if it's strictly voluntary work, make more of
                    an effort — some effort has been made at posts — at documenting this volunteer
                    work in women's resumes that they want; I mean real documentation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From the ambassador or whoever is sponsoring her
                        work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Exactly. But make it a more formal process. Because a lot of women are
                    afraid to ask for this, or think, “This is stupid, the ambassador's busy running
                    the embassy or doing his job and waving the American flag, he doesn't want to
                    document my —” Well, make it more black-and-white, so that more women will say,
                    “Well, this is my right.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There would be more routine. As soon as you do something,
                        you'd put it in and get your points.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Exactly. Make it very routine. A lot of women have problems feeling
                    comfortable about, say, “Would yo(she laughs) document my record?”So yes, make
                    it more black-and-white, more routine. There must be a number of other ways to
                    do this, I don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To get recognition and credit for the kind of work you do
                        overseas, the necessary work.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>KOTULA: And, again, I think — now, this can be part of stress management too, a
                    whole area of stress management. I'm still going back to the biggest thing, one
                    of the biggest things that happened in the Foreign Service while I was overseas
                    was real indoctrination into stress effects and how it could be managed. And
                    that could be done here in Washington and that could be done at post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But don't you think that getting some recognition for
                        one's contributions would help reduce stress?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes! That's a big stress-reliever for women, that's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you wouldn't feel so dependent on your husband's
                        identity.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: The older a woman gets overseas, and the less she has of herself, of her
                    own career, she starts to get more and more feelings of “My gosh, I'm getting in
                    my 40s or in my 50s, and if I'd been elsewhere, I'd have had a career like
                    such-and-such now, (laughing) but I don't.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That contributes to one's feelings of stress.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: And the older a woman gets in the Foreign Service and the less feeling
                    that she's had an accomplishment in her own field, or also the more her husband
                    rises in the embassy hierarchy so that more and more she is the consul's wife,
                    she is the DCM's wife, she is the ambassador's — she doesn't even have a
                    nam(laughs) —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And ironically, there's less of this when you're more
                        junior.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Oh, yes, a lot less of this. And I had — there were obviously a lot of
                    receptions in San Jose, Costa Rica, that included visiting Congressmen or
                    high-up specialty people in the Department of State, whether it be whatever
                    agency or departmen— USIS, or the Bureau of Consular Affairs. And there were a
                    number of women who would come through from time to time from Washington,
                    whether with Congressmen or from the Department of State or some other agency.
                    Coming officially or accompanying someone, what have you. These were high-level
                    receptions. I don't know how many times in a year, vis-a-vis women visitors, one
                    of them would ask me, “Oh, and what do you do in the embassy?” And I'd say, “No,
                    I'm a professional artist. My husband is So-and-so.” And that would be the end
                    of that conversation, and it would be very clear what I was thought of. You
                    know, like, “You don't count!” (both laugh heartily) I can understand, but it
                    just adds to your feelings of being a non-person. You get that feeling from men,
                    but I think I've got that feeling from women a lot more.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Especially people from outside the community, visiting
                        people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes. Women on Congressmen's staff who were visiting with the Congressman.
                    I didn't get it from female Congresswomen. I did get it from women working
                    within the Department of State or other agencies who were visiting. Several of
                    them, I recall, were working for the U.S. Information Agency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You think perhaps they could be educated a little better?
                        (she laughs)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I don't know how you'd get over that. But that's just another thing that
                    adds to the feeling “my God, I'm not a person.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “I don't fit into the embassy, therefore I don't
                        exist.”KOTULA: Exactly.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It must be particularly hard to take when you're working
                        so hard for the embassy at the same time, giving the reception and —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I don't think this is something I've made up but again I would see wives
                    who were working as local hire in the embassy at no matter what kind of job,
                    very minimal or quite interesting to have, part-time or full-time. There are a
                    lot more of them now and I can see why a lot more wives want to work as local
                    hire, even if it's a very menial job with hardly any pay, because they get
                    treated better and — wives say this — they're “in with the action,” they feel
                    more important-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then they don't have to go through the stress of
                        reestablishing their career with every move as you do. And if they've got a
                        record at one embassy, I would think that makes them more employable.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes, it makes them easier to hire in the next post they go to; sure. And
                    now there's a large percentage of embassy wives who do that. But what about the
                    wives that don't want to take secretarial jobs or don't want to take something
                    that doesn't fit into any of their skills or any of their desires?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, the Department should be delighted that there
                        are those of you who are doing careers outside the embassy, because if
                        everybody works in the embassy, there aren't going to be enough jobs to go
                        around.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: (laughing) There aren't enough jobs anyway for the number of women.
                    Especially now with Gramm-Rudman there's a cutback on jobs. I do think the
                    Department has made as big strides as they can — some women might disagre— but
                    there have been big strides in kinds of employ for women who want to work. Some
                    women might say yes and no, but I think huge strides have been made along that
                    line. Obviously, there could be more improvement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think the embassy could do anything to help people
                        in your situation who have professions but don't work inside the
                        embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I don't know, I really don't. I don't see how it can be a manageable
                    problem. You can get jobs within the community. I know, when we were in
                    Honduras, I really ran the art gallery. It was in the bi-national center. I was
                    on the board of directors and also did all the arranging and hanging and all of
                    that of the exhibits. But that was a volunteer job. You can get in universities,
                    you can teach if you're an artist or writer even without a teaching degree. But
                    these are outside jobs.</p>
                <p>Handling stress; and actually paying women to do jobs that are within the area of
                    entertaining —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Those are the two big recommendations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Hosting wives of CODELs and visiting officials around, their wives, their
                    families, their dog — (both laugh). And if perhaps it's deemed an important job,
                    some kind of payment for work in women's clubs. I don't know why you'd ever do
                    that, but there are ways that would take the stress off other people who don't
                    want to do that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right. And then the people who are doing it would enjoy
                        it.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>KOTULA: And there are an awful lot of women who do thoroughly enjoy that. Except
                    that they really enjoy it so much that they put all their time in it and they
                    can't help but resent women wh(laughs) and that's what happens.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But if they were being paid, then they wouldn't.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: I don't think they would. And they'd be less prone to do that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And that would relieve stress all the way around, because
                        then there wouldn't be so much pressure and resentment among the wives.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: One area that's not going to be relieved is the jealousy o(long pause)
                    wives' jealousy of other wives. You know, this jockeying for position. “My
                    husband does this-and-that and if youhusband looks like a threat to my husband”
                    — you're not going to get around that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But don't you think there would be less of that if the
                        women had their own jobs and identities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes. What I'm trying to say is you're never going to erase that feeling
                    entirely but you are going to help relieve some of that if women have more of a
                    sense of their own identity. And with that identity has to come recognition of
                    what they're doing, whatever they're doing is okay and it's good and it's needed
                    and it's okay for them to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right. Even if it's not doing representation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KOTULA: Yes.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>BIOGRAPHICAL DATA:</p>
                <p>Spouse: Kirk-Patrick Kotula</p>
                <p>Spouse Entered Service: 1966You Entered Service: 1966Left Service: 1989</p>
                <p>Status: Spouse</p>
                <p>Posts: 1966-67Cairo, Egypt 1967-68Ankara, Turkey 1968-69Morristown, NJ (while
                    husband was in Saigon, Vietnam) 1969-71Dharan, Saudi Arabia 1971-72Antananarivo,
                    Madagascar 1972-74Washington, DC 1974-76Ciudad Ju�rez, Mexico
                    1976-78Tegucigalpa, Honduras 1978-80Asunc�on, Paraguay 1980-84Washington, DC
                    1984-89San Jose, Costa Rica</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>Spouse's Position: 1966-73Communicator 1973-78Vice Consul 1978-86Consul
                    1986-89Consul General</p>
                <p>Place and Date (optional) of birth: Pittsburgh, PA, 1943</p>
                <p>Maiden Name: Ruth Ann Ensley</p>
                <p>Parents (Name, Profession):</p>
                <p>Carl L. Ensley, Prudential Insurance (now Real Estate Investor)</p>
                <p>Alice L. Ensley, housewife</p>
                <p>Schools:</p>
                <p>Mount Lebanon High School, Pittsburgh, PA 1960</p>
                <p>Ashland College, Ohio 1960-64</p>
                <p>Carnegie Institute of Technology, Pittsburgh, PA, Summer 1962</p>
                <p>The Cleveland Institute of Art and Western Reserve, Cleveland, Ohio 1963</p>
                <p>Fairleigh Dickenson University, Madison, NJ, 1964-65</p>
                <p>BA, Fine Arts 1965 and almost equivalent degree in Art</p>
                <p>Earned last few credits (at graduate level) for full certification at Newark
                    State College and Monclair State College 1966-68; K-12 Art Education</p>
                <p>Date and Place of Marriage: Cairo, Egypt, December 21, 1966</p>
                <p>Profession: Art Teacher and Professional Artist</p>
                <p>Children: Kirsten Kim Kotula (1973, Washington, DC)</p>
                <p>Volunteer and Paid Positions held:</p>
                <p>At Post: Dhahran, Saudi ArabiaContract to inventory and refurbish furniture at
                    the consulate Dhahran, Saudi ArabiaTaught art at the Dhahran Academy
                    Antananarivo, MadagascarTaught English to adults at the Bi-National Center
                    Juarez, Mexico; Tegucigalpa, Honduras; Asuncion, Paraguay; and San Jose, Costa
                    Rica .Cost of living report for consulate Tegucigalpa, HondurasArt director, Art
                    Gallery, and member, Board of Directors, Bi-National Center Asuncion,
                    ParaguayTaught art part-time and did workshops for teachers, “Art as a Learning
                    Tool” Turkey, Honduras, Paraguay, and Costa RicaGave numerous talks and lectures
                    on different aspects of art, art history, current trends in art, and aspects of
                    painting and design to various groups and organizations</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>A lot of volunteer time in various women's clubs, damas diplomaticas groups, FLO
                    offices, entertaining at embassy functions in all posts</p>
                <p>Exhibited and sold paintings overseas since 1967</p>
                <p>In U.S.: 1965-67Art Teacher in Chester, PA, Public Schools 1973Contract work at
                    the USIA in Education Research, project on American Architecture
                    1983-84Co-director of Springfield Art Guild Gallery in Springfield, VA
                    1981-83Show Chairperson and vice-president of Springfield Art Guild 1980-84Very
                    active in art guilds' volunteer activities in Northern Virginia, including the
                    Art League 1982Conducted workshops for teachers on “Art as a Learning Tool,”
                    Fairfax County Gave private art lessons intermittently over 20 year period Since
                    1965Exhibited and sold art</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
