<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000685">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Arthur W. Lewis </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR ARTHUR W. LEWIS</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: September 6, 1989</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>[Note: this transcript was not edited by Ambassador Lewis.]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mr. Ambassador, please give us a little of your
                        background, before you entered the United States Information Agency
                        (USIA).</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: Actually, I am a retired Naval officer. I entered the U.S. Navy in 1943,
                    served during World War II, was recalled for the Korean conflict and then
                    remained in the Service until 1966 at which time I retired. It was very
                    interesting because I went into the Navy from Dartmouth College in 1943. I was
                    on an athletic scholarship—football. I had graduated from Stuyvesant High School
                    in New York City, but I was not used to the discipline necessary to study at
                    Dartmouth. I lasted about six weeks after which I left Dartmouth and returned
                    home to join the Navy, rather than to wait for the draft. My last assignment in
                    the Navy was back at Dartmouth as a member of the N.R.O.T.C. Dartmouth, a
                    wonderful institution, welcomed me back as a matriculant student at the same
                    time. So in my last naval assignment as an instructor in naval sciences, I was
                    also a Dartmouth student trying to acquire my B.A. I then entered a Ph.D.
                    program at Dartmouth. I never finished my dissertation. In fact, I got an M.A.
                    out of it rather than the Ph.D. I was 42 years old at that point in time, facing
                    my first daughter's entry into University. The dissertation committee said to me
                    :” We like your subject. We think it will take you two-three years of research
                    and another two-three years more to complete the dissertation”. I just could not
                    afford six more years of academic endeavor at that point.</p>
                <p>I came into the Foreign Service through the lateral entry program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Looking at you Navy career, had you any contact with or
                        interest in foreign affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>LEWIS: My next-to-last assignment before going to Dartmouth had been to the
                    “Strike Force-South Navy Command” in Naples, Italy. While I was there, I was
                    elected President of the European Congress of American Parents and Teachers. One
                    of the things that happened was that USIA invited me to come to “America Hauser”
                    to lecture and talk about with Germans about these voluntary associations that
                    we Americans had. I talked in a number of these facilities and in other
                    USIA-sponsored offices in Western Europe. That gave me a sense of the Foreign
                    Service.</p>
                <p>Having been in the Navy, I had spent most of my time aboard ship. So most of my
                    life had really been spent outside the United States in foreign cultures which I
                    found very much to my liking.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get into USIA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: In 1966-67, the Foreign Service, both of State and USIA, was making a
                    historic effort to make the Service more representative. It was looking for both
                    junior—entrance level—personnel, but also mid-level candidates. I fell into that
                    latter group. I came to Washington and talked to State and USIA. I finally
                    decided that USIA was were I wanted to go because the role of USIA appeared to
                    call for greater interaction with foreigners, rather than the more contemplative
                    approach of the State Department. That to was the reason I chose USIA rather
                    than State.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What training or preparation did you receive as you
                        entered the Service? How well did you feel you were served by the
                        introductory program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: In essence, there was no real training with respect to my entry into USIA.
                    I served for a year as a recruiter. I wrote a proposal to the Ford Foundation
                    for a very special kind of minority recruitment program. The Foundation, for the
                    first time ever to my knowledge, joined with public service institution to give
                    a two million dollar grant to USIA to encourage and to bring into the Foreign
                    Service minority candidates through the “front door” rather than the “back”.</p>
                <p>The program consisted of my seeking out bright young minority students who were
                    graduating from undergraduate institutions. Then, we would bring them to
                    Washington and enroll them in a very special two-year course of training at
                    George Washington University. They would take courses in various histories and
                    social sciences to bring them to speed. They would take the regular Foreign
                    Service entrance examination at the end of their first year and again at the end
                    of their second year. This was based on the assumption that they would not pass
                    after the first year.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>This program worked out very well. Of the twenty students with whom I was
                    involved—ten the first year and the ten I chose for the second year—eleven
                    remain in the Foreign Service today. Of those eleven, eight or nine are in the
                    senior Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you seek these minority students?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: I went to large public and private Universities. I went to Emery, for
                    example, which was graduating its first two black students. I went to Tulane
                    which was also graduating its first two black students. I got one from Emery and
                    two from Tulane. I got some students from Berkeley, some from historically black
                    institutions. We took ten students the first year of whom five were black, four
                    were Hispanic-American and one was Native American. In order to find them, I
                    went to schools from Puerto Rico to Hawaii. We got ten students the first year
                    of whom eight made through that year. The other two discovered that they were
                    unsuited.</p>
                <p>The peculiar aspect of the program that I, who was not a career member of the
                    Service, was extolling the virtues of a Service I barely knew.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about your first overseas assignment. You were
                        the Cultural Affairs Officer in Bucharest from 1969-72. What were your
                        responsibilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: Interestingly enough, I arrived in Bucharest with probably a two-plus in
                    Romanian speaking and understanding. My predecessor had to leave in a hurry. I
                    became eventually in charge of the educational exchange program—the Fulbright
                    program. Subsequently, I discovered that a lot of students were really jazz
                    lovers. So I made a great effort to bring American jazz musicians to Romania.
                    Over the three years, we developed a regular routine of bringing jazz musicians
                    through Western Europe and then Eastern Europe, including Romania.</p>
                <p>Romania was in an expansive state at that time. It was opening to the West and
                    looking for opportunities to trade more with the West. The Romanians wanted to
                    get away from the “ the granary of Eastern Europe” image which they had in the
                    past. The idea of American jazz was accepted by the authorities, even if they
                    didn't really like it. In Eastern Europe, when you deal with cultural
                    attractions, you must deal through State institutions. I spent a lot of time
                    working with these institutions, bringing various cultural attractions, not only
                    jazz, but for example also American plays and other cultural attractions. These
                    gave a different view of the United States from that acquired by a lot of young
                    Romanians. I spent a lot of time working with University students' clubs. That
                    was possible only because the Romanians wanted to change their orientation.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is very interesting because today the Romanians are
                        the hard liners. But in the late '60s and early 70s, Romania was the hope of
                        Eastern Europe and was going in the direction that Yugoslavia took. How did
                        you deal with the local authorities all of whom must have been members of
                        the Communist Party? Were they cooperating under duress or did they seem
                        interested in your programs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: Romania was occupied by the Soviets until 1962. It was under the rule o,
                    who himself was a Stalinist figure. It was 1965 when he died and Ceausescu came
                    to power. It was believed that Ceausescu, supposedly the great liberator, was
                    the great “opener” to the West. Indeed he was, from an economic point of view,
                    but from the social and cultural point, Romania with the strangest kind of
                    openness in its international affairs, was still one of the most domestically
                    repressive Eastern European nations. I didn't think that has ever changed. This
                    fact has become now much more noticeable and much better known. Even in those
                    days, Romania was internally a repressive state. We were probably viewing it
                    with hope rather than realistically. Even though we have had an adversarial
                    relationship with the Soviet Union and the Soviet block, we have always harbored
                    hope of eventual change. That hope has flourished at times; at other times, it
                    has withered. We are a society that strongly believes in change and the
                    inevitability of change. We accept change. For us, therefore, it is normal
                    assumption as we enter into diplomatic relationships with other States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you believe that the cultural program was an assist to
                        that process of change?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: Yes, because, even though the Romanians knew and understood the power of
                    culture and what it can do, they were still willing to allow a certain amount of
                    cultural exchange. I have seen certain cultural attractions taking place in
                    Romania and frightening the authorities. I remember a group called “Blood, Sweat
                    and Tears” which almost caused a riot. They were almost thrown out of the
                    country along with me. The group didn't want to continue its performances in
                    Romania because of its repressiveness, as illustrated by what the authorities
                    did to the young people who wanted to hear them.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>First of all, the group was on the cutting edge of the 60s' modern musical
                    groups. They sang of a kind of freedom that young people saw and felt strongly
                    in the West and particularly the United States. Their music reflected the very
                    vital dynamism on a United States that was going through a profound change. The
                    young people of Easter Europe had heard some of this music on the “Voice of
                    America”. English is the preferred language in Eastern Europe because it is the
                    language of science and technology. At that point, no one yet understood that it
                    was also the language of finance and economics. It was a language that many
                    young people understood and responded to in Eastern Europe. While I don't
                    remember the name of particular songs, they were extremely popular and the young
                    Romanians wanted to hear them. I do remember that in the concerts, the young
                    people got so vociferous in the audience that the authorities stepped on the
                    stage and tried to stop the performance. The musical group refused; then the
                    authorities turned off the electricity so that there was no sound. They
                    nevertheless continued to play and the audience of 15-20,000 arose and began to
                    break up the chairs and lit fires. I was right there wondering what I had
                    wrought.</p>
                <p>Interestingly enough, this episode resulted in a Romanian decision that they
                    didn't want the group anymore. The group decided that it would not perform any
                    longer in Romania. We came to a stand-off. I had a meeting with the group in
                    which it became clear that my 42-year old perception was not too much different
                    than their views which were those of 20 or 21 year olds. I was young at heart. I
                    was able to talk to them and got them to agree to continue the tour if the
                    Romanian government would not interfere. I finally talked to the governmental
                    institution I had to deal with and got it to agree to lower everyone's
                    temperature and permit the tour to continue. If they hadn't allowed the tour to
                    continue, it would have complicated relationships between Romania and the United
                    States. The group had after all come at the invitation the Romanian government.
                    The tensions were calmed and the tour was completed. The group then went to
                    Warsaw and became someone else's problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What instruction were you getting from Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: “Don't let this get out of hand. It is your problem, but don't let it get
                    out of hand”. Ambassador Leonard Meeker was involved in a peripheral way, but I
                    think he was perceived by the group as an old fuddy-duddy. He let me handle it
                    and take care of it. Eventually, we were able to put the pieces back
                    together.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is what diplomacy is all about: tensions between
                        sovereign states created by a young rock group and Communist
                        authorities.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: You never think of it in that fashion. Even putting the pieces back
                    together within the American community representing different generations was
                    difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have many touring play groups and did have to be
                        careful about which plays were presented? Or other cultural events?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: Yes. We had a couple of Thornton Wilder plays which were better received
                    because they were held under University auspices and the people who attended
                    were mostly University students majoring in English or literature. They didn't
                    have the emotional content and velocity of musical groups. Somehow music is a
                    most powerful instrument. That is one lesson I learned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your next assignment was as Public Affairs Officer—the
                        chief USIA person—at the U.S. Embassy in Lusaka, Zambia. How did this
                        assignment come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: During my graduate academic programs in sociology and government affairs,
                    I became interested in economic development, particularly in Africa. That became
                    my academic area of concentration. I wanted to serve in Africa. When the
                    discussion began about my post-Bucharest assignment, I was informed that I would
                    not be sent to Africa, but probably to Mexico City or London. There had been
                    mounting complaints that blacks were being shunted off to Africa. Frankly, as I
                    said, I wanted to go to Africa. It took a lot of pushing and strong urgings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were the complaints coming from? The African
                        countries or the American black community?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: I have never had an African tell me he would prefer to have a white
                    diplomat, but on the other hand, I have heard from non-Africans that Africans
                    have expressed a preference for more white American diplomats because black
                    American were second-class citizens. I am not sure I believe that story. A lot
                    of complaints were coming from the American black community who believed that
                    black diplomats were being stereo-typed by being sent to Africa and not to
                    Western Europe or the Far East. Although blacks did serve in Western Europe, in
                    Eastern Europe, the Far East and Latin America, the bulks of blacks could be
                    found serving in Africa. I think that Personnel just had to find bodies for
                    these new Embassies in Africa wherever they could. Many of the new bodies that
                    were coming into the Foreign Service at that time were black Americans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also of course there was the other side of the coin. Many
                        Foreign Service officers, black and white, saw opportunities for advancement
                        by being assigned to these new embassies in Africa. They could be “somebody”
                        in a small Embassy whereas in a large Embassy, they might end up as
                        “nobodies”. Professionally, you could probably climb the ladder faster
                        sticking to the African or Near East circuits than elsewhere. Of course, the
                        outside doesn't always understand these Service features. Was Zambia itself
                        your target or were just interested in Africa in general?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>LEWIS: Actually, there was position in Tanzania that greatly interested me.
                    Unfortunately, that did not work out and Zambia became the next possibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You served in Lusaka from 1972-74. What was the situation
                        in Zambia at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: Economically, the situation was that the government of Kenneth Kaunda had
                    just nationalized fifty-one percent of the Anglo-American copper mines in the
                    northern province. The government was beginning to flex its muscles in a number
                    of ways with respect to central planning and control of the economy. It was kind
                    of socialism, even if it wasn't called that. It was not an ideological socialism
                    in any sense of the term. It was that the Government felt more capable of
                    managing large economic entities centrally. The benefits would be more
                    wide-spread to the people through the government if the Government owned the
                    controlling interests. At the time, the price of copper was fairly high; at the
                    time, Zambia was—and still is—one of the major enemies of South Africa and its
                    apartheid system. Zambia was still a multi-racial society. All in all, during
                    the early 1970s, things were going quite well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a tribalism problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: At that time, not really. Certainly one understood that there were
                    different ethnic groups and that some of them were more represented in
                    government than others. But it was not really a problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were American interests in Zambia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: American interests were in the success of an independent Anglophobe State,
                    the continued American access to the copper mines, the opportunity to show to
                    the rest of black Africa that we were ready to sit down with any independent
                    black African state to assist in its development.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the Embassy saying internally about Kaunda?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>LEWIS: We were observing how foolish he was to have nationalized the mines. He
                    didn't have the skills to operate the mines. Certainly, we felt some sympathy
                    for Zambia because in 1973, Southern Rhodesia declared its Unilateral
                    Declaration of Independence (UDI) and closed its borders with Zambia. Zambia is
                    a land-locked state and this action made it increasingly difficult for Zambia to
                    ship its copper, forcing it to use Tanzania. The railroad that the Chinese
                    Communists were building was not yet finished. So its was a very crucial and
                    delicate time for Zambia. We certainly wanted to be of assistance. We were
                    trying to help rebuild the railroad from Dar-es-Salaam that went through to
                    Kitwe because that was the way fuel and other supplies came in. We had to fly
                    fuel from Zaire and from Dar-es-Salaam for a while. Our relations with Zambia
                    have always been somewhat tenuous because we always had the feeling that Kaunda
                    didn't know what he was really doing or that exercised his authority well in
                    centralizing the economy of the country. While it never showed in a large and
                    clear way, there was always a feeling in the background that we shouldn't put
                    too many of our eggs in that basket. I think that Kaunda and the Zambians knew
                    this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was our Ambassador at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: When I first got there, Oliver Troxel was the Ambassador. When I came from
                    Romania, Troxel wanted to interview me before agreeing to the appointment. I had
                    to come from Bucharest to Lusaka for an interview. He left shortly after I
                    arrived and was followed by Jean Wilkowski.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did Ambassador Wilkowski run her Embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: With an iron hand. It was clear who was the Ambassador—there was never any
                    doubt about that. Jean was also clear with me that my contacts should not
                    include ministerial level persons, which were hers. Unfortunately, I played
                    tennis with the Foreign Minister and a number of other ministers and drank beer
                    with them. That didn't endear me with her.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did this impact on your work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: I didn't let it impact on my work. I did not seek out Vernon Mwange who
                    was the Foreign Minister. Or Lubia, who succeeded him as Foreign Minister. We
                    played tennis together; they would drop by the house; they would invite me to go
                    places with them. It really didn't effect my work; it was just an irritant to
                    her and to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What type of work were you doing? What were your
                        concerns?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>LEWIS: My major concern was to move the USIS out of the terrible dump where it
                    was located. We were then in the central arcade of Lusaka, right on Cairo Road,
                    which is the Cape-to-Cairo road. While it was a wonderful location because there
                    was a lot of human traffic in the area, it was still very bad because the
                    building in which we were was in dire need of repairs—in fact, it really needed
                    to be torn down and rebuilt. Then we had a couple of beatings and murders right
                    on our door-steps and those activities are not conducive to cultural and
                    educational programs we were trying to conduct. So one of my major concerns was
                    to find someway to relocate USIS, but in an area where it could continue to be
                    in the main-stream. That took a lot of doing because it meant you had to find
                    out who was building, where, who really owned the building and then to find that
                    person to negotiate a lease.</p>
                <p>A lot of my time was also spent in working at the University of Zambia—the Lusaka
                    campus. We were helping them to build the faculty and I developed a
                    faculty-enrichment program in which we would take some of their young faculty
                    members and assist them in acquiring advanced degrees through the Fulbright
                    program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did find yourself in competition with the English who must
                        have had a proprietary view of Zambia? Or did they cooperate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: There was very little competition because the Vice-Chancellor of the
                    University was American-educated. He set the tone at the University. Over the
                    years, as a USIA officer and then as an Ambassador, I always made it a point to
                    become involved in the national university of the country to which I had been
                    assigned. My wife, who is an African historian and had been the deputy director
                    of African studies program at Northwestern, has taught in countries to which we
                    were assigned. It has been a very difficult time for her because she has done it
                    without recompense and without being in a career ladder. I have always attempted
                    to become involved one way or another in the national university.</p>
                <p>What has become very clear to me is that the philosophy of education in America
                    and the philosophy of education in the U.K. are very different. Our education
                    prepared the individual to be a practical member of society—a person who was
                    willing to wear a white shirt to the office, but who would roll up his or her
                    sleeve to do the work necessary to accomplish the task embarked upon. European
                    education, particularly the British, on the other hand, to a large degree
                    provided people with very sound foundation with less of a desire to become
                    practically involved in the life that they were going to have to face in a Third
                    World country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this seen by those the decision-makers in Zambia?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>LEWIS: I don't think so. At that time, the National University was one of the
                    government's expenditures that had to be made. There were only a tiny number of
                    university graduates in Zambia at that time. There was a push to get people
                    through university and particularly Zambian University. Certainly, there was an
                    interest on the part of the government in the University and in creating an
                    institution and an environment which would train people to do the kind of things
                    that needed to be done in Zambia. For example, the Vice-Chancellor of the
                    University knew very well that an American-oriented education was going to make
                    people who would be willing to go down in the trenches to work and who would not
                    feel, despite the fact that they had a degree and not only a certificate, that
                    they had to sit in an office and could not become involved or engaged.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Surely, the guarantee of a secure, high income,
                        not-much-work position in an office must have had some attractions. Did you
                        see much of that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: Certainly the students knew that the completion of higher education was a
                    passport into a much better life for them, much more comfortable, access to
                    things that they never had before. I don't think it was as bad then as it is now
                    because now students really don't have jobs waiting for them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was America popular at that time with the Zambian educated
                        class?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: Yes, America was and is popular in Africa. We have as a nation a residue
                    of good will in Africa that can only be exhausted by thing that the U.S. I don't
                    think is capable of doing. The whole idea of having been the first colony to
                    have engaged in a revolution for its liberty and independence is a powerful
                    asset. That idea for African states, all of which except Liberia and Ethiopia
                    are new states, is an objective. The growth of a state which came into being
                    through revolution against its colonial oppressor or power, is a most powerful
                    model in Africa.I would presume that it might so also in other Third World
                    areas. But I know that in Africa, that carries with it an immense amount of
                    emotional, ideological baggage. Also America is known in Africa as a country in
                    which the mistakes of the nation are debated, surface and come out. There is a
                    dialogue between the public and the private that doesn't exist in other
                    societies. Also, America is perceived as a multi-racial society in which the
                    most significant minority is black—comes from Africa and has African roots. All
                    of these things are very powerful elements in creating in the African minds a
                    very positive image of America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any problems with Zambian bureaucrats who had
                        grown up in the British system and saw the Americans as upstarts and a
                        threat?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>LEWIS: Yes, among the older Zambians who were in the system and in positions of
                    importance certainly could view the way we did things as the ways of an upstart
                    nation. I have served in a number of Anglophonic countries and have observed
                    that even though there is a general dissatisfaction with a society which is
                    developing out of the British model, there are some aspects of it which remain
                    in the mind and hearts of the citizens of the Anglophone countries. For example,
                    no trip begins or ends except through London. For a long, long time, many of the
                    civil services of the newly independent Anglophone African countries, provided
                    for an annual trip or for a long leave every two or three years to Britain. I
                    remember being a member of a dining club—that peculiar hoary institution that
                    the British have foisted on many unsuspecting Third World countries—men only,
                    tuxedo required for dinner on Saturday night, usually once a month—in which the
                    evening was devoted to a formalism in which the events were known beforehand.
                    Among the events, for example, was a period during which all who had been away
                    and therefore may have missed a meeting, had to rise and report where and what
                    he had done. I will forever remember this wonderful African doctor talking about
                    having spent a wonderful summer “at home” in green, lush Ireland. For him, in a
                    sense, that was home. We don't have anything like that with respect to how
                    people feel about America, except in Liberia perhaps. Indeed while I consider it
                    a hoary kind of institution, certainly it binds people to a way of thinking and
                    a way of doing things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where there any problems while you were there over the
                        Vietnam war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: Yes and no. We were disengaging and it certainly was a period in which the
                    relations with the U.S. were dotted with little hiccups here and there with
                    respect to Vietnam. More importantly, it was period in which Watergate came to
                    head.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they understand what was going on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: No one that I could speak with felt that they ever wanted to be in a
                    position of authority in the U.S. if that was the way Americans treated their
                    leadership. They thought that something was really wrong. How could a society
                    treat its leader that way? It was expected that leaders would have foibles and
                    that they would be entitled to do things that ordinary citizens could and should
                    not. I was really struck by the shallowness of people's understanding of
                    democracy. This was a world-wide phenomenon. There appears to be no universality
                    of ethics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think all of in the Foreign Service had a difficult time
                        explaining Watergate. We considered the developments as a positive step for
                        democracy, many of our foreign contacts thought we were destroying
                        leadership. They were willing to accept conduct that the U.S. was not.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>LEWIS: Looking back on it, ironically that ability of Americans for
                    self-examination has always been perceived as the great strength of the American
                    society. But the attack on our leadership made a lot of people in the African
                    countries, where I served, uncomfortable. It was very difficult for them to
                    comprehend, even though they saw it as a major strength of our society.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went from a country with a relative tranquility to a
                        very difficult one: Ethiopia. You were there from 1973 to 1977. Did you
                        volunteer for this assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: I was ordered to go. For me, it was certainly an advancement because the
                    position was at a higher rank than I was. It was a much larger post in terms of
                    personnel, funds and branch offices-We had a branch office in Asmara and reading
                    rooms in six regional capitals. It was an opportunity to go to a country which
                    was terribly exciting and had the longest history in black Africa. The
                    assignment could not have come at a better time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The political situation was, euphemistically,
                        “challenging”.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: It is like Chinese telling you, “may you live in interesting times”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Ethiopia in September, 1973 when
                        you arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>LEWIS: There had a just been a drought in Welo province which is in the Ethiopian
                    north. This drought had been probably responsible for the death of a quarter of
                    a million people. This was not the first drought that had struck Welo or that
                    had struck Ethiopia. There is a cycle of droughts that occur there and about
                    every 20-25 years you have these massive droughts, which someone mordantly said
                    were like birth control because you lose a quarter of a million people—no one is
                    quite sure of the numbers. The Emperor in his traditional fashion continued as
                    if the drought did not exist. One of his grand-daughters was getting married. At
                    the height of the drought, a cake that costs 3,000 pounds sterling was brought
                    in. In taking it off the plane, in Addis Ababa, it cracked and was thrown away
                    and another cake ordered. There was a British TV producer and cameraman who
                    happened to record the cake caper. They also recorded scenes in the Welo area,
                    with children dying. They also taped scenes of the Emperor throwing scraps to
                    his dogs and the zoo animals that were kept at the palace. Earlier in the year,
                    the teachers and taxi drivers in Addis had gone on strike. There was a lot of
                    unrest in the country. We were the major aid donors to Ethiopia. It is said that
                    we did not respond to the drought with adequate force. It is said that for
                    political reasons, the Emperor wanted this to happen and we allowed it. I am not
                    sure about that. There were a number of things happening. Down in the Southern
                    desert of Ethiopia in a place called Negilly, there was a mutiny on the part of
                    some enlisted men against their officers over water. This was one of the first
                    cracks in the formal institutional apparatus of the government. The Royal family
                    members who were members of the Emperor's cabinet were being replaced with the
                    hope that someone could pull the threads together. It was beginning to become
                    clear that changes were taking place and something was happening.</p>
                <p>Shortly after I arrived in September, the Emperor was arrested at his palace by
                    members of the military—the Derg. This supposedly consisted of 120 military men.
                    Shortly after the Emperor was arrested, a number of the royal family were also
                    taken. A number of the “old guard” were executed one Saturday night. Changes
                    began to take place; neighborhood organizations were set up; our political and
                    military relationships began to deteriorate. Finally, our relationships went
                    down to zero. Ethiopia became less important to the U.S. because the listening
                    stations, particularly the one in Asmara, we had were overtaken by newer
                    technological means. We no longer supported the military and our cooperation
                    with the Navy went down to tube.</p>
                <p>The next thing we knew is that the basis for our relationship with Ethiopia
                    changed completely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As Public Affairs Officer during an interesting period,
                        what instructions were you receiving? Were you being advised to be
                        aggressive or reactive?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>LEWIS: It was a little bit of a roller-coaster which we couldn't get off.
                    Kissinger was Secretary of State and in the global scheme of things, Ethiopia's
                    importance diminished. There were no instructions to try to preserve
                    relationships nor instructions to allow relationships to deteriorate. It was
                    “che sera', sera'”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There wasn't any dynamism either from State or USIA. No
                        sense of urgency to solve a problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: No. We felt somewhat adrift. For a lot of the time, we didn't have an
                    Ambassador. There was Parker Wyman first, then Art Tienken as Charg�. He was
                    there when I got expelled.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you describe the USIA program when you arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: It was a program heavy on information and educational exchange. We had in
                    Asmara a fairly large USIS center—that was the Italian speaking part of
                    Ethiopia. We had reading rooms, which were basically medium-sized libraries in
                    six provincial centers (Gondar, Dese, Makeli, Harar, Welo and Tigre). The
                    purpose of this program was to provide information. We understood from the
                    beginning that something was happening to the Emperor; that feudalism was coming
                    to an end and that some preparation had to be made to try to help the country
                    and its people prepare for the giant step which had to be taken. Information
                    about the modern world was absolutely essential. My reading rooms and libraries
                    played a very crucial part. We made available a lot of material about
                    agriculture and basic health. The AID program was quite large in those days—one
                    of our largest programs in Africa. We were also involved deeply in educational
                    exchanges—bringing American to teach in the Universities there and sending
                    Ethiopians to get further education in the United States. Essentially,
                    information and educational exchange were the two major thrusts of my operation.
                    We did have one or two cultural events: one was a musical group which came and
                    gave a concert with the proceeds given to drought relief. A lot of money was
                    collected from that concert.</p>
                <p>My biggest job was getting around the country to the different places, providing
                    reassurance that we would continue this or that program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were a member of the Country Team. You probably
                        traveled more than the others because of your job. Did you notice a
                        deteriorating situation in the provinces or was the uprising confined mainly
                        to Addis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: The situation in the provinces as a matter of fact was relatively stable.
                    The real difficulties were in Addis and Asmara. Those took place once the
                    Emperor fell. It didn't take long for the situation to collapse.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the arrest of the Emperor surprise everyone or was it
                        anticipated?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: It was a surprise. No one really thought that the Emperor would be harmed.
                    No one really understood. As I look back on Ethiopia, it was a society which was
                    fatalistic. It was a society in which violence was just below the surface. I am
                    not sure I or anybody else could have said that then or could have perceived it.
                    We didn't understand what was going on in Tehran until it was too late. Same in
                    Addis. The institutions—so called— of government had reached a point at which
                    they could no longer be supported by feudalistic society.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is undoubtedly difficult for foreigners to perceive a
                        revolution coming, particularly when the ruling group is also blind. Did
                        your contacts change after the Emperor's demise?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: Yes. The original contacts that I had made were arrested or escaped from
                    the country because they were about to be arrested. One of the strange things
                    that happened was that I became the informal link between the Derg and the
                    Embassy. This came about because one of my local employees suggested to me that
                    I really should go up to the castle to meet the head of the derg's public
                    affairs operation—a Colonel Asarat. I decided I would do that. I didn't check
                    with the Embassy—we were downtown and the Embassy was in its compound above the
                    city. I went and he received me. We talked for a long time; he introduced me to
                    his deputy—a young major—who knew all about USIS because before joining the Army
                    he was a shoe-shine boy right in front of our building. The major was later
                    killed in a shoot-out and was succeeded by his deputy with whom I remained in
                    contact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the fact that you were a formed naval officer help
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: I don't think so. It was probably just the fact that I made the effort to
                    talk to them and that came without any preconceived ideas of their ways of doing
                    things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Derg seems to have been somewhat of a mystery to the
                        Americans. Did you use it for your regular communications?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: I talked with them. As some of my Eritrean employees were arrested, I
                    would go to the Derg. Nothing ever happened, but at least I had a contact in the
                    Derg. Most important for me was that the Embassy was given a diplomatic note on
                    a Saturday which expelled me and all the Americans in USIS. My contact warned me
                    about that note on the previous Friday night.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was in 1977. You had been in Addis for sometime by
                        then. What were your views of your program between 1973 and 1977 as the
                        local situation was changing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: The impact of the change on our operations was significant. First of all,
                    my center in Asmara was bombed twice. Then Asmara was put under siege by
                    Eritrean Liberation Force (ELF) and I was caught there for three weeks. It
                    became clear that we could not sustain that operation and we closed it down
                    temporarily. The fighting in Welo and Tigre and Gondar closed down my reading
                    rooms there. From time to time, my center in Addis Ababa was harassed—once a
                    fire-bomb was thrown through the window.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were the perpetrators? Eritreans? Tigrenians? Members
                        of the central government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: It was probably the Eritreans and Tigreans who wanted to use the incidents
                    as an opportunity to bring to public attention their dissatisfaction with the
                    Derg.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the local employees? Were they harassed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: Certainly my Eritrean employees were harassed. A number were arrested and
                    imprisoned. The secret and military police would come to the center to take
                    people from their offices. We tried to stop them, but it was impossible. Across
                    the street from us was City Hall which was bombed, shattering the glass in our
                    offices.We did not operate a normal USIS program during this period. We
                    published and distributed a lot of printed material.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With all the various factions in Ethiopia in those days,
                        were you not charged by one or all as putting incendiary propaganda?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: The charge that was levied against me in support of my expulsion was
                    “conduct inimical to the growth of socialism”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sounds like you were doing the job right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: That was what was printed in the newspaper when my expulsion was
                    announced.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Embassy try to use AID or USIS to bolster our
                        position?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>LEWIS: I don't think so because we had a large military contingent in Ethiopia
                    which was being reduced rapidly. We had a Naval medical team who were at the
                    Pasteur Institute. The Embassy had at its disposal a number of elements which
                    were in the community and which were not closed off as the Embassy itself was in
                    its compound. We had a large compound in Addis in which the Chancery and the
                    senior officers' residence stood. These people did not live in the community,
                    while the rest of us lived and worked did. The military was sent home fairly
                    quickly. It became clear to the Derg that they were not going to get ammunition
                    and military support from us. A lot of that took place in the context of the
                    Somali attack on the province of Bale in the south. After the Derg came to
                    power, the Somali nationalists attacked Ethiopian positions in the southern part
                    of Ethiopia. The Ethiopians went through a most perilous period during which
                    they almost lost all of that area—the Ogaden. Because of the relationship with
                    the U.S., we did not make the kind of efforts that normally would have been
                    expected to be made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Embassy recommending some actions and not being
                        given any guidance from Washington or did the Embassy prefer to stay out of
                        Ethiopian affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: To the best of my recollection, the Embassy's recommendations were to be
                    more activist than the Executive Branch wanted to be. A lot of it had to do with
                    the way policy-makers in the State Department perceived Ethiopia—how important
                    was it in a global context? We know that during the Kissinger period we saw
                    things in a global context rather than regional. Therefore, Ethiopia became a
                    “second-hand” player or less of a player because of the globalization of foreign
                    policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In retrospect, was there anything that could have been
                        done, public affairs-wise, that might have made a difference and perhaps
                        improved US-Ethiopian relationships?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: I doubt it. What happened was that we changed places with the Soviets. We
                    sided with Somalia and they left Somalia and came to Addis. The die was cast at
                    that point because Mengistu was emerging as the power in the Derg. There had
                    been two major shoot-outs within the Derg: the first was when General Addam, who
                    was very popular, was killed supposedly by Mengistu or his aides and the second
                    when General Bayu, who was the acting head of state, was killed. After this
                    second shoot-out, it was clear that Mengistu was getting advice and counsel from
                    the Soviets. Within a short period of time, there was a flip in Ethiopian
                    foreign policy.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>The Soviets had responded very quickly to Ethiopian requests for arms, which they
                    felt would profit them. They certainly were not profiting in Somalia. Somalia
                    had been a morass for them. The Ethiopians had been able to maintain military
                    superiority with our assistance until we stopped providing that assistance with
                    the advent of the Ogaden war. Once we went to Somalia and the Russians to
                    Ethiopia, the possibility of any positive actions in a public affairs context
                    became even less possible. The most positive thing that ever happened in that
                    period was when the Soyuz and Apollo space-crafts hooked up together. We showed
                    the movie at the USIS center. The Soviet Ambassador and couple of his staff came
                    and we had a public handshake between Americans and Soviets. But that was about
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the Soviets active in the public affairs field?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LEWIS: Not really. They weren't doing much because they were busy making certain
                    that the politico-military relationships were staying in good shape. There was a
                    political struggle going on concerning the direction of the revolution. There
                    was the creation of ?????? which required the transfer of young people from
                    Universities—Universities were closed—to parts of the country to educate farmers
                    and provide literacy and agriculture training. The purpose of this forced
                    migration was to break down the various ethnicities that had developed in the
                    feudal context of the country. The Showas and the Amharans had become one thing,
                    the Tigreans and the Eritreans another. The Derg sent Eritreans south to the
                    Aroma country, the Aromians north to areas where a different language was
                    spoken. There were cultural differences which manifested themselves in physical
                    violence against the students.</p>
                <p>All of that was going on at the time of declining US-Ethiopian relations. So it
                    was not a propitious time for a public affairs program.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
