<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000774">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Philip R. Mayhew </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>PHILIP R. MAYHEW</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 26, 1995</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wonder if you could tell me a little bit about your
                        background: when, where you were born and something about your family.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I was born in the Presidio, which is a military base in San Francisco. I
                    lived there for the first few years of my life. Then, at a rather young age,
                    went to the Philippines for 3 or 4 years. I think we came back about 1940. Then
                    I grew up in Spokane, Washington and various other locations with military
                    bases, ending in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, from which I went to college at
                    Princeton. After Princeton I was a trainee in a Wall Street bank for a year,
                    then in the military service, and then went to work after that for the
                    Washington Post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to go back for a minute. Was your father in the
                        regular army?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was his specialty?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: He was an ordnance man. He was Canadian, actually, and left home after
                    high school, not wanting to stay on the farm in Quebec. Eventually he ended up
                    in the western United States, then joined the American army.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you tempted to join the army at all, as a
                        career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: No, not really. I never had a great interest in that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went to Princeton, you graduated from there in
                        1956.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: That's right.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your major?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: English, graduated with the highest honors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did that tempt you to get into writing, or anything like
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Well I really did not want to be an academic. My parents had both died:
                    one when I was 14, and one when I was 16. So after graduating I thought I ought
                    to get a job somewhere. A businessman seemed to be the most likely thing, so I
                    went to work as an investment trainee for First National Trust Company, which is
                    now part of Citicorp.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But then you ended up in the Marine Corps for a while,
                        didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Spent a couple of years in the Marine Corps as an alternative to being
                    drafted. Then not wanting, particularly, to go back to the banking
                    business—which I found was awfully dull—I went to work as a copy boy for the
                    Washington Post. I think the salary was about $50 a week. Then I became a staff
                    reporter, doing all the things that young reporters do: obituaries, police,
                    rewrites, and some features. But I wanted to go overseas. At that time the
                    Washington Post had not expanded overseas the way it subsequently did. So I
                    decided that I would try for the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How had you hear about the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Well, I don't really recall now but it must have been in the atmosphere
                    of Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You took the Foreign Service exam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was in 1961?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I came in March '61. The exam was probably in 1960.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were right in the first wave through the Kennedy
                        era.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you in your class, when you were getting trained, did
                        you get any feel for the enthusiasm about Kennedy, and all that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I don't think so much it was the enthusiasm that was focused on Kennedy.
                    I think there certainly was an enthusiasm about being able to do things in the
                    world; to meet challenges abroad; fight communism and all of that. A great deal
                    of which must have come from thoughts of Kennedy, speeches of Kennedy. I think
                    certainly the leadership factor was there. We liked to think we had nearly all
                    the answers in the early 60s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your training like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Well, as I remember after some 30-some years, it was not particularly
                    useful. Perhaps the most useful part of it was those parts which made one
                    realize that other people thought in different ways; and had different habits;
                    came from different cultures and were going to approach problems differently.
                    This is elementary, but often forgotten, particularly by people in the
                    Department.</p>
                <p>A lot of it seemed to be focused on finding out how to read the visa manual.
                    Which, I think for most of us, was minimally useful since we had only one
                    assignment doing consular work and probably never did it again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your first post was where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: In Laos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Laos was in center stage, although a very small country,
                        at that particular time, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Yes, it was. Personally, I wanted to go to a French-speaking post and had
                    an interest in Asia but almost none in Africa, the obvious alternative. When I
                    got to Laos, it was beginning, I think, to be a real focus of attention.
                    President Kennedy in 1960 had sent U.S. troops to northeast Thailand as a
                    warning for Laos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the political situation in Laos when you got
                        there in '61?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: Confused. In 1960, neutralist military leader Kong Le had taken Vientiane
                    from rightist General Phoumi Nosavan. In 1961, by the time I got there, the
                    political situation was somewhat peculiar. Phoumi had retaken the capital, and
                    we were supporting him, but there was a neutralist faction, and a communist
                    faction. Each had foreign supporters.</p>
                <p>When I got there, wives and other dependents, who had been evacuated in 1960,
                    still had not returned, so we were bunked together in various houses. It was
                    sort of like being back in college again, in a sense. For cost, and security
                    reasons, people were sharing houses.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What type of work did you have?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I started out as a junior officer doing the consular work, which was
                    minimal. A little bit of economic kinds of things. Sort of trying to scare-up
                    something to do because being a vice consul in Laos was not a very demanding
                    job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about getting around there? Were you pretty well
                        confined to Vientiane?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: You were largely confined to Vientiane and its immediate surroundings.
                    You could fly to Savannakhet or to Pakse. The roads, quite apart from the
                    security problem, were pretty awful. The air transport was not much, so you were
                    pretty well restricted to Vientiane. Though later I was one of the first
                    diplomatic travelers, with my boss Bill Thomas, to go up to the famous Plain of
                    Jars, so-called because of neolithic burial jars on the plain. He had wrangled
                    an invitation from Phoumi Vongvichit, who was one of the communist faction
                    figures. We spent a day in the Plain of Jars. I did get to Luang Prabang,
                    because I went up as Ambassador Unger's staff aide for his credential
                    presentation to the Lao king. But travel was very difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You served under two ambassadors while you were there?
                        Went through Brown and Unger?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression? I mean, here you were a junior
                        officer, of how these two men operated.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: One thing that needs to be outlined, I think, is the setting. We were
                    carrying on some of the functions of a normal embassy in a very abnormal kind of
                    place. The Embassy really was a special purpose post, trying to maintain a
                    modicum of stability in Laos and avoid a communist takeover for the larger
                    stakes of Thailand and Vietnam. This meant trying to fuse a coalition government
                    out of the three political factions—communist, rightist and neutralist. It also
                    involved supporting a large CIA effort of the so-called Secret War in Laos.
                    There was an enormous CIA establishment across the river in Udorn, Thailand
                    working for US ends in Laos. In many ways those of us in the embassy were merely
                    ancillary to this huge project.</p>
                <p>So to get back to the two ambassadors. The most important thing that Winthrop
                    Brown and Washington special envoys were trying to do was to pull together the
                    three factions of Laos into a unified government. They finally did get agreement
                    from all three factions very close to Winthrop Brown's date of departure. I can
                    remember him getting the news at some sort of embassy function where we all
                    were; that the government had finally been formed. He departed and could count
                    himself, I guess, as having completed his mission successfully, although he was
                    under no illusions as to how stable the coalition might be. Then Unger came
                    in.</p>
                <p>Since he had these immense responsibilities dealing with the Secret War, Unger
                    was somewhat in the position, I would say, of a Chief Executive of a large
                    corporation, perhaps a defense company doing classified work, in that he had a
                    lot of different kinds of American bureaucratic interests to keep his hands on.
                    And he had to try to keep the various Lao factions in order; he had to try to
                    prevent Phoumi Nosavan from doing things that would upset the government. Of
                    course, all the factions had inner problems and foreign sponsors pulling them in
                    various directions.</p>
                <p>It was a rather difficult time because you had in Vientiane the three factions
                    each having their own armed troops. You'd see the Pathet Lao troops in the
                    markets in the mornings, walking around town with submachine guns. It probably
                    couldn't have lasted, and didn't last.</p>
                <p>These three incompatible factions could not really agree on government leaders.
                    The government was created as a result of internal and international pressures,
                    as well as the U.S. concluding that Phoumi Nosavan and his faction could
                    probably not establish control over all of Laos. It would thus be better to
                    accept a neutral Laos if that could somehow be obtained.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were a junior officer and obviously didn't have your
                        hands on the levels of power. What was the view of the officers about the
                        CIA operations and relations with the CIA?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: The agency was so important there that, in a way, they took precedence
                    over everything else. In more normal countries you would have a whole host of
                    other interests. The interest in Laos, of course, was really not so much an
                    interest in Laos as an interest in Vietnam and Thailand. Laos merely happened to
                    be a stage on which related events were happening. To the misfortune of the Lao,
                    of course.</p>
                <p>So you'd have to say that, really, the whole US interest was bound-up with the
                    security situation. There really were no other interests at all. The agency had
                    a good deal of military success initially with its irregular forces, but these
                    forces could not in the longer run resist the Vietnamese when they became
                    serious about Laos. The Lao, at great cost, fulfilled the function of buffer
                    state, protecting Thailand for a long period from having a communist government
                    on its border.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there much of a government to deal with, at your
                        level?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Not an awful lot. There were a few Lao at the top who were competent, but
                    not very honest. The immense amounts of money that we were introducing brought
                    forth the kind of corruption that you normally have. At one point, I think we
                    were handing them a check for $80 million a month to support the government.
                    This cash-grant policy was an effort to finance the Royal Laotian Army. A great
                    deal of that was raked off by the Laotian figures involved.</p>
                <p>In terms of relations, everything, of course, went to the security effort. The
                    rest of us were just sort of there, I think, doing our normal functions. The
                    Lao, certainly on the other side, must have felt much the same way. Everything
                    depended upon the security situation. They were more or less amenable to what we
                    wanted to do, considering that we were funding them. I think the Lao understood
                    that agents had them by the throat, and that the story was likely to end
                    badly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have much contact with the Lao there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Not very much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You served for a while as ambassador's aide, how did Unger
                        feel about this hodgepodge of government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: First of all, I didn't serve as aide too long. I didn't do a terribly
                    good job at that. In any case, Ambassadors don't confide very much in junior
                    officers normally.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>I think that he believed very much in what he was doing; worked very hard to make
                    the whole thing go. One of the unforgettable images that people who worked with
                    him had took place during one of the attempted coups. He had to reassure
                    Souvanna Phouma of U.S. support. He went over to Souvanna's house. He was not
                    let in, but Souvanna was up on the balcony and Unger was outside of a fence
                    talking at some 60 feet or so, sort of a Romeo and Juliet balcony scene, holding
                    what in other cases would have been a confidential conversation.</p>
                <p>I did go with Unger a couple of times when he talked with General Phoumi. Phoumi
                    had one of the softest and least audible voices I have ever heard, or tried to
                    take notes on. Ambassador Unger spent an awful lot of his time trying to keep
                    Phoumi in line. Phoumi had hard liners on his side who thought they could take
                    care of the situation militarily. It was some time before it was demonstrated
                    that the Royal Lao Army was virtually worthless, and not much could be done with
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the events of the overthrow of Diem and all in October
                        of '63 have any ripple effects?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I don't recall. I think the two situations were going along in parallel,
                    but not really connected with each other. I left in November of '63, shortly
                    after President Kennedy was shot. In fact, farewell parties that had been
                    arranged for me were canceled because of the assassination. I think it was about
                    a week after the funeral that I left Laos. I've been back to Laos, but only for
                    very brief periods since.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the role of the North Vietnamese at that time,
                        how did we perceive it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I think we certainly perceived the North Vietnamese as being the
                    counterpart to ourselves in support of their faction, that is the Pathet Lao.
                    But also the Chinese had an important role. That was the time we were much
                    concerned about a Chinese road that was being built from China. It went on for
                    years and years. Partly, it seemed that the construction schedule depended upon
                    the political events because it took so long to be built.</p>
                <p>In those days we felt that the Chinese and the Vietnamese definitely had designs
                    on Southeast Asia. This is the time of the “Domino” theory, which, of course,
                    was really the reason that we were in Laos at all. We were fearful that all of
                    Southeast Asia was going to become communist. This was a time when we had more
                    respect, I think, for the possibilities of guerrilla warfare than we do now.
                    Laos certainly was inherently unstable. It's almost born to be a buffer state.
                    The North Vietnamese from their point of view needed it for what became later
                    called the Ho Chi Minh trail. Also, they saw themselves as the natural
                    inheritors of the French in Indochina, if not of all Southeast Asia, certainly
                    Indochina—to recall that era now is to underline the immense differences.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any love between the Lao and the North Vietnamese?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Culturally, and in other ways, they're very different. But the Lao don't
                    seem to have animus for the Vietnamese. The Cambodians and the Thais do. Lao, I
                    think, basically like to be left alone and that's always been very difficult
                    because they're always a tempting target for someone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in November of '63, where did you go
                        then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I was supposed to go to the Sudan, but before I got back to Washington my
                    assignment had been changed. I was going to be on loan to USIS. I eventually
                    ended up in Zaire.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that time it was called the Congo.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: By the time I got there it was early 1964. I came back here for a few
                    months and did African regional training. I went out there in April of 1964.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I was assigned to Stanleyville, now called Kisangani. I went up there by
                    plane from Kinshasa, must have been late April, 1964, but I only stayed in the
                    Congo about 7 months because we were chased out of Stanleyville by the Simba
                    rebels. I was evacuated to Leopoldville and I have never been back. So that was
                    an interesting short period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you describe a bit what was the situation in
                        Stanleyville as you saw it, with the Simbas and all.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: When I got to Stan there was a revolt brewing further east which was led
                    by the Simbas. The revolt against the central government took on east-west
                    overtones though really at base it had more tribal overtones and plain old
                    opportunism than anything else. In fact, it probably was a continuation of the
                    instability and violence that attended independence—the earlier violence which
                    involved Kasavubu, Patrice Lumumba and all of the rest. In fact, I think some of
                    these people in the Eastern Congo called themselves the successors of Lumumba.
                    All the anti-government factions had adopted socialist or democratic forms of
                    talk, but at base it was mostly tribalism, opportunism and power seeking.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>Stanleyville, when I got there, was rather odd because it was in-waiting for
                    something to happen. It had clearly been quite an attractive town in the Belgian
                    days, but the Belgians were long gone and the real estate had begun to run down.
                    Houses hadn't been painted, stucco hadn't been repaired, there was not much to
                    eat in the markets. In fact we sort of lived on maniac leaves, which they called
                    spinach, river fish, and supplies that we sort of scrounged from Belgians with
                    connections. There was not an awful lot to buy. Near my house there was a
                    5-story Belgian supermarket that had virtually nothing in it except printed
                    cloth that was used for women's clothes, and Blue-Band margarine which was a
                    creation of some Belgian company. There were few westerners in Stan and little
                    to do off the job.</p>
                <p>The atmosphere was definitely one of unease, of events unfinished, and there was
                    not an awful lot for a USIS establishment to accomplish. We had a librarian who
                    maintained order in the library extremely rigorously, and would not allow books
                    to circulate because he thought if you lent one it was very likely to be stolen;
                    he was probably right. When we checked the records we found that there were only
                    about a half a dozen books circulating from the library at any one time. The
                    movie program was very good in terms of audience attendance because there's very
                    little else to do in the rural Congo at night. So in those villages that you
                    could get to, there was an enormous crowd. It was not quite clear whether they
                    understood any of the film since film itself was relatively new to them, and
                    many of the sophisticated production techniques, which we take for granted in
                    our films, probably just confused them.</p>
                <p>At any rate, it was a very strange place. The Congo is the only place where I've
                    ever had contacts almost continually asking me for favors or money. Clearly, a
                    rather demoralized kind of society, just sort of waiting for something to
                    happen. There was no significant leadership from the government in
                    Leopoldville.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there UN troops where you were?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: UN troops were in Stanleyville when I got there. They departed shortly
                    thereafter. I remember there was a UN police colonel, a Nigerian, who said to me
                    that he just did not know what was going to happen to these “fellows” when the
                    UN left because, you see, they're just not British. This, in light of law and
                    order later in Nigeria, is somewhat interesting.</p>
                <p>At any rate, Stanleyville when I got there was a very peculiar place. There were
                    very few Europeans there, although there were still some Belgians. There were US
                    missionaries in the area. My boss, Max Kraus, and I were in the USIS post. We
                    had a Greek secretary whose father was a UN-sponsored judge. There were some
                    British-American Tobacco Company people. Not a heck of a lot to do in your
                    off-time. We played tennis nearly every day and played a lot of bridge. For part
                    of the time we had a 4 p.m. daily curfew. Probably would have gone mad if I had
                    been a whole 2 years there. We, of course, had a consulate.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the consulate doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Well, they were mainly keeping an eye on the security and the political
                    situation. John Klingerman was the consul for the first part of the time I was
                    there. Then he left and Mike Hoyt came in. Mike was taken prisoner by the Simba
                    rebels and that's a whole long story. At any rate, up until quite near the very
                    end when I was evacuated it was quite peaceful there. No one thought that the
                    Simba rebels were going to get to Stanleyville. After all, they were way over in
                    the eastern Congo, a couple hundred miles away.</p>
                <p>But they began moving towards Stanleyville and their chief weapon was the
                    telephone. They would call ahead and say that they were coming and they had big
                    “dawa,” or magic. This usually caused a failure of nerve on the side of the
                    government. I guess because they felt they didn't have as good a witch doctor as
                    the rebels had on their side. So the Congolese Army would fall back fifty or
                    eighty miles into the jungle to the next little town. There was, however, a
                    major bridge over a very important river whose name I no longer remember.</p>
                <p>We thought there was no real possibility of the Simbas getting across that river
                    in numbers if the bridge were blown. Of course, in the event the bridge was not
                    blown, and the Simbas entered. The last day was extremely confused. We didn't
                    know what was happening until about 10 a.m., I heard voices outside and I looked
                    out and all the Congolese were running in one direction or another. We knew just
                    enough to be apprehensive.</p>
                <p>We checked with the consulate and found out that the bridge had not been blown,
                    the Congolese forces were falling back on Stanleyville, and they were mostly
                    useless anyway, even at the best of times. So the consulate consulted with
                    Leopoldville by radio, a single-side band, and it was decided in Leo that Max
                    Kraus and I, and some of the people at the consulate should evacuate.</p>
                <p>I sent home my servant, who was later killed by the Simbas. I packed a bag and
                    went down to the consulate in one of the rackety old jeeps that USIS had, and by
                    that time you could hear small arms fire. This was the middle of the day. The
                    CIA communicator was out back with the burn barrels and was throwing in
                    material. The consul, Mike Hoyt, had apparently been told to stay or rather not
                    authorized to leave. Leopoldville was somewhat behind the curve, we should have
                    all left. At any rate, all did not.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>I went into the consulate and there were 2 American girl tourists there. They'd
                    been told by the consulate that they ought to get out of Stanleyville a week
                    earlier and they'd not done so. The consulate was on a curved street which made
                    kind of a half-moon with the river passing by right in front of it. There was
                    another street which joined the two ends of the half-moon and one end of that
                    street was being held, however briefly, by the Congolese Army. There was a lot
                    of small arms fire going on against the on-coming rebels. I took the 2 girls
                    into the jeep and we went off towards the airport, which fortunately was
                    opposite from the direction of the fight. I floored it; it would go about 30, 35
                    miles an hour floored.</p>
                <p>We came to one end of the half-moon and there was a Congolese army detachment.
                    They were, of course, all armed. They stopped us and asked where we were going.
                    We said the airport. They said, fine, that's where we want to go. About a dozen
                    piled in on top of the girls. They were surprised to see the girls and I guess
                    the girls were a little surprised to have all those guys in the jeep. We went
                    off at whatever speed we could make to the airport. The airport was a confused
                    place with 3 or 4 evacuation planes belonging to the UN, to the Brazzaville
                    Congo attach�, and the Leopoldville attach�. From one C-130 an American military
                    unit had taken up positions around the planes facing outward with virtually a
                    whole battalion of the Congolese army surrounding them. So it was quite an
                    interesting Mexican standoff the Congolese didn't seem interested in
                    testing.</p>
                <p>I got out of my car. Max Kraus had driven out by a different USIS jeep. We handed
                    the keys of the jeeps to the Belgian vice consul and said, “Here they are, keep
                    them. We won't hold you responsible if you lose these jeeps but it would be nice
                    to have them back again.” We got on a plane and flew to Leopoldville leaving
                    behind Michael Hoyt, and three or four others who did not get to the
                    airport.</p>
                <p>All but one of these eventually locked themselves initially into the consulate
                    vault room, leaving a case of whiskey outside. The consulate was under siege by
                    the Simbas and finally was taken. Those in the vault had to give themselves up.
                    They were in prison for 118 days. There is a Readers Digest published book
                    called 118 Days in Stanleyville which retells some of this, now long since
                    forgotten.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were the Simbas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: They were a ragtag group, which purported to be “socialists,” but they
                    maintained a staff witch doctor. They were led by the same sorts of people who
                    were the leaders on the Congolese government side. That is, people who had been
                    educated by the missionaries or perhaps half educated, but had ended up on the
                    wrong side of the government either by tribal reasons or friendships or
                    political mischance. I never believed that they had any kind of coherent
                    philosophy</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>They were supposedly supported by the PRC, which had an embassy in Burundi. And
                    maybe they were, to some extent. If so, it was opportunistic meddling with
                    people who had no real ideology.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you getting reports about what the Simbas were
                        doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: There was a lot of intelligence reporting about the Simbas. A good deal
                    of it was rather fantastic and not terribly believable. They were settling old
                    scores and eliminating, apparently, a lot of the governmental people. In fact,
                    when they did take over Stanleyville, they executed a great many individuals
                    simply because they had some white blood, including the secretary general of the
                    province. I remember that the burgermeister of Stanleyville was killed, executed
                    in a park in front of the fine apartment that I had.</p>
                <p>But a lot of this seemed to be resentment politics and tribalism rather than any
                    coherent political motive. Of course, our people had a rather long and difficult
                    imprisonment with lots of threats to their lives, guns held to their heads,
                    triggers pulled on empty chambers, that sort of thing. Had the rebellion
                    succeeded it's hard to say what political structure might have evolved. I think
                    it would simply be African big-manism. That is, who ever accumulated the most
                    power would run the place. It would be based, to a certain extent, on tribal
                    structures; there would have been very little ideological content as we know it
                    in the western world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm just wondering about, obviously you weren't in there,
                        but this decision to keep people behind.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Well, I'm not exactly sure why it took place. You'd have to ask the
                    people who made the decision. But I'm not actually so sure it played out that
                    way. I think rather that they didn't make a decision when they probably should
                    have, or communications were not good enough to tell them in time to leave and
                    therefore they got caught.</p>
                <p>I was involved in an operation to rescue these people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dragon Rouge—was that it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: No, Dragon Rouge is the rescue operation much later when Belgian troops
                    went in and did rescue our people and other hostages.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>What I mean was sort of an ad hoc operation that seemed to have been thought up
                    largely by Ambassador Godley and various cohorts at the embassy. It took place
                    the next day. It's a very long story, but basically was a rescue effort in which
                    I participated because I was the only person who had ever been in Stanleyville.
                    It was aborted in a place called Lisala because by the time we got to Lisala the
                    consulate people had been moved to a military camp.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We've got time. I mean, what happened? You came back to
                        Leopoldville.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I came back to Leopoldville on a plane. We arrived, I think, in the early
                    evening.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By the way, I take it that the 2 young girl tourists were
                        gotten out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Yes, and they disappeared without ever thanking any of us for our efforts
                    and for a free flight.</p>
                <p>I arrived in the late afternoon. I was still on detail to USIS, and John
                    Mowinckel, who was the head of USIS, was out at the airport, as well as other
                    people. He invited me over to dinner and I told him the story of our evacuation.
                    I think John was somewhat taken aback by the Congo, he'd never served anywhere
                    outside of Europe so this was totally new to him. After Laos and Stanleyville I
                    began to think the odd was normal.</p>
                <p>At any rate, that evening I went back to a hotel and went to bed and was
                    awakened, at perhaps 1 or 2:00 in the morning, by an officious admin type who
                    said that he had been sent to summon me to an immediate meeting in the embassy
                    with the ambassador. I went to the embassy, and found a meeting going on with
                    Ambassador Godley, DCM Bob Blake, the CIA Station Chief, the Navy Attach�, the
                    head of something called COMISH, a combined military mission, and my boss Max
                    Kraus, as well as others.</p>
                <p>What was under discussion was a rescue mission. The prisoners were all still in
                    the Stanleyville consulate at this time. There was a possibility, it was
                    thought, that they could be rescued. The idea was that we would land a
                    helicopter on the consulate lawn and storm the consulate. We would have to take
                    the personnel to be involved in a C-47, along with gas for the helicopter in 55
                    gallon drums. For our cover we would have 2 T-28s piloted by Cubans left over
                    from the Bay of Pigs. Financed by the Agency, they had been assisting the
                    Congolese Army against the rebels.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: T-28s were 2-seater, basically they had been trainers but
                        we used them for ground attacks.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: We used them for ground and air support and for bombing in both Laos and
                    the Congo. The thought here was that the pilots would first “hose down the
                    area,” as the military expression was, around the consulate with 50 caliber
                    machine gun fire before the chopper landed. The mere appearance of the T-28s was
                    supposed to panic the Simbas. We would fly in with the helicopter. We would land
                    on the embassy lawn and rush the consulate, and rescue Mike Hoyt, and the rest.
                    One of the big questions of the operation was: Where was the flag pole on the
                    embassy lawn? Because the embassy lawn was surrounded by a low wall, if the flag
                    pole was in the wrong place, the helicopter might not be able to land. As I
                    recall, we never did establish the exact position of the flag pole, but it was
                    decided to try this “Operation Flagpole” anyway.</p>
                <p>So I found myself on the C-47 piloted by the personal American pilot of President
                    Mobutu, a US Air Force officer. Since it's such a long way from Leopoldville to
                    Stanleyville, we had to stop along the way. It was decided that a place called
                    Lisala would be where we would spend the next night. It was now roughly dawn.
                    And away we went. I don't know to this day if Washington approved all this.</p>
                <p>At any rate, we got to Lisala in the late afternoon without any prior notice to
                    the locals. We had a safe conduct pass from Mobutu, but it turned out that
                    Lisala, which no one ever told us, was in an area which was hostile to Mobutu.
                    His safe conduct was probably a negative rather than a positive. The Lisala area
                    was controlled by a local warlord, and he seemed to think we were the first wave
                    of an international contingent that was coming to take the Congo back for the
                    Belgians. This was a rumor that had been floating around ever since
                    independence.</p>
                <p>We shortly found out that the airstrip we were on was surrounded by local troops
                    whose garb was fatigue pants, bare on the upper torso, but with a monkey's skin
                    over their heads and down their backs. Unfortunately, they were armed. As time
                    went on, they kept getting closer and closer to the airplanes. Remember we had 3
                    airplanes and a helicopter there. There were various parleys in the town of
                    Lisala with our leadership and their leadership. These were not very productive.
                    The first parley opened with the opposite number pulling his pistol out and
                    holding it on the top of the desk in front of him, and it became obvious after a
                    few moments, that he was drunk. So these parleys were holding actions.</p>
                <p>We were there for the night. During the night the monkey-clad troops kept moving
                    closer. We began to wonder how we were going to get out. Concurrently, news came
                    from Leopoldville by radio that the Stanleyville prisoners had been moved to an
                    army camp outside Stanleyville. There was no longer any purpose to our
                    expedition. The question became, so how do we get out?</p>
                <p>In the morning it was decided that the Cubans would make a rush for their planes,
                    jump in, take off, and buzz the airport while the other planes got moving.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>All of this happened and the Cubans are zooming up and down the field at an
                    altitude of a couple of hundred feet. All the members of our party are armed,
                    and we're all trying to hold our weapons in a nonchalant way as we jump into the
                    C-47. The helicopter had gone off also. The C-47 starts taxiing and the locals
                    started running for the plane.</p>
                <p>At that moment, a young CIA type who had been with us all this time, who had been
                    in the parlays, and who had with him a rather out of place briefcase, opened the
                    briefcase. It was stuffed with Congolese francs. He began to throw the francs
                    out of the door of the airplane, causing our monkey-clad pursuers to throw down
                    their weapons and stuff their pockets with the cash. As we went off he was
                    merrily throwing out bundles of cash, the bundles breaking up immediately.
                    Hundred of thousands of Congolese francs were like confetti in the prop wash. We
                    roared down the airstrip and took off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh how wonderful! Such are the aspects of diplomacy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: That's right, that's money diplomacy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you got back and then what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: So we went back to reality in Leo and they had not even a desk for me at
                    USIS there. So I hung around the office, did small tasks and things. USIS really
                    did not have an awful lot of a function there. But the Congo was thought to be
                    important in East-West terms. When, I guess, neither the East nor the West knew
                    the Africans enough to know whether any ideology was going to work. USIS even at
                    one point had the idea that it might open branch posts all over the Congo in the
                    way that they had done in Southeast Asia—in Thailand and Vietnam—which was
                    certainly a mad scheme.</p>
                <p>Concurrently, USIS began to build up in Vietnam and USIS went around looking for
                    people, volunteers and otherwise, to go to Vietnam. Since I was at loose ends
                    and it did not look as though the USIS post in Stanleyville was going to be
                    re-opened anytime soon, I was a prime candidate for Vietnam and off I went. I
                    made it around the world from Bangkok to Bangkok in less than a year,
                    considering that I had left Laos in '63, I made it back in '64 on my way to
                    Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go back to the Department for a while from
                        Stanleyville?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: No. It was a direct transfer. I was still on loan to USIS having done
                    only 7 months of my 2-year tour. In Vietnam USIS started something called, at
                    that time, the Joint U.S. Public Affairs Office (JUSPAO), later changed to other
                    names.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>At any rate, in looking back at the African experience, you can see that we had
                    too many people there trying to do things which were really totally irrelevant
                    to a largely tribal situation. I suppose, in the longer run, you could say that
                    US policy there was more or less successful since the Congo never went, even
                    ostensibly, Marxist. But the actual government that the Congolese had was about
                    on a par with Congo-Brazzaville across the river which was Marxist. Both of them
                    were dictatorships and almost without any redeeming economic benefits for the
                    population.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you arrived, you got to Saigon again, it's still '64,
                        what was your job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I became part of JUSPAO as an advisor to the Vietnamese civilian
                    government's information service and to Vietnamese Army S-5 Psychological War
                    efforts. They had had representatives of this office at Corps level, it was now
                    decided to break that down to division level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The IV Corps, I Corps.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: One for each Corps. Now there was going to be 8 or 9, I think, and I was
                    going to have the IXth division area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which is where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Which is down in the Delta, it included 6 provinces in the central
                    delta.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: S-5s being the...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: S-5s being the military psychological warfare branch. Each province had a
                    set of US military province advisors. So we worked with a US military officer
                    advising the Vietnamese S-5s. Each province also had a Vietnamese civilian
                    information officer which we also advised. Our job was to carry on information
                    and psychological warfare.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>I had funds with which I could support various activities. We worked with
                    Vietnamese information service and with military S-5s, Vietnamese and American
                    on almost any kind of project that was thought useful. For instance, in Khien
                    Phong province, a good deal of which is watery and practically every village is
                    on a canal, I funded a showboat. It was a boat which was run by the Vietnamese
                    Information Service with a team on it of actors, actresses, singers, and so on
                    which did psychological warfare kinds of entertainment. I think it was probably
                    the only showboat in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>It was an idea thought up by one of the American military S-5 advisers who was a
                    dedicated, hardworking, very creative guy. He thought up the idea and got the
                    Vietnamese Information Service to go for it, and I funded a lot of it. We funded
                    posters for poster campaigns, we funded leaflets to be dropped over VC areas,
                    loudspeaker programs, information sheets of all kinds, even some newspaper-like
                    publications. Anything having to do with the media, we could fund if it seemed
                    like a good idea.</p>
                <p>We created a Returnee Program, for VC the government was trying to get back. We
                    funded a little booklet with pictures and very little writing—showing how to
                    come back, how you were reeducated if you'd come back, allowed to go back to
                    your family and all that. At the end of the book it said, come back with this
                    book and you won't have any problems. We had people come in with the book.
                    Whether it warranted its investment, however, is difficult to say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the first place, what was the situation—military,
                        politically, and all in the area you were in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: In the area I was, there were a few districts that were almost totally VC
                    controlled and you really could not go in except to outposts by helicopter. You
                    probably wouldn't choose to spend overnight, if you didn't have to. I think
                    every place that I dealt with, all the district capitals of all of these
                    provinces, you could drop in on by helicopter safely enough. But at night many
                    of these places were just outposts that the government was hanging on to.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, An Giang province, which was controlled by the Hoa Hao
                    religious sect, was virtually free of communists. It was almost totally safe.
                    The rest of them varied from Khien Phong, which was bad, to Vien Long and Sa
                    Dec, which were not bad at all, except in the remoter places.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>There were a number of roads which were considered unsafe in the daytime and
                    generally untraveled at night. Vinh Binh, which was one of my provinces, which
                    faced the South China Sea, was rather bad from a security point of view. The
                    only real road was the highway that went from Vinh Long, where I lived, to the
                    province capital. It was normally safe in the daytime, but David Engel, who was
                    one of the provincial reporters for the embassy, was using my vehicle and a huge
                    mine was set off in front of it. He and his driver ended up with all the glass
                    from the windshield in their face, but they managed to control the car and go
                    around the hole, which was about 10 feet across and 2-3 feet deep. They could
                    have been killed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find dealing with the Vietnamese at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I consider the Vietnamese difficult to deal with in the best of times. As
                    personalities, it seems to me, they are clever and sensitive but xenophobic,
                    back-biting, rather unpleasant people to deal with. I did not have a great deal
                    of difficulty working with them because, after all, I was handing out money,
                    substantial amounts of money. I was helping them do their jobs, but at the same
                    time pushing them to do things I thought advisable and it can't have been easy
                    for them to have me intervening. They tended to have the long Mandarin
                    fingernail, clearly did not move out of their office very much, clearly were
                    accustomed to giving orders and waiting for them. They were not accustomed to
                    what we think of as public relations. One might think they could look good if
                    they and we put some kind of program together that gave them something to tell
                    their bosses they were doing. However, this was too alien to their bureaucratic
                    culture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about JUSPAO? Who was running it at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Barry Zorthian.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I assume you would go up there from time to time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Yes, and Zorthian came down to see me from time to time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the spirit of the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: USIS was a very big place when it had JUSPAO. The field reps were
                    different from what everybody else was doing. Probably different than most
                    things USIS people have done in the past. We didn't have a lot in common with
                    people in Saigon. But I recall that we thought we were doing important work,
                    that the war was to a large extent psychological. Perhaps everyone in the field
                    thought the war was being managed wrongly.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>It seems to me that the Phoenix program had begun when I was there. There was a
                    local CIA guy that we'd see a lot of. But that was out of my purview, and they
                    were not about to tell me anything about it. I had varying relationships with
                    the US military province senior advisors. Some were very shrewd fellows, some
                    were not, some were easy to work with, some weren't so easy. But the ones who
                    weren't so easy sometimes had S-5 advisors who were fairly good. In that case I
                    could just deal with these S-5 advisors.</p>
                <p>The S-5 advisors were usually infantry or artillery and trained to fight wars;
                    doing psychological warfare was something of a change for them. But they figured
                    that was their job and they'd go along with the program. One or two were aware
                    of French experience in Indochina and Algeria and were really very interested in
                    the subject and dedicated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you left there in '66, what was your feeling about
                        whither Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I think most of us, who were at that time quite junior, felt that this
                    thing could be won, but we weren't doing it the right way. For instance, Mr.
                    McNamara felt that he never got the information that he should have. Well, if he
                    had asked the questions of most people in the field, including his own military,
                    candidly, he would have gotten some candid answers.</p>
                <p>There certainly were plenty of people in the field who doubted that we could win
                    the way we were going. In retrospect, whether the South Vietnamese could have
                    won it any way, is hard to say. But trying not to use hindsight, I think
                    certainly many of us felt, I felt anyway, that the war could be won. But you had
                    to do a lot of things differently than they were then doing them. There had to
                    be much more concentration on local development, much better Vietnamese military
                    efforts, much more local autonomy. You had to have people who were dedicated to
                    winning the war.</p>
                <p>I'm certain I would have subscribed, for instance, to John Paul Vann's ideas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in 1966.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Yes. I spent the last few months in Saigon, working for a general who was
                    deputy to Barry Zorthian for field operations. That was only three months, then
                    I went back to Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Those 3 months that you were in, sort of Zorthian's thing,
                        how did that appear? Was it sort of a never-never land?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: I was never involved with press relations and what we told the press,
                    which seemed to be the controversial area. I think a lot of people were knocking
                    themselves out, trying to do the right thing. But a lot of it was, in
                    retrospect, punching the air. By that time I think the American establishment
                    had become so huge, and so many enterprises of all kinds were going on, that
                    coordination probably was extremely difficult. I'm sure it must have been in
                    USIS, in JUSPAO. They had made a decision to go even further toward increasing
                    the size of JUSPAO. In fact, I think toward the end, they even divided my
                    territory. But eventually, of course, they got one of these JUSPAO kind of
                    advisors under whatever organ it was, CORDS by then perhaps, in every
                    province.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you came back, did you go back to Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I came back to Washington, it was '66.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I went to the Ops Center, as a watch officer. I was there through '66.
                    Then the opportunity came up to go to Thai language training, to go to Thailand.
                    So I decided I would like to do that. I was very interested in Southeast Asia,
                    it was a fascinating place, a fascinating time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You certainly were in two of the hot spots, both being in
                        Stanleyville then being in Vietnam. Just a bit about the Ops Center. What
                        sort of work were you doing in the Ops? Could you explain?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: In many ways it was a little like being back at the Washington Post
                    again, being a copy boy. Because you would be pulling things off of the wire, as
                    it were. The watch officers did all those tasks, which I guess they still do. I
                    don't remember much now about the daily routine. I was generally not involved in
                    writing the summaries. I was a watch officer, worked for some very good senior
                    watch officers. I was only there for a few months. It didn't make any particular
                    impression upon me. I think it was a useful exercise. It's certainly useful for
                    a junior officer as a training exercise to see what the people are interested in
                    on the 7th floor, to be able to read a lot of important cables. You get a better
                    feeling of what is going on and how the Department works.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thai, how did one get into Thai training?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I suppose it was like any other hard language. You hear about an opening
                    and show an interest, and I did. I decided I would like to go back to the area,
                    and this seemed to be a good way to do it. So I went into 10 months of Thai
                    training.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a very difficult language, isn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Yes and no. The tones are certainly difficult. It's difficult to speak it
                    really well. On the other hand, grammar is pretty minimal. It has certain
                    advantages in that you don't have to worry about case, number and conjugation of
                    verbs. The verb stays the same, no matter what person. So it has some
                    compensations. But there are no real similarities except for technical words, no
                    cross fertilization with western languages.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was language study done at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: My experience at FSI is that there are 2 kinds of teachers there. There
                    are the ones who are real pedagogues and keep your nose to the grindstone. This
                    may be partly a reflection of cultures. The Japanese and the Chinese are like
                    that. The Southeast Asians are amongst the very casual ones. It's more difficult
                    to learn because they're much more diffident about what you're doing wrong.
                    They're not as nearly as insistent. If you are lazy, they let you be lazy. While
                    the Chinese, the Japanese, perhaps some others, French, really keep you up to
                    snuff.</p>
                <p>At any rate, they were in the throes of changing text books and we outran the
                    text book. Unless you have things really organized, at least for me, you're not
                    going to do as well as you should. I was also getting to the age where it's a
                    little harder to be involved in something that's not problem solving. After all,
                    your whole training involves problem solving and learning languages is not
                    problem solving.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Having gone through this myself a number of times, this
                        feeling of you're going back to your childhood, practically. Where you're
                        just repeating. It's hard to make that adjustment.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: We were a very small class. Jim Montgomery and myself were probably a
                    little old to take a language. We did it well enough, eventually got our 3s.
                    There were lots of things, I think, that could have been done to bring the
                    course to a better order.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went out to Bangkok, you were there from '68 to
                        '71.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I was in Thailand from '68 to '72. It was 1971 when I went up to Udorn.
                    The consul in Udorn had gone over to Vietnam to work for John Paul Vann. They
                    needed somebody to fill-in in Udorn for a while. So I went up there. I think I
                    spent about 10 months to a year up in Udorn, my last year.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's go back to Bangkok. You went out in '68, what was
                        your job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I was an economic officer. It was a fairly large section. In fact, the
                    Bangkok establishment was huge. At that time you had a MAAG which was virtually
                    a corps headquarters without troops. There were 400 to 500 people in AID, and
                    all sorts of other people engaged in counterinsurgency. You even had the
                    Stanford Research Institute out there, and ARPA, and a special assistant for
                    counterinsurgency. It was a huge embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ARPA is?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: It was Advanced Research Projects Agency of DOD.</p>
                <p>All of them studying about how better to fight insurgencies. You had an
                    insurgency going on. Within Thailand there was not only consulates in Udorn,
                    Chieng Mai and Songkhla but also USIS branch posts in a number of places, the
                    northeast in particular. Some in the south too. It was really quite a
                    counterinsurgency structure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As economic officer, what were you dealing with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I did minerals and general economic reporting—minerals, energy, rubber.
                    Again it was one of those situations where we probably wouldn't have been quite
                    so interested had not we been so involved in security. It was a period where we
                    were tenants on so many Thai bases. We had such a huge military establishment as
                    well. I didn't mention that, but quite apart from the embassy and MAAG, you had
                    5 huge airbases and Sattahip and Utapao, one was a port and one was a B-52 base.
                    All for fighting the Vietnam War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With all these things around, on the economic side we must
                        have been flooding Thailand with American money.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: There certainly was a lot of money coming in. Perhaps the most useful
                    thing we did was for military and counterinsurgency reasons, assisting
                    construction of a good highway from Bangkok up to Korat and then on to Udorn. We
                    assisted the Thai in a huge rural road building program, mainly in the northeast
                    because that's where the insurgent threat was thought to be more serious. In the
                    north too as well but mainly in the northeast. In 1972 in the northeast you
                    could in all weather get to all the district capitals, not only provincial
                    capitals but district capitals as well. While this was done for security
                    reasons, it turned out to be an amazing economic incentive as well.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>Another thing we did in hiring and training labor and building all these bases,
                    we created a large cadre of people who were skilled or semi-skilled. When we
                    left, many of these people went off to the Middle East, and they're still going
                    to the Middle East and all other parts of Asia as construction labor.</p>
                <p>The amount of money we put in was certainly considerable for the times. However,
                    the amount of US military spending—not only construction but on everything else,
                    including vegetables bought on the local economy and trucking and all of
                    that—was helpful, but not determinative to later economic development.</p>
                <p>There is a book on AID, which came out 3-4 years ago, which concludes that while
                    US aid in all forms was helpful, it was not a major factor in Thai development.
                    Most development came from indigenous factors. But it certainly did jump-start
                    in many ways areas of development outside of Bangkok.</p>
                <p>The trouble of course with a military base is that while it spreads money into
                    the local economy, it's not something which is long-lasting. In the Thai case,
                    it certainly wasn't. Most of the cities, I understand, in the northeast have
                    done pretty well since the US presence, with one or two exceptions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the insurgency that everyone was concerned
                        about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: This was the heyday of insurgencies and the Thai communist party was
                    attempting the same “peoples' war” that had taken place elsewhere. But it was
                    never a threat to Thai national security. The Thai have always had problems
                    along their borders. In fact, one of the Thai security tenets is to support
                    various minority groups on your border who fight each other and therefore are
                    less likely to become a problem for the Thai. So the Thai were often not as
                    concerned about the insurgency as we were. We were quite concerned because of
                    the “domino theory” prevalent at the time, and also, of course, because we had a
                    commitment to Thai security against communist aggression.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>There were certain small areas in the northeast that were very insecure. A few
                    districts were largely under insurgent control. There were some very bad areas
                    in the north, particularly some frontier areas. And some insecure areas in the
                    south, where native insurgency was complicated by remnants of the Malaysia
                    Communist insurgency headquartered in Thailand, and Muslim separatism. But the
                    insurgency never managed to penetrate the Thai heartland in the middle of the
                    country. When I was there there were perhaps 10,000 insurgents, Thai and
                    minorities, out of a population, at that time, perhaps 45 million or so. A few
                    key areas, certainly, they controlled. When I was consul in Udorn in 1972, I
                    never went into Na Kaa district which was near the Phu Pon mountains. The Phu
                    Pon mountains were a redoubt of insurgents; by the time I returned to Thailand
                    in 1983 the king had police in those mountains.</p>
                <p>The Thai were fortunate in developing some comprehensive political/military ways
                    of countering the insurgency, and fortunate also in the development of
                    international circumstances. For example, the PRC dropped support of the
                    insurgents. For them the insurgency was never a major national security threat.
                    It eventually more or less withered away. There may be a few separatists and
                    communists still in the south but it's hard to tell whether they're insurgents
                    or whether they're bandits nowadays. But even there, in the 1980s there were
                    mass surrenders arranged by the government. Many of them, of course, being
                    ex-Malaysian communist insurgents.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I take it it was a large economic section at that time,
                        who was running it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Konrad Bekker was economic counselor when I got there. It had been Bob
                    Fluker before that, who, by the time I got there, was acting DCM.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you all find dealing with the Thai government
                        officials, statistics, and getting information?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: The Thai are generally easy to get along with. It doesn't mean that you
                    get everything from them that you'd like to have. Or that they are always going
                    to do what you want. They certainly aren't. Culturally speaking, they will
                    nearly always be agreeable and easy to get along with. But a tendency to avoid
                    confrontation does not mean they are ready to cede their interests.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>It's important in the Thai context to think of the historical situation. When
                    Marshal Sarit took power in about 1957, he seems to have shortly thereafter made
                    a decision for rapid economic development. Basically the Army would run the
                    government, whether or not the government had a civilian or military face. But
                    they would hand over economic development to the private sector and to the
                    people who knew how to do it. They would leave economic planning to the
                    technocrats. It was a strategy of nurturing the golden goose that brought
                    benefits to all concerned.</p>
                <p>The Thai did a terrific job, averaging around 8 per cent real growth a year since
                    the 1960s. And they had a very conservative fiscal stance. So you never had the
                    terrible problems that you had in some other countries that built up immense
                    foreign debts. The military did not overspend on weapons. Sometimes they've had
                    a debt-service ratio which was getting to the point where people were beginning
                    to wonder, but it never got to the point where it was a focus of real
                    concern.</p>
                <p>They learned to put projects together well for international financing. I think
                    they became, in certain senses, a pet of the international financing banks,
                    because they were able to put a project together, able to carry it out, and
                    carry it out well. The projects were generally very well selected. There was an
                    enormous amount of private entrepreneurship, the private sector operated
                    extremely well. Wages were low and domestic and foreign investment sufficient.
                    They've done most of the things that have since become so highly praised
                    internationally as the way to go, if you're an undeveloped country, i.e., mainly
                    a strategy of manufacturing for export.</p>
                <p>The implied contract between the civilian side, the technocrats, and the military
                    really has carried on very well, to a point where circumstances aren't the same
                    and it doesn't exist in the same form, but in the crucial years, it certainly
                    carried through. The Thai military usually exercised a certain amount of
                    self-restraint in buying weapons, in contracting international debt for weapons
                    purchases. The government, as a whole, obey a kind of golden mean in contracting
                    international debt and in projects. They did very few projects which were solely
                    for prestige, as so many other countries have done. This was just starting of
                    course when I was first there in 1968.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was corruption a problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: Corruption has always been something of a problem, but not a major one in
                    spite of its pervasiveness. The Thai have a system of what one writer called,
                    adapting a western medieval term, prebendalism, meaning that you have to pay
                    people for doing the job that they're supposed to be doing anyway. Corruption,
                    it seems to me, has operated most of the time in Thailand largely as a
                    predictable factor, in which case it comes down to a kind of tax. The Thai
                    usually have a way of arranging things so no one is too unhappy. It's only when
                    the general system gets upset and somebody wants much more than they are
                    normally entitled to, that things have gone badly. I suppose that if development
                    had gone badly, corruption might have become a major issue. But in some ways you
                    can look back and say it's not dissimilar to the 19th century in many cities in
                    the United States, where economic growth was so rapid that it could stand a
                    certain amount of corruption. It has not become, as far as I can tell, a really
                    limiting factor on economic development, as it has in the Philippines or perhaps
                    in some other places.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The time you were there Bangkok was sort of the R&amp;R
                        center. Did that create problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: You always had problems, of course, but again, the kind of places that
                    were frequented by American military were not frequented generally by Thai,
                    except by the people making money off of it. The Thai were a pretty tolerant
                    bunch. There were certainly problems which we otherwise would not have had. But
                    they generally could be settled pretty much by the respective militaries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the embassy, Unger was the ambassador when you
                        were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: The first time I was there, yes, Unger was the Ambassador. He was still
                    there when I left in 1972.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did he operate the embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: Being as huge as it was then, it imitated Saigon in structure and got a
                    touch of giganticism. Most people rarely saw the Ambassador. It was imitating
                    Saigon in that it had a mission coordinator, who had a very difficult role
                    vis-a-vis counselors of embassy. His effectiveness depended very much on
                    personality. During my time I had the impression that only one of the three in
                    the slot made anything of it. In general, Unger was faced with an enormous and
                    hard to manage structure. When you have a USAID that has 400 to 500 people and a
                    JUSMAG that has 300 to 400—and all of those military were, of course not really
                    responsible to him. They are, in a sense, but not really because they have their
                    own chain of command up to CINCPAC. It's an enormous management job. There was
                    also a special assistant for counterinsurgency, which you don't have at most
                    embassies, as well as a counselor for politico-military affairs. So you had a
                    huge country team.</p>
                <p>In fact, Bangkok always had big country teams. When I went back in 1983, there
                    were 41 sections represented in the country team meetings even then. So back in
                    the late 60s, you necessarily had a lot of meetings and a lot of consultations
                    to try to coordinate it all. The ambassador was, I think, thought by most of us
                    to be rather remote off there in his corner. We didn't see him too often, but I
                    don't see how it could be otherwise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is the 12th of June 1995. I guess we'll just start
                        when you went to Udorn. You were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: From about October of '71 until August of '72. Tom Barnes, who had been
                    my predecessor in Udorn, had not finished his tour there. He'd gone to work for
                    John Paul Vann in Vietnam, leaving the embassy in sort of a lurch, so I was sent
                    up to finish up his tour.</p>
                <p>In fact, I was not particularly interested in going to Udorn since I had enjoyed
                    Bangkok. After one got used to it Udorn was quite an interesting place. We had,
                    at that time, 17 provinces, and an active insurgency. We also had five of the
                    big bases which the US Air Force was using for Vietnam. We had a very large US
                    army supply facility just outside Udorn which was involved in bombs, munitions,
                    etc., used both in Vietnam and Laos. We had branch USIS posts and AID
                    officials.</p>
                <p>At the consulate I had two junior officers working for me. Each covered half of
                    the provinces. We were interested in the insurgency which was fairly active in
                    the northeast. We also spent a lot of time brokering relations between the US
                    Air Force at the air bases and the local Thai governors and their
                    establishments. I must say the US military did a very fine job of this, by and
                    large, had consistent liaison with the base commanders, who of course were Thai,
                    and the Thai government establishment.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>In some of these small towns, the US Air Force almost overwhelmed the town.
                    Particularly in places that were pretty far out in the woods like Ubon, which
                    was down to the southeast bordering Laos. We also, during my time there, opened
                    a sixth airstrip that had previously existed but was scarcely used. I had never
                    heard of it, had never seen it, but out in the middle of nowhere, in Khon Kaen
                    province, a $19 million airstrip had been built with nothing else around it. It
                    was scrub jungle, with few facilities. It had been used by the CIA as a training
                    site for irregulars going to Laos, and became the home of a military air wing
                    which, for military reasons, decided to get out of Vietnam. This was, of course,
                    one more thing that we had to deal with local authorities on. They were
                    instructed by Bangkok to be helpful. I remember clearly while this was still top
                    secret, and after I had to be summoned to Bangkok to be told about it, we went
                    out to the site which was off of a road that was not terribly well-traveled. As
                    we got to the turn to go into this airbase, there was a sign at the deserted
                    junction saying that an Indian tailor shop was shortly opening.</p>
                <p>We did not in Udorn have anything to do with the CIA's operations in Laos. Since
                    I was consul for Udorn, I focused on northeast Thailand. We did occasionally see
                    these people of course. Meanwhile, there was also a USIS and a CIA structure in
                    the northeast. Many of the capital cities of the various provinces at that time
                    had CIA stations because of our interest in the insurgency and support for
                    counterinsurgency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were great supporters of the insurgency?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: No, of Thai counterinsurgency efforts. AID, for example, supported a very
                    large road building program which had been underway for some time. As it turned
                    out, most of my attention was focused on the insurgency and Thai-base relations.
                    Those of us in the field generally felt that, like Vietnam, our Embassy had too
                    optimistic a view of developments in the provinces of concern. We spent much
                    time on the road because distances are long in the northeast. The northeast has
                    about 1/3 of the Thai population, but unfortunately it has very little in the
                    way of natural resources. There's not an awful lot to develop in the northeast.
                    This is still the situation today. The laterite soil doesn't hold water very
                    well, the land is not very good. You could develop, I suppose, manufactures
                    there, but there's no reason to develop them there when you can develop them in
                    Bangkok, near the port, the airfields, and so on.</p>
                <p>It remains hard to get Thai to go to the northeast because there's not much in
                    the way of entertainment or schools or social inducements. So it's a poor area
                    and remains the least developed. I think this is one of the problems which the
                    Thai have—that is, assuring that some of the prosperity of Bangkok somehow
                    trickles down to the northeast, and some of the other poor parts of Thailand as
                    well, but particularly the northeast.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned the insurgency, what was the insurgency and
                        how was it going and what were we working on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: The insurgency had various interesting facets to it. It was led largely
                    by Sino Thai. In the north the recruits, the soldiers, were by and large hill
                    people, not ethnic Thai. In the northeast they were mainly Thai. We spent our
                    time talking to province governors, and military men who were engaged in
                    counterinsurgency, trying to keep an eye on what was going on, trying to give
                    Bangkok a straight story of what actually was happening.</p>
                <p>As a consequence, of course, there were some provinces where we spent a lot of
                    time and some provinces which I only went once or twice in my entire tour
                    because they were perfectly peaceful. We had no bases there, we had no interests
                    there. You could not possibly try to give equal attention to all 145 districts
                    and subdistricts in these 17 provinces. Therefore I spent most of my time in the
                    provinces that were large from an area, or a demographic point of view, had
                    American bases, and/or had insurgent movements.</p>
                <p>The insurgency was interesting from a technical point of view. Contrary to
                    expectations, the insurgency in the northeast had developed in areas which were
                    not the poorest. In fact, Na Gao, which I mentioned earlier, was a relatively
                    well-off area. Apparently, some resources were necessary to sustain an
                    insurgency. Clearly the insurgency had a great deal to do with the fact that the
                    northeastern Thai speak a Lao dialect, are probably nearer to being Lao than
                    being Central Thai, and have felt themselves long overlooked by the central
                    government. They did not feel that they were getting a fair share of
                    development. There was also, obviously, the Vietnamese-Lao communist carry-over
                    from Laos. While the insurgency was never a threat to the national security, it
                    was certainly a threat to the stability of the north and northeast, and had the
                    potential, I think, of becoming much larger.</p>
                <p>In the end the Thai defeated the insurgency for a number of reasons, some
                    internal and some external. The chief external one being that the communist
                    Chinese removed their support, eventually, for the insurgency because they were
                    much more interested in international respectability and in establishing
                    diplomatic relations with Bangkok. They were no longer interested in
                    insurgencies that they had previously supported in southeast Asia. I think,
                    also, the PRC saw they really weren't going anywhere.</p>
                <p>Internally the Thai, due I think somewhat to our urging, but more to their own
                    decision, started to combat it in a much more intelligent way. That is, as well
                    as military involvement they began a joint civilian-military approach. In many
                    cases, they in effect bought off the insurgents, allowed them to come back with
                    amnesty, gave them land, etc. These programs had mixed success individually, but
                    as a whole they worked quite well. In the north, the fact that the insurgency
                    involved non-Thai mountain people, and received enormous attention from the
                    royal family, who interested themselves in these peoples' welfare, was a very
                    important factor.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>Another important factor was that low-land Thai could never become convinced to
                    join an organization that started in the mountains and was primarily composed of
                    mountain people. So in the long run, the Thai, by dint of great patience and
                    perseverance, gradually suppressed the insurgency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were there, were we seeing this as an irritant
                        more than as a real threat?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: No, I think we took it extremely seriously. We provided a lot of
                    assistance to AID, which had both a development and a counterinsurgency
                    rationale. We had engaged in assisting the Thai in a very large road program in
                    the northeast. By the time I got there, you could drive to nearly every district
                    and subdistrict by all-weather laterite gravel roads, it was sometimes pretty
                    bumpy but you could get there. AID had worked with a Thai agency to build roads
                    and had done, really, a quite incredible job.</p>
                <p>We also, at that time, had a special assistant for counterinsurgency with
                    counselor rank or minister-counselor rank in the embassy. He coordinated with a
                    Thai agency, ISOC, the Internal Suppression Operations Command.</p>
                <p>This was a large cross-bureaucratic operation. So the Thai recognized the threat.
                    This was the time that we saw Thailand as the next “domino.” In fact, the fall
                    of one domino, Laos, in 1975 proved to be a caution for the Lao speaking
                    population of the northeast. They saw the refugee flow and learned the
                    experience of their Lao compatriots under communism. It turned out that the Thai
                    insurgents lost some of their appeal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you see any North Vietnamese or Pathet Lao communist
                        forces playing any part in this Thai thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I don't think they ever played a major role. There were intelligence
                    reports from time to time, but I don't think they ever played any part except in
                    transiting supplies and training. After all, with the northeastern Thai and the
                    Lao speaking the same language, it's very easy to get across the Mekong River
                    that is the boundary between Thailand and Laos. But I never heard of any
                    Vietnamese serving with the Thai.</p>
                <p>It would be difficult to tell the difference between a Pathet Lao and a
                    northeastern Thai, if you captured one. I think that still, at this time, the
                    Pathet Lao had their hands full in Laos and I don't think they were active in
                    Thai insurgency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the CIA operation in that
                        area?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: I used to work fairly closely with them. It seemed to me that the branch
                    posts, certainly those that I worked with, were very good and very well plugged
                    in. The CIA was performing liaison with the Thai and providing them various
                    kinds of training and other assistance. By and large, they were very good. They
                    really knew what was going on in their provinces. They had very good contacts in
                    the Thai hierarchy. And were, I think, of some use to the Thai. The Thai
                    certainly treated them as if they were useful to them. I thought that in the
                    field, agency cooperation was pretty good. But we did always have the feeling
                    that the people in Bangkok did not quite understand the realities of the field.
                    On the other hand, this is always, I think, the feeling that the people in the
                    field have. Some of it, of course, must have been that they certainly did
                    understand what we were telling them, but they weren't able to do anything with
                    the Thai bureaucracy in Bangkok to change what, after all, were Thai
                    realities.</p>
                <p>If you're out in the field constantly, you become aware whether your counterparts
                    on the Thai side, are any good or not, judging from hints you hear from the
                    other Thai, what your own experience is, and so on. Some of the Thai military
                    were good and some were not. Some of the civilians were really quite good. Some
                    of the governors had a terrific appreciation of what the insurgency was all
                    about and how to fight it.</p>
                <p>The Thai government was not set-up traditionally to deal appropriately with the
                    insurgencies. For instance, if the governor has an agricultural agent in his
                    province, he does not really report to the governor. He reports, in his own
                    chain, to the Ministry of Agriculture in Bangkok. It's Bangkok that determines
                    his next assignment, his promotion, and so on, not the governor. When you have
                    this multiplied by 20 different government agencies—you get all of these people
                    into a meeting, you may get a consensus, but you may not, necessarily, get any
                    action thereafter if you're the governor.</p>
                <p>This was very difficult for many of these governors which is, of course, why they
                    created a communist suppression operations command which was civilian and
                    military to cut across these bureaucratic obstacles. Well, it didn't always cut
                    across them. I think, as time went on, you began to get younger military
                    officers who understood much more what so-called revolutionary war was all
                    about, and understood the civic action implications, and understood how to
                    set-up intelligence organizations, in contrast to some of the older military</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the American military? Did you have any problems
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I should have mentioned them because in addition to the 55,000 Air Force
                    and Army people who were in Thailand, we also had, by analogy with Vietnam, a
                    group of military advisers to the Thai. This had been a very controversial
                    policy question. That is, do you have such advisers, looking at the experience
                    of Vietnam, and if you do, what is to be their role? Do you take part in
                    operations, for instance, as they did in Vietnam? You had the slippery slope
                    argument, and all of that.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>The American military advisers that I dealt with were not terribly effective, not
                    because they couldn't have been, but because the Thai didn't really use them.
                    The Thai had their own ways of doing things and were not about to change them.
                    Cooperation seemed to me to be largely on an intelligence basis—what's going on,
                    and here's what we plan to do, and so on. US advice on actually how to organize
                    things, or to train and fight the insurgents probably was not taken very
                    much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find having these airmen, most of them were
                        without families, didn't that cause consular problems all over the
                        place?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Not really because they were under military jurisdiction. Otherwise, we
                    would have had hundreds of problems. The Thai and the American MPs patrolled
                    together and, by and large, they handled these things on a military-to-military
                    basis. There were always a few problems that could not be solved that way.
                    There's a famous murder case, of a child in Udorn, which happened before I got
                    there. The fellow who committed the murder was still in a Thai prison when I got
                    there. There was a case near Sattahip of lese majeste.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying there was another case?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: There were several cases. One involved a fellow who had too much to drink
                    and deliberately stepped on the face of the King on a banknote. This was lese
                    majeste, a charge we of course don't have in the US. He ended up in jail for a
                    time. The Thai finally released him to us on the condition that he immediately
                    get out of Thailand and that it not be publicized. Otherwise, he probably would
                    have served on a fairly lengthy tour.</p>
                <p>Generally what happened on the difficult cases was that the Thai would imprison
                    an offender for a time and turn them over after publicity on them had died down.
                    After 2 or 3 years they would turn them over to us, for us to get them out of
                    the country.</p>
                <p>Two things actually were amazing. One is the amount of Thai cooperation on this.
                    The other one was, and it was constantly brought up by senior officers on the
                    American military side, that we really had a new generation of Americans in the
                    military who were much better behaved than they had been in previous
                    generations. And got into trouble much less. I don't know how many times senior
                    officers told me how much better behaved these men were than they had been in
                    their salad days.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>But when you have tens of thousands of people, and you have a certain amount of
                    those with lots of free time, plenty of money and alcohol readily available
                    there's obviously going to have a lot of fights and other minor difficulties,
                    particularly on the weekends. When the Marine Air Wing came to Khon Kaen, and
                    were taken for liberty for the first time to Udorn, which was about 80 miles
                    away, it was really fight night because the Army was also in town. The Army had
                    monopolized all the places of leisure, shall we call it, in Udorn. When the
                    Marines showed up, the first night was very active for the MPs.</p>
                <p>But again, most of these problems were minor. The Thai generally did not want to
                    interfere if it's an American against an American, he'd rather leave it to the
                    American MPs. It was only crimes really involving Thai, as the lese majeste
                    case, where they got significantly interested. If you were driving a vehicle and
                    you struck a Thai, you'd have to pay some kind of compensation. But you probably
                    would not, even for careless or reckless driving, have to do jail time.</p>
                <p>You have to remember, of course, that at this time it was not a democratic
                    government which was running Thailand. We did lots of things through the
                    military. The context has to be kept in mind. Not the least of which was that
                    the Thai saw our presence as being in their strategic interest. However, if
                    there had been a democratic government in Thailand, based on party, you'd
                    probably have had much more prickly relationships. Indeed, it'd even be
                    questionable whether you could have brought in 55,000 Americans. That certainly
                    is not to praise military government, but military government for a military
                    purpose certainly is much easier to deal with than a civilian one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any more issues that you had to deal with?
                        Before we move on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I think those are the chief ones that I dealt with. I did not get
                    involved, by and large, with most consular issues. We were a special consular
                    post. We really only existed because of the interest in insurgency, and because
                    of Laos. We did not issue visas. Most of our consular local's time was occupied
                    with the documentation of Thai brides, because there was an extraordinary number
                    of military men who married Thai.</p>
                <p>Obviously, a good deal of your time in a place like Udorn is spent on
                    administration. Just keeping yourself going, particularly when we had a
                    political local, an administrative local, a consular local, 2 officers and
                    myself, the drivers. A lot of your time is spent on administration. We had an
                    American wife who was our classified secretary on a part-time basis.</p>
                <p>But circumstances later changed greatly. After the Vietnam debacle and at a time
                    when the Thai were disillusioned with the US relationship, my successor once
                    removed was barricaded in his house by students, for a couple of days. The
                    context I spoke of had changed. But the relationship, when I was there, was
                    extremely cordial and very workman-like. I got to really enjoy being in the
                    northeast and spending a lot of time out of the office in the provinces.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you came back to Washington, is that right? You came
                        back in '72.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I left about August of '72 and arrived back in September of '72. I came
                    back to Washington to work in ACDA. That's the Arms Control and Disarmament
                    Agency, which I didn't really want to do. The agency, when I got there, was in a
                    certain amount of turmoil after the 1972 election of President Nixon. It was not
                    clear how he would regard the agency.</p>
                <p>There was turmoil going in ACDA which took several months to settle down.
                    Meanwhile, I was not given much to do. I was bored stiff with reading old
                    speeches and trying to educate myself on what arms control positions had
                    been—this was, of course, entirely new to me. I was assigned primarily to
                    chemical weapons, which has some interest but it's one of those subjects that
                    seem to go on forever.</p>
                <p>The state of real interest in it, I think, was shown by the fact that when I
                    finally went to the Conference of the Committee on Disarmament, in Geneva for
                    one of its sessions, I spent most of my time taking old speeches, rearranging
                    the paragraphs, putting a new beginning and ending on them, and then we would
                    give them once again. We were basically engaged, as far as I can tell that time,
                    looking back on it, we were basically engaged in an exercise where we wanted to
                    look as though we were interested in chemical weapons control but thought that
                    the verification requirements would be so stringent that we really weren't
                    interested in pursuing it terribly well. We and the Soviets, of course, had a
                    similar interest in many of these arms control issues, and as co-chairmen of the
                    CCD had great influence on its proceedings.</p>
                <p>So going to Geneva was interesting from the point of view that it got you out of
                    the office in Washington and Geneva was a nice place to be. But from the work
                    point of view, you were not really going there to do innovative things. You were
                    there to put your brightness and your innovative thinking into rehashing the
                    same old lines. We were not, of course, going very far at that time with the
                    comprehensive test ban.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're talking about nuclear test ban.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: So there was a certain amount of ritual to a lot of what we did. We made
                    speeches expressing how we wanted to move forward. But, while the Soviets would
                    make similar speeches, the nonaligned members of the CCD, knowing the game of
                    course, would push their policy and would criticize us for not doing much more
                    on the CTB and for not undertaking our responsibilities under the
                    nonproliferation treaty in regard to the control of nuclear weapons. So there
                    was a certain amount of everyone wanting to keep this thing going for the use it
                    might have in the future, but there was not a lot going on in real substantive
                    terms.</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>You had to find little niches and little ways to keep the things going that might
                    push arms control forward. This is difficult, and, as is often the case, the
                    most difficult negotiations are in Washington and not in Geneva. I don't recall
                    in my discussions with my counterpart in DOD, more than one or two instances
                    when we agreed on a draft of anything. Their positions were always, from their
                    point of view justified, I suppose, very rigid.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately, arms control is one of those kinds of esoteric issues that it's
                    hard to get other people excited about. Particularly, it's hard to get the
                    people at higher levels to focus on them. You can get Henry Kissinger, of
                    course, to focus on nuclear weapons, but anything else, no, not really. At that
                    time conventional weapons control was one of those things that people
                    occasionally talked about, but nobody had the slightest idea that it would ever
                    move forward.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you're dealing with the Department of Defense, did
                        you catch any concern? I'm a layman in this whole field but I've read that
                        there was some concern, on the part of the military, about some chemical
                        attacks. That the Soviets had equipment which was designed to deal with
                        chemical attacks. And the chemical attacks would probably come at the onset
                        in any war, and we were not well equipped to deal with that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I'm not sure whether the judgment was that chemical attacks would come at
                    the onset of any war, though it may have been. I certainly don't want to
                    minimize the reasons for concern over chemical warfare possibilities, and the
                    reasons why we weren't moving forward. Yes, the Russians apparently had enormous
                    stockpiles of chemical weapons. They seemed much more prepared, both to defend
                    against it and use it, than we were. So the fears, if there were a European war,
                    and the fears of chemical weapons, would certainly have to be very high on the
                    list of things that any American military commander would have to deal with.</p>
                <p>I'm not sure whether Soviet military doctrine at the time called for immediate
                    use of chemical weapons, I doubt that it did. But even if it didn't, in arms
                    control you have to deal with what people are capable of doing, as well as
                    evaluating what their intentions might be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were with ACDA from '72 until when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Late '72 until early '75.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Then I went to the Korea desk.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were on the Korea desk from '75 until when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: '77. The Korea desk certainly was a relief, to be in some place that was
                    active and much more interesting. I, of course, had no Korea experience. I was
                    the deputy there to Dan O'Donohue, who had a great deal of Korean experience. I
                    dealt with the military and economic issues. It was, I think, a very interesting
                    period.</p>
                <p>After Dan left, in the latter part of that period, I served with 2 more country
                    directors, Ed Hurwitz and Bob Rich.</p>
                <p>I enjoyed dealing with Koreans and enjoyed being on the desk, but spent most of
                    my time in bureaucratic battles here. I worked with people from other agencies
                    who were really quite amenable most of the time. And, of course, dealing with
                    DOD on Korea is much easier than dealing with DOD on arms control issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there during the coming-in of the Carter
                        administration, January of '77?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I was there until about mid-'77. I think we had either Jay Taylor or Mike
                    Armacost sitting in our office for a long time doing a study, not on whether you
                    should remove US troops, but on how to remove them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is, of course, a promise that Jimmy Carter had
                        made.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: He had unfortunately made this promise, it took about 6 months to pull
                    back from it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It horrified the hell out of those of us who were sitting
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: It's certainly another instance, like so many presidential candidates who
                    promise to move the Tel Aviv embassy over to Jerusalem, during the campaign. It
                    takes you a while to step back from the mistake of it.</p>
                <p>Dick Holbrooke became Assistant Secretary for East Asia and Pacific. I suspect
                    early on he must have begun to doubt the wisdom of troop withdrawal. Maybe he
                    did all the time, for all I know. At any rate, we had somebody sitting in our
                    office doing this very long study. After about 6 months the decision was,
                    fortunately, revoked.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>I'm trying to remember whether this was the same time that I went with Phil Habib
                    to Korea, to tell them that they had to return Tong Sun Park, or was that later?
                    Yes, it must have been when I was on the Korea desk.</p>
                <p>You will recall that Tong Sun Park was the Korean involved with Congress,
                    allegations of bribery, he was a major figure around Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was called Korea-gate.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: It was the so-called Korea-gate.</p>
                <p>A real wheeler and dealer. He had fled back to Korea. It was decided apparently,
                    that Phil Habib would go out and see General Park Chung Hee to tell him that
                    Tong Sun Park had to be returned to the US, but we would only ask Park about
                    things pertinent to investigations going on here.</p>
                <p>We did not want this to become public. So one day I get a call that I'm going to
                    Korea with Phil Habib. I'm told just enough so that I think there's something
                    odd about it, but I don't know what it is. The cover story was that he was going
                    to consult about the forthcoming SCM, the Security Consultative Meeting, that we
                    have annually with the Koreans. By that time Habib was the Under Secretary for
                    Political Affairs and it's obviously a little strange to send him out to consult
                    on this, but that's the story, and it worked to the extent that the real reason
                    for the trip was not discovered.</p>
                <p>We get out to Dulles airport and I'm in the line with Habib. After a moment or
                    two he looks around and says, What are you doing in this line? I said, I'm
                    traveling with you in First Class. Obviously, I tell him facetiously the Admin
                    people in EAP were so impressed that I was traveling with you, that they gave me
                    First Class.</p>
                <p>Well, he was outraged that I had a First Class ticket, and not Economy. On the
                    plane, he has his own briefing book with him. He's reading his briefing book
                    while carefully shielding it from me. After a while, the thing becomes obviously
                    impossible and he tells me what we're doing. What could I say but—very well.</p>
                <p>We arrive in Tokyo, they have sent an officer out to meet Habib. They don't know
                    what he's up to, either. But they make sure he gets all the connections. Habib
                    is in one of his usual irascible moods, assumed or otherwise.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>We get to the airport in Seoul and there must have been 300 reporters there. The
                    Korean press knows something interesting is going on. But it doesn't know what
                    it is. The press, of course, thinks there's something of high strategic
                    significance that he's come to talk to Park Chung Hee about. So we get off the
                    plane and are virtually mobbed. It was like the crowd at a football game. There
                    was no crowd control.</p>
                <p>The next morning we have a country team meeting on the SCM. And, of course, Habib
                    has not read the SCM briefing book, a copy of which he had. So it ends up with
                    him puzzling everybody in the country team, except the ambassador and perhaps
                    the DCM, about what he's doing in Korea.</p>
                <p>At any rate, he sees Park Chung Hee and then goes off to play golf. I do some
                    consultation on the SCM, and we go back to the airport. We hold an airport press
                    conference in which Habib carefully says nothing for a few minutes. We get back
                    on the airplane, going through the same hundreds of reporters and photographers.
                    Ironically, there is only one other passenger in First Class. His name is Park.
                    He's the brother of Tong Sun Park. He knows Habib, Habib knows him; they have a
                    nice conversation. And away we come.</p>
                <p>I went back to Korea two weeks later for the actual SCM. The desk and the embassy
                    having straightened out, in the meantime, any confusions left behind by Habib's
                    extemporaneous comments during the country team meeting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As I recall, it was sort of worked out where Tong Sun Park
                        answered some queries by Guiliani who is now the mayor of New York.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I don't remember. You might as the consular type, whether he actually
                    came back or did we do it by interrogatories?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think we did it by interrogatories. I gave him
                        (Guiliani) the oath. I swore him in. It was a very peculiar thing. I think
                        the assistant attorney general, or something, Guiliani, quizzed him; took
                        some statements from him. Then I'm not quite sure what happened. All I
                        remember is being trotted out to give the oath, and then moved out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I think 2 or 3 people were convicted of something having to do with
                    bribery.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were members of Congress involved.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: Otto Passman, who has since died. I don't remember whether they actually
                    convicted Otto Passman of anything or not. He was a great friend of the Koreans.
                    It involved Korean rice.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any feel for, basically, Korean corruption
                        within the United States and Congress and all, during this time that you
                        were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: You heard an awful lot of things. Probably most of the stories were not
                    true, probably a great many of them were. The most frightening ones were the
                    activities of the KCIA in the United States, which is not quite a corruption
                    issue. Unfortunately, rice exports to Korea had become very important to some US
                    companies, and very profitable, I guess. It seemed to lend itself to
                    congressional intervention and, certainly, to the possibility of corruption. I
                    do think, if I recall correctly, there were a couple of rice companies that were
                    accused of various things. I don't recall the outcome of any investigations,
                    that's just too long ago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Koreans get after you? Koreans can be very
                        enthusiastic about being hosts and all of this. I was wondering on the desk,
                        did you find Korean hospitality coming at you or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I was still a junior officer, but one thing obvious was, at the beginning
                    when I got on the desk, the Koreans would take me out to lunch and we would go
                    to a very modest restaurant. By the end of my time on the desk, we were going to
                    very fancy restaurants. I always figured that was because no one else wanted to
                    be seen having lunch with the Koreans so they had plenty of representation
                    money. I think, toward the end, they must have been feeling pretty embattled. I
                    think a lot of their old friends did not want to be seen with them, for obvious
                    reasons, by the end of the Park affair.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression. I mean, sometimes being the new
                        boy on the block, this is not your area of expertise and all of a sudden
                        you're put onto the Korean desk. What were you getting from the other
                        Americans, O'Donohue, Habib or what have you, about the Park Chung Hee
                        regime in Korea, at that period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I think that at that period, while it was recognized that: 1 - he was an
                    extremely difficult leader with whom to deal; 2nd - the Korean military were, to
                    say the least, very heavy-handed domestically. We had continual human rights
                    problems with them. Remember, this is not too long after the kidnaping of Kim
                    Dae Jung from Japan to Korea.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>However, the importance of Korea in northeast Asia was such that we had to be
                    very careful in how we dealt with the situation. It was one of those very
                    difficult situations in which you have extremely strong security interests which
                    may conflict with an interest in promotion of human rights and democratic
                    evolution. I don't think anybody thought that Park Chung Hee was likely to
                    become at any time a genuine democrat. I think, also, there was the feeling that
                    if you had somebody different from Park it was probably going to be another
                    general who might be a great deal less competent and not much different in terms
                    of human rights.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which it turned out to be.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: But not having actually served in Korea itself, and known the Koreans
                    closely, I don't consider myself as knowing the situation all that well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It does point out a certain problem that happens to all of
                        us in the Foreign Service. Service in an area really does give a perspective
                        that just can't be picked up by coming back to Washington, I mean just being
                        assigned to a place in Washington, and to a geographic area.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I know, I was INR officer for the Horn of Africa at one point. I'd never served
                    there. I read everything but it still doesn't give you that feel that you have
                    if you actually worked in a place.</p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I think the difference is that when you're actually assigned to a place,
                    you're there 24 hours a day. Every time you go to a party, you're talking to
                    people who are also there, who are interested, your shop talk is very important
                    in a way. We tend to be great shop talkers anyway, because we find our jobs
                    interesting. When you're actually there you are talking to people, and you're
                    hearing so much more, and you're seeing the newspapers, or you're reading
                    translations of newspapers, everyday as part of your daily routine. Being there
                    gives you a great deal more, I believe, than sitting back in Washington and
                    reading the cables and the Intel reports and reading the history books.</p>
                <p>I'm not sure that if one said that to a budget-cutter, they would rate a feeling
                    very high. It's very difficult to put a numerical figure on a feeling or
                    understanding for a place. But, I still think the statement is correct.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After the Korea desk you left in '77. Where did you
                        go?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: I went through a period where the bureau wanted to extend me on the Korea
                    desk and I wanted to extend, but that didn't work out. I went to an office which
                    never really got underway. Interestingly, Paul Cleveland, who had been Political
                    Counselor in Seoul, was going to head it. It was going to be an attempt to use
                    the authorities of the Inspector General's office and put them to use in an
                    evaluation context. We would look at aid, both military and development aid, in
                    various countries and try to evaluate it in the context of the political
                    situation and the policy situation.</p>
                <p>Congress did not like the idea of spending money on this. After 2 or 3 months of
                    sitting around looking out a window, it was decided by the powers-that-be not to
                    fight Congress on it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So we're still in '77.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: '77 and a very early January '78.</p>
                <p>The only thing we really did was I took a study by an AID officer who had been
                    with me in Bangkok, and reversed all his conclusions and made a policy
                    recommendation that we should continue aid to Thailand. He later told me that he
                    was told that his study should conclude that aid to Thailand should be ended. So
                    we did not end aid to Thailand.</p>
                <p>I needed a job and it was January and there wasn't much going. There was a slot
                    open in Jordan and I was about the only guy who was available. The NEA DAS at
                    the time, Nick Veliotes, was reluctant because the Middle East, like so many of
                    these situations, is supposed to be one of those places where you can't possibly
                    understand it unless you've already been there. Which of course is nonsense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went out to Amman, Jordan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Yes, February '78.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Ostensibly, I would have left February 1980, after 2 years, but I
                    extended for a few months so that I would get on the transfer cycle. So,
                    actually it was in the middle of 1980.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>When I arrived in Amman it was in February, cold and gloomy, and of course there
                    were few trees. There is little vegetation in Amman. It wasn't what I thought of
                    as my part of the world and was kind of depressing at first. But, it was a very
                    interesting time. Very early on in my tour there, the US started trying to
                    convince King Hussein to join the Camp David peace process. We had visits from
                    Cy Vance who, I think, did his best to convince King Hussein to join. But
                    Hussein, if anything, is a survivor. He has to be very careful what he does and,
                    of course, the Palestinians were against Camp David. At least half of his
                    population was Palestinian. The Syrians were against it. He was going to
                    certainly need some cover.</p>
                <p>The one thing, which we might have been able to give him, an end to Israeli West
                    Bank settlements, proved not to be there. President Carter apparently thought he
                    had an agreement to end West Bank settlement. Prime Minister Begin, if he ever
                    made such an agreement, or if he ever thought he had made such an agreement, had
                    changed his mind on it.</p>
                <p>So, convincing Hussein to go in on those circumstances was a very difficult task.
                    I think Vance and other visitors who came at that time did their best and made a
                    very good case for it. One of the best cases for Palestinian participation in
                    the Camp David process I ever heard was by former Congressman Solarz, who in my
                    house at a dinner talked to a dozen leading Palestinians and made the case for
                    Camp David as well as I'd ever heard it argued. The Jordanian-Palestinians,
                    being moderates, were certainly receptive to his arguments. But not entirely
                    convinced and, of course, they wouldn't allow themselves to be convinced as long
                    as Yasser Arafat and the PLO as an organization were against it.</p>
                <p>I think there were a few who saw it as a good thing to do, at the time. In
                    retrospect it's very unfortunate that they didn't join the Camp David process.
                    Like so many cases with the Middle East and with the Arabs, it was a lost
                    opportunity. But we were not able, at that time, to convince Hussein to
                    join.</p>
                <p>That was probably the most important thing that happened during the period that I
                    was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again you were the new boy on the block, what impression
                        were you getting about King Hussein and his role?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: In Jordan he is, and remains, the foundation of the state. He was the one
                    person who had the authority, the public appeal, the personal charisma, the
                    political ability to keep together the Jordanian East-Bankers and the
                    Palestinians, to enjoy the general political support of both groups. I think it
                    is without question that most Jordanians admire the King, realize the necessity
                    of the throne, and are comfortable with the King.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>It doesn't mean they always agree with him. In fact, the Palestinians being a
                    very fractious bunch, there's very often disagreements on whatever particular
                    strategy or tactics he's following at the moment. But we're speaking here with
                    moderate Palestinians rather than the radical ones. Most of the radical ones
                    having departed for Lebanon after 1970.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After Black September.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: After Black September, after they almost took over Jordan. The King would
                    not allow them to do so. And they eventually went and took over Lebanon.</p>
                <p>So the ones that were left in Jordan were, by and large, very middle-class kind
                    of Palestinians. Most had been educated in the West, many of them in the United
                    States. They were very reasonable people that you could talk to, very
                    forthcoming. In fact, I always thought that with Palestinians, the problem is
                    not getting them to talk enough to write a reporting cable, the problem is
                    getting them to stop talking and to figure out what is worth reporting. Because
                    they're a very voluble bunch and lovely people. I enjoyed my time there.</p>
                <p>But to get back to Hussein. He seems to be the real glue that has kept the
                    country together for this very long time. His brother, Hassan, is probably
                    innately more intelligent a man than Hussein himself is, but without the charm
                    and the charisma. Hussein is marvelous, he can charm a bird out of a tree. He's
                    extremely good with visitors. All of the congressional figures and others that
                    we had out there, who talked to Hussein, would certainly come away with the
                    impression, that this is a reasonable man.</p>
                <p>And he is a reasonable man. But he also recognizes the limits. Jordan, after all,
                    is a very small, resource poor country and, I think has never gotten credit from
                    the Arabs for being the only country to give citizenship to Palestinians. It's
                    got Syria on the north and it's got a difficult neighbor to the South. The
                    Saudis have always been very difficult. Jordan needs Saudi assistance, or
                    someone's assistance. Jordan has to put on a very careful balancing act between
                    radical Arabs and the conservative Gulf regimes.</p>
                <p>Domestically, Hussein has the problem of Islamic fundamentalism to worry about.
                    He obviously has always in mind the fate of his grandfather, who was
                    assassinated in Jerusalem because he was ready to negotiate with Israel.</p>
                <p>He has a difficult family background. His father had mental difficulties. He took
                    over the throne very young and raised himself, in many ways. A man who's proved
                    himself with all kinds of physical feats—jumping out of airplanes, flying
                    helicopters, driving speeding cars, driving motorcycles—all of these very
                    masculine kind of things. He's had a lot of personal tragedies in his life,
                    including a wife who was killed in a helicopter crash. So he's had his share,
                    certainly, of non-political difficulties. To say nothing of the numerous
                    assassination attempts on his life.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>At any rate, he's very charming and sophisticated. Discussion is always very
                    reasonable. He speaks in a very modest kind of subdued voice. Good sense of
                    humor, understands how westerners speak and talk. A leader who has proven
                    himself, certainly over a very long time in a situation which has incredible
                    constraints.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of how Nick Veliotes as our
                        ambassador, operated?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Tom Pickering was there when I arrived. Nick later replaced him. There
                    was a great difference of style between Pickering and Veliotes. Pickering is
                    very methodical and very well-organized. Nick kind of managed by the seat of his
                    pants, but certainly everybody liked him, and the embassy ran well. I think he
                    had a real rapport with the King, but Tom Pickering did as well. Entirely
                    different kinds of people, but both very competent under difficult
                    circumstances.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again, this was an area that was unfamiliar to you. One of
                        the charges of outsiders has been, you have these Arab specialists who have
                        no understanding or sympathy for Israel, hence are almost un-American. I'm
                        talking about the American from within the American Foreign Service. How did
                        you find the view of Israel as you were dealing with them, because
                        everything had an Israeli facet to it, I suppose.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Particularly in Jordan. If you're in Morocco everything probably doesn't
                    have an Israeli facet to it. But if you're in Jordan there is only one foreign
                    policy issue, the Arab-Israeli problem. You do have economic problems; we were
                    providing assistance. But really there is only one issue. You do nothing but
                    talk about that issue, at all times, at great length. You ventilate completely
                    every facet of it. If you call on a Jordanian, whom you haven't met before, and
                    we did a lot of this, they don't assume that you're going to talk about anything
                    else but the problem.</p>
                <p>Like anything else, if you really dive into it, you soon realize the historical
                    complications. History is never really far away in any of your conversations.
                    You go talk to some of the old Baathists and they start with a recital of
                    historical events as they see them, beginning with the Balfour declaration. It's
                    half an hour before you can get a word in edgewise and they've worked up by that
                    time to 1948, maybe even to the '60s.</p>
                <p>To make a judgment whether there is a sort of Arabist misunderstanding, or lack
                    of understanding, seems to me to be extremely difficult. It's very individual,
                    but my impression is that there's little to the charge.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>I think there's no doubt that if you spend your time learning Arabic, and talking
                    to Arabs, and you're in Arab countries all the time, that you're going to pick
                    up some of the local flavor. I do not think that you're going to disobey any
                    instructions from Washington, or that you're going to go outside the established
                    policy line. Because the situation is so incredibly complicated, it seems to me
                    that it's very hard to take a different line. You can't go around telling the
                    Arabs, for instance, that they're right and that A, B and C ought to be, because
                    then they might well expect you to deliver on it in some way or other. When
                    you're in conversations in the Middle East, you have to stick to a line. The
                    line you better stick to is the one that is current US policy, because
                    otherwise, your Arab contacts are going to think that while this guy is saying A
                    and B, which doesn't seem to be what I see in the press, is this guy
                    reliable.</p>
                <p>So the complexities of being different from the official line, seem to me, to be
                    virtually insuperable. Now it does not mean that if you work with the Arabs for
                    20 years and speak Arabic that you wouldn't have a certain sympathy for their
                    point of view. I think that's natural. At the same time, you wouldn't be around
                    for 20 years in the Foreign Service, it seems to me, if you did not also realize
                    the imperatives of dealing with Israel. And, of course, many of the people who
                    are Arabists have been in Israel. But the policy imperatives, whether you agree
                    with the policy or not, in the longer run, are certainly there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go after?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I came back to Washington in 1980.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And did what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I went to PM.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went back to Washington and went to Political
                        Military. When you say Political Military, what was the bureau about and
                        what were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: The bureau has always seemed to me, not having spent much time there, as
                    rather unusual. It's security responsibilities crossed over geographic lines and
                    it had a mandate to interest itself in all of those things having to do with
                    national security. In many ways it was composed of people who were extremely
                    aggressive types, I always thought, had a lot of sharp elbows. Which of course,
                    in many ways, is necessary if you're going to try to overcome the geographic
                    bureaus on any given point. But it just seemed to cultivate that kind of a
                    personality.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>At any rate, when I was there I dealt with non-proliferation, which was similar
                    to what I had done in the Arms Control and Disarmament Agency several years
                    earlier. At that time non-proliferation effort was headed by Tom Pickering.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Larry Huber and Tom Pickering.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Tom Pickering was head of the interagency group that dealt with
                    non-proliferation and did a very good job of it, of course. We had regular
                    morning meetings involving ACDA, ourselves, and OES. It was a time, as far as
                    I'm concerned, which was kind of a dull period, particularly since there was not
                    much really going on at that time regarding non-proliferation. I had enough of
                    arms control in my earlier incarnation so I was glad to leave less than 2 years
                    later. There came a chance to go across and work in DOD to work on the Middle
                    East.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were in PM, what was Tom Pickering's method of
                        operation, as you saw it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Tom, of course, was not in PM, he was in OES. He worked, I think, in
                    rather a collegial kind of way. He made us all feel that we were part of the
                    effort. He was very good at that. On the other hand, there was no doubt, I
                    think, that Tom was running the show. But he did it in such a way that I think
                    that we all were not only accustomed, but looked up to his leadership, to his
                    efforts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was sort of the end of the Carter administration,
                        wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: This was 1980-81.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it moved into the Reagan administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Yes, and of course we had a lot of changes when the Reagan administration
                    came in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you talk about some of the atmospherics and the
                        practicalities—a new administration came in, you're talking about
                        non-proliferation. Reagan's administration, particularly in the early years,
                        was rather feisty about defense spending and all of that. Did you feel a
                        change as far as your particular bailiwick was concerned?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: Not so much as far as my particular bailiwick was concerned. There were
                    certainly a lot of changes in the PM bureau. In fact, I had sitting in part of
                    my office at one time, what was informally known as the Gang of Four, the people
                    who had headed the bureau during the Carter time and who had been displaced. All
                    of the top leadership of the bureau was changed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Non-proliferation, was there much interest in
                        non-proliferation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Not really. We always had, I think, an interest in keeping other people
                    from proliferating, but in terms of moving on things like comprehensive test
                    ban, there was not much sign of that during the Reagan years. The new
                    administration was much more concerned with what it perceived as defense
                    weaknesses than with arms control in general.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the attitude of the bureau towards developments
                        in Israel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I don't recall a particular attitude.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because Israel has been presumed, it's never been
                        confirmed but I think it's accepted by everyone, involved on a nuclear
                        weapons program.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Yes, I think that's correct. On the other hand, it's also correct, in my
                    experience, that no one ever wanted to deal with it. It was one of those things
                    that you tried your best to keep in the closet. Of course there was no demand
                    from anybody to deal with the question of Israeli nuclear capabilities. So no
                    one really wanted to do it, no one really wanted to touch it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about India and Pakistan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Yes, they had a sort of a life of their own. They go on as they have for
                    all these years, without much expectation that the situation is going to get any
                    better; with a constant fear that it might get worse. Of course, that must have
                    been the period when we became really concerned about Pakistan, during that
                    time, but never really found a way to deal with it. We still haven't found any
                    way to deal with the question.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about South Africa at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: If I recall correctly, this was the period when we detected a very
                    mysterious explosion between the tip of South Africa and Antarctica, which, as
                    far as I know, has never been adequately explained. Many people thought it was
                    some sort of nuclear test, perhaps, by the South Africans, and perhaps with
                    Israeli cooperation. As far as I know, it's never been really elucidated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this attract everybody's attention?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: It certainly attracted everybody's attention, yes. I think also that this
                    was a time too when we were becoming more severe in regard to South Africa in
                    other policies. So there was more attention given to the possibilities of South
                    African proliferation. Again, it was one of those very hard cases where leverage
                    was lacking and there was not much one could do with it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left PM and went to the Department of Defense.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: It must have been some time in '81 that I went over to Defense because I
                    was not there for a full 2 years. David Ransom, also an FSO, was the director
                    for the Near East in ISA. I became his deputy and then took over the job when he
                    departed.</p>
                <p>That was a very interesting period because it saw the Israeli invasion of
                    Lebanon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the reaction of ISA, from your vantage point,
                        about what was happening in Lebanon? The Israeli invasion of Lebanon caused
                        a great deal of turmoil in the United States because of the developments
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I would say that the ISA looked with great skepticism on the Israeli
                    invasion of Lebanon. Certainly the skeptics were right in the sense that the
                    Israelis certainly had the capability to win battles and to control territory,
                    but they never had the ability to straighten it out, as it were. Probably it was
                    an attack of real hubris on their part, to think that they could go in and make
                    some kind of an arrangement that would last more than a few minutes. Prime
                    Minister Begin and Ariel Sharon thought they had a surrogate to do their bidding
                    in Bashir Gemayel; that was very shortly revealed as supposition with no
                    credibility.</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>Basically, it seems to me, that the history of the next couple of years were
                    trying to clear up all the loose ends of the Israeli involvement there. And, of
                    course, the Lebanese problem has gone on almost to the present day, with one
                    variation and another. But I think in retrospect, things would have been a great
                    deal easier to handle, historically, had the Israelis not come into Lebanon.</p>
                <p>As you will recall, it was a very difficult period in which we ended up in saving
                    Yasser Arafat and the PLO from the Israelis, as well as the Israelis from
                    themselves, by intervening. Unfortunately, this led to a level of presence and
                    involvement which led to the Marines being blown up by the car bomb. Among the
                    more significant consequences of the time was the radicalization of the Shia and
                    the emergence of the Shia, who had really been rather politically passive in
                    Lebanon earlier on, as a political force that had to be reckoned with. Divisions
                    in the Christian camp, so many of these things that left Lebanon even worse off
                    than it had been, started during that period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would have thought that, here is the American military
                        which had to be aware of what was happening, and then eventually became
                        involved, we landed troops there and all. You were dealing, in charge of the
                        sort of political area of the Pentagon, keeping them informed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: The Defense Department was extremely reluctant to get involved, and had
                    to be pushed. Basically it seemed to me one of those cases where Mr.
                    Weinberger...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Secretary of Defense...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: ...was overruled by the President, and Mr. Shultz. DOD was always
                    extremely reluctant to get involved. They were right, I think, to be reluctant.
                    If one looks at the experience that the Israelis had, you can see why one should
                    be reluctant to get involved. Certainly the car bomb which killed so many
                    Marines is a perfect illustration of why they did not want to be there and
                    should not want to be in.</p>
                <p>I think it was a case where we were doing our best to save not only the Israelis,
                    but any prospect of dealing with the Arabs on peace for the indefinite future.
                    The disaster that Prime Minister Begin and General Sharon created led oddly
                    enough, having to save the Palestinians, to save Yasser Arafat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Here you are in ISA, which is sort of the political
                        advisor's place within the Pentagon, in an extremely complex political
                        situation, during this time who would be calling upon you and your office,
                        bureau, what have you. What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: We were working extremely hard. I must say a lot of the stuff that we did
                    may have been outdated before we even got it through channels because it was a
                    difficult, a very fast-moving situation basically run and managed by top
                    leadership. My feeling was that the policy was not being made in the Defense
                    Department. Really it was being made by the President, NSC and by the State
                    Department.</p>
                <p>Also, my feeling was that my colleagues in the State Department were doing their
                    best to let us in on as little as possible. They would call us as to how we
                    might react to things, which was often, of course, the first time that we had
                    heard such a thing, whatever it was, was contemplated. I had a feeling that it
                    was very much one-way. I think that's a feeling that people in Defense often
                    have about State, having worked there a while, that State would rather not
                    involve them if it doesn't have to, of course that is, I suppose, a natural
                    bureaucratic tendency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When the decision was first put to put the Marines in, to
                        help get the Palestinians out, to separate the two fighting forces, did the
                        people from the Marines come and say, Tell us about this, or something like
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: The forces really don't operate that way. They may make reluctance known
                    by inference from what they state as problems, but they pride themselves on
                    doing what they're told, whether they like it or not and they often are not
                    involved in the deliberations very extensively. If they are asked to do
                    something quite quickly, all concerned recognize that it's a last resort.</p>
                <p>I don't recall now the details of the decision to put in the Marines. If I recall
                    it correctly, we were forced to go in because Palestinians wouldn't trust the
                    Israelis during evacuation. The Marines were in as a kind of safety guarantee.
                    They stayed on and of course once you stay on you start to be a participant. I
                    don't recall the actual details of why we decided to stay on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If I recall, we went in to try and help them get out. Help
                        the Palestinians get out. Guarantees were made that nothing would happen to
                        the families of the Palestinians. The Israelis then allowed the Christian
                        militia to go into the camps of Shatila and there was a slaughter. That sort
                        of caused us to go back in with an international force—French and Italian
                        and all. They kind of got bogged down, there wasn't a real mission.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I don't recall at the moment what they were supposed to be
                    accomplishing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm not sure that there was much. I think it was more in
                        reaction to the massacres that we felt we had to do something. That was the
                        thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>Were you getting anything from our military about the performance of the Israeli
                    military at that time?</p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Not so much that time, but subsequently I think there were a lot of
                    studies done on it—the performance of the weapons that the Syrians and others
                    were using. On the actual fighting by the Israelis, I don't recall much in the
                    way of critiques. They did very well militarily, if you recall. The air battles
                    certainly showed the superiority of American aircraft, one or two Israeli
                    aircraft were shot down, and 80 or 100 Syrian and other aircraft shot down.</p>
                <p>I do not recall specifically any particular critiques.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left the Department of Defense to go overseas again,
                        is that right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: My time was coming to an end, my secondment to DOD. I left that job and
                    went to Thailand, for the second time, as political counselor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: From June '83 until August '88.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I was political counselor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: When I got there it was John Gunther Dean, and later it was Bill Brown. I
                    left a few weeks before Dan O'Donohue took over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the political situation in Thailand during
                        this—that's a good long period, almost 5 years.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: In terms of our relations with Thailand and what was happening on the
                    Thai scene, it was a very interesting period. The '70s had been very chaotic in
                    Thailand. That period had the overthrow of the Thanom/Praphat government in '73,
                    largely by student power. The Thai had then gone through a period of chaotic
                    parliamentary democracy. Probably, it was a time when there was more democracy
                    in Thailand than before or since. On the other hand, it was very disorderly. The
                    student groups who had led the overthrow of Thanom/Praphat found that
                    maintaining their cohesion and maintaining any kind of political unity was
                    extremely difficult. Funding and supporting democratic political process proved
                    much more difficult than opposing a government that nearly everyone thought had
                    gone on far too long.</p>
                <p>There was a right wing reaction to the disorder of the very unstable democratic
                    period, which culminated during demonstrations at one of the universities in
                    1976, which the Thai military and police put down with extreme severity. There
                    were some very strong grass roots right wing organizations, probably covertly
                    funded by the Ministry of the Interior and others that were active.</p>
                <p>Thai society is inherently conservative, and the democratic period ended with the
                    pendulum swinging sharply back to the right, with a military controlled
                    government. General Kriangsak Chomanon, who had been important during the period
                    that I had been there first—in fact he was the fellow that we came over to talk
                    to because he was the man in-charge of dealing with Americans—eventually became
                    Prime Minister.</p>
                <p>At any rate, by the time I got there General Prem was Prime Minister. Prem had
                    come in, I think 1980. Prem was a very quiet, almost diffident, public
                    personality. Did not like to talk to the press, rarely said much in public, did
                    not often say a great deal in private either. He kept his counsel very well. He
                    was a man who by intent or not, left people with the thought that he had said
                    something encouraging to them, when, in fact, he had not said very much at all.
                    A useful political trait.</p>
                <p>Prem was, I think, in his early days not thought likely to have a long tenure
                    because he was a compromise candidate. Traditionally prime ministers come out of
                    the military, and Prem proved to be a very good military politician and handled
                    the political parties well. He had an 8-year period of rule, a very long time,
                    and one of stability and economic progress. Prem, I think, was personally
                    honest, in contrast to many preceding military Thai leaders. Unfortunately, for
                    political reasons he had to tolerate a certain amount of corruption. But there
                    was an interesting contrast with the government that came after him which was
                    totally civilian politicians and was seen as extremely corrupt, that of Chatchai
                    Chunawan.</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>At any rate, during the period that I was there, the relationship with the United
                    States was changing rapidly. Because of the end of the Cold War and the decline
                    of a Vietnamese threat through Cambodia the security became of less immediate
                    significance. At the same time, the Thai economy was developing so rapidly
                    during this period that it affected the complexion of the relationship. We
                    suddenly had a whole host of economic problems with the Thai that we had never
                    had before. When Secretary Shultz visited, on his way to one of the ASEAN
                    foreign ministers meetings, we found ourselves, for the first time, doing
                    talking points for him that had to do with economic matters, where before this
                    had never been necessary. Now we had the problems of intellectual property
                    rights, dumpings, countervailing duties, textile imports, and all of these
                    things.</p>
                <p>We tried to tell the Thai that we had these problems with all of our friends, but
                    the Thai tend to look at things in a rather holistic way. We tend to separate
                    things out—deal with economic items on one hand then you send someone in 10
                    minutes later, a different person, a different place, to ask for support of a UN
                    vote. The Thai don't separate things quite as much. They look at a relationship
                    much more holistically.</p>
                <p>One of the important things which affected the atmosphere of the relationship was
                    that these economic matters began to get us a very adverse press. I'd say the
                    coverage changed about late '83, '84. We started to change from being treated in
                    the press as someone who was a great friend and who in international issues was
                    probably right—though they might make some exceptions—to a country that was
                    trying to treat them like a big brother; they didn't need a big brother; this
                    wasn't the colonial period; they weren't a colony and so on. We were “bullying
                    them,” was essentially the feeling. That particular word was used extremely
                    often. Here is the US bullying us again.</p>
                <p>From the Thai point of view you could certainly see this. In many cases the
                    economic matters on which we were continually making approaches, were on an
                    absolute basis, not significant in money terms, although they had a certain
                    amount of principle that was important for us. And of course it was a period
                    when we were trying to clear up intellectual property rights questions
                    throughout the Far East.</p>
                <p>Textiles were a major concern. The Jenkins Bill, which was a big issue in '84,
                    '85, never passed the Congress. It was a bill which would have returned textile
                    quotas to a level of those several years earlier. Never passed, but for all the
                    harm it did us in Thailand in terms of public relations, in terms of public
                    attitudes, it might as well have been passed.</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>There is an enormous reservoir of goodwill for the United States in Thailand, not
                    the least of which is because so many Thai have been educated in the United
                    States. But even some of our best friends were getting tired of the economic
                    friction. While they were always polite to us about it, it was clear that they
                    did not like it. It was clear also that when they talked among themselves they
                    thought we were picking on them for reasons which they never quite figured out.
                    They thought we must have an ulterior motive, but they were never quite sure
                    what it was.</p>
                <p>At any rate, it was a period of considerable change in the relationship.
                    Domestically, looking back on it, the 8 years that Prem was in power were
                    unfortunately wasted by the Thai political parties and by the Thai political
                    intelligentsia. During that period, Prem stayed in power largely because he had
                    military support and a relatively quiet party situation. It was calm and stable
                    largely because, I think, most Thai developed confidence in Prem. The economy
                    was expanding, and it was clear that he was approved by the throne. Personally,
                    he made no efforts to build up political parties. He was not a member of any
                    political party himself, but did not attempt to hamper their activities.</p>
                <p>The parties, which also were relatively stable during the Prem period, really
                    wasted the time. Thai political parties are traditionally based on personalities
                    and are weak on ideas. They continued so. They did not develop principles or
                    organizations. No credible civilian alternative to Prem ever emerged. The
                    politicians largely devoted themselves to enriching themselves and protecting
                    their own interests. It's unfortunate that while the Thai constitution was
                    geared, in fact, to force the creation of fewer, larger, better funded parties,
                    it only had very mixed success in doing that. There remained a lot of not very
                    significant parties, certainly not based on ideology, nearly all based on
                    personalities, very changeable. If you have an election a lot of people jump
                    parties, going to where they see an advantage. The object of politics is to get
                    into power and stay as long as possible.</p>
                <p>So it was a period when the civilians could have done, it seems to me, much more
                    than they did to develop a credible, political class and a credible party
                    system. Because they had this long period of stability under Prem. Because Thai
                    society was modernizing quite rapidly. Because the middle class was growing
                    rapidly, and because the importance of the Thai military as a group was in
                    effect, declining. It should have been a period where there was more political
                    evolution. Looking back now, I think it can be said there was more political
                    consciousness developed, at least in Bangkok, than I thought. It was the Bangkok
                    middle classes that finally forced out the military regime in 1992, albeit after
                    egregious political chicanery by the military.</p>
                <p>We, of course, favored change only by democratic means. Whenever we were asked
                    about coups and other political maneuvering, the phrase that we used was that we
                    encouraged the evolution of Thai democracy. This meant that we'd like to see
                    change by elections and democratic means.</p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>The problem of course with political change in Thailand is that change-by-coup
                    had been institutionalized over the long period since the overthrow of the
                    absolute monarchy in 1932. There had been 17 coups. They were never social
                    revolutions, there was never any significant social change after coups. Coups
                    were generally reflections of changes in political power within the military, or
                    as the Marxists might say, objective conditions. When it became clear that the
                    objective conditions for someone to move on were such that he ought to move on,
                    there would be a generally bloodless coup. You had a change in leadership but
                    you didn't really have a change in the bureaucracy or society.</p>
                <p>By the time that I went to Thailand for a second assignment there were really
                    3-1/2 important institutions: the bureaucracy, the military, the throne, and you
                    could count Parliament as a half because it had at least gotten to the point
                    where people saw it to their advantage to be parliamentarians. That may have
                    been personal advantage rather than national advantage, but people had begun to
                    think that being a member of a party was worthwhile, that the government
                    situation had evolved enough so that there was considerable freedom of action
                    and influence as a parliamentarian, whether or not one was actually a member of
                    government.</p>
                <p>In fact, one of the motive forces of the Thai system is that early on the
                    military seems to have made the decision to allow the technocratic ministries to
                    be run by technocrats. One of the successes of Thai development, is that from an
                    economic viewpoint they have a very conservative leadership, and the military
                    did not go to the budgetary extremes that it has in some other countries. In
                    fact, one of the overall reasons for Thai success is that they don't seem,
                    individually or collectively, to go to extremes. They may have had Marshal
                    Sarit, but they did not have a Marcos. They never had the kind of excesses that
                    the Philippines experienced.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a political change during the time that you were
                        there up to '88?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: It was relatively stable politically with Prem at the top. There were
                    some attempts during the time I was there to push Prem out, particularly a
                    period of about a year, which must have been '85, '86. There were difficulties
                    made for Prem by some figures in the military probably loyal to General Athit.
                    Because General Athit had become commander-in-chief and supreme commander. He
                    looked to normal progression to prime minister. But almost no one wanted to see
                    Athit become Prime Minister except perhaps his immediate followers.</p>
                <p>In Thai circumstances, if you don't make the step while you're supreme commander,
                    if you leave that position, it's almost like falling off a cliff. One day you're
                    powerful, the next day you are respected. There were times when it looked like
                    there might be some forced attempt to get rid of Prem. But he was able to
                    weather the storm, partly because the throne made its support for Prem clear. We
                    made it clear that we would not wish to see a change that was not
                    constitutional. In the context this was taken by Athit as supporting Prem.</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>In the last analysis what we did or said was not a decisive factor. It was the
                    internal balance of forces between Prem and others. The situation was a great
                    deal more complex then and later than I can outline here. But it was quite clear
                    that Prem had more of the Thai military on his side than Athit did. Finally,
                    just after the time that I departed, Prem pretty much ran out of support. The
                    military was a bit restive. General Chavalit was by that time waiting in the
                    wings. Chavalit, who had been a prime supporter of Prem at earlier times, was at
                    that time beginning to maneuver against him. Prem resigned. They called new
                    elections and, I think, most of the public thought that yet again Prem would
                    become prime minister, but when they went to offer him the job, he said, No
                    thanks, and Chatchai became prime minister.</p>
                <p>I think that Chatchai, Chavalit, Prem and all of those concerned had at least an
                    implicit, and perhaps an explicit agreement that Chatchai would be an interim
                    prime minister. The problem became that Chatchai liked the job and General
                    Chavalit, who was the putative successor, proved himself not to be the
                    politician that people always thought he was. Chatchai proved very clever in
                    playing by politician's rules, and Chavalit was not. It began to look as though
                    Chatchai would stay on a good bit longer than the year or so that was presumably
                    allotted to him.</p>
                <p>Ultimately Chatchai's government ended of course with a military coup. By that
                    time its reputation and political wrangling had left it so low in public regard
                    that there were no mourners at its end. At the time I think the Thai thought,
                    and we thought too, that with the long period of stability and the extraordinary
                    modernization and economic development which took place during the Prem
                    administration that coups had become outmoded. It's another illustration that
                    economic development can get well ahead of political evolution. And I would add
                    that Thai politics currently seem to substantiate that view.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were talking about relations with the United States
                        going down mainly because we were beginning to take a more active role.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Going down is not really the right expression. It was rapidly changing
                    circumstances bringing about changes and adjustments, some of them overdue. The
                    climate of Thai opinion was changing because of other objective developments.
                    Not the least of course was the rapid decline of the Soviet Union, but that is
                    after this period. Also important to Thai attitude was that they had finally
                    suppressed their own communist insurgency. This of course was a subject of
                    interest to us, having a security commitment to Thailand, but it was also
                    psychologically important to the Thai.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>And, of course, relations developed with the People's Republic of China during
                    this period. A factor which we haven't mentioned up to this point, was the
                    Cambodian problem. Once it became clear, I think, that the Chinese and the Thai
                    were on the same side of the street against the Vietnamese, that was a
                    significant factor in Thai public psychology. The curbing of Vietnamese
                    ambitions, and the fact that the Chinese were definitely opposed to the
                    Vietnamese, it was almost a de facto alliance of the Chinese and the Thai.
                    Certainly it was a remarkable change in climate and atmosphere, for the Thai
                    it's really a strategic change.</p>
                <p>So there were a number of factors that affected relations with the US. The
                    communist insurgency, the change in relations with China, the decline in the
                    likelihood that they would have major security problems from any of their
                    neighbors, as well as the build-up of ASEAN as an important political
                    organization, or an organization with political weight if it chose to use it,
                    all these things caused the relationship with the US to evolve into a
                    relationship which is a more even relationship, more parity, particularly with
                    their rapid economic development.</p>
                <p>A few years ago we were researching some figures for a speech. We found that in
                    1975, when everybody thought Thailand was the next “domino” which might fall to
                    communism, two-way trade between Thailand and the US was about 750 million
                    dollars. In 1995, this trade is over 15 billion. We have a trade deficit with
                    Thailand. From a period when it was almost inconceivable that you would see
                    something in Bloomingdales saying Made in Thailand, it is now quite common. This
                    took place in one generation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were there, just to get a feel for how an embassy
                        works. You're the political counselor, obviously you don't want things to
                        upset the Thai because you've got your own agenda. The economic counselor
                        has got his or her marching orders which are to challenge the Thai in
                        certain practices which we feel are to our detriment. How did this evolve
                        within the embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: You have to set the stage by saying that the embassy was one of the
                    largest in the world because it's a favorite place for regional headquarters. In
                    fact, in the country team meeting we had 41 sections represented. This is a huge
                    management problem, obviously. In fact you could nearly always count on somebody
                    doing something, amongst these 41 sections, that they should have told
                    management earlier about.</p>
                <p>At any rate, I think this is one of the things that was difficult because we
                    still wanted Thai military facilities to be available in case of need. Even
                    though military aid was on the way out. We needed cooperation on narcotics
                    suppression. We had major US investments; and significant interest in Indochina
                    refugee questions.</p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>We had to try to weld all these things into one policy. You could have one
                    policy, but you certainly had several facets because we were at many points
                    carrying on these rather irritating discussions on intellectual property,
                    textiles, and the rest of it. At the same time we really had productive
                    relationships on the security side. Fortunately the Thai military was not much
                    influenced, at least as far as we could tell, was not much influenced with what
                    was happening on the economic side. In fact during this period we negotiated a
                    couple of useful agreements with the Thai military.</p>
                <p>As I mentioned, there was a great reservoir of goodwill towards the United States
                    in Thailand with which one could operate. It's a long-standing relationship. In
                    fact, we had our first commercial treaty with Thailand in 1833. Townsend Harris
                    went to Thailand before he went to Japan.</p>
                <p>Of course, it's only since the second World War that it's become as close as it
                    has. I think that now that we seem to have passed most of these economic
                    quarrels, I would expect that the relationship would be extremely friendly,
                    cooperative, productive.</p>
                <p>Another fact which lends balance to the relationship is that the Thai and we
                    generally agree on our approach to other international issues. The Thai are
                    usually not willing to take stands on, for example, UN votes on controversial
                    matters which they're not directly involved, but they generally agree with most
                    of our positions internationally. Or at least are prepared not to speak out
                    against our position. They have a free enterprise economy. We have a lot of US
                    investment there. All of these things are the basis for a very friendly
                    relationship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Going back again to your time, how did you find as
                        political counselor, your operation within the embassy, with the
                        ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: As I said, it was a difficult management problem because of the enormous
                    number of sections and a large official population but I had access whenever I
                    wanted it to the DCM and the ambassador. I never had any problem seeing them or
                    talking to them. I should add that one half, at least, of what we did in the
                    political section, which we haven't talked about very much, was the Cambodian
                    dimension.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, would you talk about the Cambodia dimension.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: In the political section we had an internal section and an external. At
                    the largest we had 7 officers: myself, 3 on the internal, 3 on the external side
                    as well as 3 secretaries. The external side not only did those things which are
                    common to all political sections, that is Thailand's relationship with ASEAN,
                    with the rest of the world, and so on. It was also reporting on Cambodia, on the
                    efforts of the non-communist groups and the Khmer Rouge, in so far as we could
                    cover them, against the Vietnamese occupation and the government installed by
                    the Vietnamese. We spent a great deal of time on Cambodia.</p>
                <p>We also had a kind of watching brief for developments in Vietnam, at that
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I might, for the record, say that we had no mission in
                        Vietnam or in Cambodia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Since the war we had not had any representation in Vietnam. It's
                    difficult to cover one country from another and I always thought that much more
                    could have been done in Washington. Because covering Vietnam at that time, to a
                    large extent, was an INR kind of job. You needed extensive files, because you
                    had to be able to look up what happened to the last party congress, and analyze
                    the differences with this party congress and so on. It was Kremlinology in the
                    old sense and was kind of a research rather than a contact enterprise that the
                    political section normally carry on. But we did do, I think, a fair amount of
                    reasonably good work on Vietnam. We also had no mission in Cambodia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Cambodia during the time you
                        were dealing with it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: The Khmer Rouge had been forced out of power in Phnom Penh by the
                    Vietnamese invasion in the last days of 1978 and held on along the Thai border.
                    The KR were supported by the Thai and the Chinese. The Thai and the ASEAN also
                    supported two non-communist groups, which we also supported. There were large
                    Cambodian refugee populations just on the Thai side of the border maintained by
                    the international community through the UN. The Vietnamese installed government,
                    composed of Khmer Rouge, was never able to secure international recognition, nor
                    to secure the countryside.</p>
                <p>The non-communist organized themselves into a faction which was headed by Son
                    Sann and Prince Sihanouk. While they were never militarily effective they were
                    very important politically in showing that there was a non-communist resistance
                    to the government in Phnom Penh.</p>
                <p>When I got there the KR remained a major thorn in the side of the Vietnamese. All
                    of these groups, including the KR—the KR while certainly being a radical
                    communist group, it's main ideological imperatives seemed to be the same as that
                    of non-communist groups—ethnic hate for the Vietnamese.</p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>At any rate, when I arrived there the longer term prospects did not look terribly
                    good for this resistance movement. On the other hand, it was still in existence.
                    It was beginning to have some minor successes. Much of its successes, of course,
                    were really successes of ASEAN. Because ASEAN, as a group, put together a very
                    impressive anti-Vietnamese Cambodia policy. In the end, it was not successful in
                    driving the Vietnamese out of Cambodia, that resulted from other factors.</p>
                <p>But, on the political stage, it was extremely effective. They could maintain a
                    blockade or could get others to agree to maintain a blockade of Cambodia on the
                    economic side. They could mobilize international opinion at the UN and mobilize
                    UN resolutions in a quite effective way.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile on the ground, Chinese aid was getting to the KR and some to the
                    non-communists. We were assisting the non-communists not with offensive weapons,
                    but with other kinds of aid. Access to these groups really had to come through
                    Thailand. So, perforce, the political section in Bangkok was doing most of the
                    reporting on Cambodia since we had no presence in Cambodia. The resistance
                    groups were headquartered along the border, and the whole border was under the
                    control of Thai military. You had to have passes, and so on, to get there.</p>
                <p>So, therefore, one of the major responsibilities of the political section was
                    reporting on what we knew of what was happening militarily inside Cambodia. As
                    well as maintaining a watching brief on the military situation, and trying to
                    follow the changes of personalities and interests in the non-communist movement.
                    These were very volatile and very unstable groups.</p>
                <p>We did our reporting through a couple of officers who spent most of their time
                    with Cambodians and Thai at the border or in Bangkok. We had on the staff an
                    American of Cambodian origin, Sos Kem, who really was on the role of the
                    refugees section, available to us for interpretation.</p>
                <p>If there was military action going on in the border, Sos could go out and talk to
                    people and give us some idea of what was going on. Press accounts of military
                    actions were nearly always wrong, very often greatly exaggerated. We really
                    needed to have somebody on the border, and section officers would go there for 3
                    or 4 days at a time. We would try to do as extensive and as meaningful analyses
                    as we could on the state of the resistance movements, in addition to what we
                    believed was happening inside Cambodia.</p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>At any rate, the situation was relatively quiet along the border when I first
                    arrived in '83. It didn't really change significantly until the Vietnamese
                    attempted to clear their side of the border. Which, if I remember correctly,
                    began in late '84 or late '85. When one of those coincidences that happened, I
                    was out on the border. I didn't generally spend a lot of time on the border. But
                    I was out in the border when one of the battles started. When troops of one of
                    the non-communist leaders were attacked by Cambodians and Vietnamese. It turned
                    out to be the beginning of a rather long offensive by the Vietnamese. At one
                    point, the Vietnamese actually were on the border with Thailand, which is not
                    something the Thai liked at all.</p>
                <p>In the end, the attempt to wipe out the Cambodian resistance by the Vietnamese
                    and their Cambodian allies was not successful. I think in retrospect that
                    campaign severely damaged the KR, however. Because the KR decided to stand and
                    fight on a couple of occasions, especially around Pailin. This was probably a
                    mistake on their part because they did not have the heavy weapons to be able to
                    withstand the Vietnamese. I think, then, they were significantly decreased in
                    strength but I think it was also something that was not realized by most of us
                    until much later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some of this, particularly in Cambodia's situation in
                        Laos, internally, how well did you feel you were served and what were your
                        relations with our CIA establishment in Thailand?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: In terms of Cambodia, I thought their reporting was very helpful. In
                    terms of what was going on in Laos, well Laos was pretty low priority. We also
                    tried to maintain a little bit of a watching brief for Laos because our embassy
                    in Laos was so restricted. And so much of the border between Laos and Thailand
                    was not accessible to them. But Laos was not all that much of a priority for us.
                    It only really became a priority when we had a Lao-Thai border war in which,
                    quite unexpectedly, the Lao acquitted themselves well. Of course they also had
                    the principle positions. We did a little bit on that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned this Lao-Thai war, battles. What was that
                        about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: What seems to have happened, as far as I can determine, is that there
                    were Thai with timber concessions on the Thai side who may have had an
                    arrangement with some Lao to cross the border and take some of the timber there
                    too. The deal may have fallen apart. And then, the Lao military may have decided
                    they ought to get rid of the loggers and fracases may have started in forest
                    areas which were not well defined anyway.</p>
                <p>Once the fighting started and once diplomats started looking at maps, it became
                    clear that there were 2 different sets of maps, and 2 different interpretations
                    of where the border actually was. The Thai had a case and the Lao had a case. I
                    think an outside observer would say that the Thai case was probably stronger,
                    but that rarely matters in this kind of a thing.</p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>So the Thai found themselves with a rapidly escalating situation in which they
                    were attacking well-defended Lao position, where the Lao had the advantage of
                    the ground, as it were. The Thai, who always call the Lao “little brothers,”
                    suddenly found themselves getting a very bloody nose.</p>
                <p>I went up one time on a tour with diplomats to see the area in question. Once the
                    trees are taken off it's kind of a god-forsaken piece of real estate and not
                    many people would be interested in. But it was very difficult for any of us
                    diplomats, to say—well, yes the border is obviously here, or it's obviously
                    there. At any rate, I think the Thai were very unpleasantly surprised to find
                    out what military capability the Lao had. Eventually it was settled by peaceful
                    negotiation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did drugs, narcotics suppression play any role in your
                        operation or was that elsewhere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: One of the very important facets of the relationship with the Thai is
                    narcotics. Most of the narcotics produced in Burma, which is an extremely large
                    producer of heroin and opium, come through Thailand. I'm not sure it was true
                    then, but now most of the heroin on the streets in the United States comes
                    ultimately from Burmese sources. Burmese production increased substantially,
                    nearly double in the late '80s. A great deal of it is coming across the border.
                    So yes, narcotics suppression is one of the primary topics of discussion with
                    the Thai.</p>
                <p>We did have a narcotics suppression section, two State officers, and a large DEA
                    mission. I think it's the largest DEA presence overseas. Relations with the Thai
                    on this question are adequate, but the Thai have never regarded narcotics
                    suppression as the kind of priority item that we have. Working with the Thai on
                    narcotics is one of these rather long processes.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately up on the Thai-Burmese border, the Thai have had relationships with
                    various kinds of insurgent groups on the other side of the border for security
                    purposes and for economic purposes, for so long that they've developed a
                    relationship which also leads to corruption in regard to narcotics. There are a
                    great many civilian, police, and military officials in northern Thailand with
                    bad records in this regard.</p>
                <p>Dealing with narcotics is very difficult. As you know, we can't control our own
                    borders. Even with the best will in the world, you're still not going to be
                    able, I don't think, to control that border, several hundred miles of
                    jungle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did John Gunther Dean operate as an ambassador, from
                        your perspective?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: Mr. Dean is a very interesting personality, probably one of the last of
                    the pro-consular kind of ambassadors. A very formal man in many respects, with,
                    I want to say an authoritarian in approach, that's not quite it, but it will do.
                    A man who certainly has a sense of the theater that's necessary for an
                    ambassador. I think this is important in Thailand. The American ambassador after
                    all in Thailand is a very important figure. The Thai expect a certain type of
                    person. I think from that point of view, Dean filled the bill quite well.</p>
                <p>But he's also a fellow, that in many ways, I think a lot of people found
                    difficult to get along with, rather demanding, a little short sometimes with
                    people. Though I did not find him all that difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I left Thailand in '88.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then what did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I was country director for New Zealand and Australia for a year. Dan
                    O'Donohue, who had become ambassador to Thailand and whom I had worked with
                    before, said that he would like me to take over the Thai desk if I could. So I
                    was only on the Australia/New Zealand desk for a year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That would be '88 to '89.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: '88 to '89, then I took over the Thai desk. In ANZ it was a quiet period.
                    A visit by Hawke to the US had taken place just before I took over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hawke was the Prime Minister?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Hawke was the Prime Minister of Australia. Relations with New Zealand
                    were as relations with New Zealand have been for a long time, friendly, but on a
                    security level still rather acerbic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Prickly.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: Prickly, yes. At that time the New Zealanders had not really been
                    forgiven, particularly by the American military, for their anti-nuclear policy.
                    It was one of those cases where the New Zealanders had been such close friends
                    that their subsequent attitudes were really taken as a betrayal by many people.
                    And, of course, you had the situation where people in the USG thought that they
                    had been lied to by Mr. Lange, which is yet another complication. You still had
                    people in the US government then that had been involved in negotiations with
                    Lange.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lange was Labor?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Lange was the Labor Prime Minister.</p>
                <p>Some people involved thought that Lange was not only a rather nasty piece of
                    work, but a man who did and would lie to them. I don't know the truth of this
                    because I wasn't around for it. It was before my time, but I do know people who
                    felt very strongly. I think probably external circumstances have now made New
                    Zealand's nuclear attitude less important.</p>
                <p>Of course the real importance of New Zealand attitudes was the possible influence
                    on attitudes in Australia. The Australians were more concerned about what we
                    might do vis-a-vis New Zealand than anyone else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you went to the Thai/Burma desk from '89 to '92.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Oddly enough, Burma is one of those places like New Zealand where you can
                    stand on principle. You have so little in the way of countervailing
                    relationships you can stand on principle. In fact, I thought Burma would be a
                    sidelight, but I spent more time on Burma than I thought I would. One might
                    think that you would perhaps spend 10 to 15% of your time on Burma, but, in
                    fact, we spent time on Burma in the last few years simply because of the human
                    rights problem, as well as the narcotics problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On those two things, human rights and narcotics, was this
                        mostly, as you say, principle because we had no leverage?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: As a major narcotics supplier virtually untouched at the source, DEA, I
                    think, would like a much better working relationship with the Burmese. But there
                    are many people in the Congress and elsewhere who don't want any kind of
                    relationship with the Burmese on human rights grounds. There is a significant
                    question in any case whether the Burmese would cooperate appropriately on
                    narcotics. This is because of the deals they have made with the narcotics
                    producers and traffickers. Not deals having to do with narcotics themselves, but
                    political deals. That is, the ethnic groups who push the narcotics, who grow and
                    refine and traffic in narcotics, are the people who were involved in the
                    insurgencies against the government. The implicit or explicit deal is that the
                    groups retain a certain amount of autonomy and they can go on doing what they've
                    been doing as long as they don't make war against the government.</p>
                <p>It is very difficult to know what to do on the narcotics side with Burma. Even if
                    we had a friendly relationship with a different government we would probably
                    have a very difficult relationship on narcotics with them. But when you have an
                    administration in Burma that's as bad as it is on the human rights question, and
                    it's difficult to deal with, it's almost impossible to have any kind of normal
                    relationship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did we do? Sort of just wring our hands or make
                        protests about human rights and that was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Burma is taking over the conversation although Thailand is a much more
                    important place. We had as good a relationship as probably one could have with
                    Burma during the early '80s. We had assisted a narcotics program. We had given
                    them helicopters and other things, we had a spraying program going on. In
                    retrospect it was probably not as effective as we liked to think it was at the
                    time. Nevertheless, we did have a program with the Burmese.</p>
                <p>But once the pro-democratic anti-military government demonstration which began in
                    1988, were suppressed with such severity by the Burmese military, relations had
                    to change. The whole course of Burmese internal development since, has made it
                    very difficult to deal with the regime. It has resulted in calls for economic
                    boycotts and various other stringent measures against the military
                    government.</p>
                <p>The problem, of course, in dealing with the Burmese is we have virtually no
                    leverage. While I was country director we certainly carried on, as assiduously
                    as we could, a policy of trying to isolate the Burmese, make sure that they
                    receive no new international aid, no arms transfers. We spent an awful lot of
                    time ferreting out possible arms transfers to the Burmese and trying to block
                    them from countries which were suspect.</p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>We put together as much of a united front as we could. We had the EEC countries,
                    Japan, Australia, New Zealand, the Nordics, one or two of the post-communist
                    countries—we got everyone to agree that there should be no new aid, no new arms
                    transfers and that we should pursue human rights in the UN. We eventually got a
                    resolution on the Burmese human rights and there have been subsequent
                    resolutions. We also obtained appointment of a special Secretary's
                    representative for human rights to the Burmese. It had not all that much effect,
                    but we got some fairly good reports done by this representative about human
                    rights in Burma.</p>
                <p>We did, I think, as much as we could along those lines, but the Burmese had been
                    so isolated so long that these diplomatic measures don't give you very much
                    leverage. I think we may have mitigated the regime's performance, but the
                    international community has not been able to obtain some basic things. It is
                    still trying to get elementary things out of the Burmese like International
                    Community of the Red Cross visits to political prisoners.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, the Burmese situation has evolved somewhat in that they have
                    suppressed all the possible political opposition so that they are no longer
                    arresting people. They've had a good many releases of political prisoners. What
                    they have not yet done is release Nobel Prize winning political leader, Aung San
                    Su Kyi. She was imprisoned in 1989 before national elections in 1990. She's a
                    woman of immense determination and moral courage, whose party was an
                    overwhelming victor in 1990 elections.</p>
                <p>The upshot is, how do you deal with the Burmese. As I said earlier, Burma is one
                    of those places where you have very little in the way of countervailing
                    relations that would lead you to take a different tact in dealing with them,
                    unlike most other human rights situations in the Far East. Taiwan, Korea,
                    China—in these situations we have had strong countervailing pressures and
                    interests which have forced us to engage. In the Burmese case there are no
                    countervailing interests except for narcotics where progress is uncertain. So it
                    has allowed us to stand on principle, as it were. Thus you have Jim Baker
                    talking about the barbarous butchers of Burma at one of the ASEAN meetings, but
                    you can't show any result for this policy posture.</p>
                <p>So my suggestion has been that instead of maintaining the place without an
                    ambassador, as has been the case since the departure of Bert Levin in 1991, that
                    we reconsider and appoint an ambassador without abandoning or diminishing our
                    policy on human rights. But start to engage the regime.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've always felt that of all the ridiculous forms of
                        diplomatic procedure, removing an ambassador at a time of tension, it's a
                        way of showing your unhappiness but it doesn't strike me as being a very
                        effective way. It's best to keep your top man there when the
                        situation...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>MAYHEW: The Burmese case is a little different. Bert departed at the end of his
                    tour; we did not remove him. We actually nominated a political appointee named
                    Freck Vreeland. He had two problems. One was Senatorial opposition to any
                    ambassador. The other was that during his hearings he offered as his view, when
                    asked about possible economic sanctions, that if the Burmese did not shape up,
                    sanctions might have to be imposed.</p>
                <p>That was enough to push the Burmese over the brink and they removed their
                    agr�ment. Then we went through a period of saying, should we teach the Burmese a
                    lesson by not giving them an ambassador.</p>
                <p>We finally decided to give them an ambassador, Parker Borg, who was nominated and
                    had his hearing. Meanwhile, people on the Hill who did not wish to see an
                    ambassador go to Burma at all, managed to attach a provision on his approval
                    which—I've forgotten the exact wording of it—but made it much more difficult for
                    us to send him. He eventually studied Burmese for a year, then waited nearly
                    another year, then his appointment died with Congress.</p>
                <p>We are at the point now where the argument is made that to send them an
                    ambassador you have to have some significant political signal from the Burmese.
                    In my view, it is of course to make up for our mistake of not having an
                    ambassador by putting a condition on the other party to go forward.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The relations in this '89 to '92 period with Thailand,
                        which as you say was your main, from the Washington perspective...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: I mentioned earlier that Chatchai began to like the idea of being Prime
                    Minister. The military began thinking of how they could get him to move on. He
                    outplayed them politically. They were trying to play his game, but they weren't
                    even in his league. He was so clever a politician that he really had pretty much
                    outsmarted them. He was about to call elections with every prospect of
                    consolidation.</p>
                <p>So in the end they decided to remove him by a coup. Which they did and there was
                    virtually no public reaction. If you had been walking around Bangkok that day
                    you would have not known that a coup had taken place. In fact somebody has told
                    me that they had house guests who were out shopping. They came back and were
                    astounded to find that from the time that they had left in the morning to the
                    time they got back in the afternoon, the government had changed by force because
                    there were no exterior signs of it.</p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>One of the reasons for this attitude was that in the year previous to the coup
                    the government and its political components had spent most of their time
                    jockeying for the spoils, and it had been thought to be a very corrupt
                    government. The public's attitude to the coup was either one of approval or of
                    lack of concern. Of course the Thai are used to the change of their government
                    by this means.</p>
                <p>Chatchai was put under arrest and we condemned the coup. We were required by law
                    to cut off a whole range of things, cooperation and aid and so on, where there
                    is a non-peaceful transition of government. So that meant we had to suspend
                    military aid, economic aid, I think OPEC insurance, EX-IM loans were affected.
                    There was a whole range of things which were affected.</p>
                <p>I think that the Thai in general were a little bit surprised by this, and that
                    most of them were pleased by the attitude that we took. On the other hand, they
                    were chagrined that we would do things like removing funding for children's
                    health projects which had absolutely nothing to do with the military. That was a
                    little hard I think for them to understand.</p>
                <p>Once the military got in they proved to be as incompetent as politicians as they
                    had been before the coup. Their year really was a disaster from the point of
                    view of making a case for the coup. No one believed their public rationale for
                    the coup of protection of the throne and country, and their political management
                    during the time they held power reminded everyone of the problems of military
                    government.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, they installed a technocratic government of well respected
                    caliber. In fact it was so good that it was an interesting contrast to previous
                    civilian political governments as well as to the military's hamhandedness during
                    this period. They chose as Prime Minister a man who was so well respected that
                    he had a certain amount of maneuver room. They could not fully control him
                    because they got into the position where they could not afford to remove their
                    own man.</p>
                <p>The coup was led by a very large group of officers who were in the military
                    school Class 5. Class 5 was one of the largest classes, and at that time had an
                    unusual number of people in authoritative positions, particularly troop
                    commands.</p>
                <p>At any rate, we spent most of that period trying to push the Thai back to some
                    form of democratic government. The period culminated in another political mess
                    created by the military. The military scheduled elections, perhaps a good deal
                    earlier than they wanted because disapproval of the coup became strong, and
                    after a confused period where the military controlled factions attempted to
                    install a civilian figure head, the parties chose Class 5 general Suchinda as
                    Prime Minister. Under other circumstances in earlier times the general might
                    have been satisfactory as a prime minister. But these were different times.</p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>The reaction to the political cynicism of the military's maneuvers was so strong
                    from the Thai public that we had what the press called a cellular telephone
                    evolution—an enormous number of middle class people coming out and demonstrating
                    against the choice of Suchinda and keeping in contact by fax and cellular phone,
                    a testament to political consciousness that was quiescent a year earlier, as
                    well as to economic and technological development.</p>
                <p>It became clear pretty quickly that the situation was deteriorating. It got to a
                    point where the King had to intervene. He can intervene very rarely, but in this
                    particular case after several days of the Army trying to suppress demonstrations
                    and demonstrations building into violence, including one night of violence which
                    there were quite a number of deaths, the King called in 2 generals. One who was
                    a former general, leading the demonstrations, and General Suchinda, and spoke to
                    General Suchinda in a way which made it impossible for Suchinda to do anything
                    else but resign.</p>
                <p>The previous technocratic government was recalled and took over for a second time
                    while you had another set of elections. Those elections installed the Chuan
                    government which lasted until a couple of months ago. Chuan was a relatively
                    non-controversial figure who was fairly well respected, a long time politician,
                    but thought to be an honest one.</p>
                <p>I think that, on reflection, it's easy for the military to pull a coup from the
                    technical point of view. You just run out the tanks and you take the
                    broadcasting station and that sort of thing. But once you have taken power then
                    your real problems start. While we thought that the failed coup of 1981 was
                    going to be the last one, the Suchinda coup may really be the last one.
                    International attitudes are so much different now, Thailand is so much a part of
                    the global complex, and while the public may not be able to stop a coup,
                    attitudes afterwards make it very difficult to govern.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Different world.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Different world, much less tolerance for this kind of thing. Including
                    not only by ourselves but by Asians themselves. It's bad for business. I think
                    there is a different kind of military now in Thailand that realizes a good many
                    of these things. They now have an interest in not making the Thai stock market
                    go down. But there are some things that need to be done.</p>
                <p>For Thailand I think that to prevent future coups you need to have credible
                    civilian government for a reasonable length of time, to demonstrate that there
                    is a reasonable alternative to the military. The Chuan government did pretty
                    well with that, but was not in power long enough. Its successor government is
                    unfortunately seen as old style.</p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                <p>Secondly you had to change the attitudes of the Thai military. You can't have
                    people in the military academy thinking that the prime ministership is a natural
                    goal after you become a general. And there has to be some structural changes to
                    get the Thai military out of anti-riot suppression, get them out of maintaining
                    civil order. Some of those have been done. The military's ability to take over
                    security responsibility in Bangkok, for instance, has been changed.</p>
                <p>I think that the prospects are relatively good. Mostly because Thai society
                    itself is changing. You have so many more people in the middle class than you
                    did even 10 years ago. The Thai military's importance in society and as a
                    channel of social mobility is declining. There's a great deal more opposition to
                    the military taking over. Thai don't see the military as necessary for stability
                    anymore. I think that is important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left the Thai desk and you saw all of these changes
                        coming about. You left the Thai desk in '92.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: In '92. I think in September or October of '92.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: For a year, before I actually retired, I did a special project for the
                    Office for the Freely Associated States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Freely Associated means what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: Meaning Micronesia and Marshall Islands. Those states which had opted for
                    so-called free association with ourselves as a way of solving the trusteeship
                    question which had been with us since the Second World War.</p>
                <p>Palau at that time, which the office also dealt with, was still not yet
                    Associated. It had not accepted the independence option. Free Association is, I
                    suppose you could characterize as a way of becoming independent while still
                    maintaining relationships with us since we still have some responsibilities.</p>
                <p>At any rate, no one had ever calculated how much we were spending in and on
                    behalf of these Freely Associated States. Unlike any other place in the world,
                    domestic agencies operate in them because of the previous relationship and the
                    documents of association. No one had ever sat down and calculated the total
                    funding we were providing under the agreements of association. This proved to be
                    quite a job to chase all this down. It took me all my last year in the
                    Department.</p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>It finally came out that these 2 places, one of which has 65,000 people and the
                    other has I think 37,000 or something like that, we were providing about $230
                    million a year. On a per capita basis, far higher than any place in the world,
                    including Israel.</p>
                <p>I spent a year working this out. Everyday I'd go in and I'd turnover a rock
                    somewhere and I'd find a new program. I had to pole the various USG agencies
                    involved to try to chase this down. I eventually created a computer program with
                    all of these different assistance programs in it—what they cost, who was doing
                    them, etc.</p>
                <p>The idea behind it was that since the major payments to these states are limited
                    by time—they run out just after 2000—were we doing the right things or the wrong
                    things in terms of development. I must say that the prospects don't look very
                    good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I agree. I was out in Ponape last year for a little while.
                        Everything is dependent on American money coming in. They have their bread
                        fruit and they have their yams and they have their fish.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: The problem is that the islands have so little in the way of resources
                    and they're living beyond those resources. The only resources they've got are
                    tuna and possibly eco-tourism. The Marshalls for instance are a disgrace, I
                    don't see any reason why there is malnutrition in a country for which we are
                    providing such an enormous amount of assistance, but there is.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think we might stop at this point. I thank you very
                        much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MAYHEW: You're welcome.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
