<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000863">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Robert L. Nichols </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Information Series</p>
                <p>ROBERT L. NICHOLS</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Robert Amerson </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: August 30, 1988</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>ENTRANCE INTO USIE (PREDECESSOR OF USIA)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bob, let's start at the beginning in this review. What
                        induced you to look to USIA or whatever existed at the time as a
                        career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I suppose it started during World War II when I served in the Navy in
                    Asia, and at the latter part of the war, I was in China briefly. I sort of
                    determined for the usual idealistic reasons, you know, no more wars, things like
                    that, that I wanted to go into the Foreign Service, the diplomatic service.</p>
                <p>So then I had to come back and complete my education at Tufts University, and at
                    Fletcher School for an M.A. degree. Then it was just a question of getting into
                    the Foreign Service. At the time, recruiting was clogged up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is what period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: This is 1950-51. Fletcher people in those days, would make a spring
                    pilgrimage to Washington, and I did that. In the corridors of the State
                    Department I ran into a Fletcher graduate of two years previous, whom I had
                    known as a neighbor in the veterans' housing, Bob McKinnon. Bob is listed on the
                    plaque in the diplomatic entrance to the State Department where all those who
                    died in the service of their country are commemorated. Bob died in Africa about
                    30 years ago. The end of the Fifties, probably.</p>
                <p>Bob said, “What are you doing here?”</p>
                <p>I said, “I'm job hunting.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Are you interested in the Philippines?”</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>I said, “Yes.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Come with me.” He took me into the Office of Philippine Affairs of
                    USIE. I didn't know what it was, but it was part of the State Department. He
                    introduced me to Katherine Porter, and she proceeded to sit me down and talk to
                    me about my interest in the Philippines. She decided, by the end of the
                    interview, that I was the right person to go to a one-man post in Davao, in the
                    southern Philippines.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But didn't you have to come in through the regular
                        channel? How come you were being recruited in the corridor, as it were?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I had taken the Foreign Service exam the year I entered Fletcher and
                    just missed passing it. I had not taken it gain, but at that time there were
                    other ways to enter the Foreign Service. Then even those who had passed the exam
                    were put on a waiting list for their oral interviews. So I had not retaken it,
                    although that was in my future plans. But when I went into the office, they were
                    recruiting. Katherine Porter was recruiting for what was called U.S. Information
                    and Educational Program, or USIE, an was then part of the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And that's what you were recruited for.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: That's what I was recruited for. I didn't know what it was all about,
                    but it sounded fascinating, as Katherine Porter explained what they did. I had
                    no idea there was an information program. I didn't know what an information
                    program was, but that is how I was recruited.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were interested in the Foreign Service mainly from a
                        career and maybe idealistic point of view.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: That's right, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think that many of the people entering the Foreign
                        Service in those days were so motivated?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I think, by and large, most of us were. We came in as “FSS-11s,” which
                    was just above a secretarial level, and I was recruited to replace a person who
                    is today well known in USIA history, Cliff Forster. Cliff at the time was Branch
                    PAO in Davao, and I was recruited to take his place when his tour was up.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>I had to wait for the usual FBI checks and various other procedures to be
                    completed, and I remember Katherine Porter telling me, because I was also being
                    recruited by CIA at the time, “If they (CIA) come through first, let me know and
                    we'll speed things up.” Well, they did, and I called Washington, and they sped
                    their check up enough to enable me to turn down the CIA job. The USIS one seemed
                    more appealing, even though I wasn't sure what it was all about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a background in dealing with words,
                        communication, information?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Not really. All I had was a history/political science major in college,
                    and I'd gone to Fletcher with a concentration on international law,
                    international economics, and diplomacy, the courses that they teach there. Asia
                    was my special interest, but I actually had no real specialization in Asia or on
                    China.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you know about the information program at that
                        time? This was 1951, right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>FIRST ASSIGNMENT: DAVAO, PHILIPPINES</p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Correct. What I knew about it was what I had learned from Katherine
                    Porter that day in the office, and from my discussion with Bob McKinnon, who had
                    served in Cebu as Branch PAO. He was an FSO waiting to be integrated into the
                    State Department at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So your first post then was a one-man post in the
                        Philippines.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes. The State Department took terrible chances. They sent us out there
                    with very little training. I had about six weeks in Washington in the summer of
                    1951. Then my wife and my two children and I were sent out to the Philippines. I
                    spent a couple of months in Manila before I was sent for a brief one-week stay
                    in Davao with Cliff Forster. I think Cliff had to put his stamp of approval on
                    me. I'm not sure, but I believe that's how the final decision was made to send
                    me there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there, then, for the first several years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I was there for about two and a half years, until the end of '53.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What are some of the experiences you recall from those
                        first exposures? What problems did you face?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: I remember very clearly one thing, and when I think about it now and I
                    shudder a bit. It was a one-man post, really an outpost, because there were
                    about three American businessmen in town. One ran the CALTEX plant there, and a
                    couple of them were in the hemp business. There was a Chinese consul from the
                    Nationalist Government, and I was the only other so-called diplomatic
                    representative. But, of course, the Filipinos were much more impressed with an
                    American than they were with a Chinese. Even though this was a rather senior
                    Chinese career diplomat who had been in the Chinese service for 20 years, and
                    here this brand-new, wet-behind-the-ears 26-year-old arrives, and I was made out
                    to be much more important. He rode around in a Cadillac; I rode around in a
                    jeep. But when there was any sort of parade, the jeep was always in front of the
                    Cadillac. (Laughs) But that isn't what embarrassed me so much.</p>
                <p>I was interviewed when I first got there by the newspapers, and this was all sort
                    of an exhilarating and a somewhat overwhelming experience for somebody of my age
                    and experience. So the headline—I still have it in the scrapbook, and I just
                    shudder—it says, “Nichols Vows Make Democracy Grow Stronger.” Well, I always
                    remember this because I think it depicts the sort of arrogance that we Americans
                    have.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Or hopefulness, perhaps.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Hopefulness and a certain amount of arrogance, that we know how to do
                    this, and we can go out and do this. I could go into this new environment, the
                    Philippines, that I was just learning about, despite having served there during
                    the war, and I could make a vow like that! Then I think about where the
                    Philippines is today and what we have done there and haven't done there, and how
                    “successful” we've been, it's a little . . .</p>
                <p>NATURE OF USIS PROGRAM IN DAVAO</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the time of Magsaysay.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Before Magsaysay. I was there when Magsaysay was elected, and that was
                    another experience that I often think about. It has to do with what I was saying
                    about American “arrogance.” This was during the period of Hukbalahaps. This was
                    the period when the Philippines were under the threat of being taken over by the
                    Communists—the early 1950's. The USIS information program there at the time was
                    largely a negative anti-Communist program. The exception was the libraries,
                    because there was very little going on in exchanges. Most programs were mass
                    media, the press, the publications type of program, and we were putting out
                    comic books and leaflets, anti-Communist leaflets. Again I look back and
                    shudder, because I've seen these same things put out in China and other places
                    where they depict the U.S. in a negative way. We were doing the same things in
                    the Philippines in 1951-52.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>Mindanao happened to be a place where there was less of a Huk (Hukbalahap) threat
                    in the Philippines. Today it's quite a different story, but then it was the one
                    area of the Philippines where the threat of the Huks taking over was minimal. I
                    liked the positive programs, and I kept saying, “Let's do some more with the
                    positive programs.” So we got involved in helping what was then called ECA, the
                    AID type of programs of today, working with them information-wise on positive
                    things in Mindanao. And that helped a lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The early 1950's were also the time of Senator McCarthy.
                        Did you have some fallout from that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes, at the latter part of my stay in the Philippines, during the
                    Cohn-Schine visits to the European USIS libraries. They didn't visit the
                    Philippines, fortunately, but there was fall-out. We began to get orders to take
                    certain books off the shelves. I refused to take Howard Fast's books off the
                    shelves in Davao. There were also some articles in certain magazines and we were
                    told to remove those magazines. Again it was something that I just refused to
                    do. I was in a one-man post, and nobody really ever checked up on me. But it had
                    an effect on me, very definitely.</p>
                <p>AMERICAN SUPPORT IN MAGSAYSAY ELECTION</p>
                <p>This was also a period—you asked me about Magsaysay. Well, he ran for president
                    of the Philippines in 1953, and if ever the United States interfered in a
                    foreign election, it was that year. It's interesting because there was an
                    organization called NAMFREL, National Movement for Free Elections. An
                    organization of the same name was involved in electing Mrs. Aquino here a couple
                    of years ago. But in 1953 we were providing the financial support for NAMFREL,
                    the leaflets were printed at the RPC (our press and printing center) in Manila.
                    I remember being confronted by the mayor of Davao, saying, “The Americans are
                    supporting Magsaysay. They're participating, interfering in the elections.”</p>
                <p>I said, “No, we are just supporting NAMFREL, the National Movement for Free
                    Elections. We support free elections.” Well, of course, supporting free
                    elections in the Philippines was support to Magsaysay.</p>
                <p>This was also the period when the Philippines became the training grounds for the
                    whole Vietnam experience. Colonel Ed Lansdale, who later became well known in
                    Vietnam for directing the psy-war campaign, was running Magsaysay's
                    behind-the-scenes campaign in the Philippines. So it was a period which predated
                    all of this counterinsurgency type of win-the-hearts-and-minds-of-the-people
                    sort of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also, this period then launched the career of one Robert
                        Nichols with an emphasis always in your career in the Far East, is that
                        right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Not always.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not always, but with an emphasis, in any case. Just to
                        project ahead, you went from there to Italy, and then to Amsterdam, back to
                        Washington, and then Hong Kong and further experiences in the Far East.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ending, again in the Far East, your last assignment, I
                        think, overseas was PAO Taipei?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: No, Singapore. My last overseas assignment, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then Washington. Looking back again to those early
                        years of your time, you went from the Philippines then to Milan, Italy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: That's correct. That was sort of a result of an inspection. I remember
                    the inspector coming through the Philippines and recommending that “Mrs. Nichols
                    ought to be shown some of the better side of Foreign Service life” after serving
                    in a one-man post in the Philippines. So when I got back to Washington, there
                    was an effort to transfer us to a European post. That's how I eventually ended
                    up in Milan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the meantime, a parenthetical question. Your employer
                        had become the independent agency USIA.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes, after I left the Philippines in 1954, early '54, as I remember, or
                    '53. Was it the end of '53? I can't remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The ending of '53.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: So I was then a member of the United States . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this make any difference?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: It didn't seem to, except when I came back to Washington, I served a
                    couple of months in the Agency at 1776 Pennsylvania Avenue in the area office, I
                    sat on the Indonesian desk while a colleague who had been in Indonesia sat on
                    the Philippine desk. It didn't seem to make much difference, I mean, where you'd
                    served. I filled in temporarily until I went to Milan.</p>
                <p>TRANSFER TO MILAN</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sophisticated and bustling Milan, Italy, was a far cry
                        from your one-man post in the Philippines.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: It sure was. It was a very different experience. It was a four-American
                    staff post, and I went there as the information officer. It was a completely new
                    experience, different than being in the Philippines, certainly. One of the first
                    things I had to do was contend with another language, Italian.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you known any Italian before?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I had two weeks' training in Washington. That's all they gave you at
                    that time. I arrived in Genoa by boat, drove my car from Genoa to Milan, and had
                    to find a place to stay. I got a good introduction that way. I worked with a
                    staff in Milan, where the meetings and everything were conducted in Italian. The
                    PAO was Marjorie Ferguson, who always conducted her staff meetings in Italian.
                    So I had to learn the hard way.</p>
                <p>I commuted when I was in Italy. I lived in Como, and I commuted to Milan by
                    train, which was a marvelous place to have my daily Italian lesson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The type of staff in Milan was quite different from what
                        you had been accustomed in the boondocks in the Philippines?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Very much so, although I had a couple of very well-educated staff
                    members in the Philippines. But in Milan, I had people with doctorates running
                    sections, the press section, and what we called the social-economic section. A
                    man named Arturo Bassi, who was a very impressive individual. Then there was
                    Giovanni Pini, another impressive individual, the former editor of the leading
                    socialist daily paper in Italy. So this was a new experience, and I was still
                    pretty wet behind the ears.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was ambassador at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: Mrs. Luce. Clare Boothe Luce was ambassador. She was a person who made
                    an impression on everyone, the Italians, her staff and all of us, no question
                    about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get acquainted with the opera at La Scala
                        nearby?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes, and one of my great memories is going to see “Porgy ad Bess” there,
                    with the first American company that had ever played at La Scala. La Scala was
                    making an exception. This was the same American company that had traveled to the
                    Soviet Union, and was a very talent-rich group because it had three Porgies and
                    three Besses. Mrs. Ira Gershwin was traveling with them, and Rubin Mamoulian was
                    the director/producer. Gloria Davy was the lead Bess. She later ended up at the
                    Met. Mrs. Luce came to Milan for opening night, escorted by our cultural
                    attach�, the former dean of liberal arts at Howard University, Frank Snowden.
                    Frank is a handsome black man, and very distinguished-looking, while Mrs. Luce,
                    with her blond hair and good looks . . . They sat in the “royal” box in the
                    center of the theater. ~My wife and I were sitting just in back of them.
                    Everybody in that theater looked at them that night.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That must have made quite an impression.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: It certainly did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After Milan, two years in Italy, and then on to Amsterdam,
                        wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ON TO AMSTERDAM: AND LYNDON JOHNSON CLOSES THE POST</p>
                <p>NICHOLS: On to Amsterdam, again a one-man post, as branch public affairs officer.
                    It wasn't a one-man post, because there was a consulate there, a consulate
                    general. It was a one-man USIS post. But I closed Amsterdam in 1957. This was
                    during one of the budget cutbacks. Majority Leader Johnson of the Senate was
                    making some cosmetic cuts, and one of these was Amsterdam. It was cosmetic
                    because the Amsterdam operation only cost $15,000 a year, exclusive of my
                    salary. It certainly didn't make any difference in the overall budget. But it
                    abolishing a post.</p>
                <p>SO, NEXT, THE HAGUE</p>
                <p>Things moved slowly in those days. I was trying desperately to get back to
                    Washington because they'd just decided on opening up Chinese language training
                    again after several years' hiatus. I applied for it. But I sat in a closed post
                    in Amsterdam for two months with no job, waiting for a transfer, and then
                    finally I was transferred to The Hague, 50 miles away, as the information
                    officer.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the capital then. It was the only other post in
                        Holland?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes, that's true. It was the only post left in Holland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So did you start learning Chinese at that time or was that
                        later?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>AND THEN: WASHINGTON - OFFICE OF PRIVATE COOPERATION</p>
                <p>NICHOLS: That came later. After I finished my tour in The Netherlands, I was
                    returned to Washington, but still didn't get my Chinese language training. I was
                    assigned to the Office of Private Cooperation run by a man named Conger
                    Reynolds, assisted by John Begg. This office was an outgrowth of President
                    Eisenhower's People to People Program. You were called a program executive, and
                    they gave you certain committees of American citizens to work with. I was
                    assigned to the hotel committee, the magazine committee, and the book committee.
                    My job was to work with those committees of private citizens and develop
                    programs that got the American people involved with our information programs
                    abroad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a temporary type of assignment while you were
                        waiting for the Chinese program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: It was a regular assignment, but I was working behind the scenes to get
                    into the Chinese language program. Interestingly enough, the man that helped me
                    lives here on the Cape, another former staff member of USIA, Roy Benoit. He
                    headed the language training program.</p>
                <p>ASSIGNMENT TO LONG-SOUGHT-AFTER CHINESE LANGUAGE TRAINING</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did the Chinese language assignment come
                        through?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: One year after I got back to Washington. My office finally released me.
                    I went into Chinese language training in the fall of 1959.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was right after mainland China had been taken over by
                        Mao Zedong and company, right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Ten years after.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But we were still without relationships with mainland
                        China.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes. There was no relationship. The only posts where Chinese language
                    officers were being used were in Taiwan, then called the Republic of China, Hong
                    Kong, and Singapore, where Chinese is spoken. They would also assign Chinese
                    language officers to places like Kuala Lumpur, Bangkok, and Saigon, where there
                    was a Chinese population and some possibility to utilize your training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So there were not very many of you in Chinese language
                        training?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I was in the second class, I think, of Agency officers. We started out
                    in FSI in Washington, and did six, seven, eight months there. Then provided you
                    were doing well enough, you were sent on to Taichung out in Taiwan to complete
                    your training. At the time, I had three classmates from USIA, Howard Stingle,
                    Norman Barnes, and Mervin Hayworth. The others were from the State Department
                    and CIA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your expectations at the time, if you can
                        recall, about how you were going to use this language ability? Did you ever
                        envision getting into “Red China?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Oh, I had hoped so, of course. There wasn't a one of us that was in
                    Chinese language training that didn't have that goal in mind. I think it
                    motivated most everyone, this desire to go and serve in China. We felt sure that
                    eventually we would be there. That was very true.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In fact, how did this develop in your case? You went to a
                        Chinese-speaking post next?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HONG KONG - CULTURAL AFFAIRS OFFICER: EXPERIENCES WITH VISITING AMERICAN
                    ARTISTS</p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I followed my two-plus years of Chinese language training with an
                    assignment in Hong Kong as cultural affairs officer, which, unfortunately, is
                    not the best place to use Mandarin Chinese, because most of the Chinese in Hong
                    Kong speak Cantonese. However, I did get to use it, and of course, it was
                    definitely a Chinese environment and Chinese post in many respects. I was
                    dealing with a Chinese audience there, by and large.</p>
                <p>It was a very interesting assignment for other reasons. It was interesting
                    because it taught me a lot about exchange programs, being a cultural affairs
                    officer, and I was working with the type of programs I believed in—exchanges,
                    libraries, book translation, speakers, etc.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hong Kong is the kind of place where a lot of Americans
                        come to visit. You must have had a lot of American officialdom.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Every American wants to stop in Hong Kong. The entertainers were there
                    in droves. “Satchmo” was there, Sinatra was there. He was moving or trying hard
                    to move in Kennedy circles, so he came there to do good things for them, charity
                    balls and the like. We made good use of people like Sinatra and Gary Moore, but
                    more especially of Rod Serling and Kirk Douglas who came out under our auspices.
                    Serling—that was an interesting experience.</p>
                <p>I was in charge of the book translation program while we were in Hong Kong. One
                    of the plays that had been translated into Chinese was Thornton Wilder's “Our
                    Town.” I was reminded of this recently, when I read recently about Arthur
                    Miller's “Death of a Salesman” being done in China. Also I think that Charlton
                    Heston was over there directing some American play in Chinese.</p>
                <p>Well, we were offered Rod Serling as an American specialist to come to Hong Kong.
                    What are we going to do with a Rod Serling, a “Twilight Zone” man? A very
                    interesting person, but what are we going to do with him? Well, we had this play
                    that had just been translated, “Our Town,” and we had a college in Hong Kong,
                    Hong Kong Baptist College, that wanted to put on this play. There was a young
                    Chinese who had been on a Fulbright to the United States and had gone to the
                    Yale School of Drama. He was back teaching at Baptist College. So I talked with
                    him about it. I said, “Rod Serling's coming out. Is there any way you could use
                    him in the development of the production of this play?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Oh, my God, that would be marvelous.” He could help explain the meaning
                    of the play and the significance of it. He could help direct.</p>
                <p>So when Serling came, the city got very excited about this, and Serling spent his
                    time in Hong Kong helping direct “Our Town” in Chinese. Of course, he had to
                    work through the Chinese Yale graduate, but what he did was get across Wilder's
                    meanings and intentions. The thing that came across so beautifully and to which
                    the Chinese related was the use of mime in the play. There's so much of that in
                    “Our Town.” Of course, the Chinese use mime a great deal, too. This worked out
                    very well, and it played to huge audiences in Hong Kong, and it was a very great
                    success.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was in the early Sixties?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: That would be 1964, somewhere around then.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After your Hong Kong assignment, what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: It was time for a tour in Washington, because I had never done a full
                    tour in Washington. I was assigned to the East Asia area as a desk officer for
                    Australia, New Zealand, and the Pacific Islands. My duties also included liaison
                    with CU in State.</p>
                <p>If I can for a minute, I'd like to go back to Hong Kong to a couple of things
                    that happened in Hong Kong. One was that a Chinese university was established
                    during my stay there, and as I said, I enjoyed the stay in Hong Kong because I
                    learned a lot about exchange programs. We were able to establish a program with
                    the University of California and the Chinese University, an exchange program of
                    professors and students, undergraduate, graduate students, and professors going
                    both ways each year. The Chinese University was a brand-new university in Hong
                    Kong. It came from the consolidation of three private colleges, all of which
                    were actually the successor colleges to those types that had existed pre-1949 in
                    China. A Christian college, a private college and the national university
                    (government funded).</p>
                <p>These colleges had been established in Hong Kong after 1949, but were recognized
                    by the British only as “post-secondary schools.” However, in 1963 they were
                    amalgamated as one Chinese University, with Chinese the language of instruction.
                    The first vice chancellor came from Berkeley, a man named Li Choh-ming, a very
                    well-known Chinese-American educator.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which Chinese language?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: They used both Cantonese and Mandarin at the university. Mandarin, of
                    course, is the national language of China, and it was also the national language
                    of the then-Republic of China (Taiwan), and remains still the language that is
                    taught in the schools in both places. Cantonese is not really taught, but it is
                    the first language of the majority of Hong Kong people.</p>
                <p>NIXON VISIT TO HONG KONG</p>
                <p>Another thing that happened when I was in Hong Kong which had some significance
                    was my first experience with “handling” somebody of historic importance. Mr.
                    Nixon came to Hong Kong in the fall of 1965. He was attached to a law firm, but
                    everybody believed he was probably working to run again for President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He had lost the governorship of California and was a few
                        years ahead of his election as President.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: He was the lawyer for Pepsi-Cola, I believe. Cables announcing his visit
                    came into the consulate general in Hong Kong. When he was vice president, he had
                    been in Hong Kong, and somebody had persuaded him to endow a library with some
                    books and perhaps some money. It had become known as the Nixon Library. On this
                    trip to Hong Kong, the consulate general wasn't too anxious to handle Mr. Nixon.
                    He was not in public office. They didn't know what to do with him, but they knew
                    they couldn't ignore him.</p>
                <p>So the consul general said, “We've got an out. The Nixon Library and the cultural
                    officer, they make a pair.” Well, Bob Nichols was made the control officer for
                    Richard Nixon when he was in Hong Kong. Of course, Nixon got a lot of attention,
                    press attention and so forth. I was sent down to brief him on the local
                    situation.</p>
                <p>I remember the consul general called me in early in the morning and said, “For
                    God's sake, Bob, make sure he understands what's going on, the problems in Hong
                    Kong we have on Vietnam and with Peking.” He was referring to the fact that
                    Peking was accusing the United States of using Hong Kong as a base for its
                    Vietnam operations. Of course, it was an R &amp; R place for the U.S. Navy, and
                    also the Army. The fleet was visiting all the time, and soldiers were flying in
                    from Saigon daily.</p>
                <p>Just prior to Nixon's arrival, one of the R &amp; R planes had crashed at the end
                    of the runway at Kaitak Airport in Hong Kong. Everybody on board was killed. It
                    was a headline story and also drew attention to the fact that Hong Kong was
                    being used by the U.S. military to send its troops from Vietnam. I was to make
                    sure that Mr. Nixon understood the sensitivities on this score, and that when he
                    met the press, to be aware of the problem. Of course, I had heard all these
                    things about how Nixon didn't like the press, and I knew I was going to have to
                    run a press conference for him.</p>
                <p>I spent a day and a half with him, and the second day we went out to the Nixon
                    Library. He asked a lot of questions. It was just Nixon and myself in the car,
                    along with a congressman from California named Pat Hillings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your impressions of Nixon the man at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: My impressions of Nixon prior to his arrival were very negative. My
                    impressions of Nixon the man, based on this experience, were quite positive. He
                    had a tremendous intellectual curiosity. He wasn't telling me anything but
                    rather was picking my brain for everything and anything I could tell him about
                    China and about the attitude of the people in Hong Kong towards China, and the
                    attitude of the Chinese towards Hong Kong. He never stopped asking questions,
                    one after another, which was quite impressive, I thought, as an insignificant
                    cultural affairs officer in Hong Kong, what an experience to have a man who had
                    been vice president of the United States and had run for President and was to
                    run again, asking me these questions and paying attention to what I had to
                    say.</p>
                <p>Then I warned him about the press. I told him that the American correspondents
                    would try to take over and dominate the press conference, that the Chinese were
                    very passive, and that it would be a good idea if he paid attention to the
                    Chinese questions. And by gosh, he did. He took extra time. In fact, he delayed
                    his departure from Hong Kong on an Air France plane. They had to hold the
                    plane—he was going to Saigon—because he held a press conference longer, mainly
                    because he was letting the Chinese get their questions in. That was a real
                    teaching experience to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned Vietnam in this context. At that point it
                        was quiescent. The French had left several years earlier, and we were not
                        really involved.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: We were getting quite involved by '65, yes. It was after the Tonkin
                    Gulf.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is after the death of President Kennedy and during
                        the Johnson Administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: This is during the Johnson Administration. The Tonkin Gulf resolution
                    had already been passed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it was on the front burner.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: It was on the front burner, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any other intimations during that posting of
                        what was to come in Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: You had a pretty strong feeling about what was going on, because it was
                    the R &amp; R people, not only the military servicemen, but also our people
                    posted there. The USIS people and State Department people would come into Hong
                    Kong, and many of the wives were living in Hong Kong while husbands were in
                    Vietnam. So we were getting a good dose of information about what was going on
                    in the country, and it was obviously a much bigger thing than we ever expected.
                    It was a very worrisome thing. It was really front burner in our minds out
                    there, day in and day out. You could not forget that Vietnam was right around
                    the corner from Hong Kong.</p>
                <p>WASHINGTON AGAIN; AUSTRALIA/NEW ZEALAND DESK OFFICER, THEN VOA AS CHIEF OF
                    CHINESE BRANCH</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went, the next year or so, to the Voice of America,
                        and then concentrated on Chinese relationships at that time. That's all part
                        of the same fabric, I suppose.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I was only the area officer for Australia and New Zealand, etc., for
                    about six months when I was asked to succeed Jerry Stryker at the Voice of
                    America as chief of the Chinese branch. That was quite an experience. A very
                    interesting experience, and an intimidating experience, too, for me, in the
                    beginning, because succeeding Jerry Stryker, who was probably the best Chinese
                    language officer the U.S. Information Agency has ever had, was intimidating.
                    Jerry recommended me, and I don't think it was based on my Chinese; it was just
                    because Jerry had worked with me and felt that I could do the job. But to go in
                    there and be in charge, and know that you're in charge of Chinese language
                    broadcasts, boy, it worried me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: VOA had a pretty heavy schedule of Chinese language
                        broadcasts at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Oh, yes, very heavy. It was eight hours a day. Some of those were
                    repeats. I think we had three and a half, four hours of original broadcasts, but
                    that's a lot of air time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was on those programs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: News and features. We did a lot with news and features, and we had a big
                    staff. I've forgotten how large the staff was. It's still large. But it was 25,
                    30, 40 people, up to 40 people at a time, including contract people. Some of
                    them were strictly announcer types, news readers, and then there was the writing
                    staff who wrote features, some of which were original features, some of which
                    were based on translated material that was used for the back half of the
                    programs. The front half of the program was always news and commentary. Then
                    there was music, also, but most was news and commentary.</p>
                <p>Q: Since the United States had no formal relations with mainland China, to what
                    extent was the VOA used as a channel for messages one way or another? SUBTLE
                    CHANGE IN TERMINOLOGY ON VIA BROADCASTS TO MAINLAND CHINA: <pb facs="0016"
                        n="Page0016"/> ITS EFFECT</p>
                <p>NICHOLS: A very interesting thing happened while I was there in 1968. I had
                    absolutely no idea that anything was going on at that time regarding a change in
                    our relationship with China, but I was very disturbed because we, as a
                    communications agency, and the Voice of America was a tool of communications, a
                    major medium for our message, and that our main—to use the word—target audience
                    was the people in China, not the people in Taiwan. I was disturbed that we were
                    using language in Chinese that was offensive to the people in China.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Because it was our policy to do that. Our policy at the time required
                    that we call them Communist China, not the People's Republic of China. We had to
                    call them Zhonggong, and that means Chinese Communists. We didn't call it
                    Beijing; we called it Peiping, which was the nationalist name for Peking, which
                    means “northern peace.” Beijing means “northern capital.” You see, the
                    nationalists never had their capital in Peking; they had it in Nanking and
                    Chungking. So we couldn't call it that. And there was other terminology that we
                    could not use. We had to use the language that Taiwan used in describing the
                    government in China.</p>
                <p>Well, I wrote a memo to the State Department about this, and I made my feelings
                    known. I said, “Look, we're trying to communicate with people. If we're not
                    going to have them turn off right at the beginning of our broadcast, then we
                    better start using language that they accept.” This went over to the PRC desk in
                    State. It wasn't called the PRC desk, the People's Republic desk, in those days;
                    it was called the Communist China desk, the deputy director of which was an old
                    colleague of mine, Dick Donald, who has now passed away. Dick had worked with me
                    in Hong Kong. He said, “I like your memo. This is good. I'm going to pass it on
                    up.”</p>
                <p>Well, it went up to Bill Bundy, who was then the assistant secretary. By gosh, in
                    a week, I got approval to use the proper terms on our broadcast, except when I
                    was directly quoting Secretary Rusk, who always said “Communist China” and
                    always said “Peiping.” But otherwise, unless I was directly quoting an American
                    official, I could use the proper terminology.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A kind of turning point, then. To what extent did the
                        State Department pay attention to the Chinese broadcasts, use them, control
                        them, be concerned about them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: They were concerned about them. They didn't control them. They would
                    look over some of the commentaries we were putting out. I worked with them quite
                    closely, because I had a lot of colleagues in State with whom I had gone through
                    Chinese language training.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>There was a panel at that time, an advisory panel on China for the State
                    Department, which drew on academics from all over the country, people like John
                    Fairbanks, Bob Scalapino, and Doak Barnett, people who would come for a session
                    once every two or three months. I'd sit in on these as the director of Voice
                    broadcasts to China. The talk was about all aspects of U.S. policy towards China
                    and what should be changed.</p>
                <p>There was little doubt that the feeling in the Department of State then at the
                    levels below the very top was that we should be moving in the direction of
                    rapprochement with Peking.</p>
                <p>To finish up this story about the Voice of America—I've always wondered, as I
                    read later, and later when I served in Taiwan and when I read about the signals
                    that were given to China that we were moving away from our hard stance, whether
                    or not we didn't use that change in language as one of our signals. I've never
                    talked with anyone at State about this, really, because Dick Donald died, and I
                    never had a chance to talk to Bill Bundy about it, and I've never seen it
                    mentioned in the memoirs that I've read. But I have talked about it to Chinese
                    in China who listened to the Voice of America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You make your annual trips even these days to China, so
                        you are well in touch there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes. I ran into two people that told me they were listening to VOA then.
                    They heard this difference in language and to the Chinese it was very
                    significant, and people talked about it. In other words, the Chinese caught this
                    change in language. To me it made everything seem worthwhile. Whether or not
                    they were telling me the truth, it sounded sincere, anyhow, so I think it
                    probably was used as one of the early signals.</p>
                <p>The signals to China began to flow in the next two years, when I was in
                    Taiwan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is an interesting focus on the total apparatus of the
                        U.S. Government utilizing all the tools it has at its command for foreign
                        affairs purposes. One wonders whether the top echelon policy makers—Bundy,
                        Rusk, and higher—were aware of this signal and what it might have meant to
                        the Chinese at the time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I have to think that certainly Bundy knew. I mean, Bundy had to approve
                    it. He had approved the change in language. I wasn't allowed to do it without
                    his approval, so I'm sure he did. Now, whether this went up to Secretary Rusk,
                    whether it went that far . . . See, this was prior to Kissinger. Most of the
                    signals came in the next administration. The other signals have all been written
                    up in memoirs. This development came prior to that.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You might have been, you're saying, softening up your
                        Chinese audience with this idea by this change in language.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I think the whole idea in communications—you just can't communicate with
                    people unless you use language that they will accept. I mean, it's such a basic
                    principle, that maybe it was accepted on that basis. Somebody saw the logic of
                    this and accepted it for that reason.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're now at 1965 or thereabouts, '66, then '68. After
                        Voice of America, what came next?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMY WAR COLLEGE (1 YEAR), THEN DEPUTY PAO, TAIWAN</p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I went to the Army War College in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, for a
                    year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A year off?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes, it was a year off. In effect, it was a year off. It was a very
                    interesting year. I guess what it taught me more about than anything was that we
                    have some very fine minds amongst our military. It was a good sort of
                    cross-fertilization. It helped me work with the military later on. I did some
                    interesting research on China while I was there, for my paper, and it was a good
                    year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then back to active duty as what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Then I went out to Taiwan as deputy PAO in '69.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you been in Taiwan before?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: In language school. I'd spent two years there in language school, so I
                    was going back to a place I knew. I went out as deputy PAO. When I arrived, the
                    PAO was Ken Boyle, but soon thereafter he was replaced by Bob Clarke, who passed
                    away a few years ago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So the changing nature of the Chinese-American
                        relationship must have been one of your top focuses.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: When I went out there, it wasn't apparent that it was going to be. You
                    see, I went out there just after the change in administration. The Nixon
                    Administration had just come in. I was aware of the Nixon Foreign Affairs
                    article on China, written prior to his being elected, in which he said the U.S.
                    can't afford not to have relation with the most populous country in the world, a
                    quarter of the world's population. So it was obvious Mr. Nixon felt that
                    something should change, and Mr. Kissinger made it known, too.</p>
                <p>USIS'S CAUTIOUS MOVE TO SUGGEST TO TAIWAN THAT U.S. ATTITUDE TOWARD MAINLAND
                    CHINA WAS SHIFTING</p>
                <p>But very soon we began to see subtle changes taking place. Kissinger would have
                    off-the-record briefings for the press that used to come to us as “limited
                    official use.” They'd be given out by the press quoting a highly placed official
                    of the administration. Well, from the things that were being said by Kissinger,
                    you could see where we were going.</p>
                <p>Bob Clarke and I decided that what we needed to do was prepare our audience in
                    Taiwan for what apparently was coming. Of course, we didn't know exactly what
                    was coming. We had as much difficulty persuading the embassy, I think, to go
                    along with our ideas, as we had in persuading the Taiwanese, the people on
                    Taiwan, of what we were saying was happening. We gave monthly press briefings to
                    the Chinese press, and when we had the right visitor, we'd draw on that person.
                    I gave one on the Nixon doctrine. All these were beginnings, an attempt to show
                    that U.S. foreign policy was moving away from its hard position, and that a
                    d�tente was in the works.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That must have generated tremendous pressures by the
                        Nationalist Chinese in Taiwan against the American official
                        establishment.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: There was certainly a great deal, and some of it was manifested in
                    rather unpleasant ways. In Taiwan, we had branch offices down-island in
                    Taichung, in Tainan, and in Kaohsiung. In 1970 I was visiting our office in
                    Kaohsiung when we got a telephone call from Tainan, 30 miles from Kaohsiung. We
                    were sitting down to dinner at the branch PAO's house, when a call came in that
                    a bomb had just blown up the USIS Tainan office. So we went to Tainan. The
                    office had been almost completely destroyed, and several people had been
                    seriously hurt. This happened the day after Double Tenth, the Republic of
                    China's National Day (Double Ten, October 10.) It also happened at a time when
                    the United States had just given asylum or had helped, supposedly, in the escape
                    from Taiwan of a Taiwan nationalist, a man named Peng Ming-min.</p>
                <p>The Chinese government was not happy with us, and hose strong supporters of this
                    Nationalist regime were not happy with us. Who placed the bomb was never
                    officially acknowledged, but there were very strong suspicions about the
                    source.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>DIFFERENCE OF OPINION: USIS - EMBASSY</p>
                <p>This was a time on Taiwan when, again, things like language in our press releases
                    became important. The same thing I'd had with the Voice. I remember going to the
                    embassy once to get approval for some language for the press from the deputy
                    chief of mission. I said, “This is what we want to use.”</p>
                <p>He said, “You can't say that.”</p>
                <p>I said, “That's a direct quote from Kissinger's press briefing.”</p>
                <p>And he said, “Kissinger doesn't make U.S. foreign policy.” [Well, at that time,
                    of course, Kissinger headed the National Security Council; he wasn't Secretary
                    then.]</p>
                <p>I looked at him. I didn't say anything, but I looked at him and thought, “Boy,
                    there's a lack of realism here in the embassy, as well.” There really was. There
                    was a tremendous amount of resistance. They couldn't believe what was
                    happening.</p>
                <p>Another thing that happened, just before I left Taiwan to go to Singapore—well, a
                    lot of things happened while we were in Taiwan, actually. I should mention this
                    was a time when we withdrew the Seventh Fleet from the Taiwan Straits. It was
                    announced by Vice President Agnew when he was out there on one of the two trips
                    he made while I was there. Agnew brought the news to Chiang Kai-shek that we
                    were taking the Seventh Fleet out of the Taiwan Straits.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Chiang, the old Chinese Nationalist leader, was still in
                        power then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Oh, yes, he didn't die until 1975. He was there and his presence was
                    known. A lot of the work of the administration had been taken over by his son,
                    Chiang Ching-kuo, but Chiang Kai-shek was still in power. He dealt with Vice
                    President Agnew.</p>
                <p>INTERESTING DEVELOPMENTS JUST AS NICHOLS IS LEAVING FOR NEW POST - SINGAPORE</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Maybe we can jump ahead a little bit. We're talking about
                        relations between U.S.A. and China. Where were you when the renewal of
                        relationship was announced and became public knowledge?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: The renewal, first of all, the Kissinger trip. He arrived in Beijing the
                    day I left Taiwan on transfer to Singapore. I didn't know it. This is a little
                    story that's interesting, because just a week prior to this, my successor had
                    arrived in Taiwan, and I took him down-island over the Fourth of July. This was
                    '69. We visited the branch posts and missed the Fourth of July party in Taipei.
                    When we returned, there was sort of a flap because the ambassador was concerned
                    about the lack of any news in the papers about the Fourth of July party. Well,
                    there had been some in the Chinese papers, but he only read the English language
                    press, the China News.</p>
                <p>The day that I was making my farewell call and introducing my successor in the
                    ambassador's office, he said, “Bob, can't we do something about getting
                    something favorable in the press?” He'd just returned from a trip to Washington.
                    He said, “Do the Chinese know I saw the President?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Mr. Ambassador, we didn't know that you'd seen the President.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Just a minute.~” He went over to his briefcase and pulled out a photo,
                    a large photo, and he handed it to me. He said, “Can we do something with this?”
                    It was a photo of President Nixon and himself (Ambassador Walter McConaughy)
                    sitting in the Oval Office, opposite each other, staring with a blank look on
                    each face.</p>
                <p>I looked at that picture and said, “But sir, what would be the caption?” He said,
                    “Okay, okay,” and put it away. He felt I didn't like the idea. It wasn't the
                    kind of picture that would have given the people on Taiwan any particular
                    feeling of reassurance. I don't think that he was even told what was going on at
                    that time. The President didn't know what to say to him, and he didn't know what
                    to say to the President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And it showed on their faces.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: A week later, Kissinger was in Beijing. So no question, the President
                    knew that Kissinger was going to make this trip to China when he saw the
                    Ambassador. I saw the news when I stopped in Penang with my wife en route to
                    Singapore.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you did not have to face the Nationalist Chinese in
                        Taiwan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: No, I left and several newspapermen saw us off at the airport. I wasn't
                    there when it happened. I was on vacation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They must have been horrified and angered.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: Oh, I'm sure they were. I know they were, yes, definitely. But we had
                    prepared them for something like this coming.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We were talking about the moment when you were in Taiwan,
                        when the Kissinger trip became known, and some of your other recollections
                        of that post.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I have one strong recollection of the post. I was talking a minute ago
                    about Kissinger's influence and the direction we were taking in China, and how
                    poorly people in the administration understood exactly what his position was.
                    Near the end of my tour, just before I left Taiwan in June 1971, Frank
                    Shakespeare, director of the Agency at the time, and the area director, John
                    Reinhardt, arrived in Taipei.</p>
                <p>I've mentioned that we'd had these monthly briefings for the press on U.S.
                    policy. Well, Bob Clarke, the PAO, said, “We got Frank Shakespeare here, let's
                    use Frank Shakespeare and let him talk to the Chinese press, and maybe he can
                    give them something special, and maybe he can reassure them a little bit.” The
                    Ambassador thought this was a good idea. No American officials had been visiting
                    Taiwan and you could sense Taiwan was becoming a pariah of some sort. Frank
                    Shakespeare was the first American official of any significance to come to
                    Taiwan for some time, so we thought we'd use him.</p>
                <p>On the day he arrived with John Reinhardt, Bob Clarke and I presented him with
                    this idea, and he liked the idea, but he said, “I've got to get approval.” Bob
                    Clarke held a reception at his house that night for Shakespeare to meet the
                    Chinese staff. While we were there, Shakespeare drafted a cable to Washington to
                    present what we wanted to do, and to see if there were any objections to his
                    doing this. We were at Bob's house. He said, “How can I get this cable off?”</p>
                <p>I said, “We can get it down to the embassy and the duty officer will get it out.”
                    We were at Bob's house. The USIS secretary was Dotty Fry. Dotty and I went into
                    Bob's bedroom, where there was a typewriter. I read it over, and Dotty typed it
                    up. I looked at the addressees and neither State nor USIA were included. So I
                    added them. I thought it was just an oversight. I took the typed version to John
                    Reinhardt. John looked at it, and took it over to Frank Shakespeare.</p>
                <p>The next thing I knew, Frank Shakespeare came over to me and led me down a
                    corridor. He put his arm around my shoulder and said, “Bob, I know you're a good
                    bureaucrat.” (Laughs) “You've made those changes in the cable addressees, but I
                    have to tell you, I don't want this to go to the State and Agency. I only want
                    it to go to the White House, to Kissinger.” I got the message, and learned a
                    valuable lesson. I mean, here was the Director of the U.S. Information Agency,
                    but he was operating only with Kissinger and the White House, ignoring the
                    Department of State and his own Agency.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>Of course, the reply came back and he was told not to meet with the press. So we
                    never had the Shakespeare briefing. He was not granted permission. I have always
                    felt that to be a revealing anecdote.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was the nature of Frank. He was more interested
                        in...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: It was also the nature of Kissinger on China policy. That's where all
                    the decisions were made, strictly in the White House with Kissinger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. From Taiwan, then, you mentioned you had gone to
                        Singapore and had your own post at PAO.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SINGAPORE, AS PAO</p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes. I finally got my own post in Singapore, 20 years after coming into
                    the Foreign Service. It seemed like a long wait, but it was worth it. It was an
                    ideal time, you know. For years in the Agency, how we all suffered with the lack
                    of funding flexibility. You couldn't move your funds around, but rather funds
                    were locked into whatever was designated in your budget. I think one of the
                    greatest things that ever happened to the Agency was Henry Loomis' decision to
                    start the resource management system. It was initiated when I was in Taiwan, and
                    we learned to use it there. You could do all sorts of creative things with
                    it.</p>
                <p>When I got to Singapore, I thought Singapore was terrific, because if ever there
                    was a post that needed a lot of changes, at least as far as I was concerned, it
                    was the USIS, Singapore. It was sort of steeped in the past; nothing had been
                    changed in 25 years. Now with the RMS system, you could make changes and get all
                    the support in the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the change in China policy make a big impact in that
                        regard?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: No. In Singapore, no. Actually, it was not related to the changes I
                    wanted to make. When I got to Singapore, I didn't even think about China. I
                    thought about what I could do with things like the library. The library was
                    filled with students from a nearby school who came in to get into
                    air-conditioning to do their homework. They weren't even using our books. That
                    sort of thing completely turned me off. I wanted to make changes.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>This was also the time of Allen Carter's Infomat in Japan. I thought all these
                    concepts were interesting. I visited Japan wanted to see what Infomat was like.
                    I had my own ideas, and I saw some good things happening in Japan, but I also
                    felt there were a lot of things that just didn't apply or weren't good ideas for
                    Singapore. But anyhow, I had a chance to do some things with Singapore and
                    establish what was, I guess, the first “resource center” in the Agency. There is
                    nothing very original about a “resource center” as such, but it was the first
                    one in USIS. The Agency took on the name for various libraries elsewhere later
                    on and some were modeled closely on the one in Singapore.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Singapore must have been another kind of listening post, a
                        visiting station for many prominent Americans. Did you have a flow of
                        visitors?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes, it was, but most of the good people we had coming through there
                    were a result of the Star system. Remember the Star system? Ambassador Pat
                    Moynihan of India initiated the Star system. What he did was get a lot of people
                    that he knew, friends, into the AMSPEC program. Some of these people we got, and
                    we could make selections under the resource management system of those we
                    wanted. So we did get good people, some very interesting people during that
                    period. Bucky Fuller—I can remember having Buckminster Fuller there and having
                    top Singaporeans all sitting on the floor listening to him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was known as innovative.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Absolutely, full of fascinating ideas. Singaporean sitting around at his
                    feet, literally at his feet. Then we had people like Edward Teller and Norman
                    Podhoretz, who represented something else. For neo-conservative thinking, we had
                    Norman Podhoretz. And, of course, Edward Teller, that was my first exposure to
                    him, and an interesting exposure, I must say. He got a lot of attention there.
                    Whether we wanted it or not, we did get a lot of the people talking about U.S.
                    policy in Vietnam, academic types, by and large, but people that were
                    supportive. Singapore basically backed the United States on Vietnam. It was not
                    a place where you really tried to push this, and I didn't try to emphasize it. I
                    was trying to emphasize other things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the principal concerns of those leaders of
                        Singapore about the United States in those years?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: That's a good question for me because of what I was concerned with in
                    setting up our program there. In restructuring the library, I didn't think we
                    should go with an oral sort of library, appealing to and open to everyone. I
                    wanted a library that would appeal to certain individuals and groups in
                    Singapore. I wanted to build a library based on the concurrence of interests,
                    where our U.S. interests coincided with those of the Singaporeans. So that's why
                    we built the resource center. We emphasized those areas and developed a
                    specialized library. In other words, it concentrated on those areas and ideas
                    which were of special interest to Singaporeans. So we had large collections in
                    areas of business and education, and American foreign policy was heavily
                    emphasized. Also there was a big section on economics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not much concern about the big China question, then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Oh, yes. Oh, definitely. We had a section in the library on China
                    itself. Singapore's population is about 75% ethnic Chinese, so there was an
                    interest, although the Singapore government did not recognize the People's
                    Republic of China. It still doesn't today, as a matter of fact. It says it never
                    will until Indonesia does. Singapore does not recognize it, despite government
                    control being largely in the hands of ethnic Chinese. The prime minister is
                    Chinese. One of the biggest concerns in Singapore was fear of racial strife,
                    concern about integrating a society which was composed of several racial groups,
                    Malays, Indians, and Chinese. Therefore they didn't want undue influence from
                    Peking, which they felt would subvert the ethnic Chinese population.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Different conflicts. What was happening in the United
                        States at the time? You were there from '71 to '74, which is the time of the
                        change of administration, Watergate, and all that. How much impact did that
                        make there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: It had its impact, but the Singaporeans, first of all, just couldn't
                    understand Watergate, I think like many countries. They just couldn't understand
                    why we were so concerned about it. I couldn't believe it. I had a very hard time
                    believing it myself. I couldn't believe a President of the United States would
                    do these things and lie about them. I remember when I finally began to believe
                    it was all true was when a person who certainly was a part of that
                    administration, our area director for Asia, Kent Crane, paid a visit. He was
                    staying at our house. We were having breakfast, and Kent saw the morning papers.
                    There was some terrible story about what was going on in the White House. He
                    said, “It's true. There's no question about it. That's exactly what's going on.”
                    It was some question about Erlichman, Haldeman, this and that. I've forgotten
                    the story.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Kent Crane, as I recall, was brought in by the
                        administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: Absolutely. Kent Crane was Agnew's foreign affairs advisor. When Agnew
                    made his first trip to Taiwan around New Year's 1969-70, Kent Crane was along as
                    his foreign affairs advisor. That's when I first met Kent Crane. Little did I
                    know he was going to become my boss a couple of years later. When he moved from
                    the Vice President's office to the Agency. I think he saw the handwriting on the
                    wall. Knowing Crane, I am sure he saw the handwriting on the wall over at the
                    White House, and he wanted out, and someplace else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When he sort of nodded his head and said, “That's the way
                        it is,” he had seen it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Oh, yes, he'd seen it. I was almost sure. After hearing him, I began to
                    believe it myself. It was a very disturbing thing. I left Singapore, as a matter
                    of fact, on the day that the President resigned. It was also Singapore's
                    National Day, so you don't forget that. That was the day I finally left
                    Singapore.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You never were assigned to China?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MISSING ASSIGNMENT TO CHINA - BACK TO WASHINGTON</p>
                <p>NICHOLS: No, but in 1973, when the Liaison Office was established in China—after
                    the Shanghai communique in 1972 and the Nixon visit, the Liaison Office (now the
                    embassy) in Beijing was set up—I was told by Washington, Ken Crane wrote to me—I
                    still have the letter—that, “You're our candidate for PAO China.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There must have been relatively few officers who knew
                        China and Chinese language.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: There were. It was great. I was hoping I was going to Beijing. But the
                    State Department didn't want USIA in Beijing, because they didn't want the
                    Chinese to have a reciprocal organization in the United States. They didn't want
                    anything but State in there in 1973, so that prevented the assignment of a USIS
                    officer. Also, it was quite obvious that of the few tools that the Liaison
                    Office had to work with in China, the most valuable was a USIS operation—the
                    exchanges. They wanted to handle them themselves, and I can't blame them. They
                    wanted to handle the exchanges because those allowed for contacts with the
                    Chinese.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's all they had.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: That's all they had.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So then you personally got involved in an exchange
                        proposition in the Washington assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ASSIGNED TO CULTURAL BUREAU - STATE DEPARTMENT: CHINESE EXCHANGES</p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes, I was asked to go to CU as the deputy for East Asia, but with
                    specific responsibilities for the exchanges with the People's Republic of China.
                    Dave Hitchcock was director of CU EA, and I was his deputy.</p>
                <p>The first thing I faced was a huge Chinese archeology exhibit that came to the
                    United States as part of the exchange program. It opened at the National Gallery
                    in Washington, then went on to Kansas City and San Francisco. We were working
                    with members of the Chinese Liaison Office in Washington, and I worked
                    particularly with their cultural attach�, Mr. Hsieh. I used to consider him the
                    barometer of U.S.-China relations, depending on the warmth or lack of warmth
                    with which he greeted me each time we met. This was a very difficult period in
                    U.S.-China relations, because it had gone beyond the Shanghai communique and the
                    opening of the Liaison Office. We didn't realize fully what was going on in
                    China at the time; we didn't realize the intensity of the internal strife of the
                    period of the “Gang of Four” in the last stages of the Cultural Revolution.</p>
                <p>So the Liaison Office in Washington was affected by internal events in China
                    tremendously. We had advised them that for an American audience it's best not to
                    fill your catalog for the archeological exhibit full of polemic material, and to
                    present things straightforwardly. Don't talk about slave and feudal societies.
                    But they wouldn't accept our advice. Then when it came to the press conference
                    to open the exhibit, the Chinese cultural attach� phoned me and said, “The
                    Israeli, the South Korean, the South African and the Taiwan press
                    representatives cannot attend or the exhibit won't open.”</p>
                <p>We informally discussed the problem with the press representative from Taiwan,
                    and they, fortunately and gracefully stepped aside, realizing there was a
                    problem, and they'd be better off if they didn't get themselves mixed up in it.
                    But we couldn't give in on the other ones. Everybody was invited. It went out on
                    the AP and UPI wires, there was a press conference, and all the press services
                    in Washington who had representatives were invited. So the others came. I've
                    forgotten, but there was some face-saving device employed, and the Chinese went
                    along with it, and the exhibit opened as scheduled. But it was that sort of
                    thing we constantly faced in that period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were learning how to be worldwide diplomats, too, I
                        suppose.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes, they were. I always called it the “getting to know you” period for
                    both sides. We hadn't worked with these people for 20 years, and it was a
                    completely different set of ground rules. We were trying to understand what they
                    had to deal with back in Peking, and they had to try to understand what we were
                    dealing with in Washington. I mean, if you tried to talk about press freedoms to
                    these people, in terms of these press conferences, it was difficult. On the
                    other hand, we didn't really understand the pressures they were under in terms
                    of the political turmoil in China. Anyhow, it was a very interesting period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were working in those years, as well, the
                        mid-Seventies we're talking about, in ICS, in English teaching and that kind
                        of thing. You had something to do with the Vientiane, as I recall.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>AEROFLOT TRIP - VIENTIANE TO RANGOON</p>
                <p>NICHOLS: That was still when I was in CU. During one of the trips I made
                    overseas, spring of '75, Saigon fell. I happened to be in Vientiane that day,
                    and I was leaving there for Rangoon on a Russian Aeroflot plane. It came in from
                    Hanoi, and so when I boarded this plane, I was completely surrounded by Russians
                    and North Vietnamese. I was obviously the only American on the plane. They were
                    all rather lighthearted. But for me that was the day Saigon had fallen and our
                    people had been taken off the embassy roof by a helicopter. Here I was on this
                    plane with all these Russians and North Vietnamese. Aeroflot planes are never
                    the nicest flights, even in the best of circumstances. I'm sure you know.
                    They're not very hospitable or very warm in their reception anyhow, and the food
                    is terrible. So after surrounded by these people, I was never so glad to get off
                    a plane in my life. And then I was the only person that got off the plane in
                    Rangoon. (Laughs)</p>
                <p>When I got into the airport, there weren't any Burmese officials around. There
                    was nobody there to stamp my passport. I had to hunt around for somebody in the
                    airport to accept me into the country. The PAO who was meeting me, was not
                    allowed inside the custom area; so until I got through that part, I never saw
                    anyone. It was a pretty lonesome experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was the last plane out of Vientiane you were talking
                        about. When you were in ICS, this was right after that, right, the CU
                        assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ESCORT OFFICER FOR CYRUS VANCE LEAD DELEGATION TRIP TO CHINA</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: Yes. I should mention one other thing about the CU assignment, probably,
                    which is important in terms of the China relationship. I was the escort officer
                    for one of the major delegations that went to China during that period called
                    the World Affairs Delegation. It was led by Cyrus Vance and included the heads
                    of many big foundations in the United States, the Rockefeller Foundation, headed
                    by Dr. John Knowles, the Carnegie Foundation, headed by Tom Hughes, Phil Talbot,
                    the former ambassador to India, who headed the Asia Society, Carter Burgess of
                    the Foreign Policy Association, etc. It was composed of that caliber of people,
                    and was headed by Cyrus Vance. This was in 1975, before he became Secretary of
                    State.</p>
                <p>This was one of the early delegations to China, and it included 18 people
                    altogether. We were received at the very highest level when we got to China.
                    These delegations, both the Chinese delegations that came to the United States
                    and the American delegations that went to China during this period of “getting
                    to know you,” as I call it, between 1973 and '78, were very, very important in
                    developing the relationship to a point where we could normalize it in '79. They
                    established many, many contacts that have been followed up on and continued
                    since then.This delegation had some important people on it and it met with the
                    most important Chinese. This was during the last stages of the Cultural
                    Revolution in China, and we felt it while we were there, although we weren't
                    always aware exactly why things were the way they were. We were in Beijing for a
                    week, with the hopes that we were going to meet the top leaders, but they never
                    let you know in advance. You had meetings with various officials, where a lot of
                    questions were asked by us, but not answered by the Chinese officials. All these
                    questions, it turned out, were accumulated and left to be answered by Deng
                    Xiaoping, who evidently decided that the people in the delegation were worth
                    meeting. So we got the message, first thing in the morning, ~”Everything else
                    canceled. You're going to the Great Hall of the People to meet with Deng
                    Xiaoping.” [Deng at that time was in his second “come-back.” Shortly after our
                    visit, he was sent back to the countryside for “reform through labor” for a
                    third time. We met with him in the Great Hall for an hour and 40 minutes.</p>
                <p>By the way, George Bush was the ambassador at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he meet with you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: He went with us. Oh, yes. That's another reason the State Department was
                    very anxious to have the exchanges under their thumb. These were the benefits.
                    George Bush didn't often get a chance to sit down with Deng Xiaoping. This was
                    the only way he could get to do it. Q: I didn't mean to ask, “Where was
                    George?”</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: George was very much there, and it was an hour and 40 minutes. Although
                    he sat over on one side with the rest of us. We were all in big overstuffed
                    chairs, being served tea and expensive Chinese cigarettes. Up in front, Deng
                    Xiaoping sat with Cy Vance on one side and the deputy leader of the delegation,
                    Art Rosen, on the other. Art, by the way, at one time worked for the U.S.
                    Information Agency as China desk officer. After his retirement from State, Art
                    became president of the National Committee on U.S.-China Relations, which was
                    the sponsoring U.S. agency for this particular exchange. All exchanges with
                    China were done through either one of two sponsoring agencies, the National
                    Committee on U.S.-China Relations or the Committee for Scholarly Communication
                    with the People's Republic of China which handled most of the scientific-type
                    exchanges.</p>
                <p>Anyhow, Deng Xiaoping sat there, and as he talked he would punctuate his remarks
                    by spitting into a spittoon, located at his toe between him and Cy Vance. Cy
                    just sort of jerked his head back and looked, stunned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he chewing tobacco?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: No, he was smoking. He is a chain smoker. I don't know whether he did it
                    for emphasis, or even intentionally, but it was certainly startling. This very
                    interesting exchange of ideas lasted for an hour and 40 minutes. Discussion
                    revolved around U.S.-China relations, and the questioning probed where the
                    Chinese were headed in terms of their policy. Little did we realize how
                    difficult this period was for Deng. He was exiled shortly thereafter, and soon
                    after that there was the death of Zhou En-lai and then Mao Zedong.</p>
                <p>Actually all the questions that the delegation had asked other officials during
                    that week were answered one by one by Deng Xiaoping.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's an interesting example of how private diplomacy, such
                        as with this group, Cy Vance and company, and public diplomacy together
                        turns out to be the mainstream of real diplomacy, of substantive
                        diplomacy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: It was not a formal relationship. It wasn't government to government; it
                    was people to people, Chinese people to American people. We had no relations
                    with the Chinese Government, technically speaking, with the Liaison Office. The
                    two countries had not normalized relations, so everything was a people-to-people
                    relationship, and that's how it was carried on at that time. Q: You had a little
                    bit of respite from Chinese concentration during your ICS assignment in
                    Washington in the mid-Seventies, and had a chance to travel to some other
                    areas.</p>
                <p>A NEW LOOK AT USIA WORK THROUGH ICS</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: That was fun. In fact, I'm delighted that I had it. It was just a little
                    over a year, and I was in charge of—I've forgotten what it was called in ICS,
                    but it was the office that was involved with Binational Centers, library
                    operations, information centers, and English teaching programs. It had
                    supervised the regional librarians' work. It directed certain aspects of the
                    Binational Center operations, and directed the English teaching operations. So
                    it included a bunch of agency programs that I strongly believed in.</p>
                <p>I'd never worked with a Binational Center in my life. The only one I'd ever been
                    exposed to was the one in Bangkok, and then only as a visitor. BNCs didn't
                    exist, by and large, in Asia. So I insisted, with Hal Sniedman and Cliff
                    Southard: “By God, if you want me to run this office, let me go out and see some
                    BNCs.” My first junket was to Latin America, your old stamping grounds. This was
                    fascinating because the area was completely new to me in terms of the way
                    programs were run, the approach and so forth. I met a new bunch of officers,
                    most of whom I had never seen before.</p>
                <p>Then later, I went to NEA. I went out to a PAO conference in Tunis, and from
                    there to Iran, not too much prior to all the trouble. That was in 1976. I got a
                    feeling for Iran, just being there for three or four days, after which I went on
                    to Pakistan for another PAO conference, then to Israel. The trip gave me a good
                    feel for some of the NEA posts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you a question having to do with diversity of
                        programming. What you've seen with your concentration of the Far East and
                        your exposure to other areas, how universal should the Agency's message and
                        the country's message be to peoples of the world? To what extent does it
                        have to be tailored to audiences?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TAILORED MESSAGES VS. UNIVERSAL THEMES</p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I'm a great believer in tailoring messages to audiences. I think there
                    certainly are things that should be universal, but the way you do it certainly
                    should be tailored to the audience. The tools you use can vary from post to post
                    in country to country, and the way the messages are presented needs to be
                    tailored to the culture in which you're working. This, my argument, became one
                    side of a major debate in the Agency. When I left, it was still going on. I'm
                    sure it still goes on today. There was a major effort for a while in the Agency,
                    I felt, to homogenize everything the Agency did, you know, package everything
                    for the world. I was much against this because I felt strongly that each place
                    you work in is so different that you've got to take your messages and present
                    them differently. You've got to allow the field to do that, to decide how
                    they're going to present the message.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>That's also why I felt it was vitally important that officers should know the
                    language and culture of the area in which they're working. Otherwise you
                    couldn't possibly understand how to present these messages and how to get these
                    ideas across.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's much more emphasis on language and communication
                        now than there was when you came into the Agency, obviously.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Oh, yes. At the time I left, there was. I think while I was at the
                    Agency we'd learned a lot of lessons. But I think we've unlearned a few from
                    what I have read and heard recently. But we learned a lot of lessons starting
                    way back from the time that I made that statement, “Nichols Vows To Make A
                    Democracy Grow Stronger.” I'd certainly learned a lot of lessons, and I think
                    the Agency as a whole had also; lessons about how to present ourselves to a
                    foreign audience. Back in the Philippine days, we displayed exhibits that showed
                    the American kitchen and all the modern appliances to people in the Philippines
                    who had no hope of getting such things, which was just stupid. But that's the
                    way we worked with information programs back a the beginning, because we didn't
                    really understand what cross-culture communication was all about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We have learned a lot, and yet the pendulum continues to
                        swing with various emphases from time to time. Your final assignment with
                        the Agency started in 1977, and that was the time with the Carter
                        Administration and the change in the nature of USIA and, indeed, the name.
                        You witnessed all that in Washington. How do you feel about it now?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SATISFACTIONS AND DISAPPOINTMENTSAT THE LEVEL OF REGIONAL MANAGEMENT</p>
                <p>NICHOLS: That assignment I had as deputy director for East Asia, working with
                    Mort Smith, was a good way to wind up my Agency career. There was a certain
                    amount of pride in getting to a level where you could make decisions about
                    things on an area-wide basis. You felt you had some impact on Agency planning.
                    There was also quite a bit of frustration in that period. I think my
                    expectations were too high. I feel a lot of people's were, when we had the
                    change of administration and then, for the first time in the history of the
                    Agency, had a career officer named as director, as well as at all the top-level
                    positions. I think we expected too much out of them. I know I met with a lot of
                    disappointment. John Reinhardt, a man for whom I have great respect and who I
                    have always liked personally, was responsible for getting me to various places
                    in my career.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sure. He'd been focusing on the Far East a good deal.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: But I was frustrated with John. I was frustrated, and John still remains
                    somewhat of an enigma to me. I remember at one staff meeting, John was fighting
                    the idea of PAO conferences. I said, “You know, John, I think you're against
                    these PAO conferences because you never were a PAO and therefore never saw their
                    value.” It wasn't the wisest thing to say, and John gave me a funny look, but he
                    never was a PAO, and I think that had something to do with his opposition. John
                    was a CAO. He went from CAO in Tehran or someplace like that, to deputy director
                    of East Asia. PAO conferences aren't a waste of time; they're very
                    important.</p>
                <p>Then Charlie Bray, John's deputy, wanted to massage all the words of everything
                    you wrote, but never take any action about things. Mort and I were both
                    frustrated by a lot of things that were going on. John didn't want the old-boy
                    network going on personnel, yet there were some very important things about
                    personnel that only the people in the area knew about, the chemistry at the
                    posts, and what sort of combinations work well together. We in the AEA offices
                    knew much more about the personnel. John would say to me when I protested a
                    couple of assignments, “But Bob,” he'd say, “you go through that guy's record,
                    and it doesn't show that.”</p>
                <p>I would answer, “Yeah, well, a lot of performance records don't show what's
                    really true.”</p>
                <p>Then he said, “Okay. If he screws up, I'll back you up and pull him out of
                    there.” He was going to wait 'til the guy screws up! We didn't agree on a lot of
                    these things, but it was an exciting time in many ways, because we were still
                    involved in the China thing. After “normalization,” and even before, we began to
                    establish our posts in China.</p>
                <p>Then there was this business you asked about a minute ago, about tailoring
                    programs and so forth. Alan Carter and I got into it on that score regularly,
                    because Alan was all for packaging everything on a worldwide basis. And he was
                    adamant when it came to this. We felt that he wanted to homogenize all the
                    Agency programs. Of course, we were fighting it in East Asia, so it probably was
                    a good time to retire. (Laughs)</p>
                <p>OPINIONS ON VALUES OF VARIOUS PARTS OF USIA PROGRAMS</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Another one of the major changes at that time was the
                        amalgamation of CU into ICA, and there's still talk about whether that was a
                        good idea on both sides of the fence. How do you feel about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>NICHOLS: I thought the old way was crazy. Just because Senator Fulbright didn't
                    want to taint the exchange program with propaganda, placing it under a
                    propaganda agency. It didn't make any difference. All it meant was you had a
                    domestic staff composed largely of USIA officers sitting over in the State
                    Department working with USIA officers abroad, where the CAOs in the embassies
                    were all USIA officers anyhow. So it didn't really make much sense from the
                    point of view of where the programs originated. Maybe to an American audience,
                    but not to our foreign constituencies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's still being advocated, however.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: So I understand. But I think cultural exchange properly belongs in the
                    U.S. Information Agency. I think if there's a problem on it, the problem comes
                    in terms of how much the U.S. Information Agency taints itself with being a
                    propaganda agency, that is propaganda in its worst form. I think sometimes we,
                    as a country, are much too sensitive about the connotation of that word, as
                    opposed to our friends abroad, who think of “propaganda” more as in its original
                    meaning of “information.” I mean, official information. So I think sometimes
                    we're quibbling when we talk about that. Heavily slanted information, I am
                    opposed to.</p>
                <p>You see this with every turn of every administration, depending on the political
                    bent of that administration. You watch every new administration go through the
                    same problems—what do they call the AMSPECs now? They've got a new name for
                    them—AMPARTS. They went through that whole business, the same thing that we went
                    through back in the early days of Vietnam, about tainted speakers, people that
                    were going out and being flak for U.S. policy, as opposed to people who were
                    objectively speaking on things. That whole business of the writers down at the
                    Voice of America, the ones that write the commentaries. The Voice is still going
                    through that problem and will probably never stop going through it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some things won't change.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: Some things won't change. But to me, I was a believer mostly in cultural
                    programs. I believe in libraries. I like to see libraries that are tailored to
                    the interests of the country. I believe in cultural exchanges, very strongly in
                    the cultural exchanges. I believe in programs like cultural presentations,
                    representing the best of America. I believe in the speakers program. Speakers
                    programs are marvelous. It just depends on who the speakers are, of course, but
                    that's controllable.</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>The fast media, maybe it's because I'm not a great fan of television, because I
                    have some doubts about what it's done to our own society. Newspapers, I feel
                    that press programs are important, but they don't have a lasting effect. The
                    programs that have a lasting effect are slow ones—the presentations, the
                    exchange of persons, the libraries, book translation programs, that sort of
                    thing, I think those are really important things for the Agency in the long run,
                    and those are the things that interested me most when I was in it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You retired in 1979, so it's been a few years since that,
                        and you've had a chance to think back and travel through some familiar
                        areas. A final question, perhaps. Looking back on a career of achievement
                        and satisfaction and rewards, would you do anything different?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NICHOLS: I'm sure I would. If I had gone into the Agency knowing what I knew when
                    I left the Agency, I would have done a lot of things differently. I never would
                    have made that statement in Davao! But certainly, a career in the Agency has to
                    be one of the most exciting, rewarding things you can do. I always encourage
                    young people to get interested in the Agency, because I think it's the most
                    exciting part of the foreign service of the United States. You have more
                    opportunities in Agency work, in being in the press and cultural section of an
                    embassy to work with the people in a country than you do in any other part of an
                    embassy, in a productive and positive way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A nice, pleasant note to end this on. Thank you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
