<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000165">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with James R. Bullington </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>JAMES R. BULLINGTON</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: July 31, 2001</p>
                <p>Copyright 2003 ADST</p>
                <p>Q: Today is July 31st, 2001. This is an interview with James R. Bullington. This
                    is being done on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training,
                    and I'm Charles Stuart Kennedy. Do you go by Jim?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Jim, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right, let's start at the beginning if you could tell
                        me wheand where you were born and something about your family.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I was born in Chattanooga, Tennessee, 1940. My daddy was a welder for
                    TVA, the Tennessee Valley Authority, building some of the TVA dams that were
                    going up in the Depression era. He followed construction work for most of his
                    life, mostly with TVA. We moved around a good bit while I was young, following
                    the construction of the various projects he was on. We lived in North Alabama
                    and Florida and California, but eventually moved back to Chattanooga when I was
                    in the sixth grade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You have what I would consider a Southern accent.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Well, I hope so. (laughter) It becomes even mormellifluous after
                    about three beers.</p>
                <p>Q: Tell me, what's your father's family background?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: One of my relatives did genealogical research, and wrote a book.
                    According to her the first Bullington came to Jamestown some time before 1624.
                    He wasn't with the first group, in 1607, but the first census she was able to
                    find listed this fellow, Nicholas Bullington, in Jamestown in 1624. The
                    Bullingtons migrated west from there, and eventually got to North Alabama, to
                    farms near Athens, where my daddy's from. It appears there weren't any publicly
                    distinguished folks in the family background. They were mostly farmers. Some
                    fought in the Revolution and the Civil War.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, your father, did he grow up on a farm?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes, he grew up on a farm, and in fact we lived on my granddaddy's
                    farm in Athens a couple of years when I was in the third and fourth grade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he get through high school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes, he got through high school...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was quite an achievement in those days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes, that was probably well above average in North Alabama. But as
                    far as I know I'm the first one in my immediate family to go to college.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about your mother? What were some of the
                        antecedents...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Her antecedents were also in Virginia. They traced the family back to
                    Governor West, in the Colonial era, for whom West Point in the peninsula area is
                    named. They migrated into the Smoky Mountains region and were pretty much North
                    Carolina, East Tennessee hillbillies. Mother's grandfather, Jerome Napoleon
                    West, came down from the hills to live in Chattanooga in the late 19th Century.
                    That's where my mother and father met, when daddy was working on Chickamauga
                    dam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ah yes. Did your mother go to a school or a high school
                        or...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: She went to high school for two or three years, but shdidn't
                    graduate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, really the first place I guess you remember quite
                        well iChattanooga.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes, I remember going to the first grade there, then we moved around
                    and were in California and on the farm in North Alabama for a few years. We
                    moved back to Chattanooga when I was in sixth grade, and I stayed there until I
                    left for college.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Chattanooga like in those days?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: H.L. Mencken described it when he came there to cover the Scopes
                    “monkey trial,” which was in the small nearby town of Dayton. There weren't any
                    hotels in Dayton, so all the journalists lived in Chattanooga. In one of his
                    pieces for the Baltimore Sun, Mencken called Chattanooga the “buckle on the
                    bible belt.” It was a grimy industrial town, very polluted, still very much
                    influenced by the War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The War.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My grandfather charged up Missionary Ridge, by the
                        way.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh, did he? With Arthur McArthur?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, he was with the 26th Wisconsin regiment, was a
                        captain, think. Came over with Hooker's Corp.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh, yes. Well, my folks first lived in North Chattanooga, north of
                    the Tennessee River, but later moved to very near Missionary Ridge. When I would
                    go back to visit I often walked along the crest of the ridge, where they have
                    all the markers, and relived some of the Battle of Missionary Ridge. Chattanooga
                    was a medium sized town. At that time there were only two big high schools in
                    the city of Chattanooga, but they were very big. My graduating class had six,
                    seven hundred students.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good heavens, that's big.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: That's because there were only two in the whole city.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Instead of a sort of elementary school, what
                        subjectparticularly interested you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I don't know that I had any favorite subjects that early. By the time
                    I got to junior high school and high school, I liked to read a lot, mostly
                    fiction: Charles Dickens, Ernest Hemingway, Dostoevsky, Tolstoy, Victor
                    Hugo.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Classics like that. In high school, did you play sports or
                        otheextracurricular activities?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, I wasn't very athletic to begin with, and then in 1952 I had
                    polio. This was the year before the Salk vaccine came out, and polio was really
                    a scourge at that time. A lot of people got it. I got it the summer between
                    junior high school and high school. It left my leg affected, though not really
                    badly. I could walk well, I even jogged a lot for many years, but it was bad
                    enough that I couldn't be competitive in athletics.</p>
                <p>Q: In high school, did you get involved in any drama, music, anything of that
                    nature?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not very much, to tell the truth. I was not an outstanding student. I
                    had good grades, but they came very easy. I never paid much attention to
                    studying because I didn't have to. I could make B's without studying, so I
                    didn't. Couldn't go all the way to make A's. I was a little bit active in
                    student politics, ran for office once but didn't win. Didn't really get too much
                    involved in that. One thing I did get involved in was ham radio. That was one of
                    the first things that got me interested in the Foreign Service, the first time I
                    knew there was such a thing as an embassy.</p>
                <p>Q: So you know, being in Chattanooga is sort of in a heartland city. The buckle
                    on the Bible belt. Did the outside world intrude much?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No. I don't think we even had a Chinese restaurant in the town at the
                    time. It was a very limited horizon. There weren't any foreigners there; there
                    weren't any international businesses. It was very insular.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With the ham radio, how did you hear of it, what got you
                        to knoabout it? Embassies and Foreign Service and all that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: One of the things you try to do in ham radio, or a lot of people do
                    anyway, is to talk to other hams in as many different countries as possible. At
                    that time, it was still exciting to be able to talk to the other side of the
                    world from your own “ham shack.” Some of the people that I talked to overseas
                    were associated with AID and embassies and the military. It did serve to broaden
                    the horizon of a small town hick like me in Chattanooga. It made me realize that
                    there was a big wide world out there that I didn't know very much about, and I
                    decided I wanted to learn more.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about your home? Was your mother and father, did you
                        havbrothers, by the way?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I only have one brother, who is eleven years younger. As kids we
                    weren't very close, because by the time he got old enough to talk to, I was off
                    to college.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>Q: I was just wondering, did you ever, I mean was it sort of the dinner table
                    place people got together and talked about what was happening?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not much. Dinner conversation was mostly about affairs of the family
                    and what was going on with the neighbors and things like that. Maybe about
                    church. There was no discussion of international politics or intellectual
                    matters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Does your family, were they democratic, republican, or
                        noparticularly...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Southern Democrats, for the most part, but they weren't politically
                    engaged in any major way. That was the era of the “solid South,” and the only
                    meaningful election was the Democratic Party primary. Daddy was a union member,
                    but not politically active.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then, you were ready to graduate at about 1958, was
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I graduated from high school in 1957. I graduated when I was 16
                    because I started school a year early and then skipped a grade in elementary
                    school. So I was quite young when I went off to college.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, when you were in high school, how did the family
                        feel abouyou going to college?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh, they were all for it. They certainly were for education and going
                    to college, and they wanted me to do something other than manual labor like my
                    father had done. Q: Where did you go? What were you pointed toward?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I was pointed towards engineering. The first satellite, Sputnik, was
                    launched in 1957, and everybody was excited about engineering at that time. I
                    was pretty good in math and science and some of my high school teachers
                    encouraged me to go in that direction. Actually, one of the interesting things
                    about that era was the quality of the public schools, especially the high school
                    I attended in Chattanooga. It was good, it was really good. There were private
                    schools there that were perhaps better, but in Chattanooga City High School we
                    even had calculus. The English courses were rigorous and the teachers knew their
                    stuff. They were mostly older women, since at that time teaching was considered
                    mainly a woman's profession. I got an excellent high school education. That
                    became evident when I went to Auburn and was academically ahead of most of my
                    freshman class.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why Auburn?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I didn't have money to go to college and the family didn't have money
                    to pay for it. There was what was called a “co-op program” in many engineering
                    schools in the South, where you would work for a semester and go to school for a
                    semester. A company and the school would usually arrange for a partner who would
                    be on the opposite schedule, to work when you were in school, and you would work
                    when he was in school. Auburn used a quarter system, rather than semesters, so
                    you worked a quarter and went to school a quarter. I managed to get a job with a
                    Chattanooga company called Tennessee Products and Chemical Corporation. They
                    made industrial chemicals. So I went to college to become a chemical engineer,
                    starting in the fall of 1957 and coming backto work for a quarter and then going
                    back to school in the spring.</p>
                <p>Q: Tell me a little bit about Auburn. What was sort of the background, how was
                    student life during the '50s?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh it was a lot of fun. One reason I went to Auburn was because it
                    was cheap, even though I had to pay out-of-state tuition; so with the income
                    from my co-op job, I even had a little left over to party with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is it private?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not at all. It's the Land Grant University of the state of Alabama.
                    The tuition was seventy-five dollars a quarter, for out-of-state students, and
                    even less for those from Alabama. The cost of living in Auburn was very low.
                    Also, Auburn had more flexibility in their co-op program than some of the other
                    schools I checked out, and they seemed to be more interested in having me come
                    there. I was a semifinalist on the National Merit Scholarship exam, and they
                    went out of their way to be nice and recruit me. So that's why I ended up in
                    Auburn. I joined a fraternity there, Sigma Pi, and had a great time. Lots of fun
                    football weekends, and of course Auburn's a huge football school. We won the
                    national championship my freshman year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would have thought that being so in and out, you know,
                        did yoend up with an 8- year program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, it would have been a six-year program had I stayed a co-op
                    student. But after three years of the co-op program I had pretty well decided
                    that I didn't want to be an engineer. This was mainly because of the experience
                    working in the chemical plant, seeing what engineers did. I didn't find that to
                    be particularly interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do they do? What does a...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: In this case mainly supervise the production of chemicals. It just
                    didn't hold much fascination. At the same time I got interested in journalism,
                    because beginning in my freshman year I went to work for the Plainsman, which is
                    the student newspaper at Auburn. I was first a sports reporter, and eventually
                    worked my way up through the hierarchy and became editor of the paper my senior
                    year. So my interest in journalism plus the fact that I did exceptionally well
                    in my English courses and liked to write led me to change from engineering to an
                    English major after my sophomore year. After that, I managed to go to school for
                    the full academic year, by holding a part-time job at the Auburn publicity
                    office and working at the Chattanooga Times during the summer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you graduate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I graduated in '62. Started in '57 and graduated in '62.</p>
                <p>Q: While you were doing that did sort of the outside world intrude much or, you
                    know I mean we were having the Cuban missile crisis and, well that was after you
                    graduated.</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: We also had the Bay of Pigs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bay of Pigs. Well, you know the cold war was running hot.
                        Dithat...?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I developed some interest in international affairs in high school and
                    regularly read either Time or Newsweek or both, so, yes, I was more and more
                    interested in what was going on in the external world. This interest increased
                    as I became involved in journalism. I was able to quit co-oping because I got a
                    part-time job working for the school news bureau, the publicity office of the
                    university. From doing that I got picked up as a stringer for the Montgomery
                    Advertiser and the Columbus Georgia Ledger Inquirer and wrote some stories for
                    them about what was going on at Auburn. This experience helped me get a summer
                    job as a reporter and copy editor for the Chattanooga Times. All of this
                    together really opened up the external world a lot. Moreover, becoming editor of
                    the Plainsman was truly a seminal experience, and wonderful training for the
                    Foreign Service, first of all because of the writing, but also because of a
                    particular challenge there that was very character building, I think. This was
                    the era of desegregation in the South. In 1961 when I became editor, we were
                    having the “freedom rides” coming through Alabama. People would get on the
                    interstate buses and come down south to try to integrate the Greyhound bus
                    stations. Up until that time I had never really thought much about the whole
                    issue of segregation. I just took it for granted, as the way things were and had
                    always been. Now that I had become editor of the school paper I felt some
                    responsibility to think about it and comment on it, especially because of what
                    happened to the freedom riders when they came to Alabama. People in Birmingham
                    pulled them off the buses and the cops, rather than protect them, egged on the
                    crowd. The same thing happened in Montgomery. This was major news all around the
                    country. I felt like I should say something about it. So I wrote a front-page
                    editorial, after I'd been editor maybe three weeks. The editorial said that what
                    Alabama was doing to the freedom riders was wrong, that the people of Alabama
                    were wrong, and not only that, the whole premise on which they were acting, the
                    system of segregation, was wrong, and Auburn ought to be forthwith desegregated.
                    I gave 'em hell; I really gave 'em hell. This was met with great shock
                    throughout the community. It was the first time that any major state university
                    newspaper editor in the Deep South had publicly advocated desegregation. The Ku
                    Klux Klan burned a cross on the front lawn of my fraternity house, where I was
                    living; the president of the university called me in and gave me all sorts of
                    unshirted hell; the student body gave me hell; most of the faculty gave me hell
                    (although I had a few friends on the faculty); I was called a damn Yankee
                    agitator who ought to go back up north to Chattanooga where I came from.
                    (laughter) They called me a Bolshevik, among other nasty names. That was a
                    pretty heady experience for a twenty-one year old kid. And it got into the state
                    legislature, where they had a “committee on un- Alabama activities,” believe it
                    or not, which threatened to cut off Auburn's appropriations unless the school
                    administration did something about that editor of the school paper who was
                    writing all this inflammatory trash. The Governor also got upset. This was John
                    Patterson, to whom George Wallace lost in his first campaign, because as George
                    Wallace famously said, “He outniggered me.” George said 'I'll never let that
                    happen again.' And he didn't. So Governor Patterson also got on my case with
                    some negative comments. The Associated Press sent out a story about all this
                    nationwide, and the story was in the New York Times and the Washington Post. The
                    American Association of University Professors also got involved. They sent a
                    message to the university saying 'You better not do anything to this noble young
                    editor of the school paper there.' So I kind of dared the administration to
                    throw me out of school, and I'm sure they wanted to, but they didn't.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did your fraternity react to this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Most disagreed strongly with my position, but they tolerated me. Very
                    few agreed with what I was saying, but many supported my right to say it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you had enough contact with African Americans?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No. None whatsoever. It was a totally segregated society that I grew
                    up in. There were certainly none at Auburn, none in the high schools in
                    Chattanooga or anywhere else in the South. Like most white southerners at the
                    time, I had no social contact with African Americans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: John...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Nearly twenty years later, in 1979, the State Department had sent me
                    to the Army War College for training. At the end of each year of training the
                    Army invites a group of distinguished citizens to come to Carlisle Barracks to
                    show off the class and lobby for more appropriations for the Army. The year I
                    graduated, among this group of distinguished citizens was John Patterson, former
                    governor of Alabama, then a lawyer practicing in Montgomery. They had a
                    reception, a sort of mixer for the students and VIPs. I had seen his name on the
                    guest list, so I walked up to him and said “Governor, I'm sure you don't
                    remember me, but when you were Governor of Alabama, I was editor of the
                    Plainsman over there at Auburn.” He immediately drew back and pointed his finger
                    at my chest and said, “So YOU'RE the son of a bitch that wrote that editorial!”
                    (laughter) I was proud to say, “Yes, I was the son of a bitch that wrote that
                    editorial.” I was so pleased that it had bothered him all those years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You know, sometimes you do something like that and it
                        begins ttake over your life.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh, indeed yes, absolutely. From that time on I was notorious on the
                    campus as the “integrationist editor” of the paper. The university
                    administration was watching me and calling me in for warnings and the students
                    were harassing me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were any of the outfits, you know freedom riders who,
                        SoutherBaptist kind of folks.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The Southern Christian Leadership Council, Martin LutheKing's
                    organization.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Southern Christian leadership. Were they making contact
                        with yoor were you sort of off to one side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: They really didn't make contact. I was doing my thing pretty much
                    independently. Later on after I graduated I got in contact with them to some
                    extent. My first tour was in the Department in Washington beginning in 1963, the
                    year of the March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom. I participated in that. An
                    Auburn buddy and I carried a sign saying 'Alabamans for civil rights.' People
                    looked at us with some skepticism. But I was there in the crowd when Martin
                    Luther King made his 'I have a dream' speech at the Lincoln Memorial.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you graduated; did you have any problem on the
                        academiside from your professors?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No. At least some of the professors were of a liberal persuasion, and
                    thought what I did was pretty good. Much less than half, but some of them. I
                    didn't have any academic problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the ladies, the co-eds of the University of
                        Auburn?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: They were mostly Southern Belles. To the extent thehad any
                    intellectual aspirations, they were mostly against me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As an English major, what did you perceive yourself
                        pointetowards?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I wasn't too sure when I first became an English major. I remember
                    one of my teachers who said I should be an English professor. He thought to
                    encourage me in this direction by giving me some assignments to do in PMLA,
                    Proceedings of the Modern Language Association. I found that so deadly dull I
                    decided I didn't want anything to do with a profession that highly valued the
                    production of such drivel. About halfway through my junior year I began to aim
                    specifically toward the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you find out anything much about it when you were in
                        Auburn?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I wrote to the State Department and got the exam booklet, and I
                    subscribed to the Foreign Service Journal. But there wasn't anyone at Auburn who
                    really knew much about the Foreign Service. However there was one person who was
                    a big help to me. We had a student-run activity called the Auburn Conference on
                    International Affairs, which I had been involved with before I became Plainsman
                    editor. Through that we had Ambassador Clare Timberlake come to Auburn. He had
                    been in the Congo. At this time he was the State Department representative at
                    Maxwell Field in Montgomery, the Air War College. My senior year, when I had
                    signed up to take the Foreign Service exam, he invited me to come and see him in
                    Montgomery. He was very encouraging and in fact wrote a letter of recommendation
                    that was useful when I got to the oral. He was the first and only Foreign
                    Service Officer I'd ever laid eyes on at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you take the exam while you were still in the
                        college?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I took the exam in my senior year. Came up to Washington, first time
                    I'd ever been on an airplane. Went to Atlanta on the train, got on an airplane
                    and flew to Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that the written exam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, that was the oral. I took the written exam iMontgomery.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the oral exam go? Do you recall any of the
                        questions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The one I recall most vividly, was if I thought we should open an
                    Embassy in Ulaanbaatar. On the way to Washington on that Delta flight from
                    Atlanta, I'd picked up National Geographic and read an article by Mr. Justice
                    Douglas on Mongolia. Had that not been the case, I wouldn't have had the
                    foggiest notion where Ulaanbaatar was, much less whether we ought to have an
                    Embassy there. Because I had read the article I was able to answer the question
                    with some reasonableness.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was at that time sort of one of those issues that was
                        floatinaround.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It was in the Sino-Soviet context.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you get at all involved, in the cold war and the communists versus the
                    west, did they intrude at all in what you were up to, I mean your studies and
                    conversations.</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It was just a given part of the background. It waalways there.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't imagine there was a young Communists league in
                        Auburn.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh no. (laughter) No, nothing like that. Auburn is about as
                    conservative a place as you can get, not to say reactionary. It's the land grant
                    university of the state of Alabama. It trains mostly farmers and engineers and
                    veterinarians, that sort of school, although they did have a pretty good English
                    department. The great rival is the University of Alabama, where the doctors and
                    lawyers and most liberal arts students are trained. It's a cultural clash within
                    the state of Alabama, and that annual football game is really something. You've
                    gotta be either Auburn or you're Alabama, never the twain shall meet. Families
                    are split over the issue. Few things are more important than football in
                    Alabama.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about, you graduated what year now?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I graduated in December of '62. I had passed the oral that spring. I
                    had one more quarter, the fall quarter, to complete my degree. I came into the
                    Foreign Service in December of '62, right after Christmas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you come in with a class?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes, it was a fairly small class, I think sixteen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were its members like, as a basic officer corps.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: That was still the era when there was some validity to the notion of
                    the Foreign Service as an Ivy League, East Coast establishment. I don't remember
                    the exact figure but I think two-thirds of my colleagues were Harvard, Yale, or
                    Princeton. The Service was already talking about the need for greater diversity,
                    so I think I was the token hillbilly in that class.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you play that to the hilt?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: To some extent. I was also the youngest in the class. was just
                    22.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any idea at the time whither you wanted to go
                        anwhat you wanted to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No strong idea, no. I didn't have any real geographic preference. I
                    liked the political cone because I had always been interested in history.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what did they do after you, what was your first
                        assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: First, they sent me to FSI to study French, because at that time you
                    had to get a three-three exam score in at least one language before you could be
                    promoted. So I had sixteen weeks of French and I was able to get the
                    three-three. Then they assigned me to NEA, the Bureau of Near Eastern and South
                    Asian Affairs. I was the Assistant Desk Officer for CENTO, the Central Treaty
                    Organization, in the Bureau. That was my first tour of duty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did that what through '60...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: That would have been '63 to '65.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: CENTO, trying to think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The Baghdad Pact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was just going to say, the Baghdad Pact went down the
                        tubes i'58.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It changed. Iraq pulled out, and what was left became the Central
                    Treaty Organization with Turkey, Iran and Pakistan, plus the U.S. and UK.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of things were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: As with most international organizations there were committees and
                    lots of meetings and preparations for those meetings. We wrote position papers
                    and briefing books for the senior level participants. Parts of the work were
                    fascinating. I got to go to the Ministerial Council meeting in Tehran with Dean
                    Rusk. To ride on the Secretary's airplane, meet Dean Rusk and be part of the
                    delegation, that was a real thrill for a young officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Doing this, did you get much of a feel for how CENTO
                        played iour international concerns? Was this pretty peripheral by this
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It was increasingly marginal, yes. It was part of the John Foster
                    Dulles construct that some called pact-o-mania. With CENTO and SEATO, the object
                    was to contain Communism in the Middle East and Asia the way NATO contained it
                    in Europe. But of course those countries were of a different order militarily
                    and otherwise as compared to NATO countries. I don't think it ever worked too
                    well, and by the early '60s it was pretty marginalized.</p>
                <p>Q: Where did the Middle Eastern Bureau, I would assume at that time, as always,
                    meant it's whole effort was much more concentrated on Arab-Israeli matters and
                    all that, did you sort of feel a bit like stepchildren?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: A little bit. The CENTO desk was part of the Office of Regional
                    Affairs, and yes, we had nothing like the attention that Arab-Israeli issues
                    drew. Or even some of the other issues of the day. Turkey and Pakistan
                    individually had a lot of things going on that were interesting, but CENTO did
                    not play in that too much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about Iran at that time, was it, it hadn't started the
                        greaarms buildup yet, had they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I think you can say it had started, but it wasn't that far along. The
                    Shah's government seemed to be pretty stable and, most people felt, was fairly
                    progressive. There was nothing we worried about much with Iran in terms of its
                    stability. Of those three countries, we were most worried about Pakistan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the Soviets felt to be a real menace at that time in
                        thaarea?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: They were to an extent in the Northern Iran - Eastern Turkey area.
                    They were thought to have some aspirations there, and also to be trying to
                    destabilize those governments and promote a communist takeover. Their success on
                    the ground, however, was hard to discern. There wasn't any active pro-communist
                    movement that I'm aware of in Iran or Turkey or Pakistan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then, you did this for?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Two years.</p>
                <p>Q: Two years. By this time, had you, or had you before been married or?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No. I was single.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Footloose and fancy free.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Absolutely. I had a girlfriend or two here iWashington, but they
                    didn't want to marry me. (laughter)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then you went in '65 where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: In '65, I was assigned to Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this by mutual agreement?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It came out of the blue, actually. One day I got the call that 'Hey,
                    you're going to go to FSI and study Vietnamese for awhile and go to Vietnam.'
                    They assigned me to Hue as Vice Consul. I'd never followed Vietnam affairs. I'd
                    heard of it, but that's about all. The war at that time was not really a big
                    deal like it later became. We had military advisors there, but we didn't have
                    any American combat units. Vietnam was still seen as pretty remote, and our
                    involvement was only at the margins, or so it seemed. But it was obviously a
                    growing concern, and growing very quickly. The State Department was rapidly
                    building up the Embassy and what was called the Provincial Reporting Unit, which
                    I was to be a part of even though I was stationed in Hue. It was a unit within
                    the Political Section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said you're going to be in Hue, but acting as the
                        ProvinciaReporting Officer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: That's right. That's what I was to do. Travel around in the five
                    provinces of I Corps, the five northernmost provinces of South Vietnam. I was to
                    send in reports to the Embassy on the political situation, economic situation,
                    pacification in the countryside, those sorts of things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, first let's talk a bit about the training. You
                        tooVietnamese at the Vietnam training center?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes. Not the full course, I think eight or ten weeks, so I could get
                    by but I wasn't really fluent in Vietnamese. It got a little better after I'd
                    been there for awhile, but I did have French, so I could use French with most
                    Vietnamese I needed to talk to. All educated Vietnamese at that time spoke
                    French.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Around you was Vietnam, before you went out has it
                        becomcontroversial, our commitment there...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, it wasn't really all that controversial at that time, in early
                    1965. I'm sure there were some people in academia and elsewhere that were
                    criticizing the involvement already, but it wasn't something you saw in the
                    papers. There were no demonstrations or anything like that. It was not that big
                    a deal in 1965.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you went out in late '65?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I went out in July '65.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: July of '65, and right to, did they sort of brief you in
                        Saigofirst?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes, I spent two weeks, maybe three, in Saigon, went around with some
                    of the people in the Provincial Reporting Unit there. People like Bill Marsh,
                    John Negroponte, Dick Holbrooke, Dick Teare, David Lambert, Vlad Lehovich.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By the way, who was taking Vietnamese with you? Were you
                        takinVietnamese with other Foreign Service Officers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: There were just three of us in the class. Lyn Baldygwas one, a USIA
                    officer. I don't remember the other.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, when you got to Vietnam in '65, how did the
                        situation othe ground seem? What was the image you were getting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It was deteriorating. That seemed to be pretty well established. The
                    Provincial Reporting Unit was the part of the Mission that would bring the bad
                    news, more than any other. The official MACV military chain of command was not
                    giving as realistic reports as the State Department provincial reporters. Or the
                    journalists. That was when the journalists were beginning to change from
                    supportive to more and more questioning and sometimes downright hostile.</p>
                <p>Q: Were you given any kind of firm, the Embassy Reporting Unit, were you given
                    any equivalent of marching orders, go out and find this or find that?</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, no it was not to prove any point, or to look for anything in
                    particular other than the normal things you would look for: how is the
                    government doing, what do the people think, is there corruption, is the
                    government winning or losing, are the hamlets safe or not safe?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you moved to Hue, what did we have in Hue at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: We had a small Consulate there. Sam Thomsen was the Consul and I was
                    Vice Consul. There were the two of us, plus the communicator, Joe O'Neal, who
                    later went on to become a Foreign Service Officer, along with three or four
                    Foreign Service National support people. And that was it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was, Hue was what, was it Marine or Army?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It was in the Marine AOR, Area of Responsibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find relations with the Marines at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The first Marine combat units got there not long before I did, in
                    March of 1965. At first they were only in Da Nang, protecting the airbase. We
                    had the MACV advisors, and they were mostly Army. Those were the people I
                    interacted with much more than Marines during that period. I was traveling,
                    visiting the provinces (or sectors as they were called in military terms) and
                    districts (sub-sectors in military terminology). The Americans I dealt with were
                    mostly career Army people. I also visited some of the Army Special Forces teams,
                    including one in Khe Sahn. There were lots of places in the mountains where we
                    had Special Forces A-teams, they were called. I'd spend two, three, four nights
                    usually, staying with the military folks in those districts or provinces or in
                    villages with the A-teams. I'd use those as a base of operations and talk to the
                    Vietnamese government people and military, and to anybody else who seemed to
                    have information about what was going on. I'd gather information and try to
                    develop a feel for the situation, and then come back to Hue and write a report
                    on “The Situation in Quang Tri Province,” or something like that. It was very
                    akin to journalism.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you have the feeling that the military reporting and the CORDS reporting
                    was very much, you know, body count, pacified / non-pacified villages, it got
                    very quantified in all that. Was the feeling that this is really not giving a
                    very good picture?</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: This was before CORDS, which came later. Hamlet evaluation surveys,
                    which sought to quantify everything regarding pacification, were begun later,
                    '66 and '67. In '65, the only other reporting was in the military channel from
                    the MACV sectors and sub-sectors. Yes, that did tend to be less than full. It
                    relied on body counts and other numbers too much, largely overlooked the
                    political and economic context, and really didn't give a good picture of what
                    was going on, or so most of us in the Embassy felt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, there was a lot of pressure on the military people,
                        to shoimprovement.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh, yes, their performance was measured in how many new hamlets their
                    team had pacified. Of course they were just advisors, and it seemed to me
                    awfully unfair to hold them responsible for the performance of the South
                    Vietnamese military forces and government. It also led to overly optimistic
                    reports.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the impression you were getting of the South
                        Vietnamesforces?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Mixed. In some areas, they were darn good. And in some areas they
                    were awful. In northern I Corps, Quang Tri and Hue, was the ARVN First Division.
                    That was reputed to be and was, in my opinion, a fine military outfit. It
                    remained so through the rest of the war. The leadership was good, and so were
                    the soldiers. In southern I Corps it was much different. The Second ARVN
                    Division and some of the other forces down there were not nearly as good. The
                    Rangers and other specialized units were quite good, but they were part of the
                    central reserve and would only be deployed from time to time. When they did come
                    they were quite effective. The militia, the Regional Forces and Popular Forces,
                    would vary even within a province, according to the leadership of the district
                    chief and other officials there. In some districts they were good and in others
                    they were not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well what was going on, sort of one of the, North
                        Vietnamese wait or was it mainly Vietcong in that area when you were
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: In I Corps, by then at least half the problem was regular NVA units.
                    Also, they had reinforced Vietcong units with a lot of NVA troops. By that time
                    we had regular NVA regiments in both northern and southern I Corps.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it must have been pretty dangerous, prancing around
                        froplace to place.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Well, hell when you're 24, 25 years old you're invulnerable. You
                    don't worry about that sort of thing. It was foolhardy, but I never felt a great
                    sense of fear as I was traveling around. I did get shot at a couple of times,
                    but as with most young people, personal safety wasn't at the top of my concerns.
                    Should have been.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about, did you have problems with your reports, did
                        you geany feedback on what was going, what you were reporting?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Some, but after I'd been there a few months, domestic politics began
                    to take over from the provincial reporting. This was the time of Thich Tri
                    Quang, whose headquarters was in Hue. He and his An Quang Buddhist movement
                    began to make all kinds of problems for the central government, as did one of
                    the leading military figures, Lt. Gen. Nguyen Chanh Thi, who had been I Corps
                    commander and before that, ARVN First Division commander. The political
                    situation was really spiraling out of control, with a lot of student
                    demonstrations and Buddhist demonstrations. After November, December of '65,
                    that became the consuming issue we were focused on, reporting on the political
                    unrest in I Corps. Hue was correctly seen as the center of it, although it was
                    going on in Saigon and other places as well. Hue was particularly important for
                    the political stability of the country, so I began reporting more and more on
                    those sorts of things, talking to the Buddhist leadership, the dissident
                    military leadership, folks like that. Those reports were very much noticed. I
                    was front and center among Embassy reporters, as a matter of fact, because of
                    being in Hue. I remember one occasion in early '66 when there had been lots of
                    protests and student demonstrations, and the central government had replaced the
                    commander of I Corps in an effort to get better control of the political
                    situation. The new commander was coming up to visit his division in Hue for the
                    first time, but the division was essentially in rebellion and didn't want to
                    receive him. I'd gone out to the division headquarters compound for the arrival
                    ceremony. All the MACV advisors were there as well. At the same time the
                    students were demonstrating, and they decided to march out to the First Division
                    to protest against this new I Corps commander. Moreover, some of the First
                    Division soldiers had entered a conspiracy to assassinate him. And indeed, after
                    he made his speech and as he got into his helicopter to take off, some of the
                    First Division soldiers started shooting at the helicopter, to try to kill him.
                    It was an American helicopter, with an American crew and the commander's MACV
                    advisor accompanying him. In self defense the door gunners on the helicopter
                    started shooting back and killed some of the people on the ground that were
                    shooting at them. But Thich Tri Quang and the students got it wrong. They
                    claimed the Americans had come in and wantonly attacked their compatriots and
                    killed their brethren. I started driving back to town just as the students got
                    there, and they poured over my car, banging on the roof and shouting
                    anti-American slogans. I thought they were going to take me out and kill me, but
                    they didn't. After they passed by I went on to an appointment with Thich Tri
                    Quang, the leader of the Buddhists. He was well known, had even been on the
                    cover of Time magazine just a couple of weeks earlier. The previous week he had
                    sent a message through me to President Johnson, and I was to deliver that day
                    the President's response. So I went to his headquarters at Tu Dam Pagoda and
                    delivered the message. One of the Consulate FSNs, Tuy-Cam, who is now my wife,
                    was with me to interpret, since Tri Quang spoke no French. Just as I was
                    finishing that task, a firefight broke out between the Vietnamese troops around
                    the pagoda and the Catholics in the neighboring area. We couldn't get back to
                    the Consulate for awhile. But when we did, I wrote all this up, the
                    assassination attempt on the Corps commander, the demonstrations, delivering the
                    President's message to Tri Quang, the Buddhist-Catholic firefight in the middle
                    of Hue. This was a hell of a report, a good day's work for a young FSO-8. Sam
                    Thomsen, the Consul, had gone to Da Nang on temporary duty, and I was Acting
                    Consul at the time. That report went all the way to the White House, and Dean
                    Rusk was kind enough to send a special commendation, which was surely helpful
                    when the next promotion panel met. Those anti-government demonstrations
                    continued and became increasingly anti-American. There were daily demonstrations
                    outside the Consulate. And finally in March student demonstrators burned down
                    the Consulate and the USIA library.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Tony Lake was there at the time, was he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, I replaced Tony Lake. Tony had been there before, in my job.
                    Shortly before the Consulate was burned, the Embassy sent up Tom Corcoran. He
                    was Deputy Chief of the Political Section in Saigon. Since I was one lonely
                    FSO-8 up there in Hue, and all these things were going on, they sent Tom to fill
                    in as Consul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Tom was the last man out of Hanoi too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: He closed down Hanoi and Hue and... Vientiane as well, think?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think Vientiane, at least for a little while.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: He was quite a guy. We did a lot of reporting on that crisis, and had
                    to evacuate American citizens from Hue. Both Tom and I were given Superior Honor
                    Awards for our performance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your reading at that time of the Buddhist
                        leadership?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Thich Tri Quang?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thich Tri Quang and all. Where were they coming from? How
                        diyou see them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: A lot of people felt they were basically tools of the communists. I
                    think probably they were, but unwittingly so. They served some communist
                    objectives, and the communists certainly got behind them and were pushing that
                    kind of anti-government and anti-American position. But the Buddhist leadership
                    was not communist. That was pretty well demonstrated after the war. Thich Tri
                    Quang was eventually imprisoned, but I don't know what happened to him
                    thereafter. He certainly didn't emerge as a leader of the new society when the
                    communists took over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the head of Provincial Reporting in Saigon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Bill Marsh was head of the Provincial Reporting Unit.His boss was
                    Phil Habib, the Political Counselor.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>Q: Did you feel that the Embassy was sort of with you, often if you were in the
                    Consulate that they don't understand us or they're getting it wrong, did you
                    feel for that?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: They got it pretty well right. They kept sending up people for TDY,
                    during the course of this Buddhist “struggle movement.” John Negroponte was one.
                    He was in the Provincial Reporting Unit. He came and stayed for two or three
                    weeks. Colonel Sam Wilson, who was the military advisor to the Ambassador, came
                    and stayed for two or three weeks. They not only were getting my reporting, they
                    were sending people up to be on the ground from time to time, where I could talk
                    to them and brief them, and they could see the situation for themselves. So I
                    think they had a pretty good handle on what was going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your feeling, by the time you left there
                        when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I left right after the Consulate was burned down iMarch.</p>
                <p>Q: '68?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, this was March of '66. After that, the Embassy (primarily Phil
                    Habib) brought me down to be staff aide to Henry Cabot Lodge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk a bit about your impression of Henry Cabot
                        Lodge.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I liked him. It was a really heady experience for me to be a young
                    FSO right at the very heart of the most important American international
                    engagement at the time. Obviously I didn't have any decision power, but I was
                    certainly sitting at the right hand of power, filtering all the information
                    coming and going to the Ambassador. It was an exciting time. I liked Lodge,
                    thought he was competent, thought he was a decent man. I got along with him
                    quite well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he get out much?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Some. In fact I usually went with him. I carried his briefcase on
                    several trips. He both got out some himself, and he would listen to the other
                    people in the Embassy that got out, especially the young officers in the
                    Provincial Reporting Unit. I remember one time he went on home leave for a
                    month. I didn't have anything to do during that month, so I asked if I could go
                    spend some time in the provinces. He agreed that I could go to Long An province
                    down in the Mekong Delta where they were having a special experiment at the time
                    involving Colonel Sam Wilson, who had been with me in Hue for awhile. They put
                    him in charge of both the American combat units in the province and the MACV
                    military advisors and civilians involved in pacification. This was something
                    that had not been done before. So I thought it'd be interesting to go down and
                    do some reporting on how that was going. I wrote a long report to Lodge when he
                    got back. He sent it on to the President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were things going that sort of southern tip of South
                        Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It was going pretty well, by this time. In '65 the security situation
                    was clearly deteriorating. In '66, once we got through the political turbulence,
                    it had become stabilized. I'm not sure that we were making much progress, but
                    the overall situation there and in most of the country was no longer
                    deteriorating and had been stabilized.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to develop sort of good relations with
                        youVietnamese counterparts or was this a problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh, yes, good relations. Obviously it depends on the individuals, but
                    for the most part we were able to develop quite close relations with them. In
                    fact I married a Vietnamese..</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you meet your wife?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: She was a Foreign Service National employee working at the Consulate
                    in Hue. As I mentioned before, she was my interpreter when I met with Thich Tri
                    Quang. We had developed an interest in each other when I was there. After I went
                    to the Embassy as Lodge's aide, she was transferred to AID in Saigon, and the
                    courtship became more serious. I'd been engaged to a woman in Washington before
                    I left for Vietnam, and the idea was when I finished my tour in Vietnam we were
                    going to get married. But when I finished that first tour and came back I found
                    that she had decided she didn't like the Vietnam War or anything to do with it
                    including me. Then my courtship with Tuy-Cam really got serious. We were married
                    right before I left Vietnam in '68.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, a lot of relationships have broken up over the
                        Vietnam war.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No doubt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you aware of the building intensity of the
                        anti-Vietnamovement in the United States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I was aware of it in the sense that I was reading Stars and Stripes
                    and occasionally Time and Newsweek, but I guess I was not really personally,
                    dramatically aware of it until I came back, after I had completed my time with
                    Lodge. That was when my lady friend in Washington told me she didn't want
                    anything to do with me or the War. Moreover, I saw all the snow and ice around
                    Washington (it was in January), and I quickly decided I wanted to go back to
                    Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '68.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, January '67. It was then that I first got a feel for what was
                    going on in the U.S., and how much anti-war sentiment there was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you came back, you came back in '67 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I was there until March of '68. This was my third job in Vietnam.
                    First Hue, and then staff aide to Lodge, and the third tour I came back to work
                    in what by then was the CORDS program in Quang Tri province, the northernmost
                    province of South Vietnam. I could have gone other places. I had an interview
                    with John Paul Vann in III Corps, and he wanted me to work for him. But I went
                    back to I Corps, mainly because by this time Tuy-Cam was there. She was in Da
                    Nang, where the US Consulate had been moved after it was burned in Hue. I wanted
                    to be in that region so we could continue the courtship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, before we leave, your time with Henry Cabot Lodge...
                        Whawere his work habits?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: He was a methodical sort of guy. He would listen, especially to Phil
                    Habib, who I think was by far the most influential person in the Embassy. He had
                    regular relations with Westy, General Westmoreland. I didn't see them either as
                    particularly close or particularly negative in any way. It was a businesslike
                    relationship. Westy would come over once or twice a week and that was about it.
                    The CIA Chief of Station was also influential, as was Barry Zorthian, the JUSPAO
                    chief.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: U.S. Public Affairs Office.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Joint U.S. Public Affairs Office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you deal at all with the press or have any social
                        contacwith the press at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes, even in Hue. With my background in journalism I was interested
                    in the press, and there were a lot of journalists who came through when I was in
                    Hue. Joe Alsop, Frankie Fitzgerald, Johnny Apple, Neil Sheehan, Don Oberdorfer,
                    several others. There was Keyes Beach, Chicago Daily News. A reporter I got to
                    know well when I was in Saigon was George MacArthur, with Associated Press and
                    the Los Angeles Times, mainly because George was dating Eva Kim. Eva was Cabot
                    Lodge's secretary and I was the staff aide, so we were in the same social circle
                    there. In fact I had dinner with George and Eva last night.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I tried to interview Eva, but she didn't want to.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: She would be a wealth of information.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I know, she was the institution.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: She's a dear friend. Q: Well then, you were up in Quang Tri...</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The northernmost province, right up on the DMZ.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in '67, you know, prior to
                        Tet?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: We had the big war up there. There were large combat units, mostly
                    Marines at that time. All along route 9, which runs south of the DMZ from the
                    coast to the main road junction in Laos, called Tchepone, there were heavy
                    battles. Camp Carroll, the Rockpile, Cam Lo, scenes of big, big battles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: At that time with CORDS there was a senior province representative in
                    each province, and under the province rep were two deputies, at least this is
                    the way it was in Quang Tri, one for the military side, and one for the civilian
                    side of the pacification effort. I was the deputy for the civilian side. That
                    was the position. But the first job really was totally focused on an operation
                    to remove about 10,000 people from the southern half of the DMZ. The DMZ was a
                    river and a strip of a couple kilometers on each side of the river. McNamara had
                    come up with this scheme (which did not work at all) to have electronic barriers
                    along the DMZ to prevent infiltration from the north. We called it derisively
                    the McNamara Line. We had to remove these people from the southern half of the
                    DMZ preparatory to building this McNamara Line. My job was to take care of the
                    refugees and help resettle them south of there in a place called Cam Lo. The
                    first day I got to Quang Tri they started coming, about 10,000 refugees to
                    organize feeding and care for. The Marines assigned a colonel to work with me. I
                    also had an ARVN colonel for a counterpart. And we got 'em resettled.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, you can resettle people but we're talking about people who are working
                    and fishing and farming and all that, you move them and you give them shelter
                    and all, but were they able to sort of gainfully support themselves?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, they were basically on the dole. And we had to feed them with
                    bulgur wheat and other things that they didn't much want to eat. Some of them
                    were able to do a little bit of farming eventually. Largely they were on the
                    dole or they were employed as militia, in the Popular Forces. These people were
                    mostly Catholics, and there was a very active priest who got them organized.</p>
                <p>Q: So, was there a major invasion down there, or was this... What were the
                    northern Vietnamese doing, just testing or were they really trying to get
                    across.</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Some were coming across the DMZ, right through the McNamara Line. But
                    they were mostly going around it, going around through Laos down the Ho Chi Minh
                    trail and then coming back into areas of northern and southern I Corps and
                    attacking all along a north-south front.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At one point, it was later I guess after you left, at
                        Khe-Sahn?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh, no, I was there. In Quang Tri. Khe Sahn is in Quang Tri province.
                    I visited it a couple times. During the Tet offensive is when it became so
                    notable. I had quite an adventure during the Tet Offensive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about the Tet Offensive.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I was working in Quang Tri, but I had decided to go down to visit
                    Hue, to see Tuy-Cam. We were engaged by this time. She was working in the
                    Consulate General in Da Nang and had come up to her home in Hue, and I was to
                    come down from Quang Tri, to be with her for her last Tet in Vietnam before we
                    were to be married in March and go off to the U.S. So it was a big deal for her
                    and the family. I had done some favors for a French guy, he was
                    Franco-Vietnamese actually, whose company ran the power plants in Hue and Quang
                    Tri. I had put him on some Air America flights when the roads were blocked. So
                    he had invited me when I visited Hue to stay in a little guesthouse they had at
                    the power plant there. I flew down on the afternoon Air America flight from
                    Quang Tri, arriving in Hue on the afternoon of January 30th, 1968. This proved
                    to be a poor choice of time to visit Hue. I went by the CORDS headquarters, and
                    was able to borrow one of their USAID jeeps to get around town. We'd had some
                    intelligence in Quang Tri that there might be attacks during that period, but it
                    didn't seem to be anything unusual. There were always attacks of one sort or
                    another. When I got to Hue I asked at CORDS headquarters if anything special was
                    going on, and they said no, though there were some low-level rumors that there
                    might be problems during the Tet holidays. But nobody seemed to be especially
                    concerned. We had dinner that night at Tuy-Cam's house. We had two other
                    Americans there. One was Steve Miller, who was the USIA representative in Thua
                    Thin province, where Hue is located. He had been a Foreign Service classmate of
                    mine. The other was Steve Haukness, who was a friend of Tuy-Cam's at the
                    Consulate in Da Nang. He was a Foreign Service communicator. He had never
                    visited Hue so he wanted to come up to the old imperial capital for some
                    tourism. After a nice Vietnamese dinner at Tuy-Cam's house, the two Steves went
                    to Steve Miller's house, and I went back to the power plant, to the guest room,
                    to spend the night. About two a.m., I was awakened by the sounds of incoming
                    mortars. It was evident that there was some serious fighting going on. Of course
                    there wasn't much I could do about it. I expected that it would be over by dawn.
                    There had never been a North Vietnamese or VC attack in a major city where they
                    had come and stayed. It was always a hit and run thing. They would get out of
                    town by dawn because by occupying fixed positions in an urban area they became
                    vulnerable to counterattacks. By dawn things had quieted down, so I figured
                    that's what had happened, they had come in and raided the town and blew up a
                    bridge or something like that and were gone. I walked out of the door of the
                    guest room and across the courtyard into the power plant looking for my French
                    friend. He was in the power plant, but when I got there he said, “Oh, my god,
                    don't you see what's happened? There they are!” And he pointed to the other end
                    of the courtyard where for the first time I saw armed men with pith helmets.
                    They obviously weren't friendlies. My friend said “Get back, get back,” and I
                    did. I went back to the guest room and spent several very anxious hours there.
                    Eventually that afternoon my friend came by and knocked on the door. It was with
                    some terror that I opened that door, not knowing what I would find, but
                    thankfully it was my friend instead of the NVA. He told me a little more about
                    what was going on. The power plant obviously was a main target of any invading
                    army that's going to occupy a city. The NVA had set up a command post right
                    there in the power plant, not more than 25, 30 yards from the guest room where I
                    was staying. My friend said that it's not a good idea to stay at the power
                    plant, and I certainly agreed with that. So we worked out a signal. That evening
                    he was to stand across the courtyard and give me a thumbs-up when it was clear
                    to move across. The first time we tried he gave me a 'don't come' signal because
                    the NVA were evidently looking. But the next time, about sundown, they were all
                    busily cooking dinner around a campfire, and he signaled me to 'come on.' I
                    walked across the courtyard with my heart in my throat. If the NVA soldiers
                    noticed me they didn't do anything. They probably assumed I was a Frenchman
                    working at the power plant. I passed within 25, 30 yards of them. When I got to
                    the other side of the courtyard my friend guided me over some fences, through
                    some backyards to a house where two French priests welcomed me. One, Father
                    Cressonier, had been in Hue for 30 years with the Soci�t� des Missions
                    Etrang�res, the missionary society headquartered in Paris that was active in
                    Vietnam. The other, Father Poncet, had been at Khe Sahn. Because of the fighting
                    at Khe Sahn he had to leave a few weeks before that and was staying with Father
                    Cressonier in Hue. Cressonier was a big guy like me, and he gave me one of his
                    soutanes, the black gown, and the beads and the whole priestly outfit; so for
                    the next nine days I became a French priest behind the North Vietnamese lines in
                    Hue. For an East Tennessee hillbilly raised in the Church of Christ, that it
                    itself was quite a thrill. A couple of times the local VC cadre came to the
                    door, but they didn't demand to come in. If they did, the story was going to be
                    that I was a visiting French-Canadian priest. I don't know whether that would
                    have worked or not, but thankfully we didn't have to put it to the test. The
                    greatest danger turned out to be the counterattack, especially incoming
                    artillery from friendly forces. The fighting was pretty intense around there,
                    and we saw a lot of refugees and a lot of North Vietnamese units, including one
                    tank, which they had evidently captured from the ARVN. There was a lot of
                    incoming mortar and artillery fire. Father Cressonier's house was a two-story
                    French Colonial type. When the artillery starting coming in heavily we would all
                    go downstairs, and huddle under the staircase. And thankfully so, because we
                    took a direct hit from what was probably a 105 mm artillery shell. The house
                    became one-story all of a sudden. The second story just was no longer there. But
                    we were downstairs and didn't get hurt. After nine days of this, the U.S.
                    Marines, working their way house to house in fierce combat throughout Hue, got
                    to where I was, the priest's house, and liberated me. The company commander was
                    Ron Christmas. He later went on to become a Marine Lieutenant General. I was
                    never so glad to see anyone as Captain Christmas and his Marines. They wrapped
                    me in a blanket and carried me out as if I were a wounded Marine, so the
                    neighbors would not see that these priests had been harboring an American. I had
                    invited, in fact urged, the two priests to come with me to safety, but they had
                    pastoral duties they felt kept them there. There were Catholic refugees they
                    could now get to at a nearby cathedral, several thousand people. They wanted to
                    stay and minister to the flock. The Marines took me to MACV headquarters. I
                    spent one night there, and was interviewed by reporters. The next day the story
                    of my liberation was on the front page of the Washington Post. In fact that's
                    how my parents found out about it, through a newspaper report. They'd been told
                    by the State Department that I was missing. They eventually saw the newspaper
                    report from the Washington Post via the Chattanooga paper. After another day at
                    MACV, I went to Da Nang to take a bath, which I hadn't had in nearly two weeks,
                    and get some food as well as to report in to the CORDS regional headquarters
                    there. After the staff at CORDS debriefed me, I told them I had to go back to
                    look for Tuy-Cam. Even though the house where she lived was no more than 500
                    yards away from Father Cressonier's house, there was no way I could get there
                    because it was on the other side of the Phu Cam canal, which was one of the many
                    lines along which the fighting took place. I knew the Marines would eventually
                    get there, so I wanted to go back to Hue. My CORDS bosses told me no, you can't
                    go. I told them the hell with that, I'm going. By that time I'd been around long
                    enough and knew the territory well enough to arrange my own travel, so I just
                    went out to Da Nang airbase where I knew the appropriate sergeant. I got on a
                    helicopter back to Hue, to look for Tuy-Cam. When I landed at the helicopter
                    pad, she was there! She and her family had just made it to safety that morning,
                    and she had come to the helicopter pad to look for me, and was trying to go to
                    Da Nang. So that's where I found her. We were reunited on Valentine's Day at the
                    helicopter pad outside the MACV compound in Hue. Her family was at a nearby
                    refugee camp. She had two brothers who were military officers, one was an ARVN
                    officer and the other was an Air Force cadet. They were both home on leave for
                    Tet. They had successfully hidden in the attic of the house for the first few
                    days. But eventually because of all the incoming ordnance they decided it
                    wouldn't be safe where they were. The family all left the house and was on the
                    way out of town with other refugees when a group of VC or NVA stopped them and
                    took out all the young males in the group. Tuy-Cam's two brothers were taken out
                    and apparently shot. They were never heard from again.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened, let's see, Haukness was killed there,
                        wasn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: And Miller. After I got back and found Tuy-Cam, I began looking for
                    them too. A couple of days later the Marines found Steve Miller's body with his
                    hands tied behind him. He had evidently been executed, shot in the back of the
                    head. Haukness was last seen being led off toward the west, out into the jungle.
                    We never did find his body at the time. I don't know whether his remains have
                    ever been found since then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened to you... she was your fianc� still?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: We got married. It was near the end of my tour, in March. We got
                    married at the Consulate General in Da Nang. Before Tet, we had planned a
                    traditional Vietnamese style wedding in Hue, but now we couldn't do that. We
                    organized the wedding right at the Consulate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was consul general?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Chuck Cross.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He's now in Seattle.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Is he? Chuck had been in Da Nang only a few months. Barney Koren was
                    before him, Chuck replaced Barney. Chuck was away on vacation, and at his
                    invitation we spent our wedding night in the Consul General's residence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you went back to the states?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not immediately. After about a week, we went down to Saigon, but had
                    all kinds of trouble getting Tuy-Cam's passport. They kept asking for official
                    papers that were in Hue. We pointed out that we couldn't go back to Hue, and
                    since Hue was largely destroyed, particularly the government buildings, we
                    couldn't get those papers even if we went there. Eventually I had to get Vice
                    President Nguyen Cao Ky to intervene. I was able to do this because I knew Ky's
                    aide from the time I had been Lodge's aide.</p>
                <p>Q: So, you then at that point went back to the States?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Went back to the States, and spent three or four months working in
                    the Department on the Vietnam desk and getting ready to go to Harvard. The State
                    Department decided that I needed more education, and they sent me off to the
                    Kennedy School of Government. A real battlefield, as it turned out.</p>
                <p>Q: Okay. This is probably a good place to stop. I'll put at the end where we are
                    so when we pick this up, probably, maybe in a year or so, that you're now
                    running the Peace Corps in Niamey?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I'm Peace Corps director in Niamey now.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is July 10, 2002. Jim, you're back from Niger on
                        homleave. You were at the Kennedy school from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: From September '68 through the academic year, May oJune of '69.</p>
                <p>Q: This is right in the middle of all the protests about Vietnam and all this.
                    How did, what was your observation as a student at the Kennedy school about how
                    this was playing out there?</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: After they began asking me how many babies I'd killed while I was in
                    Vietnam, I tended not to like the student protestors very much. It seemed to me
                    they were mouthing slogans rather than espousing policies. Eventually I grew a
                    beard and got a bicycle and blended into the background and avoided them. But it
                    was discomforting, coming from Vietnam, to see that sort of blind hostility. I
                    think I wouldn't have minded so much a reasoned debate. But that's not what it
                    was, even in this bastion of learning, Harvard University. These students were
                    burning books of professors with whom they didn't agree, like Sam Huntington and
                    Henry Kissinger. I thought that was abominable. But I enjoyed Harvard
                    nonetheless. I had some interesting courses, including Henry Kissinger's seminar
                    on national security policy. I'd met him while I was in Vietnam. He had come on
                    some study missions and stayed at my house once in Hue. So I took his course,
                    and really enjoyed it. I learned a lot and enjoyed Harvard except for the
                    student protests.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the faculty, was the faculty slamming
                        thgovernment all the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Parts of it were and parts of it weren't. Certainly Henry Kissinger
                    and Sam Huntington and the likes of those were not. That fall there was a pretty
                    violent protest movement where the students occupied the administration building
                    and were rifling through the personnel files of the faculty, and publishing in
                    their underground journal nasty things that they had dug out of the files. The
                    University eventually called the police to remove them. They resisted violently
                    and spat on the police and then of course claimed police brutality when the
                    police hit them back. The police finally got them out of there. I was dismayed
                    by the pusillanimous reaction of the administration and the faculty to these
                    kinds of provocations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now Harvard did not come out of this very well.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I didn't think so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some Universities showed that they had the ability to
                        havreasoned debate and not allow the crazies to take over, but
                        Harvard...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: They abdicated. There was some reasoned debate occasionally, but it
                    was drowned out by the slogans and the violence and the nastiness.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then, you got out in '69. Whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: My first assignment was to INR, but I wasn't there very long. By this
                    time Kissinger, my former professor, had become National Security Advisor. He
                    created a project called the Vietnam Special Studies Group to investigate the
                    results of the Tet Offensive and the counteroffensive that had been launched by
                    the U.S. and South Vietnamese forces thereafter, and to see where we stood on
                    pacification of the countryside, the guerrilla war, the insurgency war. This was
                    an inter-agency study, involving the NSC staff, the State Department, CIA, DIA
                    and the Joint Staff of the JCS. There were five of us on it, and I was the State
                    Department representative. We were working out of the NSC. So even though I was
                    nominally assigned to INR, what I did for thenext year was work in the NSC on
                    this project. That involved a couple of trips back to Vietnam and writing up a
                    long report and going around to the various agencies to brief them on our
                    findings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '69 to '70.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Right.</p>
                <p>Q: How did you find the outlook of, you know the State representative, CIA,
                    Defense and others? Were you coming at it from different angles?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not too much. Perhaps our agencies were, but not the members of our
                    group. We had been given a charter to determine what was going on, and although
                    coming from different backgrounds I don't think we had any preconceived notions
                    because we genuinely didn't know. We all had Vietnam experience. We did
                    research, including going back to Vietnam, each to two or three provinces, and
                    then putting our findings together along with the information that was coming in
                    from CIA and Defense and from the Embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I went to where I had spent most of my time, I Corps. I was traveling
                    around in Quang Tri, Hue and Da Nang primarily. We all went to different areas
                    and then put our information together in the final study. We really didn't know
                    what to expect. And frankly I was very surprised by the positive developments I
                    found. I had left right in the wake of the Tet Offensive in '68, when things
                    looked pretty bad. By the time I got back there on this study in '70 things had
                    really turned around in terms of the counter-insurgency effort. Places that were
                    very much under enemy control before were now secure. Roads that you couldn't
                    travel at all before were now open and being used for normal commerce. We
                    determined that something approaching ninety percent of the populated areas of
                    Vietnam were by that time under good government control. They still had not
                    gotten control of some of the far outlying areas, and they certainly didn't
                    control the largely unpopulated jungles where major North Vietnamese Army
                    elements were still operating. We, the Americans, were withdrawing our forces at
                    that point, and the South Vietnamese forces did not have the offensive punch to
                    go out and deal with these large units. However, they did have the defensive
                    capability, along with militia forces, to pretty well defend the populated areas
                    of South Vietnam. It turned out that the enemy, particularly the VC part of it,
                    the guerilla part of it, had lost tremendously in the Tet Offensive. Tet had
                    been a military victory for the Americans and South Vietnamese. We didn't
                    realize at the time the full extent of the damage we had inflicted. In late '68,
                    '69 and '70, when we began pushing back into the countryside, there wasn't much
                    resistance there. The South Vietnamese with our help were able to re-establish
                    control over the countryside. Our study found, and reported to Kissinger and the
                    other principals in Washington, that by that time, in mid to late '70, the
                    counter-insurgency part of the war had essentially been won. There was still
                    some mopping up to be done, still some problems, but we had basically won that
                    part of the war. What we still had to deal with were the large, regular North
                    Vietnamese units, the more conventional part of the war. But that was just the
                    time when the American combat elements that were best equipped to do this were
                    being withdrawn. The idea was that we would beef up the South Vietnamese army
                    further and give them the ability to deal with this threat, but we never did
                    that, unfortunately.</p>
                <p>Q: Was it within the NSC? Were you sort of involved with the NSC or were you not
                    in it but sort of sending papers to it or something like that?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Somewhere in between. We had an office in the NSC, in the Old
                    Executive Office Building next to the White House, and that's where we spent
                    most of our time, but I also spent some time at my desk in INR. I really
                    regarded the NSC people that I reported to as my bosses. I was more or less
                    seconded from INR, but still my home base was INR and that's who wrote my EER
                    and where I got my personnel support.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, actually there was a pretty solid cadre of
                        VietnaVeterans, Foreign Service veterans in the NSC at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, they weren't there yet. At that time there weren'any of my
                    generation on the NSC staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there an attitude about Vietnam of the NSC, a 'let's
                        just gethe hell out of there and move on.'?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, not at that time. This was the beginning of the Nixon
                    Administration. Henry Kissinger had come in with it in 1969. Particularly that
                    first year or so, they knew that we had to do something differently, but there
                    was no defeatism that I found. This was really when they put meat on the idea of
                    Vietnamization. I think our group's positive report of what happened in the
                    countryside in 1969 and the first part of 1970 gave some encouragement to that,
                    to the notion that 'well, hey, maybe this Vietnamization thing can really be
                    done,' that we can turn over the war mostly to the South Vietnamese. In fact by
                    that time or soon thereafter we more or less had turned over the anti-guerrilla,
                    counter-insurgency part of it to the Vietnamese. But we never successfully
                    turned over the rest of it, the big unit conventional war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When that was done did you go back to INR?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No. I then went to Thai language training. I was ready to start in a
                    new direction, and I didn't like the boss I had in INR, so I lobbied to get out
                    of there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were you put in INR?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I was in the Southeast Asia part of it, basically the Vietnam desk. I
                    didn't like the guy that ran that office. After the NSC job I managed to get
                    myself assigned to Thai language training, studied for ten months at FSI and
                    went off to Chiang Mai.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find Thai language and the training?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh it was an excellent program. I learned Thai pretty well, with a 3+
                    on my exam. There were just two of us in the class, so it was very intensive.
                    Hal Colebaugh was my classmate. The teachers were great. When I got to Thailand
                    I still had a lot of language learning to do, but I was basically able to
                    communicate at the professional level and read a newspaper. That's not easy in
                    Thai because it's a tonal language and doesn't use Roman script. I felt the
                    language training was very good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Chiang-Mai, when you went there, you were in Chiang-Mai
                        from wheto when?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: That would have been 1971 to '73.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Chiang-Mai like when you got there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Beautiful place. It had the reputation then of being the nicest city
                    in Thailand. It was certainly a lot nicer than Bangkok, which even then had
                    grown to be a metropolis with all the typical big city problems of traffic and
                    pollution and crime. Chiang Mai was more the 'real Asia', more what one's
                    romantic notions of Asia were, but at the same time it had modernized to the
                    point where there were a couple of first class tourist hotels and a few good
                    restaurants, a fairly good infrastructure in terms of roads and public
                    utilities. It was a really pleasant place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the staff of the consulate like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: We had three officers. I was the number two to thConsul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Jim Montgomery was Principal Officer. I was the political-economic
                    officer, and the third officer did the consular and admin work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Jim Henderson. Mahlon Henderson, he went by Jim. It was fairly quiet,
                    but we got very much involved in narcotics work. Chiang Mai at that time, and
                    still today for that matter, was at the heart of what was termed the 'golden
                    triangle' of opium production in northern Thailand, Laos and Burma, where the
                    opium was grown and transformed into heroin, and then trafficked down through
                    Bangkok to markets in the United States and Europe. That was the biggest U.S.
                    interest there at that time and what we spent most of our time on. There was
                    also the remnant of an insurgency in northern Thailand that was still of some
                    interest. We were just at the tail end of our AID program, so we were still
                    doing some economic assistance; we still had one AID officer there. But I would
                    say 70-80 percent of our time was focused on narcotics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, as the political economic officer, what were you
                        doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Reporting, traveling around the provinces, meeting the local
                    officials, learning about the situation. Talking to the opposition parties, if I
                    could find them. Going out to the areas where the poppies were growing. Working
                    with some of the NGOs and international organizations to see what they were
                    doing in terms of crop substitution, trying to get rid of the opium production
                    and replace it with beans or corn. They were trying to get the farmers to grow
                    beans, and they found out eventually that the beans simply provided a great
                    fertilizer for the poppies and made them grow better. Farmers began to
                    inter-crop them, one row of poppies and one row of beans, and it just did
                    wonderful things for the poppies. None of these efforts worked. I became, after
                    those two years of working on narcotics, a little bit... a lot disillusioned
                    with the whole idea of trying to deal with our domestic narcotics problem in
                    places like northern Thailand. I know it didn't work there and I'm dubious that
                    it works anywhere. There's just too much corruption involved. The poor peasant
                    growing those poppies gets almost nothing for the opium, but by the time it gets
                    to the streets of Washington or New York in the form of heroin it's worth tens
                    of thousands of dollars. The profit margin is just too great. Suppressing
                    production didn't work, and I'm dubious that it ever will.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you sort of find payoffs at almost every level?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh, there was enormous corruption, yes. The labs that transformed
                    opium to heroin were just across the Thai border into Burma where we couldn't
                    get at them from Thailand. But I'm sure had we been able to get at them from the
                    Burmese side they would have gone to Laos or somewhere else. Interestingly the
                    biggest traffickers were elements of the old Kuomintang army that had fled China
                    in 1949. For a number of years they still had some connections with Taiwan. But
                    by this time, the early '70s, any political content had disappeared and they
                    were just criminals, even though they had originated as a division of the
                    Kuomintang army that had come down out of China.</p>
                <p>Q: Were there efforts on the part of central government to get non-corrupt
                    governors and local people in or was it pervasive up and down the whole..?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The government made some efforts and for a time they would have
                    limited success. In particular they established a new outfit called the Border
                    Patrol Police, BPP, and we had advisors with them. Both the Agency and DEA had
                    agents in Chiang Mai, working with the BPP. But this did not succeed for long,
                    as even the BPP became corrupt. If you got the traffickers at one level they
                    would go to another level, if you got them in one area they would simply move to
                    another. In my judgment our war on narcotics has been unsuccessful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were the drug lords themselves living, I mean the
                        ones whwere making at least the primary, the first cut of the big
                        profits?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Most of them were living in that border area, over in Burma. But many
                    of them reportedly had mansions and girlfriends and families in Chiang Mai and
                    would periodically come there for the high life. They managed always to avoid
                    being arrested.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you, was there any political life going on
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not a lot. The Thai government is very centralized, and the regional
                    governors are creatures of the central government. There was some interesting
                    economic development activity going on, already the beginnings of substantial
                    foreign investment, and lots of new dams and roads. You could see it was a
                    fairly rapidly developing country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about, well this would be about the textile period,
                        wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes, there were textile plants there that were coming up. My wife
                    bought a lot of beautiful cloth. The Thai silk of Chiang Mai is famous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you travel around fairly easily, or were places
                        todangerous to go to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: You could go almost anywhere. There were a couple of places way up
                    into the border regions where it got a little difficult, but the government
                    didn't put any obstacles in the way. If we judged it to be a reasonably secure
                    place we could go there. I traveled a lot, including close to the Burmese
                    border.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Vietnam war play any role where you were at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Very little. We didn't have any U.S. bases in northern Thailand. They
                    were over in the northeast, pretty far away from Chiang Mai, so we didn't have
                    any GI's visiting or any real impact from the war in our consular district.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did, would you give tourists, I mean American kids getting
                        itrouble, that sort of thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes, there were a lot of those, the hippies. Chiang Mai was a stop on
                    the narcotics road. They would typically go to Nepal and then to Chiang Mai and
                    Vientiane and places like that where narcotics were available. Some of them got
                    in trouble, and we had occasional consular problems of that sort, but not an
                    awful lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have much problem getting them out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No. The government was friendly and cooperative, anworked with us
                    very nicely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go to Bangkok much?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not when I could avoid it. I preferred being in ChianMai. It was a
                    much more pleasant place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the Ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Goodness, you put me on the spot now. That shows you how much I went
                    to Bangkok (laughter). I remember Ed Masters was the DCM. He came up to visit,
                    but I don't think the Ambassador ever came to Chiang Mai while I was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: '71 to '73.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It would have been Len Unger.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Len Unger, that's it, Len Unger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, after this rather pleasant interlude...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Back to the Vietnam business. This was 1973, with the Paris
                    Agreement. They needed lots of people with Vietnam experience to work both in
                    Vietnam and on Vietnamese affairs in Washington. I ended up in the latter
                    category, on the Vietnam desk in the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sort of like the tar baby, you couldn't get away from
                        it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes. After learning Thai and two years in Chiang-Mai, the idea was
                    that I would move to the Embassy for the next two years. But that didn't happen
                    because they decided they needed people with Vietnam experience and I was
                    tapped.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now you were there from '73 to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Through the fall of Vietnam, '73 to '75. It was called the Vietnam
                    Working Group, basically the Vietnam desk in the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was in charge of the group?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Bob Wenzel was the director. Ammon Bartley was the deputy director.
                    There were seven, eight officers and three secretaries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I was the internal political officer, looking at internal political
                    affairs in South Vietnam. Elections, political parties, those sorts of things.
                    We had an economics guy, an external political guy, a political-military
                    officer, a few others.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was happening internally?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The main focus was on the evolution of the situation under the peace
                    agreement. There was supposed to be a cease-fire, but neither side observed it
                    very well, and each was trying to consolidate its hold wherever there was gray
                    area, disputed area. We dealt a lot with Congress, the public and the anti-war
                    movement. I spent a lot of time writing responses to Congressional committees. I
                    wrote speeches for Ellsworth Bunker. We were also focused on the continuing
                    negotiations in Paris, and supported the delegation over there. A lot of our
                    analyses were about whether the South Vietnamese were going to be able to
                    continue to resist in the situation that was brought about by the Paris
                    Agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you went in there and started looking at that, what was
                        youimpression of the strength or lack thereof of the South Vietnamese?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I had no strong opinions on it one way or another at first. I'd been
                    off in Chiang Mai for a couple of years, and in Thai language training before
                    that. I'd read the newspapers, but I'd really lost touch with what was going on
                    in Vietnam. So I really hadn't focused on Vietnam for three years, and things
                    had changed dramatically. I came to believe after a few months that the South
                    Vietnamese could have held on and eventually a Korea type solution might have
                    emerged; but as time went on and U.S. support declined they were getting weaker
                    rather than stronger, and the enemy was getting stronger rather than weaker.
                    Pretty soon the balance tilted, and it was clear that the North Vietnamese were
                    not willing to settle for less than the whole of Vietnam. It also became
                    apparent, particularly for someone in Washington working on Vietnamese affairs,
                    twenty hours a day it seemed like, that the United States was no longer
                    politically willing or able to sustain South Vietnam. That's eventually what
                    happened. We assured their defeat by cutting our military and economic support
                    to insufficient levels. I made a couple of trips back to look at the situation
                    on the ground, one in December of '73, the other and more important one in
                    December of '74, and again I spent a lot of time in northern South Vietnam where
                    I had worked, but also in some other places including Saigon and the Mekong
                    Delta. Putting together what I had learned in Washington with what I saw was
                    going on in Vietnam, it became evident to me that the end was nigh. The Embassy
                    would not admit that. Graham Martin was the Ambassador then, and was in my view
                    out of touch with reality, both in the United States and in Vietnam. There was
                    no indication that the Embassy realized the gravity of the situation and how
                    near we were already to the total loss of South Vietnam, or the political
                    impossibility of a U.S. rescue. I still can't understand why they didn't see it,
                    why everybody didn't see it. It was clear if you looked at just the logistics
                    picture. I got the figures from the Pentagon, of how much ammunition and spare
                    parts and POL and everything necessary to fight a war, how much of it we were
                    sending into South Vietnam, and how much they were using up, and it didn't
                    balance. Even at the level of warfare that was going on in December of '74, the
                    South Vietnamese were using it up at such a rate that you could see the end.
                    Probably before late '75, or certainly by early '76, they would run out of
                    bullets, quite literally. And if - as I saw to be almost a certainty - the North
                    Vietnamese launched a major offensive as soon as they perceived this growing
                    South Vietnamese weakness, then the end would come a lot quicker than that. The
                    evidence of this was everywhere when I visited Vietnam in December '74. The
                    artillery tubes that were limited to one or two rounds a night because they
                    didn't have enough ammunition, the soldiers that went out on patrol with only
                    one hand grenade because there weren't enough to issue them more. VNAF, the
                    Vietnamese Air Force, was essentially grounded for lack of spare parts and POL.
                    I put that together with the economic troubles and declining morale. And no
                    army, no army fights to the last bullet, literally. The South Vietnamese
                    officers that I talked to clearly saw what was happening. They said 'You, our
                    allies, are not giving us the support we must have to handle the situation that
                    we are facing. And if the North Vietnamese attack, we won't be able to contain
                    them.' So what happens in such a situation is that morale collapses before they
                    literally get down to the last bullet. That's what did happen shortly
                    thereafter, in the spring of 1975, when the NVA launched a major offensive and
                    the South Vietnamese army basically collapsed. I wrote a paper when I got back
                    from that trip, this would have been the final days of December or the first few
                    days of January in '75, and gave it to Phil Habib, who was Assistant Secretary
                    for East Asia. Although I didn't know it at the time, he gave it to Kissinger,
                    and Kissinger read it and apparently thought it meritorious, because in his
                    memoirs published four or five years ago, the volume of his memoirs on his
                    service under the Ford Administration, he quoted my memo at some length. I was
                    proud of that. I was the only career FSO, I think, to have a paper quoted in
                    that volume of his memoirs. He said something to the effect that at least a few
                    people recognized what was coming and warned that South Vietnam was about to
                    fall, and one of them was Jim Bullington. Then he quoted the memo. I was pleased
                    that somebody heard my warning; but it didn't make any difference in the
                    end.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you working on this when Vietnam collapsed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you all doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The main thing I was personally concerned about was trying to get the
                    Embassy and others to take action to save the South Vietnamese for whom I felt
                    we were responsible, especially the Foreign Service National employees. There
                    were three or four of us mid-level officers, Lionel Rosenblatt was one of them,
                    I guess he was in INR at the time, and somebody else, I can't think of his name,
                    but this guy went to Vietnam with Lionel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: You know who I'm talking about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, I do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes. He was in the Executive Secretariat, I think. Anyway, the three
                    of us and maybe there was one or two others involved, but basically the three of
                    us formed a sort of cabal, trying to get the U.S. government to do the right
                    thing by the South Vietnamese to whom we had special obligations. We really
                    worked on that as much as we could. Lionel and this other guy ended up just
                    taking off and going back to Vietnam without authorization and trying to save
                    our Vietnamese friends on a retail basis, one by one. I didn't feel like I could
                    do that, but I did everything I possibly could to move the Department, to move
                    the Embassy and Graham Martin, to get them to take action on evacuating these
                    people. And it was like moving a mountain, I'll tell you. Graham Martin did not
                    want to be moved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any talk that you heard of getting them out of
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: We certainly talked about it. We literally thought that he had lost
                    touch with reality. Not that he was insane, but what he said and what the
                    Embassy was reporting was so different from our perception of what was actually
                    going on, we seriously discussed whether or not he had lost touch with reality.
                    We told that to a lot of people, and we worked with Phil Habib and other senior
                    officers, trying to convince them of that. But of course they felt like they had
                    to listen to their representative on the spot, as opposed to these midlevel
                    officers in Washington. So I don't think our view ever prevailed, but we may
                    have affected the situation a little bit at the margins.</p>
                <p>Q: Was there an apparatus set before the final collapse as they were going to
                    have a hell of a lot of people coming, are we going to do something about
                    it.</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I called for it in memos; I even came up with some numbers. A million
                    people or more would be in immediate and grave danger with the collapse of the
                    South Vietnamese government, people to whom we had a moral obligation. There was
                    just a total resistance in the Embassy and the Department to, number one,
                    accepting that it was going to happen. They would not believe that South Vietnam
                    was about to fall. And number two, that we were obliged to do anything about
                    these people even if it did. So that was a very, very uphill struggle. We left
                    lots of good people behind, and we were slow in preparing to assist those who
                    did get out, mostly on their own and with no help from us.</p>
                <p>Q: This is one of the things that really struck me about all the touchy-feely who
                    were concerned about our involvement in the war and all the people there, and
                    all of a sudden when there was a real crisis, they washed their hands and went
                    away, they washed their hands even before because once we stopped drafting
                    college kids, the protests went down.</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Absolutely. They didn't care about the South Vietnamese people. They
                    were not their friends. I expected that of the anti-war movement. But I didn't
                    expect it of the State Department and the Ford Administration, but that's
                    basically the policy we got at first. Eventually they came around.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you get involved? When the collapse came was there a moment when everybody
                    says “It's gone?” I mean like when Da Nang fell or something like that?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Well, I had predicted in December it was coming. And so as it
                    started, when the first province capital fell, I guess that was in February, and
                    the South Vietnamese couldn't take it back, this to me just confirmed what I had
                    said in my December memo, and I wrote that at the time. When Quang Tri and Hue
                    fell, and the best South Vietnamese units, the Marines and a big part of the
                    Airborne and the First Division, fell along with them, that should have made it
                    as clear as it could be to anybody knowledgeable about Vietnam that the end was
                    at hand. But Graham Martin kept talking about how they would draw a perimeter
                    around Saigon and the Mekong Delta and defend that and hold on. That seemed to
                    me totally out of touch with reality.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for how Kissinger responded to
                        this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, I never did. I never talked to him personally during that period,
                    and I didn't know what his real feelings were. I hoped that he could see what
                    was happening, but I just didn't know. Of course they had to deal with Congress
                    at that level. They were getting a lot of pressure from the Congress not to do
                    anything, to even suggest that we were going back in to save the situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there, I mean was anybody passing out in the State
                        Department at some point an alert and say 'Here it comes. It's going down
                        the tubes and we're going to have refugees, and we're going to have this and
                        that.' I'm talking about sort of official..</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not beyond me and Lionel and a couple of others at lower levels.
                    There was a guy in the Agency in Saigon named Frank Snepp who was giving some of
                    those kinds of warnings as well. But at the senior level, no. Nothing. At least
                    that I was aware of.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Craig Johnstone is the other guy. Well, when the
                        thincollapsed, what did your working group do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: We were just trying to focus on issues like setting up the refugee
                    camps and moving the refugees off the boats to Guam, what would happen to the
                    Vietnamese Embassy here, the government's assets, just sweeping up the mess
                    basically.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any particular part of it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I worked on setting up some of the refugee camps, but I was
                    approaching the end of my tour, and that summer, a couple of months after Saigon
                    fell on April 30th, 1975, I left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where'd you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I went to Burma. I spent a few weeks in Burmese language training,
                    just enough for the basics, and then went to Mandalay as Principal Officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from '75 to?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I was in Mandalay from '75 to '76 and then went to Rangoon, where I
                    was chief of the political-economic section. I was there for two years,
                    '7'78.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well let's talk about Mandalay first. What was Mandalay
                        like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It's not like Kipling says. (laughter) It's not where the flying
                    fishes play, and the sun comes up like thunder out of China 'cross the bay. No,
                    it's not like that. It's dusty and sleepy and remote. There was an Indian
                    Consulate and an American Consulate there and that was the diplomatic community.
                    I pretty quickly came to question why we were there. The government was
                    basically the same as it is today, a military dictatorship, then under Ne Win.
                    It was nasty, isolationist to the point of being hermit-like (they didn't even
                    want tourists), anti-American, suspicious, difficult to work with. The Burmese
                    people were great, but there wasn't much I could do in Mandalay. For a whole
                    year I couldn't even get in to see the provincial governor. As the U.S. Consul,
                    he wouldn't see me. Didn't want anything to do with American representatives.
                    So, frankly I didn't do a whole heck of a lot. I learned to play tennis and
                    tried to write a few reports on whatever I could find that was interesting, but
                    there was not much there. I recommended that the post be closed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then, I take it there really wasn't any opposition
                        you wento talk to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh, no. And in fact they restricted movement, so I couldn't travel
                    around very much. There were just a few places foreigners could go. The Burmese
                    government was engaged in counter-insurgency operations all along the frontiers.
                    The Burmese heartland is the Irawaddy Valley, but all along the periphery of the
                    country are various mountain tribes, the Shan states to the east bordering
                    Thailand and the Karen and Kachin and half a dozen other groups up along the
                    Chinese border to the north and over to the west along the Indian border. Most
                    of those people were not under government control and were in varying states of
                    rebellion. Also, there were the warlord narcotics traffickers in those areas.
                    The Burmese government didn't promote or condone the narcotics trafficking.
                    While they didn't much give a damn about U.S. domestic narcotics problems, they
                    did care about the narcotics traffickers because they realized that much if not
                    most of the insurgency was financed by narcotics trafficking. So our interests,
                    though differing, converged.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved with any, while you were in Mandalay
                        witany anti-narcotics?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, because there was nothing that could be done. We didn't have a
                    good enough relationship with the Burmese government that we could work with
                    them in Mandalay. Later, however, after I moved to Rangoon, we became very much
                    involved with them there. At the senior level, exchanging intelligence, the
                    Agency was active. DEA came in with a resident agent. Most importantly, we had a
                    military assistance program giving the Burmese helicopters to go after the
                    narcotics traffickers - from our point of view narcotics traffickers, from their
                    point of view insurgents. They happened to be the same guys. Particularly
                    because of my experience in Chiang Mai, I had reservations about working with
                    this really nasty government on narcotics, particularly giving them military
                    assistance, because once we gave it to them we didn't have the kind of
                    relationship that would enable us to exert a lot of influence, much less
                    control, over how it was used. I was very concerned that they would use it for
                    things that were not in our interests, basically to go out and suppress innocent
                    people as well as narcotics traffickers. They would go after narcotics
                    traffickers insofar as it so happened that they were also insurgents. But they
                    likely would not make the distinction between people who were insurgents because
                    of religious, political or other reasons, and those who were just criminal
                    narcotics traffickers. They were using our equipment for all of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well when you were in Mandalay, what was the staff of
                        ouconsulate there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: There was me and a vice consul and three or four FSNs. Q: I take it
                    no visa work or?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No. I don't believe we had a single tourist the wholtime I was there.
                    The Burmese didn't want tourists to come.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was vice consul when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Jim Marx.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the Indian consul, was he doing anything?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: He didn't seem to have very much to do, but there was an Indian
                    community there. Burma was part of British India, and many Indians moved to
                    Burma during the colonial period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you went down you were in Rangoon from '76 to
                        '78.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Right.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the Ambassador when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: David Osborne. And he was replaced by Maurice Bean.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you were what, economic?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Political-economic Counselor. We had a combined political and
                    economic section that consisted of me and two other officers and a
                    secretary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Burma at that time was there anything that could be
                        recognizeas an opposition party?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: There was the insurgency, the armed opposition. Political opposition
                    simply was not tolerated. As now, the opposition was thrown in jail.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any contact there within the Burmese
                        government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: We had some but it was rather limited. I worked with the Foreign
                    Ministry in my job. I was also the narcotics coordinator for the Mission, so I
                    got involved in that quite a bit. Also I spent half the time as Acting DCM. For
                    health reasons, we had two DCMs evacuated. I was the number three guy, so I
                    spent nearly half of my tour there as Acting DCM.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would think that DCM is responsible for the staff and
                        all that,it sounds like there wasn't an awful lot for people to do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not an awful lot, it wasn't that busy. The busiest part of the
                    Embassy's work was connected with narcotics. There was some economic work, oil
                    exploration. One American oil company was active there. Responding to the many
                    inquiries from the Department on human rights and trying to find out what was
                    going on (with very limited success) took some time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Un-Sung....</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Aungsan Su-Chi?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Su-Chi, was she a presence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: She was not a presence at that time. She was nosomebody that we had
                    ever heard of.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ne Win was the long-time ruler. Was there any feeling
                        about whahe was after or what sort of person he was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh, he was a corrupt military dictator, to sum it up. Power hungry,
                    would not tolerate opposition, and he had a clique of military people around him
                    who kept it that way. They were in it basically for power, not ideology.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It sounds like sort of almost a sterile place, wasn't it,
                        as faas what one could do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes. We played a lot of tennis, and those who wanted to golfed. Ne
                    Win was a great golfer, and consequently they had a couple of nice golf courses.
                    We played tennis, we socialized, there was a fairly good-sized diplomatic
                    community. The biggest adventure I had there was an aborted coup attempt. This
                    was one of the times I was Acting DCM. The duty officer called about nine or ten
                    or clock while I was at a dinner, and said that a man has appeared at the
                    Ambassador's gate, and he's hiding in the bushes and he's asking for political
                    asylum. So the duty officer picked me up and the two of us went to investigate.
                    We finally induced the guy to come out of the bushes where he was hiding. He
                    turned out to be a young Burmese army captain who had been the leader of a plot
                    to assassinate Ne Win and overthrow the government. The plot had gone awry, and
                    he had come to the American Ambassador's house seeking political asylum. Well,
                    we wouldn't let him in; we couldn't really, as sorry as we felt for him. We
                    drove him around town, got his story, and said 'hey, gee I'm sorry, but there's
                    not much we can do for you,' and we put him out at the railroad station. He was
                    later captured and executed. That was exciting but sad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Burma, is that part of southeast Asia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It's on the border between south and southeast Asia, between India
                    and Thailand. I was pleased to have served in the three most romantic sounding
                    Consulates in Southeast Asia, Hue, Chiang Mai and Mandalay.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would be '75, I guess. I mean '78.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: '78, when I finished up in Rangoon. Then the Departmensent me to the
                    Army War College, for senior training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With Carlisle Barracks?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Carlisle Barracks. By this time I was an FSO-3 and eligible for
                    senior training, and that turned out to be a wonderful assignment. Our children
                    were small, and we enjoyed living on post. Moreover, the training did what it
                    was supposed to do. I learned a lot about leadership and management and all the
                    things that one needs for more senior positions. I just wish I'd known about a
                    lot of it sooner. It was a delightful time, and it was a productive time in that
                    it prepared me to be a better leader and a better senior officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was Vietnam playing itself out at Carlisle?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: This was the generation of young military officers that I was with in
                    Vietnam, who were now senior Lieutenant Colonels and Colonels. They had been the
                    battalion commanders; some of the younger ones company commanders. They were
                    suffering; the Army was suffering the hangover from the Vietnam War. They felt
                    the Army was in deep trouble. They were dumbing down the manuals to the level of
                    comic books, they had narcotics problems, they had recruiting problems. It was
                    what has been called the 'hollow army.' It looked like a sound organization on
                    the surface, but when you got inside it was empty or rotten at the core. These
                    guys recognized that and they determined to do something about it. This was the
                    generation of Colin Powell, and a lot of others who really turned the Army
                    around from that time, developed some new ideas including the all-volunteer
                    Army, and made the Army and the armed forces generally what they are today. I
                    thought they were talented, dedicated, decent people. I very much enjoyed
                    getting to know them and living and working with them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would be '79, I guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I graduated in 1979, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I was eager to get a senior assignment, preferably a DCM job. Then
                    (as I suppose now) DCM jobs were hard to come by. But I lobbied for it, came
                    down to Washington. There wasn't anything available in my 'home' East Asia
                    bureau, where I'd had all my geographic experience. So if I was going to be a
                    DCM it had to be somewhere else. The opportunities were much greater in Africa
                    than anywhere else, and that's indeed what turned up, Chad. At this point Chad
                    was in the midst of a civil war, which had been ongoing to some degree ever
                    since independence in 1962. It was in a particularly heated phase at that time.
                    It had been at first between the Muslim north and the Christian and animist
                    south, but by this time the Muslim north had by and large won that struggle and
                    had chased all the Christians out of the north, including the capital,
                    N'djamena. However, various factions of the Arabized, Muslim north were now
                    fighting among themselves. The two principal ones were called the Forces Arm�es
                    Populaires (or FAP) under Goukouni Oueddai, and the Forces Arm�es du Nord (or
                    FAN) of Hissen Habr�. They had reached a very unstable cease-fire, and the two
                    principal factions along with a couple of smaller factions had formed a
                    so-called coalition government in N'djamena. However, it was just an armed
                    standoff, and the government was not real. By this point, mid '79, we had
                    evacuated dependents and closed the Peace Corps program, but we still had the
                    core staff of the Embassy there. We were in between Ambassadors, so when I was
                    sent there as DCM I immediately became Charg�. This was a big responsibility for
                    a brand-new DCM who had never been in the country or even in Africa. I did the
                    best I could. Eventually, after about four months, we got an Ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Don Norland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now, when you went out there as charge', who was
                        there ttalk to in the government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: There were plenty of people to talk to, but there was no government.
                    You could talk to one faction and they'd tell you one thing and another faction
                    would tell you the opposite. The Minister of Health was illiterate. It was that
                    kind of government, just warlords and their lieutenants. They were backed by
                    their militia armies occupying different parts of the capital. These armies
                    included lots of twelve and fourteen year old kids with AK-47's. They also had
                    some heavier weapons, mortars and the like. They had nominally formed a
                    coalition government, but it was as close to anarchy as you could get.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now was Qadhafi playing games?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes. Qadhafi had at one time or another supported all of the
                    different factions and was very much involved in the civil war, stirring things
                    up.</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were American interests there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Very few that I could discern. We were interested in what Qadhafi was
                    up to. Also, this was before the Cold War was over, and we still had Russians
                    and Chinese and others to worry about there. Chad had even then been talked
                    about as a potential source of oil. Subsequently they found some, and they're
                    now producing oil there. But other than that, few American interests. The French
                    were Chad's principal patron. They had an airbase just outside of N'djamena,
                    secured by a battalion of the Foreign Legion, and they were the main players
                    there politically and economically. We had a fairly substantial Embassy, but not
                    as big as the French.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was our relationship at that point with the French
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Pretty good. We didn't have any serious issues with them. I would
                    describe relations as good if not cordial. We worked together well, had no
                    conflicts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But I suppose also you saw them as being a refuge, a
                        source ostability or something?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes, we really looked to them to help in emergencies, and in fact
                    that's what eventually happened. In the spring of 1980 the government, such as
                    it was, totally collapsed and war broke out again, right in the middle of town,
                    between the two major factions, Goukouni and Habr�. As we reported, the FAP had
                    hit the FAN. There was heavy firing all over town. They weren't after
                    foreigners, but we were right in the middle of it. Most of the fighters were
                    these 14-year-old kids with AK-47s, not trained, not disciplined. Also, they
                    were firing mortars and 'Stalin organs,' World War II era rocket launchers they
                    had gotten from the Russians by way of the Libyans, which are very much an area
                    weapon. You aim it at a city in general, and it may hit that if you're lucky. So
                    this stuff was falling all around and we were in pretty dire straits for awhile.
                    It certainly was dangerous. This is where my experience in Vietnam proved very
                    helpful. Basically that's why I got the job, because they knew that this sort of
                    thing was possible, and they wanted somebody who knew something about being in
                    war and had proved that they don't panic under fire. That's indeed what was
                    needed. I was able to help a lot of people who had not had that kind of
                    experience to do the right thing, that is, to tell them you don't run out in the
                    street and try to get away from it. With mortar shells and gunfire coming in you
                    get in a corner with strong walls and cover yourself up and chances are you're
                    going to get through it. So I was constantly on the emergency radio, and was
                    able to calm several people who might have done dangerous things otherwise. We
                    were able to get through the fighting without losing anybody. This went on for
                    three or four days before the French and we could arrange a temporary cease-fire
                    so foreigners could move out from town to the French airbase. We got there
                    safely, and the next day the French flew us out to Douala.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Douala is in...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Cameroon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cameroon. In a way we just ceased relations, suspend
                        relationwith the government there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: There was no government to relate to. There were just these armed
                    factions at that point. And we had to abandon the Embassy. In those years we
                    didn't have Marine guards in all embassies, and Chad was one where we didn't in
                    spite of the danger there. The Embassy was right in the area between the two
                    opposing forces. The fighting broke out late at night, around midnight, so
                    nobody was in the Embassy at the time. We knew things were dangerous so we
                    didn't have but one drawer of classified material, but we had code equipment
                    there. The Department wanted us to go back in and destroy it, but the Embassy
                    was right in the middle of the fighting. We couldn't go there without seriously
                    risking someone's life. This became even more evident when we talked to the
                    Defense Attach�, an enterprising young lieutenant colonel, whom DIA had tasked
                    with getting some ordnance that the Libyans had given the Chadian forces. He had
                    been able to collect some artillery shells, and had assembled them in his office
                    in the Embassy, thus turning it into an ammo dump. He had not told either me or
                    the Ambassador that he had done this, so when we started talking about possibly
                    going back to retrieve the classified material and destroy it, he said 'Well,
                    there's something you should know. If one of those mortar shells hits in the
                    right place, that whole Embassy is going to blow up.' So we didn't go back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long were you in, where was it, Jalalabad?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Douala.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long were you there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Long enough so they could give me a passport, some moneand a ticket
                    to get on the plane to come home. Maybe two days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you just abandoned the place?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes. It's all we could do. The Agency sent some people back to hover
                    on the border to try to get back in as soon as they could to destroy the
                    classified material. Eventually they did get back, but it took at least two or
                    three months. Until the fighting died down, there was just no way you could get
                    there without military intervention.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the end result of the fighting?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The end result was eventually a victory by Habr� and his FAN faction.
                    He took over as President but didn't do a good job. He's currently being hunted
                    for human rights violations but has been given asylum somewhere. Chad remained
                    unstable for several more years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever go back?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No. Lost all my household effects there, everything,just had to
                    abandon it. The Embassy wasn't re-opened for a long time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your wife with you...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No. Even before I got there dependents had been evacuated, and
                    consequently my wife and our two daughters in elementary school stayed behind in
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you came back, what did they do with you? You went
                        outhere in '70...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: In the summer of '79, and came back in late spring of '80. They gave
                    me a nice post, perhaps as a reward for my being in danger so much from Vietnam
                    and now surviving another war in Chad. I went to Benin, which many people
                    wouldn't think of as a reward I guess, but the job was as Chief of Mission and
                    Permanent Charg�. It was the same as being Ambassador, but without the title.
                    Three or four years before we had downgraded the level of our representation
                    from Ambassador to Charg�, because the government was so nasty and hostile. It
                    was run by Matthew Kerekou, a former sergeant in the French colonial forces who
                    had successfully mounted a military coup. At that time he was in his rabid
                    Marxist-Leninist phase and was very anti-American. He had all kinds of Russians
                    and Chinese and North Koreans and Cubans and Libyans around. He subsequently
                    became a militant Islamist for a few years, and then mutated into a born-again
                    Christian, his latest persona. Currently he's again the President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well you were there for how long?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Two years. Q: In Benin?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: In Benin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again, what did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: In spite of poor U.S.-Benin relations, we still had a Peace Corps
                    program, but we didn't have any foreign aid program. There were a few American
                    citizens around to take care of. There was oil exploration off the coast, and in
                    fact they found some. But there was not an awful lot you could do with that
                    government other than to try to stay out of its way. We were not entirely
                    successful in that regard, unfortunately. Toward the end of my tour, in late
                    '81, we had another interesting adventure. Cotonou was a small Embassy, with
                    only one communicator. At this particular time our generator needed some
                    maintenance. The centralized maintenance facility was in Monrovia, so we had a
                    generator repairman from Monrovia come in. He arrived on Thanksgiving Day. Our
                    communicator met him and the two of them went off that evening to a Thanksgiving
                    dinner that some other Americans had organized. On their way home that night,
                    about 9 p.m., they took a wrong turn on a dark, unmarked road into what turned
                    out to be a Beninese military base. When they approached, the gate guards did
                    not say 'Halt, who goes there?' but simply started firing their AK-47's. They
                    shot up the car pretty badly, and wounded our communicator. His ankle was
                    basically destroyed. They took him to the hospital and put the generator
                    repairman in jail, even though he had a diplomatic passport. He had all his
                    generator repair tools in the car, so the Beninese said, 'Oh, we're sure this
                    guy's a spy, coming in to do nefarious things at our military base, and we
                    caught him red-handed.' The most immediate problem was that with our one
                    communicator shot and in the hospital we could not communicate because he was
                    the only one who knew the code to get into the communications vault to operate
                    the equipment. We had a Collins KWM-2 radio outside the vault for emergency
                    communications and we called on that, but nobody was listening. Lagos, less than
                    a hundred miles away, about a two-hour drive, was our backup facility for
                    emergencies. It was a big Embassy, but for some reason they didn't turn their
                    KWM-2 on that evening, so we couldn't communicate with them. I'm a ham radio
                    operator, and because I was Charg�, I had been able to talk the Beninese
                    government into giving me a license. I'd set up a good ham radio station in the
                    Ambassador's residence, where we were living. So when we couldn't communicate
                    from the Embassy I went home and got on the ham radio. I contacted a ham in New
                    York and had him call the State Department operations center and tell them our
                    situation, that our communicator was shot and the generator repairman from
                    Monrovia was in jail, and please first thing tomorrow morning have Embassy Lagos
                    send us a doctor and a communicator. This worked, and the message went right
                    through. So early the next morning the doctor, a senior officer from the Agency
                    who was looking after the communicator, and a new communicator arrived. The
                    doctor and the Agency man went into the hospital and managed to spirit our
                    communicator out under the noses of the Beninese, who weren't guarding him very
                    carefully. (We often called Benin a police state poorly policed.) They took him
                    back across the border to Lagos, and were able to save his foot, which the
                    Beninese doctors had been on the point of amputating. But the government kept
                    the generator repairman in jail, and it was over two months before we finally
                    got him out. This was 1981 and early '82, very close on the heels of the Iranian
                    hostage crisis, and we were very sensitive at that time to nasty governments
                    putting Americans with diplomatic passports in jail. But we didn't want to
                    publicize the incident and kept it out of the press, because we knew if it
                    became public that would cause lots of complications and likely make it harder
                    to get our man released.</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>Q: And of course the state, I mean one of your provinces was such a small state,
                    that you know a military action against it would not have been precluded. Which
                    is not a good idea.</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, we didn't want to take that path. We wanted to use diplomatic
                    means to get him out. We tried everything. We got the local Ambassadors to make
                    a demarche on our behalf, and we got the UN representatives in Benin to do the
                    same. In Benin the French were by far the most influential. So eventually the
                    Department enlisted French President Francois Mitterrand to call President
                    Kerekou directly. Mitterrand persuaded him to let our generator repairman go.
                    That was an interesting adventure for me, perhaps less so for the communicator
                    and generator repairman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I take it you didn't get your generator fixed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, not right away. By that time I was approaching thend of my
                    tour.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find much contact with the people of Benin?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The people were friendly, but the government was snasty that it
                    limited the amount of contact we could have.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I take it there's no real political reporting to be done
                        oanything like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I could do quite a bit. As I said, it was a police state poorly
                    policed. There were a lot of people that you could talk to, a lot of information
                    that one could develop, and it was possible to travel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Around Benin...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Around it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bounded, what, to the South was...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Nigeria.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Nigeria. To the north...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: To the north is Niger and Burkina Faso, and to the wesis Togo.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Togo. Were there any problems with these states?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not really, no. Benin served as a vast entrepot for smuggling into
                    Nigeria. We benefitted from that. You could buy Johnnie Walker scotch for three
                    dollars a bottle. Luxury goods of all sorts were legally imported into Benin to
                    be smuggled into Nigeria, where at least some people had lots of money to spend
                    on them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One thinks of the Benin bronzes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, that's the Benin state of Nigeria. Benin, the country, was the
                    former Dahomey, under the French, a part of French West Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about tribal problems, any?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Benin is so fractured that there weren't any major ones. In that tiny
                    country of perhaps three million people, there are something like twenty
                    different ethnic groups, and none of them dominant. So they have to get along
                    one way or another if they're going to have a government at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they a trading people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not particularly.</p>
                <p>Q: Because some of these smaller countries end up either producing traders up and
                    down the coast or good clerks or something...</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The Beninese were regarded as the intellectuals of French West
                    Africa. A lot of them had relatively more education and served in the colonial
                    civil service as clerks and teachers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about again, was this a place where the French were
                        dominant?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Very much, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we sort of keep out of it, were they looking at
                        ususpiciously, the French?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not at that point. We got along quite well with the French and didn't
                    have any real problems. I sent my two daughters to the French school there,
                    since there was no American school. The school at first wouldn't let them in
                    because they didn't speak French. I went to the French Ambassador, and he was
                    nice enough to intervene and cause them to be admitted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did they find that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: They were in the second and third grade at that point, and it was
                    traumatic for a few weeks, but only a few weeks. Within five, six weeks they
                    were speaking French pretty well, and after three or four months they were
                    speaking like little French girls.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did social life, was there much social life?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Within the diplomatic corps there was. There was little other
                    entertainment. Some of the Beninese would occasionally join us. As Chief of
                    Mission I was obliged to give the Fourth of July receptions and other official
                    functions. Tuy-Cam and I enjoyed doing that at first, but it was a lot of
                    work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Cold War intrude at all there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not much. We got along well with the Russians there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Soviets in those days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The Soviets in those days, yes. And with the Chinese. The only people
                    we didn't get along with were the North Koreans. They had an Embassy there, and
                    they were just nasty. They would turn away when they saw me coming. I didn't
                    want anything to do with them either.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But our interests there were...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Minimal.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Minimal.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: In fact toward the end of my tour the Beninese government told us to
                    relocate the Ambassador's residence and the Embassy to a diplomatic compound
                    where they wanted all of the Embassies to relocate, better to keep control over
                    them. Because of Tehran and other Embassy security problems we had already had
                    the Inman report and imposed greatly increased security requirements. To build a
                    new Embassy, the security for it has to be such that it becomes an enormous and
                    very expensive undertaking. We had a preliminary survey team come out, and they
                    concluded it would cost something like five million dollars to build a suitable
                    Embassy and Ambassador's residence where the Beninese wanted us to put them.
                    These would have been the grandest buildings in town. My recommendation was that
                    we simply close down rather than do that, because in my opinion our interests in
                    Benin did not justify that kind of expense and having that kind of Mission
                    there, particularly with all the ongoing costs of operating and protecting it.
                    It never came to that, because the government backed down and didn't make us
                    move.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you beginning to be part of the African Mafia by this
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would think that, you know, there are a lot of these
                        Embassiethat one could shut down.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But it would mean no more Ambassadorial ranks for the
                        Africacorps, you know. It's a potential problem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: My closure recommendation was not taken well, I think, in the Africa
                    Bureau. But the only effective counter-argument I ever heard was that the
                    Congress, specifically the Black Caucus, will not let us close. I think that's
                    probably still the case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anybody, any visits from anybody?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: We did have the Pope come. I lined up on the airport tarmac to greet
                    him along with the rest of the diplomatic corps. No senior visits from the
                    U.S.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you got out of there in what, '82?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: '82.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '82. Then what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Then I got my Ambassadorship, in title as well as in substance. I was
                    named Ambassador to Burundi. But that was a long, drawn out process. We left
                    Cotonou in August of '82. After a couple weeks leave I went to New York to wait
                    out the confirmation process. I was assigned to the U.S. Mission to the UN as
                    senior advisor on Africa in the U.S. delegation to the General Assembly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would be general assembly of '82?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes, the General Assembly that began in early September. I stayed
                    there all fall, waiting for the Senate to get around to acting on my
                    Ambassadorial nomination.</p>
                <p>Q: Let's talk a little about your experience in the UN. The African bloc of
                    course is very large, and worldwide has to be quite important. Did you find
                    there was really, I mean was there a unit? Was there an African bloc?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh, yes. They got together and consulted, both formally and
                    informally. On some things they voted as a bloc; on other things you could
                    separate a few off. On many issues a lot of them didn't really care very much.
                    It all depended on the issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of issues were you getting involved with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: To tell the truth, I didn't think that many of the issues that I got
                    involved with were very important. This was still the Cold War, still the
                    standoff with the Soviets. And the United Nations, particularly the General
                    Assembly, was a great hall of the winds. There was a lot of talk and very little
                    action. The bureaucracy was just awful. The thing they were most exercised about
                    in that General Assembly, it seemed, was a plan to celebrate the 500th
                    anniversary of the “discovery” of America by Christopher Columbus. The Nordics
                    got all excited, and said 'Hell, he didn't discover it at all; it's Lief Erikson
                    we should be honoring.' And then the South Americans said 'All he did was come
                    over and start exploiting the poor Indians.' The Italians and Spanish championed
                    their man. And that debate went on and on. They were taking this seriously.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any problems going out to Burundi?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, it just took time. The General Assembly was over in late
                    December, but my Senate hearing still hadn't been scheduled. So the Department
                    sent me to the Federal Executive Institute in Charlottesville for a leadership
                    course. The course was really good, but I'd had much the same training at the
                    Army War College, so for me it was just a reinforcement of what I had already
                    learned. I finally got the call from President Reagan there at the Federal
                    Executive Institute. I was in a class with some 50 other federal executives,
                    when the secretary from the Director's office came into the classroom and said
                    'Mr. Bullington has a call from the President.' All these feds definitely took
                    notice. (laughter) So I went out to take the call, and it really was President
                    Reagan. He always called new Ambassadors personally. He said 'I want you to be
                    my Ambassador to Burundi.' When I walked back into that classroom, silence fell.
                    The professor said 'Well, who was it? What kind of joke was this?' 'It was
                    President Reagan,' I replied. 'What did he want?' 'He asked me to be his
                    Ambassador to Burundi.' Then everyone cheered. That was a fun moment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, this is sort of not always standard, but you get
                        this. Buit never happens to the rest of the government.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, I don't think it did. They were all amazed. became the class
                    celebrity.</p>
                <p>Q: You went out there when?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It was April or May of '83. We got there in time to do the Fourth of
                    July reception.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of '83.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: '83.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were there how long?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Until after the Fourth of July reception in '86.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bad timing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I couldn't avoid that.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, in the first place, I've got a map in my eyes,
                        Burundi ithe lower or upper one?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It's the lower one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lower one. Rwanda, Burundi are always going together.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: They're twins.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lower one. What was the situation in Burundi when you went
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It was difficult. Burundi and Rwanda are truly twins. They're about
                    the same size; they were both former Belgian territories, League of Nations
                    mandates. They were originally colonized by the Germans in the 1890s, but they
                    were awarded to the Belgians after World War I, under the League of Nations.
                    They both have the same ethnic makeup, about 75-80% Hutu, and about 15-18%
                    Tutsi, with a few other sorts of people. The conflict has been between the
                    Tutsis and the Hutus. Long before the Germans came, both Rwanda and Burundi had
                    been Tutsi-ruled kingdoms in more or less the current geographic boundaries of
                    what is now Rwanda and what is now Burundi. So this is not one of the many cases
                    in Africa where the white colonialists came in and drew stupid boundaries and
                    got different ethnic groups all mixed up. It was that way when the Europeans got
                    there - two Tutsi-ruled kingdoms in what is now Rwanda and Burundi. When the
                    Belgians were forced to give them independence in 1962 they took different
                    paths. In Rwanda the majority Hutus took over and proceeded to persecute the
                    Tutsis. In Burundi just the opposite happened. The minority Tutsis were able to
                    maintain themselves in power and proceeded to do nasty things to the Hutus,
                    denying them access to education and all positions of power. In 1976 there was a
                    Hutu uprising in Burundi that was viciously suppressed in what amounted to a
                    genocide. It was not quite on the scale of what happened in Rwanda in 1994, but
                    still tens of thousands of Hutus were slaughtered after they had unsuccessfully
                    tried to overthrow the government. It was said that the Tutsis either killed or
                    forced to flee the country every Hutu with more than an elementary school
                    education. As time went on each of these situations played off the other. In
                    Burundi the Tutsis could say 'See, see Rwanda, what has happened there, what
                    they have done to the Tutsis, and how nasty they've been. That's what will
                    happen to us if these guys ever get power here.' Same thing in Rwanda. They said
                    'See, see these Tutsis in Burundi, what they did to our brethren there. That's
                    what they will do to us if we give them half a chance.' So the two problems
                    reinforced each other. In 1983, when I got there, Burundi was fairly calm, but
                    it was only a calm imposed by the Tutsi military government. They held all the
                    important levers of power, most importantly the Army. There were no Hutu army
                    officers, none. There were no Hutus, except a few tame ones they had co-opted,
                    at any significant level of government. The Tutsis ran things, keeping the
                    country quiet, but suppressed. The government was paranoid. They saw enemies
                    everywhere, particularly Europeans and Americans. They saw us as people who
                    wanted to come in and organize the Hutus in a rebellion that would overthrow
                    them. Harassment and expulsion of missionaries was one of the things that I
                    dealt with from the beginning. There were still twenty or thirty American
                    missionaries as well as a lot of European missionaries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Americans were mostly Protestant.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The Americans were all Protestant. The Europeans were almost all
                    Catholic. But both groups were equally mistrusted as foreign agents who were
                    working to support and educate the Hutus who would eventually rise up and
                    overthrow the Tutsi government. So the government didn't like missionaries, and
                    they were suspicious of the countries from whence the missionaries came. They
                    were suspicious of almost anything we did. We had an AID mission there. For a
                    rural road construction project, AID had shipped in several boxes of machetes,
                    to clear brush along the road. The government seized those machetes, and said
                    'This is obviously something you're planning to hand out to the Hutus to come
                    and slaughter us!' It was paranoia. They were constantly harassing and expelling
                    the missionaries. One of my closest allies became the Papal Nuncio. I worked
                    with him to try to moderate such problems. The biggest crisis we had, however,
                    was over our diplomatic pouches. The American government, unlike any other as
                    far as I can tell, allows its personnel to use the diplomatic pouch for personal
                    mail, including packages. Consequently the American pouches are physically
                    bigger and more numerous than any other country's. This has been going on for a
                    long time, but one particular pouch shipment came in that was especially huge.
                    There were thirty large diplomatic pouch bags addressed to the U.S. Embassy.
                    Because of their paranoia the Burundi government seized them and wouldn't let
                    them out of the airport. They said 'This is surely a shipment of arms to arm the
                    Hutus and overthrow us.' This led to a serious confrontation that lasted several
                    months. We had no idea what was in those pouches. And the State Department
                    couldn't tell us what was in them. They just came through the U.S. mail. Nobody
                    had opened the boxes they contained. Nobody knew what was in those pouches.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was anybody in your Embassy waiting for something?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Not that we knew of. No one had ordered any personal mail of that
                    bulk. But it was not only those particular pouches; they then blocked all the
                    subsequent ones that came in. So that stopped both our official pouch mail and
                    our personal mail. This was just before Christmas, November of 1985. So nobody
                    got Christmas presents for the kids and other things we'd ordered. This went on
                    for about three months. We didn't even get the checks that were in the pouches
                    that were needed to pay the rents for our housing and salaries for our local
                    employees. We didn't get medical supplies. We didn't get all these things that
                    normally come through the pouch. This made it very difficult to operate the
                    Embassy. Also, there's an important principle involved, the inviolability of
                    diplomatic pouches, which could have repercussions far beyond Burundi. I was
                    doing everything I could to try to get a resolution, but the government wouldn't
                    budge. Finally, I wanted to begin gradually shutting down the Embassy, to say
                    'Ok, we can't pay our rents, we can't pay our salaries, we have to start laying
                    people off, and eventually we'll just close up and go home.' I didn't think our
                    interests in Burundi were important enough to justify caving in on the principle
                    of inviolability of diplomatic pouches. The Africa Bureau took another view and
                    said no, we should try to accommodate them, don't make any threats, just stick
                    it out and eventually the problem will go away. Some parts of the Department
                    whose interests were more focused on pouches and diplomatic procedures and the
                    precedential implications of the situation seemed to share my view, but my
                    instructions came from the Africa Bureau. They said no, don't do anything, just
                    live with it. After three months I decided we couldn't live with it much longer,
                    and we ought to do something one way or another. By interpreting my
                    instructions, let's say, very liberally, the solution I came up with was to
                    invite the Foreign Ministry to send their people into the Embassy along with the
                    pouches that were at issue, and observe us as we opened them. I didn't know what
                    was in them, but I knew damn well it was not arms or anything else that the
                    government of Burundi had any legitimate reason to be concerned about. Whether
                    or not the Department would have approved this procedure I'll never know, but
                    anyway we did it. The pouches were opened and the contents turned out to be
                    seeds addressed to Peace Corps. The Peace Corps director had gotten an offer
                    from an American seed company that said 'we have some seeds we'd like to give to
                    Peace Corps Volunteers to plant.' She thought she was ordering these little
                    packages of seeds that you get at hardware stores. Instead of little packages,
                    they were gross lots of five hundred packages. So that's what caused the
                    diplomatic confrontation, pounds and pounds of Peace Corps seeds. Although the
                    problem was solved, I don't think the Africa Bureau much liked me for resisting
                    their instructions just to do nothing and wait it out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have much contact with Rwanda, our Embassy in
                        Rwanda?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: To some extent. I visited John Blaine, our Ambassador there, during
                    the first part of my tour. But it wasn't a daily kind of thing.</p>
                <p>Q: Given the history of those places, one would almost be taking the temperature
                    every day of the Hutu-Tutsi relationship, was it sort of known that at any time
                    this could blow up?</p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: We were concerned about it because in Burundi it had blown up less
                    than ten years previously, in 1976, in a terrible massacre. We knew it could
                    happen, but the government had been successful in keeping the Hutus so
                    suppressed that there was no visible internal threat at that time. There were
                    Hutu opposition movements based in Brussels and across Lake Tanganyika in
                    eastern Congo, Zaire at that time. But they weren't really doing anything inside
                    the country. There was no significant fighting at the time I was there, but it
                    was always a potential.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there at that time a Hutu educated class and all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, they had wiped it out in 1976, and didn't permit any more Hutus
                    to get advanced educations or to rise to leadership positions. Almost all
                    educated Hutus were outside Burundi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well this must have put quite a crimp on the missionaries
                        didn'it? I mean did you find yourself having to sit on the
                        missionaries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: We tried to intervene on their behalf with the government, to keep
                    the government from expelling them and doing nasty things to them. The Seventh
                    Day Adventists were one of the groups that were active there. My cook was a
                    Seventh Day Adventist. He had been the cook for previous Ambassadors for several
                    years. The government had a corv�e labor system, inherited from colonial days,
                    where they would assemble people supposedly on a voluntary basis, but basically
                    they just rounded them up, and made them do things like repair roads. Saturday
                    was the appointed day for this communal labor. This poses a problem for faithful
                    Adventists, who are not supposed to work on their Sabbath. They refused to do
                    the Saturday labor, but they offered to do it on Sunday or some other day. Since
                    they were all Hutus, the government wouldn't accept this and threw the Adventist
                    leaders in jail. They also jailed my cook. This was during one of the times we'd
                    been having some controversy with the government, about the pouches among other
                    things, and I was pretty well convinced that they had picked on him because he
                    was my cook. He was not a minister; he was not a leader of the Adventists. There
                    were thirty, forty thousand Adventists in the country and yet they only put
                    forty or fifty of them in jail, but he was one of them. I think that they did it
                    because he was the American Ambassador's cook. 'We'll show you Americans, you
                    can't mess with us.' Jail is not a nice place to be in Burundi, especially for
                    doing nothing but maintaining one's religious faith. I was trying to get him
                    out. This was near the end of my tour, and I wanted to make a personal appeal to
                    the President during my farewell call on him. When I told the Department this,
                    the Department hemmed and hawed and eventually told me no, don't do it. Their
                    stated reasoning was that this would be unfair, that we couldn't get all the
                    Adventists out of jail so we shouldn't intervene on behalf of my cook. That
                    infuriated me.</p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's nice when you don't ask.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Right. In hindsight I would not have. But I thought it was so
                    automatic, I was just submitting the list of the things I would be reviewing
                    with the President on my farewell call, and on the list was an appeal to release
                    my cook. I never imagined that there would be a problem with it. I told them
                    that this was a very curious moral position, to say that because we cannot save
                    everyone we will therefore save no one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sounds like the lawyers got into it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Yes, probably. The decision came to me from the Africa Bureau. I
                    wrote some, let's say, rather heated remonstrances. Finally, after considerable
                    discussion, I did what I felt was the right thing, appealed to the President,
                    and got my cook out of jail.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now, who was the President of Burundi?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Jean-Baptiste Bagaza. The year after I left he was overthrown in a
                    military coup by the current President, whose name I can't recall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It'll come. But what was your impression of, what were
                        ourelations with the government, could you talk to them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: You could talk to them, but not very productively. They were so
                    suspicious, literally to the point of paranoia. They saw us as wanting to
                    overthrow them when we didn't. We didn't much like this government, but we
                    certainly weren't plotting to overthrow them or arm Hutus or anything remotely
                    approaching that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any other countries, how about the role of
                        thBelgians, was it all a role or?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: They were a major influence there, as were the French.Certainly
                    economically, they provided more aid than we did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel they were at all fishing in troubled
                        waters?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The French or Belgians? No, not really. They would have liked to the
                    extent possible to see some improvements in human rights, but no country was
                    working to bring that about in the sense of trying to overthrow the
                    government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that time, was there concerns about the growth of
                        populatiothen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Burundi and Rwanda are the two most densely populated countries in
                    Africa. It was obvious, at least to me, that there was no way they could
                    accommodate the kind of population growth they were experiencing and have any
                    hope of achieving economic development.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we able to do anything, did we have anything on
                        birtcontrol or anything of that nature?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No, we didn't. Others did, some UN agencies and NGOs,but we were not
                    active in that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we have any aid going on there? BULLINGTON: I expect
                        we do now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But at that time...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: At that time? Yes, we had a small AID mission. I looked at the AID
                    mission and discovered that the total amount of assistance it was dispersing was
                    on the level of a million dollars per year, a very small amount. To maintain
                    that AID mission with its staff and overhead was costing well over a million
                    dollars a year. This did not make sense to me, and I recommended that it be
                    closed. The Department didn't want to do that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well this is often, we talk about the AID money we're
                        giving to country, and yet we throw in the cost of the AID mission.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Particularly when it's tiny like that you're spending more on housing
                    and staff than actual money going to economic development.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about tourism?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No. None.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The mountain gorillas were up in Rwanda.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: In Rwanda, yes. There are no wild animals left in Burundi, because
                    it's so densely populated. There's not a lot to see there. It's a beautiful
                    country, though, with one of the best climates in the world. Lake Tanganyika is
                    there, a beautiful lake. Lots of mountains. But it's so densely populated that
                    unless you like seeing a lot of little bean fields and rural huts, there's not
                    much there for tourists.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any problems from Tanganyika or Zaire?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Right across the lake is Kivu province of Zaire. It was as always
                    very unstable. There was all sorts of banditry and very little government
                    control, but it didn't really spill over into Burundi when I was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in '86. The massacres occurred on your
                        watch.Where did you go then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Then I was sent back to Washington. I didn't get much of a job. The
                    Africa Bureau didn't seem to want to take care of me. The only job I could get
                    was as Associate Dean of the Senior Seminar. At that time the Dean was Jane
                    Coon, a really nice lady. She wore two hats, one as head of the School of
                    Professional Studies at FSI, and the other as Dean of the Senior Seminar. As
                    Associate Dean, having been an Ambassador, for me it was like being cast into
                    the wilderness. As it turned out, however, Jane didn't really want to do both
                    jobs, and she was more than fully occupied as head of the School of Professional
                    Studies, so she left the running of the Senior Seminar almost totally to me.
                    Then the next year on her recommendation they made me the Dean.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you did that from '86 to...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: '89.</p>
                <p>Q: '89. I was in the senior seminar back a ways, '74 or '75, but I think the
                    thing that struck me, I thought the senior seminar was very good, really enjoyed
                    it, getting to see the United States, but one thing that did strike me was that
                    the military officers who were sent there, fine people and all, but this was
                    sort of a throwaway, this was sort of the end of their careers, so it wasn't as
                    though you were meeting with future admirals or something, they were all off at
                    the war college, at least in my time.</p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I didn't have that impression. A few of the military officers during
                    my tenure there went on to become generals and admirals. I changed the Senior
                    Seminar pretty dramatically. Before it was more like a graduate course. You had
                    great field trips, but you had to do a research paper, which was much like a
                    master's thesis. And the curriculum was all policy oriented as opposed to
                    leadership and management training. I made a few changes the first year, but
                    since I was only the Deputy, there was not much I could do. But the second year
                    I made some big changes, not only because I wanted to, but also because Charlie
                    Bray came in as Director of FSI, and he was really enthusiastic about leadership
                    training. He gave me a mandate to redesign the curriculum between the first and
                    second year. That summer one of the students in the previous seminar, Jim
                    Purcell, a very senior Civil Service officer in the Department, was assigned to
                    assist me in coming up with an entirely new curriculum. We went to the Army War
                    College, the National War College, the Federal Executive Institute, the Kennedy
                    School of Government, and to business training programs and looked at what they
                    were doing in terms of executive training. We basically threw out the old
                    curriculum and redesigned it from scratch, with a focus on leadership. We even
                    put in ropes courses.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's the ropes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: It's a leadership training and teambuilding technique where you learn
                    through physical exercises involving ropes and obstacles. Another element I put
                    in was wellness. I had a professional trainer come in to do a fitness program
                    and nutrition counseling. We had MED do cholesterol tests. The students were all
                    forty-ish people who were getting to the age where you can have heart attacks,
                    and you need to take care of yourself. That's a fundamental element of good
                    leadership. You can't do much unless you're healthy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying you got rid of the papers and put in
                        projects.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The projects could be an activity, for example working on Capitol
                    Hill in a Senator's officer for a month. Visiting and studying conservation in a
                    national park. Working with a police department on security. Working in state or
                    local government. The students had a whole month to do a project they picked.
                    Then they would do a report and the group discussed it. I also put in an element
                    of community service during the week of Thanksgiving. Instead of just studying
                    about poverty, with some experts to come in to talk about it, I sent all the
                    students out to work in a homeless shelter or a soup kitchen for a week, or some
                    similar activity, and then come back and discuss the experience. We stressed
                    experiential learning as opposed to academic learning. We continued the field
                    trips, which I thought were very good. But just about everything else was
                    dramatically changed. It worked out well, everybody liked it. I also had the
                    students design most of the curriculum. I designed the program for the first
                    month, while the students got together in committees to decide what the seminar
                    was going to study for the next eight months. Whether we're going to study X
                    instead of Y, whether we're going to place A or place B, they decided. When the
                    students decide, they take ownership of the decision. It's much more effective
                    than just directing them to do this or that. Particularly at the senior level,
                    when you have people with lots of experience who know what they need and want to
                    learn, it's much better to let them decide rather than for anyone to tell them
                    what they're going to do. That worked very well. As I understand it, the
                    curriculum has evolved, but it is basically that kind of curriculum that is
                    still in place in the Senior Seminar.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excellent. Well then by this time we moved up to '89 I
                        guess.What happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: The Department told me I was no longer needed, at the age of 48.
                    While I was Ambassador I had been promoted to Minister-Counselor. At that time
                    you had three years to be promoted from Minister-Counselor to Career Minister or
                    be 'selected out,' (the euphemism then in use); or you could be given what was
                    called a 'limited career extension.'</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now did you think you'd aroused animosity by saying 'why
                        don'you close' this type... I mean you weren't a team player.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I was not beloved in the Africa Bureau I guess, which by that time
                    was my home bureau. Training assignments then, and I expect even now (although
                    Colin Powell's doing his best to change it), were not career enhancing
                    assignments. So even though I'd done, I think, an unusually important job in
                    changing the Senior Seminar so fundamentally, and that was recognized at FSI, it
                    was not recognized anywhere else in the Department. Training has long been
                    regarded by the Foreign Service as where you shuffle people off when you've got
                    nothing better for them to do. So I didn't get much recognition for the Senior
                    Seminar job. I was not even offered a limited career extension, and I was
                    forcibly retired at the ripe old age of 48.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good god. Now when does that, what did that do, that
                        really huryour pension didn't it, or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: No. I had twenty-seven years of service. I came in right out of
                    college, when I was barely 22. So I managed to get in almost 27 years of
                    service; but still, forty-eight is too young to be put out to pasture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, sort of going to pasture, what did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: I got a job as Director of International Affairs for the city of
                    Dallas, which turned out to be a good job. In terms of money it was great, since
                    they were paying me about what I had been making as an FSO, plus I was drawing a
                    Foreign Service pension. This was a job that the mayor and the business
                    leadership had created to try to internationalize Dallas, the better to compete
                    with the likes of Atlanta and Houston. It was a bit like a municipal foreign
                    ministry, if you can imagine such. I was among other things chief of protocol
                    for the city, welcoming foreign guests and arranging the mayor's foreign trips.
                    We made several trips to Russia, Israel, Mexico, Europe. The mayor at the time
                    was Annette Strauss, the sister-in-law of Bob Strauss, the Democratic Party
                    power broker and former U.S. Trade Commissioner. She was a wonderful lady to
                    work for, and we I got along well. I was also working with the business
                    leadership of the city, the oil money, and others in the Dallas establishment.
                    Texas Instruments, Halliburton, J. C. Penney, Exxon-Mobil, all those big
                    companies. We were trying to promote international trade, attract foreign
                    investment and do the things necessary to attract it. For example, we worked
                    with a French lady to start a French school in Dallas, with French government
                    support, so that Europeans coming to Dallas could have an alternative to the
                    American school system. We facilitated cultural exchanges, assisted sister
                    cities groups, worked with the local consular corps, tried to get countries to
                    open new consulates in Dallas. I also got involved with NAFTA, which was being
                    negotiated at the time. We wanted to position Dallas as a lead player in NAFTA.
                    I went to Washington along with the President of the Chamber of Commerce, and we
                    persuaded the U.S. trade negotiators to bring one of the main NAFTA negotiating
                    sessions to Dallas. Eventually they put one of the organizations created by
                    NAFTA in Dallas. This was an excellent job for a retired FSO.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did that from...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: From '89 to '93. In '92 there was an election and a new mayor came in
                    replacing Annette. He didn't focus on international affairs the way she had. We
                    got along fine, but he just wasn't very interested in international activities.
                    Also a new city manager came in who also was not internationally inclined. At
                    the same time a friend who had been the Senior Vice President of the Federal
                    Reserve Bank in Dallas, whom I'd worked with on several projects, retired from
                    the FED to become Dean of the College of Business and Public Administration at
                    Old Dominion University in Norfolk. He called and asked if I would be interested
                    in applying for a job he was creating there, directing a center for global
                    business in the college. Norfolk being a seaport, with the biggest navy base in
                    the world, having that kind of organization in the principal university in the
                    city seemed to make sense. I'd always wanted to work in a University, teach a
                    course or two and do international activities. I thought this was a great
                    opportunity, so I went to Norfolk. Unfortunately, the Dean, between the time he
                    recruited me and the time I got there, had a fight with the faculty about
                    creating new international programs, and they finally rose up against him.
                    University faculties, I soon discovered, are the most conservative lot of people
                    in the world. Not in the political sense (they're mostly left-wing), but in
                    resistance to change. They eventually forced the Dean to resign. He submitted
                    his resignation the same week I arrived, and that left me hanging in the breeze,
                    a creature that this Dean had brought in for a job the faculty was all against.
                    That was an uncomfortable position. The Dean stayed on through the next academic
                    year, because things move so slowly in academia that they didn't recruit a new
                    Dean for another year. To find something for me to do, he said, “We have this
                    continuing education unit in the College that's been losing money, and we're
                    going to fire its director. If you take over that unit and make it
                    self-sufficient financially, then the faculty can't get rid of you.” By that
                    time I'd sold our house in Dallas, bought a new house in Norfolk, moved the
                    family and all we owned, so there wasn't much choice but to make the best of it.
                    I changed the existing continuing education unit into the Center for Global
                    Business and Executive Education and tried to make a go of it. Eventually I was
                    able to turn it around from a money-losing operation to profitability, mainly
                    because I got a big contract with the Navy Exchange Service, headquartered in
                    Virginia Beach, to do leadership training for their senior executives. I'd been
                    doing leadership training in the Senior Seminar, so I had an appropriate
                    background and credentials. This was a 1.6 million dollar contract over six
                    years. Before that, this unit's highest gross was something like a hundred
                    thousand dollars a year, and it was losing forty or fifty thousand. We went from
                    that level to about a five hundred thousand dollar a year gross on which we were
                    making a hundred thousand dollar profit. With that they couldn't fire me, and I
                    stayed on there for seven years running this Center for Global Business and
                    Executive Education. We provided all sorts of leadership and business-related
                    training for both private and public sector customers, including the Navy. I was
                    also doing a lot of international things, not in the university but in the
                    community. I wrote for the local newspaper, gave talks on international affairs,
                    and was active in the World Affairs Council. I also became a Senior Fellow at
                    the Joint Forces Staff College in Norfolk, and helped with some of their
                    training exercises and war games. But the ODU faculty never would let me
                    participate in the academic side of the university. In seven years I was never
                    once invited to visit a class, or make a talk. As a former Ambassador with lots
                    of international experience, I felt I had something worthwhile to contribute,
                    but they would not let me near the academic program.</p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>Q: Well, it's a guild. I'm finding the same thing with this oral history program,
                    obviously this is of great benefit to the academics, but almost, I haven't heard
                    a word of encouragement.</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: Oh, they're not interested; they're just not interested.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They'll be feeding off this for another couple of
                        centuries, but...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: To my astonishment, I discovered that even though this was the
                    College of Business and Public Administration, most of the faculty didn't know
                    much about the practical side of business or government. Their top priority and
                    value was writing academic papers to be read by other professors. No businessman
                    or government official in his right mind would waste time with such trivia. I
                    decided that if this College were a business it would be bankrupt and if it were
                    a government it would be overthrown. Yet it was a college of business and public
                    administration, training people for practical work. Needless to say, I didn't
                    get along very well with the faculty. I was glad to get out of there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, just a brief thing on the last part of your career.
                        You'rdirecting Peace Corps in Niger? How did that come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: After a few years of growth at the Center I was running, I was able
                    to hire a deputy. He was a splendid salesman, did a great job, got new business,
                    and we were growing even faster. But a student accused him of sexual harassment.
                    I didn't know whether he was guilty or not. He made a strong case to me that he
                    wasn't. For some reason the President of the University got involved. I told him
                    'If the guy's guilty, have a hearing, do whatever's necessary to demonstrate
                    that, and fire him.' However, the President said 'No, sexual harassment is too
                    hard to prove, and we can't fire him for that. We want you to fire him for
                    incompetence.' I said 'He's not incompetent; he's done a great job.' I refused
                    to do what the President asked. His response was 'Well, we'll fire you too.' And
                    they did. Thus I was suddenly looking for a job. Peace Corps is something I had
                    long thought about. I graduated from college in '62. That was the heyday of
                    Peace Corps, which was created by President Kennedy in '61. I had decided to
                    become a volunteer when I graduated, but to my surprise I passed the Foreign
                    Service exam and became an FSO instead. As I was assessing job possibilities
                    after being fired from the university, I recalled that the current Deputy
                    Director of the Peace Corps, Chuck Baquet, had been one of my Senior Seminar
                    students. After the Seminar he had become an Ambassador and then was assigned as
                    Deputy Director of the Peace Corps. I contacted Chuck, and he encouraged me to
                    apply for a Country Director position. I was able to get the job in spite of the
                    fact that there is a great deal of suspicion of Foreign Service Officers (and
                    particularly Ambassadors) on the part of most Peace Corps staff. They don't want
                    anything hinting at a close connection between the Peace Corps and the State
                    Department. But I was able to convince them, with Chuck's help, to give me the
                    job of Country Director in Niger. I've been there for two years and I've enjoyed
                    it immensely. I've done a lot of what I'd hoped to do at the university in terms
                    of working with young people. It's been a great experience.</p>
                <p>Q: What is the Peace Corps doing in Niger?</p>
                <p>BULLINGTON: We have about a hundred volunteers now, and we're going to expand the
                    program in consonance with the President's initiative to double the size of
                    Peace Corps over the next five years. We're going to add a new sector and go up
                    to about a hundred and thirty-five volunteers over the next two years. The
                    volunteers currently are in agriculture, environmental protection, and public
                    health, and we're going to add an education sector. They are some really
                    outstanding young Americans, and I'm proud to be their leader.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And how do you find your work with the Embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                <p>BULLINGTON: There's no problem. Having had some experience in Embassies and
                    having been an Ambassador, I feel pretty much at home, certainly not
                    intimidated. After overcoming some initial suspicion by Peace Corps staff, I've
                    had no problem with the cultural gap between the State Department and Peace
                    Corps. In my view it's a hangover from the culture wars of the '60s and '70s,
                    which should have been put aside long ago, but unfortunately has not been. I've
                    done my best to bridge that gap, at least in Niger. I think I've been successful
                    there, and maybe to a much smaller extent in Peace Corps generally. As far as I
                    know, I'm the only former Ambassador ever to have served as a Country Director
                    in Peace Corps.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, great! Well, Jim, I guess this has come to an end.
                        Thiis great. I thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
