<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000879">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Dan Oleksiw </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Information Series</p>
                <p>DAN OLEKSIW</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Hans N. Tuch </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: February 8, 1989</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good morning. This is Hans Tuch interviewing Dan Oleksiw
                        in Bethesda, Maryland on February 8, 1989.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Good morning, Dan.</p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Good morning, Tom.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dan Oleksiw was born in 1921 in Wilkes-Barre,
                        Pennsylvania. He is currently the director for marketing of the Washington
                        Export Information, Incorporated, a private consulting firm.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I am interviewing Dan this morning about part of his career in the foreign
                    service, in USIA. He retired from USIA in 1978, having spent the last five years
                    in his USIA career as thechief inspector of USIA.</p>
                <p>He spent over thirty years in government service, most of it in USIA. How many
                    years? When did you start in USIA?</p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Forty — well, before USIA?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, in the State Department.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Nineteen forty-nine.</p>
                <p>1966 - '70: Period as Assistant Director, USIA, Far East</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of his most significant and, as far as I'm concerned,
                        most interesting assignments in USIA was as the assistant director of USIA
                        for the Far East, which is now called the Pacific area, during a very
                        important period in our history, namely between 1966 and '70, during the
                        Vietnam war.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I would think it is particularly useful for this oral history project to talk
                    about your experiences, your impressions, your recollections of that period in
                    your career in USIA.</p>
                <p>Now, you were assistant director, you became assistant director for the Far East
                    area in 1966, just at a time when we were expanding our involvement in
                    Vietnam.</p>
                <p>Let me ask you: who appointed you? Why were you appointed director for that area?
                    What were your initial responsibilities, or what was your particular mission in
                    that job?</p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Leonard Marks appointed me as area director in '66. I asked him why he
                    appointed me when he did, or when he talked to me about taking on the job,
                    because at that time I had never been west of California or east of
                    Calcutta.</p>
                <p>I had served in Turkey, Egypt, Iran and India. That was the part of the world
                    that I knew something about. I knew something about Africa because I had been
                    program coordinator and, for a while, deputy to Ned Roberts in Africa. I knew
                    very little, if anything, about the Far East.</p>
                <p>Mr. Marks said very nice things about why he wanted me to be the area director.
                    Frankly, I think that he just couldn't find anybody else available at the time
                    to take the job.I went into the job with a good deal of question about my own
                    qualifications for it. I tried to do it with a great deal of humility. I was
                    somewhat intimidated by some of the great Far East hands who were PAOs in the
                    area at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Barry Zorthian was already there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Barry Zorthian was director of JUSPAO at the time.</p>
                <p>To focus on Vietnam, which you've asked me to do, I think we now have the benefit
                    of — the usual benefit of hindsight.</p>
                <p>Oleksiw Views on, and Questions About, USIA's Actions in and Commitment to
                    Vietnam</p>
                <p>My views on Vietnam now — USIA and Vietnam — my views on Vietnam now may be a
                    little bit different than they were while I had the responsibility for the area,
                    but not all that different, if I recollect properly.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>One of the questions I asked myself in preparation for coming to talk to you
                    today, and which I used to ask myself when I was area director and dealing with
                    Barry Zorthian, Ed Nickel and the other people who were responsible for Vietnam
                    —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And of course the director of the Agency.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: — and the director of the Agency. The directors of the Agency, because I
                    worked under — on Vietnam specifically I worked under Leonard Marks and Frank
                    Shakespeare.</p>
                <p>The question that I asked myself then, but more in the last few days, in
                    anticipation of coming here for this interview, was: What did we accomplish,
                    what did USIA accomplish in Vietnam?</p>
                <p>I try to simplify the question without being simplistic by asking: What was USIA
                    supposed to accomplish in Vietnam?</p>
                <p>When I became inspector for the Agency, I used to try to differentiate, in
                    looking at our programs, differentiate between effort and accomplishment.
                    Without denigrating effort, I felt that what really counted was the
                    accomplishment. Obviously, the effort is essential in order to get to the
                    accomplishment.</p>
                <p>In Vietnam we saw a great deal of effort, very commendable effort, many times
                    courageous effort, effort under very difficult conditions.</p>
                <p>To try to measure accomplishment was very, very hard. Measuring accomplishment in
                    areas which are not terribly tangible is difficult.</p>
                <p>When people cannot demonstrate accomplishment, and they know that they are being
                    measured, compensated, promoted, advanced, reassigned on the basis of their
                    reputation in an assignment, when they can't demonstrate accomplishment
                    adequately, they're very busy demonstrating effort. That's translated into
                    activity very often.</p>
                <p>I would not denigrate in any way the effort of our programs — plural, programs —
                    in Vietnam. People who were undertaking them, from the directors of JUSPAO down
                    to the most junior people on the staff, most of them, almost all of them, were
                    working with a great deal of sincerity in trying to accomplish what they thought
                    was in line with the responsibility that was thrust on them.</p>
                <p>At least in those days, that is the perception that the leadership in Washington
                    reflected, that this was a responsibility thrust on the Agency.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>I've often tried to figure this out. I try to question this: Did we seek that
                    responsibility, that role, which came during Carl Rowan's directorship? Did we
                    seek it or was it imposed on us?</p>
                <p>I get various believable answers, contradictory but believable answers from
                    different people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your predecessor as assistant director?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Dan Moore. In the original days it was, in the days of the establishment
                    of JUSPAO, Ken Bunce.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was the reflective scholar type of person; and his
                        expertise, especially in regard to Japan, was based on his deep knowledge
                        and experience in that particular area, rather than being an activist in the
                        field of public diplomacy.Am I correct in my judgment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Yes, if you mean that without in any way minimizing his abilities in the
                    field.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: He had a very responsible position in General MacArthur's staff as the
                    religious advisor. He had a great deal of experience, and he had post
                    experience. He had been PAO in India.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And PAO in Japan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: And Korea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As far as I am concerned, one of the heroes of USIA. He
                        was not, by inclination, as others have been, a sort of gung-ho person who
                        would, because an administration felt we ought to get involved, just go in
                        blindly and say, “This is what we're going to do.” He was a person who would
                        have to be convinced that what we were doing was the right thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Yes, I want to agree with that. I would agree with that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm sorry. I interrupted. We were talking about whether
                        this mission in Vietnam was thrust upon us, or whether we actually sought
                        it.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>That was during the period 1964 - '65, when Carl Rowan was the director of USIA.
                    It's something that one would have to explore with him some day.</p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about Leonard, Leonard Marks? What about his view on
                        this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Mr. Marks was, in my judgment, an honest pragmatist; I thought, a very
                    logical conduit for policy and operational requirements that we received from
                    the White House, and policy guidance from the State Department.</p>
                <p>He was a terrific administrator and had the benefit of having Howard Chernoff at
                    his elbow during those years.</p>
                <p>I have this impression, and I think it is based on a lot of conversations that we
                    had on the subject.</p>
                <p>I believe that he was concerned that we were over committed in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>The expense of JUSPAO, in dollars and in people — because there were finite
                    resources available to the Agency — was at the risk of jeopardizing other very
                    important programs.</p>
                <p>Working in that area during the Vietnam years reminded me somewhat of earlier
                    days in Africa when Africa got very high priority at the expense of other
                    posts.</p>
                <p>Judgments on Accomplishments Compared to Goals in Vietnam</p>
                <p>My original, my question: What did we accomplish in Vietnam? To ponder the
                    question, the argument could be made that, by the end, the resources that we put
                    into JUSPAO, the people who worked in Vietnam for all those years, that we did
                    not accomplish what we set out to accomplish. This is a very sad thing to have
                    to reflect after all that investment of people, money and energy.</p>
                <p>Stated against the question of what did the United States accomplish in Vietnam,
                    that may not be such a devastating judgment if that judgment is correct. It's
                    especially hard to address people who worked in Vietnam, who did so with such
                    great dedication and great enthusiasm and sacrifice. Maybe that was one of the
                    problems, that people tend to get intoxicated by their own enthusiasm.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any discussion in depth here in Washington at
                        the time in the leadership of the Agency, among the leadership of the
                        Agency, evaluating our tremendous investment?It was an unprecedented
                        investment in manpower and materials that we made in Vietnam at the time,
                        especially in comparison to what we were doing in the rest of the world, and
                        we had other priority areas: Eastern Europe, the Soviet Union, you had
                        mentioned Africa during the '60s.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Discussions at Agency Headquarters Re Value of USIA Role in Vietnam: Marks and
                    Shakespeare</p>
                <p>Was there any major discussion, at that time, is this worthwhile? Is this what we
                    should be doing, or is this really beyond our capabilities, or is this not the
                    mission that USIA ought to fulfill?</p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Yes, very much so, led by Leonard Marks and later by Frank
                    Shakespeare.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Certainly!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Frank Shakespeare, too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Oh, yes, very thoughtfully!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because I thought he was just so involved in doing it that
                        the question of why and whether didn't arise. I may be wrong. I'd like to
                        hear you —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Yes, that would be wrong. I recall — and I think this can be
                    demonstrated by a search of the records. I would say that Leonard Marks was
                    interested in maintaining the level and containing the level of our involvement
                    in Vietnam, which was a very great involvement.</p>
                <p>Ten percent of our foreign service employees were in Vietnam at any given
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was in 1966 already?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: From '66 through '70 at least. We built up very quickly. I refer you to
                    the records. It was in 1966. It was a hundred and thirty plus. I'm talking about
                    American job slots, not money. The money was easier to come by in those days
                    than people.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Ten percent of our foreign service personnel were in Vietnam, one
                    hundred and thirty-some out of thirteen hundred-some American foreign service
                    people.</p>
                <p>My instructions from Leonard Marks were that this level reflected the
                    instructions and guidances that the Agency then had from the White House,
                    President Johnson's White House, and policy guidances from the State
                    Department.</p>
                <p>But Leonard Marks also believed that we — at least, this is my reading of his
                    belief — that we should not at that time get more deeply involved in
                    Vietnam.</p>
                <p>We were trying to limit, then, our involvement in Vietnam to carry out our
                    worldwide responsibilities. We just didn't have the human resources to do
                    more.</p>
                <p>By the time Frank Shakespeare became director we were definitely trying to cut
                    —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '68, right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Yes. We were trying to cut down our investment in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>Even before that, during Mr. Marks' leadership that had started already, and not
                    only Vietnam but related programs in Thailand where USIA found itself, as I used
                    to say to Lew Schmidt's chagrin, we were involved in everything from midwifery
                    to supporting the internal ministry of information programs in Thailand and in
                    Laos, because these were part of —</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were related, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Very, very, very closely related.</p>
                <p>Oleksiw Delineates What He Views as USIA's Role(s) in Vietnam</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how would you define, then, during that period, the
                        principal mission that was thrust upon us, or that we assumed in Vietnam
                        with all those resources, with all those people — how would you define what
                        we were supposed to accomplish there, or what we were supposed to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Leonard Marks inherited a complex and to some degree ambiguous role for
                    USIA. It was more than bifurcated; it was more than trifurcated. It was probably
                    quadrafurcated, or whatever the term is. Depending on what you're counting, we
                    had four roles.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>A. Influencing U.S. Opinion Re Vietnam Involvement</p>
                <p>One of the roles which I'll mention first is one that maybe is the most
                    questionable, and that is influencing U.S. public opinion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had the mission of influencing U.S. public
                        opinion?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: JUSPAO was implementing that mission. How we got the mission has always
                    been very fuzzy to me.</p>
                <p>It could be defended that technically the mission was the military's and that
                    JUSPAO, which was the Joint U.S.-Public Affairs Office, was directing or
                    “coordinating” the effort, but the cover was that the military was doing this.
                    Who could say that we did not have the mission or accept the mission of
                    influencing U.S. public opinion? By simply servicing the press that was covering
                    the war we impacted on public opinion everywhere, including the U.S.</p>
                <p>We definitely were, there's no question about it. We were trying to justify U.S.
                    policies and U.S. actions during a hectic time in this country.</p>
                <p>Of course, we were involved in informing the American public, and therefore,
                    inevitably, in influencing American public opinion about Vietnam. USIA was
                    deeply involved in that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is very interesting, particularly because perhaps for
                        the first time it really goes against both the legislation and tradition of
                        our Agency, namely, that we should not and would not be involved in any way
                        vis-a-vis the American public, but that our mission was always directed to
                        foreign publics, foreign public opinion and attitudes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>So this is one specific mission that you identified.</p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Yes, except that I would like to say this, too: that traditionally,
                    also, USIS posts had the press attaché function, the care and feeding of foreign
                    correspondents.</p>
                <p>American correspondents and others who came to a post, when they were writing and
                    reporting on what was happening in Country X, it had nothing to do with Vietnam,
                    whatever country, India, Germany or whatever.</p>
                <p>Inevitably, USIS was involved in helping them understand American policy toward
                    that country and American activities in that country. To differentiate between
                    justifying American policy and influencing American public opinion is impossible
                    under such operational situations.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>So I think that, although the legislation says, “You don't do it,” our
                    activities, if they didn't step over the line in other countries, they were
                    smudging that line. I believe that, frankly, they did step over the line of many
                    countries.</p>
                <p>(Pause.)</p>
                <p>Okay, your question was about USIA's role. I believe you have to dissect it.
                    There are a number of roles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned four. We've talked about the first.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Right, we've talked about the first one, which was servicing foreign
                    correspondents.</p>
                <p>The spokesman role in any embassy, in any USIS mission, exists, and I personally
                    see this as an unavoidable anomaly. In other words, sometimes we are really
                    serving U.S. correspondents who report to the U.S. public, but is that somewhat
                    out of the ordinary for us to do?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In other words, our focus is the foreign press.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Oh, yes, yes. Our focus is the foreign audience. In any, especially in
                    any large country, or any country that's in the news, USIS gets involved in
                    handling American and other foreign correspondents.</p>
                <p>When you're handling the American press, you obviously try to explain and justify
                    U.S. foreign policy. In doing so, you get involved in influencing American
                    opinion. Should we be ashamed to explain, justify an administration's policies
                    to a groping newsman?</p>
                <p>I've had to be as guilty of that as anybody. So I'm not sticking my finger in
                    somebody's eye in Vietnam, saying “You shouldn't have done this.” Because of the
                    nature of the coverage of the Vietnam war, the tormented interest in that war
                    and the number of correspondents there, the television aspects of it, we were
                    constantly and very deeply, deeply, deeply involved in that.</p>
                <p>Incidentally, insofar as they handled the press, when I say the foreign press
                    they were handling press from many countries, not just the American press. There
                    were correspondents from all over the world there. Through them JUSPAO informed
                    and clarified the war to millions in every corner of the globe.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>So it was a quite legitimate role, at the same time, quite a legitimate role for
                    JUSPAO to be facilitating the coverage by the press from every foreign country
                    where we had an interest in explaining American policies and the implementation
                    of American policies.</p>
                <p>One could not have done one without the other. So, insofar as it was right, let
                    us say, to try to set straight the record in Sweden, which was highly critical
                    of U.S. involvement in Vietnam, we couldn't have done that without also getting
                    involved with American coverage.</p>
                <p>B. Psychological Warfare Role</p>
                <p>Okay, we have the psychological warfare role, psy-warfare.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's the second role.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Well, I don't put them in any particular order. One is the foreign
                    press; two, the psy-warfare, which is not and certainly has not been a
                    traditional USIA or legislated USIA role.</p>
                <p>C. Addressing Population of South Vietnam</p>
                <p>The third role was addressing the population of South Vietnam. The traditional
                    USIA role, the information and cultural affairs role.</p>
                <p>Then related, perhaps, to psy-warfare, and to that traditional role, was our
                    involvement with the South Vietnamese ministry of information.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Their infrastructure?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: The infrastructure.</p>
                <p>D. And Explaining/Supporting the Activities of South Vietnam Government to Its
                    Own People</p>
                <p>Yes, explaining and defending the activities of the government of South Vietnam.
                    We were deeply involved in that, explaining it to the population of South
                    Vietnam and to the rest of the world, including the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were then two areas which were unique to USIA. One,
                        psychological warfare, the psychological warfare role, which we heretofore
                        had not been involved in —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: No, we had.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: We had, in Central America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, indeed, you're right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: One might question whether, because it wasn't all that many years before
                    that — in El Salvador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Precedents for USIA Involvement in Psy-War Activities</p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: There are precedents.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Limited, limited precedents.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Limited number of precedents?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean limit of involvement and intensity, right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: When I was in Iran as deputy PAO to Bob Payne and then Burnett Anderson,
                    USIS was very, very, very deeply involved in supporting the Shah through the
                    Iran Ministry of Information.</p>
                <p>We were deeply, deeply involved in a form of psychological warfare, working
                    hand-in-hand with the British, with the Baghdad Pact countries, with the secret
                    police of Iran.</p>
                <p>There are other examples of that around the world. But Vietnam was our greatest
                    ever involvement, both in intensity and in size, but there were other
                    examples.</p>
                <p>The one which could have led to activities in Vietnam was the Central American
                    experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, now you had these four central missions for which we
                        had responsibility.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>There was, at that time, as you said, a great increase in our activities to
                    fulfill the responsibility.</p>
                <p>Impact of Heavy Agency Resource Commitment in Vietnam on Other Agency
                    Programs</p>
                <p>How were you able to manage that within the overall USIA complex? Having ten
                    percent of our people there, having probably more than ten percent of our
                    resources involved in Vietnam, this must have been a tremendous burden on you as
                    the area director to implement that.</p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: It was a tremendous burden on the Agency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just to find the people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Just to find the people. We had the priorities and the authority to
                    draft which made it a lot easier for the area and for the program in
                    Vietnam.</p>
                <p>What impact it had on other programs can't be documented specifically, but PAOs
                    from all over the world and all the other area directors told me, of course,
                    that it had an operational impact on their programs, and everyone knew it had an
                    impact on morale in the Agency.</p>
                <p>My conviction is that most people in USIA who served in Vietnam would not have
                    chosen to serve in Vietnam — and I don't want this to mean that when they were
                    there, once they were assigned to Vietnam, and once they hit the deck there,
                    that they didn't work as hard as they possibly could, or work as well, as
                    imaginatively, as courageously. Most of them tried to fulfill the mission.</p>
                <p>And Impact on Families</p>
                <p>Some of them didn't want to leave their families. Remember that this was a time
                    when you left your family, either at home on the United States or at a safe
                    haven country, Thailand, the Philippines or whatever. It was wrenching.</p>
                <p>At one point the personnel officer for the area, in 1970 I think it was, told me
                    that we had had eighteen divorces, related to but not necessarily totally caused
                    by Vietnam.</p>
                <p>We had wives coming to see us, sometimes without their husbands' knowledge,
                    sometimes with their husbands' knowledge, telling us how assignment to Vietnam
                    would affect the marriage, how it would affect their children, who needed the
                    father's attention.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>It was difficult to handle. We did have a protocol for handling it. That was that
                    if there was, say, a psychological or psychiatric problem involving the family,
                    we asked the State Department doctors to evaluate this with the officer's own
                    family doctor. Obviously, we would listen to reason.</p>
                <p>Relationships with Officers in the Field</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me, how did the operational relationship work between
                        Washington, you as the area director, and the field PAOs? Was it smooth? Was
                        it a good relationship, or were there major policy and operational
                        differences between Washington and the field?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: From my standpoint, I thought that the relationship was amazingly
                    smooth, given the necessarily confrontational nature of the relationship when we
                    had to contain and reduce our involvement — necessarily confrontational because
                    there seemed to be some split loyalties in Saigon when the program was trying to
                    be responsive to the urgings of the ambassador and other people in the country
                    team — and the area was operating under policy interpretations as Washington saw
                    them.</p>
                <p>I say “amazingly smooth” in that Barry Zorthian and Ed Nickel never put poison in
                    my food when I visited them, and I visited them quite often.</p>
                <p>We argued a great deal about what was the proper level of program and the
                    character and degree of that involvement. They felt, with considerable
                    justification, that they weren't getting the support that they thought they
                    needed. I had to represent Washington's view, which was that here is the support
                    we were able to give, or that we thought was proper.</p>
                <p>When I say “we,” I wasn't speaking just for myself. I was speaking for Mr. Marks
                    and Mr. Shakespeare, and what White House judgments were regarding our
                    involvement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For the record, let me just interject. Barry Zorthian was
                        the head of JUSPAO, the public affairs officer in Vietnam until 1968 or
                        so.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Ed Nickel succeeded him as director of JUSPAO. Barry stayed on for a few
                    months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As the personal advisor —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: To Ambassador Bunker.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's very interesting that your difficulties in running a
                        program, in operating a post, very often really come down to personalities,
                        to the actual putting the right person in the right slot and convincing
                        others that you've made the right decision, and convincing the person that
                        you've made the right decision that he should or should not be in the
                        particular job. I mean, one spends a tremendous amount of time in personnel
                        matters when one manages an operation or manages a post. Do you agree with
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Yes, and related, considering the impact that Vietnam had on other area
                    directors and other posts seeking people to assign to their program when Vietnam
                    could pull the rug out from under almost any assignment in the Agency. This
                    happened repeatedly.</p>
                <p>Oleksiw Comments on Things He Might Have Done Better Re Vietnam</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dan, we've been talking about your experiences in relation
                        to Vietnam, and we may want to talk about something else, too. In conclusion
                        about Vietnam, do you find that you learned anything or that you had any
                        lessons that became clear to you after Vietnam that you think are
                        interesting or important or significant to mention here?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Yes. Let me mention a few things that have bothered me since Vietnam,
                    because these are things that I should have tried to do and we just didn't, or
                    didn't do them well enough.</p>
                <p>One is this, one of the problems that our people in Vietnam worked under was the
                    atmosphere that pervaded American society during those years.</p>
                <p>They were there working very hard, working loyally, but they were not persuaded
                    of the correctness of American policy and American actions toward the issue.</p>
                <p>Although all those I knew, all, as far as I knew, worked loyally and as well as
                    they could, as effectively as they could, obviously they would have worked more
                    effectively had they been persuaded that the American position was correct, that
                    American policy was correct, that American actions were correct.</p>
                <p>Where we had failed them, my area had failed them, was that we did not arrange
                    sufficient orientation before they went there. That's my fault.</p>
                <p>We should have spent more time on educating them about American policies and the
                    reasons for American policy, and persuading them that what we were doing was the
                    best that the administration could do at the time. We didn't do enough of
                    that.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>We spent a lot of time on teaching them the language. I question the value, the
                    little language that most of them learned before they went to Vietnam. Some
                    learned the language well and found it useful. Those who went through language
                    training, by and large, my judgment is that those whom I knew who talked to me
                    about it, they were not able to use the language effectively. It was not a good
                    investment in the case of many people.</p>
                <p>The other thing that I might bring to bear here is that I know that some of the
                    officers who served in Vietnam were, in a way, tainted by association with
                    Vietnam when they went on to other posts later.</p>
                <p>They found that having served in Vietnam could be an embarrassment in a future
                    post. They were considered by some of the people in the countries where they
                    went later as having been involved in non-USIA activities, which they were. Some
                    told me that they were suspect in the countries where they were involved.</p>
                <p>That's something to consider, especially if you look at what USIA officers really
                    were doing in Vietnam. This is the advantage of hindsight, but we're talking
                    about lessons for the future.</p>
                <p>Many of the positions held by USIA people in Vietnam could have been handled as
                    well, or better, by non-USIA people on a contract basis, and thereby not
                    disrupting our ranks and cutting the availability of our people for jobs
                    elsewhere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Field support people, especially. We had people in field support
                    positions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What does that mean? Again, for the record, field
                        support?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: Well, in a way, they were supply sergeants. They were sending things to
                    our field posts throughout Vietnam, everything from candy to be distributed to
                    children to prove to them that America loved Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Field support people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>OLEKSIW: That was one. People in the field, too, who were then supporting sign-up
                    operations and who were facilitating the travel of correspondents and who were
                    doing sign-up operations — it was a fairly simple nature.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>The direction had to be by experienced USIA officers, but the support could have
                    been — we could have, say, maybe a third of our positions in Vietnam that way. A
                    third would have been maybe forty-five positions.</p>
                <p>USIA Lessons to Be Learned from Vietnam Experience</p>
                <p>I guess the most important lesson that I came away with relates to supporting a
                    crisis situation of this sort — and it was a crisis situation. USIA comported
                    itself with dignity and professionalism in Vietnam, even though we can't measure
                    what we contributed to the overall effort, whose accomplishment I question, and
                    therefore I have to question the accomplishment of the Agency in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>If we get into another crisis situation of this sort, and it's predictable that
                    we can in the future, a very important component of the planning for our
                    participation in something of this sort has to be: How do we do it without doing
                    damage to other programs, especially other critical programs around the
                    world?</p>
                <p>Now, the obvious answer to that might be, well, of course we were trying to be
                    sure that we did not adversely affect critical programs in other parts of the
                    world.</p>
                <p>I think there are imaginative ways that ought to be considered in the future.
                    Indeed, that kind of planning can be done ahead of time, and bringing on some
                    contract people for short term would strike me as an obvious part of the
                    planning.</p>
                <p>When we think out loud about Vietnam during the four years that I had some
                    responsibility for supporting Ed Nickel and Barry Zorthian in various programs
                    there, I am not being critical of any individuals. Everybody worked there under
                    great difficulties, and many of them with considerable reluctance, and certainly
                    at a cost to their convenience and their safety and their family bliss. I admire
                    those who did it in good spirit.</p>
                <p>But looking toward the future, we ought to learn all the lessons we can from that
                    very costly experience.</p>
                <p>I thank you for giving me the opportunity to think out loud with you.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
