<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000849">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Beauveau B. Nalle </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>BEAUVEAU B. NALLE</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Thomas Dunnigan </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: April 19, 1994</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is Thomas Dunnigan and the date is April 19, 1994.
                        Today I will be talking with Beau Nalle on behalf of the Oral History
                        Program of the Foreign Service Institute. Mr. Nalle spent over 30 years in
                        the Foreign Service and served on 4 continents.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Let me begin by asking you Beau, how did you first get interested in a Foreign
                    Service career?</p>
                <p>NALLE: It was an evolutionary sort of thing. I had developed earlier an interest
                    in teaching when I was at the University of Virginia. I had wanted to be a
                    school teacher and had not found any particularly appealing openings in the
                    United States. I heard from a friend about the existence of the Near East
                    College Association which was the successor to the American Board of foreign
                    missions of the congregationalist church and through a complicated chain of
                    events, I ended up spending 3 years in Roberts College in Istanbul.</p>
                <p>Then somewhat to my surprise I was drafted, although I had served in the American
                    Field Service in 1945. In 1952 I was reclassified to 1-A, pulled into the army
                    and sent off to Arlington Hall station where I spent 2 years. Came out of the
                    army, had the GI bill and went to Johns Hopkins School of International Studies
                    here in Washington because at the time I was looking around for opportunities
                    other than school teaching. My years in Istanbul had awakened me to the world of
                    international affairs.</p>
                <p>I was recruited by a friend of mine at the CIA, to come and work for them. The
                    process took some 4 years from start to finish. But to sum it up, when I finally
                    took the Foreign Service exam and passed it and went for the orals, I had in my
                    pocket a letter from that agency offering me a job as a GS9. The letter made it
                    an awful lot easier to pass the Foreign Service oral exams. Both my wife and I
                    decided I would be more likely a success as a diplomat than as a spy. So I opted
                    for the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I note that not unnaturally your first post was Turkey,
                        were you pleased with that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>NALLE: Well, I should point out that actually my first assignment was Washington,
                    DC, where I spent 2 pretty awful years as one of the first 3 FSOs ever assigned
                    to the Office of Security. I was a Special Agent, or as we used to call
                    ourselves, a gunslinger.</p>
                <p>It was kind of funny, when the A-100 class ended we were all lined up; there was
                    no bidding system, there was no democracy. Max Krebs stood up in front of us and
                    said—You go here, you go there and don't argue, boy. In this case, one
                    woman.</p>
                <p>Along with Dick Morefield who subsequently was one of the hostages in Tehran, and
                    a very bright chap named Ed Walters, who resigned some years ago unfortunately,
                    we were sent to the Washington field office of the Office of Security. And I
                    spent a year investigating people. It was really pretty awful stuff.</p>
                <p>I had a badge, which was known in those days as a buzzer, and I would drive
                    around investigating FSOs, investigating elevator operators, investigating
                    political appointees, the whole bag. I still have authority from Secretary
                    Dulles to carry firearms whilst on duty! I guess my only real success was that I
                    investigated a man who was wanted by Secretary Dulles to be his Special
                    Assistant.</p>
                <p>I uncovered the fact that the guy was a fair going alcoholic and was drunk about
                    23 hours a day. It was pretty simple to do. You just had to go around and ask
                    people. The case was taken out of my hands, not as a security matter but as a
                    suitability matter. The man was not on for the job and I heard that Secretary
                    Dulles was livid. I thought it was all kind of funny.</p>
                <p>But it was also interesting because, this mind you was in 1956, we weren't that
                    far away from Senator McCarthy. It was an experience to me, a man who worked for
                    the old Henry Wallace-Glen Taylor Progressive Party in 1948, it was an
                    experience and a somewhat frightening experience. To see the way the whole
                    government of the United States quailed and quivered if somebody mentioned the
                    word “communist.”</p>
                <p>I had the pleasure of working for sometime with the infamous, or famous if you
                    will, Otto Otepka. Who in fact was a pretty decent guy.</p>
                <p>After a year of investigating I was then sent up to a little office that had
                    liaison with agencies within the United States that generated material of
                    interest to the State Department. That was primarily the FBI although we also
                    had liaison with local police agencies around the country. And our main interest
                    was the behavior of diplomats credited to the United States. And also of quote
                    “communist front” unquote organizations and publications.</p>
                <p>In order to keep an eye on the intellectuals of the country, we used to subscribe
                    to a lot of magazines like the New Republic and The Nation and other things
                    considered by my superiors to lean dangerously to the left. And we had a lot of
                    fun reading those as official business.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>We also were involved in the activities of the trade unions, the Greek trade
                    unions I remember, particularly the Greek Maritime trade unions, were considered
                    ready to blow up the Capitol.</p>
                <p>It was a pretty grim business. We all 3 of us one time went to Mr. E.T. Bailey,
                    the Director, a career FSO himself, new to the job and hating it as much as we
                    did. We said in effect, “Mr. Bailey we joined the Foreign Service to do foreign
                    service work and we find ourselves being as it were special agents, cops,
                    police. Were there any options?” Mr. Bailey looked up and said in a thin dry
                    voice, “Yes, you can quit.” Which was typical I think of the attitude of some of
                    those old folks. You did your job or you got out. You didn't fuss around too
                    much.</p>
                <p>So that was my first assignment and then as you said, because of my experience at
                    Roberts College, I was sent for a year's language training at the Institute. And
                    then to Iskenderun, Turkey with my wife and our 2 children.</p>
                <p>Iskenderun, also known as Alexandreta, is a post that we opened in the late
                    1930's, kept open during the war, closed it, then reopened it again, I don't
                    know what all. But anyway, I went there in the Summer of 1959. There was a
                    principal officer Malcolm Thompson and his wife, Marion; an American secretary,
                    Jonny Margaret Whitley; and myself and my wife Sheila and our two small
                    children, aged at that time about almost 3 years and about 2 years.</p>
                <p>It was a fascinating and awful experience. It was awful for my wife, as is
                    typical of the way the wives were treated in those days, and up until not more
                    than 5, 6 years ago I would say. We lived in an indescribably uncomfortable and
                    small little apartment in the same building as the office.</p>
                <p>The Consul lived directly over our head. He was a middle-aged man with no
                    children. The secretary lived across the airwell from us. She was an old time
                    secretary who had been in Iron Curtain posts and had been an Ambassador's
                    secretary at one time in her career. And wanted a little peace and quiet where
                    she could drink scotch and coke to her heart's content. And our two children
                    were like other children, they'd fuss and they'd carry on, their cries could be
                    heard throughout the building. Sheila was mortified and was angry.</p>
                <p>There was little or no electricity in the building. Water was sporadic and an
                    open sewer ran by the front door.</p>
                <p>Sheila had not one single minute of Turkish language training. There were none I
                    suppose in Iskenderun, less than 10 people who could speak English. One of the
                    tragic memories of my life was seeing Sheila sitting on an overstuffed ottoman
                    talking to the wives of Turkish generals and business people who couldn't speak
                    English. It was a terrible experience for her. And I think embittered her
                    towards the Foreign Service for the rest of my career.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do, what was the real work in the
                        office?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: We had a huge consular district that extended all the way east to the
                    Iranian border, the Iraq border and the Syrian border. Most of it was off
                    limits. The Embassy contended that since the Turks gave us all exequaturs for
                    those provinces, we were allowed to go there. The Turks said we had to ask
                    permission first. The Embassy said, “We don't ask permission.”</p>
                <p>And so the Consul, Mac Thompson, and I would each take a long swing through the
                    consular district. He would usually go in the spring, and I would go in the
                    autumn. We'd be gone for about 2 weeks. We tried to visit every province except
                    Hakkari, we agreed to the sensitivity of that. The problem was of course the
                    Kurdish problem. The Kurdish problem then was no different from what it is
                    today.</p>
                <p>I, at least twice, was shot at and in each case I assume it was by Kurds. And in
                    one case, they hit the old green jeep station wagon we had, and I drove home
                    cheerfully with a bullet hole in the rear end of the car. There was that.</p>
                <p>There was a very interesting group of U.S. social security recipients who lived
                    up the mountains. We had to take care of them, getting them their social
                    security checks once a month, there were about 150 of them. We distributed a lot
                    of money out there through social security. There was modest American
                    investment.</p>
                <p>There was in the city of Izmir a U.S. army transportation corps port detachment,
                    2 officers and 3 or 4 enlisted people. And in the city of Adana, some 110 miles
                    away, there was the famous Incirlik air force base.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excuse me, you talked about Izmir, did you mean Izmir or
                        Iskenderun?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Iskenderun, I'm sorry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I just wanted to straighten it out because I know there's
                        quite a distance.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: There is indeed.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>About 100 miles from Iskenderun there was the famous Incirlik air force base
                    which made history as the take-off place for Francis Gary Powers. I knew Powers
                    reasonably well, had a lot of dealings with him. And was amused. One time he
                    came to me, (I used to go up to the base once a week to do consular services)
                    and wanted his passport renewed. It was a Department of the Air Force civilian
                    special passport. I said, “Well, Mr. Powers I'm sorry, we don't normally renew
                    passports until a couple of weeks before they're due to expire.” I said, “But
                    look, you get me a letter from your supervisor asking for early retirement and
                    I'll be more than happy to do it.” He said, “No sweat.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not early retirement.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Early renewal. He said, “No sweat.” And I went back the next week and
                    there he was with his letter. It was addressed to—Beau Nalle, Vice Consul;
                    Subject-Powers, Francis Gary; social security number so-and-so; Passport-Early
                    Renewal of, Request For—that kind of army/air force talk.</p>
                <p>The body of the letter said—”It is requested that the passport number so-and-so
                    of Francis Gary Powers be renewed early since Mr. Powers frequently travels in
                    areas of the world where U.S. consular services are not readily available.” And
                    about a month later when he was shot down, I thought to myself, yes sir-ee
                    there's no consular office in Central Russia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How true, how true.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Actually I was on the base the day that the bird had been shot down. It
                    was pretty exciting. You used to see, what do they call them? The thing he'd
                    flown?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The U-2.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: The U-2. You used to see those things flying around Iskenderun quite
                    often.</p>
                <p>They had sort of 3 different cover stories. The first one was, what airplane? We
                    never saw anything. The second cover story was, yeah, it's a special high
                    altitude research plane that we're using for weather reconnaissance.</p>
                <p>The third one, if you had every clearance known to man and a few more, they would
                    admit that what the thing used to do was to fly up along the Russian border, but
                    still well within Turkey's airspace, analyzing Russian ground to air defenses
                    and what they call “quick alert reaction” or “quick reaction alert.” To see how
                    long it would take to scramble the Russian air force when a hostile aircraft
                    flew into radar view.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>The original story they handed out was that the airplane crashed inside Turkey.
                    And I told the guy who was my contact up there, the Deputy Commander, that both
                    the consul and I knew that area intimately. We traveled there a great deal, we
                    knew the governors, we knew the police officials, and if we could do anything by
                    going out on the spot, we'd be very happy to do so. But it all came out in the
                    mail, in the laundry, so to speak. We never did anything more.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can I write that after several years in Iskenderun you
                        were transferred to Ankara?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Yeah I went up to Ankara as acting head of the Consular section for 3 or 4
                    months while the incumbent was on home leave. And then I went into the
                    Political/Military section, working for Bill Dale who was Counselor. That was a
                    wonderful embassy in those days.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador was one of the very few heroes that I look at in the Foreign
                    Service, the late Ambassador Raymond Hare, a man of enormous ability, a man of
                    enormous integrity and decency and skill and everything else that he ought to
                    be. I rank him right along with Loy Henderson and perhaps even a little bit
                    ahead of Henderson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What particular issues did you deal with there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I got all of the scraps that fell off the table. Bill Dale spent most of
                    his time on very heavy serious matters, Turkish-American political/military
                    affairs. Anything that he didn't do I kind of did.</p>
                <p>I had to negotiate or help negotiate a labor agreement between the Turkish trade
                    union that worked on the bases and the Tumpane Company. Tumpane was based out of
                    Ohio and looked upon trade unions as something only less dangerous than perhaps
                    Aids. The Turkish unions were just starting to get fairly antsy and, as it were,
                    militant. And the negotiation was kind of interesting. One of the sticky points
                    was—what do you do with the bacon fat left over from the grill at the Officers
                    Club and the Enlisted Men's Club. That took us a couple of days to arrange.</p>
                <p>What other things did I do? We got involved in a case when a couple of young kids
                    got drunk. To put it bluntly, carved up a Turkish whore with a butcher knife and
                    nearly killed her. And took off across the Anatolian plateau in the middle of
                    August with the temperature over 100 degrees, trying to go to Syria. We caught
                    them, or the Turks caught them. We, very properly, would not issue a duty
                    certificate although some felt it would have been appropriate!</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>So they went into a Turkish jail and eventually we got a letter from the Senator
                    of their home state. Ambassador Hare brought it down to me and said, “Give me a
                    draft reply.” I said, “Fine, Mr. Ambassador, how do you want to handle it?” He
                    said, “Tell them the truth, be short, be blunt.” And I said to him, “Well Sir,
                    I've just gotten from OSI some photographs of the woman taken after these guys
                    did their trick on her. Would it be useful to send them along?” And he said,
                    “Yeah, it's a great idea.”</p>
                <p>The letter from the Senator was talking about these fine young American boys and
                    how they're being subjected to brutal Turkish torture and one thing or another.
                    So we replied and the Ambassador sent the letter. We never heard another word
                    from that Senator. I tell you, sending the photographs did the job.</p>
                <p>Another time, one of the major news magazines had a stringer in Beirut who was
                    not an American citizen, he was Lebanese. He was driving through Turkey on his
                    way to Paris, was in an automobile accident and killed a Turk, and was in jail.
                    We were aware of it. The man was not an American citizen, he was an employee of
                    a news magazine but there was nothing we saw that we could do. And it kind of
                    bounced around between political/military and consular section.</p>
                <p>Finally the Paris Bureau Chief came to Ankara, had an interview with the
                    Ambassador and I was asked to sit in as a note-taker. And the man first of all
                    got a briefing from the Ambassador as to the status of the case, then wondered
                    if the Ambassador had talked to the Minister of Justice. And the Ambassador
                    said—no, he hadn't, furthermore, he didn't see really why he had any right to
                    talk to the Minister of Justice on a matter like this. The Bureau Chief had
                    trouble accepting that fact. And then he asked the Ambassador, somewhat
                    obliquely, if he had any funds available for taking care of judges. And the
                    Ambassador said very tartly, that he didn't do business that way, nor did the US
                    government. Finally the guy said, “Well Mr. Ambassador, I should tell you my
                    magazine has a very wide circulation in Washington. And I would hate to see
                    anything unfavorable towards you or your Embassy appear in the pages.” Then the
                    Ambassador stood up, looked at me and said, “Mr. Nalle, would you show this
                    gentleman downstairs please.”</p>
                <p>He was livid. His little moustache was sticking out like this, his eyes were
                    sparkling. He would have physically assaulted the man in another minute, I
                    think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't very diplomatic of our “friend.” Now, those were
                        the years, were they not, of great unrest in Turkey? The overthrow of the
                        Menderes government as I recall?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>NALLE: Well, yes indeed there were. In fact that happened when I was still in
                    Iskenderun. But yes, there was enormous turmoil then. The army stepped in.
                    Menderes was hanged along with Zorlu and 2 other members of the Cabinet. I think
                    there were a total of 4 people hanged. There were various military interventions
                    and various efforts at intervention.</p>
                <p>We had found a little house, there was no government furnished housing in those
                    days. So we had a kind of grubby little house not too far away from the embassy.
                    I used to walk to work everyday. Come home for lunch, walk home from lunch, if I
                    wasn't doing something else.</p>
                <p>One morning, quite early, we heard a jet flying very low over the house. Sheila
                    kind of jumped over the bed and said, “My God, it's the revolution!” I said,
                    “No, it's just Pan American flight 3 coming in early.” Because the airport
                    wasn't that far away. Well they kept flying back and forth and I realized that
                    something was wrong. So I got up, got dressed and walked down to the
                    embassy.</p>
                <p>That was the Talat Aydemir revolt. And that's the one and only time that I've
                    ever taken live fire from the Turkish air force. We were out front of the
                    embassy and the Swiss Military Attach� came by. I'd never seen a Swiss officer
                    in dress uniform, a pretty impressive sight. And then a column of troops went by
                    and the Assistant Army Attach� asked me if I would walk along with him and
                    interpret while he talked to the troop commander. I said, sure. And these were
                    loyal to the government, they're the presidential bodyguards.</p>
                <p>Then we walked down, if you know Ankara, the embassy's not all that far away from
                    the Parliament and the offices of the general staff. So we walked down there and
                    the cadets from the military academy, the Harp Okulu, were trying to seize the
                    general staff headquarters, There was sporadic firing going on. And we were
                    marching along and suddenly one of the Turkish F81s or 85s, came in behind us
                    flying very low and cut loose with a couple of bursts of something-millimeter
                    cannon, I don't know what millimeter it was. But we could see the shots hitting
                    the ground. They were coming in short, they were aiming at the cadets but they
                    were coming in more directly at us and the troops.</p>
                <p>I'm a civilian! I'm not paid to get shot so I took off and ran. I've never run so
                    fast in my life. I jumped under a tank, which I'd noticed, it was lying there.
                    And behold, the Assistant Army Attach� was about 2 seconds behind me.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>Yeah, there was a lot of political stress in those days. It was very interesting
                    because through my work I got to know a great many of the senior Turkish army
                    officers. Ambassador Hare did not want us in the Political/Military section
                    mingling with non-NATO diplomatic personnel. He said that our work was not
                    understood by most of the NATO people, let alone the rest of the world. In
                    particular, he wanted us to have nothing to do with Soviet personnel. But he
                    encouraged us to make contact with Turkish military people and of course with
                    JUSMAT and TUSLOG, the 2 big US military organizations there.The drawback to the
                    job was that I had nothing to do with Turkish political affairs. Except
                    peripherally I might get material of interest. I was able to build up some
                    contacts with the Turkish Socialist Party.</p>
                <p>But our kids went to Turkish school. Indeed, we began to worry when our older
                    daughter came back from school one day and said, “Mommy, Daddy, you know next to
                    God I love Ataturk best.” This is when we decided we better put them in the
                    American military school.</p>
                <p>Another indication I forgot to mention in Iskenderun how things were. Our 2
                    little girls, little tiny things, 3 and 1 � year old, in 2 separate cases were
                    molested by a dirty old man who hung around the front of the office. We didn't
                    know about it until a couple of days later when the children mentioned it to
                    us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A Turk?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: In this case he was not a real Turk, he was one of the many minorities, he
                    was an Alawi. We complained to the police and the police chased the guy away but
                    he kept showing up again. It was one hell of an introduction. I found it utterly
                    fascinating but it put a strain on our marriage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this the period when Vice President Johnson came out
                        to Turkey?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Yes indeed it was. I suppose you've gotten stories of that but it was
                    funny. He wouldn't stay with the Ambassador. He wanted to get next to the
                    people. So we hired the top 3 floors of the best hotel in downtown Ankara. And
                    set-up a control room there that had to be staffed 24 hours a day by a Turkish
                    speaking language officer-an American, by one of the Marine security guards and
                    by a Secret Service special agent.</p>
                <p>Since we only had 4 or 5 Turkish speaking officers, we spent a lot of time in
                    that control room. There was Marty Polstein, there was myself (Marty's dead now,
                    a nice guy), Tom Metcalf who retired a good many years ago. Who else? George
                    Harris I think took his turn down there. I can't remember the other language
                    officers we had. One of the USIS chaps was a language officer.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>It was fun, it was interesting, it was an education to see how the mighty and the
                    omnipotent move around the world. The person we all fell in love with was Mrs.
                    Johnson. When the party left, the Vice President went down in the elevator, down
                    to his car and the word came in, “Spear,” that's his code word, “Spear had
                    departed.” We had the Gunny on duty and myself and a couple of other fellows.
                    The Gunny knocked the head off of a bottle of whiskey and we were all having a
                    drink.</p>
                <p>Suddenly the door opened and somebody walked in and we heard a voice saying, “I'd
                    like to thank you men.” And we turned around and there was Mrs. Johnson. She
                    walked around and shook hands with everyone. And said, “Now, you understand that
                    when the Vice President and I travel we're a tremendous burden for you people.
                    We make a mess and things get confused, it's your job to clean up after us.” But
                    she said, “I want to tell you how much we appreciate the way you do it, the way
                    you don't complain, you're always friendly and cheerful. We really genuinely
                    thank you.” Well, as they say, there wasn't a dry eye in the house.</p>
                <p>If she said, we make it bloody messy, we're sorry to bother you folks,
                    we'd—sigh—drop dead lady. But here she was, she said, we make a lot of trouble
                    and you guys clear it up. She was honest, she was candid, and she was utterly
                    charming. And if she had been running for President, every man in that room
                    would have voted for her. It was a brilliant performance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know, I feel the same way having met her later, she was
                        just wonderful.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: She picked up all the pieces.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One other question that I would like to ask you about
                        while we're talking about Turkey. Was Cyprus boiling at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Yes, very much so. I did not get involved in the Cyprus issue. It's a
                    matter of infinite complexity. But it was very much involved with us. We were
                    very much involved in it. It was handled by the Political Section, Charlie
                    Tanguy was the Cyprus specialist for the embassy. As I say, I was in no way
                    involved in the Cyprus problem.</p>
                <p>I was working at that time, do you remember the old multilateral force idea?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was doing that in Bonn.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>NALLE: They were going to put out missiles. They were going to take the Jupes,
                    the Jupiters out of Turkey. They were going to mount these things on a boat with
                    a multinational crew that would sail around the world. The problem existed—Who
                    is going to push the button? And we made it clear that no matter where the
                    missiles were, how multilateral the crew was, we would push the button. Well it
                    didn't get anywhere.</p>
                <p>I was also there for the Cuban missile crisis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wanted to ask you about that because as we know, the
                        administration proposed apparently to take our Jupiters out of Turkey in
                        exchange for the Soviets taking their missiles out of Cuba. How did that
                        play there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: That thing was frightening. It's the first time and one of the few times
                    in my life when I have felt real heart wrenching fear. There was something, it
                    may have been Kennedy's speech, it may have been some step we were going to
                    take. But because of the time difference, we knew about it before the actual
                    event took place in Washington.</p>
                <p>And I remember Bill Dale had briefed me on it even though it had such secret
                    security restrictions, you couldn't believe it. But he said, “There are only 2
                    people in the embassy right now who know about it, the Ambassador and me. I want
                    to brief you.” I guess he was being overly dramatic, I don't know. He said, “In
                    case something goes wrong, somebody else ought to know something about it.” Well
                    I thought that was a tad silly, I don't know. But anyway it was frightening.</p>
                <p>And I remember walking back to my house for lunch. It was a lovely day and there
                    were some birds singing, I'm a bird watcher by hobby. I remember just being
                    afraid that the war might begin, the first nuclear war might begin. It was a
                    terrible, terrible experience for me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the Turks take it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: The way they always do, in a business like manner. My memory tells me, God
                    this is a long time ago, but my memory clearly tells me that we had started
                    discussions with the government of Turkey prior to the Cuban business, about
                    withdrawing the Jupiter missiles. That there was no quid pro quo for the
                    Russians in this matter.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>The Jupiters were terribly old. I think it took them some 3 hours to get them
                    actually in the air from a cold start. And if they were in their intermediate
                    position it still took an hour to get them to fly. And you never could tell if
                    they were going to blow up on the pad or anything else. So I'm convinced that my
                    memory serves me right, we had entered into serious negotiations prior to the
                    missile crisis. Then we also offered, this is kind of interesting, in return for
                    the removal of the Turks, we agreed that we would keep an SSBM on station within
                    the general Eastern Med region. Once again this is a long time ago and my memory
                    is vague, but I'm pretty certain that that is the case. We even brought in, I
                    think it was the Sam Houston, to Izmir harbor and offered to take Turks out on
                    board for a demonstration. Just so they could see how effective, how powerful
                    these vessels were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And see those missiles on board.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: And see those missiles on board The Turks weren't interested.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: No. They had a funny attitude. We used to laugh about them and say that
                    the old Turkish generals were convinced that the submarine would go down under
                    water, sail submerged the length of the Mediterranean, through Gibraltar and
                    back to the United States without telling us. They might have been right for all
                    I know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you certainly had an interesting beginning of your
                        career, both in Washington and in Turkey. Now I notice that your next move
                        was to something quite different, East Africa. Was this a request or by
                        direct assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: In September of 1953, I was in my office on a Friday afternoon getting
                    ready to go on a camping trip with Sheila and the children along the Black Sea
                    coast. I'd signed up for 2 weeks vacation, we had tents and stuff in the car.
                    The phone rang, it's Bob Barnes, the DCM. He said, “Beau are you sitting down?”
                    I said, “Yes, sir.” He said, “I'll read you a cable.” Which said I was to depart
                    post immediately, go through the counterterrorism course. Do you remember
                    that?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I took one.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>NALLE: Take the counterterrorism course and was assigned as Officer-in-Charge of
                    Uganda affairs. I said to Bob, “My God, where is it?” He said, “I'm not sure but
                    I think it's in East Africa.” He said, “Come down and we'll talk about it.” He
                    was a superb DCM, a wonderful man, Bob Barnes. We chatted a little bit about it.
                    “Look,” he said, “I think it's a good job.” He said, “I think you probably ought
                    to do it.” But he said, “If you don't want to do it then I'm more than willing
                    to call the Department and fight for your assignment.” But I said, what the
                    hell, let's give it a shot.</p>
                <p>So I went back and entered into 8 years of my life that I spent wrestling with
                    Uganda.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And not only Uganda I gather, didn't you also have Kenya
                        and Tanzania at times?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: From time to time, just as backup. We had Paul O'Neill who's the Kenya
                    Desk Officer and a guy by the name of Johnnie Meagher was Tanzania Desk Officer.
                    We had a wonderful office.</p>
                <p>We had Jesse McKnight for Office Director who was a super guy. Another man I rank
                    very highly in my list of fine, fine people. He'd worked in the Department of
                    Labor for many years and wasn't much on Foreign Affairs. But knew how Washington
                    worked. It was maybe McCarthy or at least McCarthy's minions, he told to go to
                    hell, one time. He was Director of East African Affairs, Ed Mulcahy was Deputy
                    Director, Wen Coote was there. We had some wonderful people. And I learned from
                    them a lot about how the Department operates.</p>
                <p>Soapy Williams was Assistant Secretary for African Affairs. A fascinating man and
                    I think people are a little unfair to Williams, they kind of laughed and joked
                    at him a little bit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He took an interest in African Affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: He took a great interest in it. He was a decent human being. He was a
                    funny human being. He was a square dance caller among other things. He would
                    hire, with the vast money that he had in his bank account, he would hire a
                    hillbilly band to come in to the upstairs reception rooms in the State
                    Department and give parties for the African diplomats and we'd all do square
                    dances.</p>
                <p>The Africans were just utterly dumb-founded. They simply could not believe that
                    this very senior official in the State Department would come in a red and white
                    bandanna shirt and cowboy boots, and would be calling these tribal dances. We
                    poor Desk Officers were called in on-duty, there's no getting out of it. You
                    took your wife and you went, babysitter or no babysitter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dosey doe.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>NALLE: It was kind of fun. Sheila got a very real kick out of it. Eventually the
                    Africans sort of came to enjoy it. It was a side of America that was a little
                    different.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right, that they wouldn't normally see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Exactly right. I think the idea that such a senior official could engage
                    in such, what they thought perhaps, undignified, unofficial behavior gave them a
                    little more education about what this country of ours is all about. A little
                    bit, it was no big thing, but it was another piece they would fit into the
                    mosaic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now when you took over, Uganda had recently become
                        independent, did it not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Yes, they'd been independent for just a year. The tragedy of Uganda is
                    that Tanzania or Tanganyika in those days and then Kenya, had so much to offer.
                    They came very close to unifying the 3 African states.</p>
                <p>Uganda had an excellent school system, there were school fees charged but they
                    were very modest. And just about every kid, boy or girl, in the country received
                    an education through the 6th grade. They had a competent, and relatively
                    speaking, honest bureaucracy. Purely Uganda, there were no white British
                    officials left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: None left in the country.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Not a lot. Mike Davis, a very dear friend of mine, was the Director of the
                    Uganda Institute of Public Affairs. Which was a quasi-government job. He had
                    been District Commissioner in Acholi and he was the last British DC.</p>
                <p>But the civil service itself was purely Ugandan. This mind you from a country
                    where there were at least 14 significant tribal vernacular languages spoken.
                    Where the Prime Minister would on occasion speak through an interpreter to his
                    own people.</p>
                <p>Yet they had a very effective civil service—a good school system, the judiciary
                    was honest. There were foreigners on the Supreme Court, on the High Court—there
                    was a Cypriot Turk, there was a Brit—but the court became Ugandanized
                    eventually.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>The police force was honest and efficient and well trained. There were 2 or 3
                    British technical specialists with the police force. There was a ballistic man,
                    there was a fingerprint man, but there was nobody in the actual line of command
                    in the police force. One felt comfortable with the police. Even in those days,
                    one did not feel comfortable with the army.</p>
                <p>The army was a very real problem, both the officers and the enlisted men came
                    largely from one tribe in Northern Uganda called the Acholi. They're up on the
                    North along the Nile, right up to the Sudan border. The Acholis were basically
                    very nice people. They're big people, they're strong, tall. I'd often thought
                    they'd make wonderful swimmers, long arms and long legs. But they were recruited
                    in the army both for officer and enlisted personnel. In spite of the efforts of
                    the British, they became very aggressive, fairly ill disciplined, very much
                    interested in furthering their own affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's go back and see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: But I don't want to get into the country of Uganda without going over some
                    of the goings on, the activities in the 4 years that I spent as Uganda Desk
                    Officer prior to going to Kampala as Political Officer. Because it was a very
                    interesting and informative period in my life.</p>
                <p>Among other things, we went through the anguish and the chaos of the turmoil of
                    the murder of President Kennedy and his subsequent funeral. We had a delegation
                    from Uganda, actually it was the Vice President, who happened to be in town on a
                    Leader Grant. So I had to shepherd him around and that was very interesting.</p>
                <p>But being a Desk Officer is one of the 2 or 3 basic ultimate jobs that every FSO
                    has to go through. I found it very interesting for the most part, a good job, a
                    useful job. Although there were times when I got pretty thoroughly tied down by
                    the rigidity of it. By the rigidity of the whole State Department structure.</p>
                <p>I didn't for a minute, for example, want to or felt that I should have the right
                    to go up and see the Deputy Under Secretary or even the Assistant Secretary at
                    anytime. But I felt terribly constrained and I think all of us did. That we
                    weren't being very well utilized.</p>
                <p>I was there when we went through the change to the Country Director system. I
                    guess this shows the resilience or the rigidity of the bureaucracy. Because we
                    were told that this new system was instituted, that things were going to be much
                    better. That there would be a kind of a river running along with a series of
                    smaller rivers running into it and the collective knowledge would work its way
                    up to the 6th floor. Bugger all happened, there was not one jot nor tittle
                    difference from the old system. A lot of us got pretty cynical about it. We also
                    learned all of us, and I suppose this is only human, how much coincidence,
                    personality, the old-boy network, how much all of these things influence your
                    day-to-day activities.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>And I guess in the private world of business, in that great free enterprise
                    system that we all bow down to, I guess the same thing applies.</p>
                <p>But one learned that there were certain people up in the Executive Secretariat to
                    whom one could go to get something through in a hurry. One also learned that
                    there were people in the Executive Secretariat who were far more interested in
                    telling you how important they were than they were in getting your paper into
                    the Secretary's office for his meeting with the Ugandan Ambassador.</p>
                <p>There were periods of enormous frustration. So much also depended on the whims
                    and fancies. And indeed I might even say the political orientations of ones'
                    superiors. One expects obviously the Secretary of State and those of his
                    immediate suite, will reflect the political beliefs and ideals of the man who
                    appointed him, the President. And that's as it should be. But I got a little
                    startled, my impression is that the situation has gotten worse, at how far down
                    this went.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:But clearly, you must have known that Soapy Williams is a
                        power in the Democratic party.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Indeed I did. I don't point this particular finger at Soapy. I did think a
                    couple of his deputies, Tasca and—that old bald fellow from Baltimore, what the
                    hell was his name—didn't know Africa from Siberia. Bill something or other.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not Bill Trimble.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Yeah, right. I mean Trimble didn't know a thing about Africa. Anyway,
                    Wayne Fredericks on the opposite extreme, was sort of more a loyalist than the
                    king, more royalist I mean than the king.</p>
                <p>My impression is that this is very much the case now in the Department. That this
                    polarization has seeped its way, along with the political appointment, to
                    positions of Office Director and so on. That the political polarization had
                    become substantially worse. And this is a very sad state of affairs.</p>
                <p>But all-in-all the Desk Officer job was a fascinating one. The hours were long,
                    the strain on my family was immense, I was probably drinking too much from time
                    to time. At the same time in spite of the excitement, the occasional vibrancy,
                    there was also a feeling of wheels spinning.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>Certainly I got the impression that there was an awful lot of attention from time
                    to time to form and not all that much attention to substance. An otherwise
                    excellent paper would frequently be sent back at vast waste of time, to correct
                    a very minor typographical error. Now if I were a principal up in the top floor,
                    I would much rather get the paper early so that I could have the chance to look
                    at it than to worry that “weird” was misspelled, that “i” didn't come before “e”
                    or that a sentence in a paragraph by mistake got indented. But no, it would be
                    sent back and some secretary, because we didn't have any of the word processing
                    machines in those days, some secretary would have to retype the whole damned
                    thing.</p>
                <p>This irritated the hell out of me. I guess it's a reflection of my own
                    personality to some extent. I'm not the world's tidiest nor am I the world's
                    most efficient individual but I just felt that. I used to laugh at the ponderous
                    words we used: You may wish to tell the Foreign Minister that he's got holes in
                    his head. I mean why don't we just say, our policy is so-and-so and you should
                    tell the Minister this, period. And if Secretary Rusk doesn't like that, he
                    won't do it. Anyway, that's enough.</p>
                <p>The Desk Officer job was interesting but very frequently awfully frustrating. And
                    these never ending collection of clearances on one thing and another. Clearances
                    that frequently meant nothing at all because people would just override
                    them.</p>
                <p>Anyway, so after 4 years as Uganda Desk Officer, I went to Kampala as Political
                    Officer. And began what I think are among the 4 of the happiest years of my
                    life. I count 3 periods in my life as being truly periods of great joy: the 3
                    years in Roberts College, the 4 years in Kampala, and the 4 years as Consul
                    General in Izmir, Turkey later on.</p>
                <p>We had a good team at the Embassy. A man by the name of Henry Stebbins was the
                    Ambassador. He had formerly been Ambassador to Nepal, he was the first American
                    ambassador to Kathmandu. He was Harvard College, class of 1920 something or
                    other. A man of great personal dignity and self-assurance. A man with no African
                    experience and I don't think any particular strong feelings about Africa.</p>
                <p>But a man who knew what an ambassador was all about. A man who knew when to step
                    in and do something, and when to step back and let his staff do it. A man who
                    would listen to advice, accept it or reject it quickly with good reasons. A man
                    with a delightful wife who expected certain things from her staff but who was
                    not overpowering at all. Who was always very nice about asking and not telling,
                    thanking and not ignoring when the job was done.</p>
                <p>We lived in a gorgeous house. One of the things I always felt about the Bureau of
                    African Affairs, was that more than any other bureau I had served in, they take
                    care of their people. Housing was very good in Kampala. The AFEX people, Greg
                    Kryza and the others, were constantly looking for ways to make it better.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>Our Embassy itself was relatively small. We were limited by the Ugandan
                    government to a total of 15 people, not including the AID mission, the Ugandans
                    were not dumb enough to cut back on that, it was feeding them. It did include
                    Agency people, it did not include USIS. We had a small, I think effective, USIS
                    operation in Kampala.</p>
                <p>We had Agency people, we had 2 in the Embassy. One was declared. I would say on
                    the whole, they were very capable people. To the best of my knowledge they were
                    very good team players. I'm not aware of anytime where an Agency guy was out
                    wheeling and dealing, that the ambassador didn't know about it.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Stebbins was very firm with his Station people, he'd never let them
                    get out of control. And he told them that he wasn't going to take any nonsense
                    from them. They respected him, I think, and it made the working relationship
                    easier. They knew what their lines were and they followed them.</p>
                <p>We had some very good people there. One of the guys was Chief of the Consular
                    Section. We didn't have a tremendous burden of consular work but there was
                    enough. He worked damn hard at it and he was a good consular officer. He said it
                    was worth his while to do it because it was excellent cover. He could travel
                    around and see people and stuff that as a political officer or economic officer,
                    he couldn't do.</p>
                <p>Ritchey was the DCM, a wonderful fellow, he died about 6, 7 months ago and I was
                    very sad to see it happen. Of course Ambassador Stebbins' mysterious death at
                    sea, is something to this day I don't understand. I suspect it was a heart
                    attack and that he, a man of 6'4”, had toppled overboard.</p>
                <p>But we had a good Embassy. A pretty good AID mission, Will Muller was the AID
                    Director, and I have enormous respect for Will.</p>
                <p>It so happened that I spent a period of 14 months as Charg� D'affaires between
                    ambassadors. Stebbins retired, Ambassador Ferguson, a political appointee wasn't
                    appointed, didn't arrive until 14 months later. During that 14 months when I was
                    running the Embassy, Will Muller who was several grades my superior and a good
                    many years older than I am, was a model player on the country team and all of
                    that. He never tried to override me, he never tried to pull rank on me, he never
                    tried to play the big boss or anything like that. He accepted me as if I had
                    been an Ambassador. It made my job so infinitely much easier and my respect and
                    affection for Will is very deep as a result of that.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>We had some problems. One of the young AID employees had his girlfriend come to
                    visit and she got tired of staying in a hotel and moved in with him. I was
                    waited upon by a delegation of angry AID wives who wanted me to put an end to
                    that situation. I refused to do it. I said that it did not appear to me that
                    this was giving the Embassy a bad name. I didn't hear any loose talk or gossip
                    around town. I got around town a hell of a lot. I didn't hear anybody commenting
                    about it. They were not flaunting their relationship. I said until such time
                    that it becomes a public problem, it's none of my damned business what the guy
                    does, what he and his girlfriend do. The ladies were not happy. But I talked it
                    over with Will Muller and he said, “Yeah, they'd come to me and I told them I'm
                    not going to get involved in it.”</p>
                <p>We had a very well run operation. We had good relations with the government
                    although Obote was a difficult man to get along with. We had good relations with
                    the other diplomatic missions there. We were very close to the Israelis and
                    obviously close to the Brits.</p>
                <p>We were there during the days of ping-pong diplomacy and as we had both the
                    Chinese and the Soviet Embassies in town, it was absolutely fascinating when I
                    was told that I was at liberty to speak to the Chinese. I went to whoever it was
                    at parties, and one thing or another, we'd chat about the weather, Ugandan food
                    and utterly insignificant matters and occasionally venture into policy matters.
                    The minute it was over, Dmitri Safanov, the Soviet, would come up to me, “What
                    did he tell you? What was he saying?” I'd say, “Oh Mr. Ambassador, we were just
                    joking together.” “You were talking to him about NATO matters. You were talking
                    to him about Russian policy in Africa.” It was hysterical, it was worth the
                    price of admission alone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this the period when Idi Amin threw Obote out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: It began.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you see it coming?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Yeah, everybody saw it coming. It was like an express train coming down
                    the track. It was not subtle. Uganda at the time of independence had a
                    functioning multiparty government. There was Obote's party, the Uganda People's
                    Congress, the UPC. There was the opposition, the Democratic Party led by a very
                    dear friend, Alex Latim.</p>
                <p>And there was a regional grouping of the Buganda tribe, the Baganda people who
                    were the dominant tribe in Uganda and who lived around the Kampala area called
                    the Kabaka Yeka—the Kabaka alone. And all 3 of those parties essentially
                    functioned in parliament.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>Obote was becoming more and more authoritarian, more and more vaguely leftist,
                    although I pretty consistently refused to call it leftist. I said it was
                    nationalism, fuzzy head London School of Economics socialism, that kind of
                    stuff. He had a lot of young kids who did have an LSE degree and they reflected
                    that attitude. The London School was well known in the 50s, 60s, and 70s and I
                    think was pretty harmless. If you'd ever suggested to those people that they
                    ought to be real socialists, they'd turn pale with horror.</p>
                <p>The army role was growing ever larger. About a year before Amin took over the
                    government, somebody took a potshot at Dr. Obote at the Annual National Congress
                    of the UPC—shot him right through the mouth. The army went amuck. And for about
                    12 hours it was a pretty horrifying situation. There was no Ambassador, I was
                    Charg�.</p>
                <p>It was frightening. They beat up American citizens, they killed a fair number of
                    people, they beat up Brits, there was a strong anti-foreign element in it. There
                    was a strong anti-white element in it. And as I said, it lasted for about 12
                    hours. I take some pride in having been able to get a formal, written apology
                    from the GOU for all of this.</p>
                <p>Amin cut and run. Jumped out the back window of his house in his pajamas and
                    disappeared. Which really mystified us all. Why did he run? We thought he was
                    going to make his move one of these days. Why did he do what he did? We spent a
                    lot of time pondering that.</p>
                <p>I was a member of an institution called the Uganda Club. Which was set-up as an
                    answer to the all-British, all-white Kampala Club. I was one of 2 white members
                    of this particular club. Everyone from the Prime Minister to the Cabinet to the
                    Governor was a member and Ugandan. I made it a habit of stopping in there and
                    having a couple of beers every night. The drinking that went on at the Uganda
                    was mind boggling, just unbelievable.</p>
                <p>You could be assured of meeting 2 or 3 Cabinet ministers anytime you went up
                    there. I used to take newspaper people there who were thrilled with it. What's
                    his name? Apple, Charlie Mohr, a whole bunch of them I would take there and they
                    loved it.</p>
                <p>But one evening after this happened, Amin appeared at the Club. In full uniform
                    with 6 of his senior officers, with sidearms. Everyone was sitting around,
                    laughing and joking. I was at the bar. Suddenly I heard the whole Club go
                    silent. I was wondering, what was going on? I walked out of the bar and there
                    was Amin, a huge man, an enormous fellow, with his officers with their weapons.
                    Sitting in the main lounge, sitting at attention, not talking just looking
                    around. I thought, Jesus, what's going to happen. They sat there for about half
                    an hour, and then Amin said something in one of the local languages, and they
                    all got up and walked out.</p>
                <p>What it was, I'm convinced to this day, was a threat on the part of Amin at
                    reestablishing his position. Because he knew that he was laughed at because he
                    ran away. This was his reprisal, his counter-threat. And it worked. People were
                    scared to death.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>Relations got worse and worse between Amin and Obote. A senior army officer was
                    murdered. He was taking a bath on his front porch. It was an old fashioned town,
                    he was sitting out there scrubbing himself, humming away. A land rover drove by,
                    boom boom, and that was the end of Brigadier Okoya. He was one of the senior
                    Acholi officers who were opposed to Amin.</p>
                <p>On the night of January 24th, I had Fred Hadsel and Bob Moore visiting me. Sheila
                    and I gave a reception at our house to which we invited mostly Americans because
                    I'd had some complaints from the American community that when hotshot visitors
                    from Washington came through, I did nothing but entertain Ugandans. I said, well
                    goddamn it, that's what I'm here for. I'm here to entertain Ugandans, not
                    Americans. But still and all, in this particular case we did invite mostly
                    Americans.</p>
                <p>It was all over around 11:00. Fred had left, that's right, Fred had flown that
                    afternoon after a tennis game down to Nairobi. So it was just Bob. I took him
                    back to the hotel where he was staying, I got back to the house around midnight.
                    A friend of mine who was the Dean of the School of Agriculture at the
                    University, called me and said, “Can you hear machine gun fire?” I said, “Let me
                    step out on the porch.” I went out on the balcony and heard the tat-tat-tat all
                    over the city.</p>
                <p>And that was it. Obote was out of town at the Commonwealth Conference in
                    Singapore. We all felt when Obote left—the Station Chief, the Israelis—we were
                    all pretty much in agreement, that Obote felt he was in command of things or
                    else he wouldn't have gone off to Singapore. But he did.</p>
                <p>And Amin took over the government. I would say inside of 3 days, the killing
                    began and it never stopped. The first people he killed were 6 Canadian
                    missionaries. It didn't get much publicity.</p>
                <p>We had about, I forget what our E&amp;E plan said, we had about 800, maybe a
                    thousand Americans in the country. I put in the hold fast in the home system and
                    to my delight and pleasure it worked. We had a notification, a network of radios
                    and stuff, and by-golly the system worked, which surprised me a lot.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>There was a tourist group in town and they were a problem because they thought
                    they were important and wanted to get out of town. I said to them, “Look the
                    airport is closed.” And later the tour leader turned to me and said, “Well Mr.
                    Nalle, these are important people, they haven't got time to wait around, they're
                    going to miss their connections in Nairobi.”I said, “You're damn right they're
                    going to miss their connections in Nairobi, and they're going to get hungry,
                    they're going to get tired, they're going to get dirty and they're going to want
                    to get their laundry done. And it's not going to be done. Because I don't see
                    any chance of these folks leaving for 4 or 5 days.” And that was just the case.
                    They were furious.</p>
                <p>One guy, the president of this big liquor distributing company in Hartford, CT.,
                    Highblood or Hugh Blind or something, he beat me about that on the head and
                    shoulders. He had to get back to sign a contract. I said, “You can't do it.
                    There are soldiers at the airport who will kill you.” He kind of walked away
                    scratching his head.</p>
                <p>It was funny if it hadn't been serious. But the killings went on and they never
                    stopped.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What attitude did we take to that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Another interesting thing, goddamn there are so many interesting things
                    about this. I was able to get up that night when I heard the firing, got the
                    Deputy Station Chief who lived fairly close to me, and we drove into the office.
                    We didn't get back to our homes for over 48 hours. We were at the office and we
                    turned on the radio, South African broadcasting had it already within 3 hours
                    after the coup. BBC came in about 6 or 7 hours later and VOA was tail-light
                    charlie as usual.</p>
                <p>I called the OPS Center and was able to get out one phone call message. I thought
                    of sending a Critic message but I thought, this is not critic material. You
                    know, Uganda and the United States, come on. So I just telephoned the Operations
                    Center and told them what happened. Then all the phones went out and we lost
                    communications completely.</p>
                <p>The only thing we did have was a voice-radio with Embassy Nairobi. And bless his
                    heart, dear old Alan Lukens was DCM in Nairobi and every afternoon for about 2
                    weeks around 4:00 the radio would crackle and it was Luke calling up to know how
                    we were and did we need anything. That was our only communication for about 2
                    days. Then the communications guys did get things set-up so we could send
                    messages out and receive messages on a limited basis.</p>
                <p>The coup took place on a Sunday night. Ambassador Ferguson was away, knowing that
                    Obote was going to Singapore. He went up to Switzerland to put his older
                    daughter in school in Lausanne and take a week's vacation to go skiing. So again
                    I was in-charge of the place. The Station Chief was away, it was his Deputy that
                    I was doing business with. I mean when Obote took off, everybody took off.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>So anyway, the coup took place on a Sunday night. And I think it was Tuesday, I
                    got a message from Newsom, David Newsom, saying that we were going to recognize
                    the government. That we recognize countries not governments. That there would be
                    no question, that the issue would not come up. We would not make a formal
                    statement saying that we recognize the government. If asked, we would say that
                    the diplomatic relations had never been broken, they continue on. In retrospect
                    I wonder if we should have done that, but everybody is smarter the day
                    after.</p>
                <p>Then I got a message from Amin's principal private secretary, saying that he was
                    convening the Heads of Missions that afternoon and wanted me to attend. I called
                    Dick Slater, the British High Commissioner, and Ohran Ofri, the Israeli
                    Ambassador, and I think I may even have called the Russian but I'm not sure. I
                    said, are you going to the meeting? And they all said, yes. So I went along
                    without consulting Washington. I operated on the theory that Washington put me
                    there cause they thought I could do the job and goddamn it, I'm going to do
                    it.</p>
                <p>So I went along and it was a very brief meeting. Amin was pretty articulate, I
                    mean, to digress a minute. Amin was everything people said he was. He was a
                    murderer, he was a racist, he was a thug, a bully, a sadist, quite possibly a
                    cannibal, but people don't face up to the fact that also he was a very shrewd
                    political manipulator.</p>
                <p>He just met with us for no more than 10 minutes. He said he wanted relations to
                    continue between his government and all of us. That he was not taking sides to
                    the East-West strife. I remember the Soviet looked over at me and smiled. The
                    Soviets have a sense of humor. That he would continue to look to Great Britain.
                    Dick Slater groaned at that one. It was pretty routine and we all left. I was
                    able to report on it. Then he announced his new Cabinet which had some pretty
                    competent people in it.</p>
                <p>The next day I got a message from Slater, the Brit, saying that he had just
                    received a message from Amin that he wanted a one-on-one. And that Amin had
                    mentioned that he was also going to ask me to come in for a one-on-one. The
                    Israelis, because the Israelis had a huge aid program in Uganda in those days,
                    Amin said he wanted the Israelis to come in. Dick had given me a little tip-off.
                    Well in that case I thought I had better talk to the Department. So I called
                    David Newsom. The phone service was getting a lot better or maybe I used the
                    radio, I forget. But anyway I got through to Operations Center and Newsom. And
                    he told me to go to the meeting, listen and say as little as possible. He said
                    make no commitments whatsoever. Which I did.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>Amin wanted us to get into the military assistance program and he wanted us to
                    double our economic assistance. And specifically he wanted helicopters and
                    airplanes that could fly to Dar-Es-Salaam and return without refueling. Also
                    that he wanted to join NATO. The guy was off the wall a lot of times. He wanted
                    to join NATO and he was also thinking of joining the Warsaw Pact and in this way
                    (yes, yes, this comes back to me now), by being both a member of NATO and the
                    Warsaw Pact, he could be a balancing act between the 2 super powers. Which was a
                    lovely thought.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:What were his relations with his East African neighbors?
                        Kenya and Tanganyika?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Pretty bad. The East African Federation was a dead duck by then. But even
                    so, they looked at him as a kind of a clown. Although it's interesting there was
                    always an element in Africa and Uganda that supported Amin because he kicked out
                    the whites. A lot of Africans looked up on him because he beat up on white
                    people.</p>
                <p>A very good friend of mine and a distinguished professor at Makarari Univ, a
                    university professor, political science man named Ali Mazrui, he was a Kenyan
                    from Lamu island. He was a very bright guy, a distinguished Ph.D. from some
                    American university. He wrote a book. He wrote several books. But one of the
                    points in his book, or his long article after the takeover, was that Amin was
                    doing a good thing in kicking out the Asians, and in beating up on the whites,
                    and one thing or another. I happened to run into Ali after I was back here in
                    Washington. I said, “Ali, that's just disgusting. You should be ashamed of
                    yourself.”</p>
                <p>But anyway, then things really started deteriorating. Deaths increased. One man I
                    remember was the Director of the police band. We were at that time planning to
                    send him, I mean before the takeover, we had permission from the commandant and
                    the police to send him to the InterLachen festival at Michigan, where he could
                    get a summer learning band techniques. The police had an excellent band. This
                    guy was a good musician. He graduated from some British band school in the UK
                    and we'd just polish him up a little bit. He was a first class musician. He got
                    beaten to death with re-bar because he was from another tribe.</p>
                <p>The son of a very good friend of mine, the Permanent Secretary of the Ministry of
                    Lands and Natural Resources, the Permanent Secretary's son was an officer in the
                    army. The night Amin took over the government, he ran away. Then realized that
                    he'd have to come back sooner or later. He went to see his father. His father
                    counseled him that he should go back and see Amin and try to make his peace. He
                    said that he would go along and support him. They met Amin and Amin said,
                    “That's all right my friend, you go back and you join your unit. We'll forget it
                    all.” The father said, thank God, and he left. Three days later they started
                    discovering bits and pieces of this young boy chopped up around the
                    barracks.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>One of his favorite tricks was to handcuff a person to the steering wheel of an
                    automobile, set the car on fire, and push it down the road. It went on and on.
                    The strain on us was just unbelievable. You talk to Bob Keeley about it at some
                    time. It was never ending.</p>
                <p>There was curfew. I had to go out at night one time and one of the Ugandan army
                    armored personnel carriers came down the street. The lids were open and there
                    were people sitting on it looking around with their—they didn't have AKs, no
                    they had a few AK47s, but it was mostly that FN, that NATO gun, the rifle with
                    Fabrique Nationale from Belgium they got from the Australians curiously.</p>
                <p>Anyway, you talk about scared. I was able to walk in behind a telephone pole, in
                    some bushes and just lay there shaking. Another time, I was up North with one of
                    the members of the staff, about 2 months after the revolution. I wanted to go to
                    Ocholi country because they were anti-Amin, they were the wrong tribe. And a guy
                    cut loose on us with a burst of automatic fire from his weapon. Which was
                    another unpleasant experience. But it was like that constantly.</p>
                <p>Sheila and the children were under terrible strain. There was a fire fight that
                    took place outside our house. We had a lovely house there. I was away on a
                    business trip. I think it was while I was up North getting shot at up there. A
                    fire fight took place outside our house between gangsters and soldiers.</p>
                <p>And Sheila and the children literally spent the night in the bathtub. That was
                    about the safest place as any. When I came home from the trip, there were bullet
                    holes in our house. It was stone. It was rough. It was very, very rough.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No congressional visits during that period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Not the immediate period, they came later on.</p>
                <p>One American who went up North and nearly got killed, was Nick Stroh, from Stroh
                    beer people in Detroit. He was an awfully nice guy. A stringer for a couple of
                    the U.S. newspapers, just starting out on the world of newspapers. He
                    represented a Tampa newspaper, he represented a couple of small papers from
                    Michigan, he was stringing for the Kansas Star, is it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Kansas City Star.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Kansas City Star, yeah. He went away on a trip, this was in July, and he
                    left on a Wednesday in his car, went out into the western part of the country. I
                    didn't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Alone or with an interpreter?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: With a friend. You didn't use interpreters much in Uganda, most people,
                    you get enough English to get by. I never used an interpreter.</p>
                <p>With a friend from the faculty at the Makarari College, an American professor of
                    sociology. He didn't tell me he was going. If he had, I would have tried
                    desperately to talk him out of it because it was not a safe area to be in. But
                    he just went. His wife, Gerda, came and told me this and I said, oh God. He said
                    he would be back Thursday. Thursday rolled by and he never showed up, she came
                    to me. Nothing happened. I started looking around, I talked to police, I talked
                    to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. Ambassador Ferguson put out calls through
                    his sources.</p>
                <p>Then we were due to leave on Sunday. On Saturday when we should have been
                    finishing our packing, I got an anonymous phone call from a town out in the
                    western region. That 2 white men had been seen being driven around in an army
                    automobile with an army officer driving and someone was beating these guys up.
                    And the phone hung up.</p>
                <p>And this is where we really went out of our minds. I went to every Ugandan, every
                    source I had built up in the course of 8 years working in that country, people
                    who were in the habit of sitting down and having long open candid conversations.
                    They'd look at me and say, “Beau, don't ask. Please don't ask me because, just
                    don't ask.” Windows were shut in my face, doors slammed in my face. And we left,
                    Sheila, the kids and I left the following Sunday morning.</p>
                <p>And Nick Stroh's body was found. Bob Keeley and Ferguson went through hell. But
                    eventually there was an investigation mounted and a British high judge wrote his
                    report, dropped it at the registered mail envelope of the post office and drove
                    directly out of the country. He never went back to Uganda again. Because it
                    pointed a finger directly at Amin and his troops.</p>
                <p>And after I left, things got even worse. The Asians were kicked out. It was sad
                    because Uganda was a beautiful, lovely little country. God damn, I spent 8 years
                    working on that place. It was absolutely fascinating.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this entirely the cause of Amin or were there
                        others?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I don't know of any other real cause that you could say, other than Amin's
                    personal ambition. I mean, he was an incredible character. I was up at the Club
                    one evening when there were problems in India. Mrs. Gandhi was Prime Minister
                    and was having difficulties with her Parliament I mentioned this to Amin and he
                    chuckled, “Who wouldn't with all those bloody Asians?” he asked.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well Beau, after your Ugandan adventure where did fate
                        take you next?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Well, I left Uganda with very real sorrow. It was a country that I had
                    grown to understand to some extent. I knew a great deal about it. I could see
                    only clouds, clouds, clouds on the horizon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excuse me, how could you say that you left there with
                        sorrow when you'd just been telling us about the horrors that the Amin
                        regime was perpetrating. Wouldn't you be glad to leave?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Well that's true, that's very true. I was desperately glad.</p>
                <p>My last weekend in Uganda, instead of packing, well not my last weekend because
                    my last weekend was trying to find poor old Nick Stroh. The weekend before that
                    I had been invited by Amin to come along as his personal guest while he was
                    going out on a political tour of the eastern province. And so I spent 2 days and
                    2 nights bouncing around in a Land Rover, drinking banana beer with General Amin
                    while he gave political speeches in the villages. That part, aside from the
                    curiosity, I don't miss.</p>
                <p>What I do miss are the many many Ugandans whom we came to know and like and
                    considered to be truly close friends. Who are dead. What I do miss is a little
                    African country that had so many prospects for a bright future. A little African
                    country that at one time had an active, vibrant democratic political system.</p>
                <p>What I do miss is the university of African professors where you could go and
                    have spirited, happy go lucky, beer-sodden times talking politics and solving
                    the problems of the world. That's the sort of thing I miss from Uganda. And the
                    magnificent game parks which are completely destroyed now. And the superb
                    wildlife and birds, those are the things you miss.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think I can understand that. Now from there where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: From there I spent a year at the Newport Rhode Island at the National War
                    College. Which was not particularly taxing intellectually but a very restful and
                    happy year for the whole family.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>And useful for me in that it confirmed in my mind, a number of theories I've long
                    held about the American professional military people. Namely that there is no
                    such thing as a typical American military officer. And I say thank God for that.
                    There is no military class in the United States. The bulk of these people, the
                    career officers, still maintain a strong identity as a civilian. They are the
                    ones who are most opposed to the development of a military class.I was pleased
                    at the ability that these men, now these are guys that are expected to move
                    ahead in the navy, the army, the air force and the coast guard. I was very
                    impressed at their ability. This is not a do it by the numbers, hut two three
                    four, kind of an operation. These are some very damn bright men and women. So
                    all in all, it was a happy and pleasant year.</p>
                <p>I recall some less than happy moments when one of my colleagues from the National
                    War College came up. Mind you, this was when Vietnam was on our minds and very
                    active. We got to arguing about it and this fellow said, “Well, you know, 98% of
                    the people in the United States are opposed to our Vietnam policy.” And my
                    military colleagues looked at each other with shock and amazement. And I said to
                    him, “Gordon, you're as full of shit as a Christmas goose. A vast number of
                    American people for better or for worse vigorously support the Vietnam
                    policy.”</p>
                <p>And then we got going with the military who were talking about how many of them
                    oppose the policy. And it was a very interesting experience but my colleague did
                    not show any sense of political awareness of what was going on in the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>Anyway, it was a good year. And from there I went to Liberia, which was a horse
                    of a different color.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Another part of Africa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: West Africa. Uganda, among other things being 4,000 feet high had a very
                    pleasant climate. Liberia being about 3 feet high, had a just vile climate—hot
                    hot hot humid humid humid.</p>
                <p>The Liberians, I am sorry to say, are just not very nice people. The so called
                    America-Liberian class I found extraordinarily difficult to get along with. I
                    found the corruption, the mental and the moral, as well as the fiduciary
                    corruption, to be overwhelming.</p>
                <p>The bitterness that exists between the city of Monrovia and the rest of the
                    country is very unpleasant. I think Liberia is probably the only, or was the
                    only country in the world, where the legislature still passed laws which were
                    applicable only to, and I quote “the tribal elements that remain within the
                    country” unquote.</p>
                <p>Doing political work was extremely difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excuse me, what was your position there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I was head of the Political Section. I was very carefully told that I was
                    not to call myself Political Counselor. But I was Chief of the Political
                    Section.</p>
                <p>Sam Westerfield was the Ambassador, he died 2 days after I arrived of a heart
                    attack. His place was eventually taken by Ambassador Mel Manfull. He was Chief
                    of Mission the whole 2 years I was there.</p>
                <p>Housing in the Mission and the Embassy in Monrovia was not good. Monrovia was the
                    only place I ever lived on an Embassy compound. Whatever the advantages might
                    have been, and I never perceived them, they were totally outweighed by the
                    disadvantages. The thought that anybody might pop in for a plate of tea or a sip
                    of whisky was ridiculous. When you had to get through Marine guards, when you
                    had to wander around through the compound with only Americans there, children
                    and one thing or another. It simply cut you off from any reasonable contact.
                    There was no reason for it. FBO if they wanted to, could have found some houses.
                    I don't see much that justifies compound living anywhere in the world. Why we
                    have it in the developed world, in Western Europe, I can't for the life of me
                    understand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But certainly wouldn't it have been useful later when
                        Sergeant Doe took over and they had great unrest in Liberia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Yeah they didn't come on board the compound, that's true enough. But if
                    you're going to sit around building up walls against somebody who may or may not
                    takeover, you're not doing your job, I don't think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a good answer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Sergeant Doe, was a pretty nasty piece of work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was our principal interest in Liberia during the
                        years you were there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: There was what the Liberians called “A Special Relationship.” The
                    Liberians being of course the descendants of the returned slaves. They called it
                    a special relationship, we tried to call it an Historical Relationship, but we
                    never got very far with it.</p>
                <p>We had some fairly substantial economic investments—Sun Oil was there with a
                    refinery; United States Steel was there with an iron mine.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Firestone was there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Firestone was there, it had an enormous operation. I mean the General
                    Manager of Firestone back in the 20s or the 30s was probably more important than
                    the American ambassador.So there was the commercial and economic interest,
                    American banks. The dollar was the official currency in Liberia. There was this
                    sociological, historical relationship that existed. A massive American citizen
                    population.</p>
                <p>And the idea that Liberia, along with Ethiopia and of course the Republic down
                    south, were the only countries in Africa that had not been ruled by some sort of
                    colonial master—the French, the British, the Belgians or the Portuguese.</p>
                <p>So for all these reasons. We also had a little military mission, we had a big
                    embassy there. I forget how many people, all told, we had on the embassy staff.
                    But it was big. We had the compound, we had the old building with the
                    generators. We had the famous employee whose name was “Saturday.” That was his
                    only name, just Saturday. And Saturday used to wander around the grounds
                    emptying Butt cans, and for this he got paid, I guess about 200 a year U.S., I
                    don't know. But he was the Butt can man.</p>
                <p>I don't think I can honestly say that I predicted Sergeant Doe. I doubt that my
                    successor did. And I'm very certain that my predecessor didn't. I think all of
                    us, all the political officers and all the ambassadors and everyone else, felt
                    that major change was overdue in the country but we did not foresee this
                    outcome.</p>
                <p>We all felt that Tolbert, who had taken over of course after Tubman died, was on
                    the right track. But with his campaign of, what was it “Beds to Breakfast” I
                    don't know, he had all kinds of campaigns to exhort people to rise to higher
                    heights. That's another one of his mottos, “Higher Heights.” We all felt that he
                    was trying his damndest to whip the system. But from what I understand,
                    subsequent to our times there, the system whipped him. He operated I guess on
                    the theory that: If you can't beat them, join them. Little whispers of
                    corruption that we began to get in my day grew into a shouted chorus of
                    corruption in the years following. And eventually led to his overthrow and
                    brutal and tragic death. He was a nice little guy.</p>
                <p>As far as the family was concerned, Liberia was characterized essentially by
                    dullness. We had a pretty good American community school there, both girls were
                    there. They enjoyed it. Sheila had fun because she, both in Uganda and in
                    Liberia, was very active on the school board. I think Sheila enjoyed our years
                    in Africa. There were things for her to do, school board work, she had done a
                    lot of garden work around the houses we had, particularly in Kampala. I think
                    she was fairly happy, the social burden was heavy. We had staff, in most cases
                    incompetent and dishonest, but they were there anyway to rearrange the dirt.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>So Liberia was not for me a particularly happy place. I found the work stifling.
                    We had some good people there. David Gamon was DCM. I just saw in the newspaper
                    that he died. Kind of a dry stick but a warm person, in spite of it all.</p>
                <p>I was perfectly happy to leave and go back to Washington. I hadn't been
                    there—well what 4 years in Kampala, a year at the War College, 2 years in
                    Liberia—I hadn't been there for 7 or 8 years. We'd get the children back in
                    American schools and I would work in the Bureau of Personnel as Chief (whatever
                    the heck they call it) of the African assignments division in PER. Which were 2
                    fascinating and quite rewarding years contrary to what I thought at the
                    beginning.</p>
                <p>I found my years in PER very much worthwhile. Operating on the theory that if the
                    foreign service didn't run its own personnel system, a bunch of geeks, far less
                    competent and far less sympathetic than we were, would come in and do it for us.
                    My job was to keep all of our posts in Africa fully staffed with superstar,
                    overachiever, ultimate genius, soon to become ambassadors from the level of
                    FSO-8, on up the line. Nothing but the best will suffice to be GSO in
                    Bamako.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find it hard to attract people to Africa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: No, not a bit, that was the least of my troubles. I didn't have trouble
                    attracting people either in terms of quantity or quality. I was also responsible
                    for staffing a couple of State Department offices, namely INR. Which is probably
                    the hardest office to staff anywhere in the State Department system. Which is a
                    pity because INR jobs are interesting, they're excellent training. People learn
                    how to write when they're in INR and given the lack of writing skills of the
                    youth in America today, that's something to think about. But putting people in
                    INR was like sending them to Eastern State Penitentiary or Siberia.</p>
                <p>But staffing Africa was not difficult. We had a wonderful bunch of people.
                    Starting with Art Wortzel who was head of PER. The Director-General I did not
                    think much of, but it may have been just a personality clash, it was Carol
                    Laise. I just didn't see any bright, shining star there. I didn't see any
                    leadership there. I think of the DG as being a job to get out, and to fight for,
                    and to defend the foreign service while running it with a relatively iron hand.
                    I didn't see any of that in Carol Laise.</p>
                <p>A case in point, as I was due to leave PER for my next assignment, I was asked if
                    I was willing to extend for a year. I said, yes. My family was enjoying
                    Washington, I liked the work and I would be perfectly happy to stay on for a
                    third year doing the African assignments job. So that was agreed upon.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>And then one day Art Wortzel came down to me looking rather embarrassed, and
                    said, “Beau, what would you feel if we asked you to leave the African
                    assignments job and move over to the Junior Officer counseling and assigning
                    branch?” And I said, “Well Art, that position's already been filled, we've got a
                    fellow coming in to do that job. I just saw the assignment notice the other
                    day.” As I said, the position had been filled, it was an ADMIN officer, I didn't
                    know him but I had met him, he'd even been through the briefings and one thing
                    or another.</p>
                <p>And Art looked even more embarrassed because he was a very principled man. He
                    said, “Well Carol Laise is worried, this fellow has come in, as we used to say
                    in the navy, in through the hawse pipe. He was a former staff officer and became
                    an FSO.” I said, I used the old Hebrew, Yiddish expression, “Nu? What's wrong
                    with that? He's got incredible record. The guy is obviously in the top 10 among
                    the mid-careers, below senior administrative people. This is an excellent
                    assignment.”</p>
                <p>Art squirmed in his chair. He said, “Carol thinks it would be more suitable if a
                    career FSO ran the Junior Officer Program.” I said, “God damn it Art. I can't
                    think of anything better than having a guy who started off as a FSS, counting
                    nuts and bolts down in the general services shop, and who worked his way up the
                    hard way. I can't think of anything better to take these young guys, who have
                    been getting the sugar tit all their lives, and doing their assignments.” He
                    said, “Well, Carol doesn't want it.”</p>
                <p>In retrospect, I should have raised a bigger beef. But I said, “Ok, I'll take the
                    job.” I was interested in it anyway. So I did the Junior Officer counseling. It
                    was an eye-opening experience.</p>
                <p>I had one young tiger call me from Jakarta. Using the old system, he was an
                    FSO-6. An economic officer who was doing consular work. This very frequently
                    happens because we need so many junior consular officers. People of political
                    and economic value are put into the consular side of things. This kid had done
                    very well, excellent record. He called me and said he wanted to go to an 05
                    economic job in Paris.</p>
                <p>I said, well I didn't really think I could do that. I could put him in an 05
                    consular job in Paris. In fact, I thought I might be even able, based on his
                    record, to get him a Section Chief job in Paris, head of the IV section or the
                    NIV section. Because his work was good. I said, I have a lot of guys in the
                    economic cone. This guy was in the consular cone. I said, I've got a lot of
                    economic guys who are looking for that same job, who are in consular jobs just
                    like you. Who've served in hardship posts, just like you.</p>
                <p>In your cone, I'll move you up. Outside your cone, you'll have to go into an 06
                    economic job. He said, “But I've got a B.A. in Economics from Yale.” I made an
                    effort not to laugh, but I said, that's the best I can do for you. He said, “You
                    are ruining my career.” That's the end of it, we hung up.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>A month later I got a memo from the SS. There was a letter attached and it was
                    this guy's letter of resignation. He said he blamed his whole resignation on Mr.
                    Nalle in PER who was not interested in having him advance as rapidly as
                    possible. It was the usual letter to the Secretary. It said: “Mr. Secretary, I
                    should be in Washington on Friday, December 15. I still have open on my schedule
                    anytime between 2:30 and 3:30 in that afternoon, if you'd care to talk to me.”
                    There was a query plaintive little note on this thing from the line guy in SS,
                    who knew me, he was my usual source, he said “Beau, who is this jerk?”</p>
                <p>But that's the way it was. Now as I look back, I see some of them taking DCM jobs
                    and stuff. It was interesting work, I enjoyed it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes it was, it was interesting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: It was rewarding work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was rewarding and you met some very fine young
                        people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Indeed. The panel I think was as good a way as I could think of, of
                    challenge and response, between the counseling officers and the assignments
                    officers. It was a good a way as I could think of to keep our overseas offices
                    staffed up with good people. We worked, with occasional losses of temper, we
                    worked very harmoniously. Even the odd loss of temper was done and over with by
                    the time we opened up for business the next day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's the way I remember Personnel too. Very very seldom
                        was anything held overnight, any arguments held overnight.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>After this interesting assignment in Personnel, what came next?</p>
                <p>NALLE: What I really wanted was Consul General in Istanbul but good old Bob
                    Houghton took that one out of my hands. He couldn't speak a word of Turkish but
                    that's alright.</p>
                <p>I went down to a crazy little place in Central America called Belize. It was a
                    strange business. Belize of course is former British Honduras and the only
                    remaining British colony in the Western Hemisphere. I went there as Consul
                    General, had a staff of 4 Americans and about 8 or 9 locals. And was somewhat
                    startled.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>I was told that it was an independent reporting post which meant, as I understood
                    it, I did not have to go through London. I could report directly to Washington.
                    That's the sort of bureaucratic double-talk that I would have been just thrilled
                    to ignore. But anyway, after I'd been there for a couple of months, I got a copy
                    of the famous Kennedy letter.Only in this case it was from President Carter,
                    saying—as Chief of Mission in Belize, you have this, that—I was looking at it
                    and said, “What? Chief of Mission in Belize?” Nobody ever told me about this. So
                    I put it away, really didn't think much about it.</p>
                <p>Here's good old Mother State at work again, about a week after that I got a
                    cable, I think it may have been immediate, from Washington saying, “You will
                    have received your copy of President Carter's letter.” I paraphrase this, “Yes,”
                    it said, “it's true, you have the title of Chief of Mission in Belize. However,
                    we instruct you that under no circumstances are you to use the title. Under no
                    circumstances are you to call yourself Chief of Mission. Under no circumstances
                    are you to advise the British or the other members of the diplomatic corps that
                    you are Chief of Mission. You are not to use the term Chief of Mission in
                    talking matters over with your Belizean colleagues and friends.”</p>
                <p>It just went on and on and on. I thought, what the hell is this all about? To
                    this day I don't know what it's all about. It totally mystifies me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Obviously the White House had sent this to all posts and
                        since Belize was a semi- independent post, someone just sent it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Well, why did they send me the original letter from Carter?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's what I mean.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I think it's some legal connection with the fact that it's an independent
                    or reporting post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I would think so.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I was in the same category as Hong Kong.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There may be one or two others but I'm not sure.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Maybe one or two others but that was it.</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>So anyway, the reason I went to Belize, by this time I was getting old and
                    promotions were fewer and fewer. The bird watching was good and above all in the
                    post report inventory, I noticed the listing of a 21 foot Boston Whaler with
                    2-75 horsepower outboard motors on it, for use by the Consul General in the
                    performance of his official duties. And also used by the Consul General and his
                    wife every Saturday and Sunday to go skin diving out on the reef or to go bird
                    watching before they do anything else.</p>
                <p>We also at that time in Washington, had a little 20 foot Swedish built diesel
                    powered motor sailer which I was able to ship down to Belize at very modest
                    cost. Which we had there for the almost 3 years I spent. And we'd go off on
                    vacation and leave instead of going off to Guatemala or going to Salvador. We'd
                    get on the boat and go to sea for a week, up or down the barrier reef, which
                    next to the reef in Australia, is the second longest cargo barrier reef in the
                    world. The scuba diving and the snorkeling are just unbelievable.</p>
                <p>Belize was a very interesting post. It is, was the last British colony in the
                    western hemisphere. It was ruled by a “Governor and a Commander-in-Chief.” A
                    very nice old gentleman formerly of the colonial office. Who'd been born in
                    Kenya, raised in Kenya, spoke Swahili and Kikuyu very fluently. An irascible
                    Scott, we got along quite well together, Peter MacIntee.</p>
                <p>The problem was everybody wanted Belize to be independent except Guatemala.
                    Guatemala laid claim to the entire territory of Belize based on a treaty that
                    had been drawn up by the then Central American state, empire I think they called
                    it, existing in 1840 or 1835, around there. The treaty was very badly worded. I
                    used to point out to junior officers, my staff, what would happen if you
                    couldn't write well. You could start a war.</p>
                <p>So based on their misunderstanding of this treaty, the Guatemalans claimed all of
                    Belize. The question of the resolution of this problem was the so-called Belize
                    Resolution in the UN. Every year the UN would vote that Belize should be
                    independent. Every year the Guatemalans and a few other South Americans
                    supporting their brothers in Guatemala City, would vote, no. For many years the
                    U.S. vetoed the resolution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excuse me, you said the U.S. vetoed, would it not be the
                        British vetoed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: No, the British wanted to get rid of Belize as fast as they could. They'd
                    get down on their hands and knees and beg us to vote for the Belize Resolution.
                    It had complete internal self-government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And so we had to do it.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>NALLE: Because we liked the fascist military thugs that were ruling Guatemala.
                    Even today I become angry with our military program piling money into Guatemala
                    with those butchers that were ruining that country. The conservative elements in
                    the US government said that we can't turn loose this good anti-communist friend
                    of ours. And so for years we either in some cases vetoed, in some cases we
                    merely abstained from voting, for the Belize Resolution at the UN.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Belize Resolution would not have given the territory
                        to Guatemala would it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: No. It would have just said that Belize would become independent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then the Guatemalans would assume that they could swallow
                        it up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: The Guatemalans would assume that they could swallow it up or at least
                    this is what some thought. I was never convinced that the Guatemalans were going
                    to invade. And besides the British agreed to keep their troops there. The
                    British had 2400 troops. Part of the agreement was the British could keep using
                    Belize as a jungle warfare training center because they could no longer use
                    Sarawak or Borneo or any of those places. The only place in the world they had
                    for jungle warfare training. And they'd rotate great regiments, the Black Watch,
                    the Queen's Own Foot, and others for 6 months training exercises. And they would
                    keep them there after independence. And they had harrier jets just to fight off
                    the hateful Guats.</p>
                <p>I mean, it struck me as the United States government and the State Department at
                    its worst. Because these butchers in Guatemala city were “anti-communists.”
                    There was some thought that George Price might be little bit on the left-side
                    himself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think there was.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: George Price was gay. That's the only problem with poor old George Price.
                    He used to go out to Miami and cruise from time to time. But everybody
                    overlooked that, that was his business not ours.</p>
                <p>I worked so hard along with Jim Cheek who then was Deputy Assistant in NRA. And
                    John Blacken was Director of ARACEN. The 3 of us worked desperately to get us to
                    change our position on the Belize Resolution up at the UN. Finally, by God, we
                    finally did it. In October of 1980.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It became independent in 1981.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>NALLE: That's right. Then I left 3 weeks after that.</p>
                <p>And narcotics was the other problem. This was when I first really faced the
                    narcotics problem. It was unbelievable: overflights, illegal aircraft. We didn't
                    have a narcotics man in Belize. He came over from Guatemala, he came over about
                    once a month. It was primarily marijuana but more and more there was evidence
                    that it was becoming a transit point for cocaine from South America. And more
                    and more it was obvious that senior members of the government, Belize government
                    not the British, were involved in it and it was a very difficult matter. Also,
                    the Nicaraguan situation was degenerating.</p>
                <p>We had a plane land, I get called out to the airport. It was an American twin
                    Beech I think it was, with 2 guys in the cockpit who didn't have pilots
                    licenses, didn't have drivers' licenses, didn't have credit cards or passports.
                    They had lots of cash, U.S. dollars cash. The aircraft itself had no aircraft
                    log, it had no air maintenance log, it had no airframe log, it had no engine
                    log. There were no tail numbers on the aircraft. There was nothing. Just these 2
                    guys with no identification. And an aircraft that couldn't be traced, all the
                    numbers had been filed off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they were American?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Oh yeah, couldn't have been more so, straight out of Mississippi or
                    Alabama, nice bunch of guys. Like this fellow who got shot down in Nicaragua. Do
                    you remember?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes I do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: He was the same kind of guy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do with them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I wanted to throw them in jail. The Belize government said, what the hell,
                    let them go. Money probably passed hands out at the airport, I'm sure. They said
                    they were lost.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The plane was searched, I take it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: The plane was searched, there was nothing in it. As I said, I think money
                    passed hands. The Belizeans let them go, they said, “We've got no reason to hold
                    them.” I said, what do you mean you've got no reason to hold them? These guys
                    are as illegal as they can be. They said, no, the plane's all right. So off they
                    went.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>About 4 days later a cable came in from San Jose. Saying that a twin Beech with
                    new Panamanian identification numbers. Two Americans—it was obviously the same
                    aircraft—had crashed in the mountains in Northern Costa Rica, just on the edge
                    of the Nicaraguan border and some 500 rifles and a half a million rounds of
                    ammunition had been discovered.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A prominent press story.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: A prominent press story. The plane at that time had had a tail number
                    painted on it in Panama. Which was untraceable. They go down along with this
                    stuff in Costa Rica and had crashed flying north from Panama to Nicaragua. It
                    was a crazy place.</p>
                <p>Another time a plane landed at Belize International airport. It requested
                    emergency landing, engine problems. Here's one of these good old Southern boys.
                    Superb pilots, unbelievable pilots, they're so good. He was sitting there behind
                    the wheel, a mechanic was working on his engine. The mechanic, I knew him, a
                    U.S. citizen who was a drug smuggler himself but we never did catch him.</p>
                <p>I think the only honest policeman in the country of Belize was on duty at the
                    airport at the time. He came out and looked over the airplane. And back in the
                    after section of the aircraft, were a whole lot of garbage bags very neatly
                    wrapped up and tied with tape. And the policeman turned and said, “Hey man, what
                    that? Give me one man.” And the pilot went back and got one for him. The guy
                    opened it up, it was very neatly baled marijuana. And the fellow said to the
                    pilot, “Man you've got about 5000 kilos of pot in the back of your aircraft.”
                    The pilot turned around and he looked at the policeman and said, “Son of a
                    bitch, where do you suppose that came from?”</p>
                <p>He stayed 2 days in jail. Our consular officer, Bernie Gross, was down in the
                    jail talking to him. And a guy, Bernie told me later, with pointy toed alligator
                    Gucci shoes and electric blue suit came in with a briefcase full of hundred
                    dollar bills. And Bernie was saying, “Hey, we can get vitamin pills and
                    something for food rations.” And the guy says, “Why thank you Mr. Gross, I
                    believe my problem is being taken care of.” He got up and walked out of the
                    jail.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is just a modern style.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: It was unbelievable. The police would shake down the tourists, they'd go
                    up to tourist and say. “Welcome to Belize, man.” And would pat him in the back
                    and in doing so they'd leave a couple of marijuana leaves. The cop would say,
                    “Oh, what's that on your shoulder? Hey boy, you've got pot. You come on down to
                    headquarters with me. Unless you want to take care of me right now.” And the
                    poor tourist would pull out a $5 bill and give it to him.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there for the independence ceremony?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: No I left. I was ready to get out, I was tired and it was a hard post. The
                    old Governor had left and a new guy came in. And he was not helpful. The old
                    Governor had tried to get the Independence taken care of through persuasion.
                    Also the British had a great deal of trouble in working out with Belize just
                    what the terms of independence would be. This went back and forth.</p>
                <p>So I was very happy to get out. I had a phone call from PER and they said
                    that—How would you like to go as Consul General to Izmir? I said, I don't even
                    have to talk to my wife about that, well, I'm ready. I made up my mind in 2
                    seconds. Sheila was tired, housing was just excruciatingly bad, just awful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Belize.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Yeah, in Belize, just unbelievable. Living was difficult. Next to
                    Iskenderun, it was the hardest post we were ever stationed in. Sheila had liked
                    it at first but she got tired.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you not have a Principal Officer's residence
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: An apartment over the office building. We couldn't stand this. She was
                    sitting at the place one time, kept scratching her head, couldn't figure it out.
                    It was a termite, it was eating away at the wood and the sawdust was falling on
                    her hair. We had a hurricane that nearly blew away the whole city at one time.
                    The Department sent down a fire expert, he got one look at the building, turned
                    to me and said, “Twenty minutes.” I said, what do you mean? He said it'll take
                    this place 20 minutes to burn to the ground.</p>
                <p>It was hard duty. Fortunately we did have the boat and it was cheap to go to
                    Miami. Get a round trip ticket to go to Miami from Belize Air for $200.00. It
                    wasn't very safe but it got you there. And so Sheila would spend a lot of her
                    time up in Washington. It was awful hard. Again, I was probably drinking more
                    than was good for me.</p>
                <p>I didn't get along with the new Governor at all. He's one of these matey Brits
                    who slap me on the back and started calling me Beau from the first time we met.
                    I don't think that's an appropriate way to behave. I was a little reluctant, I
                    never called his predecessor anything other than “Governor.” It just seemed
                    appropriate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No wonder then you were pleased with the prospect of going
                        back to Turkey.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>NALLE: In Izmir we had a very nice, well organized office. We had a gorgeous
                    official residence to live in, beautiful house. You know Ken Burns? Did you ever
                    meet Ken Burns?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No. I've heard the name but I never met him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Ken was responsible for building this house in late 1950s. He'd come up to
                    Ankara from time to time when I was with the Embassy there, and I'd meet him in
                    social affairs. He'd talk about the house he was building.</p>
                <p>A beautiful place, wonderful FSNs, and this time we really went first class. We
                    had a boat from Hong Kong, a 30 foot diesel trawler. We'd go to sea and be out
                    for 10 days without touching land, except maybe stock up on fresh vegetables and
                    drinking water, that kind of stuff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Beautiful islands near there too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: The Turkish coast is the last unspoiled part of the Mediterranean Sea. It
                    is so beautiful. You can drop anchor there and there won't be another boat
                    within 5 miles of you. It's not that way anymore, the 15, 10 years we've been
                    away. It's turned into a very popular cruising area. When we were there it was
                    just deserted. And the work was fascinating.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your principal functions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: We had 2 major NATO offices, Allied Forces Land South East, with a Turkish
                    4- star commanding and a U.S. 2-star as his Deputy. In the old days that had
                    been an American 4-star slot but we changed it around, it's a Turk job now. The
                    Deputy was an American. We had a tactical air force with a Turkish 3-star and an
                    American 2-star as his Deputy.</p>
                <p>I mentioned at lunch that I was delighted and thrilled at the way the American
                    military personnel were behaving in Turkey. We had very few problems, town and
                    gown problems, very few. We had a lot of Americans who had volunteered for
                    Turkey. Some of them in 2nd tours of duty. They obviously liked it. There were a
                    few bad apples, for the most part they behaved well. We had quite a number of
                    ship visits, U.S. ship visits. We had growing U.S. investment. We had the Aegean
                    Sea dispute.</p>
                <p>SIDE B</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>NALLE: So as I was saying, we had increasing American investment. We were trying
                    to attract more. We had the annual Izmir Trade Fair. It was always kind of a
                    cliff hanger, whether or not we were going to participate. It was a joint
                    USIS-State Department-Department of Commerce operation. I think it was very
                    successful. The U.S. pavilion always, after Perils of Pauline kind of
                    adventures, always ended up as one of the most attractive and heavily visited at
                    the fair.</p>
                <p>That was a lot of fun. I used to go down there every night. Spend time at the
                    Pavilion, talking to people, sit around and drink coffee or go to look at the
                    other pavilions and stuff. It was summer and the weather was pleasant. It was
                    just good fun. We had a few individual business companies coming in.</p>
                <p>We had some consular problems but not many. The case that hangs in my mind is the
                    case of Mrs. Jean Lapere. Who is the daughter of the guy who gave that big
                    statue gallery down here on the Smithsonian. You know that round one? Anyway,
                    Mrs. Lapere is the daughter of that man. He's a billionaire, American, who gave
                    his collection of modern sculpture. He built the whole gallery himself, right
                    next to the Air and Space Museum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not the Hirshorn?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Yeah, the Hirshorn. She was Hirshorn's daughter. Well, she got arrested
                    for trying to take antiquities out of Turkey. She claims she didn't know there
                    was such a law. I contended at that time, the daughter of Hirshorn must have
                    goddamn well known something about the business in antiquities, in statues.
                    Particularly in view of her father's record in that matter.</p>
                <p>Well anyway, she was caught and thrown in jail. And such a deluge of
                    congressional attention, I'd never seen in my life. Some of it was sickening. I
                    got a message from Senator Percy saying he didn't know Mrs. Lapere himself, but
                    his children did and therefore she was all right. Therefore, she should be let
                    loose from jail immediately. Pat Schroeder's husband, Jim, came out in person to
                    help Mrs. Lapere get out of jail. Jim Schroeder turned out to be a very nice guy
                    who very quickly realized that there was very little, or nothing, that he could
                    do and went home. He couldn't have been nicer. I spent a lot of time with Jim
                    Schroeder, I've seen him since. And he knew what was up.</p>
                <p>The work we did was unbelievable on behalf of that woman. She got back to the
                    states and wrote a book that's sort of wishy washy. I don't think it
                    acknowledges everything that was done for her, not just by the Post but the
                    whole US government. Jane Lapere left an extraordinarily bitter taste in my
                    mouth. We put it on the line for her and never a word of thanks.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>At the same time we had a young Air Force kid in jail, nobody gave a damn about
                    him. No letters coming in for a black air force sergeant who was in jail. No
                    letters coming in from Senator Percy for him. No letters from the Department.
                    The Department also was pretty craven on this thing. They said—we'll back you
                    up—but they never said, we'll get out in front of you. I felt awfully bitter
                    about the Department's response. No effort what so ever, to take any monkeys off
                    my back.</p>
                <p>I had a superb young officer who did the econ/consular job there. A genius, he's
                    going to be an ambassador to Japan one day. His mother was Japanese, his father
                    was a retired American army officer. He and his wife were both FSOs and they are
                    some of the nicest and brightest young people I've ever worked with in my life.
                    He's studying Chinese now, he's a language freak. He just soaks it up. He did
                    just unbelievable heroic work for Jean Lapere, never a word of thanks. The same
                    for our wonderful FSN staff.</p>
                <p>So we had a little consular work. A great deal of sort of semi-representational
                    work. I've always felt that one of my absolutely essential jobs is traveling
                    around the consular district. Izmir was about the only post in Turkey that did
                    any traveling. Dan Newberry, bless his heart, I'm not ashamed to say this, I
                    used to tell it to him in his face, never left the town limits of Istanbul.
                    Nobody at the embassy in Ankara ever left the embassy for fear that there would
                    be somebody sitting in his desk when he got back. The people down in Adana were
                    too busy to do much traveling. We were the people who had a real travel
                    program.</p>
                <p>I think the only time that anything I ever wrote got over to the White House,
                    came when I was in Izmir. I had been on a long trip, just at the time of the
                    infamous Armenian resolution. Part of my trip was to assess the damage that the
                    Armenian resolution would do to us if it were passed. It was a brutal
                    experience. I made it a point to visit the provincial headquarters of all the
                    political parties. And the anger was palpable. I'd never seen anything like it.
                    One place we got into a real shouting, name-calling, I was using fairly bad
                    language talking to these Turkish politicians about what they were saying about
                    the United States. It was unpleasant, it was not a friendly discourse, it was
                    nasty bitter argumentative disagreeable anger. Bile was being let loose.</p>
                <p>At one point I stopped in to buy gas out in the middle of the Anatolin plateau,
                    along the road. And the old fellow who was pumping gas, started beating my ears
                    about the Armenian resolution. And I put that in as almost an afterthought on
                    what I thought was my more meaty report on the political reaction.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>I got a letter from a friend who said my little thing on the gas station had so
                    caught the eye of the people at the Operations Center that do the briefing
                    books, that they had put it in the Secretary's briefing book. And they were
                    given to understand that it had eventually been sent over to President Reagan
                    for him to see as being on the level of something he could understand it. All
                    this talk of the political parties didn't interest him very much, but this old
                    guy pumping gas, white-bearded old Hajji Bektash kind of fellow pumping gas, was
                    the sort of thing that would grab Reagan's eye. So that I think that is the only
                    time I'd gotten out of the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sentiments ran high in that question.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: We had very major security plans growing up in the event that the
                    resolution might be passed. It was not passed. The Turks just don't understand
                    the American political process. A congressman can introduce something like this,
                    it was Tony Coelho from California of Portuguese background not Armenian
                    himself. And now I believe under strict investigation for corruption in office.
                    He was the one who introduced it because his district is heavily Armenian. And
                    this was done simply to make the Armenians happy and to get him votes.</p>
                <p>The Turks would take the high moral ground and say, this is no way to treat a
                    faithful and loyal ally. By any terms, other than American terms, it is no way
                    to treat a loyal and faithful ally. But Coelho doesn't give a rat's ass about
                    what the Turks think. Coelho wants to get reelected. It's kind of disgusting but
                    you have to put up with it.</p>
                <p>And then we left Izmir, sold my boat and went to Switzerland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, now you're in Europe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Now I'm in Europe, after 30 years in the Foreign Service, in a developed
                    country, and bored to death.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your job there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Counselor for Refugee and Migration Affairs at the US Mission in Geneva.
                    Which was a very anomalous kind of job, I was in the Mission but not of it. The
                    Mission is run by IO. However, my office is not run by IO. I did not report to
                    IO, I had my own budget, I reported to RP, the Office of Refugee Programs. My
                    own budget, my own administrative staff, everything, except that the Ambassador
                    was my boss and that I went to staff meetings. I participated in all the embassy
                    goings-on. But I had a 500 million dollar budget for refugee programs, and I
                    forget what my administrative budget was.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any staff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I had 3 FSOs, 7 locals. It was a very busy job. I was primarily dealing
                    with the UNHCR but I also dealt with, do you remember Jim Carlin?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Jim Carlin was there in what we call ICM, the Intergovernmental Committee
                    on Migration, a very well run organization that Jim worked with for so many
                    years. I dealt with both the ICRC, the International Committee of the Red Cross.
                    I dealt with LiCross, the League of the Red Cross. I developed an unbelievable
                    admiration for the ICRC. It's all Swiss, there are no non-Swiss in it. And the
                    things they could do are incredible. They are the operating arm, you might say,
                    of the Red Cross. Particularly in as far as the treaties regarding
                    prisoners-of-war and all that kind of stuff and refugees are concerned.</p>
                <p>I was sitting in an office there at Geneva, they had a little headquarters in
                    Geneva, talking to one of the fellows who was the Director of East African
                    Affairs. I asked him a question and he said, “I'm not sure of that, wait a
                    minute.” Then he held what I thought was a telephone on his desk, he picked it
                    up and said something in French. Then he continued, “I have Mr. Nalle of the
                    American mission here and he asked me about this problem in Kenya. What can you
                    tell me?” They talked on the phone back and forth for a minute. Then he hung up.
                    Yes, he said, that was my agent, my representative in Nairobi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good communication system.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Then I remembered there was an antennae field a couple of miles out of
                    town out of Geneva, along the lake. That was always said to be, theoretically it
                    was classified but everybody always said the ICRC antenna farm for all their
                    communications. A very well run and efficient organization.I might dwell, if I
                    could, on the political ambassador there. He is the 4th political ambassador I
                    have worked for and he epitomizes everything that is wrong with political
                    appointees. The others I worked for—Ferguson was an intelligent, thoughtful,
                    hardworking, receptive man. Strausz-Hup� I did not get along with him at all, I
                    did not agree with his political opinions, I didn't agree with the way he was
                    handling Turkey, I'd have disagreed with him if he had said it's black, I'd have
                    said it's white. But he was an able, intelligent, ill-tempered mean little man.
                    I watched him at an archeological ruin translating the Greek and Roman
                    inscriptions on the stones which not many career ambassadors could do today. So
                    Strausz-Hup� was there.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>Well this one was Gerry Carmen and his claim to fame was that he had been
                    Chairman of the Republican State Committee of New Hampshire and had delivered
                    New Hampshire to Ronald Reagan. He was a used tire salesman. Everything that was
                    wrong could be wrong. He hated the Foreign Service, he hated Foreign Service
                    people. I have watched him twist and torture his Admin Officer till the guy had
                    tears running down his cheeks. The Admin Officer was no genius but he was
                    perfectly competent. He had the mission running and running well. He was saving
                    money, he was doing a good job, he just wasn't very dynamic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was this man's DCM?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Ron Flack when I was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know Ron.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Poor Ron was suffering, you can't imagine how Ron suffered under this
                    guy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is our ambassador in Bern?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: In Geneva, the US Mission in Geneva.</p>
                <p>He could speak no French. I suppose that's all right, I don't speak that much
                    myself, I can get along. He held the UN in contempt. He was an anti-UN guy. As I
                    say, he hated FSOs, FSO people, he hated the diplomatic life, he was the
                    laughing stock of the diplomatic community in Geneva. My colleagues would come
                    up to me and make jokes about him and I had to defend him, much as the thought
                    filled me with horror.</p>
                <p>He got after me one time. My predecessor had quit because of him. They're on a
                    round-the-world tour inspecting refugee camps and my predecessor, Carl Beck,
                    sent a cable from Bangkok where they were, saying that he wanted an immediate
                    transfer, that he could no longer get along with him (Ambassador Carmen). That
                    relations were such that he had to leave. And the Department sent back a
                    soothing message saying, yes, of course, as soon as you get back to Geneva we'll
                    arrange for your transfer. Carl cabled them back and said, “You guys don't
                    understand, I want a transfer, now, from Thailand.” And they gave it to him.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>I got into a fight with him one time. He wanted to do some inspecting of refugee
                    camps in Africa, which we all thought was probably a good idea to get him out of
                    Geneva for a couple of days, if nothing else. But he wanted to go to Washington
                    first and he wanted me to pay for his ticket out of my RP budget. I said, “Mr.
                    Ambassador, I really can't do that. We can get down to Africa from Geneva very
                    quickly and easily, Swissair flies down there everyday.” But no, he wanted to go
                    into Washington first. Well, I said, I really can't do it. I'll tell you what I
                    said, “I'll write a first person cable, I'll put your case to them in the
                    strongest words I can, you can sign it, read it, do whatever you want. But I
                    cannot pay for the ticket until I have written orders.”He said, “Oh Beau, you
                    fancy pants State Department guys.” Those are his very words. “You fancy pants
                    State Department guys, call somebody, your hotshot friends back in Washington,
                    they'll cut a deal.” I said, “I'm sorry Mr. Ambassador, I need written orders
                    from the Department.” And he said, “Come on, call one of your friends, they'll
                    take care of it for you. Nobody has to know about this.” I lost my temper. I
                    stood up and said, “Make your own fucking phone calls Mr. Ambassador,” and I
                    walked out of his office.</p>
                <p>From then on he practically never bothered me. He'd kid me at staff meetings,
                    “You all watch out for Beau, he has a quick temper.” And I looked down at him
                    one time and I said, “Yes sir, I do,” and I smiled at him. But I mean, what he
                    did for the United States was disaster piled up on chaos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By the way, did he go to Africa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: No. He couldn't stick it to Washington. And then he forgot.</p>
                <p>Another thing. AID had bought some German trucks, Mercedes trucks, for use in
                    Sudan, in their refugee operations in Sudan. This is long before I got there.
                    But shortly after I got there, I got a phone call from the Ambassador in his
                    office upstairs and he said, “Beau, what's this truck deal?” I'd only been there
                    a couple of days, I said, “Mr. Ambassador, what truck deal are you talking
                    about, I'm not familiar with it yet.” He said, “AID has a lot of German trucks.”
                    I said, “I don't know about it, let me check. I'll get back to you.”</p>
                <p>So I pulled out the file, John Campbell, my assistant, and I looked through it.
                    We discovered that AID needed trucks, they had gone to all the major American
                    truck companies with the specs that they had, the American truck companies don't
                    build trucks like that. Another example of American industry at its best. We
                    don't do anything like that. AID went to Mercedes. Mercedes, said, yes sure, we
                    can give you 50 of those next week. AID got a congressional waiver on the
                    purchase of foreign goods. Went ahead and bought the trucks.</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>Well, it turned out that they weren't all as good as they were all cracked up to
                    be, they kept breaking down. So the cost of maintenance was getting pretty high
                    and there was a lot of cable traffic. And Carmen got on to it and he got on to
                    me. And kept badgering me about these trucks and I kept saying, “Mr. Ambassador,
                    AID signed the trucks deal before I got here.” He put it on grounds that it was
                    sort of my fault that AID bought these trucks. I said, they bought the trucks
                    before I ever got to Geneva. It looks like it's a pretty bum deal but there it
                    is. They complied with the law, the law provides that under certain
                    circumstances AID can go outside of US channels for procurement. They got the
                    necessary congressional waiver. That means that the Congressmen from Detroit,
                    and Michigan, and General Motors, Chrysler, Ford either didn't object or voted
                    in favor. There's nothing more that could be done of it.</p>
                <p>Every staff meeting almost for 2 years, he'd beat me about on head and shoulders
                    about these trucks. I just got to the point where I didn't pay any attention to
                    it.</p>
                <p>He gave a series of conferences on the free enterprise system, which were
                    actually not bad conferences. But he wanted me to provide funds out of my
                    representation funds for these conferences. “Mr. Ambassador,” I said, “I'm in
                    the refugee business, I'm not in the free enterprise world.” I said, I'm all for
                    it but I can't misuse representation funds. He got after me, and after me, and
                    after me.</p>
                <p>Finally, Ron Flack said, “Beau, I don't want to tell you how to run your
                    business, but you can be in real trouble if you don't come through with
                    something for the Ambassador's conferences.” So I signed a voucher for I think
                    $150.00 or whatever. I never got caught but if an inspector got hold of it, I
                    think I'd have been medevaced back. Carmen would never have given me a hand.</p>
                <p>So I quit. I knew I was going to be selected out, I said, screw it. And came
                    home. The Department with its usual warmth and friendship and one thing or
                    another. I went through the retirement seminar and they gave you that little
                    card. You know, I have 2 Foreign Service stories I love. They gave me this
                    little card that said blah-blah-blah, always performed, loyal, valuable,
                    honorable service. I looked down on it and I discovered they spelled my name
                    wrong.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:You gotta have confidence in the system.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: The other one, was one time in Guatemala. We used to have to take the
                    classified pouch over on pro-courier service over to Guatemala City. I took the
                    pouch over one day. Then you get to spend a couple of days leave. Guatemala is a
                    beautiful country, I would go bird-watching with my wife. She'd collect orchids
                    and I'd watch birds.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>One time I got over there and thought I should visit the DCM. So I went up to his
                    office, hot, sweaty, wearing a guyabara and I said to his secretary—well I'm
                    here, I guess I ought to stick my head in and say hello. She said, well as a
                    matter of fact, he's leaving tomorrow to go someplace. But he's free right now,
                    why don't you pop in. I said, sure if he doesn't mind that I'm like this. She
                    looked at me and said, I guess not. We were pretty informal in Belize, it's a
                    place where you have to be informal. So I walked into the office and there was
                    this guy in a white shirt, necktie, beautiful silk suit, polished tasseled
                    loafers, the whole bit. He got up with his manly friendly FSO smile, stuck his
                    hand out, and shook hands and said, “Did you go to Princeton?” I said, “Hell,
                    no.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What a way to introduce yourself.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: What a way to start off. But you know, would I do it all over again. I'm
                    100% certain I would. I had some wonderful times. Did I make any friends? I
                    don't really think so. I don't think Foreign Service people make friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It depends on what you call friends. You mean friends in
                        your foreign posts?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: No, I mean American.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, some of your colleagues obviously.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: George is a good friend. But he quit the foreign service 15 years ago to
                    work for NOA. I understand he's done very well over there. I didn't make many
                    friends. I'm not the kind of person who makes friends, I think that is one of
                    the problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well you were obviously at interesting situations in
                        interesting times.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I went to some wonderful posts. What would get me to do it all over again
                    would be the ability to spend 4 years in Uganda or 3 years in Belize or 11 years
                    in Turkey. But forget about the Foreign Service.</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>More to the point, did I or did any of my colleagues, did I ever make foreign
                    policy? Never. I don't think I saw a Secretary of State more than 2 times in my
                    life. I carried up Ambassadors up to see Dean Rusk. The last thing he wanted to
                    do was to muck around with a bunch of Africans. He had other fish to fry. He'd
                    always say when the meeting was over, “Mr. Ambassador, it's been wonderful to
                    see you and please remember, anytime you have any problems whatsoever, don't
                    hesitate one instant to call Mr. uh Mr. uh” He'd look at the briefing paper.
                    “Mr. Nalle here, your Desk Officer will be very glad to help you out.”</p>
                <p>You don't, except with very rare occasions, really get involved in the policy
                    making business.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well that's a whole another discussion. Whether foreign
                        service officers should be making policy or not.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: All right, influencing policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Influencing is another thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: But I didn't do that really. I did play a role in Belizean independence.
                    Well, hell's pecker, the world's not going to stop turning around because Belize
                    is independent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well you also obviously had some things in Uganda. The
                        Department must have had to pay attention to the things you were
                        saying.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I don't really think so. I was told, long before I had a chance to make my
                    opinions known, that our relationship with Uganda would be unchanged. They
                    didn't ask me for my opinion, they told me how it was going to be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's the point I was trying to make. That officers in
                        the field have little opportunity to make policies.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: That's declining.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's declining now? I'm afraid it is. Although the thing
                        that encourages me is, and I think it probably encourages you if you think
                        about it, are the quality of the people you brought in 20 years ago and the
                        quality of the people I brought in 25 years ago. Now rising to the top.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I'm not so sure they're all that damn good.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Many of them were good.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Many of them were, and many of them remind me of the young man I noticed
                    one time when I was in a reception in Nairobi when Bob McIlvaine was Ambassador.
                    He was talking to a Minister of Kenya, the Minister of Defense. The National War
                    College was there, we had a joint East African briefing. The Minister of Defense
                    poured beer down his front and Bob was talking to this guy and the junior FSO.
                    It was obvious that the Minister's beer needed replenishing. And Bob turned to
                    the junior, and said, “Would you mind getting the Minister another beer,” very
                    politely. The guy said, “I'm not a butler.” That's the new breed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm sorry that isn't the new breed that I handled.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I'm not all that impressed with them. There are some bright ones, sure
                    there are.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any last comments you would like to make?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I've got a lot of them</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's have them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Another point I have is one I've thought about. I'm not certain that being
                    all that smart is an asset. I don't think you have to be a goddamn genius to do
                    the bulk of the work that we do in the Foreign Service. Now, if you go to some
                    of our critical posts, yes. Ability of the highest order is required. But to be
                    anything from Charg� D'affaires to Admin Officer in Uganda, you don't have to be
                    all that smart.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You can't be a dummy either.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: Can't be a dummy. You've got to be what Harold Nicholson called, “a humane
                    skeptic.” I'm reading some of Nicholson's books right now, half way through
                    “Curzon.” Curzon strikes me as one of the dumbest guys to come down the pike.
                    Not dumb but inept.</p>
                <p>Anyway, I often think, they used to say that the qualifications for the Foreign
                    Service, were a smattering of French, a good tailor and a private income. And
                    maybe that's not such a bad policy after all.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>I'm perfectly serious. You don't have to be another George Kennan or a Chip
                    Bohlen or a Tom Pickering or a Raymond Hare, to do a vast number of jobs in the
                    service. And I think we're trying to oversell the business too much perhaps.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You see, when those people you mentioned rose to the top,
                        we were glad that they were men of character and extremely bright. Now I
                        agree with you, they do not need this when they're on the visa line in
                        Jamaica or in Manila or other places. They are pounding those things out day
                        by day. That's the way we start out in the Foreign Service. But we're always
                        looking for our people to rise to the senior positions where we do want them
                        to be bright.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: There will be a few who will always be there. But people should not get it
                    into their heads that they're going to be the people who are providing advice on
                    the conduct of relations of this great country of ours. They may be providing
                    advice but it won't be listened to.</p>
                <p>And finally women and wives. My dear wife used to say, kind of sadly, she sort of
                    wished somewhere along the line, somebody had said, “Thank you.” Never once did
                    she feel that anybody had ever taken into consideration her interest, her
                    abilities, she was a Political Science honors graduate from Bryn Mawr College.
                    That nobody had ever stopped to consider that she was a living person. She was
                    regarded as a machine by everybody. Even the good ambassadors tended to just
                    take her and her colleagues as something that was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a shame. This is inexcusable.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: She just dropped out of the Foreign Service. She did a little bit in
                    Turkey, she likes Turks. But in Switzerland, she'd say, “You want to have a
                    party, go ahead have a party. I'll just go upstairs and read a book.” Her cancer
                    was also starting to be very serious. But she was just fed-up. We'd get invited
                    out and she'd say, “I'm not going. I don't need to sit next to the (whatever
                    they might be) Taiwanese Charg� D'affaires or I don't need to sit next to the
                    Director of the African branch of the ICRC. I don't want to talk to them, I'm
                    not interested in them.”</p>
                <p>And this attitude came directly from the fact that she had been, and all wives, I
                    think, generally, just so ignored and neglected. When she had things to do, like
                    the school boards in Africa, she was just thrilled. But the fact that she was
                    sent out to Iskenderun without one minute of Turkish language was just
                    inexcusable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>NALLE: And this happened to dozens and dozens of other wives. I don't see much
                    improvement except in the case of working couples now. Where you have a career
                    wife who is able to find a job in her own career. But the wife who goes along to
                    support and be helpful, my impression is, is just as bad off as Sheila was 30
                    years ago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And yet in many posts we have opportunities for these
                        wives that just go along to take language lessons.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I've never seen that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My wife has taken them at several posts and found them
                        very useful. Three posts, I know of.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: I can't remember any place where we had a functioning language program. It
                    was always something the Inspectors fussed about. But nothing ever came of
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well Beau, I want to thank you and unless you have any
                        final comments, we'll wrap it up. I want to thank you for being very frank
                        and very good in your comments.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>NALLE: It's a mixed bag.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
