<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000461">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Philip C. Habib </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>UNDER SECRETARY PHILIP C. HABIB</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Edward Mulcahy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 24, 1984</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, Phil, here are our first questions.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: You wanted to know whether or not my parents were married in the States.
                    Yes they were. They came here to the United States with their families. Well, my
                    father came individually as a young man. He was in his late teens, I guess. His
                    older brother had come before him. What they were doing was escaping the Turks.
                    My mother had come over with her brothers, and they met in the States and were
                    married in the States. They came in the latter part of the 19th century from
                    Lebanon. They didn't know each other before they came.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What towns did they come from?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: My father came from the Sidon area, my mother came from a little town
                    north of Beirut. I suppose it was one of those semi-arranged things in the sense
                    that someone decided that this man would make a good husband, and someone
                    decided they better get rid of their sister and mutual arrangements were made.
                    They were married in New York.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were both Maronites.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>HABIB: No, my mother was not a Maronite, my father was a Maronite, but naturally
                    in the States we were raised in the Roman Catholic church when we were kids,
                    except on special occasions we'd go to the Maronite church. But I can also
                    remember going with my mother to church. They're all under the jurisdiction of
                    Rome so it was part of the greater Universal Catholic Church. Like so many of
                    those people, of course, when they immigrated, they brought their families. For
                    example, my father's older brother came, then he came, and when they had settled
                    in they brought his younger brother and his mother who was the only one left in
                    the family. Their father had died when they were young. So my grandmother came
                    with them. I remember she lived with us until she passed away, I was about 7 or
                    8 years old. And naturally, as a result I would presume the language spoken in
                    the home was always Arabic, but I was the youngest in the family. As a result by
                    the time I was growing up English began to replace Arabic, so we spoke a mixed
                    language in the home. They would speak to me in Arabic, and I would answer in
                    English and as a result my Arabic is not as good as my older brothers, or my
                    sister who spoke better Arabic than I did. And then I left home when I was 18
                    years old and went to school, so it all faded. My association with that
                    immigrant ethnic world faded when I went west to go to school. As you probably
                    know I was born in Brooklyn, lived almost all of my early life in an area of
                    Brooklyn called Bensonhurst, which was about...I think, even in that district
                    today, the Congress has more Jewish voters than any other district in the United
                    States. It was an almost solidly ethnic Jewish neighborhood that my immediate
                    congressman's home was in. And I went to school...on Jewish holidays, for
                    example, the school would practically shut down. I never went to school on a
                    Jewish holiday.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You probably learned more Yiddish than Arabic.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>Habib: I learned a little bit of Yiddish. I learned how to curse in Yiddish very
                    early in my life. But I was also what they called in Yiddish, the shoppers boy.
                    The one who goes around and light the fires on Fridays. It was a fairly orthodox
                    neighborhood. Sometime I'll send you a tape that I made. I was speaking at a
                    Jewish Federation meeting not long ago, and one of my childhood friends was
                    there. I had seen that he was invited, he was the president of another Jewish
                    Federation. All my childhood friends were Jewish, everyone. And they asked me at
                    this meeting after dinner one night to reminisce about what it was like to grow
                    up in a Jewish neighborhood in Brooklyn, and somebody taped it. It was very
                    spontaneous, very extemporaneous. I'll send the tape because its a very amusing
                    account, you know what it was like, and never dreaming, of course, that 50 or 60
                    years later I would be involved in events that are fundamental to both. In fact,
                    the State of Israel and Lebanon all of it came together in my old age. The
                    primary school I went to was just a block and a half from where I lived. Within
                    a radius of two blocks there were two synagogues, one of them was Sephardic, and
                    one of them was Ashkenazic. One of them catered to a community of Jews that had
                    come from Syria, interesting enough, Syrian Sephardic Jews. And then there was
                    the other group that were the Eastern European immigrants—Russians, Polish Jews,
                    Romanian Jews, and the categories were all there. At any rate, they didn't have
                    many German Jews because they were the elite, they lived up on Riverside Drive
                    and Ocean Parkway, they didn't live down where we were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Sephardic, they still spoke...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Habib: They spoke Arabic. The group that I lived with when I was a boy at the age
                    of about 7 until I went to university at 18, we were a very tightly knit group.
                    There were about 8 to 10 of us at various times, never any more. We were
                    organized...in those days you had these cellar clubs. We had a clubroom in the
                    basement of one of our member's homes. I was the only non-Jew in the group.
                    Three of them were Sephardic, Syrian Jews, the rest of them were of Eastern
                    European origin. Some of them Orthodox, some of them Reform. It was a very
                    amusing mix, of course, in many ways, it's very unique. And of course it made me
                    very early in life aware of not only Jewishness, but it also made me aware of
                    anti-Semitism because, being that I traveled in that crowd, I was one of them
                    and everything they felt, I felt. Well, beyond that anti-Semitism is basically
                    directed against Jews, and beyond that people would assume that I was Jewish
                    even though I wasn't, especially if you come from Brooklyn. If you have a big
                    nose, automatically you have to be Jewish. So all my life I've been very
                    sensitive to that problem of anti-Semitism, so its a factor.</p>
                <p>About two years ago now when I sort of became notorious in international service,
                    the teacher from the primary school I went to wrote me a letter saying, the
                    students here are following you because they all know that you went to this
                    grade school, and sometime would you correspond with them. So I wrote her and
                    said, I'll come and visit you, and I finally got around to it.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a public school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: A public school, PS 205 in Brooklyn. And I finally got around and visited
                    the school, and they had a day in my honor. The children had obviously been
                    following me because in their classrooms they had pictures of me, and they had
                    pictures of the various countries where I'd been. They were using it to give the
                    kids a little feeling, at a young age, for international things, including
                    geography. And by golly if they didn't turn up one of my teachers, my sixth
                    grade teacher, and I remembered him because he was remarkable...Harry Weber was
                    his name. He was retired, an old man of course, and he and his wife came to this
                    day in the school. It was a wonderful day. There was a full spread on the front
                    page of the New York Post, with pictures and all after the occasion. It was one
                    of those experiences that you remember. The kids used to write to me, and I'd
                    sometimes write back to their teacher so they'd know I hadn't forgotten
                    them.</p>
                <p>Incidentally, it was that teacher particularly, Harry Weber, Harry remembered me,
                    and he remembered me because I was very interested in the world and how to get
                    places, and how to travel, and I was. Harry remembered, even I didn't remember.
                    He must have records from his teaching days. He remembered we got to talking
                    about different parts of the world, and I was telling the class about different
                    parts of the world, and he asked me how I knew this, and of course I got the
                    travel folders and all that sort of thing. I was very interested in the
                    world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sounds like my students(?).</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>HABIB: Well, that's the way you develop your interest to carry on in life. I was
                    always interested in geography, always interested in out-of-doors, nature. I was
                    very much involved in nature. I was a boy scout. I was always outdoors. On
                    weekends I would go hiking. We used to go up to the Palisades, the Bear Mountain
                    area up into the hills. If we didn't have that long we'd go out on Long Island
                    where there was a little bit of greenery. And then in the last couple of years
                    before I left, especially when I got out of high school, we got to going up to
                    Fire Island. Fire Island has gotten notorious since for other reasons, but in
                    those days there was an end to Fire Island that was a State Park down by the
                    lighthouse. It was sand dunes and very open and you could go there and you could
                    camp. We used to set up our tents. I remember in my sixteenth year when I
                    graduated from high school, I spent a few weeks out there, just living alone. My
                    friends would come over on the weekends. There were no roads to that place,
                    you'd take the ferry to get there. I just loved the out of doors, and when I
                    graduated from high school of course there was no money, it was the middle of
                    the depression and I couldn't go to university, but I was taken up with this
                    idea of making my life out of doors. When I graduated from high school I went to
                    work after I'd had that little vacation on Fire Island. I went to work in a
                    factory in Brooklyn. It was a sheet metal plant manufacturing metal boxes, metal
                    cabinets, metal medicine cabinets, and I was the shipping clerk. We assembled
                    the medicine cabinets, put the mirrors in them, packed them and prepared them
                    for shipping. It was the first job I ever had. I was sixteen years old, I got
                    paid $10 a week for a 52 hour a week. And when I left it two years later I was
                    making $15 a week, but I had a deal with my father. My father was a grocer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That grocery background...all my mother's family were
                        grocers.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: My father had worked in a bank up until the crash of '32 when his bank
                    went under. He began doing odd jobs, he was an accountant—he knew how to keep
                    books. My father was an educated man, he had gone to St. Joseph's College, the
                    Merrimack college as a boy. He was educated in the French tradition and spoke
                    excellent French. My mother spoke French also, interestingly, because she came
                    from an educated family. But my father said, we have no money to send you to
                    school. If you want to go to school, you go to work, get a job, you don't have
                    to contribute to the house.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I was the youngest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of how many?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>HABIB: Four. There had been five but one had died as an infant. The other three,
                    my two brothers and my sister, worked and contributed to the family, when they
                    could get work. That was a complicated story too in those days. I remember my
                    oldest brother working under WPA. I can also remember him on strike when he was
                    working in the garment trade, he went on strike and he was fired. He later
                    became a union official. As a matter of fact he was well known in the garment
                    workers' union, my oldest brother. He was a brilliant man, died very young. All
                    my family died young.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He must have been a token Christian in the garment
                        industry.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, he was one of Dubinsky's people. He was an organizer and then he
                    became a business agent. He's still remembered. The old timers all remember him
                    because he really was a brilliant man. But in any event my father said to me,
                    you save your money. So every Saturday when I would get paid, I would give to my
                    father my pay, and he would put it away for me. The factory I worked for was in
                    Brooklyn, so I used to ride my bicycle to work so I wouldn't have to pay subway
                    fare, 5 cents. The factory was on Bergen Street, it was about a 45 minute bike
                    ride from our house, and I used to cycle to work and cycle back to save five
                    cents, which is what you were saving, five cents each way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I used to do that when I was in college.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I used to take my lunch naturally, or if I didn't take my lunch we used to
                    be able to get— for 15 cents—you could get a pretty good lunch in those days, a
                    bowl of soup and a sandwich, 15 cents. At any rate, I saved my money. I went to
                    work in 1936 when I graduated from high school. In 1938 I applied to go to
                    school. I didn't tell my father I was doing all this. I remember I applied at
                    Syracuse, which had a school of forestry because that's what I wanted to go
                    into—my interest in the out of doors, nature, natural things was very great.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Seeing so few trees in Brooklyn.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: We used to see a lot of them on the weekends too. But I also applied at
                    the University of Idaho, and I was accepted. I was accepted at all of them, but
                    I decided to go to the University of Idaho.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get a scholarship?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>HABIB: Well, I'll tell you a story. No, I was out of school, I was never a very
                    good student in high school, I was too busy having fun. By this time I was 18
                    years old. So I went to my father and said all right, I've been accepted at this
                    school, the course starts in September, and I want to go, where is my money that
                    I've been giving you for two years? For two years I had been giving my father
                    this money. And my father looked at me and said, things got very difficult, and
                    he had to use the money for the upkeep of the family, these are not easy times.
                    And the money was not there. Of course, I got absolutely furious. I was terribly
                    upset. My brother, my father, they were all supportive, nobody blamed my father.
                    After all, he wasn't putting the money on the ponies, he was a very devout, very
                    serious family man, he supported the family with the aid of my brothers and
                    sister who would bring home small sums of money. Pop had a grocery store on
                    Atlantic Avenue, which was the heart of Lebanese community.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My sister lived on Atlantic Avenue.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I was born on 8th Street which is right off Atlantic Avenue. That's
                    becoming a very nice area now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A lot of Arabs live there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: There, on the avenue, you'd be surprised. Those brownstones are getting so
                    expensive. They're being fixed up by the young couples who work on Wall
                    Street.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like my son-in-law.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: At any rate, it was decided that I would go to school. I remember very
                    well. I took a bus. My father gave me some money and my oldest brother—the one I
                    told you by that time was working for International Labor Union...my oldest
                    brother who had been a brilliant student, he graduated from high school, I
                    think, when he was 14 years old, and had received a full scholarship to go to
                    Rutgers University. He was the top student in the state of Jersey at that
                    time—we were living there for a few years—he didn't go because times were rough,
                    and they didn't want this young boy to go away from the family. So he had gone
                    to night school at Brooklyn Poly, studying chemistry in fact. He was then
                    working in this trade union, and he said he'd see what he could do to help me
                    with money. I remember, I think I left home with $90 in my pocket and a bus
                    ticket. I went across the continent by bus, and the bus ticket was such that I
                    didn't have to spend a night anywhere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would have been about when?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>HABIB: 1938, the Fall of '38 I went to Idaho, across the continent in a bus. I
                    never got out of the bus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You hadn't been west of the Hudson by then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Well, I'd been to New Jersey, that's as far west as I'd ever been. I rode
                    across the country in a bus day and night, maybe you'd have to wait an hour or
                    two to connect with another bus, a Greyhound Line went right on through—into
                    Spokane, south of Spokane down to Moscow, Idaho. I remember the fare was
                    somewhere less than 100 bucks, and that was my first glimpse of the great United
                    States, and it was a very impressive thing for an 18 year old kid. I can still
                    see the moon when we were driving across South Dakota and North Dakota, the
                    Dakotas by moonlight I remember that. And it was a beautiful trip. At any rate,
                    I arrived in Moscow, Idaho, I didn't have a room to stay, I didn't know where I
                    was going to stay, I didn't know anybody, didn't know a soul. I went up to
                    register and they had a place there where you could room and board. I roomed in
                    a home, I couldn't afford a dormitory, I roomed in a home with a family, I had a
                    roommate. We had a little attic room in this house, two of us, Daryl and myself.
                    I used to have to walk quite a ways to get to the campus, but it was cheap. And
                    I started the first semester, and fortunately I got very good grades the first
                    semester. I remember the Dean called me in and offered me a scholarship to pay
                    for my tuition. The tuition at that time was $100. So I got the scholarship and
                    I didn't have to pay my tuition, and I never had to pay tuition again in the
                    next 3-1/2 years at the university. They maintained this tuition-free...well, I
                    lived with this family for a while, and then the next summer I went to work in
                    the woods...I never came home the whole while I was in university, couldn't
                    afford the trip. As a matter of fact, I didn't see my family until I was a 2nd
                    lieutenant in the Army in 1942. Meanwhile my mother had died, and I never saw my
                    mother again. I saw my father for the first time in 1942 when I graduated from
                    OCS in Ft. Belvoir, Virginia. My father came down to see me graduate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you do ROTC?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: You did two years of ROTC but I didn't take advanced ROTC, so I was
                    drafted in 1942. As soon as I graduated from college, I was in the Army within
                    one month.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, now back to your summer jobs.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>HABIB: I used to work in the woods. The first summer I worked for the Forest
                    Service on the blister rust control program, which is a disease of white pine. I
                    worked in the woods the entire summer, and in those days you could work in the
                    woods and save your salary. We didn't get paid huge amounts, but you got a bunk,
                    you got your food—we lived in tents the first summer up in the St. Joe National
                    Forest, in northern Idaho. We'd go out early in the morning, work all day, and
                    come back at night.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this treating trees?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: What we were doing was removing the alternate host. The alternate host for
                    this disease is the gooseberry family, Ribes, wild gooseberries. They're the
                    alternate host. In order for the disease to spread it has to have an alternate
                    host, and we used to eradicate the Ribes. It was called the Blister Rust Control
                    Program. As a matter of fact, over the years it was done and it was quite
                    effective, otherwise you'd lost all the white pines in Idaho. In any event, I'd
                    work all summer, save my money and when I'd go back to school in the Fall I
                    would have enough money to get through. There was another program at that time
                    called NYA, National Youth Administration. The National Youth Administration had
                    a program which you could earn, as I remember...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: $40 a week.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, no, it wasn't that much. When it started out it was $13 a month you
                    could earn under NYA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We made 40 cents an hour.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: 25 cents an hour. I'm earlier than you possibly. Anyway, the NYA would
                    take students. The first year I was in NYA I was swabbing out johns in the
                    dormitory. Then I got the cushy job the next year, I was custodian, librarian,
                    or whatever you want to call it, of the School of Forestry Methodology
                    Collection, dried fungus. I used to have to keep the cards made out, and the
                    filing of them, and the records, and that sort of thing, of the dried fungus
                    collection which was a very nice job. I could work anytime I was free. At any
                    rate, I got that $13 a month. And the second year I was there I had saved enough
                    money by working in the summer on the Blister Control Project. And I got along
                    fairly well. I was still wearing the suit that I'd graduated in from high school
                    for my best suit. I remember it had a Clark Gable back. Do you remember the
                    Clark Gable...pleated in back...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And a belt.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>HABIB: It was a blue suit that my father had bought for me for $17, I remember it
                    very well. I remember the bargaining that he went through to get me that suit
                    for $17. I'll never forget it. But in any event, what we would generally do is
                    we'd buy a good stout pair of pants in the fall after we came out of the woods,
                    forest green twill trousers, and enough shirts to get you through, a sweater and
                    a coat for the winter, and that was it, and you'd go through the winter. And
                    then come Spring you'd go out in the woods, wear out that pair of pants, and
                    then you'd get another pair of pants for the Fall. I did that each year. That
                    was great. The first year I had a full summer's work, and then I was a
                    sophomore. In that school there was a summer camp and you had to go to summer
                    school, and that was a shattering thing because it meant...eight or ten weeks
                    and that was a period when you couldn't work. Not only that, you had to pay fees
                    and tuition, room and board.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That would have been about 19...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: The summer of 1939...I'm trying to remember what I did in the summer of
                    '39. Oh, it was the summer of '40 and the summer of '41...now what did I do the
                    other two summers? There's a gap in my memory and I'll have to figure it out.
                    One of them I know what I did, and then I know what I started out to do before I
                    went into the Army...there's a gap in my memory, I'll have to figure that gap
                    out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a long time ago.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It's a long time ago. Anyhow, the summer camp thing really put a crimp in
                    me, it was terrible. As a matter of fact, when the summer camp was over I went
                    right to work fighting forest fires as part of a fire fighting crew.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was tough.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Nothing is tough when you're 20 years old, and I was in very good physical
                    condition, lean, tough and muscular.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they have Indian fire fighters up there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>HABIB: No, we were all various mixtures of anything, but they were not solid
                    crews. There were a lot of CCC crews in those days. But we were treated a little
                    bit differently by the rangers because we were forestry students, and they would
                    use us to supervise a group, even as a student. But I fought fires all over
                    northern Idaho, I mean big fires, forest fires, and learned a great deal about
                    how to do that. But I remember that summer when I had to go to summer camp was
                    so difficult because when I got back to school in the Fall...I remember very
                    well, it was two weeks before the opening of school. We had a nursery in the
                    school, and the guy who ran the nursery, the manager, was a friend of all of us,
                    and he let me sleep above his garage. He had a cot up there and I slept on that
                    cot. I got myself a part-time job...that's an area around Moscow, Idaho where
                    they're famous for seed peas, and there was a seed cleaning and packing plant.
                    These are seed peas and they're packed in 50 pound sacks, 100 pound sacks. And
                    my job, which was the night shift, was to clean the sacks by putting them up
                    against an air blower. I'd clean the sacks and then I would stack sacks, eight
                    hours a night, 25 cents an hour and I'd work eight hours a night. I did that for
                    about two weeks, in the daytime I was living in this little area above a garage.
                    I remember very well what I used to do. I was desperate to save money because I
                    needed the money to get me through the school year. For breakfast every morning
                    I would get some apples—there were plenty of apples around free—I'd eat apples,
                    I'd buy a loaf of bread and a jar of peanut butter, and I'd eat peanut butter
                    sandwiches and apples. And then one meal a day I'd go down to this greasy-spoon
                    where for 25 cents you could get a three course meal, soup, the main course, and
                    dessert, and I managed to save a few more dollars. But still no money. So that
                    year was a very bad year for me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was your junior year.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>HABIB: That was my junior year. It ruined my grades in the sense that was the
                    year when my grades fell off because now to get through the school year, what
                    did I do? I started out in the Fall, I had a NYA job, I was living with Roy
                    Keeler, a kid from Wyoming in a little room that wasn't big enough to swing a
                    cat in, the two of us had shared. The house was the only Chinese family in town,
                    they ran a Chinese restaurant. The only Chinese family in the town of Moscow,
                    and Roy Keeler and I lived in a room above them that they were renting out to
                    roomers. And I washed dishes in a greasy-spoon restaurant, I remembered it was
                    called the Bangles Cafe. Bangles was a sports game. And I washed dishes, and let
                    me tell you every single day in the summer time I was down there washing dishes
                    in that restaurant, and on weekends it was long hours, particularly on Saturday
                    night. The net result was that with the NYA job, washing the dishes, living in
                    these cramped quarters, my grades just plummeted. Whereas I'd been getting A's.
                    The first two years that I was in the School of Forestry in Idaho, I was the top
                    student. I got the highest grade of any student. There's a bronze plaque still
                    on the wall of the School of Forestry where every year they put the name of the
                    student in each grade who had the highest grade. When I was in Idaho last year
                    for a special occasion, I was the distinguished Idahoan of the year and they
                    gave me an award. It was a very nice occasion. The plaque with my name on it as
                    the student with the highest grades for the years '38-'39, '39-'40 was there.
                    Not for '40-'41 or '41-'42 because my grades just fell off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When your grades dropped did you jeopardize your...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, they kept you going. The Dean liked me and kept me going. By that time
                    I had established the reputation as the best student, so no matter what happened
                    it hung on. I never lost the scholarship interestingly. The Dean was very nice
                    to me. For some reason or other he liked me. You know, professors get to like
                    certain students, and he liked me. And I think the fact that I had gotten the
                    highest grades the first two years, nevertheless my reputation was great. But at
                    any rate, that was a very rough year because I'd fall asleep in classes. As a
                    matter of fact there was a great picture in the annual for one year of me sound
                    asleep in a classroom. The reason they put it in was because that was not a
                    common posture I was in. I was tired.</p>
                <p>Well, it came to the big year, and I realized I couldn't go on this way. Then
                    something very nice happened. The group of boys that I had known as a child in
                    Brooklyn, the Lone Eagles we called ourselves, that was the name of our Club,
                    the Lone Eagles. We had rayon jackets with Lone Eagles on the back. The Lone
                    Eagles, with whom I had corresponded at various times, the Lone Eagles knew
                    about my predicament, and they gave me $100, a lot of money. I took the $100, I
                    quit the job at the Bangles Cafe, and I moved into a cooperative dormitory. I
                    had the NYA job, I had the $100, and I had whatever few bucks might have been
                    left over from what I'd earned the previous summer fighting fires and working in
                    the pea factory. And that got me through the second semester, living in this
                    cooperative dormitory where we could live...these dormitories were wonderful.
                    They were wooden buildings, two to a room, a little tiny room...</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the campus?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: On the campus, built by the university, and the students ran the dormitory
                    on a cooperative basis. We hired a cook, that's the only person we hired, and we
                    had a manager who was a student who got paid to be the manager, to keep the
                    accounts, and do the buying. We all worked. Sometimes you were passing, sometime
                    you were hash slinging, sometimes you worked in the kitchen, sometimes you were
                    swabbing the floors. Everything was cooperative. You could get through, believe
                    it or not, one month, the total cost, the cost of the room pro rated—I think the
                    room was $27 a semester, and the food, you could get through a month on about 17
                    bucks, for one month. Of course, I had no other expenses because I never had
                    dates. It wasn't that I had no other expenses, that was the period when I
                    learned how to drink, we used to buy beer and get loaded, but only once in a
                    while. Beer was 15 cents a bottle. Or sometimes you'd get a pint of Green River
                    rye whiskey and go to the local grange dance and see if you could pick up some
                    of the farmer's daughters. I mean those were the days when we lived a fairly
                    wild life, the student life of the pre-war period. It would be considered tame
                    today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ninety-eight cents a pint for New England Rum.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I remember Green River, which was a blended...I forget what it was, a
                    bourbon or a blend, it was cheap, and it was very rough. But I remember we used
                    to go to the Grange Hall on Saturday night and see if we could meet some of the
                    farmer's daughters so to speak. We were all poor. The group of foresters, who
                    were a close knit community on the campus, most of us didn't have any money. My
                    roommate, Hal Watson, he was the son of a Mormon family, and Hal and I were
                    roommates for the rest of my tour. We roomed the last half of that year, and
                    then the full year the following year. Hal was a great fellow. I'll tell you a
                    story about him. I went home with him at Christmas time for example, whereas the
                    previous year I'd gone home with my roommate in those days—that's where I met my
                    wife. He was from Reno. I never went back to see my family. At Christmas I would
                    take a vacation by going off with my roommate, and each time I went to their
                    home, and stayed with them. And my sophomore year was Henderson, and I went home
                    with him and that's where I met my wife in Reno, Nevada, where his family was
                    from.</p>
                <p>At any rate, I got through the junior year with lousy grades. Then the next
                    summer I was a full-time lookout on the Payette National Forest down in central
                    Idaho, and I lived on a mountain top at about 10,000 feet, and I'd watch for
                    fires the whole summer long. Before the fire season got in full force, we were
                    stringing telephone wires, and working on the roads. At any rate, I spent the
                    whole summer as a lookout. Very good pay, I think I got paid $125 a month. It
                    was good pay, and of course you had the cabin to sleep in and all I had to do
                    was buy my food because I lived alone all summer. I think I didn't see more than
                    two or three people the whole summer.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were on duty when the fire season started.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Oh, yes, when the fires started, when lightning struck... You'd have to
                    check it every once in a while, and then if you got a lightning storm at night
                    you woke up and looked around. You could see the lightning striking. I remember
                    one night we had a spectacular storm, lightning hitting all over the place, and
                    a fire would start here, and a fire would start there. I remember I would call
                    in the fires...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have radio or telephone?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I had a field telephone. I remember at one point they said, you go take
                    care of that one yourself. And in the early morning I started out with an axe,
                    shovel, no bucket, we fought fires with axe and shovel, and a couple of
                    sandwiches on my back and I went down the mountain, crossed the valley, up the
                    mountain to get to the fire, worked on the fire, turned around and went back up
                    the mountain. I was in fantastic shape because in order to get my water all
                    summer long I had to go down the mountain about a mile, and then back up it.
                    I'll tell you what, carrying 45 pounds of water on your back at 10,000 foot
                    elevation, you develop muscles and lungs. At any rate, I was in excellent
                    physical condition. I made a lot of money that summer. I went back to
                    school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No place to spend it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I remember when I came off the mountain, the first meal, I walked into a
                    restaurant...it was in McCall, Idaho, and I told the waitress that I wanted a
                    sirloin steak smothered in pork chops. She looked at me, that's right I want the
                    biggest sirloin...I hadn't had any fresh meat, I want a sirloin steak and laid
                    across it I want pork chops. That was my first good meal after I came off the
                    mountain.</p>
                <p>At any rate, I went back to school, I was well off comparatively speaking. I
                    still had my NYA job, I still didn't have to pay tuition, and I'd saved over 400
                    bucks that summer and that was enough to get me through the whole school year.
                    $400 was plenty to get me through the school year</p>
                <p>Well, I graduated that year and like many others the war had broken out in my
                    senior year. Pearl Harbor came when I was a senior, a Sunday morning. I was
                    naturally asleep, somebody came running in, woke the whole god-damned dormitory
                    up to tell us that the Japanese had bombed Pearl Harbor. And, of course, the
                    first question was, where the hell is Pearl Harbor?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were a good geography student.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I think I knew where Pearl Harbor was, but I don't think very many people
                    did. In any event, we were all registered for the draft, of course, but they
                    deferred— if you were a senior you got deferred—but as soon as you finished the
                    school you were going to be drafted. Well, school ended, we all graduated. I
                    remember graduation was distinctive by the fact that I actually bought myself a
                    new suit, for which I think I paid $25.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You could buy a tuxedo for $25.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: And I went to work waiting to see what would happen with the draft. I went
                    to work for a lumber company, at that time it was called the Boise Payette
                    Lumber Company. I was working as a company forester, we were cruising timber in
                    Idaho. That company later became Boise Cascade. I was the assistant to the
                    company forester. We'd cruise timber, and we'd make the map of the timber.
                    Cruising timber is measuring timber so you would know how much timber there was
                    in a given area, and I used to run the compass for him so he could map the area
                    properly. It was up and down the mountain, state line, through the brush,
                    through the trees, no matter what. You get in pretty good shape again. And lo
                    and behold there came the draft. The board called me and obviously I stopped by
                    and they said...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You'd effectively established residence in Idaho.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Yes, I'd never left Idaho. By now it was four and a half years since I
                    left home...four years as I remember. I remember I got the word that I was going
                    to be drafted. And I went in, and they drafted me, and I raised my hand, and
                    they said, you're now a private in the United States Army. In those days they
                    gave you two weeks to finish up your affairs. So I decided to go down to Reno,
                    Nevada to visit that girl that I'd met three years ago. I had corresponded with
                    her, a beautiful blonde from Reno. We had had a sporadic correspondence for
                    three years. So I went down to Reno, Nevada, and the next day I got married. And
                    that was how I got married</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All within the...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: All within the two weeks and we took our honeymoon. You want to know how
                    we got our honeymoon. We got $100 from her mother. Her mother loaned me $100.
                    Her mother, of course, was not very happy that her daughter was marrying this
                    broken down strange looking kid with no future, who was going to be a private in
                    the Army. In those days the starting salary, if I remember for a private, was
                    $50 a month.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: $52.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: So we took off on our honeymoon. We went to Lake Tahoe, and from Lake
                    Tahoe we went down to Yosemite—you could see that I was still interested in...we
                    went down to Yosemite and stayed in the Great Ahwanee Lodge. About 25 years
                    later I took my children back to Yosemite, and we stayed in the same lodge. At
                    any rate we got married...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was August 27th.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I was drafted into the Army on August 25th, I was married on August 27th,
                    and I left on the troop train for basic training two weeks later. I remember I
                    had to come back up to Idaho...</p>
                <p>HABIB: It was Christmas of 1938, or was it '39, no, it was Christmas of '39 I met
                    met my wife through Henderson, who was my roommate that year and he took me home
                    to Reno. We drove down to Reno. What a ride. We borrowed a car, a convertible,
                    you can imagine what a ride it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Open?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Yes, it belonged to one of the forestry students who wasn't going to use
                    it. At any rate, that's when I met...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Gas was 18 cents a gallon.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>HABIB: His father was well to do, he was the manager of a packing plant. He
                    didn't actually work for money. He was very free with his dough, he never
                    stinted, he bought the gas. He knew I was broke. At any rate, we went down and
                    spent Christmas at his home, and that's where I met my wife. His mother worked
                    for his father, her mother worked for his father. And one day we got a chance to
                    meet this daughter of hers who at that time would have been about 19 years old,
                    and was a gorgeous blonde, so I naturally was very enamored. We saw a lot of
                    each other during Christmas vacation and then I went back up to Idaho and we
                    corresponded. Three years later I went back down there, and we got married.
                    After the honeymoon, she drove me back to Boise...I'll never forget that car. It
                    was a LaSalle convertible. She owned it, I didn't have any money. It was a great
                    car. Anyway, she drove me up to Boise, I went into the Army, got on a troop
                    train and went to Ft. Douglas in Utah to start my Army career, basic training.
                    We started basic training there but then I was assigned to a battalion that
                    interestingly enough was stationed on the Feather River in California in the
                    valley. The battalion lived in an old CCC camp, and it was military police
                    battalion of all things. It was guarding the rail lines, the Western Pacific
                    Railway, against sabotage. Well, that's where we got our basic training, and
                    then we were assigned to the battalion...beautiful country, Feather River
                    country, I remember very well. I later went back there about 20 years later, my
                    wife and I, as a matter of fact we camped in the area of the old battalion
                    headquarters where I got basic training.</p>
                <p>In any event, I was a private just like everybody else, we finished our basic
                    training, and I got assigned to the headquarters of a battalion. And guess where
                    it was. Reno, Nevada.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No kidding.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>HABIB: No kidding, which is where my wife was. My wife was working. She was a
                    legal secretary. She was making very good money, legal secretaries make good
                    money, and she was a top notch legal secretary working for one of the big firms
                    in Reno. She was making excellent dough, and lo and behold, the battalion
                    headquarters in Reno, in an old camp outside of Reno, and I get assigned to the
                    intelligence section of the battalion headquarters. By that time I was a private
                    first class, and I got assigned to battalion headquarters, and I got promoted
                    from private first class to to staff sergeant, which was a big promotion. I'd
                    jumped corporal, I'd jumped a full buck sergeant, I was a staff sergeant, three
                    strips and a rocker. And I began making very good money myself as a staff
                    sergeant. My wife was working. We had a nice apartment in town, and we still had
                    her car although there wasn't much gas in those days. In any event, I put in for
                    OCS and I got assigned to go to Officers Candidate School, the engineer's school
                    because of my forestry background. I went to Ft. Belvoir, Virginia and became a
                    2nd lieutenant. She didn't come to Ft. Belvoir. When I got my bars I was
                    stationed up in Massachusetts at the Air Force Base, Chickapee near Springfield,
                    and she came back and joined me. I was assigned to an Air Borne battalion, it
                    was a glider battalion, engineer and glider battalion. We lived in Springfield,
                    and she worked. She could always get a job because of her skills, she worked as
                    a secretary and made a few bucks. Then the battalion was moved to Grenada,
                    Mississippi, Grenada Air Force base for training. We had the gliders, the C-47s,
                    and all our equipment was assembled, and we lived in a town called Coffeeville,
                    Mississippi, which is right down the road from Oxford. Coffeeville, Mississippi,
                    was where we found a room. I remember the room was not very big, it was one
                    room, a bedroom-living room, and one small room for a kitchen, and a wood
                    burning stove. We had a bedroom/living room which you could heat up and get it
                    red hot and maybe you'd get a little heat. That's all the rooms we had. We
                    rented these rooms in a house from a lovely southern lady called Mrs. Johnson.
                    Mrs. Johnson was very nice to my wife. Once again my wife got a job working for
                    a local law firm, she then got a letter from them saying she was the finest
                    legal secretary in the state of Mississippi when we left. In any event, through
                    that we got to know a few people around town. So we spent the basic training
                    period in Mississippi.</p>
                <p>(Gap in tape.) Then we were sent back to England to prepare for the famous drop
                    across the Rhine. Fortunately we stayed on the airfield and the operation
                    fizzled as you remember if you've ever read the book “A Bridge Too Far”. We were
                    supposed to go into the area where the British brigade was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go into France?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, we were on boats, never did go on gliders for some reason or other.
                    The paratroopers went in, and the combat flyers went in but they never took us
                    in. We went back and were ready to go across the Rhine and that was called off,
                    so we never did go in on a combat drop—thank god, because those things were
                    coffins. Those things were terrible. If you survived the landing...even when in
                    training, we would tip over; no one got seriously hurt but it was bad, no
                    question. In any event I spent a couple years in Europe and came home.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where in England were you based?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Before the invasion, first we were in the Oxford area, Cotswold, then we
                    went out of Southhampton on a boat and landed on Omaha Beach. We landed about
                    two weeks after June 6th, my battalion was brought in. I remember we spent the
                    first night up on the bluffs overlooking Omaha Beach, and I remember my first
                    experience with the Germans, they would come over at night—they didn't dare come
                    over in daytime—and they would bomb the area, or try to. But the anti-aircraft
                    was more dangerous than the bomb because the shrapnel would be coming down and
                    we'd be in the foxholes. And then we moved out of there, went up into the
                    Cherbourg peninsula right behind the troops, and they took Cherbourg. And we
                    built the first flight field on the Cherbourg peninsula; we were working on
                    airfields. And I remember my battalion built the first field that would take
                    heavier planes. Then we started following behind the troops across France
                    repairing front line airfields, building and keeping them going. I remember I
                    was involved in the famous bombing that proceeded the movement with Patton's
                    third army which had landed at Cherbourg and came up across and went right past
                    us. It was some show. They sent 1,000 bombers over and we were standing there
                    watching. The ground was shaking. I was just a few miles away from Saint-L�, and
                    the third army came through and that was the great breakout. We didn't know what
                    the hell was going on. What did we know at our level? We didn't know who was
                    winning, we knew what we were doing alright, we were there.</p>
                <p>When the war ended, my battalion was in Germany, but I was not. I had been
                    detached from the battalion. I was engineer officer-in-charge of three air bases
                    outside of Paris. Villacoublay, the great military base was mine, and two others
                    that were temporary airfields. The French air force used it, we had taken over
                    and we rehabilitated particularly Villacoublay so they could be used. And the
                    war ended. I rejoined my battalion in Germany, and then some guy said...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The record says you were captain.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>HABIB: Well, I was a 1st lieutenant by that time, and then I was promoted to
                    captain at the end of the war. I remember a guy coming around saying, any of you
                    guys want to go to school? We were all waiting. We were counting our points to
                    come home. Well, I said, what's this school business? At that point I was the
                    commander of a prisoner of war camp. I hated it. I mean, I didn't like running
                    prisoners. They were using them for clean up and construction. We were in
                    Wiesbaden, Germany and building the air force headquarters, and I was in command
                    of a prisoner of war camp, is what I was. I was the Commandant in a prisoner of
                    war camp. And this guy came around and I said, geez, anything to get out of
                    this. Well, this was a program called Training with Civilian Agencies. And, if
                    you wanted to, you could go to school in England, you could go to Berlitz, you
                    could go to Paris at the Sorbonne. So I put in for it. By that time my French
                    had improved to the point where I could claim some competency in French. So in
                    October of 1945, while I'm waiting for my points, so I could come home, I got
                    the call, you want to go to school, you can go to Paris. I went to Paris to the
                    Sorbonne, and they had a three-month course they called French Civilization— you
                    took language, you had seminars, you took history, geography, philosophy.
                    Jacques (inaudible) was our lecturer in philosophy at the Sorbonne in 1945. I
                    had a room at a place called the Paris Pavilion, and it was a marvelous
                    experience. It was better than running a prisoner of war camp. And that was sort
                    of the clinching element in my sort of awareness of what you might call the
                    foreign community. Well, anyway, soon our numbers came up and we returned to the
                    States and were discharged.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you get back to the States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I got back to the States in February of 1946. I went back to school. I
                    decided to pick up where I was before the war. Before the war, my last year, my
                    senior year, I had received a scholarship to the University of California School
                    of Forestry to do graduate work. My professors were always urging me to do
                    graduate work. I was a hell of a good student, except for that last year when my
                    grades fell off but I was still recognized as sort of the best student in the
                    school. So the professors for the good students would try to tell me to do
                    graduate work. And I had a scholarship. So what the hell, I'll go back to where
                    I was going to be four years previously. So instead of going to the School of
                    Forestry in the University of California in 1942, I went in 1946. Only this time
                    they didn't give me a scholarship—they said that was four years ago...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you start in the summer session?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>HABIB: No. Well I did start in the summer session doing something. I took a few
                    months off and in the summer of '46 I registered...I knew that you had to have
                    two languages for a Ph.D., so I took German because I didn't know German.
                    French, I didn't have to because I knew French. I took German in the summer,
                    then in the Fall I registered for the full courses in the Department of
                    Agriculture and Economics. And I spent the next three years there, the usual
                    thing, after the first semester I became a research assistant. Then I became a
                    teaching assistant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get a Master's degree?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No. I went straight to the Ph.D., and I taught an elementary economic
                    section up at Davis, California. I used to go up there to teach.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I visited that campus.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I was on the Berkeley campus. They gave courses up there. They wanted me
                    as a teaching assistant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is basic economics?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Basic economics. Economics 1A. I was one of the teachers. While I was in
                    Berkeley, I was a research associate assistant to one of the professors. We did
                    research on various crop problems. My first publication—I was the co-author of a
                    pamphlet issued by the University of California—on the asparagus situation, or
                    the spinach situation in California. I was the co-author, I had done the
                    statistical research.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Filed in the Library of Congress?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB:I filed in a lot of places. There's another one on the premium peach market
                    in California. My first publication, however, was as co-author of the spinach
                    situation in California. At any rate, it was not bad training in terms of
                    economic reporting in the Foreign Service. Let's face it. I later wrote hundreds
                    of crop reports as an economic reporting officer in my first post in the Foreign
                    Service. My first post in the Foreign Service, I was assistant agriculture
                    attach� in Canada.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>HABIB: Yes, and I used to write crop reports. I was an FSO assigned to the
                    economic section, and I was assigned to the agriculture attach� as his
                    assistant. I wrote hundreds of crop reports in the two years in Canada. In any
                    event, I finished my goals. And a recruiting team came around. A State
                    Department recruiting team, and they were looking for people with different
                    backgrounds. They didn't want the old Harvard-Yale-Princeton political science,
                    international relations major.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's why we both got in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: They wanted guys from ranked colleges who were doing something different,
                    and they were particularly looking for guys with economics. They spoke to the
                    graduate students at Berkeley in our department. And I said to one of the guys,
                    “Let's take the exam, what is this Foreign Service”? It was a three-day exam in
                    those days, written, with a language exam on top. I took the exam in San
                    Francisco...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the Fall of '46.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, this was '48. The Fall of '48 I passed my oral examination. I began
                    doing the research for my thesis, Ph.D. thesis, which was entitled, “The
                    Economics of the California Lumber Industry.” I did a lot of original research
                    that had never been done on this sort of thing. Nobody had ever looked at it
                    from that standpoint on the question of economies of scale, location theory and
                    that sort of thing. I did all the research, assembled all of my material. And in
                    the Spring of '49 I had to get a job. Well, I had an offer from the forest
                    service to come back to Washington as an economist in the headquarters of the
                    Forest Service. I had an offer from AID, which one of my professors had gotten
                    for me, to be an economist at his mission, and of all places the AID mission to
                    Korea. And if you will look in the State Department listing of posts and people
                    in 1948-49, in that period, you will see my name listed as an
                    economist-statistician in the AID mission in Korea. They had written to me,
                    offered me the job, and before I signed up finally, I had the job, it was
                    offered and, if I remember right, $5700 was my pay, I forget the rank. Well, I
                    was a married man with education. I had taken the Foreign Service exam in '48
                    and I hadn't heard from them. One of my professors knew a guy in the State
                    Department, called Paul Savage. I said to him, “I wish I knew what was going to
                    happen.” He said, “I'll call Paul Savage and find out what's happened.” He
                    called Paul Savage—it was May of 1949, May or June—to find out. Paul Savage
                    said, “I'll let you know.” And he called back my professor, and said, “he's
                    going to be appointed very soon.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had taken both your written and orals?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>HABIB: I had taken the written exam, and the oral exam, and had passed them both.
                    Yes, I'd flown back to Washington at my own expense in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The only one place you could go.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: The only place you could go for the orals was Washington. I had flown back
                    at my own expense. I remember I'd bought a new suit because I thought I'd better
                    have a decent suit, the best suit I'd ever owned that I bought in my life. My
                    wife, as usual, was working so we had plenty of money. In those days that was a
                    lot of money. At any rate, enough to buy a good suit. And I passed the orals,
                    and I was waiting. Paul Savage told my professor that I was going to be
                    appointed and, lo and behold, in late June I got the word that I was in the July
                    '49 class. At that point I'd dropped the AID, and told the Forest Service that I
                    didn't want to take the job in the headquarters of the Forest Service in
                    Washington in the economic division, and went to the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you live while you were in Berkeley?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Oh boy. We lived in San Francisco because my wife had a good job in San
                    Francisco. And I lived in the heart of the San Francisco tenderloin. We had a
                    one and a half room apartment, with a Murphy bed that pulled out of the wall, in
                    the heart of the tenderloin district which in those days, of course, was deadly
                    - drinking and prostitutes. Nowadays, its gambling, drinking, prostitutes and
                    drugs, and murder. It is the area of San Francisco which the mayor in the
                    present day is trying to clean up. But it was the toughest district in San
                    Francisco. We lived right in the heart of it. When I tell people today, who I
                    knew from California, that I lived in the tenderloin on the corner of Jones and
                    Eddy, they can't believe it. I remember the rent was $36 a month. My wife worked
                    and made a good salary, I used to commute to Berkeley.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had a car by then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No. I didn't have a car until 1948. So for two years I commuted, and
                    finally we bought a car, and I used to drive over to the campus, but not until
                    my last year. The first two years I commuted on the old T train. I used to walk
                    down to the end of Market Street, not too far from where we were, and get on the
                    train that crossed the bridge to Berkeley. Then, when I taught at Davis, I used
                    to take the train from Berkeley up to Davis, and back in the evening. You know,
                    between the GI Bill, my pay as a research assistant which was about $110 a month
                    if I remember right, and my wife's salary, we had enough money to live.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You could go out to dinner once in a while.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>HABIB: We used to go out regularly to Chinese restaurants. In those days you
                    could get a fantastic meal in Chinatown for a couple of bucks. We didn't have
                    any luxuries or anything, but we were young...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My wife was working in San Francisco in those days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: San Francisco was a wonderful city, and the Berkeley campus was a great
                    place, that's a great campus. They treated graduate students very well,
                    especially in the department I was in. And the graduate students - for example,
                    I shared an office with another graduate student. The guy I shared with was an
                    Israeli student. My roommate, for one year, was a graduate student. My roommate
                    in terms of office, meaning he wasn't Israeli, Asafra, born in Israeli, Vernon
                    Hursh, and also a graduate student. He never went back to Israel. Vernon later
                    became the head of the Department of Economics at UCLA, believe it or not. And
                    the last time I saw him, he was the head of the department. I think now he's the
                    president of something at UCLA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But he was a Sabra?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: He was a Sabra. That's the first time I ever heard the word “Kibbutz”. He
                    was from a kibbutz. I think he was doing his thesis on something to do with
                    kibbutz, if I remember. Vernon and I were naturally good friends. It was an
                    interesting collection of students at Berkeley at that time. First of all, most
                    of the Americans were veterans, graduate students were almost all veterans. One
                    of them was an Iraqi. I remember him very well. Hassan was the president of the
                    Arab Students Association at Berkeley. He was a graduate student in agriculture
                    and economics. Years later, he became the Director of Economic Development in
                    Iraq before the fall of the monarchy, then he was finished. He married an
                    American. Another one of the students was a Turk. Rushard was indebted to me the
                    rest of his life because in 1948-49, Rushard came to me. He was enamored of an
                    American divorcee with two children, and he kept saying he was going to marry
                    her. And I kept saying, Rushard, how the hell can you marry her? What will your
                    family...he came from a very prominent Turkish family, how can you go back to
                    Turkey with an American divorcee that you've been sleeping with. In any event,
                    she's got two kids, and you're going to take her back to Turkey, because he was
                    determined to go back. Rushard was determined to go back to Turkey, he was not
                    going to stay in the U.S. And he thought about it, maybe I'll stay in the U.S.,
                    I won't go back. No, no, you're determined to go back, you've got to go back to
                    your country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would she adjust?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>HABIB: How would she adjust, and what would your family think of her. Finally,
                    Rushard decided he couldn't marry that girl. I left the campus before he did,
                    and he went back to Turkey. He later became the civilian head of the department
                    of agriculture, he later became Under Secretary of Agriculture in Turkey. And he
                    and his beautiful Turkish wife came over to the United States when he was
                    professor of economics at the University of Ankara, and Under Secretary of
                    Treasury. He came and stayed with me in Arlington, Virginia with this gorgeous
                    Turkish wife of his. And he and I quietly reminisced about the girlfriend at
                    Berkeley, and laughed about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Saved him from a tragedy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: But, in any event, unfortunately Rushard was killed in an automobile
                    accident several years ago. He was a very, very fine person. I helped him -
                    because his English wasn't very good - I helped him write his thesis because he
                    couldn't write English that well. Another one of our students was a guy called
                    Garvey Murak. Garvey was a Haitian, a wonderful fellow. Garvey's English was
                    lousy, but he was a graduate student. He sat next to me in economics because he
                    couldn't understand what the hell they were talking about. So I used to tell him
                    in French what the lecture was about. Then his English got better and better.
                    Garvey Murak married an American black, whom we all liked. Garvey went back to
                    Haiti and became the director of one of the great development projects. And then
                    his family had a falling out within the regime, Papa Doc, and Garvey ended up
                    working for the UN in New York, and from time to time I would hear from him or
                    see him. As a matter of fact a few years ago, when I was Under Secretary of
                    State, he was looking for some help with UNDP and Brad Morse was with the UNDP,
                    and I put in a word with him with Brad Morse.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: UNDP...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Well, Garvey was one of my friends and a graduate student. You know, you
                    met people like that. I remember there was a guy from Brazil, then, of course,
                    there were guys from all over the U.S. Some of the guys I still run across from
                    time to time. Down in Arizona where I go, there was a guy who was the head of
                    agriculture and economics at the University of Arizona who was one of my
                    classmates. It was a good group. One of my classmates was vice president of the
                    University of Wisconsin later on. Now he's the Washington representative of an
                    association. The last time I saw him, we had a meeting on how to use the land
                    grant colleges for the development of relations with the Eastern Caribbean, and
                    he was brought to a meeting at the White House.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Old school ties.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>HABIB: Why not? But at any rate, we better run.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Phil, that's great.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>May 29th with Phil Habib. Phil, you got to Washington, and entered the Foreign
                    Service, and went to the Foreign Service Institute, and you probably expressed a
                    preference for your first post. Where did you want to go to start with?</p>
                <p>HABIB: It wasn't very clear what the score was. About that time I thought I
                    wanted to go to India, and I think I put in India. I ended up going to Canada.
                    What happened, they needed somebody in Canada in the economic section. I would
                    be the assistant agriculture attach� being that I had had some economic analysis
                    experience in crops, and I'd had some professional training at the university,
                    they decided to send me to Canada. I spent two very pleasant years there. There
                    was an awful lot of reporting. We used to have a very heavy, regular reporting
                    schedule, and I shared it with the agriculture attach�. He was a marvelous man,
                    called Francis Flood. He died some years later. Francis was an old newspaper
                    man, a lecturer. Francis Flood was the first man to ride a motorcycle across
                    Africa from Lagos to the Red Sea, along the southern Sahara. They rode two
                    motorcycles, his companion wrote a book about it which Francis gave me. He was
                    an adventurer. You know, rafted down the Yukon, and the Irrawaddy, and things
                    like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he an agriculture specialist?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: He was an agriculture...he came out of Oklahoma originally. Francis would
                    never claim to be an economist, he was just a practical guy who knew how to
                    write. At one time he was head of the Foreign Agricultural Service. He was a
                    very prominent guy, but beyond that he was just a wonderful human being. And he
                    and his wife treated me extremely nicely. My first post, and I was lucky to have
                    a boss like that. We got along from the first day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>HABIB: The first ambassador was Laurence Steinhardt, who got killed in an
                    airplane crash in Canada as a matter of fact, flying out of that airfield up
                    there in a C-47. And the next one was Stanley Woodward, who was a great fellow,
                    a great guy. I still love Stanley. I used to travel with him. Dean Brown and I
                    used to write Stanley's speeches for him. He was a political officer, I think it
                    was his second post. Dean Brown was a political officer, and I was in the
                    economic section, being the assistant agriculture attach�. Stanley liked to give
                    talks, and travel around the country to the different groups. Dean and I used to
                    write his speeches and travel with him often and take care of the press. So it
                    was a very good exposure to me. First of all, writing speeches, both on
                    political and other matters, and then handling the press for him when we'd go
                    places, handling the luggage, if you had to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hold the door open.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, he was not that kind of guy. We used to have a great time with him.
                    You know, we'd be traveling west through Canada and by the time we'd get to
                    Winnipeg, he would send his secretary out to get a copy of Robert Service poems,
                    and we'd read “The Cremation of Sam McGee,” or one of those things. He loved to
                    read from Robert Service. We'd come back from a reception, or a dinner, and we'd
                    sit in his room. The famous one that we all loved the best was probably “The
                    Cremation of Sam McGee.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I used to know it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: The Marge of Lake LaBarge. It's one of the amusing Robert Service's poems
                    where Sam McGee was from Tennessee - is the way it started out. I did, as I
                    said, an awful lot of reporting, a lot of commodity reporting on everything. As
                    I used to tell the guys who worked for me years later, when they wouldn't get
                    their reports in on time, I'd say...everything was deadline, you had to get a
                    report in by a certain time, and I'd say, “when I used to sit up all night
                    writing a hops report, a British Columbia hops crop report, just to get it in on
                    time, and you guys left it... “ Of course, nowadays everybody wants to make high
                    policy from the day they enter the Foreign Service. But in those days you
                    learned from the bottom up, and I wrote commodity reports about everything from
                    poultry and eggs in Ontario, the crop situation in Montreal, the wheat situation
                    in the western province, very important reports in terms of the commodities.</p>
                <p>I used to tease some of the guys that are ambassadors now who I used to help
                    train years ago about how they didn't realize how important it was to get
                    something in on time. The one thing that Francis Flood and I used to pride
                    ourselves on was that all our reports went in on time. If I remember right, we
                    had 65 crop reports a year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Better than one a week.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>HABIB: Better than one a week. He used to write some, and I used to write some,
                    which meant you had to get the information, you had to get the statistics, you
                    had go to the departments in the government in Ottawa. You had to know somebody
                    in the trade. Also, it probably was the first time I ever sat in on an
                    international negotiation. It was in Ottawa. I remember when the Secretary of
                    Agriculture came up to negotiate something about potatoes with the Canadians. I
                    was part of the delegation. It was good experience. In those days, of course,
                    the Foreign Service didn't take care of you as thoroughly as they do now. You
                    had to find your own place to live. I remember the first place we lived in was
                    real Victorian. I remember getting up in the middle of the night with a tennis
                    racket banging the bats down because they were flying in the bedroom.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had to bring along all your furniture too. Or buy
                        it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: We didn't have any. As a matter of fact, I used to play a lot of poker in
                    those days, and I won enough money playing poker...within this group, we had
                    about six of us, we used to meet once a week to play poker—small stakes. But I
                    was very lucky, I used to win regularly. My wife is awfully fond of saying when
                    the fellows would come to our house to play poker, they'd point to the furniture
                    and say, well, I lost that, and I paid for that one. I remember we went down to
                    Sears Roebuck's in Ogdensburg, New York and bought furniture for the first house
                    that we had. I still have two overstuffed chairs, that have been recovered at
                    least three times, from that first furniture, and a couple pieces of sort of a
                    bedroom set. That's about all I've got left from that first batch of furniture I
                    ever bought in the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very fine pieces.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Yes, that's right. I've still got them. It was hell in Canada, that's what
                    I remember about Canada, about how cold it could get in the wintertime.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember once being told in Ottawa when complaining
                        about the cold in August, and they said, oh, you should have been here last
                        month, we had summer.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>HABIB: I remember once I went to Manitoba, I was in Winnipeg...I guess Stanley or
                    somebody was making a speech somewhere, and I walked from the consulate to the
                    place where the speech was being given, it was 37 degrees below zero. I had
                    never been so cold in my life. The consul said, come on, it's not far, we'll
                    walk. Of course, he had winter underwear on, and a fur hat and everything else,
                    and there was I in just a plain old common overcoat. Well, anyway, we survived.
                    In those years we had some very nice trips across Canada. The Ambassador once
                    took a speaking tour from coast to coast, and I wrote the speeches, took care of
                    the press, went to the formal dinners. The first time in my life I ever wore
                    striped...well, the first time I ever wore a tux was in Canada. Never owned one,
                    never wore one all my life until I was in Canada. But the first time I ever wore
                    striped pants was on a formal occasion and I borrowed a pair from a guy at the
                    embassy because I didn't have any.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any children by that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: The first child was conceived in Canada, was born in New Zealand - we had
                    left Canada.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like us, we made three transfers halfway through
                        pregnancy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: The first one was born in New Zealand. We got to New Zealand about three
                    months before the baby was born. And, three months after we left New Zealand,
                    the other baby was born.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you had about two years in Ottawa.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>HABIB: Two years in Ottawa and then we went to New Zealand. And the other thing I
                    did in Ottawa, which took a lot of my spare time, I was trying to finish my
                    thesis. I hadn't finished my thesis, so I hadn't gotten my degree. The degree
                    was not granted because my thesis was not completed. I had completed all the
                    research, I had to write it. I had written part of it out in California, but
                    then I entered the Foreign Service. I remember when I was in Washington at the
                    Foreign Service Institute, I'd get home at night and I'd sit there trying to
                    write it in the heat of the summer of '49. When we got to Canada I was so damn
                    busy working, learning a new job, I didn't have time to work on my thesis. But I
                    finally got around to working on it, and finished it and sent it off to the
                    university. And they sent it back to me with some requests for corrections,
                    elaborations, and it sat there and sat there and I had a full time job, I was
                    working my head off. But in the summer, I guess it would have been before I went
                    to New Zealand in '52...guess what, talk about coincidences, you asked me about
                    Bob Clodis. Bob Clodis at that time was a professor. He came up to Canada for a
                    vacation and stayed with us...I had a little summer cottage, and he stayed with
                    us there, and Bob said, come on, we're going to finish the thesis. All I had to
                    do was make these corrections. It had been sitting there for months without
                    having the time to do it. Bob said, we're going to make them. And having him
                    there to talk about the thing, I finished it off with Bob Clodis, and my wife
                    typed it all out. And I sent it off, and I got the degree. Otherwise, if it
                    hadn't been for Bob Clodis, I often wonder whether I would have made those last
                    few...you get out, and something else is very hard to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The record said that you got your Ph.D. in '52. Were you
                        present for it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, I was in New Zealand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left Canada in '51.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Yes, I left Canada in the Fall of '51, and actually stopped by in
                    California, saw the chairman of my committee, he said it's fine, the thesis is
                    acceptable, and I went on to New Zealand, and the degree was granted a couple of
                    months later. I wanted to finish it in order to get the degree, and I'd done so
                    much work on it, a lot of the research. It was just a question of writing, and
                    writing, and writing, and I finally got it done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're both lucky having wives with good typist
                        skills.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: She typed it enough times, I'll tell you that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you went to Wellington, and you had home leave in
                        between.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>HABIB: It was a short home leave because I really didn't have much of a place to
                    stay. We stayed with some friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go to Brooklyn?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No. I had been down to Brooklyn when I was in Canada, so I didn't go
                    there. By this time my father had died. I went to see my brothers and sister
                    once or twice from Canada, and my oldest brother came up to Canada and went
                    fishing with me. He was a great fisherman, he came up with his son and went
                    fishing.</p>
                <p>Then we went to New Zealand where I was economic officer. It was a two man
                    economic section, and I was the chief economic officer. I think I did 99.9% of
                    the reporting. I had a lovely fellow for a boss. He was the commercial attach�,
                    a sweet man, but he let me do a lot of the work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Emil Kekich, a lovely man. He was very kind to me. I was lucky - I had
                    good bosses in the sense they were decent guys. Roy gave me all these
                    assignments - if you want to do it, you do it.</p>
                <p>He was economic officer, and I did a lot of the economic analysis, budgetary
                    analysis, balance of payments analysis, commodity reporting, WTDRs, all of the
                    routine of an economic section, there were two of us. And then when the
                    agriculture attach� was away, I'd substitute for him and do his crop reporting.
                    I had very good bosses which is nice. The ambassador was Bob Scotten. Bob was a
                    sweet man, and his wife was one of the most charming women I've ever met. We
                    still see her. She came to our house in California last month and we spent a few
                    days. He had been career, then retired and came back in again as a political
                    appointee. He'd been ambassador in Latin America, or Minister in Ecuador, or
                    somewhere like that. But he was relaxed, and he was an ambassador of the old
                    school, but a sweet man. I loved them both, they liked me. The first DCM I had
                    was a guy called Brown, and he was replaced by Norris Haselton. Betty is like a
                    mother to my daughter, she watches over her like an aunt. She calls herself Aunt
                    Betty to us. Norrie and Betty were wonderful. And then when Norrie was
                    transferred, Sam Berger was named DCM. Sam and I became very close over the
                    years. Sam was a sort of mentor to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was my DCM in Athens.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>HABIB: That's right, he was DCM in Athens, he was ambassador to Korea. He stopped
                    in Washington and changed my assignment and took me with him to Korea as
                    political counselor. And then, of course, years later I did him a favor. I had
                    something to do with Vietnam, and I saw to it that he got sent as deputy
                    ambassador to Vietnam in the last days of the war. But Sam was a very marvelous
                    fellow. (Gap in tape)</p>
                <p>She lives in Washington. She has a place in Hawaii, spends the winter in Hawaii
                    and stops in California, plays bridge with my wife. But one thing I did in New
                    Zealand which was very beautiful later on. I learned how to speak in public. I
                    gave a lot of speeches, Rotary Club, Chambers of Commerce, from one end of New
                    Zealand to the other, and I belonged to the Royal Economic Society. As a matter
                    of fact, I was the first foreigner ever elected to the council. I was very
                    active in the society, went to all the meetings, and that's how you get to know
                    people. I knew hundreds of New Zealanders up and down the coast, from one end of
                    the country to the other. I traveled all the time in New Zealand when I had a
                    chance. You could get around, you'd get in a car and you could drive the whole
                    north island, or else I'd go south. We'd didn't leave the country for our
                    vacations. I remember we took a vacation and drove to the south island, Mount
                    Cook, and all around. Interesting things happened to you. I remember we were
                    traveling and we kept running into this couple, a young American woman and her
                    husband, they were just married and sort of taking the same route that we were
                    taking. We'd run into them at each hotel. This was in the 1950s. Well, ten years
                    later, lo and behold, I meet the same guy and the same American wife, he was a
                    New Zealander. He, at that time, was administrator of the island of Antigua in
                    the British West Indies when I was stationed there, and we renewed our
                    acquaintance. But I did a lot of speech making, and I did all sorts of things. I
                    used to go to rugby matches every weekend with a civil servant, the senior civil
                    servant. The only club I belonged to was the Civil Service Club where the senior
                    civil service would go to drink beer and play pool, and amuse each other.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that was a small enough post.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Oh, as active as we wanted. We made a lot of friends, people we still see
                    to this day. You know, 32 years later and we still write to them, and they write
                    to us. Some of them we met stationed elsewhere, guys we met stationed here in
                    Washington that we knew when we were young in New Zealand. One of the New
                    Zealand ambassadors here later was one of my best friends, years later. He was
                    ambassador here in Washington. When I was in New Zealand as second secretary, he
                    was a junior officer in the foreign ministry. I did a lot of speech-making.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there housing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>HABIB: We started out in a rented flat, and this went on for a while, and then
                    the ambassador approached me one day - there was a nice house that the military
                    attach� lived in, and the military attach� was being transferred. And the
                    ambassador said, “I don't see why we should give that house to the military,
                    we'll give it to you.” The government leased it and it was a lovely house,
                    magnificent grounds, small but beautiful and my wife was crazy about gardening
                    and we made it a show place, because we'd built gardens all over the world. That
                    was the first real garden that we built. We had flower beds—I still have
                    pictures of it, it was magnificent, and we did it all at our own expense, nobody
                    gave us money in those days. But we liked to do it. We had maybe 15 or 20 flower
                    beds, rose bushes, a vegetable garden, everything. Well, that was the last year.
                    A baby was born there, the oldest child was born there. In those days they
                    insisted you spend two weeks in the hospital. My wife spent two weeks in the
                    hospital, and I think the whole thing cost something like $28, because they had
                    socialized medicine. I remember I used to go to the drug store to get medicine,
                    there they didn't pay for prescription drugs. I used to insist on paying, I said
                    but I don't pay taxes, I think I have to pay. It was more bother to them than
                    just putting it on the books.</p>
                <p>I did another thing there which I was always very proud of. The famous Milford
                    Track Walk. I walked the Milford Track which is a three day walk over the
                    mountains in the southern tip of New Zealand. Beautiful, beautiful scenery. I
                    got some magnificent photographs that I took.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Back packing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Yes. Well what you did was if you backpacked, you went from one...they had
                    huts built at one day intervals. You started at a hut, you walked all day, spent
                    another night in a hut, walked another all day, spent another night in a hut,
                    then you walked down into the fjord. There were 27 of us in the group, a bunch
                    of New Zealanders, very, very outgoing, lovely people. A couple of Britishers, a
                    couple of Australians. Years later, I remember the British couple that was on
                    the trip, an elderly couple, he was a lawyer, a solicitor. Years later when I
                    went to England, we went out to visit them in their home in the suburbs of
                    London. We looked at pictures all over again of the famous walk. It is a
                    beautiful walk, beautiful country up over a pass and down into the fjord, South
                    Island.</p>
                <p>At any rate, I traveled New Zealand from end to end, and I knew people in every
                    corner of New Zealand, was widely acquainted in the city itself. So I got around
                    a lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get into sailing down there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>HABIB: No. What I got into in New Zealand in all my spare time in the right
                    season was hunting birds. I used to hunt pheasants with the deputy director of
                    agriculture. The Foreign Agriculture attach� had a great place up country, and
                    then I would go down and I would hunt quail and ducks with a sheep farmer down
                    in the South Island who had a most beautiful place right on the lake, a small
                    lovely home. But you know, everything in New Zealand was simple. Nobody lived
                    high on the hog down there. I remember we had a housekeeper-nurse for the baby,
                    a lovely retired English nurse. She was actually a nurse, and she loved the
                    baby, and she took great care of her. It was a simple life, very pleasant,
                    lovely people, and I learned a lot about the business, did a lot of writing, did
                    a lot of speech-making. Whenever anybody wanted somebody to go to speak in some
                    small town in New Zealand they'd ask me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a good way to make friends.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: And I had good bosses. Norrie Haselton was a real gentleman. Sam Berger
                    was a brilliant man. Roy, who was my immediate boss, was a sweet man and to this
                    day we are very good friends. Poor Roy was not exactly what you would call
                    overly ambitious, but he retired from the Foreign Service some years later. They
                    were awfully nice men. In those small posts you got to know each other.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And we were a small service generally in those days, and
                        1200 at the time the Wriston program came over. I think I was told when I
                        came in in '47 that I was about Foreign Service officer number 780—there
                        were 780 ahead of me.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It was a good post. I did a lot of nice, interesting things. Then we got
                    to Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Washington '55-57 in INR.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That was the period when they decided to put FSOs in INR, remember? And
                    I've been told that I was the first FSO, actually chosen as a normal rotations
                    to be assigned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would have been sitting around a placement panel about
                        the time you were sent in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: They picked me obviously because of the background I had in advanced
                    training. A lot of the people in INR at that time were the fellows that had been
                    there for years. But I got assigned there and I spent three years there. It was
                    all right, I didn't object. First, I started out doing economic research.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What branch of INR?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I was in DFI, it was called the division of functional intelligence, where
                    they did economic research. Then I got into something that was very interesting
                    because it exposed me to a lot of the Soviet stuff. I was one of the principal
                    watchers of what the Soviets were doing in the underdeveloped world. We began
                    publishing a weekly account of everything the Soviets were doing anywhere in the
                    underdeveloped countries. That was the period when people used to talk about
                    Soviet penetration in the underdeveloped countries, or Soviet economic
                    activities. We used to call it Soviet economic military assistance and all that,
                    and we were the authority on the subject. At the same time we worked jointly
                    with CIA in the publication. It came out every single week. And every year we
                    did an annual. It meant that you got into a lot of the Soviet stuff, and as a
                    result I learned something about what the Russians were up to around the world,
                    which was very useful later on. I spent three years doing that - it was
                    something. Also, the second baby was born, and I bought the first house I ever
                    owned in my life. I paid $20,000 for it under the GI Bill. A lovely little
                    house.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Bethesda.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, it was in Virginia, a great location. It was the cheapest house in
                    Lake Barcroft.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That probably wasn't even developed at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It was being developed for the first time, and I bought this house for as
                    little as $20,000 with a GI loan. The interest, if I remember, was 4%. I wish I
                    still had the house, it's still there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wish I'd bought a house at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: My problem was I was very stupid. I sold the house when I got transferred
                    because I needed the money, and I made $5000 profit. I was broke, I needed
                    money. I'd saved some money in New Zealand, that's what I used to buy the house
                    and get it equipped, furniture. The house was bare and we must have spent
                    everything we'd saved in New Zealand on equipping the house, and another, a
                    second baby—we had two babies in the house. I remember I bought a used car, I
                    never had a new car, but carpooling into the Department. The house was good, it
                    could have lasted a long time for us. I was here for three years, and then I got
                    transferred and I needed the dough to get set up for the next post. I lived from
                    salary to salary in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Didn't we all.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>HABIB: It was very difficult to save money with two kids and a house on my
                    salary. So, when I left, I sold the house, which was one of the big financial
                    mistakes in my life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It could be worth $100,000 right now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That house would be worth $150,000, minimum, now. In any event, I sold it.
                    As a matter of fact I bought a car to take to the new post, clothing, and all
                    that stuff that you need for a new post, and went to the Caribbean.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Washington during the Wriston thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Yes. A lot of people who were in INR, who were civil servants, used to
                    talk to me—”should I join, what's it like,” and I used to tell them, “come on
                    in, it's a great job.” And many of them did. Some of them lasted, some of them
                    didn't. Some of them didn't like the Foreign Service, took one assignment
                    abroad, and would get out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was rough on a lot of people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Again, I was very lucky, I had very good bosses. I was really lucky most
                    of my career. I can only think of one or two guys that really irritated me. In
                    Washington, my immediate boss was an excellent economist. And then I had a woman
                    for a boss for a while, a lovely person, she was very considerate and it didn't
                    hurt me to have a woman boss for a while. The division chief was Ed Dougherty,
                    and Ed and I have been friends through all our life ever since. As a matter of
                    fact, we served together years later in Korea. He was DCM when I was political
                    counselor, and we've been friends ever since. Ed was an interesting man, a very
                    thoughtful man. So that experience in Washington was another thing for me, it
                    exposed me to Washington. I used to sit in on departmental committees, CIA,
                    Treasury, Commerce and State.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also, it expands your acquaintance within the
                        Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: You got to know people. I also got to know a lot of people in the
                    Department who later on were around. There were guys that I met in that period
                    that I still see from time to time. There were guys in that period that I would
                    meet again somewhere else overseas in later assignments. As I said about Ed
                    Dougherty who later was DCM. I just had lunch the other day with Henry Owen, who
                    was in INR at that time. There were a lot of guys I met in that period. Joe
                    Greenwald, Hal Sonnenfeldt. Hal was in INR on the Soviet desk.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>You asked me why I'm going to Cleveland. Because Coby Swank is the director of
                    the World Affairs Council in Cleveland and Coby twisted my arm to come to
                    Cleveland and make a speech for them. And Coby was in the Soviet sector, I met
                    him in that period. It was the first time I met some of the Arabists, a guy
                    doing research on the Middle East, Harry Symmes. There were a number of those
                    guys that I met in that period. I would never have met him if I weren't around
                    Washington and in INR. An interesting bunch. Doing what I was doing about
                    following Soviet affairs all over the world meant that I had to get acquainted
                    with what was going on all over the world. So there I was, going to meetings on
                    Latin America, South Asia, Africa, and I was picking up a bit of knowledge about
                    all of these places in the world which later was very helpful to me when I
                    became Under Secretary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You learned the basics.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: ...that I never knew before. I didn't work very hard. It was sort of a
                    nine to five job, you didn't feel compelled to come in on Sundays. You weren't
                    working on high policies, but what you were doing was informative.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that was the only period in my life I had a nine
                        to five job.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's right. That was the only time in my life I ever had a nine to five
                    job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very little social life, you weren't on any embassy's
                        guest list.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's right. You socialized with your friends that you made. We were back
                    into gardening again, we planted trees, built flower beds out of the clay soil.
                    I went out there last spring, I was in Washington, and saw the crab apple trees
                    that I planted were in full bloom. I planted ten crab apple trees, they were in
                    full bloom.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And I know that red soil, it's pretty rough to deal
                        with.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I used to get loads of top soil to dig in the grass. It was a good
                    experience from that standpoint.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then the time came to go overseas again.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>HABIB: At that point we used to do our preferences. I think my first preference
                    was India, I was fascinated with the idea of going to India, I thought it would
                    be interesting. I wasn't particularly interested in going to Western Europe. I
                    would put down my preferences South Asia, Africa, Middle East, Latin America,
                    everything. I wasn't interested in civilized [countries].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I never asked for Europe after my first post. I asked to
                        be sent to The Hague.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I was interested in the older civilizations. Well, at any rate, what was
                    happening in the Caribbean, the British had gotten together with the people on
                    the island, and they wanted a political officer there. They set up a new
                    position, a political officer, and sent me as political officer to the
                    Caribbean. I was stationed in Trinidad, but we were responsible for the area at
                    that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you had a roving commission.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, well I roved. Our consular district extended from Antigua to Trinidad.
                    At that point the Federation headquarters were there, and I got very much
                    involved in the policies of the Federation, elections. It was good training
                    reporting on elections. I spent lots of hours running around chewing the fat
                    with politicians. An interesting period. Probably one thing, we got a little bit
                    too deeply involved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We were in the Caribbean Commission. It used to be we had
                        to deal with them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Frances McReynolds is what I remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I worked with her in IO.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Frances knew me very well. She us come down there, or else I'd stop in IO
                    and see her.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right. I first began hearing about you from
                        Frances.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>HABIB: Yes, Frances McReynolds and I were...she liked me, and she thought I was
                    doing good work, and was very interested in what I was doing. She was interested
                    in the Federation, which I was. I thought the Federation was a great idea and
                    should not be allowed to fail. I think the Federation failed because we didn't
                    support it properly. The British didn't do the right thing, but we didn't do the
                    right thing either. We did absolutely the wrong thing by not supporting it
                    sufficiently. We thought that was behind us, not doing what could have been done
                    to preserve the Federation. In fact, we got caught up in this business. We had
                    naval bases there. The Navy didn't want to give them up, and of course, the
                    local guys wanted us out. We got involved in the famous Chaguaramas naval base
                    in Trinidad. Eric Williams became Prime Minister, and he was dead set against
                    the base and wanted us out. And we began to try to manipulate the situation. And
                    one of my bosses, a wonderful, wonderful man - he had spent some time with CIA,
                    he had a tendency to get involved in political situations, and he got me
                    involved. We were good at it. I knew everybody, as usual. In every post I went
                    to, the first thing I would get to know more about the post and the people than
                    anybody in the embassy, or consulate, or whatever it was. I covered the
                    waterfronts. I knew every politician in Antigua, I still know some of them. Some
                    of them, I knew their fathers before them. I went down to the Caribbean in '79
                    to take a look and see what could be done, which I did do and made a report,
                    which unfortunately required some money and therefore they didn't do it. Now
                    they're spending 20 times what I recommended to be spent. I saw some of the same
                    guys that I knew back in the old days, or their sons. A son of a man I knew very
                    well in Barbados is the present Prime Minister of Barbados. The son of a man I
                    knew very well in Antigua is the number two man, his father is still around. The
                    son of the man I knew in Jamaica, the first Prime Minister in Jamaica, when I
                    was working on the problems there. The principal leader of St. Lucia, I used to
                    travel around the islands with him while he was showing me the problems of the
                    island in a broken down Ford convertible - the door on my side wouldn't open. I
                    always had to leap over the door to get in - he was the chief minister of St.
                    Lucia. He was showing me what their problems were. He didn't like the British
                    colonialism...this was on the threshold of independence for all these countries,
                    all of whom later became independent individually. And I knew them all. But I
                    got into the business of ethnic politics, black-versus white. It was an
                    interesting period, and I learned a lot about political reporting at the
                    electoral level, because they had elections. And I got to know my way around
                    very well indeed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Always to allow yourself an out in case the election
                        didn't go the way you thought it would. Well, the British never succeeded
                        anywhere in getting an independent federation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Even if the federation could have been supported it has held together. The
                    trouble is Jamaicans had been dominated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well Jamaica is still not in the current association with
                        those British islands.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>HABIB: Of course, Guyana didn't even join the federation. They always talk about
                    it. The Federation was still there when I left, but it faded not long after, it
                    broke up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your Consul General?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Walter Orebaugh. He and I are still very close friends, in fact I played
                    golf with him a couple of months ago in Florida where he retired. He was a man
                    who had an extraordinary career in the Foreign Service. He had been consul in
                    Nice when the war broke out. He was captured and interned by the Germans, and he
                    escaped from a German prisoner of war camp, and he spent the rest of the war
                    leading partisan groups behind the lines. In fact, he got the Medal of Freedom
                    for it. He later became Consul General in Florence, and somewhere on the Mexican
                    border. He ran the Italian and the western European desk in CIA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When they were getting organized.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: But he knew everybody. He had led partisan groups, and he knew
                    everybody.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think Pete Hart was telling me this story one time. I
                        don't think I ever met him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: He's writing a book about it. He asked me to write the forward. I've read
                    some of the chapters. He's still writing it. He's retired, we see each other
                    even to this day. He has a place not far from the place where I have a place in
                    Florida. He likes to come down to the place where I have. So he goes and uses my
                    apartment. I have this small apartment down in Naples, Florida, and he goes down
                    and spends the weekend there. It's there anytime he wants it, he just calls up
                    the person I have to keep it clean. He was a good boss, and we became
                    exceptionally good friends.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>But in any event, he left and I had an interesting experience, I won't tell you
                    his name, I had a Consul General who turned out to be an alcoholic. I remember
                    one time I was waiting to meet his plane, and when he got off, all of a sudden
                    his wife ran up, she knew what was wrong. He had to be dried out, anyhow she
                    kept him at home for a couple of weeks. I ran the god damn office and didn't
                    tell anybody. I don't know what you should do in those circumstances. Should you
                    report it to the Department that the man is non compos mentis, and he's out. Or
                    do you just do your job. So I decided, what the hell, he'd stay home while he
                    was drying out, but it would take weeks. And I was running the office, sending
                    all the reports in, everything that had to be done. Go up and see him while he
                    was drying out. The funny thing was before this experience, he kind of resented
                    me because I knew everybody, and I knew everything that was going on. He was new
                    and didn't know anybody, and he kind of resented me. But after I had covered up
                    for him, from then on there was nothing I could do wrong. He decided somehow or
                    another that I had made him, and I had. Hell, all I had to do was send a message
                    to Washington telling them the truth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I never had a problem with a chief, I've had alcoholics
                        under me.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: A very difficult problem to work with, especially when he was under the
                    influence. He would get awful mad. I would fluff it off. A very interesting
                    experience. But I decided I'd just ran the place and I ran the whole god damn
                    place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you second rank in the office?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I was an FSO-4. After Wristonization they knocked us back. I had been
                    promoted to 4, then I went back to 5. They [promoted us] very rapidly. When I
                    joined the Service we went from 6 to 5, and I went from 6 to 5 in the first
                    year. Then I went from 5 to 4, and then I got knocked back to 5.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was one of 16 lucky FSO-4s at that time and stayed in 4.
                        We were on the list.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: What had happened to me interesting enough, was that...you remember the
                    McCarthy period when they took all that time to give everybody another full
                    field check.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And we went two years without any...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>HABIB: That's right, and I lost a promotion. I was on that promotion list, I know
                    it. But I was young and made up for it. One of the guys that worked for me
                    there, a consular officer, later on was with me in Vietnam, and Paris, and I had
                    the pleasure to meet with him and made him an ambassador. A lot of my boys
                    became ambassadors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's great.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: When I was in Trinidad I had the biggest political section that was ever
                    put together—not Trinidad, when I was in Saigon in the '60s. I had this huge
                    political section, and a lot of those guys have become ambassadors. And then
                    when I was Assistant Secretary in Washington the guys I had working for me when
                    I was Deputy Assistant Secretary, a lot of those guys became ambassadors—Bob
                    Miller, Jim Rosenthal, Tom Corkland, John Burton. Dick Smyser who is not an
                    ambassador, but is Deputy High Commissioner for Refugees. John Negroponte,
                    Honduras, these guys were all my boys. I took them all with me, most of them
                    were with me in Paris. Dick Holbrooke was one of my guys I took to Paris. A
                    political appointee but when I took him he was an FSO. A lot of those guys were
                    first class. They did good work, and I picked them, you know, spotted them. And
                    then later on, of course, when I was in Washington, I spotted a lot of guys. But
                    even at that time I was spotting good guys. Just like Sam Berger did for me.
                    Well, anyway, Trinidad was a good post from that standpoint.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your first solid political work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Also the first post where I had some [authority]. Despite a small embassy
                    because of what we were doing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From a family point of view...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It was very comfortable. We had a nice little...not a fancy house, but a
                    comfortable house. That was the first time that we ever really had a house, with
                    servants. We had a housekeeper-nurse in New Zealand. But this time we had a cook
                    and a maid, and houseboy who also doubled as a driver and gardener. He was an
                    Indian and the other two were black. But I was in Trinidad in '79 on a mission
                    to look the place over. Some of the people in the consulate still remembered me.
                    Lo and behold here comes my old gardener and driver driving up to see me. He
                    heard that I was there. He was now prosperous, an East Indian gentleman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Saved enough money to go into business for himself.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>HABIB: When I left I got him a job with somebody else in the Trinidad government.
                    He was a very bright boy. My wife taught him a lot of things, she taught him an
                    awful lot of things, and he remembered me very well. She would teach him how to
                    cook western style. Most servants if you take the trouble to teach them our ways
                    of doing things, was appreciate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And don't cry at them the first time they slip up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: In all the years I was in the Foreign Service, we only fired one
                    servant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By this time had you given thought to specializing? They
                        were pushing everybody to specialize.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I didn't want to go to school. I figured I was educated enough. I didn't
                    want to go back to university or anything like that. So while I was in Trinidad
                    and the time comes to be transferred, what I do, I put in my preference again, I
                    put India. But I got assigned to India. I'm sitting in Trinidad, and I get
                    assigned to Delhi as economic officer, which was exactly what I wanted. I think
                    I would have been number two in the economic section in Delhi. I had some very
                    good East Indian friends in Trinidad. I remember one fellow, and I got books and
                    started to read up all about India. About a month before I was due to ship out,
                    I get the word from Washington that I'm not going to India. The assignment had
                    been broken. I'm coming to Washington for a very special job. Remember I told
                    you that when I was in INR I had done a lot on Soviet activities in less
                    developed countries and what they were up to. I was reporting facts. Well,
                    somebody had decided—this was when Douglas Dillon was Under Secretary. At that
                    time was he Deputy Secretary?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think Ball was the last Under Secretary.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>HABIB: Dillon was both at one time. He had the symbol U, so he was Under
                    Secretary. They decided to set up under him, a staff called U/CEA. He had a
                    special assistant. The CEA stood for Communist Economic Activities. U/CEA, a
                    small group that he put together that was supposed to develop ways of
                    counter-acting Soviet activities in the less developed areas of the world,
                    military, economic, the full range but particularly economic. And he had a
                    special assistant, a guy called Bob Terrill, and then the staff under him. The
                    staff had three sections. One of them was for European and sort of trade
                    matters. One of them was for underdeveloped countries. And I was selected to
                    come up and head one of those little sections. There were three of us in the
                    section. One of them was Tom Buchanan, another was a guy called Stevens, and I
                    was chief of the section. We were supposed to develop counter strategy to
                    counter-act Soviet action in less developed countries. And we worked at it, in
                    those days the way those kinds of staffs would do. But by working with guys that
                    we knew in different bureaus, we at least made ourselves somewhat acceptable,
                    and we would do work for them so they didn't mind. We'd write papers, figure out
                    analyses and proposals for action. When the Congo went independent...the only
                    thing I ever regretted about it was they broke my assignment to India to bring
                    me back for that particular job. They wanted me because I had had those earlier
                    years of experience of following the Soviets.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But that doesn't show on the record at all, does it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: The assignment to India doesn't show on the record because I never got
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, but I mean...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Sure. I was assigned to Washington in 1960 to 1962. I didn't work for
                    Ball, I worked for Dillon. Then I worked for Ball. And then the thing broke up.
                    They decided not to keep it there. They put it into INR for a couple months and
                    at that point I was ready to get the hell out. I was assigned to E Bureau,
                    economic and trade. And Sam Berger came to town, and said, how would you like to
                    go to Korea with me? And I said, anything Sam to get out. I was actually anxious
                    to go with Sam. I said if you want to break my assignment, you've got to go to
                    Ball and get him to help, which he did do, broke my assignment to the E Bureau
                    and took me to Korea with him. We did a lot of work in that U/CEA. Some of it
                    was worthwhile, some of it was worthless. For example, we did the basic paper on
                    the Congo at the time of independence in my little section, with Tom Buchanan
                    and myself, and we sold that paper to the African Bureau, Mark Hurst and Jim
                    Penfield. Henry Owen was involved. He was up in S/P at that point. And Jack Bell
                    and those guys. We wrote the basic paper on the Congo. It was adopted and used,
                    and it was the basis of our action in the Congo at the time of independence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Particularly because we may have misunderstood despite a
                        messy situation down.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>HABIB: We did very well. It was the first State policy...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're still in there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: The first big policy on [Africa]. And then I did Guinea, I was out there
                    twice in that period. Sekou Toure was breaking away from the Russians, and I was
                    sent out and did a job of beginning to reintroduce American presence in the
                    Guinean development, which was very important. We got an AID mission back in,
                    and did a number of things. Bill Attwood was ambassador most of that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, and he wrote a book, The Reds and the Blacks.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: If you look in there you'll see a reference to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I haven't read that for a long time. I hated it because of
                        that book he blew all our station in Nairobi.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: The Beast and the Red and the Black was about the same deal I did in
                    Guinea. After I'd been out there on survey, he and I went up and spent a couple
                    of days in the hotel in Dakar. He wrote the book, came back to Washington and he
                    took it over to the White House and gave it to Jack Kennedy. And I peddled it
                    through the Department, and before we went back he writes in the book that I
                    taught him a very good lesson. I wrote instructions for him before he went back
                    to his post, and got it cleared while we were here. He doesn't really...in a way
                    it's rather strange. I had a great deal more to do with turning the thing around
                    than he did in some ways. But he had influence in the White House. I did all the
                    figures, and he did all the lobbying. That's why it worked out very well.</p>
                <p>Well, from there I went to Korea. Korea was an entirely different world, of
                    course. There I not only ran the political section but I was in many ways the
                    man's right hand man. He had two DCMs. We did some very, very good work there.
                    Sam was a man who believed in democratic rituals. On the other hand he was very
                    practical. He knew what you could do, and what you couldn't do. Of course, we
                    had a junta. And elections which they kept putting on and then postponing until
                    we laid the law down to them, and we made it stick. And that was the restoration
                    of something like an electoral process in Korea. But in any event, Sam and I
                    were a very active team, very active politically. And, of course, again I got to
                    know a lot of people in my usual [way]. There were two things, learning as much
                    as I could about the country, traveling all over and getting to know as many
                    people as I could. I knew everybody, anybody that counted at any level,
                    military, civilians, business, I knew them all.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you try to learn Korean while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I studied it at breakfast time in the morning. It's not a language you can
                    learn that way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Or use anyplace else.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: How did I know that I would be back there in eight years. We trained a
                    couple of guys. One guy we trained of all the guys we had in the post, only one
                    guy could speak Korean well enough to interpret at that time. That was Ed Hurst,
                    and the way he did it he had a year of training in the States. We sent him out
                    there to a year in university where he lived in a Korean house. And after that
                    he came back to the embassy. That's the way he learned. At the end of his tour,
                    two or three years later, he knew enough that I could use him to interpret.
                    Otherwise, I used Korean-Americans. I had a marvelous CIA fellow, David Lee, he
                    was CIA, but he was my interpreter. He was in my political section, but he was
                    with me all the time. And then there was another CIA guy who was an absolute
                    language freak. He was not a Korean-American, Scandinavian origin. He was a
                    fantastic linguist. He could interpret Japanese, Korean, or Chinese. He was one
                    of these language freaks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Three oriental languages.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: But he was a CIA man. He was just a linguist, that's all he was. He wasn't
                    worth much else but he was a fantastic interpreter. Well, at any rate, those
                    three years in Korea with Sam Berger were very, very intensive hard work. We
                    went from crisis to crisis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Crisis in the sense of internal Korean development. The
                        DMZ was fairly quiet in those days.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>HABIB: The DMZ was fairly quiet in those days. You know, from time to time
                    getting into it but nothing big. The Pueblo came later, and the Blue House raid
                    came later. But in any event, those three years with Sam in Korea I really got
                    heavily involved in political action, and negotiation, all sorts of things, and
                    very complicated maneuvering. I think that's where I made my reputation as a
                    political officer, and manager in the political section. So one day Sam asked me
                    to come into his office. Bill Bundy was there. I had been involved in the
                    negotiation of normalization relations with Korea and Japan. In the Department
                    was a drinking buddy of mine, I was at his house all the time while the
                    negotiations were going on constantly, breakfast, lunch and dinner. I used to
                    play poker with the Prime Minister every Sunday afternoon. I knew everybody in
                    the country. I'd go drinking with the Minister of Defense, and the generals. I
                    knew more Koreans than anybody except for one guy who was the military man who
                    had been there since 1945. He knew more than I did, but he and I were great
                    friends and he would teach me all the time. But I knew everybody, and I was very
                    active.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you got a chance to travel around the country?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I was all over the place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about up around the far east?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I went to Japan a couple of times. I went to Japan on business a couple of
                    times. And then I took a vacation in Japan with the kids. You know, I still
                    didn't have a lot of money to go gallivanting off. But I traveled a lot around
                    Korea itself. But at any rate, one day Bill Bundy arrived. And he said, we're
                    looking for the best political officer in the business, at the time as chief of
                    the political section in Saigon, the war was heating up in 1965. How would you
                    like to go to Saigon? It was in early 1965. He said, well, you don't have to
                    answer, you go talk it over with your wife and let me know. I said, Bill I don't
                    have to talk that over with my wife, that's a decision I make, and the answer is
                    yes. At that time you could take your family. It was months later when they
                    bombed the embassy and wounded several people, that they decided to make it a
                    non-accompanied post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: 1965, February, I think it was. Well, I had already been assigned as a
                    matter of fact when it was bombed. I had been assigned to the embassy as
                    political counselor. I was to go home and have the home leave, and then go to
                    Saigon, and my family was going to go with me. Well, as it turned out you
                    couldn't take your family. So I took home leave and went home and settled them
                    in California, in Belmont, the town I live in now as a matter of fact. We rented
                    an apartment, got the kids in school, and I went off to Saigon.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The kids were about...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Phyllis was 13, and Susan 10 I believe. I was gone two years and came home
                    once two years later on leave. They lived there and I went to Saigon as chief of
                    the political section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you stay three years in Seoul without getting home
                        leave?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I had nowhere to go. Saigon, of course, was a very traumatic experience.
                    Around the clock, seven days a week. Not long after I arrived Henry Cabot Lodge
                    came as ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was there when you first got there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Max Taylor was ambassador and Howard Johnson was deputy. And Max Taylor
                    was replaced by Cabot Lodge. And Cabot Lodge came with a fearful reputation
                    about how he brought his own people, and he didn't use the Foreign Service at
                    all well. Cabot Lodge was a different man. He wasn't running for president, and
                    he was very good to me, and I became in many ways his right hand on political
                    matters, and many other matters too. We became very close to each other.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well I technically worked for him at the UN Trusteeship
                        Council. I think I shook his hand once, and never never saw him again.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I saw him every single day. As a matter of fact usually the first thing
                    every morning I'd be in there, talking over the business of the embassy and how
                    we were running it. Then Bill Porter became deputy. When Bill Porter became
                    deputy, we set up this separate organization to run the field program. And Bill
                    became administrator of the field program while I was in effect deputy for the
                    normal affairs of the embassy. In my own way, of course, Bill was the deputy. I
                    remember we became very good friends. But that was the period when I...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had political officers out in the provinces.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>HABIB: The AID program, Bill was the coordinator of all that. He was very busy
                    running that. It was CORDS, it got to be known as CORDS, at one time it was
                    known as something else. Bob Komer later replaced Bill. But I had a very big,
                    and very good political section. I think we ended up with 23 officers, and of
                    course we worked very closely with CIA. There was another group, a special group
                    set up, the famous Lansdale group which were in many ways very difficult to get
                    along with because they were a bunch of big dealers. But it wasn't very long
                    before Cabot Lodge decided the political section was the one he was dependent
                    on, and we became the center of the embassy's political and coordination
                    activity, political and military as well. I was very much involved, again knew a
                    lot of people. I was very much involved on military issues. I was a member of
                    the mission's council for the embassy before they moved the people, myself,
                    Westmoreland, Barry Zorthian, the public affairs man, Roy Worthly, the economic
                    man, Garth McDonald before him, Charlie Mann the AID guy, Ed Lansdale for his
                    group, Jorganson, the station chief guy. That was the group that ran the war,
                    and some of the local boys.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Coordinating the operation. Well, I think that worked
                        pretty well.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It worked pretty well, but of course you had first rate people. I mean,
                    nobody was assigned in those days to Vietnam unless somebody picked them out by
                    hand. Everybody was hand picked. And it got me into the big league. I was at the
                    Manila conference in '66, then I was in Guam. I was involved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the big picture in Southeast Asia.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>HABIB: And it was because of that when the time came and my time was up after two
                    years, Len Unger was leaving the bureau as deputy to Bill Bundy, and I was
                    brought back as deputy and then I became deputy assistant secretary. And I was
                    the deputy in charge of Southeast Asia. I was in charge of Vietnam, Laos and
                    Cambodia and Thailand in the bureau. I had the Vietnam working group under me,
                    and I was the principal liaison between the Department and the Defense
                    Department, CIA. The Vietnam experience in Vietnam itself prepared me for the
                    Vietnam advisory role in Washington, the planning role. When I came to
                    Washington as deputy, I was Bill Bundy's deputy. Bill, of course, is a brilliant
                    man. He is one of the most brilliant man I ever worked with, and I was his
                    deputy for Vietnam and saw him on a daily basis. I had a meeting in my office
                    every day of the week. It was called the 11:00 group. We used to meet in my
                    office every single day. And there was George Carver from CIA. I knew Jorden
                    from NSC, and myself. We'd meet every single day at 11:00. Then there was a
                    senior group called the Thursday Group which had Harry Katzenbach, Bundy, Gerald
                    Wheeler, Paul Wormsby, Dick Helms. These guys met in Katzenbach's office every
                    Thursday and I was there as liaison with the working group because I was the
                    junior guy in the room. They would tell us what to do and then we would carry it
                    out. If they wanted an instruction drafted, they would tell me, and the next
                    morning at 11:00 I would talk it over with these guys who had gotten their
                    instructions from their bosses, and that's how we worked. It was a very
                    efficient way of working. And then, of course, you had the Tuesday luncheon
                    group which met with the President, which was McNamara, Bill Rostow, and Bud
                    Wheeler. That was the way things were done. It was a fantastic mission. When you
                    got your instructions, when the policy was laid down, you had your own input,
                    you could say what you thought, it was a free wheeling discussion group. But
                    there was a lot of talent believe me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A good cause too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: The war was undertaken for noble reasons, and fully consistent with our
                    view of where our policy interests lay in the world. I was in Saigon when the
                    first American troops arrived in '65. I was the assistant secretary of state in
                    the '70s. So I spent 10 years. I went to Paris for the peace talks, and I had
                    that little interlude when I was ambassador in Korea. Even in Korea, I was
                    involved because we had 50,000 Korean troops in Vietnam. I remember the time I
                    had to get the president of Korea to give his F-5s to the Vietnamese before we
                    all left them there. I had to persuade him to give me his F-5s. Not an easy job
                    but I got them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To take them back home? The ones we'd given the
                        money...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>HABIB: Flying in his air force, and we took them away from him. Got them from him
                    and gave them to the Vietnamese. Of course, they're probably still flying them.
                    That's the way it's done. It wasn't my fault. As a matter of fact the problem as
                    deputy assistant secretary when we had this intensive period was to watch the
                    war being managed. As a matter of fact, I had something to do with what happened
                    in '68. The Wise Men period. I was one of the principal leaders in the Wise Men
                    Group in 1968. I had been sent out there after the Tet offensive to look at the
                    political situation. I went with Wheeler. Wheeler went to look at the military
                    situation. I was put on his group to look at the political situation and we came
                    back and we reported. An interesting period. It's been written up in a number of
                    places more or less accurately. Henry Smith wrote about it as accurately as any
                    in the New York Times. This is the group that Johnson used to call on from time
                    to time. There are lists in some of these books that have been written about it.
                    He had Harriman, he had Lodge...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bunker?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, Bunker was not there. He had Douglas Dillon, Arthur Dean, he had Abe
                    Fortas. He had Arthur Coburn, McGeorge Bundy, he had Clark Clifford, Walt
                    Rostow, Max Taylor, Buzz Wheeler. All these guys were members of this group. Of
                    course, Dean Rusk had McNamara as secretary. He had General Ridgway—Matthew
                    Ridgway, the famous general, Omar Bradley. A talented group.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some of the greatest talent we had.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's right. Dean Acheson was the most important of all. Well, when I was
                    deputy assistant secretary, Dean Acheson—Bill Bundy was his son-in-law as you
                    know—Dean Acheson wanted to be briefed about Vietnam and I'd go up and brief
                    him. I used to keep Dean Acheson briefed on Vietnam. One time I said to him, if
                    you want to get a real briefing, I'll bring some people up who will cover the
                    whole war for you—I brought my 11:00 group. I brought George Carver, General De
                    Puy, and Bill Jorden and myself, and we went up there and spent three or four
                    hours telling him what was going on. This is in '68. And then the Wise Men...the
                    way they did it, they'd get briefed and then they'd see the President. Oh, Cy
                    Vance was a member of the Wise Men group. Well, in any event, I'd get a call to
                    be in the Operations Center conference room at 6:00 in the evening to brief the
                    Wise Men on the situation in Vietnam. I'd gone out with Wheeler to look it over
                    in the post-Tet period in '68. And Bill De Puy briefed on the military
                    situation, George Carver briefed on the communist infrastructure, the communist
                    position, and I briefed on the political situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That would be once a week?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>HABIB: No, this is a one-shot briefing. We had briefed the Wise Men. They were
                    never there all the time. They were just brought together, for example, in the
                    post-Tet period. A very significant group there. Johnson wanted to get their
                    view. Remember this is '68, an election is coming up. We'd just had the Tet
                    offensive which was being played up in the media.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think we all know that now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's right. But nevertheless...I remember when a team came into the
                    embassy, the VC came over the embassy compound...hell, I was on the telephone in
                    Washington talking to the duty officer in the embassy while they were in the
                    embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I heard a lot about that period from Rostow.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Arch (Calhoun) was the political counselor. Arch replaced me as political
                    counselor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He came to Tunis as my chief in the embassy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Allen Wendt was the duty officer that night, and I was talking to him on
                    the telephone in the embassy while the VC were in the building. In any event,
                    the Wise Men - I don't remember when I briefed them, but I remember I spoke from
                    an outline on a yellow pad. I never kept any papers, I don't know what the hell
                    I said. All I know is its been said that that briefing was the crucial briefing,
                    the three of us briefing. They went to the President the next day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they didn't say anything.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: They were divided on the war, the most important part of it was Acheson.
                    They told the President, you've got to get out of it. I remember Clark Clifford
                    - Clark Clifford at that point had been named Secretary of Defense. McNamara
                    left, and the first day that Clark Clifford was Secretary of Defense we met in
                    his dining room, a small group - he wanted to put together his recommendations
                    for the President...well, to the Wise Men. The Wise Men had gone no further when
                    they...as a matter of fact, the day after they told the President - this also is
                    written I think in LBJ's memoirs...if it's not LBJ's memoirs, it's in some other
                    memoirs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He didn't write his memoirs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: LBJ? Sure he did, from his vantage point.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's a great picture of me in his memoirs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's right, in LBJ's memoirs. LBJ is supposed to have said when he got
                    these briefings, “Who poisoned the well?” Because these guys were always
                    supporters, Atcheson, and Clark Clifford, people he counted on, telling him that
                    we had to get out of the war. So they told him that they had been briefed. Who
                    briefed them? Well, it was De Puy, Carver and me. Bring them over to the White
                    House, I want to hear what they have to say. I'm sitting in my office, and a
                    phone call comes from Walt Rostow. The President wants to see you. He heard
                    about the briefing, and he wants to be briefed. I said to Walt, I'm just walking
                    out the door, I'm leaving for Dayton, Ohio, I'm making a speech to a thousand
                    students on the Vietnam war telling them the policy. Well, of course, if you
                    insist, I'll cancel and I'll be over there. He said, just a minute, I'll call
                    you back. Five minutes later he called me back and said, that's alright, you go
                    ahead and make the speech. De Puy went and told the President what they had
                    briefed to the Wise Men. But I didn't, because I'd gone to Dayton, Ohio, at the
                    crucial briefing. This is at a period when we were bombing. The assumption was
                    that we'd stop the bombing. I remember Clark Clifford asking me if the war was
                    win-able or not. I said to him, “Not under the present circumstances, and the
                    present mood.” They said to me, “What would you do?” And I said, “I would stop
                    the bombing, and try to negotiate.” Well, of course, that was my reputation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which is exactly what happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: So, at that point we started meeting in Clark Clifford's office - it was
                    official now, Clifford was the Secretary of Defense, my boss Bill Bundy was
                    there. Again, I'm the junior guy. Buzz Wheeler was there, Paul Warnke was there,
                    Bill De Puy was there, Walt Rostow, Max Taylor. Max was also a member of that
                    Wise Men's group.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Everybody who was anybody.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: John J. McCloy. Joe (Califano), what's his name, in the Cabinet who left,
                    is now in New York, very important. Fowler, Clifford, Nick Katzenbach, Bill
                    Bundy, Buzz Wheeler, Paul Warnke, Bill Bundy, myself, that was the group. I
                    wrote a paper on Vietnamization, the importance of providing equipment etc. At
                    that point we didn't even have M-16s throughout their forces. I remember I wrote
                    a paper about the importance of providing at least M-16s, the importance of
                    building up the Vietnamese forces.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was the beginning...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>HABIB: That was the beginning of Vietnamization. A lot of people say Laird
                    introduced that. That was the beginning in that meeting. I wrote papers, others
                    wrote papers...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, this was...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: This must have been April-March of '68. At that point Bill Bundy said to
                    me, “The Secretary of Defense is going to make a speech on Vietnam.” He said,
                    “They are going to write the speech, but they wanted a draft from us.” So Bill
                    Bundy and I wrote a draft speech for the President that went very well. Bill did
                    most of the work, he was a brilliant guy, and I helped, we worked together on
                    it. Bill wrote the first draft. They brought over a draft and we went over that.
                    What I was told was the speech the President was going to make would be that
                    night. I was home that night, turned on the TV, the President was going to make
                    a speech, and the President goes through the speech, and I remembered it, and he
                    gets to the end and he keeps going. I looked at my wife and said, but that's the
                    end of the speech, he's supposed to stop there. That was the statement where he
                    ordered the partial bombing, that's what the speech was all about. That's where
                    we had come as a result of all of these reviews of the war. But we didn't know
                    that the other part of the decision that he made was that he was not going to
                    run for president. That was the last paragraph of the speech. I remember turning
                    to my wife saying, he's supposed to stop there. There's no more. And then he
                    went on which I didn't know anything about, very few people did know - that was
                    the speech of March of '68.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: March or April of '68. Well before convention time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's right, April of '68.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was a shocker.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: You can imagine how shocked I was. Here I was working on this speech and
                    all these great ideas on how to bring negotiation about. We did what we set out
                    to do as a matter of policy, we had a great influence between the working level,
                    had an influence on the bosses, and the bosses then had influence. That was a
                    good example of how the career guys, CIA, Defense, State, the White House—we
                    were the peons. We had a tremendous influence. We followed the war every single
                    day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then you were trusted.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>HABIB: We were trusted, people trusted us—Harriman, Katzenbach, Bundy, Dean Rusk.
                    Well, in any event, Dean Acheson was very important at that time. We then were
                    embarked upon a negotiating process which eventually led to the Paris peace
                    talks, and, in all of the preliminaries of that, I was involved. And then when
                    Harriman and Vance were chosen as head, Harriman asked me to put together the
                    staff and to be the chief of staff. I put together the staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were deputy assistant secretary, and you went to
                        Paris, and you really sort of straddled your Washington...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I was the deputy assistant secretary until '69 when Bill Sullivan came and
                    sat in my chair, but I still kept the title until '69. That was under Nixon, it
                    was after the election. Nixon got elected in '68.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These talks really got underway in '68.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: May 13th, if I remember right. Cy Vance and I went to the first meeting to
                    set the rules of negotiation. Then we had the first primary meeting. Harriman
                    sat in the chair—I've got a picture of the whole delegation the first day. I had
                    put together the staff, recommended it to Harriman. I recommended naturally that
                    from the White House they take Bill Jorden to handle the press and to be a
                    member of the delegation, but also to be responsible for the press. I
                    recommended everybody on that delegation. I took Dan O'Donahue, who was one of
                    my boys in Korea days to run the secretariat, to set it up. He was then working
                    in the secretariat. He was to set up the secretariat. I took Bob Miller, Jim
                    Rosenthal, Dick Holbrooke, John Negroponte, Dave Engel, who was the best
                    Vietnamese language officer in the business, and then I even persuaded the
                    military to take...Harriman had picked Andy Goodpaster. And then I recommended
                    George Seignious, and also the next guy, Paul Gorman. Paul Gorman was the Army
                    officer that I knew who was in the Pentagon and had been in the 1st division in
                    Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Seignious was in Europe at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>HABIB: He was out of that, he was somewhere around. We took him as military
                    adviser, and his assistant was Paul Gorman, who now is the commander of our
                    forces in the Caribbean and Central America. There's an interesting story about
                    him I'll tell you sometime. In any event, this was the beginning of the
                    delegation. Hal Kaplan was assistant to Bill Jorden, he was also a guy who I had
                    worked very closely with in Vietnam. He was the press officer at the embassy
                    under Barry Zorthian, a brilliant guy dealing with the press on a daily basis.
                    At any rate, these are the guys that I put together as a team, and I was the
                    chief of staff. We did all the papers for the negotiation. We had a smaller
                    group in a secret negotiation which I set up also. That was the beginning of the
                    negotiation which then went on for years. From May of '68 until I left in the
                    fall of '71, three and a half years later. Harriman and Vance were the first
                    people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they keep you in Paris permanently?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I was assigned temporary duty and I was there all the time, never left
                    except for briefing trips back home. We started out living at the Crillon Hotel
                    and after seven or eight months of eating out all the time, I rented a little
                    pad, a two and a half room pad up in an old house about five minutes from the
                    embassy. I could fall out of bed and be in the embassy in five minutes if
                    anything happened, and we began the negotiations. The negotiations were for the
                    purpose of a total bombing halt, and to negotiate the end of war. From our
                    standpoint, we were willing to go for a total bombing halt, but we wanted to get
                    a proper negotiation going including the South Vietnamese. We had South
                    Vietnamese liaison guys there in Paris. But the actual negotiations were between
                    us and the North Vietnamese. We started in May and by the fall of that year we
                    had negotiated the total bombing halt under conditions of bringing about full
                    fledged negotiations, and also with certain understandings as to what would not
                    be done. It's beginning to fade from my memory, but it's still quite clear what
                    we did, including such things as no major attacks on cities. We had all sorts of
                    things which were quite clear from what had gone on in the negotiations.</p>
                <p>We had two levels of negotiations. We had the formal talks every Thursday. We
                    would convene at the Majestic Hotel at avenue Kleber. The delegation would file
                    into this magnificant conference hall, and we'd sit there and read statements to
                    each other, and go out and talk to the TV cameras, and go back to the office and
                    meet again the next Thursday. Well, that went on for a while, and obviously we
                    weren't going to do anything under that spotlight, so we had a couple of private
                    meetings, and then we set up the formal secret negotiations. They had a safe
                    house, and we had a safe house. Our safe house was staffed by the CIA, but with
                    Defense people living there, and a couple of secretaries took care of the safe
                    house. And they had a safe house which was supplied to them by the French
                    communist party. Sometimes we meet in our safe house, sometimes we'd meet in
                    their safe house.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was their's?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>HABIB: Outside on the fringe of the city.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: (Inaudible)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's right. That was the Kissinger thing. Now, we ran it secretly.
                    Nobody knew, nobody had a clue where they were. They knew that something was
                    wrong, but couldn't figure out what. I remember one CBS reporter said, now we've
                    figured it out, you're meeting on a houseboat on the Seine. Yes, that's right,
                    on a houseboat, you get a rowboat and follow us out. They never discovered it,
                    and why? We ran it, we were professionals. Nothing ever leaked from them, or
                    from us. We had a whole series of good meetings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Maintaining secrecy on both sides.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's right, and we held I don't know how many dozens of these meetings
                    until we negotiated the terms of understanding. As a matter of fact, they were
                    finally initialed and signed on the last day, but I wasn't there. When they were
                    finalized and initialed, I had been ordered back to brief the President because
                    there was a lot going on back here so I came back to Washington to brief people
                    here on where things stood. I didn't attend the last secret meetings with
                    Harriman and Vance which was the only time that they allowed photographs up
                    until that time. There were photographs taken at the last meeting. I don't have
                    a copy because I wasn't there - one of the photographs I really would have liked
                    to have because I had been one of the players right from the beginning. Cy Vance
                    and I had carried on most of the secret negotiations. We would bring Harriman in
                    for the key ones. Cy and I had meeting after meeting, and a couple of times I
                    had meetings alone - at the last stages when we were drafting terms in getting
                    the agreement on the shape of the table. All that was done in that period under
                    the secret negotiation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you would have the press come in...around for those
                        once a week meetings.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's right. The press was there for the once a week meetings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they thought they knew everything that was
                        happening.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>HABIB: The time when the press arrived, after the formal, once-a-week
                    negotiations, with nothing going on, we were having intensive 7-8 hour-long
                    meetings with the Vietnamese that the press knew nothing about. Now the way we
                    managed it - I set up the system. For example, let's say the meeting was in our
                    safe house—we had a safe house in a place called St. Cloud. We had one somewhere
                    else and a third one in another place, then the Vietnamese had a safe house out
                    at Choisy-le-Roi. Harriman would stay out in Auteuil. Vance would be at the
                    embassy with me. We had a CIA guy, with an unmarked car rented by this CIA guy.
                    He was not a guy from the station. He was a special guy brought in nobody
                    knew.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Even the station didn't know him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Well the station knew him, but he would rent a private car. He would park
                    the car up by the Madeleine. The meetings usually consisted of Harriman, Vance
                    and myself, John Negroponte and Dave Engel, Bill Jorden. Negroponte and Engel
                    would do the notes, and I would take notes too. If it was just Vance, it would
                    be Vance, myself and probably Negroponte, the three of us, or maybe Engel
                    would.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you each talk in your own language and then use a
                        translator?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't compromise on French or anything like
                        that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, they wouldn't do that. They wouldn't negotiate in French. They
                    wouldn't do it even in the big meetings, they would not negotiate in French. The
                    only time they would speak French and negotiate was privately. One night I had
                    the deputy guy over for dinner at my apartment, and we spoke French.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have your wife come over?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Not at this point, not at the early stages.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't know how long you were going to be there.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>HABIB: My wife stayed with the children at home, one kid was finishing high
                    school. At any rate, the guy would park the car up there at a given hour - let's
                    say the meeting was going to be at 10:00, a half hour drive so. At 9:00 Dave
                    Engel carrying the documents in a sachel would wander up toward the Madeleine,
                    get into the car, the driver would then drive down and he would go up the
                    Champs-Elys�es. Meanwhile, Cy Vance and I would go out the back door of the
                    embassy and we would walk as if we were taking a stroll in the park along the
                    Champs-Elys�es, and at a given moment we would be at the curb on a certain spot
                    on the Champs-Elys�es, the car would stop, and he and I would get in the car,
                    and we would then drive out to where Ambassador Harriman would be outside of a
                    flower shop at a certain time. We would pick him up and we would head out. Of
                    course, nobody knew where the hell we were going. We did that from May until
                    October, and then we finished the negotiations. We finished them actually in
                    October. Of course, at that point we thought we were going to be a big success.
                    Of course, Harriman was very anxious to get this done before the elections to
                    avert, as he put it, the greatest disaster - Richard Nixon. That was the way he
                    felt. So he was doing everything to get Humphrey elected. Vance was marvelous.
                    They were very political. Of course, we stayed out of the politics. In fact, I
                    think most of those at the meetings wanted to get it done before the election
                    too, because they were being stubborn as hell - from May, June, July, August,
                    they wouldn't give a thing. And all of a sudden, one day, we had been pressing
                    them what would we get if we gave a total bombing halt. At the total bombing
                    halt we wanted specific things to happen. And finally, one day, the head of
                    their delegation, a member of the Politburo, said to Harriman and Vance, “If we
                    do so and so and so, will you stop the bombing?” At that point, you knew you had
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had the agreement.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It was just that stubbornness and reading reams of propaganda bullshit,
                    even in the secret talks. They finally agreed to what we needed, and what we
                    wanted, and the deal was cooked. And then something happened.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before the election.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Before the election. First of all somebody got to Thieu on behalf of Nixon
                    and said, don't agree, come to Paris.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was the source.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>HABIB: It was done right here in Washington. A Republican went to a famous woman
                    called Anna Chennault. Anna Chennault went to the Vietnamese and told the
                    Vietnamese, “We'll get a better deal under Nixon.” So Thieu refused to accept
                    the agreement and sent a delegation to Paris. Clark Clifford was fit to be tied,
                    particularly Clark. Harriman was about to climb the wall. Well finally, of
                    course, the election was held and Humphrey lost.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It could have turned out differently.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's correct. I'm convinced that, if Humphrey had won the election, the
                    war would have been over much sooner. I know what we were going to negotiate
                    under Harriman and Vance, and that was not what we negotiated under the later
                    generation, basically under Henry Kissinger and Nixon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It took them a long time to get cranked up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Kissinger was somewhat familiar because he had been a consultant. As a
                    matter of fact, the great article that Kissinger had written about the
                    negotiations, he really stole that from us. It was in the form of a briefing
                    which I gave him in Paris before he wrote the article. It was exactly the
                    position that I had in some way espoused. And also I had written a special paper
                    for Harriman on what to do about getting the negotiations on track which he was
                    going to buy. Of course the election was held and a new group came along. First
                    of all, Henry Cabot Lodge was appointed head. You couldn't get the thing cranked
                    up until after the inauguration which meant you marked time until January.
                    Meanwhile the Vietnamese agreed to come, so they formed their delegation, and
                    the Viet Cong came with their delegation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember the table problem.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>HABIB: A round table, with no sides—our side, your side was the formula we used.
                    It was a simple thing to arrange. People said it took them three months to
                    decide on the shape of the table, that was a bunch of shit. We knew what the
                    table was going to be from the beginning, it was going to be a round table. It
                    was the only way you were going to solve the problem. We knew that but we had to
                    go through this whole routine of satisfying the South Vietnamese, and beating
                    down the arguments of the North Vietnamese who wanted the VC as an equal
                    delegation. They talked about a four-party negotiation, and we talked about an
                    “our side, your side” negotiation. We finally resolved the problem by a round
                    table. We knew we were going to do that. But you couldn't solve anything when
                    you didn't have delegations. And then we had an election and we had to wait
                    until the new administration was in. The new administration appointed Cabot
                    Lodge as head of the delegation and, of course, he had a so-called number two
                    called Walsh, a lawyer from New York who didn't know anything about the problem.
                    He was a Republican lawyer from New York who was in the early Nixon
                    administration. But Cabot insisted that I had to remain. At this point I wanted
                    my just rewards. I could have an embassy anywhere I wanted - I might as well get
                    an embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was '69. You were two more years there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: In February '69 Nixon came to Europe. I had gone back to Washington and
                    briefed the new cabinet. I briefed the NSC. Kissinger was there, Mel Laird, John
                    Mitchell, Spiro Agnew, they brought Ellsworth Bunker back from Saigon, and John
                    Mitchell, the famous Attorney General who later became somewhat notorious,
                    Watergate notorious.</p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>At any rate, I've got a great picture. I had kept the same small group, a couple
                    of changes of people in the group - Dick Smyser joined us. Bill Jorden left, Hal
                    Kaplan became the senior spokesman. By this time George Carver had finished his
                    tour as the military adviser. I got word that all they really wanted to send us
                    was an Air Force colonel as military adviser, or maybe he was a Brigadier
                    General. A nice guy, I knew him, but he was semi-political and I wanted a ground
                    forces officer who knew the war. This guy didn't know anything about the war, he
                    was away from the action, a military man in the NSC. I went to Cabot Lodge and
                    said, “Jesus, I know that guy - he'll want to tell us how to run the god-damned
                    negotiation instead of being our military adviser.” The funny thing is I saw the
                    guy in an airport about three weeks ago when I was flying to Atlanta - he's
                    retired now. And I said to Cabot, “No, we can't take him. We've got to get an
                    Army man who stays on the ground.” “Well who do you recommend?” I said, “I know
                    just the guy, and a guy you liked, Freddy Weyand.” He says, “Where is he?” I
                    said, “They've got him in some crummy job in charge of the reserves in
                    Washington.” “Get Freddy Weyand.” Freddy had been 25th division commander, and a
                    guy whom I had worked with in Saigon. So we were at breakfast at the White
                    House, Lodge, myself, Wheeler, the President and Henry Kissinger. Lodge
                    approached this business, we didn't want this guy Walt Rostow had fobbed off on
                    Henry. Henry didn't know. They didn't intend to make those negotiations much
                    anyway. So I said we'd take Freddy Weyand. And that's how we got Freddy Weyand.
                    We saved Freddy Weyand's career, he later became chief of staff of the Army. And
                    the reason he did was because from Paris he went to Saigon as deputy commander,
                    and then he became commander of MACV, and then he became chief of staff of the
                    Army.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He'd been on the slow track.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's right, a good soldier. Just like Paul Gorman is a four-star general
                    now, a Lt. General. Paul was a colonel with us. I pinned the DSC on him, as a
                    matter of fact, when he left us. He was assigned to some routine job. I said,
                    “What do you want?” He said, “I want to go back to Vietnam as a combat
                    commander.” I was in the office of Mel Laird, and I told him about this guy and
                    said he wants a job as combat commander, he's a good man. He was a battalion
                    commander, he was decorated by the President with a DSC. And Mel Laird turned to
                    Bob Pursely (phonetic) who was military assistant and said, see what you can do
                    about it. And they made him assistant division chief of the 101st Airborne. He
                    went back to Vietnam and from there he was commander of the 4th division in
                    Colorado Springs, and a few other assignments. He's now the theater commander in
                    the Caribbean and Central America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's because they got their rewards.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>HABIB: Cabot came, and we began sort of floundering around. At that point Henry
                    Kissinger entered the negotiations by deciding that he's going to run the secret
                    negotiating. And he starts out, in my opinion and I told him later...he had Dick
                    Walters who was then the military attach�, set up the god damned negotiation,
                    and said nothing to us. Henry's lack of confidence in the secrecy of the Foreign
                    Service...here I had run the secret negotiations, and he knew me. He knew me for
                    a long time, hell I knew him when he was at Harvard. And yet, instead of getting
                    me to set up the secret negotiations, he gets a military attach�, this secretive
                    fellow called Dick Walters, to set up the negotiations through a Frenchmen, mind
                    you, who was a friend of Kissinger's. I should say his wife was a friend of
                    Kissinger's, a guy called Jean Sainteny who was an old Indo-Chinese hand. He
                    gets the god-damned first secret meeting with them set up through Walters and
                    Sainteny in Sainteny's apartment. And they go to the meeting and Henry thinks
                    Walters is going to do the interpreting and speak French - he finds out the guys
                    won't speak French in the negotiations. So he didn't have them. Instead of
                    taking my man, Dave Engel, whom I had offered him. I said to him, I knew that
                    they were doing this. He had with him Winston Lord, Tony Lake and this
                    character, Walters. None of them knew anything about anything at that point
                    compared to us. He wouldn't use...I had Dave Engel, I had John Negroponte, I had
                    Dick Holbrooke, Dick Smyser, and he decided to do it this way. Of course, he
                    soon learned that he had to have Dave Engel. Years later, years later, John
                    Negroponte was head of the delegation, but he was working for Kissinger, not for
                    me. He was on the NSC at that time. He wouldn't use the mechanism that we had,
                    either in terms of...now, first of all, they ended up by not being secret. Lodge
                    left because he didn't want to hang around any longer. I became acting head of
                    the division and lasted about nine months, and then they decided to make it
                    appear as if we were upgrading our interest and had David Bruce come. David
                    lasted several months, I forget how long. He was there for about nine months,
                    and he got fed up and he left. I was acting again, and then I finally broke
                    loose and went as ambassador to Korea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go to Henry before you started trying to leave
                        there? I mean, did you talk to Henry?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, no. They knew I wanted to leave. Henry was operating on his own
                    directly with the President and I would see him rarely. That was about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Department didn't get in at that time on
                        guidance.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>HABIB: Nothing. He didn't take any guidance from Bill Rogers. Who was going to
                    give guidance. By this time he had enough sense to get a few guys with him. Bill
                    Sullivan was with him. I don't think Bill Sullivan actually got there until
                    about '71 or so. George Aldridge helped him with the drafting at the end. These
                    are the sort of things that went on at that time. John Negroponte and Dave Engel
                    was the interpreter. Negroponte had left the delegation and went to Stanford for
                    a year and when he came back Henry asked me to hire him for the NSC, and I gave
                    him a high recommendation. Dick Smyser was also one of my guys who was in the
                    delegation who later went to the NSC. Henry used to take my advice about FSOs in
                    the NSC. He did that from the beginning. When he first came to Washington he
                    asked me who were good people, and I gave him the names of good people, and he
                    took them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You played your cards well with him because he obviously
                        liked you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Well, we got along because I knew him very well. As I said to you earlier,
                    with Henry you had to speak your piece otherwise you didn't get a chance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had he come on missions to Vietnam while you were
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Yes. The first time I met him was when he came to Vietnam. You probably
                    never heard him tell that story about the time I threw him out of my office. The
                    first time he ever came in, the first time I ever saw him. He was a professor
                    and Henry Cabot Lodge called me in and said that Johnson was sending this
                    professor out. Did I know this Professor Kissinger? I said, I don't know him but
                    I know who he is, he's written that book that everybody knew about: Nuclear
                    weapons and Foreign Policy. So this guy shows up at my door one morning. I was
                    in one of my particular moods, so I looked at him and said, “Professor, you
                    don't know a god-damn thing about this place. I'm a very busy fellow. If you
                    want to learn something about it, I'll give you a couple of my guys who know the
                    language, know the country. You go around the country, spend a couple of weeks
                    looking the situation over, then you come back and I'll have time to talk to
                    you. In the meantime, get the hell out of my office.” That's exactly the way I
                    greeted him. He tells the story all the time, I literally told him to get the
                    hell out of my office, I didn't have time for him. But he followed my advice. As
                    a matter of fact, I gave him Dave Engel, and I gave him Vlad Lehovich to take
                    him around, take him up country and show him around. I think John Negroponte
                    went with him too to show him a little bit about what the hell the war was all
                    about. Interesting enough, Henry hated to fly, you know, at that time. He was
                    literally pained flying, but he would do it. He would grit his teeth and he'd go
                    up in these god damned little airplanes and flit around the countryside. Then he
                    came back and we became very good friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was chairman of the day, I guess, at the Senior Seminar
                        and he had recently come back from Vietnam and we had him talk to us. My job
                        was also to go out and meet him at National Airport at some ungodly hour
                        like 7:30 in the morning when he came down on the Eastern shuttle from
                        Boston. I bought him breakfast, and I even managed to get a State Department
                        limousine. I literally spent until 10:00 at night with him that day, except
                        in the afternoon he had an appointment over in the Executive Office Building
                        and I more or less cooled my heels out in the corridor while he was doing
                        that, and I found that he'd sneaked across to the White House in the
                        meantime and came back. I remember we had a terrific storm that day and his
                        plane was delayed getting up to Boston - he was supposed to go off on the
                        7:00 shuttle - and I think he got off finally on the 10:00 flight. We had
                        sandwiches and beer waiting for the weather to clear up. Had a long time to
                        talk with him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Well, after I came back from Vietnam as deputy, I used to see him at
                    Harvard. He once had me lecture to his famous seminar. I actually stayed with
                    him that night.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was a high honor.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: He had a bachelor apartment at that time. He was separated from his wife.
                    Yes, I lectured to his seminar. He told that story many times. He told it to my
                    staff when he first visited me in Korea when I was ambassador. He told that
                    story to the assembled staff, about how good my judgement was that I threw the
                    future Secretary of State out of my office. Those were days when we were working
                    very hard and didn't have time to waste our time talking to people who didn't
                    know anything. He took my advice. He actually went out and spent those two weeks
                    flying around the country, learning what the hell the war was all about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had three and a half years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Yes. I left there in the fall. I was due to leave earlier and, when Bruce
                    left, I stayed on a couple of months and then came home. By that time, my wife
                    was living in Paris, my oldest daughter was in college. So we came home and
                    spent a few months waiting to go to Korea, and then took off for Korea. Arrived
                    in Korea, if I remember, about November of '71. It was fine, found a lot of
                    people I knew, things were moving along. Immediately sort of got occupied with
                    the...of course, one of the things that was still occupying us was the Vietnam
                    war. First of all, of course, in February of '72, I'd only been in the post four
                    months, and I got ill and got evacuated to Walter Reed. I had my first heart
                    attack, had it in Walter Reed. I was having chest pains and I went to the doctor
                    in Korea, and he took one look at my cardiogram and put me in bed. Two weeks
                    later I was on a medical airplane to Walter Reed Hospital in Washington. And it
                    was while I was at Walter Reed that I had my first heart attack. It's a good
                    thing I was at Walter Reed.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, he evacuated you before just on the basis of
                        pressure.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: They were talking about an operation while I was in the cardiac care unit
                    and I had this massive seizure, and fortunately I was there, otherwise I never
                    would have made it. They saved me, and I spent three months recuperating, then
                    went back to my post. They came out to the hospital to see me and said don't
                    worry, the post is there, it's waiting for you. You get better, you go back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your DCM?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Frank Underhill. So I went back to Korea and started the recuperation. I
                    went back in late May—remember I went to the hospital in February. In May I went
                    right back to Korea. I remember I hitched a ride on Secretary Laird's plane,
                    went to Korea and for the first month I sort of worked half a day, four hours,
                    then I boosted it to eight hours, then pretty soon I began the usual...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The routine of twelve or fifteen.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Well, sporadic. Then, that fall, the negotiations on Vietnam were winding
                    down. It was in that fall, after Henry had negotiated the first agreement, he
                    asked me to come down to Saigon. I went down to Saigon and met him there. Then
                    we went over the agreement, just the two of us together. He wanted my opinion
                    about it, and I told him I thought it was as good as you'll get. It was a shame
                    it had taken so long to get, but it's as good as you'll get and you ought to
                    stick with it, you ought to jam it through. Of course, the South Vietnamese
                    balked at part of it and didn't want to go through with it. That's all written
                    up in Henry's book and then he went back to meetings with the North Vietnamese.
                    They wouldn't make any more concessions, and that's when I think you got the
                    Christmas bombing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was Christmas '72.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>HABIB: And they came back on, and Henry had asked me if I would come back as
                    Assistant Secretary. And I said, “No, I couldn't do it, I was just too soon out
                    of the hospital. The doctor didn't think I should do it.” I said to him, Bob
                    Ingersoll was ambassador to Japan, I said he would be a good man, he's a very
                    good, sound fellow. So Bob Ingersoll became Assistant Secretary. That would be
                    the fall of '72 or the spring of '73, somewhere in there, anyway we were very
                    active in Korea with this business of, first of all, support for the Vietnamese
                    and getting the equipment down there. Then there were some conversations going
                    on between the north and the south, and we got a little bit involved. It was a
                    very busy time, a big embassy, lots to do, the Korean communists were moving
                    ahead very strongly. I spent a lot of time on economic-commercial matters,
                    business, visitors, the usual thing. And then, of course, we had the military. A
                    large military establishment, the United Nations command, it was called the 8th
                    Army. There were all sorts of changes going on, the relationship with the
                    Vietnamese. It was a pretty successful time. We were hoping that Park would go,
                    and have a proper election. But he ended up by perpetuating his rule a little
                    longer. I'll never forget that assassination attempt on him when his wife was
                    killed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It happened right in front of me. I was there when it happened. A funny
                    thing. They were having this annual sort of national day celebration which was
                    traditional for him to speak in an auditorium up on the edge of town. When we
                    drove up, there were guards all along. I remember saying to Marge, my wife,
                    something to the effect that there were a lot of guards, wouldn't it be
                    something if there were an attempt on him. And within an hour there was an
                    attempt on him. It had popped into my mind. Because you always thought of it
                    anyway. At any rate, they missed him. They killed his wife. At that point, I had
                    already received my orders to return to Washington as Assistant Secretary. I
                    stayed for the funeral, I represented the U.S. at the funeral, then left and
                    went back to Washington and began the two years as Assistant Secretary, before I
                    moved up to Under Secretary. That was a very hectic period because of the
                    Vietnam war - the war had started up again. We couldn't get money out of
                    Congress. I was constantly up on the Hill testifying on what was going on,
                    trying to get funds to finance military purchases for the Vietnamese. We were
                    doing very badly. Then of course in '74 and '75 it really began to turn bad. The
                    North Vietnamese defeated the South Vietnamese in the highlands. You had them
                    sneaking down across the border. I was having a great deal of difficulty with
                    the embassy because the embassy took a somewhat different attitude toward what
                    the hell was going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who do you mean?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>HABIB: Well, in the embassy...I'm talking about in Saigon. Graham Martin was
                    ambassador at this time, he replaced Ellsworth Bunker. Graham is a strange man.
                    He was wrong about a lot of things, and he is very stubborn.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He didn't come out of it very well.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It destroyed him, it destroyed him physically and somewhat mentally
                    too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I came back with him on a plane from Rome when he was back
                        on consultation and I had a talk with him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: He and I had a real falling out, we later made it up. My staff was
                    convinced, of course, that, once that breakout began, the war was over, the
                    North Vietnamese were going to sweep right down.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well the South Vietnamese had based their strategy on
                        stopping them well outside.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: They came down right through. Well, in any event, the great evacuation.
                    Then we began getting involved with the question of refugees. I was up on the
                    Hill constantly during that period, before the fall of Saigon in our attempt to
                    try get more help for them. But it was only American power that could hold them
                    back even though Richard Nixon had promised them that if the agreement was
                    broken, we'd be back to save them. Gerry Ford never got to keep that agreement,
                    the mood of the public the way it was. I remember the famous ship, the Mayaguez,
                    that was the end.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was back in the Department by that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It was a very active time. We had the incident on the DMZ when we took
                    some very strong measures. But we didn't do some of the things some of the
                    people wanted to do. There were suggestions of great drastic actions,
                    fortunately they were not carried out. I was preoccupied with a lot of things.
                    We had China. I guess I went three times with Kissinger, and President Ford's
                    trip.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go on his first trip?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>HABIB: No, no. I was back in Korea on his first trip. I went on some of the
                    negotiating trips when we were trying to negotiate normalization. And then we
                    had Ford's trip to Japan, first trip to Japan by a President. I was Assistant
                    Secretary at that time. Then we had the Ford trip to China. I was Assistant
                    Secretary and I went on that, and did a lot of the preparatory work, donkey
                    work. After the trip to China the President went to Indonesia and the
                    Philippines and I accompanied him. There was a lot to do, I was working day and
                    night. I think Henry and Joe Sisco had gotten along up to a point. Joe wanted
                    out, or whether he wanted out or he didn't want out, it was about the time Joe
                    was leaving and Henry asked me to take his job, and I took it, and I became
                    Under Secretary for Political Affairs, and that got me involved in everything
                    from then on, including another trip to China.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It would be interesting for purposes of this book because
                        Bob Murphy went into that job and writes in his Diplomat Among Warriors
                        about...in a way he had been almost entirely a European man, European and
                        Mediterranean.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's right, and skipped the line about everything else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right, but you'd had a broader experience.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I'd had a wider, broader experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You'd served on three continents.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: So when I moved into the job, even though I'd spent most of my career in
                    East Asia, I'd had some experience, largely in the Washington context, which is
                    important. So I didn't have too much trouble with shifting to a broader range of
                    interests.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you pretty much control your own day?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                <p>HABIB: No. The way I ran the job, I had good relations with all of the Assistant
                    Secretaries fortunately. Even in the case of EUR they would sometimes come to
                    me, but the guys in NEA were used to going into that office, so I began getting
                    deeply involved in NEA. I even got involved with some of the AF stuff. Wherever
                    anything was going on, Henry would ask me to do it. For example, I got involved
                    in the Maldives-Honduras argument. I got involved in the Cyprus business. I went
                    to the UN each fall to the sessions with Henry. And, of course, we had the China
                    thing going on all the time. The China thing was always there. In the latter
                    part we began the Rhodesian business. I was involved in all the planning for
                    that. Then, of course, I was very much involved in personnel matters in the
                    Foreign Service. I was the liaison with CIA in terms of covert action. I was the
                    clearing point. I was a member of the committee that parceled out intelligence
                    community money. I'd been all of these things that were constantly coming at
                    us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You always had to be interested in the subjects that the
                        Secretary considered most important at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It wasn't a question of just telling you. He handled everything, he never
                    let anything go. Therefore, he was involved in everything. And then I got so I
                    was the referee between the bureau and him. It changed, of course, when the
                    administration changed. When Ford lost to Carter I was Under Secretary and I
                    remember I got a phone call in December from Cy Vance before the new
                    administration took office, and Cy said, don't think you're going anywhere,
                    you're going to stay right there. I had known Vance when he was Secretary of the
                    Army briefly, and then I knew him intimately when we were in Paris. We used to
                    see each other constantly every day, and I'd be over to his house especially
                    when I was alone they would have me over for meals with the kids, I was sort of
                    like an older brother in the family. Vance and I had stayed in touch, he's a
                    fine man, I enjoyed him, a great man, really a decent man. At any rate, it kept
                    me busy as hell.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went into the Under Secretary's job when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: June or July of '76, and the administration changed in '78, and I stayed
                    on. I guess I was about the only guy at that level in the entire government that
                    stayed on. I got deeply involved in the Middle East. I was very much involved in
                    the Israeli-Arab relationship and how things were going. I traveled with Vance
                    through the Middle East. We went all over testing the water. When Kissinger
                    left, of course, the Department lost a nimble mind and vision(?) of thinking.
                    But in Vance they got good solid sincerity, honest and straightforward.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The thing that touched me about Vance is that shortly
                        after the Carter administration came in he had all the ambassadors to the
                        Arab states in Aman and I went over for that while you were briefing him on
                        your area and the Secretary of State taking notes on what you had to
                        say.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>HABIB: Very organized. At any rate, I stayed on and the range of problems
                    continued. Probably at that point in '77 we concentrated a great deal of
                    attention on moving the peace process forward in the Middle East. So I had a
                    number of trips to the Middle East with Vance. Of course, I was supervising the
                    work in the bureau at the 7th floor level. I did all sorts of things. But one
                    day when Sadat made his opening pitch before he had actually done very much, the
                    Secretary asked me to go to Moscow to meet with Gomulka. I met with Gomulka and
                    tried to persuade them not to be so negative to the Sadat initiative. At any
                    rate, I took off to meet Cy in Brussels for a NATO council meeting, and then he
                    and I flew together to Saudi Arabia, Egypt, Syria, Lebanon and Jordan. Well, on
                    the way home I was feeling pretty punk. The airplane landed at Andrews that
                    evening about 6-7:00, maybe a little later. I got home slept, got up in the
                    morning, it was cold as hell in December. There was ice all over the windshield
                    of my car. Now there's a good example...I had a chauffeur-driven car, but I
                    never had him pick me up at the house in the morning, I drove my own car to
                    work, and then I'd use it only for officially...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A good way to stay out of the newspapers.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: A good way to stay out of the newspapers, but it ended up I was scraping
                    the ice off the windshield of my car when I had a seizure. I barely made it to
                    my office, practically collapsed in my office. It was 7:00 in the morning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From Andrews going...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No, this is in the morning after we'd arrived at Andrews.</p>
                <p>I barely made it to my office. I remember Hal Saunders...I was due at the White
                    House for breakfast, Menachem Begin, Cy Vance and the President. And I had told
                    Cy the night before when we got in to Andrews, I'll meet you at the office at
                    7:00 and we'll go over together. But I got to the office at 7:00 and barely made
                    it to the room, collapsed and they called an ambulance and I got hauled out to
                    Walter Reed. So I didn't make the breakfast with Begin and the President. They
                    put me in intensive care in Walter Reed...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They had your file.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>HABIB: Yes, and I had an arrest that day. They had sedated me so they shocked me
                    back with the paddles. They kept me there for a few days, and by golly I had
                    another arrest. I got over it, and they put me on a lot of pills, I was taking
                    at one time something like 36 pills, each a different kind, in one day. I'd have
                    to get up in the middle of the night and take a pill. They were trying to adjust
                    the rhythm of my heart by pills. What had happened, of course, the first heart
                    attack left a scar and a bulge in my heart and that would always stay with me,
                    and the pain. So the next thing I know, they said I'm in the hospital
                    recuperating and when I recuperated I came back to the Department. Oh well, now
                    you can go back to work, other people do. And I said, no, I don't think so. I'll
                    take some time off to see if I can get my health back. So I went out to Stanford
                    as Diplomatic in Residence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you stepped down from the office.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Obviously I wasn't going to be able to keep up that pace anymore. So I
                    went out as Diplomat in Residence at Stanford in 1978. Well, I had another few
                    bad incidents, arrests. What was happening, I would feel them coming on, and I'd
                    get to the hospital.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were at Stanford, did you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I had it at Stanford, yes. And finally I went to this doctor of mine. He
                    had been my doctor at Walter Reed. He was once chief of cardiology at Walter
                    Reed and he had retired, and he was now a professor out at the University of
                    California hospital, a teaching professor. He started working on me. He got me
                    an angiogram again to find out what was wrong. Quite obviously I had serious
                    blockages in my arteries. So it was operation time. In '78, August-September, I
                    had the operation. He gave me two by-passes, and they took the bulge out of my
                    heart that was there from the first heart attack. They just removed the scar
                    tissue and sewed the heart back up together again. After the operation everybody
                    thought everything went so well. I'm lying in the intensive care unit, and I had
                    a stroke, I was completely paralyzed. It was a clot. Well, that was bad and they
                    really got frantic at that point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was a clot from the operation probably.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: They don't know what it was. Don't you know they never admit the operation
                    went wrong. It happened. At any rate, they saved me. I'm still to this day don't
                    know what happened. So I relaxed for a while, when I was supposed to teach I
                    just postponed. And then I ended up by teaching two quarters instead of four
                    quarters. I taught in the quarters in '78 and the spring of '79, and then in
                    June of '79 I came back to Washington ready for work up to a point at any rate.
                    I'd had the operation and I was feeling pretty good. So I became senior adviser
                    to the Secretary, and worked on odd jobs like the Caribbean.</p>
                <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like the Ambassador-at-Large function.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It was a little different in my case in the sense that my personal
                    relationship with Vance was very close. I went to China with him too, I had been
                    earlier to China. But in this period I did special jobs. I did the Caribbean, I
                    gave my time to some of the Central America stuff. He asked me to chair a
                    committee on the recruitment and examination of the Foreign Service, a
                    commission report which should be around. It was a very good report.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It had a big impact on the new legislation, the
                        1980...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It did in the sense that we produced some ideas on what to do about the
                    problems of getting in other people in the affirmative action program. At the
                    end of that it was quite clear that I wasn't going to be the same, so I retired.
                    I went back to California.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we retire on the same day? Did you retire in 1980?
                        February 29th. That was the best day to resign because you'd get the
                        kick-back from the raise before, and the raise after. Well, anyway, it was a
                        good time to retire.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I resigned because I didn't think I could carry a full load.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And here you are.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I went back to Stanford. I was a senior fellow at the Hoover Institution,
                    and they kept me on there. I lived in a house I had bought some years earlier in
                    Belmont, California. About that time a guy called George Shultz called me up, he
                    was president of Bechtel, asked me to drop around. I did and he offered me...I
                    would be a consultant to Bechtel on a retaining basis from month to year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: An offer you couldn't refuse.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: He was a nice guy and we had an understanding.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't know him before.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                <p>HABIB: I had met him early on, when he was Secretary of Labor, and we had mutual
                    friends. One of my good friends, and one of his good friends, was Jim Hodgson
                    who earlier was ambassador to Japan. Jim and I got along very well, in fact we
                    actually played golf with Shultz. At any rate Shultz offered me this, and I took
                    it. I became a trustee of the Asia Foundation, trustee of the World Affairs
                    Council, and trustee of the Pacific Basin. You know, how you take on those do
                    good things. This is what I was doing in California.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you travel for Bechtel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: No. I had an understanding with George that my job was not to lobby in
                    Washington, and not to go abroad to seek business. It was not my job. My job was
                    to be available when they wanted to sit down and talk about things, be available
                    for meetings, and advisory. And on that basis I took it. I was offered other
                    things, I just didn't take them. Then I was offered a seat on the board of a
                    company in Hawaii by a friend of mine working in that part of the country. He
                    asked me to join him in his private company. So I began doing things like
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you got elected.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Back in 1980, in '81 Reagan gets elected. By this time I'm down in Florida
                    playing golf in the middle of winter, and I get a phone call from Bud McFarlane
                    who was going to be Al Haig's counselor, and said Al wanted to talk to me. Bud
                    said Al wants to know if you might be willing to come to Washington, he wants to
                    talk to you. I said, well, ask him to call me, we'll talk about it. So Al
                    called...I knew Haig from Vietnam days, and also when he was in the NSC, we
                    worked together and always got along. And Haig called me and said, I'd like you
                    to come up to Washington, I'd like to talk to you. What about? He said, I want
                    to talk to you about personnel, who are the good guys, who to put in what job.
                    So on January the 20some odd, I arrived in Washington. Haig was Secretary of
                    State, and I gave my advice. We went through a list of people whom I thought
                    were good. Some of them he took, some he didn't, some he made assistant
                    secretaries, some he made ambassadors, some he just didn't do anything about.
                    But I gave him what I thought were the best guys in various fields, and he made
                    notes about it. He was very good about it, and I left. I went back to where I
                    was in Florida, and suddenly I get a call one day, it was the missile crisis.
                    The Syrians had moved, the Israelis were back in the [middle] of the fight, shot
                    down two Syrian helicopters, and the Syrians had anti-aircraft surface to air
                    missiles in the valley. The Israelis were going to knock them all out, or else
                    they had to be out. Well, quite obviously we stepped in to try to tranquilize
                    the situation. The Israelis were very unhappy about Palestinian action along the
                    northern border. At any rate, I negotiated an understanding, sort of ad hoc,
                    unwritten, sometimes ambiguous agreement on the matter in which the PLO would
                    behave in southern Lebanon. I negotiated all that just by going back and forth.
                    That was the beginning of my...</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...shuttle. We'd see you on television every night.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Well, in that period I completed tranquilizing the border, things were
                    quiet, and I came back to Washington, and went back to California. And the
                    Secretary asked me, what to do, and I gave him my views. At one point it was
                    decided that I would go back to the Middle East to see if I could improve the
                    security conditions in southern Lebanon and get the PLO a lower profile to
                    soothe the Israelis a little bit. So I decided I would do that and combine that
                    with a vacation, so I told my oldest daughter to come with me, I'd take her to
                    the Greek islands and show her the Greek islands, and we'd come back. Then I had
                    meeting on the Middle East, this was in '82 at Fitchley House. So my daughter
                    and I arrived at Fitchley, and I've got reservations, we're going to go to
                    Greece and tour the islands. It was June of 1982, I guess it was June 6th or the
                    5th that the Israeli ambassador got shot in London. Again, the Israelis are
                    going to use that. The President was at a summit meeting, I got a phone call
                    from him, we're sending a plane for you, the President wants to see you. So I
                    went over there and talked to Haig, met briefly with the President, and was
                    re-launched to the Middle East to try to...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We turned that around.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: And that was the beginning of the major Lebanese war operation. All of
                    that, the Lebanese thing is all pretty well written. Maybe I'll write the
                    history of the period, I don't know. There's a lot of crap that has been
                    written.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:Do you by any chance know the one by Johnathan Randal?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Yes, he describes the political structure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I found it quite...this was very early.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: He was very anti—the Christian Militia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gotten about half way through it, I'm reading it right
                        now. It's good on the cultural, ethnic, and internal political faction of
                        Lebanon. I see some place later he gets around to talking about your...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Well, you see by the time he wrote that book I'd already had the first
                    operation.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right. It's not up-to-date.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: At any rate, I got re-launched. That was a period of very intensive
                    shuttle diplomacy to try to find a way to cool that thing down.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you stand it physically?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Well, you know, I took care of myself. The problem was I ate too much and
                    gained weight. When you're only doing one thing, you concentrate on that. I used
                    to get tired, sure, but I'd lie down. My real problem was eating too much,
                    that's what got me in the end, I'm sure. We went through very long periods of
                    frustration there. What we started to do in Lebanon was to do a number of
                    things. Number one, get the Lebanese sovereignty reestablished, so things would
                    be sovereign in their own country. Secondly, we wanted to get all the external
                    forces out. We wanted a (inaudible) in the Lebanese government. And we wanted to
                    get assurances that Lebanese character wouldn't be used for hostile action
                    against the others. We had arranged that meeting. There was practically no
                    evidence of any hostile action from Lebanese territory directly into Israel. The
                    Israelis won't admit that, but it's true. We kept track of those damn things.
                    Now, they had this plan, Sharon had this plan that had been made in Lebanon to
                    crush the Palestinian movement. That's what he told me when he told me about
                    this plan, and showed me what it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Instead of stopping.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0077" n="Page0077"/>
                <p>HABIB: I told him it was no god damned good, and I was right, but he didn't pay
                    any attention. The next day you know the war is on and everything that goes with
                    it. At that point we began to question, how do you stop the war? I had eleven
                    ceasefires, then the twelfth one. Sometimes a ceasefire would last for a day,
                    sometimes an hour, sometimes three days, it never would last. And it was not
                    always the Arab's fault. The Israelis had this strange notion that if you
                    declared a ceasefire, you could move your troops around. So they would accept
                    the ceasefire and then they would move their troops, and the other guys would
                    shoot at them and they'd say, they broke the ceasefire. I once said to the Prime
                    Minister, a friend of the Defense Minister and the Foreign Minister, that I was
                    going to have to get this new definition of a ceasefire written up in the annals
                    of the War College. But that's what happened. I was terribly busy running from
                    country to country. Trying to the Saudis and get the Syrians to do things,
                    talking to the Syrians directly to get them clued in, keeping the Israelis on
                    board, flying in and around and up and down. It wasn't too bad. Well, I then got
                    to talk ceasefire and it held long enough to...I got to a point where I was
                    really fed up with the senselessness that was going on. I had practically got an
                    agreement with the PLO and the Syrians to get their troops out of Beirut. I was
                    negotiating the details and what follows and all that, and still the Israelis
                    were hitting the cities. So I used to call them up on a secure line and said I
                    wanted to talk to the Secretary. When they got the Secretary on the phone, I
                    said, now this has got to stop. Its just can't go on this way. He said, what do
                    you recommend? I said, I recommend the President pick up the telephone and talk
                    to Mehachem Begin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which he did.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: That's what happened. That led to a disengagement of forces, and bringing
                    in the multi-national force and a ceasefire that held long enough to get an
                    election in Lebanon. Things seemed to be going in the right direction, and the
                    war started all over again. At that point, we were in negotiation involving
                    Israel, the Lebanese, a negotiation which...I opposed that negotiation. The
                    Israelis insisted they wanted a negotiation. So I'm not getting anywhere. I went
                    to the President and Secretary and said, my idea is that I should go over there
                    now with a solution and say, look fellows, tell me what you want and we'll put
                    it together. I talked to the Lebanese, they were alright, I had a pretty good
                    understanding with agreement to them. I go to Israel and I had the whole
                    cabinet, the senior members of the cabinet. I started talking about my ideas of
                    how to solve...and Sharif pulled out a piece of paper and he said, in effect
                    we're way ahead of you, we've got this working paper with the Lebanese, this is
                    the start of the settlement [talks] in Washington. I couldn't believe it, I
                    didn't know anything about it. I had not been in that part of the world in
                    several months. I was out in California. My deputy, Maury Draper was there and
                    nobody had told him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they had had secret meetings with the Gemayel
                        government.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0078" n="Page0078"/>
                <p>HABIB: That's right, with an intermediary, Gemayel who was an amateur, a
                    businessman, a friend of his. And when I went back to Gemayel, I said, what the
                    hell is this. You didn't tell me about it. Oh, it's nothing, it's just a
                    guideline for the negotiation. They didn't decide because they were supposed to
                    remain secret. Well, they were made public yesterday. I know, I know, it's
                    causing me a lot of trouble, my people want to know what the hell I'm doing,
                    what did I negotiate, who negotiated it. Well, at any rate, it was a bad turn of
                    events. So we began plodding back to the negotiations, and finally got them
                    through. By the time they were finished, they weren't worth the paper they were
                    written on because they obviously couldn't be implemented. I remember I used to
                    sometimes say to the Lebanese, you can't demand this. You can't demand [that]
                    because if you do the Syrians won't accept it. They wanted to get the maximum
                    benefits to justify the war. But by now the war had turned sour. Those attitudes
                    were very sour towards the war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the Syrians were very proud of their negative
                        reality.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: All of this took so much time, the Syrians get reinforced, and yet fooling
                    around with the travel groups, the animosities, the Israelis supported the
                    Christians, they supported that other group. The fighting began to stir up
                    again. After the agreement was signed I was going over to Syria to talk with
                    Assad, I got the word back that I wasn't welcome because I had misled him in the
                    early days on the ceasefire. I didn't mislead him. The Israelis would agree to
                    them and then they would break them. But he held that against me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That you had deceived him on the ceasefire.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: So I said to the President, well, if he doesn't want to see me... That's
                    when I resigned for the last time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you had gotten along pretty well with Assad, hadn't
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Oh yes, I had gotten along personally very well. I've been told on good
                    authority, by somebody who was present in a meeting with the Syrians that Assad
                    said he had made a big mistake in dumping me and declaring me unacceptable, that
                    I should have been kept on. So at least I knew then, and knew what the problem
                    was. Others were not so well prepared. But that doesn't prove anything. At that
                    point in life I decided for final retirement. I'm now on the board of various
                    organizations. I go to meetings. I teach. I'm doing a lot of speaking now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I hope you won't push yourself too much.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0079" n="Page0079"/>
                <p>HABIB: No, I try to pace it and take a few weeks off now and then. I take my time
                    when I can but sometimes you can't. You're never quite the same after these
                    seizures. So now I belong to all these various organizations, and I go to
                    meetings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many honorary degrees have you had?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Three honorary degrees so far, I'm getting another one. The University of
                    Idaho gave me a L.L.D. in 1974. Yale University gave me a L.L.D. in 1982, and
                    the University of South Carolina Medical School gave me a Doctor's of Humane
                    Letters. And I'm going up to a commencement...degree to get I don't know what
                    from Elmira College in New York where my daughter went to school, and I'm going
                    to speak at their commencement. All together I've had lots of awards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Medal of Freedom, all kinds of other ones. Well, they
                        can't make you Lord Habib, or Lord Habib of Belmont.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It's all right...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You'd never be a rich man, Phil.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It's easy to make money out there if you want to spend the time in the
                    business world. You know what the Foreign Service career is like. You go from
                    all responsibility, or no responsibility, but it's responsibilities. That's the
                    whole story of the Foreign Service. Why don't you go through this stuff and if
                    you have any questions, call me. I'm always at the end of the phone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't think I've really...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: There were a lot of interesting things that we did that we haven't even
                    talked about. Like the period in the 1960s when I was in Washington and we
                    politicized the American Foreign Service Association. I remember that period
                    particularly. I cooperated with that group. It was called the Young Turks when
                    we took over the association in a fair election. I was elected president of the
                    association in 1967.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right. I had forgotten that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: We tried to do all the work. There was Lannon Walker.</p>
                <pb facs="0080" n="Page0080"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well that wasn't the time that Hemenway took over. That
                        was the next go-around.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: He tried to abort the whole thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I quit the Foreign Service Association.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: The guys I was associated with were Ted Eliot, who's now Dean in Fletcher.
                    Dean Brown who is Middle East Institute, and myself, were the three running
                    officers. Below us there were a whole bunch of Class 5, Class 4, Class 6 and 7
                    officers like Lannon Walker was the spark plug. Frank Weir, and then there was
                    Charlie, the guy who is now ambassador to Ghana who was in USIS, he was
                    spokesman in the Department at one time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm thinking of Tom Smith...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I think it's Ghana, or was he in Senegal. He then went to USIA as deputy
                    director but he was in the State Department...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, Charlie Bray.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Charlie Bray, myself, and there was Frank Weir, Lannon Walker, and we
                    brought other guys in all the time.Anyway, it was a good group. The young guys
                    were the spark plugs, the old guys like myself helped them out. Of course, we
                    were cursed by some of the old timers. I think it was inevitable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I rejoined the AFSA after a couple years of dropping out
                        when Hemenway got out of the way. I think they've done a pretty good job,
                        and I think they lobby for us. At least they're associated with all the
                        federal employee lobbies. Not that one trade union, or association, can
                        change history.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: His idea is fair representation of the views of the membership, I think,
                    as a whole. This new generation in the Foreign Service is a lot different. There
                    were a lot more privileges, there were a lot more comforts, there were a lot
                    more assurances.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Each generation has taken over for a while.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0081" n="Page0081"/>
                <p>HABIB: Now the wives want to get paid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you've got all this dual employment business.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Larry Eagleburger's wife, Marlene but she's in favor of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Larry couldn't shut her up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I don't know whether he tried.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We began [a study] for the president years ago when you
                        had some of the wives of the younger officers who didn't want to be
                        bothered...into painting, or being presenfor the ambassador. They were into
                        this and that, and do their own thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: The real thing is the dual posting is another problem. The wife is in one
                    section, what happens when one gets promoted and the other one gets underneath
                    him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I think Personnel could probably avoid that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Yes, they probably could if they wanted to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Or in the case of a couple we know, she's in London and
                        he's in Paris. I think these are freak cases.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Bob went to Somalia and she stayed in Washington on the Afghan [desk],
                    she's a FSO.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you've got Carl Coon and Jane as ambassador...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: They're both on their way home. One of them is in [leave-without-pay
                    status], the other one gets paid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think it's a lot better Service than when we went in,
                        Phil, all in all.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Well, it's a more effective one now.</p>
                <pb facs="0082" n="Page0082"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The terms of service got better and better, basically the
                        quality of the young people taken in was as good if not better than the
                        pre-war service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Well, it's a different operation. Any other questions?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If you had it to do all over again, would you do it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Oh, of course. Why do you think I came back in '81 and '82 was because I
                    knew it might be risky to my health, but it was worth it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like an old fire horse.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: It was worth it to get back in the action again, the things that really
                    count. That's what we're supposed to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're all subject to principles of recall. But I can think
                        of few besides you who have ever been recalled except for ACDC or whatever
                        they call the classification-declassification.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: Yes that stuff is boring of course, but it has to be done, and gives
                    employment to some of our colleagues for a few thousand dollars anyway.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Most of them generally work a few months before they
                        exceed their...Well, being this book has brought me into the Department a
                        time or two every month for the last couple of years and that's been fun,
                        walk around the corridor every now and then, and stop and knock on a door
                        and stay in touch with the people there. I don't bother them very much, I
                        try not to bother them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: When I come to town I see very few people unless I'm asked to. Usually the
                    Secretary asks me to come down and see the NEA guys, and I go down and see
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I had a good talk with Roy Atherton two weeks ago.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HABIB: I used to stop and see Roy because of my interest in the appointments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Phil, I may think of some other things to ask you
                        about.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0083" n="Page0083"/>
                <p>HABIB: Give me a call.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
