<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000145">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with David S. Brown </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR DAVID S. BROWN</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Melbourne Spector </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: March 15, 1989</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Professor Brown has been a newspaper reporter, has served
                        in state and national government, and has been on the faculty of George
                        Washington University since 1954, where, among other positions, he has
                        chaired the Department of Public Administration. He is the author of several
                        books, numerous articles, and monographs. He's served on many commissions
                        and on international delegations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>My name is Melbourne Spector, and I am the Director of the Marshall Plan Oral
                    History Project. I had the pleasure of serving with Professor Brown in the
                    Marshall Plan, and I will take the advantage of our friendship by addressing him
                    informally, if I may, Dave, during our interview.</p>
                <p>Dave, let's go back a little bit. Tell me how you got involved with the Marshall
                    Plan. How did you ever come to be in that August organization?</p>
                <p>BROWN: I was on the Secretariat of the Air Coordinating Committee, which was a
                    committee made up of five or six government departments to deal with aviation. I
                    think it was Bud Rupard, who was in Don Sonn's office, who suggested that I talk
                    to Gordon Reckord. I did talk with Reckord, and as a result, I moved over there
                    a month or so later.</p>
                <p>I served from 1950 to 1953 in the Marshall Plan, and as a result of a project
                    undertaken by the Public Advisory Board, a study of national trade and air
                    policy—which, incidentally, was the first presidential-level study ever done of
                    this subject—I did not ingratiate myself with Governor Stassen. Along with 800
                    or 900 other people, I was dropped from the agency.</p>
                <p>I went from there to the staff of a commission that was set up as a result of our
                    study to encourage development of a national trade policy—tariffs, trade, and
                    other things. I was there until I came to George Washington University, as
                    you've indicated, in 1954. I've been with this university since 1954 to 1986,
                    when I retired, having reached retirement age.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>As a matter of fact, I had completed all my work for a doctoral degree, except
                    for the dissertation. The subject of my dissertation was “The Public Advisory
                    Board and the Federal Government,” with major emphasis on what happened at the
                    Marshall Plan. I was just looking at the table of contents of the dissertation,
                    which is a long one—500 pages—to see if there were any other chapters which
                    might apply, and there might be. I remembered those two in particular.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I understand that you'll make these chapters available to
                        be made a part of this study.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes, I'd be glad to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I think the two chapters, which you already have, are useful in the fact
                    that I did considerable exploring of the origins of the public advisory
                    group.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think it's very important.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes. One of the functions of the secretariat was that of serving as a
                    staff to advisory boards. I took that on when I joined the agency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fascinating! Do you feel that the advisory board of the
                        Marshall Plan made any new advances in the whole conduct of advisory boards
                        in the government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Only one, and that was one in which I was particularly closely associated
                    with. That was the study undertaken by President Truman to explore national
                    trade policy and tariff policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's amazing. In all this time, we've never had a
                        high-level study until the board took it on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: We never had a high-level study until 1952.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Amazing.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>BROWN: It's a study which we could not possibly complete by the time President
                    Eisenhower took office, and overtures were made to him to determine whether or
                    not he wanted us to conclude this study. Because Eisenhower was, in general,
                    afraid to lower tariffs, he indicated to us that he was interested in having us
                    complete the study.</p>
                <p>We completed the study and made it known to the press, I think in March 19__,
                    which turned out to be the day Stalin died. Even with that, the reports of the
                    study made the front pages of The New York Times and the Washington Post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The study did not continue at the very end under the aegis
                        of the foreign aid agency, is that right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes, it did continue under the aegis of the foreign aid agency, but the
                    director of the agency at the time, Averell Harriman, then later Harold Stassen,
                    were not members of the board. Harriman excused himself from it. In 1952, if you
                    remember, he was running for the Democratic nomination for President, and he
                    felt it would be improper to sit on the board. The board selected another
                    person, Daniel Bell, who was then the president and chairman of the board, I
                    think, of the American Security Bank here in Washington. He had been an Under
                    Secretary of the Treasury and also one of the first budget OMB directors in the
                    country, and was a thoroughly reputable person. He was selected by the board
                    unanimously to serve as its chairman for the purpose of making this study.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In reading one of the chapters of your dissertation, I was
                        interested when I read the little biographical statement on Bell, that he
                        started out as a stenographer in the government. It shows that you can begin
                        at the bottom and work your way up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: William A. Jump, whose name is known to many people for his work as
                    Director of Finance for the Department of Agriculture, started as an assistant
                    messenger. I think I was hired over there because one summer, I'd served in
                    Washington as a grade-one—in those days, it was CAF-1—as a messenger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And a delightful job to get when you were first coming out
                        of school.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I was pleased to get it, even though I had a ____ degree at the time. I
                    think that the reason he selected me was because both he and his assistant,
                    Harry Nelson, had been messengers along the way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, really?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>BROWN: Yes. I can't think of any other good reason.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You don't think there was any other, either your training
                        or so on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: It was a very humble job, and they felt, I think—neither one of them had a
                    college degree—that if someone with a college degree who had done a number of
                    things on campus, that is, with the yearbook, etc., was willing to take that
                    job, there must be something good in him. In any event, they hired me. For about
                    six months, my education was continued because Jump took me into his own office
                    and I had a desk beside his.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, how wonderful! That must have been terrific.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I made the acquaintance of a number of people—Paul Appleby, Milton
                    Eisenhower, and other persons who later went on to significant roles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go from that job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I went from that job directly into flying aircraft for the Navy. I was a
                    pilot of dive-bombers. I joined the fleet in the early spring of 1945, and
                    served in the Pacific. Before that, I had also been an instructor of
                    dive-bombing at the Naval Air Station in Miami.</p>
                <p>I brought along something for you that you can look at later, a couple of things
                    which I have written, which you may be interested in looking at.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would. Thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: They don't have very much to do with this project. One of them is the
                    things obituaries leave out, which is whimsical.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good. Thank you very much. Then you went from the
                        Navy into civilian life?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I went from the Navy into the Civil Aeronautics Administration. Then from
                    there I later went onto the Air Coordinating Committee. I was in personnel work
                    at the Civil Aeronautics Administration.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>I think that my struggle, as long as I served in the federal government, was to
                    be in a substantive area, and my years in staff functions were on the weight of
                    that. I never made substantive area until I joined the faculty of this
                    university.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You don't feel that being the secretary—if that was the
                        title—to the Public Advisory Board was a substantive position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Well, of course it had matters of substance in it, but really it was a
                    staff kind of position.</p>
                <p>One of the unfortunate things about the study of public administration, and
                    having served at this university for many years, is that its graduates are hired
                    primarily by persons who are in staff areas. That includes secretariats, budget
                    offices, management divisions, personnel, etc. I always wanted to serve in an
                    area that was concerned with some of the substantive things directly. Of course,
                    as your own career suggests, you have an impact in many kinds of ways, but this
                    was to come later in my case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's interesting. You feel that the graduates of the
                        public administration departments don't generally get into substance, as
                        such.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: It isn't a matter of feeling; it's a matter of knowing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's interesting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: A lot of people aren't disserved by that. The present faculty here is not
                    disserved by it. Ultimately I became a professor of management. I first was a
                    professor of political science and public administration. Then in the past 15
                    years, I've been a professor of management. You'll see in my writings I'm
                    identified as “professor of management.”</p>
                <p>My feeling is that people in public administration should focus more than they
                    have done in the past upon teaching people who are in economics or law or
                    forestry, whatever area they have chosen to take their initial degree in, should
                    help them with the business of managing within the federal system. The students
                    that I like to get best here are those who had experience and training in other
                    kinds of areas, so I can begin to talk about subjects such as managing and
                    subjects such as working for a public agency, both of which have peculiar
                    aspects that are different from what they would ordinarily get.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>I've continued to be a speaker at the Office of Personnel Management's executive
                    programs, and will be speaking this week. I'm delighted, because nobody in there
                    will be from the staff areas; they'll all be from substantive areas. They'll be
                    from Immigration and Naturalization, from the Defense Department, from Housing,
                    from the Washington Police Department, etc. I can talk with them about getting
                    their job done and the kind of management situation that they find while they're
                    working for the public service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's very interesting, Dave.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: That's what I've tried to do here, I might add without some of the
                    successes that I had hoped to have.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One never does, probably.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Well, I suppose that's true.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To get back to the Public Advisory Board of the Marshall
                        Plan, do you feel that as a board for the Plan, for ECA and MSA, that it
                        served its purpose, that it got things done? What would you say were the
                        main purposes of the Board?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I would say that the main purpose of the Board, number one, was to assure
                    the Republicans in the 80th Congress that somebody outside of the Truman
                    Administration would be having a hand in the running of the agency. I think
                    that's what happened, and I think that because the members of the Board were, on
                    the whole, good men and one woman, that they did that.</p>
                <p>Secondly, they would have been willing to do more if they could have done
                    more.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you mean by that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: The directors of the agency, chiefly presidents like Hoffman, had no faith
                    whatsoever in advisory boards. It was all a pretense, as far as he was
                    concerned. Hoffman was a person who was very charismatic, and he could be
                    talking with me in a briefing before the Board, and say, “Well, you know, I
                    don't see any particular purpose in doing all this,” etc. “When I was at
                    Studebaker, we ran the agency with the help of an attorney, a comptroller, and
                    one of the engineering people, and that's all I really need.” He would say this.
                    Then he would go into the board room and captivate all of the members of the
                    Board.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>That wasn't true of all of the people. It certainly wasn't true of one of his
                    deputies, Richard Bissell. If you've been following any of the kinds of things
                    on television and in the literature that have happened to Bissell since that
                    time, you can understand why most of them didn't work out. Bissell would come in
                    to the Board, and as the Board said to me, “He uses us like a bunch of school
                    children. He wants to tell us how much he knows and how bright he is.”</p>
                <p>So as a result of that, we would not put Bissell on at each session of the Board;
                    we would put him on perhaps one in four, because the members of the Board didn't
                    care for him. They did care for Hoffman.</p>
                <p>I'd like to say, additionally, that when Harriman took over as director of the
                    agency, we found this person who had a great deal of difficulty communicating
                    with his fellow man, to be a man who did believe that the Board was a good thing
                    to have. He would talk to the members of the Board in a slow, labored kind of
                    way. They had an opportunity to make comments to him. Many times I've talked
                    with George Elsey, who had been a Truman assistant. He was the assistant to
                    Harriman when Harriman became administrator of Mutual Security. He said, “Mr.
                    Harriman would like such and such done.” For the most part, what I remember
                    about Harriman is he said, “Do what you think you need to do with the Board. Of
                    course I want to know about it, but the only advice I give you is don't get me
                    in any trouble as a result of what the Board does.” Of course, we didn't.</p>
                <p>Harriman, peculiarly enough for a person of his background and nature, did
                    believe in listening. He would listen to the members of the Board. He would
                    often say, “What do you think of that? Do you think we're going in the right
                    direction?” The Board ordinarily said, “Yes,” or made some suggestion to him
                    that they'd like to have him do more of this and this and that or something of
                    the sort. Harriman did listen. I never was sure whether he heard or not, because
                    his service at that time was in a period when we thought he needed a hearing
                    aid, but he hadn't decided that he needed one yet. He later adopted one.</p>
                <p>As a matter of fact, the decision that was made with agreement by Harriman for
                    the Board to undertake a study was as a result of his efforts to involve the
                    Board more fully, and was also the result—perhaps some of the members of the
                    Board had communicated it to him—that they felt that all they were really doing
                    was putting on a pretense of giving him advice. So we discussed with Harriman
                    the possibility of the Board undertaking a study, possibly a presidential-level
                    study.</p>
                <p>I talked with as many people as I could talk with about some subject that we
                    would like to have studied, and some subject in which we thought the Board would
                    come out with some findings that the administration could live with. A number of
                    things were suggested. Willard Thorp, who was then Assistant Secretary of State
                    for Economic Affairs, said, “You know, it would be helpful if we undertook a
                    study in which we put everything together and looked at everything, trade and
                    tariff policy in this country.”</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>When I had concluded my visits to quite a number of other people concerning what
                    the Board might do, it seemed to me that this was the most reasonable one and
                    the most useful one, because certainly it wouldn't interfere with anything that
                    the agency had done. It ought to be helpful to Mutual Security, etc. And I
                    recommended that this is what we undertake. It so happened that this
                    recommendation was followed.</p>
                <p>Then I had the job of trying to find a chairman of the Board, somebody who could
                    provide leadership to the Board in this area, but was not so fully committed
                    that the leadership would be later said to be all in one direction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the chairman of the Board supposed to be the head of
                        the agency?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: The chairman of the Board, according to the statute, is the head of the
                    agency. The head of the agency was asked to consult with these 12 other members
                    of the Board.</p>
                <p>Hoffman frequently said that this was a waste of a day or a day and a half's
                    time. And the members of the Board said, “We think that the chief contribution
                    we have made is that of taking up a day and a half of your time.” Hoffman always
                    denied this. He said, “No, I want to meet with you,” and so on.</p>
                <p>I might add, parenthetically, that Hoffman began his career in the automobile
                    business as a car salesman. When he learned that the Secretary of Commerce at
                    the time under Truman, whose name I don't recall, didn't own an automobile,
                    Hoffman undertook the business of selling him an automobile. As a result of
                    this, he did sell him a Studebaker. He called on his wife, he sent flowers to
                    her, he did all of the kind of things that a first-rate salesman does. Life
                    magazine and some other magazines made quite a splash of Hoffman really
                    fulfilling the role of Secretary of Commerce and that of doing some things that
                    were helpful to American business.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But in this instance, you were able to have Bell appointed
                        as the chairman of the Board for the purpose of this study?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes. As a matter of fact, a number of names were suggested. I did a
                    recruiting job to try to find somebody who was acceptable to all of the members
                    of the board. Dan Bell, after his governmental service, moved over to American
                    Security Bank. As a person, he was a very conservative person. He would never
                    throw a paper clip away. He would never do anything of this sort. It wasn't easy
                    getting him accepted, but ultimately we got him accepted by a 12-to-0 vote.
                    There were two or three members of the Board who had doubts concerning him. One
                    member was opposed to him. That was resolved by my getting the 11 other members
                    to favor Bell, and he went along.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So the twelfth went along.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: The twelfth went along because he didn't want to make it 11 to one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't think at this date it would matter to know who the
                        twelfth one was.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: The twelfth member of the Board was Alan Kline of the Farm Bureau. Because
                    Jim Patton was also on the Board and Patton was a liberal and the head of the
                    most competitive farm organization to the Farm Bureau, the Farmers' Union, Kline
                    had a tendency not to favor anything that Patton favored.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So with Patton and Kline, you had agriculture represented
                        on the Board.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: We had a third agriculture representative, the National Grange.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the other parts of American life that were
                        represented?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: The labor unions had three representatives, including George Meany, who
                    was then Secretary-Treasurer of the American Federation of Labor. We also had
                    three representatives from business. We had Eric Johnston, who was then the
                    president of the Chamber of Commerce and also the movie czar. We also had a very
                    important man, George Meade, who was head of the Meade Paper Company, a large
                    concern, a strong Republican. But Meade was one of the more creative and more
                    thoughtful people on the Board, and if something made sense to Meade, he favored
                    it. He would always listen to what somebody else had to say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you had industry, labor, agriculture.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes. Three members of industry. The third, I suppose, was Orin Lehman. He
                    was hardly a businessman, although he had to fit in that category.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In reading part of your dissertation, I noticed that the
                        industry business seemed to attend meetings more consistently than either of
                        the other areas. I don't know whether that's true or not. Is that how I read
                        the statistics?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>BROWN: It depended, in part, on how convenient it was. For example, Eric Johnston
                    attended a lot of meetings. George Meade attended a lot. George Meade was in his
                    seventies at the time, and one surmises that he was not the CEO of the company
                    any longer, although he probably was the most influential. Patton attended. His
                    headquarters were in Denver, but the farmers' union was always somewhat strapped
                    for money, and the aid agency paid his way to Washington for attending the
                    meetings. I presume he was attentive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think it would be interesting for the historical buffs
                        to know what was the honorarium that you paid these people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Fifty dollars a day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And how much per diem, in lieu of subsistence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I don't remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I can tell you. Ten dollars, according to your study. Ten
                        dollars! Unbelievable. (Laughs)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I'd forgotten.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So under the aegis of Daniel Bell, you went into this
                        foreign trade study.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes. Bell had been chairman of the board of the American Security Bank and
                    served the President by looking into problems in the Philippines. These were
                    economic problems. In doing so, he had worked with the man who was formally on
                    the ECA staff. His name was Vincent Checchi. Also he had worked with a person
                    who was head of research of the International Monetary Fund, Eddie Bernstein,
                    Dr. Edward Bernstein. Bernstein became the chief economist or executive
                    director—I guess he was the executive director, but he was the chief economist,
                    and was responsible for the study, by and large.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get him on loan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: He was on loan from the Monetary Fund. As I look back, there wasn't much
                    activity at the time at the Monetary Fund. This was a period before we had
                    decided to finance everything in South America that needed financing. I felt
                    that Bernstein welcomed the change for a while. He came here, he brought his
                    secretary with him, both courtesy of the Monetary Fund, and undertook the
                    study.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say Checchi was on it, too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: No, Checchi was not on it. Checchi was a great admirer of Bell, and he
                    provided me with some useful information about Bell's capabilities and about
                    what he could be expected to do. But Checchi was not involved in the study at
                    all. I later became very friendly with Checchi. I became very friendly with
                    Bernstein, and even though he was one of these whiz-bang economists that one
                    often talks about, and I was not an economist, merely a young fellow trying to
                    make a living, Eddie and I became good friends. The friendship still
                    remains.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: He's retired, also. He's probably eight or ten years older than I am. Last
                    I heard, he was doing some consulting in Washington and discovering that there
                    was money to be made at it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Someone like him should do very well. Was this study
                        approved by all of the Board?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: It was approved by all of the Board. There were no elements of it that
                    were not approved. The Board made a single report. All of the board members had
                    influence in it. It was a good report. For the first time, the Board followed a
                    pattern of indicating that we needed a trade and tariff policy that was
                    concerned with national problems and not merely individual and local ones.</p>
                <p>Previously, our trade and tariff policy had been made in bits and pieces. One of
                    the elements of it was the Smoot-Hawley Tariff. If anybody went into the
                    Smoot-Hawley Tariff hearings with the desire to have the tariff raised on any
                    given subject which they might manufacture, which persons from other countries,
                    Portugal, Spain, or Italy, and so on, were providing competition for, Hamilton
                    Fish, who was important in that on the House side, would give them what they
                    wanted.</p>
                <p>I once heard Hamilton Fish make a speech, in which he had indicated that he would
                    like to have a higher tariff on poultry than existed. Smoot asked him to write a
                    letter to that effect to the committee. So he did write the letter, saying, “I
                    would appreciate it very much if you would put a higher tariff on poultry.” And
                    he signed it “Ham Fish.” According to his version, they put a higher tariff on
                    poultry and ham and fish. This is an anecdote which I heard him make in a
                    speech, which I've always remembered.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any major recommendations from the report that
                        had taken place? For instance, did the report recommend, as we have today, a
                        special person for trade? We now have a special trade representative.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: No, it did not make that recommendation. Its primary purpose was saying
                    that we ought to have a trade and tariff policy that reflects, as best as we can
                    identify it, national, rather than local, interests.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which is good enough.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Which is a tremendous idea, if you stop and think of it. Shortly after
                    that, Governor Stassen, who felt that this was always an undertaking aimed at
                    making life difficult for him and the administration, persuaded the
                    administration to undertake another presidential-level study, which was done.
                    This new study—for a moment I forget the name of it—had members of Congress on
                    it. There were several minority reports filed, and they never got it all
                    together. As a result of this, the recommendations that we made were undercut.
                    Eisenhower went on with what amounted to, in effect, a Republican counterstudy
                    to the one that we'd undertaken. But it came down in several pieces, not all in
                    one piece, and this handicapped the trade-lowering business for some time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Please refresh my understanding. Why was Stassen and, I
                        suppose, the Republican administration, against it? These days, in 1989, the
                        Republicans are noted for wanting a free-trade policy. So back then you had,
                        I guess, the Republicans not quite in favor of a free-trade policy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Republicans historically in this country have always been a high-tariff
                    party. While Stassen was probably more reasonable in that respect than some of
                    the others, he was really running for President himself. If you will note the
                    fact that he's run for President six or seven times at least, this was, I
                    suspect, all part of his efforts. At least he indicated to me his feelings which
                    were somewhat along this line. He felt that this was an effort to make life
                    difficult for him.</p>
                <p>I talked with him shortly before I was removed as secretary of the Board. I said
                    to him, in effect, “I've always been civil service.” He said, “Yes, but the
                    dossier that I have on you indicates that you've been particularly close to a
                    number of the Democrats.” I said, “Yes, Governor, that's all that there was on
                    the administrative side for a number of years.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For quite a few years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: It seemed to me that he did it out of affection, rather than duty.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Stassen was a very, very interesting person, I must say,
                        having worked with him myself. Is there anything else that you'd like to say
                        about the Board, any summation? What do you feel about boards in general,
                        that kind of board, as a device?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I've written a number of articles on it. Recently a member of the faculty
                    of the Hebrew University of Jerusalem came here to deliver a paper at the
                    Woodrow Wilson Foundation, and he sought me out because he'd read some of the
                    things that I had written before. I come down strongly in favor of boards. I
                    think they are a device by which one can find out how some of the clients are
                    feeling, and I think it's a good thing to have this as a device.</p>
                <p>Most of the boards in this town are put to special uses. Administrators like to
                    have them when they feel that the Board will support them in some of the
                    problems they have, particularly with respect to Congress. I might add that a
                    couple of times Hoffman did this by saying, “I think it would be useful if some
                    of you people got in touch with your congressmen. Here are the telephone
                    numbers. You can call him now.” The Public Advisory Group suspended while people
                    went out and went to telephones to tell members of Congress how they felt about
                    certain pieces of legislation which they agreed with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So he used it as kind of a congressional relations
                        device.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes. I feel that administrators use them for those purposes. I also feel,
                    as in the case of the Institutes of Public Health, they use them when the
                    administrators don't want to make a decision themselves. They put the matter up
                    to the board. Boards have been used in the national institutes to grant people
                    monies for research, etc.</p>
                <p>If you are a member of a board at that time, and your university is putting in a
                    claim for more money, you'll leave the room for that particular incident, and
                    the board goes on without you. I think this is very bad, because it's merely
                    another way of getting around what was initially intended. That sort of thing
                    did not happen with the Marshall Plan</p>
                <p>This idea of the Marshall Plan was so unique and unusual, and I'd like to use the
                    word “good,” that the members of the Board accepted it as such and were willing
                    to do what they could do, with a couple of exceptions, to support it. Exceptions
                    did not include most of the organizations represented. It did include, among
                    other things, labor, where they felt that they were wasting their time by
                    attending and didn't care to come in and be counted as members when they were
                    really having very little to do with what was decided. One can look up in the
                    chapters I've written the attendance records of the members of the Board, and
                    this sort of speaks for itself.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>I am very much in favor of the boards in the private sector, as well as the
                    public sector. However, experience with boards of directors of companies
                    indicate that in almost all respects, they're beholden to management itself, and
                    they will do what the president of the company wants them to do. The only thing
                    that they really do, by and large, is to find a replacement for the president
                    when his term is over or, for one reason or another, he has to be replaced. I
                    think that there are lots of little boards around the federal government which
                    do a very great deal to bring information to the attention of administrators,
                    who tend to isolate themselves within the federal government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would you say is the difference between a commission
                        and a board?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: We usually use the word “commission” to indicate either the old Civil
                    Service Commission or the terrace commission, which was a way that Congress
                    found of getting some of the things that it badly wanted put into practice.
                    That's one of the meanings of the word.</p>
                <p>Another meaning of the word “commission” is that it's an alternative to
                    “committee.” I tend to find them used interchangeably and are generally used
                    with respect to presidential commissions. For example, President Reagan
                    appointed a commission to see what could be . . .</p>
                <p>[End Tape I, Side 1. Begin Tape I, Side 2]</p>
                <p>BROWN: Its assignment is that of making a finding, and that's what we try to do.
                    We had no power whatsoever, except through the power of ideas. We attempted to
                    put forward this idea that the tariff and trade policy should be done according
                    to what we can best determine to be the national interest, rather than the
                    interests of somebody in West Virginia or Tennessee or someone there.</p>
                <p>I think that the presidential commission here is something of a replica of the
                    Royal Commission in Britain, although the Royal Commission has higher standing.
                    It's a term which can be used as anybody would like to use it for committee or
                    special board or something of that sort. Generally speaking, it has no power
                    except to make a report, to undertake the study of a particular matter, and make
                    a report.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's true.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>BROWN: I have tried to say in some of the writings, most of which have been
                    rejected by publishers who felt that I was not aiming at the right thing, that
                    there are uses that can be made of committees if you will try to find out how
                    the members of the committee read the tea leaves in either the industry that
                    they're representing, the general public, or something of that sort. I've
                    testified twice before Congress as an expert in advisory committees, and I've
                    had some material of mine published, but I've gone on to other things. Nobody
                    was buying that. I'm going to give it another shot at the nation's business.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Frankly, the whole business of commissions, committees,
                        and boards, I think an appropriate time has come for the general use of
                        those. You have recently the pay commission, I believe it was called, that
                        did very badly its job. Just a few years ago, you had another commission.
                        You had this other commission recently on the national debt. That hasn't
                        done well.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you've had one on ethics. Two or three years ago, we
                        had one that did very well on the Social Security matter. So it would be
                        interesting to find why did one of them work and why didn't the others
                        work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Often one of the reasons that they don't work is because they are not
                    given an assignment where the objectives are specified clearly enough, or
                    they're given an assignment, as in the case of the recent pay one, where they
                    make a recommendation that has power behind it. Power always encourages
                    anti-power. So the best commissions come in and, with a straight face, try to
                    make the results of looking at a particular problem known to the general public.
                    If the general public cares enough about it to read it and will think about it,
                    then all of this is good. If they don't, then it's a waste of time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you say that a commission on which the members have
                        some authority—for instance, I'm thinking of the two Hoover Commissions, at
                        least the first one was a very successful commission.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One reason I think it was successful—and I'd like your
                        views on this—is because it had members of Congress on it, as well as public
                        and, I think, the Executive Branch. What came out of the commission's
                        recommendations would take ultimately a congressional legislation of some
                        kind.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>BROWN: Well, I'm going to disagree with you there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I think the commissions that have the most difficulty are often those with
                    members of Congress on them, because they're wearing two hats. They're wearing
                    the hat of members of the commission, and they also are wearing the hat of
                    members of Congress representing constituents. There's often substantial
                    conflict between the two.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's interesting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I've written on the subject of the kind of people who ought to be
                    commission members. I've found that the people who were on the Public Advisory
                    Board were, on the whole, very decent people. They were people who understood
                    their assignment and tried to contribute to it. I think that these represent the
                    kind of ones that we ought to have. They paid attention, some of them read all
                    of the material we sent them. We heard what they had to say.</p>
                <p>Interestingly enough, if I had stayed on with the Public Advisory Board, I had
                    another project in mind that Sara Blanding, who was then resident of Vassar,
                    agreed to take. That was a study to indicate what some of our foreign policy
                    assignments would be, and the kind of knowledge that students who would
                    ultimately be asked to fulfill these jobs ought to have. How much should the
                    universities be encouraged to go into the teaching of the knowledge of Russian
                    history, for example? Or pick any other country that you want to. The State
                    Department has to take a look at the kind of people that it has on the payroll
                    and whether or not any of them can speak Russian. Rarely is somebody able to
                    speak Russian or Albanian or God knows what.</p>
                <p>My feeling was that if we could make available through studies to university
                    systems—and this is well before I came here—what would likely be required of
                    people getting into the Foreign Service or related services such as we
                    represented over at the Marshall Plan, this would be enormously useful.</p>
                <p>Miss Blanding bought the idea immediately. The field that Sara Blanding was from,
                    I forget. I have a feeling that her doctorate was in physical education or
                    something like that, totally unrelated to what we were talking about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But as president of Vassar.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>BROWN: She had been made president of Vassar because, presumably, she could
                    administer the affairs of the university. She was a very decent person. I
                    sounded her out on this, and she welcomed this as an idea. Governor Stassen took
                    care of my future insofar as he could before any of this had a chance to break.
                    As a matter of fact, he fired Miss Blanding, along with me and all the other
                    members. (Laughs) But that's more or less the effect. This is what happens when
                    you get close to the top.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then the Advisory Board could really be used in almost
                        anything that was related to the functions, including making various kinds
                        of studies. The kind of thing that maybe a policy planning staff might be
                        doing at the State Department could be done by the Board.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I have come to the conclusion, primarily after I've been here at this
                    university, trying to understand business and governmental organization, that
                    one of the things that a lot of administrators are most concerned with is who
                    might be a menace to their authority. It's an interesting thing. We have the
                    idea that there ought to be a chain of command, kind of a pyramidal effect, at
                    the top. All you have to do is know something about American history. All you
                    have to do is read the Constitution, to realize that the system of government we
                    have depends on the cooperation of a lot of people. The sum total of what I've
                    learned over 50 years is that what we need to go toward, what we need to be
                    driven by, is the need for establishing systems where people cooperate with each
                    other voluntarily, because they believe it's the right thing to do, and they
                    believe there is not really any good alternative.</p>
                <p>If we don't cooperate, we have the US Government producing 8,000 atomic warheads
                    and the Russian Government producing 5,000, which probably 20 will serve the
                    same purpose, not 20,000.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Twenty.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Twenty will serve the same purpose.</p>
                <p>I would like to make an example of it. For example, President Bush's cooperation
                    with the Congress is essential. I call this building a pyramid. I'm going to get
                    into something that I've written, a new piece which is already at the
                    publisher's. Actually, the pattern that you and I lived under has been the
                    pattern of the pyramid, the pattern of “I'm in charge of this,” the pattern of
                    the father who wants to make all the decisions in the family, or the mother,
                    because the mother is peculiarly equipped to make the decisions and they have
                    some means of enforcing them, which every man in his maturity knows something
                    about and can speak to.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>What I feel is the pattern that we need to be looking to, how things are done,
                    are universities, hospitals, symphony orchestras, voluntary community
                    organizations, the military in combat, and I could give you other illustrations.
                    People today say, “You want us to run a business the way you run a university?”
                    We say, “Yeah, why don't you try it?” Some of them already have and are doing
                    well with it. “You want us to run a hospital the way hospitals are currently
                    run?” “Yes! Yes, I do.”</p>
                <p>In the past three years, I spent six weeks, at least, in hospitals, with nothing
                    to do except turn the TV on to the lousy programs that come on in the middle of
                    the day, or to think about what I can observe from my bed. When you need a
                    doctor, they can't possibly find one. They might find you a two-year medical
                    student who's called “doctor” but isn't.</p>
                <p>So if there's something the matter with you and you have an emergency which isn't
                    a life-threatening emergency, but one that threatens your comfort, you need a
                    catheter put in or taken out, or you need, as I did, an attack of gout to be
                    treated because it was so goddamn sore, my foot was so sore that I couldn't even
                    keep a sheet on it, what do you do? Well, I tell you. You talk with a nurse. I
                    say, “Now, I know you're not a doctor. I know you can't prescribe medicine, but
                    I know you know what the doctors prescribe. Don't you have some way of getting
                    it?”</p>
                <p>She goes out and reads her job classification, and she said, “Well, you know I
                    can't provide you with this.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, why don't you tell one of these second-year medical students who
                    goes by the name of “doctor” what is usually needed and let him get it for me.
                    Let him sign the RX.” I find that this cooperative system, the nurses cooperate
                    with doctors.</p>
                <p>By the way, I talked this over with a number of doctors. I am also prepared to
                    tell you that Peter Drucker has published the same idea after I had initially
                    sent my stuff to the publishers, using hospitals as an example. He used
                    hospitals as an example, but he didn't copy from me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You both came to the same conclusion.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: We both came to the same conclusion at roughly the same time. His was
                    written, I know, at least three months in advance of publication, as was
                    mine.</p>
                <p>I learned this from military. I learned this from hard-nosed colonels who had
                    been in Vietnam. The military knows that the only thing that can possibly save
                    them from the enemy shooting at them is what their men are able to do. So
                    whatever the general has said, other than people like Oliver North, is not
                    nearly as important as what the situation demands and what the troops will be
                    able to do.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>At universities, we identify who is president. But when you need to know
                    anything, you don't come ask a president, because what he would have to do in
                    most instance is ask one of the faculty members most concerned.</p>
                <p>I asked a new young professor what to do, and he said, “We do this.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Why do you do this?”</p>
                <p>He said, “The dean asked us to do it.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Why don't you go ask the dean what he deserves to be told?” Because
                    you're recording this, I'm not going to tell you what I said to him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the precise language.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: In the precise language. Also, voluntary organizations. If you're trying
                    to raise money for such and such a thing, you only ask people to do what they
                    will do. However you ask them, this usually includes, “What do you think about
                    this, Mel? Is this something that you're willing to undertake?” And you tell
                    them whether you're willing to undertake it or not.</p>
                <p>I think it's proper, as perhaps you do, too, for your assistant to go over to the
                    Civil Service Commission. I don't think it's necessarily wise, but I think it's
                    proper to go over there when you and he disagree, and I'm glad you're able to
                    show him that the Commission supported your point of view. I think if he'd had
                    any sense, he would have tried to work it out in the agency and he might have
                    gotten more from it from you if he had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's turn that one around a little bit, in all honesty.
                        What we're talking about, by the way, was on the secretariat, I was the
                        Deputy Director of Personnel, and the Chief of the Central Secretariat of
                        the Marshall Plan had proposed raising some grades. The Chief of
                        Classification, who served under me, lowered them, saying that they weren't
                        worth that, that they were only comparable to what they call mail and file
                        clerks.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I disagreed with him. I agreed with the Chief of the Secretariat, and so I
                    exercised my authority, which is very seldom done in Washington, by the way, and
                    I classified them myself. In effect, I took the authority away from the Chief of
                    Classification for that instance, because I delegated it to him to begin with.
                    Then he protested this to the Civil Service Commission. I went to the Commission
                    representatives, they agreed with me, and the classification was allowed to
                    stand.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>But to go back to the point that you just made, Dave, maybe it was incumbent on
                    me, as I look back all these many years, to have worked it out with the Chief of
                    Classification so it never would have had to go to the Civil Service.</p>
                <p>BROWN: Perhaps so. My feeling is that what we need to achieve is cooperativeness,
                    and that's what I'm indicating. I think there were many things the Public
                    Advisory Board could have been asked to do, which it did in a lesser respect,
                    than were asked. While I come down strongly on the side of the decency of Paul
                    Hoffman as administrator, and I have considerable admiration for him, I do know
                    his opinion of the board, and I do know that he was unwilling to really work
                    with them on the terms that they had to be worked with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It would be interesting to study Mr. Hoffman's career, as
                        to what his relationship was to the Board of Directors of the Studebaker
                        Corporation, later what his relationship was to the Board at the Ford
                        Foundation, where he later went, how he treated them as distinctly from the
                        Public Advisory Board.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: I know you had a large number of contacts with him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I didn't.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Well, he was delightful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I personally never did.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: He was delightful. I remember one time after he had left as administrator,
                    that I talked with him on the telephone. The phone rang, he had some questions,
                    and I identified myself. We talked for ten or fifteen minutes on the phone, and
                    he was delightful. He was personal in the sense that he asked how things were
                    going, asked about family, etc. In a sense, I valued him and Tyler Wood
                    greatly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: An excellent man.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Tyler wanted to take me to Korea with him, and I told him that in view of
                    the circumstances, it could not be approved, and I would willingly go with him
                    if it could be approved, but I knew it couldn't be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this under Stassen by then?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>BROWN: Under Stassen. If you remember, he was made mission chief in Seoul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd forgotten that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: He asked me to go with him. Later, when I was on assignment in Pakistan
                    for an aid contract with the University of Southern California, he was the
                    number-two man in the embassy in India. The number-one man was Galbraith. So I
                    got to talk to him then about Pakistan and India. I had a very warm feeling
                    towards him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm very intrigued by, and I support your idea of
                        cooperativeness, rather than this direction.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Sometimes you have to direct.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sometimes. Back again to Hoffman. Aside from the Advisory
                        Board, how did he deal with the Marshall Plan in terms of getting ideas and
                        using them? Or was he always trying to be a dictator?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: No, he was never a dictator. You must remember that when Hoffman came to
                    Washington, he didn't know much more about affairs of government than any other
                    businessman of his stature might have known. So in large part, this was the
                    business of trying to break him into the governmental system. You know the
                    problems that you all had with breaking Mullen in. Mullen, Director of Public
                    Relations, had some useful ideas, important ideas. Later we learned that the CIA
                    siphoned all sorts of money through his company to take on certain tasks. At
                    least that's what was in the paper.</p>
                <p>Hoffman was terrific. We did a number of things. Sometimes both of us, sometimes
                    one of us took notes of what went on in the morning staff meetings early in the
                    week. Let's say that the agency went to work at 8:30 in the morning. The staff
                    meeting was usually called at about 8:00, and it would go on for half an hour. I
                    well remember Don Stone coming in late at one meeting, and how apologetic he
                    was, because almost everybody else was there. It was like a kid coming in late
                    to school. I'd always had a very high regard for Don and still do. He invited me
                    to consider joining him at Pittsburgh on the faculty, and I was delighted. He's
                    done a number of things since he's left Pittsburgh full-time as dean. I greatly
                    appreciated his offer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If I may interject a moment, I think that Stassen
                        inadvertently did the country and other professions a lot of good by some of
                        the terminations that he effected. Don Stone is one of the best examples of
                        that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>BROWN: I have no problem with that. Our relationships professionally were nil
                    when I was in the agency. I have known him since, I've known of his efforts to
                    encourage public administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To bring this to a close, what are your views on the
                        secretariat? Did Hoffman and others use the secretariat? Did they see it as
                        a useful device?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: What I was about to tell you is the fact that Hoffman learned that
                    something was taking place, someone was reporting, he would then say, “Can you
                    take care of this?” And the person would reach in his pocket and take out an
                    envelope, which was probably a laundry list, and then make some notes on it.
                    Gordon Reckord said, “What we need to do is send this person a note saying what
                    the administrators ask him to do, and not depend on his writing on the back of
                    an envelope.” I remember Tyler Wood reaching in his pocket, taking out these
                    things, and writing on the back of this envelope to do something.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was probably also on that envelope a little figure
                        or a doodler. He was a great doodler.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Yes, he doodled in—how can I say it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very intricate forms, as I recall.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Intricate forms. That's a good term.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When the director or the administrator would say to one of
                        his people, “I want you to do this,” Gordon Reckord or yourself would then
                        prepare a memo for Hoffman's signature?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: No, we'd just send a note on our own signature to say, “The administrators
                    ask you to do such and such. Are we correct in this assumption? When can we
                    expect an answer?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a tickler file to follow up?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't gig them in any way?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>BROWN: No. They were important people. What we might do is put it on the next
                    week's agenda.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And have the administrator say, “By the way, Ty, how is
                        this coming along?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Sure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: This is one of the things that were done. Gordon is a peculiar person, and
                    he's peculiar in the sense that he was very bright, but he also wanted to be in
                    the position of “making policy” and giving other people a chance to carry out
                    the details. He had some useful ideas, but he always was trying to achieve a
                    level which I felt he had no chance to achieve whatsoever. His knowledge of the
                    agency, his knowledge of economics, his knowledge of geography—he was a
                    geographer—was always considerably greater than mine.</p>
                <p>Joe Turner, in addition to being bright, could remember all sorts of things of
                    this nature, Mel. I suspect that this ingratiated him to Stassen. I couldn't
                    remember them. You remember Ellis May?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BROWN: Ellis would immerse herself in policy in the agency, and I had a hell of a
                    time understanding this. I'm not an economist by nature, I'm kind of a
                    behaviorialist, I notice what people do and make a mental note of the fact that
                    they're likely to do it again. I make judgments concerning situations. As a
                    matter of fact, coming over here today, I got to thinking about the agency. When
                    I thought of Stone, there also popped into my memory the name of Alden Boyd.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
