<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001439">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Cecil S. Richardson</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2007</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>CECIL S. RICHARDSON</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: August 5, 2003</p>
                <p>Copyright 2004 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is being done on behalf of the Association for
                        Diplomatic Studies and Training and I'm Charles Stuart Kennedy. To begin
                        with, do you go by Cecil?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Cy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cy. Okay. Let's start at the beginning. When and where
                        were you born?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: New York City: 1926.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you tell me a bit about first your father and his
                        side of the family and where the Richardson's come from and then your
                        mother's side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, let's see. My father was born on the Dutch side of the Island
                    of St. Martin. And my mother, an English woman, was born in Antigua.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, in the Caribbean in other words.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's talk about the Richardson's. How did they get
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: To the Dutch side ... they were transported on a slave ship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how long were they there? I mean do you have any
                        idea of the history?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No. Probably in the eighteenth century ... the first one. Of course
                    they weren't named Richardson then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was your father doing, you know as a young
                        man?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, he was working in a store in St. Kitts. Many of his friends
                    were moving to the United States. He followed them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your mother, what's her background?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Her father was an Anglican minister. He came from England to serve in
                    the West Indies. Her mother was from a family of plantation owners or
                    managers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So this is all in Antigua?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No. I do not know where they married. My maternal grandfather had a
                    number of parishes around the Caribbean, one of them being in St. Croix,
                    American Virgin Islands, which as a result my uncle, my mother's brother, was
                    born an American citizen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your grandfather.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Early in the century, my maternal grandfather was reassigned to a
                    church somewhere in the southwest of England. World War I started in '14 and he
                    shipped the family back to the West Indies. He spent 4 years of the War in the
                    trenches in France. For some reason, he either did not send for the family or my
                    maternal grandmother chose not to rejoin him, and they remained separated. In
                    the early ?20s my maternal grandmother came to the States. A sister of hers had
                    moved to the U.S. somewhat earlier. The following year, 1922, my mother and her
                    brother followed her, but within nine months, my maternal grandmother died, and
                    they were orphaned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where had they gone in the States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: They went to Harlem where the family had friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about your father, had he gone to Harlem too?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, that's where they met. They left the island of St. Kitts
                    independently. They didn't know each other there. They were from different
                    social classes. But they both ended up around 135th Street in Harlem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I imagine, though, they probably, the way these things
                        usually operate, they probably were essentially in colonies of, New York is
                        full of clusters of people from different places that are very close.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: That's true. I can think of only 3 friends from my childhood who
                    weren't children of West Indian families.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, did, what were your parents doing when they got to
                        Harlem, were married, they were both very young.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: My mother, was she, was she even 18?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your mother and her brother were orphaned very young. How
                        did they sustain themselves?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: With the kindness of friends from the West Indies. After the
                    marriage, my father worked as an elevator operator during the ?30s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, the thirties were a terrible time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're talking about with the depression and all, but you
                        were born in '36.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: '26.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '26?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you recall, how do you, these were supposed to be
                        the high years of Harlem, I mean as far as an interesting place, and
                        all.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Right, that was actually more in the twenties. That was the period of
                    the Harlem Renaissance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, so the twenties. What was, how was it being in kid,
                        young kid in Harlem when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, we were poor. When both of my parents had jobs we would move to
                    a nice apartment and when one of them would lose his job and he or she did not
                    get another one pretty quickly we would move to less expensive quarters. Either
                    to another building or to a higher floor in the same walk-up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what about as a kid, were you, did you get out and
                        play stick ball and do a lot of things that kids in New York City did?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I remember once getting a double playing stickball and then promptly
                    got trapped off at second base with the hidden ball trick.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [Laughter]. What about, at home, did you have brothers and
                        sisters?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, only child.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your family, did you all sit around at dinner together
                        and talk and things like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, but they separated and divorced, when I was about 12.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Up to that time, where did you say you went to
                        school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, it was PS 184 on a 116th Street between Lenox and Fifth Avenue.
                    Two buildings, one elementary school, the other junior high (grades 6-9). The
                    junior high had been a Jewish school. Not too many years before, this part of
                    Harlem had been a predominantly Jewish neighborhood. The church across the
                    street from the junior high building still had the Star of David from a pervious
                    incarnation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then, in school, how many subjects were particularly
                        agreed with you or ...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Most, I was a very good student up through junior high through the
                    ninth grade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I know about some communities, such as the Greeks,
                        the Jewish, and Vietnamese and Korean which were within, a lot of emphasis
                        put on education and seeing the success of so many West Indians in the
                        United States, how about, I mean from your perspective, was there much
                        emphasis on education?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There was encouragement, but the response among the children was not
                    good. I was just thinking that you might ask something like this. Of my personal
                    friends, only 2 went directly to college from high school. Both of them children
                    of professional men. The rest of us dropped out and went to work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there at that time, much mixing between, I don't know
                        if you want to call it, the native blacks and the island people coming over
                        ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Most of our social contacts and associations were with other West
                    Indians. I can remember my mother's had a good friend who was an American black.
                    Of course, my mother worked in the Garment District so she had contact with all
                    the great diversity of people and cultures in New York City.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about as kids? I'm not a New Yorker so how about
                        gangs or just ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, none of my friends belonged to a gang, but there were streets we
                    avoided because there were what we called hostile elements in those streets</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I talked this with someone who said that he grew up, he
                        was Jewish, and he grew up in a neighborhood, and he said he really didn't
                        know if there were any people other than Jewish people, but he said there
                        were places you just didn't go, they might be Italian, they might be Irish
                        ... everybody has their little map of don't go to places.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, there were streets of Harlem we did not ever go. But when my
                    mother came to the United States, she was very surprised to find that there were
                    Jews here. She had thought of them as ancient figures in biblical history and
                    then she came to New York City.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The stories that come out of that area, people working,
                        living in these little islands and then finally making, moving out, how
                        about in grammar school, was this a pretty mixed bag or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: What, racially?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, there was one Jewish kid in PS 184. His father was the Yiddish
                    term for it, caretaker of a small synagogue on 114th Street. He represented
                    integration at that time. [Laughter]. We used to live on 114th Street and I can
                    remember as a kid passing this little storefront synagogue before the High
                    Holidays and smelling the wine he was making.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did, was there anything when you were in elementary
                        school, by the time you got to junior high and all, was there anything that
                        I guess we would call black studies today or was this ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, there was Black History Week which my school observed. Now I
                    think it's Black History Month.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. How did you find your teachers? Do you remember any
                        of your teachers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. Mrs. Citron from the third or fourth grade. I liked her. She was
                    well known in this city and caught hell during the McCarthy period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. J. Parnell Thomas and somebody from Texas.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: She came under fire during that time. But I do not remember anything
                    politically tainted in the classroom at that age.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But, looking back on it were, do you think it sort of the
                        elementary and junior high level ... did you get a good education, you
                        think?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, yes. It was very good school. It is sad, the condition that
                    public education has come to. No, it was first rate. It got me into one of three
                    of the finest high schools in New York City, Stuyvesant High, and I could have
                    gotten into either of the other there, too, Bronx High School of Science or
                    Townsend Harris.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I mean you didn't find that there had been a
                        breakdown so that the United States educational delivery system wasn't
                        curtailed by Harlem or anything like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, I don't think so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, obviously.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But anyway, but the system is breaking down everywhere, whatever the
                    cause, either the poor response of the students, or the lack of high
                    expectations on the part of the teachers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Discipline, I mean you know.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Motivation, discipline...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All sorts of things. But we knew that it was, we were
                        supposed to get on with it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, there was discipline in the classroom. There was no rapping of
                    knuckles with a ruler or physical intimidation by the teachers, but there was
                    never any real defiance of the authority of the teacher.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No. When one went to high school in the New York City at
                        that time with good enough grades you could pick your school.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I do not remember if I took an exam to get into Stuyvesant or if they
                    simply took me on the basis of my record. I think they took me on the basis of
                    my record.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, tell me about Stuyvesant.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, there's an end to happy children. I, for some reason, and I
                    never went to a shrink, lost interest in school and with the result that when I
                    went into the army, I was drafted at 18, I still had only a ninth grade
                    education, but somewhere along the way I had picked up tenth grade math. I went
                    to work at 16.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But, what as you recall, did you go to Stuyvesant?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I went and then I stopped going and I never really sat down with a
                    shrink to figure out why. Perhaps at that time I could have used a shrink
                    because obviously I was going through some real confusion in my life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, your parents had broken up ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, and you don't have to be a shrink to know that there
                        may be some connection with that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about, could you just plain drop out at 16?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, yes, you can get working papers at 16.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what did you go into doing when you dropped out, did
                        you like your work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, at 16, though. This was during the war so, '42 so there was no
                    problem getting a job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: First, I took a job delivering, but soon I got into a war plant and I
                    handled the supply room and did shipping and a variety of things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did, so by the time you were 18 in what was it '44, was
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: '44.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were prime draft?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, sure.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were drafted.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, I tried to get in earlier. I got my hands on a relative's birth
                    certificate and registered for the draft under his name when I was 17. When
                    papers from the draft board arrived, my mother kind of went through the
                    roof.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: She marched me down to the draft board and exposed my story so that I
                    had to wait another year until I was drafted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what did they do with you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: What in the army?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, so they sent me to basic training and Fort McClellan, Alabama.
                    After training, I shipped out to Europe on the old Queen Mary in time to get one
                    battle star.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What, was there any particular division?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, I was in the Seventeenth Airborne Division. When the war ended,
                    I didn't have enough points to come home so I was transferred to the 82nd
                    Airborne for the occupation of Berlin, so it was an interesting time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, very interesting time. You a paratrooper or glider
                        infantry?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Glider Rider. I went to jump school after the 82nd returned to the
                    U.S.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did they put you, when you were out in the
                        battle?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, but in division headquarters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The airborne. The army was moving too fast to use them,
                        though.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Crossing the Rhine was the last Airborne operation of the war. There
                    were British paratroopers, gliders of the British Airborne and the 17th in the
                    operation. One-third of my platoon jumped in, one third went in by a glider and
                    my third crossed the Rhine in landing craft.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how long were you in Germany in the occupation of
                        Berlin?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Until, until November 1945.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So April, May.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Before we went to Berlin from France we were in Epinal, a lovely part
                    of France. I left the division the month before it left Berlin for the U.S.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was going on in life when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: The center of Berlin was one pile of rubble that was unimaginable.
                    That's all you could see, climb up on a pile of rubble and all you'd see was
                    more rubble to the horizon. I'm taking my wife there at the end of this month.
                    Scenes in the movie, “The Pianist,” reminded me of Berlin in ?45.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The was a movie called the Pianist and it showed both
                        sides at the end of the War.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: It was like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, what were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: In Berlin?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I was in the division Military Police so we were keeping the
                    troops from getting into too much trouble.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would imagine that the troops, there wasn't anything
                        else to do, but get into trouble, was there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, you do when you occupy, you keep order and enforce the orders of
                    the occupying authorities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, in a way of a, I'm sure the population of Berlin was
                        so depressed, those who were left and they weren't going to have any
                        particular problems with the rules.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: They were no problem, we had more trouble keeping our troops, because
                    they're pretty rambunctious guys.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was going to say, a bunch of, a bunch of, hepped up
                        paratroopers at the very end of the War, so much testosterone and the air is
                        so hard to be an MP, you must have had your, was there a black market?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: A big black market, big black market.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, the cartons of cigarettes for which we paid, I don't know, was
                    it a dollar? Two dollars? It sold for a hundred dollars on the black market so
                    the temptation was to give up smoking.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I did when I was in Korea and a couple years later there
                        was the Vietnam War. Did, now the war was over, you're an MP, you guys were
                        going to be pulled out fairly soon, what were you thinking about doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I stayed in longer than I needed to because I had a chance to
                    go to Alaska to test material in the winter of '46-'47. I spent the winter in
                    Central Alaska outside of Fairbanks testing equipment and men. Because the
                    Department of Defense didn't really know much about fighting in the Russian
                    Winter and the Germans had lots of experience, we had German handbooks
                    translated into English. I still I think I threw my last ones away a couple of
                    years ago. We were up there with a company of paratroopers, artillery, tanks,
                    engineers and spent the Winter seeing how equipment, clothing, and men
                    functioned in extreme cold.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there mistakes?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There was one infantry operation with tanks where we stood out there
                    in the open in 40 below for three hours before the tanks showed up. I think that
                    this was deliberate to create an opportunity to observe how the infantry
                    performed after three hours in extreme cold. There were accidents, too. We lost
                    one trooper but not on a jump.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good, God. How does that work, I mean?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: On our first jump we landed on a plowed field of a dairy outside of
                    Fairbanks. It was similar to the plowed field we used in South Carolina. Well,
                    this field, unlike what we were used to, was as hard as concrete. I made a bad
                    3-point landing, heels, butt, back of the head. I was groggy and there is a
                    photo of me being led off the field by hand by a fellow named Andrew Jackson
                    Barnes III. He claimed descent from AJ. Our last jump, on the contrary, was pure
                    pleasure. We came down on the same field, but this time it was covered by two to
                    four feet of snow. In addition, we used a new aircraft from which we exited by a
                    rear cargo door avoiding the prop blast we were used to in C-47 and C-46
                    airplanes. The whole thing was so delightful that I just lay in the snow instead
                    of jumping up and getting on with the operation. Lieutenant Garcia, thinking
                    that I must be injured, crawled through the snow to get to me and was not happy
                    to find me reveling in the experience. “Get up, you son of a bitch.” He was so
                    pissed off, but I wasn't worried. It was my last jump and by far the best.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, well after this experience did you want to head south
                        again, or does the cold weather appeal to you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, no. This was great. This was one of the great adventures of my
                    life. We gained confidence. We learned, we used skies, we used snowshoes. They
                    gave us a four-man tent and a stove and blankets and stuff like that and a sled
                    and a harness with which we could pull the sled and we did. And we pull the sled
                    and set up at night and the next morning knock it down and pack and pull the
                    sled again. This was great when you were at the age of, what was I then? That's
                    marvelous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I don't know if you have ever heard of him, but I think General Gavin
                    was the youngest division commander during the War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: General Gavin, commander of the 82nd, came up from North Carolina to
                    see what we were doing. We were going to put on a demonstration jump for him and
                    it was at that time, I think it was to be the farthest North mass jump. The jump
                    was canceled because the coldest I can remember seeing was 60 below. That night,
                    I never got to sleep because somehow I let my feet get cold and could never get
                    them warmed up, so I spent a sleepless night, but that's the only bad thing I
                    remember. We had a snow “pool” on the snowfall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, well a “pool.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Guess how many feet of snow they're going to see. Someone guessed a
                    fantastic 18 feet. Well, no one came close. We had only 3 or 4 feet where we
                    were based.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, by this time were you thinking about getting out of
                        the military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I left in 1947. I got called back into the Reserves during the Korean
                    War, the only time I thought of perhaps a career of it. In 1947, I wanted to get
                    back, get home, and go to school so I came back to finish high school in a
                    year.</p>
                <p>My experience with race in the Army may be worth a mention in that I served in
                    three different armies from the standpoint of race: segregated white,
                    integrated, and segregated negro. I had registered for the draft as white. I had
                    heard that the Negroes were being issued shovels and I wanted a gun. But when
                    President Truman ordered racial integration of the military, I had my personal
                    record changed to read negro and as a negro I was recalled as a reservist during
                    the Korean War. But my experience in the integrated Army lasted only six months
                    when I was transferred from an integrated unit to the newly-created 25th Signal
                    Battalion (NEGRO). Guess someone did not get the message. This incident did get
                    me a letter to the editor published in the Sunday “New York Times.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you graduate from Queens?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: 1953.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What year did you graduate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Let's see. Probably '53 because I got called back to the Reserves and
                    spent a year and a half in the Army and then went back and finished school.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What, what were you doing when they called you back, were
                        you back in the paratroopers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, no. No, no. I was in, finished up in the 25th Signal Battalion
                    and never went overseas. I didn't, in fact, I didn't leave commuter distance of
                    New York City so it was kind of a waste of my time and their money.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you went back to Queens College.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And got your degree in what, '53 then about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, that must have been because I was working for 3 or 4 years
                    before I entered the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I was in the general area of social work, I was working for the
                    Department of Welfare in New York because that was what I had planned to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What, how about let's talk about social welfare in New
                        York City, we're told it's a middle class Jewish relief after Korea, I mean
                        heavily dominated by the Jewish population.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But as the recipients or as the administration?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There were a number of Jews who were in it, but there were a lot of
                    other people, too. My immediate supervisor was a lady of Italian extraction and
                    my fellows, the other people in my unit were other groups, German, there were a
                    great variety, but yes, the boss of my supervisor was Jewish.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were doing what?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There was fascinating case work because my district extended from 5th
                    Avenue to the East River, the North Side of 32nd Street to the South side of
                    105th. I still had some Irish down on 32nd Street in that area. I had Puerto
                    Ricans in the ?90s and I had blacks in 105th Street and in between I had Germans
                    in Yorkville, I had one woman who, when I went to look, to look up her
                    background I had to look in a book of European nobility, the Almanac de Gotha.
                    That's where I had to look up her family. It was a fascinating caseload. Now
                    they were all depressing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you finding and what were you doing about
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I looked after people receiving public assistance. I would see
                    how they were managing in terms of what was available to them and make sure they
                    were getting it. If there were children to go to school, to make sure that they
                    were well cared for and had the materials, the books, pencils and so forth,
                    clothing and shoes to start the new school year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how did you find your clientele, were they doing
                        what they should do and all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, I had so many who reached retirement age. Working people who
                    reached retirement age, went down and applied for Social Security, got their
                    first Social Security check, and realized they couldn't live on it and they
                    didn't have any savings. So they go to the Welfare office and apply for welfare
                    and the idea was to keep them in their homes, in their apartments, because there
                    was no financial savings, you know, squeezing them so they would go someplace
                    else, there wasn't any other place to go, but in those days, unlike today, there
                    was modest cost housing available. We've lost a lot of that inexpensive housing
                    and that's another problem. But there was housing then that was reasonably
                    priced where the poor could live.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But again, we're talking about a reasonably disciplined
                        group that were looking, they needed extra help.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And then there were, I used to work with, not delinquent children,
                    not latch key children, but single parent households, mothers whom we didn't
                    require to go out to work then. We wanted them home to supervise the children.
                    Society has changed since then and now they're happy to drive them out into
                    jobs, into minimum wage jobs. Who's looking after the children?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you were saying, but I mean, this is not something
                        where you were, going out today can be very depressing to do this type of
                        work.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But it, there is nothing depressing, I would not find it depressing.
                    Something changed later on, but then adult children were considered responsible
                    for their parents. They and putative fathers could be taken to court to force
                    them to contribute to the welfare recipient's support. Sometimes we realized
                    that they were providing a telephone for their parents, which is something they
                    would not be entitled to on a welfare budget. So we would go there and the
                    client would be terrified that the phone would ring. But I didn't find it
                    depressing at all because I felt that we were in a situation where we were
                    actually helping people at that time. We weren't pursuing them because they were
                    Pariahs or something like that. We didn't talk about “Welfare Queens.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the city, the administration, was there
                        concern of sort of a Patronage Tax System?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Do you mean in the city?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, the city.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I didn't have anything at all. I once voted for a man named
                    Impellateri because I thought he was against the system and he turned out to be
                    as big a part of the machine (Tammany Hall) as anyone else so I pretty much
                    withdrew from local politics. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then. In all this time, in school, with family,
                        military, social service and all and getting caught up in wars, did
                        International Affairs intrude, you know the Cold War or what was going
                        abroad, the creation of Israel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, I was very conscious of them and had an interest in what was
                    going on, I remember the period, was '48 before Israel was founded, the
                    discussions of the UN, what they were going to, how it was going to be arranged
                    and that map, it looked like a mosaic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did, had you run across anybody who was involved in the
                        foreign affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: This was a constant discussion at the university either during class
                    or otherwise. Also, this was the time of McCarthy so politics and foreign
                    affairs and what was going on in the world was very much a daily diet.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about communism, sort of home-grown communism, cause
                        New York, as an immigrant community and all, many of them came out of
                        Europe, many of them brought the sort of socialist/communist point of view
                        when you had the Daily Worker and you had other papers and one thing the
                        left being rather vocal anyway and did you run across that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, sure we had a couple of, at least one devoted communist on
                    campus, but what is funny, she turned out to be married to a fellow I served
                    with in World War II so we all got together and I was at their house one night
                    when they were having a party and they played the Internationale and everybody
                    stood up, but it wasn't serious, they were very much of the left and they would
                    probably describe themselves as communists and readers of the “Daily Worker.” I
                    had, I had friends all over the spectrum. This was a guy I met in basic training
                    during World War II, and I was going to school with his wife.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then, how did you, you were doing social work for
                        what about 3 years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: 3 years, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Then I past the exam and entered the Foreign Service in '56.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how did you hear about it, I mean how did you know
                        about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: We were talking on campus, a whole bunch of us went down and took it:
                    Bill Woessner who later was DCM in Bonn. Do you know him, you know Billy?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I'm the only person who calls him Billy. After he left school he
                    became Bill. No, we are friends going back to the mid-'50s, no, no earlier ...
                    sure, the late ?40s because he had a party for me when I was going back into the
                    Army.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well what was, was there any particular push to take the
                        Foreign Service Exam?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, yes. Well, one thing that was in my mind is I thought that they
                    owed me. Here I'd been to Europe in World War II and had never so much as gotten
                    so much as a 3-day pass to go to Paris or any other interesting place,
                    Copenhagen or the Riviera, I had one guy go to the Riviera and so I felt
                    cheated, I went to Berlin which was a rubble heap so there was always a
                    resentment. I came back, and was going to go back to school, but I planned next
                    summer I'm going to take that student boat to Europe, and next summer came and
                    of course I'm 23 years old and I need those 6 credits. Each summer was like that
                    until finally the last summer came, I got my degree and I was too broke to go
                    anywhere [Laughter] and I had to go to work. So I felt that they owed me and so
                    I took the exam and I was accepted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you take, you took the oral exam too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you recall anything on the oral exam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, the opening line. The first words they said, I've got four guys
                    sitting up there and I'm sitting here in my double-breasted blue suit and the
                    first thing one says to me was, “Mr. Richardson: Your mother was white and your
                    father was colored”... or maybe he said Negro? and what a beginning ... so I
                    said, yes, yes, that's right. So I mean you know what [Laughter] ... and that
                    was the end of that discussion. But that was the opening, and I was conscious of
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, oh I can imagine.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But, of course, at that time there weren't many blacks, Negroes, or
                    colored or whatever the term was and the Department was conscious of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, it was you know ... I won't even say things were
                        changing because I don't think they changed for some time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But, there was consciousness that, so, they didn't set out, they did
                    not have a formal affirmative action program, but there was an inclination, an
                    interest in recruiting, they hadn't formalized it, but ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So in a way, you think this comment was more almost on the
                        positive side than the negative side.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I, they knew this from the record, they didn't have to ask the
                    question. What I've always suspected is that they wanted to see what my reaction
                    was to the question.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, well, I mean I used to be on the panel of various
                        things and would have never done that, but this is 20 years later so, but we
                        were interested in reactions, you know I mean because somebody you know if
                        it was something you might come up against and you don't want to, you want
                        to find out ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Or how the person reacts under stress.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Stress.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Stress, does this cause any stress, how does he react? I mean, you
                    know I was you know yes, that's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [Laughter] Do you recall any other questions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. Embarrassing one about the Reconstruction 1870, and the
                    election, on which I showed abysmal ignorance. [Laughter] I think it all worked
                    out, I just washed out. [Laughter].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I used to give the oral exam and sometimes we had
                        people who used to get the Civil War and the Revolutionary War mixed up, you
                        know, I mean [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I didn't ... I don't think I made any mistakes because I don't ever
                    remember saying “I don't know” in so many different forms in my life. No, that,
                    I don't recall that period and I don't think I ever knew that. There was
                    something of total ignorance, but I handled that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By this time had you run across anyone who had been in the
                        Foreign Service to find out what the hell you're going to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any feel for what you might be doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. I was going to somehow affect ... eventually the world. It was
                    an adventure and you don't always know when you're going to climb the mountain,
                    you don't really know exactly where you're going to put your feet.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I think most of us were in that position. What, when
                        did you come in to the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: '56. It would have been in July of '56, in fact, the anniversary of
                    which was last year. That must have been 47th?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: '56 to '03, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, well do you recall, what was your class like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: That was a good bunch. We were very small, I mean I look at the
                    classes now a days and ... .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have a number on it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: 16, that's all. 16. and Harry Cahill who is still around here ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right, I know Harry, we served in Belgrade together.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, yes. Did he, you know his wife?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I haven't seen her ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Nikki.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Nikki. Argentinean. I haven't seen her since '56, but I remember she
                    just charmed us all. Absolutely charming girl.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, she's very nice.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, several, one fellow left, oh ... I believe that's the only name
                    I remember, but Dick Christiansen, he ended up in, retired in Southwest
                    somewhere, yes, but it was a small enough class and one of them, I think, yes,
                    he decided that he was going to leave before we finished the A-100 course, he
                    decided that he could have more of an impact if he went to work for a
                    congressmen than if he worked his way up within the Foreign Service. I once
                    wrote the poem for Harry Cahill, a Dadaist poem that went something like “The
                    ashtray grows but a short walk down the hall.” And I've forgotten the rest of
                    it. [Laughter]. I hope he has preserved it. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now, where did you, where were you assigned your
                        first post?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Dakar. And now that was interesting because you know when I did the
                    A-100 course there weren't any Negroes around State except in janitors and
                    messengers and so I thought I was unique in the service and I found out later on
                    that Liberia was only entry post for Negroes. That's the term that was used at
                    the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask a question. Did you feel “Negro,” “Colored,”
                        “Black” or something at that time, because looking at you, and so often I
                        wouldn't, I couldn't categorize you as anything, but I mean, how did you,
                        did you consider yourself to be part of a group or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, in my particular circumstance, I'd lived in an integrated
                    society, at least in a small group of people, all my life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I was going to say for example, in the Army, you
                        must ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, well, no. In the Army, I wanted a gun and they weren't giving
                    guns to Negroes, they were giving them shovels, so when I registered for the
                    draft, I registered as white.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And that's how I got into 2 elite airborne units.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, does the question ever come up or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, once you say you're this, that's what you are.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, but you know the whole categorization is so
                        fallacious anyway that ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well that was the way things were categorized so in making an
                    assignment, they're not looking at the person, they're looking at an information
                    sheet ... white ... you can go to that one ... black ... you go to that one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then, but when you went to, you went to Dakar
                        first.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you take French before going?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No. They gave me a week or two which I don't know. It looked like,
                    that, I've always suspected, was a design for failure because to go in an
                    entirely foreign language ... here's what my responsibilities were, I was the
                    admin. officer, the only admin officer. So I was the administrative officer, I
                    was the general services officer, which is fairly heavy and also the consular
                    officer. In consular function I had a consular assistant who worked, also served
                    as American Secretary and on the administrative side, I had an administrative
                    secretary, a French woman who also did my translations of leases and things like
                    that. But to send somebody out with no more French, with no French, into an
                    entirely French speaking environment with those responsibilities, looked like
                    somebody was trying to sabotage the operation. Anyway, they didn't succeed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's talk about Dakar and you were there in
                        ?50s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: '56 to early, early January '59.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, I mean this is really before the, you want to call it
                        the de-colonization of Africa.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean this is sort of the old Africa still.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is Dakar like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Dakar was a French city set down in the West Coast of Africa. Abidjan
                    was even more so, but Dakar was French. You had French restaurants. I ate
                    entrecote grill� every night for three months because that was the only dish I
                    knew in French. [Laughter].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, yes, we have to stick to the facts. [Laughter].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, well it was, it had a good climate, too. The weather time of the
                    year in the fall, what would be the winter, where you would not be uncomfortable
                    wearing a jacket.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was Consulate General at the time, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And it had essentially, it was sort of the administrative
                        capital for a whole series of places that later became...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, my consular district was about 2/3 the size of the United
                    States. It extended all the way down to the border of Nigeria, Algeria to the
                    north, Sudan to the east, and to French Equatorial Africa in the south.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I left in '59 for Saigon, came back to West Africa 3 years
                    later and what had been my Consular district, one political unit, was something
                    like 7 or 8 independent countries. [Laughter]. All of the sudden, you're
                    crossing a border whereas before you could travel thousands of miles or
                    kilometers, whichever you prefer, without ever having presented your passport in
                    customs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how was the Consul General when you got there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Mallory Brown who was I think of USIA and the next one was Don Dumont
                    who was out of the Africa office, Africa Bureau in State.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was, I mean did you get any feel for Africa per
                        se or was this so French that it was, you lived in a French world, or
                        not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: One tread carefully between two worlds. All significant authorities
                    were French. The instructors, the teachers were French. Colonel John Edwards,
                    political officer, who was the representative of another agency, advised me when
                    I arrived, “You cannot mix at a small social event the Africans and the French.”
                    And I thought, oh my he's old fashioned, we're moving into the new world. Well,
                    I had a dinner one night and I carefully chose the guests, they had all gone to
                    the same university, Toulouse, and they were young, young open to ideas, and had
                    been, had the same university experience. Well, out of all the entertaining my
                    wife and I had done in all of these years, that was the worst evening and if it
                    hadn't been for the wife of a Frenchmen, an extremely vivacious young woman, who
                    never stopped talking, it would have been an even worse evening. My wife and I
                    couldn't wait for it to end. [Laughter].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned a wife. When did you acquire a significant
                        other?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: A week before I left for my first post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was her background and where did you meet her?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: She was a teacher in New York, went to City College of the city
                    university. She was teaching when I met her in April of '56 and we married in
                    November.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, did she speak French?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, but she has a remarkable capacity for communication and it
                    doesn't matter whether she speaks the language or not. She communicates ...
                    .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know. Some people can.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Amusingly, she, of course, picked up kitchen French, kitchen Spanish,
                    kitchen Farsi. But, a Frenchman once said to her, “Madame Richardson, you speak
                    French perfectly without any agreement of verbs.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What, where you studying French while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, yes. I had to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever get Nicola Declare, I don't know what the
                        term is, but “out in the brush or something, sort of beyond the French orbit
                        and all?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no. I was busy. I was busy with 3 functions and when we were
                    closed on the weekend, there was a note on the door that said if you need to
                    contact someone from the Consulate, call Mr. Richardson and gave my phone
                    number. I was permanent duty officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, how nice. [Laughter]. Did we have any particular
                        ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: My wife got to travel while I was trapped in town. The single women
                    there had to put her to the test before they would travel with her. She was the
                    only American-born wife. The consul general's, no, not Mallory Brown, but Don
                    Dumont's wife was Moroccan-born French. Tony's wife was German, Marcel
                    Vanessen's wife was Belgian, Colonel Edward's wife was Swiss. My wife was the
                    only American-born wife. We had some great single women, Pat Wiggleswort and
                    Joan Clark and Jeanne Vertafeuille. The latter was instrumental in unmasking the
                    “mole” at CIA a couple of years ago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ames?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Ames, that was, if that was the one because I get confused, one of
                    them was at the CIA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ames was CIA.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, she was instrumental in unmasking him and she, her picture was
                    on Newsweek or Time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how do you say that the single women tested your
                        wife?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How does that work?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, they all went out one weekend in a van, went to visit an
                    important Muslim shrine at Touba, and the van broke down. So they have to take
                    refuge for the night in the home of a Lebanese merchant out there in the bush.
                    And she evidently comported herself well because when she came back the girls
                    thought she was alright [Laughter]. And she went off, she then traveled with
                    Jean, my secretary and the consul general's secretary, to Timbuktu by boat on
                    the Niger. Another time, they went off together, just the two of them, to
                    Mauritania by commercial truck. Purely by chance they were at the founding of
                    the new capital of Mauritania, Nouakchott, the day they founded Nouakchott and
                    they brought back amusing photographs of signs mounted on stakes driven into the
                    sand that said: “Gendarmerie” and “Palais de Justice.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But, this I have to tell you. They did this to me twice. I had no
                    wife at home and no secretary at the office. It was a bad time. So I fixed them,
                    it was the best gag I've ever pulled in my life so I'm using this as an occasion
                    to spread it. I was out at the airport when they came back from Mauritania. They
                    had gone up by truck and then they flew back. So I'm out at the airport and this
                    DC-3 comes bouncing down the field and I put on the longest face I could. And
                    they're bubbling over and they're very excited about seeing me and they're not
                    noticing that I'm not looking all that happy. Finally, it dawned on one of them
                    that I'm not showing sufficient enthusiasm about their return, so they asked me,
                    “What's wrong? What's the matter? Aren't you glad to see me?” So I said, “It's
                    just a damn good thing for you two that my mistress knows how to type!”
                    [Laughter]. And I didn't have any problems with them going off together again.
                    But, I never pulled a better gag than that one. And that happened early in the
                    marriage, you know. [Laughter]. I've never been able to match that one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then, how about some of the work you were doing? Was
                        it difficult working in Dakar or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Difficult. Well, don't forget this was my first post, everything was
                    brand new and I didn't have French, at least at first. Before I went, the staff
                    had been living in really crummy facilities that had been made available by the
                    local French government. The consul general was living in a big house, also made
                    available by the French, but I saw these awful buildings that my predecessor had
                    lived in when he first went to the post. It was pretty grim, but Department
                    opened up and he was able to lease two grand apartments. They were only one
                    bedroom, but they were big. So that's what I went into so I had good housing, I
                    could have a party. There's lots of space for entertaining, but only one
                    bedroom. So they gave us permission to lease 0other places and that's when I got
                    into leasing, when I hired a French woman to act as my administrative secretary
                    and translate and she did the leases for me so that was interesting. That was a
                    major activity, getting housing for the staff. They no longer had to go out on
                    the market on their own. On the Consular side, there was very, very little, very
                    little. Not like today where West Africa is busy with Visas. There were almost
                    no visas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get visitors through there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: At that time, I never saw a congressman in the two years I was in
                    Dakar. Then we opened Abidjan as a consulate, as a constituent post while I was
                    there and there was some working connection with that. The Consul General didn't
                    feel like going, so he sent me down to inspect it, which was pretty
                    presumptuous. I'm going down to inspect Consul Park Massey. He was a veteran of
                    World War II with the same 17th Airborne division I had, but he was a senior
                    officer and I'm being sent down there to inspect him, but things went off
                    alright.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When Senegal didn't ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: De Gaulle came down and made his tour of West Africa, not only West
                    Africa, but Equatorial Africa also and plugged the new 5th Republic
                    constitution. Guinea chose to leave the Community. And so that was exciting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, that was when the French pulled and took the faucets
                        and light fixtures.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were going to show the Guineans ...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, I'm trying to remember, it was still in tact when I left, but
                    they were going to vote. So there was excitement in connection, who was going to
                    do what to whom. There was a territorial assembly in Dakar. So all of these
                    people like Houphouet-Boigny, Sekou Toure, Leopold Senghor, and Diori were all
                    there in Dakar, political figures from the territories, who later became
                    presidents of new countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, were we making any effort to cultivate these
                        people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No and certainly not with ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I recall interviewing somebody who was involved at this
                        time in one of the places like Ivory Coast or some place, one of the slower
                        places, saying that Dakar was sort of, really didn't want to give up the
                        colonial ... empire, this was on the American side, they were not very
                        forthcoming because they felt they were the center of the universe and they
                        had very much a colonial attitude.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I think that would be true. That would be my estimate also. Yes, and
                    they were very pro-French. I don't know if this would illustrate that, but at
                    one time because my secretary and my wife did so much traveling, they got
                    written up in the local French paper suggesting they were involved in espionage
                    and the French intelligence went to my Consul General and accused my wife of
                    transporting, transmitting, carrying messages to, for the FLN in Algeria. And he
                    did not, he didn't treat it with the skepticism I thought he should have. He was
                    totally unsupportive. Inspectors came out in early December of '58 to check on
                    these reports. I think they were also looking to see how well prepared the post
                    was for the oncoming independence, but while they were there, they took the
                    trouble to reassure me that I shouldn't worry about this accusation, but it
                    really disturbed my wife.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, of course it did, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And she got, we got no support, she got no support from my Consul
                    General.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, in a way, many of our people early on were sort of
                        in the pockets of the French, in a way wouldn't you say?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, the other agency, I was not aware of any contacts they had.
                    They may have had because certainly these people were going to lead these
                    territories and independence was coming soon. So I liked to think that they were
                    in contact, but I never saw it.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And also, the French were very suspicious and if they saw us
                    cultivating Africans, they would have resented it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this is of course, this went on in particular during
                        the early years, but has gone on and even exists somewhat today and that is
                        the French not really trusting, thinking the Americans have designs on these
                        places which from an American point of view, “Why the hell would we have
                        designs, let the French take care of it.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Even after independence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: The only time we got interested in new independent states was when we
                    needed votes in the UN to keep China out. Otherwise, if there hadn't been China,
                    I don't think we would have ever gotten interested.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did, while you were there, were the French were fighting
                        the FLN in Algeria, weren't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did that intrude at all into concerns of ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no. The only time was when my wife was accused of being a
                    messenger for the FLN [Laughter]. I don't know to whom she was supposed to
                    deliver the messages.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I, you know, I'm sure security people don't like to
                        see people travel, foreigners, it makes them nervous.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, so in early '59 you were due to leave and what
                        happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Then, after spending 2 years as Admin, General Services, and Consular
                    Officer in Dakar, they sent me to French training in Nice, with a humble
                    assignment in the Department. Now you tell me, does that make any sense?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [Laughter].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: At breakfast in Nice one day, I got into a conversation with a man
                    who was also taking the course. He was going out to be DCM or Political
                    Counselor in Laos and I had been reading about Indochina and I said to him, you
                    know how much I was envying him, I'd love to get out there. Well, I planted the
                    seed in the right place, unknowingly. Because when I got back to Washington and
                    reported to the desk, they said oh, you're not staying here. Go down the hall
                    and see the people in whatever the Bureau is ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Southeast Asia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Southeast Asia. I went to Saigon, which delighted me. That was a good
                    time to be there. The French war was over a couple of years and the American War
                    had not yet started. It was a war alright. It was a Vietnamese War, but this was
                    the period when they were developing the plan, how to win the hearts and minds
                    of the people and send in the Green Berets and small groups to give medical
                    attention and this and that. That was when that was going on. So that was an
                    interesting time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were there from ... ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: '59 to '61.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I was the political section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON:Elbridge Durbrow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went back, he was an old China hand, wasn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no. He ... where would he have been before? I don't know, but I
                    don't think he had had any previous experience in that area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, maybe not.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And then he was soured by old things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How, what was the situation in Vietnam when you arrived,
                        we're talking about South Vietnam.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, we were solidly in support of Ngo Dinh Diem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: We were not yet, not yet disillusioned with him as happened later on
                    in the Kennedy Administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, were they still talking about Diem being Arguit the
                        Abonese Magsaysay, and all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, that, if no one ever said it in my presence, but certainly he
                    was our man. He was Syngman Rhee. He was Magsaysay. He was our choice. After he
                    was, what in a convent, or a monastery in the States when they anointed him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What, where'd you live and how was life there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I lived in an apartment. The first place I had was a completely air
                    conditioned apartment and it was dark. Then there was an opportunity to move to
                    the top floor of a small apartment building that wasn't air conditioned at all
                    but it was so bright and cheerful so my wife and I moved there and enjoyed it.
                    Yes, we really enjoyed Vietnam. We traveled all over the country north of
                    Saigon. One time, I put something like 2,000 miles on that car, on the
                    Volkswagen and it's such a little country I can't figure out how I got that many
                    miles on it. [Laughter]. And the people are hard working. They're cultured, I
                    mean in terms of their own culture and of course they absorb the French culture
                    and so for most and the food was ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you get French and Vietnamese food, you couldn't ask
                        for two nicer cuisines.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no. So we enjoyed that very much and it was a good time because
                    as I said the French War was over and the American one had not begun.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the head of the Political Section?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Joe Mendenhall. I think later Ambassador in Madagascar, I think. I
                    know that he went from Saigon to head up the AID mission to Laos, at a time when
                    it was a very big operation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What piece of the action were you given in the political
                        section?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: You call “dog's body.” The one thing that I had that I did all the
                    time was in North, was a weekly report on North Vietnam. Now, where did I get
                    that information from? Very often I got it from people who'd been there. They
                    had the international commission.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: These are Canadians and Indians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, but Canadians, Indians and Polish.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, the Poles, we didn't have much luck with them but the Indians
                    and the Canadians, we were able to ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they traveled back and forth.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And I would include stuff that I'd been given from the political
                    section that they'd picked up, a lot from the agency people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how, was the CIA outfit the station, or a
                        substantial station?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. I would say that in my 35 years service, the best relations that
                    I've ever experienced in my time. When I arrived, Nick Natsios was the head of
                    the office and he took me around his shop to meet his people and you know there
                    were no new barriers. And he was followed by Bill Colby, later Agency director.
                    My wife and Mrs. Colby still see each other. So there were excellent
                    relationships between political and the agency. As a matter of fact, they even
                    called on me once because they wanted some cover. They wanted to make contact
                    with a Pole and he played bridge so I invited him over to play bridge and the
                    fourth was the guy who wanted to meet him. And when we left Saigon, Mrs. Colby
                    gave a big tea for my wife. This produced a lot of question within the embassy,
                    “Why is Mrs. Colby giving your wife a tea party?” Because they got along well,
                    but it had nothing to do with Bill and me. Later, a few years later, sort of a
                    happen stance, we traveled from Europe to the States on the same ship so we've
                    had lots of contact, but if you go back to the professional part of it, I've
                    never had or seen better and closer integration of effort and activity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what were you seeing up in North Vietnam at the
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Who were we seeing?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you seeing developments up there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There was activity in agriculture collectivization and efforts to
                    keep people from fleeing south.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have much contact with Vietnamese, South
                        Vietnamese?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. Matter of fact, I'd go out one weekend, yes I had Vietnamese to
                    my home all the time. Very often they'd turn up without their wives and a bunch
                    of flowers, but still they came. And I'm glad our relations with French too, who
                    are still there. There was this colonel who headed up the brewery there. 33 is
                    the brand. Another was a doctor who lived right opposite the presidential
                    palace. Oh, and there were French there with whom we had very good relations.
                    One amusing thing, I don't know if you think, we just talk, I was at dinner one
                    night and I met an absolutely charming Frenchmen, delightful fellow. And his
                    name was Oquinel. It sounded like something that you eat. At the end of the
                    evening, we exchanged cards. His name was Raymond O'Connell. His father or
                    grandfather was some Irish adventurer who ended up in Indochina in the 19th
                    century.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, did you get out and talk to the French on the
                        plantations and all that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, but we had a better informant for that. I did spend one weekend
                    up with the French at a rubber plantation, but we had a secretary, Larry Pat
                    Hughs who was up there every weekend.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the American presence sort of overpowering at that
                        time or very small?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, but they were there. My guess is there were probably as many as
                    1,900 U.S. Military, but I can't speak with any exactness about the figure. This
                    is the impression I have from that period, there may have been as many as 1,900.
                    No combat units. It was definitely a highly desirable assignment for the
                    Military at that time because this was the only war going on and they would come
                    out to get their cards punched.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about, were the French Military around?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no. The French had even given up training the Vietnamese Army in
                    1954. They turned that over to the U.S. a couple of years earlier. When was Dien
                    Bien Phu? 1954?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ah, '54, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And so, in fact, I think in '56 they turned over responsibility for
                    training the Vietnamese Army. to the U.S. so the French Military were there
                    maybe only as attaches.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did, how about, did you have many, much communication with
                        the Chinese community and so on in other places?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about ... ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: With them, there would be mostly a language problem. I don't know how
                    good their French was. So one night, I was astounded, when it was very late,
                    11:00 at night and some, for some reason I think it was, my wife and I in
                    Chalon, eating, why we'd be eating that late, I don't know, but we got into
                    conversation with the waiter who spoke very good English. And so we asked him
                    some questions about that, and do you know where he learned his English? From a
                    Chinese teacher of English. [Laughter]. His accent was good. But, that's as I
                    say that's the only serious conversation I've ever had with a Chinese.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about your days going down to the Delta and often
                        times to the Highlands?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Highlands, I would, North of Saigon we went everywhere up to the DMZ.
                    That's where I had my Volkswagen bug.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: My Volkswagen bug, the car.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But the Delta was out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Because guerilla activities had picked up. When I first arrived, Tom
                    Barnes and I talked about using public transportation and going down to the
                    Camau Peninsula, to the Delta, to see the country, but we didn't. Before we
                    could put that into operation, within 6 months there was so much guerrilla
                    activity that we could never get permission to go down there so we ended up
                    going North to go hiking in the Highlands. On another occasion I traveled to the
                    North and back. Up along the coast and back through the highlands.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do we have anything on Da Nang?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: You mean as a consulate?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No we had only Hue. Da Nang was military.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any sort of North-South, I'm talking about
                        difference within the political spectrum between North and South Vietnam and
                        Southern-South Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, of course, you had the Northerners who had escaped from the
                    North, but they had moved South and they were predominantly Catholic so you had
                    a difference there. Both of geography and of religion. And you had more
                    political opposition that probably came from Buddhists or types that didn't have
                    any particular religious affiliation, but the government was not very tolerant
                    of them, tolerant of opposition.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Were they having that battle, I can't remember,
                        between I can't think of the name right now, it was sort of a sect, a
                        religious sect?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Bao Dai. Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, but there were guys who ran the whorehouse.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I mean ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: That was a gang.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a gang essentially.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, well he squashed that before I arrived. What were they called,
                    I've forgotten?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd say Wha Wha or something like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Hwa Hao.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hwa Hao, something like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, yes. No, that was, that gang, but there were two of them: Wha
                    Hao was one, which we're calling Wha How and then there was another one, they
                    were Hoods, I think. And they were operating the whore houses, they had that
                    kind of activity and it was also a threat to law and order, but while I was
                    there, there was an attempt by some army unit to overthrow the government and
                    that was in November, I know it was November 11th because that's the Marine
                    Corps birthday is. So it was November 11th, the night of the 11th/12th.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>That coup attempt lasted the entire weekend. After the Marine Corps birthday
                    reception Friday night, there was no ball due to security concerns. My wife and
                    I went to an after-hours club where we fell in with a bunch of Canadians and
                    Political Section secretary Mary Pat Hughes. We got home about 2:00 after
                    dropping off Mary Pat. As I was putting the car in the garage, heavy gunfire
                    broke out nearby with tracers passing over the house so thick it looked like a
                    lighted path in the sky. Along the way I found Mary Pat on the street curious
                    about what was going on. She jumped in with me confident that a secretary would
                    be useful. And she was. Other than communicators and Marine guards we were the
                    only staff at the embassy until Sunday afternoon. The ambassador had set up a
                    command post at the residence where he was getting reports from our people on
                    the street. He dictated cables to Mary Pat and I signed off for transmission. On
                    Sunday afternoon a couple of us were going out to the top floor balcony when we
                    stopped because of nearby gunfire. The fellow immediately in front of me spun
                    around and was pressed against my chest. Just then he caught a bullet in the
                    back. He was other agency with a sense of humor. Reaching around to his wound he
                    complained “someone has put a hole in my cloak.” He survived.</p>
                <p>Mary Pat certainly deserved an award for her work, initiative, and devotion to
                    the job, but I don't know if she ever got one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think November 10th, as I recall.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Okay, that night. That would have been '60. Colby was already there
                    so it must have been '60 because one of our junior officers, John Helble,
                    distinguished himself by reporting by telephone from the balcony of the Colby
                    house overlooking the presidential palace and was able to give the ambassador a
                    blow by blow report. Well, have we talked long enough?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, no. I'm thinking in terms of, I want, I'd like to
                        finish up the Saigon bit and then we can stop. How about, did we have much
                        contact with say the Buddhists. I assume we had relatively good contact with
                        the Catholics and all.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: With the Buddhists as Buddhists?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I don't know. I'm not aware of it in the political section, but I
                    would, I think I have to assume that this would have been something the
                    intelligence agencies would have been doing because the political section, the
                    embassy as the embassy would have been very much concerned about alienating Diem
                    by being seen to cultivate his enemy so I think that ... they would have to
                    leave that to the intelligence people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about, did you run across the news, I was thinking
                        Madame Ngu of course and her husband which was, who was it Tim's
                        brother.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, I didn't. No, what's his name? Nhu.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, anyway ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Nhu.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Were they figures when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, very much so. We regarded Nhu as the principle advisor and
                    confidante of his brother. The one person he trusted. And, remember, he had
                    ambitions and evidently had real influence, this was the impression we had. She
                    was a power to be reckoned with ... a very strong personality and she still is I
                    think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Well, were there any attacks on the embassy or ...
                        ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, but right after I left they blew up the embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes the bomb went off right in front of it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes and there were, there was a bomb of sorts thrown over the wall at
                    one of my colleagues, I think he was USAID. I don't think anybody was injured,
                    but there was concern, but not, if, there wasn't so serious a situation that I
                    couldn't get permission to drive all over the country except down South.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then maybe this is a good place to stop?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Except, do you want to finish Saigon?</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: LBJ was coming out as Vice President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well wait, he wouldn't have, he didn't come in until
                        '61.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: As Vice President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I mean Kennedy was elected in '60 and they came in
                        '61 and you were still there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from '59 to '61.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, now so LBJ is coming. Of course this is a big deal so they get
                    us all together and I had not had too high of an opinion of the Admin.
                    Counselor, but when I saw how he organized this big deal that was coming up ...
                    my esteem for him went up considerably. Well, my job was to organize a
                    reception, guest list of about 600 people and by then I had left the political
                    section, I was staff aid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For Nolting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: For Nolting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ambassador Nolting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, yes. Durbrow had just left. He wouldn't let me leave until he
                    left. So I get out a guest list and did what everyone has to do to organize a
                    big affair and the morning of the affair, I boarded a ship going out to the
                    South China Sea. [Laughter]. At 6:00 when the first guest was due to arrive, I
                    was just clearing the river going past Vung Tau with tears in my eyes, into the
                    South China Sea. So, it's the only time I'd really run away from my
                    responsibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, that's probably a good one to get away with. I think
                        when the Kennedy's, Jack and Bobby, sent Lyndon Johnson out to get him out
                        of town more than anything else.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. But I was very saddened to leave. I'd had such a good time, I
                    had become so attached to the country that I literally stood in the stern of
                    that ship as we went past Cape St. Jacques and tears were rolling down my face.
                    I went back there just a couple of years ago as a tourist and got to Hanoi which
                    of course I couldn't have gotten to except as a prisoner in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: okay. We were able to, when did that bombing of that
                        waterside restaurant, The Barge, did that happen while you were there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I don't think so. I don't remember, I think I would remember that.
                    Oh, but one thing I do want to include on this note is for several years after I
                    left, '61, I tried to get back to Saigon and I did until the number of troops in
                    the country reached the figure of 100,000. Then I stopped asking to go back
                    because it was no longer a Vietnamese War that I could support, it had become an
                    American War which I could not personally support and so that- (end of tape)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1961 where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I went back to West Africa. I went to Lagos, Nigeria.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Alright, we'll pick it up next time then. Did you say at
                        one point you went hiking with your wife and what did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no this was with Tom Barnes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tom Barnes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Tom Barnes, when we decided, it was decided for us that we couldn't
                    go through the Delta and the peninsula by public transportation as we had hoped
                    because of the guerrilla activity so we went North into the Hill country and
                    drove the Volkswagen up the footpath to a Montagnard village where we left the
                    car, hired some people to carry our equipment, because we were going to be
                    camping to the next village and we worked our way around the hills for about a
                    week and made a circle and got back to the Volkswagen and this was my only real
                    contact with the people other than the lowland Vietnamese and they couldn't have
                    been more gracious and accepting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for the division between the lowland
                        Vietnamese and the Montagnards?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Not when I was traveling there because we had a Vietnamese armed
                    guard with us, but he was very, he was courteous and circumspect in his duties,
                    but everything else we heard was that the lowlanders, the Vietnamese were
                    contemptuous of the “primitives” in the hills. We found them gracious and very,
                    very open. Now we're up in the hills and the streams there are pretty cold. When
                    we would come to a stream, our porters would get a bar of soap and take off
                    their clothes and jump into the water. [Laughter]. And so Tom and I got into the
                    habit and we took off our clothes and jumped in after them which was just as
                    well because that was the only occasion we had to bathe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that point had we put special forces in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no, no. We were talking. The embassy staff were working on the
                    anti-insurgency plan. That was in development while I was there in my last 6
                    months or so and everybody was contributing to it actually. Hansbacker of USIA
                    had an important input and everybody got a piece of that one. And that was the
                    anti-insurgency plan which involved bringing the green berets in for medical
                    assistance and things like that, to win the hearts and minds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, again we'll pick this up in 1961 when you're off to
                        Lagos.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Horrible. [Laughter].</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is the 14th of August, 2003 and 1961 you're going to
                        Nigeria. You were there from 1961 until when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I was there just one year. But before we get into that, on
                    reflection there's a couple of things we touched on when we last met, I think
                    that could use some expansion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Great.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I remember you asking me what was my interest in joining the Foreign
                    Service. You know I got home, I gave you a glib answer about them never having
                    given me a 3-day pass when I was in Europe. Simply, that was an element. But
                    there were other things, I can remember, in the 30's being aware that there was
                    a world out there. My earliest international recollection as a child was the
                    attack on the American gunboat Panaj in China.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: About 1936 or something like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, well about the same time the Spanish Civil War broke out and I
                    can remember being very interested in that. Actually, on occasion fantasizing
                    about if I were enough to join the international brigade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: So, I guess I was a pre-adolescent, premature anti-fascist in the
                    30's. But there was also a very important thing that happened when I was in
                    college. I read a book called an American in India by a noted Negro historian
                    named Saunders Redding. And that was probably the last thing that triggered me
                    because I was attracted to the idea that here was somebody doing an interesting
                    job; it was a record of his year in India as a Fulbright scholar.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wouldn't have been a Fulbright, because Fulbright came
                        later ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, but that sort of thing. He was out there on a government grant
                    in India. And he was somebody doing something interesting in an interesting
                    situation, meeting interesting people as an American. At home, he would have
                    been a Negro, period. Abroad he was an American and that intrigued me and
                    certainly that was an element in attracting me to the Foreign Service. Many
                    years later in West Africa, I met Doctor Redding and was able to tell him that
                    he was responsible for where I was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How interesting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: At that point, I was in Nigeria and I wasn't very happy about being
                    in Nigeria so the total irony was I could have told him “It's your fault that
                    I'm here.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Something like you son of a bitch. [Laughter].</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no. I was really grateful and delighted that I had the
                    opportunity to meet him. The other thing that I wanted to bring up was I
                    remember making a remark that I have always, mostly, lived my life in a racially
                    integrated environment, but we have talked about my parents. That was just a
                    small part of the world. The danger of beating the subject to death, but I think
                    I ought to expand it beyond, sincerely beyond my immediate parent, my immediate
                    family. There was my mother's brother, Walter who was English, born in American
                    soil. He was married twice. He was married the first time to a Cuban woman of
                    color by whom he had two daughters. Oh, incidentally the Cuban's father was a
                    Syrian. His two daughters, my cousin's, each of them married three times. For
                    each of them, one of the three husbands was white. One was a doctor and the
                    other was a wholesale butcher. On the other side of the family, my father's
                    brother, Godfrey, his daughter, Betty, had three children. Betty was married to
                    a man whose father was an English doctor married to a Trinidadian woman of
                    color. He and my cousin Betty had three children. One, the son married the white
                    daughter of a congregational minister in New England, I forget where,
                    Connecticut or Massachusetts. The other daughter is married to a Jewish fellow
                    of Russian background. And my uncle Walter on my mother's side was married
                    twice. The first wife was a Cuban woman of color. His second wife was a Jewish
                    woman of Russian ancestry, totally removed from the other two sides of the
                    family, but a typical New York experience. Walter and his second wife had one
                    child, a boy who was raised as an Episcopalian and he married a girl from an
                    Italian family in Connecticut. And I think, I think that covers it. The only
                    thing is I'll expect to be in Prague in a few weeks and I'm looking forward to
                    seeing Betty's son there, where he's been working for an American firm. And that
                    catches me up on two things that I wasn't very interested in dwelling on, race
                    and my family, but I thought since it came up I would expand it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I think it's very interesting. Also, too, I think
                        you're reflecting the Caribbean culture which was much more from what I
                        gather was less caught up in mixing or not mixing or anything else and also
                        people who came out of, I mean you know we have the example right now of our
                        Secretary of State, Colin Powell who seem to come out with much more
                        confidence and those who sort of rose in the ranks with, were native born
                        Americans.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: So this might really be more of interest to a sociologist or a social
                    psychologist than a Foreign Affairs narrative. Okay. So I got rid of that and we
                    were talking about Lagos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, you were there for a year, about a year '61 to
                        '62.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: '61 to '62, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I went there as the Ambassador staff aide. Oh, wait, how did I get to
                    Lagos? While I was in Saigon, which obviously I enjoyed hugely, they called for
                    volunteers for the posts that they were opening up in Africa. This was ... I
                    think '60 was the big independence and there was our original plan, what I
                    understand talking to people who have come out from State, was to have embassy
                    in Abidjan and Dakar covering the hinter lands, but we suddenly became
                    interested in accumulating UN votes to keep China out and so we started opening
                    up in all these obscure places and they called for volunteers. So I volunteered,
                    expecting to go to one of the former French territories in the interior of
                    Equatorial Africa or West Africa. They sent me instead to Lagos. That was a bit
                    of a disappointment because I had just come out of two French colonial posts and
                    I figured another was natural. So that was a disappointment but the job was
                    Staff Aide and there wasn't a hell of a lot to do as staff aide. So as I was
                    also, getting to the political section, which at that moment didn't have a heck
                    of a lot to do either, it was just the first year after independence and Joe
                    Bennett was covering it very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: He went on later to be the Assistant Secretary for Africa. Who?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll pick this up later.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Gosh, I remember Joe Palmer. I went to his funeral or I guess his
                    memorial service several years ago. Oh, and then I doubled when the Consular
                    Officer wasn't there. And it was the only of my 11 or 12 posts that I ever
                    curtailed. There is a story in that, too, later on. I was disappointed, it
                    wasn't a post I enjoyed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was Nigeria like when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, it was the first year after independence, '61. There were still
                    officers in the bush, they had not become completely Nigerianized. I think I
                    would like it even less today than I did then. The traffic was horrendous. The
                    islands that constitute much of Lagos, because it's an island. Lagos island was
                    joined to the mainland with one bridge, Carter Bridge. I didn't enjoy it. I
                    didn't like it and I didn't particularly care for the people. They're pushy,
                    which probably reflects my being American, Americans are pushy too. And there
                    was a conflict, they weren't as accommodating as some other cultures are. Well,
                    let me jump ahead 30 years, I retired in end of June 1991. In September a phone
                    call comes to the house. I'm not home. My wife answers the phone. And it's
                    CEA/EX asking if Mr. Richardson would be interested in going on TDY to Lagos.
                    [Laughter]. It had my wife rolling on the floor with laughter. I went because I
                    was interested in seeing how the place had changed, would have changed in all
                    those years, since the oil money came in. The biggest change was that there were
                    now 3 bridges connecting the islands to the mainland and the traffic was worse
                    than ever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The political section, the ambassador are really... There
                        really wasn't much of a political movement at the time. Was it more that
                        people were getting ready, just sorting out things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: The people who had been the notable politicals in the last years of
                    the colonial eras, like Mamadou Bello, the Global Voice of the North, were in
                    charge. There hadn't been yet the military coup when I left, but it did not wait
                    very long. There were no disturbances, there was no public demonstrations and
                    street crime was not a problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about social life?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, active social life both with Nigerian and the international
                    community. To go back to this question of street crime because I was conscious
                    of the difference having returned what 30 years later, '61-'91. We did things
                    like an Englishman and I made a home movie and we needed a boat for it and there
                    was a stranded fishing boat on a beach by Badugery near the Dahomey boarder.
                    With our wives, we didn't hesitate to go out there and sleep on the beach at
                    night so we would have a full day of sunlight the next day. That would be
                    unthinkable today. After parties a couple of times, we went out, a few of us
                    went out to the beach in Lagos to watch the sun come up. Unthinkable today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then. When you curtail. What do they do to you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I mean I didn't say I'm not going back. See I was interested in
                    getting an assignment back to a French area. I should tell you why I was able to
                    do this. I went on direct transfer from Saigon to Lagos and orders said do not
                    pass by the United States, do not take leave. I'd been in Saigon almost two
                    years. I was staff aid to the Ambassador those last 9 or 10 months, working 7
                    days a week. Wound up working even more those last weeks, sending off one
                    ambassador, breaking in the new ambassador's aide, and organizing the reception
                    for the Vice President. I was tired and Ambassador Durbrow suggested, “Since you
                    won't take leave en route, why don't you sail to Lagos by ship?” So I went on
                    the S.S. Cambodge from Saigon to Marseilles, three weeks. That was the best
                    leave I've ever had of my life. I arrived in France refreshed. I left my wife
                    behind in Saigon. She was flying, paralleling my trip, but sightseeing. The
                    agency had said there was no room and I would have to share the cabin. Well, I
                    ended up not having to share the cabin, but anyway she was content to parallel.
                    So I was in Marseilles, full of energy, refreshed, relaxed, let's go let's do
                    things, I said. My wife had gotten deadly ill in India and she was all washed
                    out so our conditions were just the reverse of what they had been when I kissed
                    her good-bye in Saigon.</p>
                <p>Okay, so having gone to Lagos on a direct transfer, I was eligible for home leave
                    after a year. I came back here to Washington and I went around trying to promote
                    an assignment in the Maghreb, that is to say Tunisia, Algeria, Morocco. I was
                    particularly keen on Algeria because flying one night out of Kano, Nigeria. We
                    went across the Sahara and passed over Algiers in the dark, and its great
                    harbor. There are roads around the lights like three strings of pearls, that's
                    what they look like, the lights, the streetlights around the harbor. I fell in
                    love with the place from 10,000 feet up. [Laughter]. And I wanted to get there.
                    Well, PER remembered that I was interested in it. So I was home, at my in-laws
                    and the phone rings and Jeff Frederick is on the phone and he said Cy, we
                    remembered that you wanted a French-speaking post. Well, I hadn't asked for a
                    French-speaking post, I asked for something in the Maghreb. Well, he had
                    conveniently forgot that and he said so I think you'll be pleased to know you
                    don't have to go back to Lagos, you're going to Niamey, which was not the
                    Maghreb. Okay so I had shipped my Volkswagen from Saigon to Lagos and had driven
                    it there for a year. I went back to Lagos, got in my car, and drove to
                    Niamey.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Niamey being the capital of ... ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Niger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Niger.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Nigeria's northern neighbor. Do you want to hear about Niger?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, absolutely! You were probably in Niger from '62 to
                        ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: '65.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Three years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, it would have been late '62 to March of '65.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, 2 and ? years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. Yes, I had been in Dakar which is on the edge of the Sahara, but
                    still you can get some green. You have to drive out of town to get to the
                    desert. I'd been in Lagos, I'd been in Saigon, these are, you know, lush with
                    green. They are moist and green and lush. I drive in from Lagos and the country
                    is getting drier and drier as I go in and then I arrive in Niamey and I had
                    never seen anything as dry as that in my life, having no familiarity with the
                    American Southwest. I went into a deep funk and my wife who had been there
                    several years before when she traveled with my secretary was exclaiming: “Wow,
                    hey, this has changed. It certainly looks a lot better than it did when I was
                    here before!” And I'm thinking what is this woman talking about, I've never seen
                    anything so ghastly in my life. Well, I was in a deep funk for three days,
                    literally, then I threw it off and made more friends there than at any of my
                    posts except maybe Paris and Saigon. What I did there, I think I was called the
                    FSO general, I did everything. I was the only junior officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, do you remember who the ambassador was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. The last one was, I'll work backwards, the last one was Robert
                    Ryan, who had been Admin. Counselor in Paris. And his predecessor was a noted,
                    by this time I guess we were African-American, Academic, named Mercer Cook, who
                    later was ambassador in Senegal, so those were my ambassadors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now, what was the sort of the political situation,
                        economic situation in Niger?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well there really wasn't much. Exports to the United States consisted
                    of a small quantity of very fine goatskin so my commercial work was not very
                    heavy. There was one party and on the political side the guys who the French had
                    been bringing along during the last years of the colonial period, they were in
                    position and the French were there as their advisors so they simply switched
                    roles, switched offices. Now the French were still very important and very
                    jealous of their position and viewed us, so I thought in Niger than when I was
                    in Dakar, with less suspicion of our intentions because I think we'd made it
                    clear by that time that we were quite content in letting them run the show. We
                    weren't interested in taking over their empire. So there was a more relaxed
                    atmosphere.</p>
                <p>But they were still covering the gap in the budget and still had advisors at
                    every minister's elbow. I'll give you an instance: I, this is also sociological.
                    My wife and I were at the swimming pool which was operated by the French Army as
                    was the hospital. There was a Colonel Bremer who was in charge of the hospital.
                    One day, across the pool, I could see a Frenchwoman with her two children, who
                    obviously had an African father. There were a whole bunch of Frenchwomen and
                    their children on that side, but it was as if there was a “cordon sanitaire”
                    around this woman. No one was talking to her, they were nattering among
                    themselves but no one talked to this woman, and no one came any closer than like
                    the wall there ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: About 3 or 4 feet.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, so this “cordon sanitaire” around her and none of the children
                    were playing with her children. I got a little annoyed at that and said to my
                    wife, “Why don't you go over and talk to her? No one is talking to her.” So my
                    wife went in the water, came out on the other side and said a couple of words to
                    her and the woman looked so happy to have somebody talk to her and in no time at
                    all the children were climbing all over my wife's lap. Well, it turned out this
                    woman was a neighbor on the next street and her husband was in the Office of the
                    Budget, which was fine because for some reason that year I was responsible for
                    reporting on the budget, so we became friends. We exchanged dinners, you know.
                    And I told him I was interested ithe budget so he took me in one day to meet the
                    “Director of the Budget Nationale” who didn't have a clue as to what the budget
                    was all about. You know, I chatted with him for a little while and I said, “I
                    see, I see.” He says, it's all here. It's all in the budget, it couldn't be more
                    clear. I explained this to my friend and he says “I bet you need a little more
                    information.” My friend, this man whose wife, my wife had befriended.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say your friend took you down...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes he took me down the hall to this cubbyhole where this little
                    Frenchman was sitting who could tell me everything about the budget. So the
                    French were still very, very strong there. I went through 180 degrees. I went
                    from being in the pit of despair the first three days, thinking they must hate
                    me in Washington to positively enjoying the place. And it was, you want me to
                    tell war stories. One of the nicest things that happened to me was a day I spent
                    with the African pharmacist, the name will come to me, it isn't important. He
                    was Dahomian originally and he told me his life story or his story as a boy, and
                    it was, not word for word, but an absolute parallel to this book I had read
                    called “L'Enfant Noir,” about the author, who also came out of a remote village,
                    but he was a bright young boy and somebody recognized that he was bright and saw
                    that he went to school and the big thing was that when he left the schooling
                    that was available to him in his area, he traveled to the capital, to Dakar, to
                    go to high school. Well, this Dahomian, that was the story of his life, too, and
                    the trepidation with which he was leaving the village to go to the big city.
                    That was a thrilling story and he also had an absolutely beautiful daughter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then did you get any official visits from anybody
                        while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, official, we, I know we had an inspection, but not Congress, I
                    don't think congress had yet discovered Niger. But, if I can back up I did have
                    a notable visitor, I was control officer for Vice President Gore's father when
                    he came to Lagos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Senator Gore of Tennessee.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Albert Gore.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Albert Gore. He was a very pleasant, very undemanding gentlemen. He
                    came through for a very short time. So we, I don't remember any notable visitors
                    in Niger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any reflection of the problems that were
                        beginning to develop in Algeria? How far along the independence movement had
                        gotten in Algeria?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, that was past. When I left Niger, I went out of Africa by way
                    of Algeria, driving to Algiers, and this would have been in the first year after
                    independence, so they must have gotten independence in late '63 or '64.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I wasn't sure.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. So, things were fairly tranquil in Algiers, in fact, very
                    tranquil.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did, in Niger, was there a tribal situation, so many you
                        know the North is more Muslim and the South, course Niger is right in
                        ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, Niger is all Muslim so its, your Peule, Fulani, and other
                    divisions like that, but there's nothing divided on religious grounds. There
                    were all Muslims. Diore was the president. He had represented Niger in the
                    colonial legislature before independence. Diore used to come to Dakar regularly.
                    So they all inherited their positions with independence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have much chance to travel around?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, yes. Peace Corps had come in several years before. And you had
                    the people crossing the Sahara going south. This is where they would come out,
                    in Niamey. I met a number of them ... adventurers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But, what was the town or city of Niamey like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, when I would drive my wife to shop on a Saturday morning, I
                    always thought that Tombstone, Arizona must have looked like this in about 1890.
                    And I had the feeling that I should be tying up a horse rather than parking a
                    Volkswagen. My butcher literally had the false front that you see in the Western
                    movies. That was my butcher shop. So there should have been a hitching post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [Laughter]. Did you find that there were, how about social
                        life? Was there much mixing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Not so much with the Nigerians because they were much more reserved,
                    not hostile, not hostile. But, they did not live the way the Europeans and the
                    Americans did. By that time we had air conditioning and things like that. But
                    there were African diplomats from other countries. One of the most amusing and
                    delightful people I knew then was a Malian who was there as a representative of
                    some UN organization. He was very Westernized and I marveled at his sense of
                    humor. Then there was the Charg� d'Affaires of Nigeria, very charming young man.
                    So we had those kinds of ... And who else was there? ... Many Israelis were
                    there, very good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the Soviets, were they doing anything?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, we used to play volleyball with them, and I'm trying to remember
                    where we used to play volleyball with the Soviets. I remember playing volleyball
                    with the Israelis. I don't think, the Soviets weren't represented there, no.
                    Egyptians were there. The Egyptian Ambassador lived in Lagos, but he came up
                    very frequently. I would have him to dinner when he came up. You know, I'm
                    trying to remember because there was a question, where we would play volleyball
                    with the Soviets. It was with the Lebanese compound.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. [Laughter]. Ah, well you were at 12 posts ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Something like that 11 or 12 posts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you left Niger when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: In March, early March 1965, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then what did they do with you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, I was assigned to Paris which was great. I went around telling
                    the French, “I'm going home. I'm going home.” [Laughter]. Well, after so many
                    years of learning French in the boonies, it was like going home because many of
                    the people I had met along the way, when they came home, came to Paris so I got
                    to see them and continue the relationship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you were in Paris from '65 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: '68.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '68, what were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I was, that was my first full-time Consular job, I worked exclusively
                    in American services for three years. And that was a very satisfactory ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did the American services consist of in those
                        days?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I guess it's kind of, anything pertaining to the welfare and
                    protection of American citizens as well as citizenship and notarials. There were
                    all kinds of situations where their welfare is in jeopardy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, tell me about how, do you have any good counselor
                        stories.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: [Laughter]. Yes, I don't know, do you want to hear how I got to
                    Paris?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sure.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Because that takes some doing. In fact, I don't know if it has a
                    place here, it was the single greatest adventure of my 35-year career.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sure.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, in my second year or sometime in my first year in Niamey, I had
                    hepatitis. And, so you get desperately ill, you lose weight. So I recovered and
                    went back to work, but after a year I was very tired ... really fatigued. And,
                    there was no question I was going to go somewhere to rest. But the idea of going
                    to Europe or the Mediterranean to sit in a resort didn't interest me much.
                    Somebody mentioned that there were passenger-freight ships that go down the
                    coast, turn around at Pointe Noire and go back up the coast. That would be a
                    week, 10 days trip. That was perfect. So I did that. It was on a ship called the
                    Jean Mermoz, the famous flyer. Okay, so I take the trip, because my liver was
                    tired. Of course, I'm on a French ship, they served wine twice a day [Laughter]
                    and good food. So, I came back, stopped off to visit some bachelor friends in
                    Cotonou and I returned to Niamey, not at all refreshed. I checked back into the
                    hospital [Laughter] where I stayed for the better part of a week. On the ship,
                    they had printed menu cards, lunch and dinner and when I had something, a new
                    dish, that I particularly enjoyed, I saved the card, checking the item on the
                    menu and presented these cards to my wife when we got to Paris. Well, she worked
                    her way through all of those cards. And the last dish was something called
                    poulet chaud froid, which is an elegant chicken dish covered in aspic with
                    truffle diamonds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, boy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: She hasn't forgiven me for this to this day. Well, she said to me the
                    day before we were having guests over, “You know, this dish is a hell of a lot
                    of work. What should I do for a first course?” I reminded her that a friend had
                    come back from Russia and had brought us a tin of caviar, I think like 500 grams
                    of caviar. It was big. And I said so why don't you put out the caviar and we'll
                    nibble on that and since that probably won't be enough, get a side of smoked
                    salmon. So everything came together, it was very elegant, very nice. And the
                    guests enjoyed it. But, when she cleared away the remains of the caviar and the
                    smoked salmon and brought her hard work, her poulet chaud froid, they groaned.
                    They'd eaten so much caviar and smoked salmon. [Laughter].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, [Laughter].</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: To this day she has not forgiven me. She reminds me, “I can still
                    hear those groans.” Well, go back to the, so this was on the recipes from the
                    Jean Mermoz. Well, having recalled the lovely time I had the Mermoz, I had
                    gotten a passage on the Cambodge to take us from Dakar to Marseilles. In
                    Marseilles I was going to catch the Constitution or the Independence to go to
                    New York. Well, in discussing the Paris assignment with my wife, I happened to
                    break out a map and she looked at me and said, “Look, there's Paris. Paris is
                    just straight north from Niamey, why don't we drive there?” I said No. I had my
                    heart set on this ship which I knew from an earlier trip. I said, “Don't be
                    absurd. We can't do that.” And I went to bed. Well, during the night, I was
                    tossing around at 2:00, I woke up and thinking about this, I said to myself, you
                    know, this woman has gone through a lot including gunfire, she's lived in all of
                    these hell holes, and never asked for so much as a lace handkerchief. If she
                    wants to drive across the Sahara, we'll do it. So I got up the next morning and
                    she was making breakfast and I said we're going to do it. We're going to do
                    what? I said, we're going to drive north out of Niamey. And we did. It was our
                    greatest adventure. It took me several weeks to do it, but we left Niamey and
                    came out in Algiers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a road or what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There was a trail in the sand. It consisted of the tracks of vehicles
                    that had crossed earlier in the year</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A trail.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: A trail, yes. You don't pick up a road, paved road until you're well,
                    well into Algiers. I forget what town.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are there places to get gas and ... ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, not for 700 kilometers between Agadesin, Niger and Tamanrassat in
                    southern Algeria. We had to carry our gas. During the French time, there was a
                    place right on the border between the two territories where the French did truck
                    in gas, a considerable effort because they're bringing it over hundreds of miles
                    where there's no roads. So it must have cost a fortune. Anyway, by the time I
                    got there, there was no town there and there were just two pumps like the legs
                    of those of Ozymandias. I think I photographed them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this Volkswagen didn't use up a lot of gas as ...
                        ?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, but you can't weigh down the vehicle with gas and water and so
                    forth because then you'd never get out of the sand so what you do, is you find a
                    truck that's going that way, because there is commerce, there is commerce. I got
                    together with a man who was transporting dried tomatoes, sun dried tomatoes, to
                    northern Algeria and he carried my excess baggage, clothing, suitcases, and my
                    extra gasoline, etc. I just filled up the tank and gave the other stuff to him.
                    The one thing I carried was a goatskin of water. I was going to rendezvous with
                    him every evening and then I could fill my gas tank and we always tried to
                    rendezvous at a well to fill the water skins. After Tamanrassat, the places are
                    close enough together that we can go without the truck. But, for that section,
                    whicmust be 400 miles, 300 kilometers or so, there is no gas. But, the striking
                    thing about that trip and this is what pains me so much when I read what the
                    Algerians were doing to each other and to foreigners, like the Italian priest
                    killed several years ago is that out there people were really helpful to each
                    other. We encountered numerous instances of human solidarity. You take too long
                    to get out of the sand, and somebody would come clomping up on a camel to see if
                    they could help. We didn't want any help because my wife and I had worked out
                    the routine so that if we got stuck in the sand, we could be out in 25 minutes
                    if nobody turns up to help us. If someone turns up to help us, it takes twice as
                    long.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Well, I take it you weren't upset by Bedouin or
                        something like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: As I said, I found so many instances of human solidarity. The first
                    day, we drove about 100 kilometers until we stopped at the well where the truck
                    driver had said, “I will meet you tomorrow.” Well, he didn't turn up for three
                    days. Where did we sleep? We just slept out, put things on the sand and slept on
                    the ground. I did have a camp bed for my wife, and a bed for myself. Well, in
                    the morning, there was this little Arab who observed us and came to the
                    conclusion that these were two greenhorns that he better take in hand or they're
                    not going to survive out there. So he came over, little guy and our common
                    language was French, of which he spoke a little, enough though. He asked me, “Do
                    you have rope?” And I said, “Yes, I had rope.” “Do you have a blanket,” I said
                    yes, I have a blanket. I was curious, why is he asking me this? He said, “Show
                    me, show me.” So I showed him and he showed me how to make a shelter against the
                    sun, which I would never have had a clue. There was the remains of a small mud
                    house and he showed me how to use that broken down wall and my car and create a
                    shelter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [Laughter].</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. And my wife said to him in the second day that the truck did not
                    show up and she expressed concern that, you know, I don't know how long it's
                    going to take him to get here, I wonder if our food will last. Our food
                    consisted of cans of sardines in tomato sauce. To this day I can't eat it. Well,
                    he's got nothing, he's camping by the side of the road waiting for his son to
                    show up. I don't know why he was there but he was waiting for his son to turn up
                    with a camel or something. He comes over and brings my wife some of the couscous
                    that he had and offers it to her. And this is just the first illustration of
                    this human solidarity I found out there in the desert.</p>
                <p>Another instance, I think it was in In Salah. We arrived in this place and I'm
                    out of money, I'm out of local Algerian money. But we want to eat so I go to
                    this place and I order. I had French money and I had Moroccan money and I have
                    dollars, so I'm not worried. So I go to this little restaurant in this town and
                    this is still the Sahara, you've got towns in it and I ordered a simple meal.
                    Maybe the whole thing came to a dollar and a half for the two of us and I tried
                    to pay him with foreign currency and he won't have any of it. No, he said I
                    won't have anything to do with foreign money, you come back and pay me when you
                    get dirham, if that's the currency. And, so okay, so I'm leaving after lunch and
                    he comes after me as I'm going out the door and in his double negative he says
                    and “Do not, not come back because you do not have money.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ah, oh, boy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But, and there were all kinds of instances like that. I don't know
                    how much of this you want to hear because there were just a whole host of
                    adventures. One day, this was right in the middle of the desert, my battery is
                    no longer charging, I can tell the warning light has come on. But it turned it
                    was the bearing, the generator had worn out and it wasn't charging the battery
                    while the engine was running so I had to keep the engine running. Well, I'm also
                    into a sand storm and just as I'm kind of despairing, I got two things wrong: If
                    I stopped the car, I probably won't be able to get it started again, or may not
                    be able to. I'll be draining the battery. Two, I am in a sand storm. Well, like
                    an unbelievable mirage, I suddenly find myself on a black top road, an asphalt
                    road. This is weird. So what do I do, I turn left, I was about to cross it, I
                    turn left because that was still the direction, roughly the direction I wanted
                    to go and I follow it and eventually I come to a building and I go in and what
                    is it? A bunch of French soldiers. There, that was the area where the French,
                    special weapons testing was conducted down that road.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, the soldiers, they said you can't stay here. I said but what
                    are we going to do. They said stay on the paved road and several kilometers down
                    you're going to find a post of the gendarmerie. And they will let you stay, and
                    they did. We went down there, the gendarmes had no problem at all giving us
                    refuge from the sand storm and they greeted me with a bottle of red wine and a
                    big loaf of bread and gave me a room.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You know, I find it incredible that going across the
                        Sahara, one of our Foreign Service officers went with his wife, he died, do
                        you remember that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She had to bring his body out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. I can believe it. But, I don't remember hearing that story.
                    Well, I did this 30 years ago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that was..</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Maybe that's more recent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, not really because I knew Russell something or other,
                        last name is Russell. Anyway ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well there are routes that are more difficult than the one I
                    took.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, the station, the refuge with the French police for a couple of
                    days. And other travelers came in and before we were done, we got up a table of
                    bridge. In Northern Algeria we recovered our baggage from the truck driver and
                    continued on to Casablanca where we took a plane home for leave.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. [Laughter]. Well, finally you get yourself to
                        France.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To Paris. What are you doing there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I'm doing welfare and protection of which about, almost half of it
                    was exclusively in death and estates. Let's see, yes, I would guess I did Death
                    and Estates for about 14 months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well an awful lot of American expatriates and tourists
                        would come there and die.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, well, the resident expatriates were no problem. If they're
                    working for a company, the company looks after them. It's the tourists and the
                    walking wounded, some of whose families pay them to stay out of the U.S.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Remittance men. Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. Because they're too much trouble, it's less of a strain for the
                    family to have them abroad than home.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But all kinds of misfortunes can befall a person. If you give me a
                    couple of million Americans going through, you're going to get all kinds of
                    problems. So it was a very active and interesting time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. I'm sure it was.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And very satisfying.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about people who were in trouble with the police? How
                        did the French police treat them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Correctly, correctly. I never had any instance where the, where
                    people would claim that they were abused. The women were looked after in
                    institutions where there were nuns. And the men were in ordinary prisons. Maybe
                    the food wasn't very good, you wouldn't expect it to be. But I had no complaints
                    about physical or even mental abuse.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from '65 to '68, which was sort of the
                        beginning of the era of the college students who went off and had their
                        wanderjahr or vacations and drugs and you know hashish and all were just
                        coming in ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, if they were in France they were only transiting on their way to
                    India and Nepal. I saw much more of them when I got to South America. That was
                    the regular trek for them going down the spine of South America. There weren't
                    any great problems in Paris. Drugs, there were. Mostly marijuana, I had some
                    musicians who were picked up for marijuana and we had an active anti-drug outfit
                    in the embassy. One of the several predecessors of the current DEA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the consul general when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Perry Cully.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Perry Cully was a social animal, wasn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, yes. He didn't have much to do with consular work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I was going to say, I suspected that. He was, he
                        inspected me in Belgrade ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: In what year did you go?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, about '63 or something like that ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, that's how he got to Paris, when he was an inspector he'd seen
                    the home occupied by the consul general in Paris and he says “that's for
                    me.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also he got there and he never left, I guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: He didn't. He divorced Mrs. Cully and married an English nurse at the
                    American hospital, so he may still be there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't know. How did you find social life there at the
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Fine, fine. I was comfortable. Well, that wasn't nearly as important,
                    the social life, I had French friends coming in from the colonies so I didn't
                    make many, yes there were a couple of lawyers, people I had met on business that
                    I'd have to dinner or have a drink with. I became friendly with a man in one of
                    their intelligence services and we used to meet for coffee and drinks until he
                    told me that he'd been instructed by his superiors to break off our
                    relationship. Either they thought I was trying to penetrate them or they decided
                    I wasn't worth cultivating. [Laughter]. I like to think it was the latter, not
                    the former. [Laughter]. And there was a good bunch of Americans both in the
                    embassy and among the expats. I recently did a WAE TDY in Haiti and the woman I
                    was working for there is the daughter of somebody who was in the ambassador's
                    office when I was there. Barrett was staff aide. Social relations were no
                    problem. The real big thing for me there was not the social but the cultural
                    life. I'd been in the boondocks, at this point, for nine years. The only music
                    and opera I had seen was Chinese opera in Saigon and a German string orchestra.
                    They brought out a string orchestra and that was it. For 9 years I had depended
                    on recorded music and it was great. And movies, because Paris is a great town
                    for films.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: So we went to the theater, we went to concerts, we went to all kinds
                    of things of that sort only three weeks of the month because one week every four
                    weeks I was duty officer in the Welfare and Protection Section. It was so active
                    you didn't have one consular duty officer. Passports, Welfare and Protection,
                    and Visas each had it's own and that was busy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about when people came and they were in trouble and
                        the place didn't have a consular post or something? In some distance, did
                        you have trouble with that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, the police were good about notifying us when people ended up in
                    hospitals, automobile accidents miles away. If it was within reasonable
                    distance, we'd go see them. We didn't have any problem and we had so many of
                    them that managed to get into difficulty in Paris or in the immediate environs
                    of Paris ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, if you're going to get in trouble ...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And we had a lot of consulates in France. At this time we have none
                    except Strasbourg today. But in those days we had Lyon, Strasbourg, Bordeaux,
                    and Nice, so the country was well covered. I don't know what they would do now.
                    But you were asking me about the kinds of trouble people get into. Well, my
                    first day, I had just set up shop in Paris, in Welfare and Protection and this
                    was in the days before everybody ended up in cubby holes. I had a proper office
                    with a window and a beautiful tree outside the window in the garden. One of the
                    clerks came in saying there's an American gentlemen outside who's very anxious
                    to speak to somebody, to speak to an officer. So I said, send him in. My first
                    client!</p>
                <p>So he comes in, a well set up, trim waisted man in his upper thirties, early
                    forties. Neat double-breasted blue gray suit. Obviously agitated, he opened this
                    conversation with me with “I got no satisfaction from that woman. I got no
                    satisfaction from the police, but I damn well mean to get satisfaction from the
                    American Embassy.” And that was his opener! So I said: Fine, fine, have a seat,
                    sit down. What was his story? He had hired a “lady of the evening” the night
                    before, had been unable to perform and had asked for a refund. [Laughter]. Of
                    course she did not oblige him, so in high dungeon or whatever, he goes to the
                    local police station about 2:00 in the morning and complains to the night
                    sergeant. The night sergeant listens very sympathetically and says ah, Monsieur,
                    that is really abominable. I'm going to ask my colleagues to come out and hear
                    what the terrible things that happen to tourists in our glorious city of Paris.
                    He goes in, wakes up the night crew and the emergency staff, and brings them to
                    hear the story. He comes up and says Monsieur, tell my colleagues the terrible
                    things that have happened to you. He tells the story and they all burst into
                    laughter. So he is very T'd off when he comes to see me. What am I going to do?
                    This is my first client in Paris. It was never so amusing again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I let him talk himself out. He wanted someone to listen to him and
                    not laugh. I was able to do that. [Laughter]. I was the first person who was
                    able to hear his story and not laugh. And that's the satisfaction he got. He had
                    said he meant to get satisfaction from the American Embassy. And that was the
                    beginning. There were all kinds of foolish things, but lot of real tragedies,
                    too. Now, one, Texas. There's a city in Texas called Paris.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I'm in Paris. There is a group of high school students, now it wasn't
                    for lack of adult supervision, there were maybe 14 students. I think they had
                    four adults with them. That, I would say was good coverage. They are in one of
                    these hotels with the old fashioned caged elevators.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And this kid from Paris, Texas wants to know, where's the elevator?
                    You know he's rung the bell and it's not there so he looks over the wall of the
                    cage at the very moment the elevator descends. It decapitates him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, how awful.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And I have to inform his grandfather. I think the boy was an orphan.
                    I had to call his grandfather in Paris, Texas. No, I didn't have to call him.
                    The grandfather called me. First I went down to the station house, where I
                    interpreted for the police and the guardians. The kids were wiped out,
                    desolated. And then, my time 2:00, they notified the grandfather, then the
                    grandfather called me from Paris, Texas to discuss arrangements for shipping the
                    body in and so forth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I got no more sleep that night.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. That's one of the awful things that happened. At
                        that time, particularly in Paris, the French had the reputation, it's
                        changed quite a bit, but had the reputation for being rather abrupt and not
                        very pleasant to deal with, with Americans or foreigners...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I'll tell you about that because I certainly had lots of
                    experience with the Parisians. Metropolitan French I would know best. I'll tell
                    you, my wife encountered any number of tourists complaining about the French
                    being rude and brusque and her standard line was: “Stand still for a minute and
                    observe the way they treat each other; it's not anti-American. That's the
                    Parisian. He is impatient. He has little tolerance for even his own kind and God
                    help you if you don't speak French. You're just so much worse off.” But there
                    were times when there was, particularly amongst the intellectuals, strong
                    feelings against things that represent American values. They'd call it the
                    Coca-Colazation of France and of Europe, but at that time, the government,
                    because we had supported them in Indochina and Africa, or they needed us, the
                    government to government relations were fine, but the relations further down the
                    line were lousy. At one event in Normandy where I represented the embassy, I was
                    heartily booed by the crowd over the Vietnam War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there during the May and June of '68, I
                        guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. They had the general strike.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. I mean this is very exciting. How, what were you
                        observing in this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I was observing a degree of courtesy and cooperation among the
                    Parisians that I had not encountered before. I saw people with gasoline stopping
                    their autos and taking on people walking. I don't know if they took money. I
                    know I got into the habit and I would offer people a ride if they were going my
                    way. I'd offer them rides and sometimes somebody would offer to give me a few
                    frames and I would say, “No, no. Let's go have a coffee or buy me a beer or
                    something like that.” One day, there was a woman with a cane, because I think
                    she had difficulties with a prosthetic device. I think that was one of her legs.
                    She was walking with difficulty up a hill in Montmartre and I pulled up to ask
                    her if I could her a lift. And she was very grateful, she got in and it turned
                    out she was walking up this hill to visit her husband in the hospital.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, boy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And I saw Parisians doing that, but of course there was no traffic,
                    so there was none of the usual road rage and impatience. There was an incident
                    though, I remember where an Algerian pompier, a gas station attendant, was
                    killed because people got nervous and excited when the gas ran out. And another
                    incident of violence, some protestors down in Lyon rolled a truckload of heavy
                    stones and things like that down a hill, and it killed a policeman. I really
                    thought “it was going to hit the fan now.” But somehow they got through it.
                    There were many demonstrations in Paris. One night my wife and I didn't get to
                    the theater because we ran into a wall of tear gas and couldn't get through.
                    But, that was an exciting time and much of my work consisted of finding people,
                    tourists, particularly students, and trying to reassure their parents that they
                    were fine. And I said for “God sakes. Write home.” They said but there's no post
                    office. Well, call them on the telephone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have problems with students getting out there and
                        joining the protests because this was many a student movement.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, yes, but not much. Most were simple tourist bystanders.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was wondering whether they were getting picked up along
                        with...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: You know sometimes the cops would go through and they would surround
                    a neighborhood or an area and make a complete sweep of everybody. And so the
                    Americans caught up in it would complain they pushed us around, but they didn't
                    really keep them in there. When they found that they were foreigners and they
                    didn't have anything on them, they let them go. But, they'd hold them for a
                    while, while they went through their papers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Chuck [Chet] Bohlen. He was the ambassador all the time I was
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was always a thorough professional.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. But, I saw him just once when I made a call on arriving.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the French staff in the counselor
                        section?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There were those hired right after the war, a few of them were still
                    working. They had more middle class backgrounds than working class because right
                    after the war, they were the ones who spoke English and they were from a
                    different class and I had, we had one of those left. I'll tell you a story about
                    her. One of the things that I was always doing in Death and Estates was
                    collecting the personal effects of the deceased, packing them up and sending
                    them off to the family. And she was very impressed with the packages, with my
                    packing, how well, how neatly they were done. And she remarked on this to one of
                    the other Vice Consuls and one Vice Consul of them said to her, “Well, it's very
                    possible that he did this before the Foreign Service, maybe he was a shipping
                    clerk or wrapped packages in a department store.” And that was a very wild ...
                    that was absolutely absurd, she thought. [Laughter]. Diplomats don't do things
                    like that. So we had one person like that. The others were good solid people,
                    but they were not of that class. One of them, who I was closest to, I could say
                    she trained me in Welfare and Protection work, like any second lieutenant gets
                    trained by a good sergeant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, oh, absolutely.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. I stayed in touch with her for many years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then in '68 you left to go there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I went back to Africa. I went to Accra in Ghana.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Was this by request or ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ICHARDSON: No, that was an instance I didn't volunteer, that was what came up and
                    it was very good. It was very good. I ended up spending 3 years there ... what
                    was a 2 year assignment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would be '68 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: '71.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '71.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. I enjoyed the tour because of the people. I still find it to be
                    true, because I meet a lot of Ghanaians here in Washington, they were, without a
                    doubt, among the most gracious people I have ever worked among or worked with.
                    They're delightful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in Ghana?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: In Ghana, very small consular section, I was it. It was a light
                    consular workload. I had two employees, two national staff, that's all. This was
                    before visas became a problem in West Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: McIlhenny.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where stood the government of Ghana when you were there
                        ... things fluctuate ... ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: By the time I got there, was it Nkrumah?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Nkrumah? Was he still there? No.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No. It was the military police coup, which evidently didn't cause us
                    any problem and there didn't seem to be any serious abuse of human rights and
                    there wasn't evidently much to steal so it may really have been typically
                    political reasons for getting rid of Nkrumah.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, was it, you were saying the Ghanaians were an easy
                        people to work with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Gracious, really. I've never served or worked with people more
                    gracious. For me, they're an outstanding quality of the time I spent with them.
                    And I was there ... I had originally gone for 2 years, and I spent a third. I
                    spent a third, you want to know why I spent the third?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: When I went to Ghana, I went there first and my wife followed me by
                    about a month or so because she had gone to Tunisia and Libya because we had
                    both gotten very interested in French North Africa and Libya. We had read a book
                    on North Africa written by one of the Sitwells. He'd written a book called
                    Mauritania. Not what we call Mauritania today, but evidently in the Roman times,
                    it was much of the Northern tier and we had read about, in his book, about it
                    was a trip in that area. And we'd gotten interested in it, particularly in
                    reference to some underground dwellers called Troglodytes. I couldn't go because
                    I had to get to post. You know, you should have arrived yesterday. My wife
                    stopped off, and when I met her at the airport in Accra, almost her first words
                    to me were, “I will never set foot in Libya again unless my plane is shot down.”
                    No problem. There's no chance of me going to Libya so ... well, almost two years
                    later, I get a cable from the department, and guess where they're sending me to
                    ... Tripoli, in Libya.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, boy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Suddenly that conversation comes back to me: “I'm never going to set
                    foot in that country again.” Well, I wasn't all that keen on going there either
                    so I went to my DCM, McFarland and said look at this. And he said, “So.” I said,
                    “I can't take this home.” [Laughter]. He says, “Okay, I'll fix that.” So he got
                    me a third year in Accra, which couldn't have pleased me more.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was the consular ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But, I later met the man who got that assignment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And what did he think of it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I didn't ask him, I didn't want to hear. He might have said he liked
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the consular problems of Ghana?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Very few. Very, very few. There were no visa problem. And the one
                    plane crash I had was a DC-3 put down on a beach somewhere, but the one American
                    on the plane walked away from it. The only other, I don't remember, oh, there
                    was one incident of a group of African-American youngsters who had come out on a
                    charter flight, whole bunch of them, with not too many supervising adults, but
                    enough. They weren't a problem as delinquents or anything like that, but the
                    charter went bust and they were stranded. And so, they were anxious and their
                    parents were anxious and the American woman who was in charge of them was very
                    anxious so that was a problem. But, they finally got some transportation
                    arranged for them. But my DCM was concerned they were demonstrating outside and
                    inside of the embassy. The embassy wasn't one of these fortress things like we
                    have now, this was completely accessible to the street, no physical security,
                    you could, anybody could walk in, walk up the stairs. It was one of those
                    showcases of American architecture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. It looked like a drum.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. And set up on piles. Well, it was a beautiful building, but
                    lousy office space [laughter]. You could, if it's raining, you could not go from
                    one office to another without getting wet. So they were demonstrating and
                    McFarland took them, the whole bunch of them who were demonstrating, got them
                    into cars and took them home and fed them hotdogs and defused the situation. I
                    thought that was very good. But, there were no notable consular problems. The
                    highlights of that tour was a long conversation with Sidney Poitier. He played
                    the young man in, “Guess Whose Coming to Dinner.” Well, Sidney Poitier calls up
                    and asks for an appointment with me. Wow! So, sure he could come in, you know,
                    fix the time. And I'm apprehensive because my idea of what celebrities are, like
                    you know, coming in and making demands because of who they are. This could not
                    have been more different from the way he was. He was one of the sweetest, most
                    gracious people I've ever dealt with of any importance. No, his daughter was
                    marrying or had married a young Ghanaian engineer and he wanted to know what was
                    involved in him getting a visa to come to the United States. And he didn't
                    really make any demands, he actually just wanted to know what's involved. He
                    wasn't demanding any special speedy service or anything of that sort. I would
                    have given him the store. He, oh he, was charming. And also his daughter was
                    beautiful and the young engineer was handsome. They made a beautiful couple. So
                    that was a high point of my consular work in Accra.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [Laughter].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, something else must have happened in three years, but I never
                    had to increase the staff. As a matter of fact, I fired one of the two of them
                    for malfeasance, for work that was so sloppy it had to be deliberate. Anyway, I
                    fired him. So I ended up with one clerk, so you know we weren't very busy,
                    nothing very serious happened. My office was beyond the clerk's office and the
                    public entrance so I heard somebody come in and so I called out to them and I
                    said, “Well the clerk's not here. Come in. What can I do for you?” Not looking,
                    you know, hollering because it was a short distance ... they could hear me. I do
                    this two, three times. Finally in exasperation, I get up and I go to the door
                    and there I'm looking at two deaf people who are talking to each other with
                    their hands. I felt like a horse's rear end. I forget why they wanted to see me.
                    But I felt terrible. [Laughter].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I think this is probably a good place to stop and
                        we'll pick this up again in 1972.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: When I went to Belgium.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So we'll pick it up then. Well, I'm off for the next week,
                        but how about the week after?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, the week after is when I'm leaving for Europe ...</p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is the 6th of October, 2003 and you were mentioning,
                        you met the American movie actor, Sydney Poitier. You might have mentioned
                        this.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I got a call one day and the person identified himself as
                    Sidney Poitier, this was in Ghana. In Accra and asked if he could come in to see
                    me. Well, of course he could come into see me. When would you like to come in?
                    He said his flight leaves tomorrow, 10:00, fine. But, I'm a little concerned
                    because this is a big, high powered guy and I didn't know what he wanted and he
                    might very well be someone difficult to deal with. He turned up and he wasn't at
                    all difficult to deal with. He was one of the most charming, delightful,
                    sweetest person I think I've ever dealt with in the Foreign Service. And what
                    his problem was wasn't a problem, he just wanted information. His daughter,
                    beautiful girl, was marrying a young Ghanaian engineer and he wanted to know
                    what was involved in them getting a visa to go to the United States and that's
                    all it was, but it was a thoroughly delightful, oh 35, 40 minutes I spent with
                    him. [Laughter]. Memorable because I had been apprehensive of what the person
                    was going to be like and he turned out, he charmed me, absolutely. You could
                    tell he is a real gentleman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, 1972, you're off to Belgium. You were in Belgium
                        from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I got there, the last days of '71 and I left in February of '75.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Alright, what was your job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I was head of the Consular section there. It was a stand alone
                    operation so I wasn't in the embassy building or in the chancery. And had,
                    except for the staff meeting, very little contact with the chancery, except when
                    somebody wanted a visa for some V.I.P. [Very Important Person]. I was called to
                    the embassy only twice, once because some Americans were stranded by a bankrupt
                    charter flight and another time when I refused a visa to the personal doctor of
                    the King's sister.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, was it at all complicated for you because you had
                        something like three embassies in Brussels, don't you ... ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. NATO and the European Community, any relations I had with them
                    were social. They did not impinge on my operation at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the main type of work you were doing as Consular
                        Officer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, the main operation of the office, we had modest consular
                    operation. Very little in the way of I.V.s and I had a very competent staff. The
                    biggest part of the operation was in American services because of the military
                    presence there, they were forever registering births. And, as a matter of fact,
                    the army even gave the office a full-time clerk, a military man who came in and
                    assisted in the American services section to deal with the military side of our
                    operation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I had that same thing in Saigon where the army sent
                        us a clerk who was a Harvard graduate, getting his Ph.D. and got drafted so
                        it was a good place to put him, I guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I didn't realize they were drafting graduate students.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, they got them. They got them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Because we got several people, I think they're still in the Senate
                    who got Ph.D.s in those ends [Laughter].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have many problems with arrest cases, seamen,
                        shipping, this type of thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Seamen and shipping, no, because at that time, Antwerp was still open
                    so if any seamen problems came up, Antwerp dealt with them. No, we had lots of
                    Americans, one group insisted on sending Bibles to Muslim countries and their
                    people doing the distribution would get in trouble in various Muslim countries.
                    The headquarters of this outfit was in Brussels and so they'd come in and demand
                    that the U.S. government do something about their people who were under arrest
                    for distributing Bibles. But, the usual, you would get in a place like Brussels,
                    and certainly it was true in Paris. You'd get people who are maintained abroad
                    by their families ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Remittance men and women.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: [Laughter]. Yes and some of them were quite delightful. I had one in
                    Brussels who later turned up in Ecuador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they cause problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no. Sure they caused problems, but no. But no, no serious ones.
                    They weren't violent, they were eccentric. For instance, the one who later
                    turned up in Ecuador had an amusing incident with a Vice Consul working for me
                    who later distinguished herself in Bordeaux, Judy Heiman. She was taking this
                    fellow out to the airport to put him on a plane. We were repatriating him and he
                    was very tall, with a silky gray beard. The carpet at the airport there in
                    Brussels is bright red and he thought it would look splendid if he stretched
                    out, something like Christ on the cross, with his beard. Judy said he was a
                    stunning sight. She had to speak to him in her most schoolmarmish fashion to
                    persuade him to get up and get on that aircraft. [Laughter]. Yes, he later
                    turned up in Ecuador when I was filling in for the Consul General down in
                    Guayaquil. The Consul General had to take his wife up to the hospital in Panama
                    so I went down to fill in for him and I got a report there that there was an
                    American up at the last small port before you cross over into Colombia who was
                    running down the street stark naked. Okay. I heard about him and when he turns
                    up in Guayaquil, he greets me like an old friend. It was this guy from Brussels
                    who was then pleased to give me a photograph of himself because we were such
                    good old friends. So, those were the kinds of things we had, there were no
                    serious problems, I don't think I had any serious, I had people under arrest,
                    but that's routine for most places.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Belgian police give you good access?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Excellent. I had very good relations with the police chief in charge
                    of foreigners. And so I had no problem in terms of cooperation at all. As a
                    matter of fact, you'd say it was an easy tour. There were interesting things.
                    Russians turned up. This was back in the ?70s and Russians turned up demanding
                    to go to the United States. They were registered as refugees and things were
                    moving too slowly for them so they came in, they wanted some action out of the
                    embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any, from the consular point of view, any sort
                        of ripple effect from the fact that for so long Belgium had had the Congo,
                        and Rwanda and Burundi... There were a lot of missionaries down there. Did
                        that have any reflection ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No because at this time, at this point something like at least a
                    decade had passed ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">'61 was essentially when the Congo blew up ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes and by this time they, any things that might have turned up in
                    Brussels as a result of their colonial activities were long since passed and the
                    movement from the Congo, Rwanda and Burundi, the migration seemed not to be
                    very, very active.</p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Things had pretty well settled down.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: In fact, several years later when I visited Brussels I became
                    conscious of the neighborhoods in which sub-Saharan Africans were very well
                    represented.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you, in your work and all, pick up any of the split
                        between the Flemish and the, what was it the Flemish and French ... ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Flemish and the French, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean in Belgium?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, yes, you're very conscious of that even in Brussels where the
                    language is French. When, for instance, when I traveled in the Flemish area, I
                    spoke more English than I spoke French. If I had to ask someone directions or
                    was in any way approached in Flemish, I would speak in English. Half the time
                    they spoke English so there wasn't any problem, but if they spoke no English,
                    they would initiate French, “Well, do you speak French?” And then we could go on
                    from there. I wasn't going to put myself in the spot of annoying anyone by
                    starting off in French because I had seen that happen and I had heard, others
                    had told me about it. For instance, Ken Brown... I was sitting in on a briefing
                    Ken Brown was giving to some young diplomats in the Foreign Office. He initiated
                    his briefing in French to the great annoyance of some of them who then reminded
                    him that there were two languages in the country and all of them spoke English
                    anyhow. [Laughter].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about, any of the staffing of the consular section,
                        was it purely French speaking?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: My staff was all French speaking Flemish, certainly the lady, the
                    senior member who handled notarials and things of that sort, she was Flemish.
                    She was from Antwerp. The three women doing visas, at least 2 were Flemish, I
                    think the third one was Flemish also. And when I arrived, my receptionist was
                    Flemish. She left and I got a young woman. Her mother was Argentine, her father
                    was Austrian and she was fluent in French and spoke some Flemish and she was the
                    receptionist. But, I would say I was not conscious of any division, but I
                    realize I didn't have any basis, I just realized I didn't have any basis for
                    that. I was not conscious of it in the embassy, but Ken who worked, actually
                    worked in the chancellery could better tell you about this. The staff was
                    bilingual French and Flemish as well as English. And several of them had German
                    as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you left there, how did you find the social life
                        there? Were the Belgians fairly open?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. Yes because of the language I did better with any Belgian who
                    spoke French and/or English, so my social relations tended to be more in the
                    Walloon side, but I had lots of contacts, useful contacts, Flemish contacts. The
                    police chief, I think was originally Flemish, but her English and her French
                    were fluent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in '75. Where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Ecuador, which was very exciting because I had never been in the
                    mountains before.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were in Ecuador, you were up in the Quito from '72
                        to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: '75.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excuse me, '75 to ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: '75 to '77.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your job there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Head of Consular Section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: When I went there, the ambassador was a man named Robert Brewster and
                    his DCM with the surname Brewster whose nickname was Bru.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the political situation in Ecuador when you got
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: When I got there, there was a military regime. There had been a
                    military coup some years before and the dictator was a little round man, what
                    did they call him: “El Gordito.” Is that the fat one, something like that. While
                    I was, in fact while I was still in the hotel before I got permanent housing,
                    because it took a while to get me housed permanently so I spent three months in
                    the Colon Hotel. There was an attempted coup and there was a lot of gunfire
                    actually, it was right outside the hotel, woke us up. But it was a dictatorship.
                    After I left they had an election and elected a president.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of consular work did you have?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, some drugs, but most of it was Welfare and Protection.
                    Americans managed to fall off Machu Picchu, drown in the surf off of Guayaquil,
                    get lost in the jungle, get into difficulties like that. As I recall, the drug
                    traffic had not yet developed into anything serious. That was later on when I
                    was in Peru. So it was a time of the wandering, youth taking a year off from
                    college, and so they'd go down the spine of the Andes, smoking pot. So we got a
                    lot of them and they had a regular hangout ... hostels and small inexpensive
                    hotels. So if I needed to locate them, or one, I could leave messages. There was
                    a bookstore that was very popular with them named Leaves of Grass in Spanish and
                    you could leave a note on the board up there if the family said they were
                    heading that way and they would turn up. That was useful, that particular
                    bookstore. An American had disappeared, one of the backpacking wanderers, in
                    Central America, and the family produced a notice with his photograph and a
                    description and nailed it to all of the consulates down Central America and down
                    through South America. We posted it on the bulletin board of this bookstore and
                    somebody turned up and said he thought he might know something about that. He
                    had been asked, I forget in which Central American country, to see if he could
                    identify the nude body of a possibly American male that they had found. They
                    suspected it was a gringo that they had found, stripped of clothing, everything.
                    And the young man said no, I've never seen him before, but when he saw the
                    photograph on the bulletin board, he said, “That looks like him” and we put him
                    in touch with the family and whoever was conducting the investigation for the
                    family and I think it was a positive identification.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, were there problems about these young people on
                        their “wanderjahr,” with the local populace? I mean there must be bandits
                        and other things of that nature.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. There were. As a matter of fact that's how I made national
                    television, NBC did an expose of the government, but didn't I discuss this
                    before?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I don't think so, no.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No. During my tenure, we had 3 Americans disappear in our consular
                    district. Two of them, a young couple, engaged, traveling together went off into
                    the headlands leading down to the Amazon looking for herbs that could be useful
                    medically. Neither of them had any medical background, but that's what they were
                    supposedly doing. And they disappeared. Now, they had been the guests on the
                    farm of this one man who operated a restaurant down in the south that catered to
                    the young wanderers, passing through, I say wanderers because there were Germans
                    and French going through also. He cultivated them so of course he came under
                    suspicion but nothing came of it. No, nobody knew anything. They just
                    disappeared. Okay.</p>
                <p>Then there was a young woman of South Asian origin, a very adventurous type, she
                    climbed- (end of tape)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying this young woman in the ?30s who had been
                        all around ... she ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And so obviously a very capable person, she disappeared one Sunday
                    morning from the town of Ba�os. Sunday morning, people were out on the street,
                    on their way to and from church. We had the embassy in Stockholm interview a
                    Swede who had been staying in the same hostel as she and with whom she had had
                    breakfast that day. Her room, in her room were her climbing boots so it isn't as
                    if she was going off to do anything, any difficult walking or climbing this
                    Sunday morning. She simply disappeared and the police weren't able to find her.
                    Friends she had made prepared circulars which they spread around. She had made
                    many friends. She was very sociable. I prodded the police in Banos and Quito but
                    nothing came of it. Well, with three such things happening in a relatively short
                    space of time, this attracted press. And we had an NBC investigative reporter
                    coming down to do a story, to find out what had gone on. That sort of thing.
                    Well, there were all kinds of curious things with it. An investigator hired by
                    the families of the couple from one of the agencies in Florida, but the name
                    doesn't come to me, it's a well known agency ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Pinkerton or something ...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Something like that. One of those. So he came down. I briefed him on
                    what we had and he went off, didn't come near me again. He went back to Florida
                    and reported that he had been visiting an Indian village not far from where
                    they'd disappeared and the people were very nervous about him and he thought he
                    saw a couple of shrunken heads being hidden. [Laughter] He didn't come in and
                    tell us and police about it. He doesn't tell the police about what he suspected,
                    but goes back to Florida where it's now, three weeks have passed since the
                    incident so if there had been anything there, it was long since gone. Why he
                    didn't report it to us so we could tell the police about his suspicion was
                    probably that it didn't amount to anything anyhow. Shrinking heads ... it's
                    pretty far out, but it could have been followed up. Instead, that became another
                    mark against the embassy and the police because they didn't know about the
                    shrunken heads, alleged shrunken heads. An NBC reporter came down and got
                    apprehensive because he wasn't getting anything. And NBC had spent all this
                    money and brought the camera crew and I thought they're not going to leave
                    without some story. So, I had an inkling of what it was going to be. It was
                    going to be an expose. This is how things work. And it turned out, that's what
                    it was.</p>
                <p>They opened with my interview, I guess I got about five, six minutes on screen
                    out of a total of about 45 minutes, 50 minutes. It started off with one of
                    these, “when have you stopped beating your wife” questions. So I knew where it
                    was going. Oh, yes. Before I can tell you about that, I had not notified the
                    parents immediately of the disappearance of their daughter. I tried to get a
                    lead on it. I went down to Banos. I took our police liaison down with me. I
                    prodded the police because nothing's worse than a disappeared child. You would
                    rather have a body, you'd rather have something of definite news about “what
                    happened to my child?” So I didn't notify them for a week, trying to get a lead
                    on her. When I couldn't, I sent a cable through the Department, you know the
                    relay system, to the family informing them. Well, when another week went by and
                    I hadn't heard from them, I telephoned Washington and found out that that cable
                    had never gone on to them. So somebody in the Department then telephoned them so
                    it was on the order of almost three weeks after the disappearance that the
                    family finally heard. Well, that looks bad. So the first question that he put to
                    me was: “Mr. Richardson, don't you think it was terribly callous to not inform
                    the family of the disappearance of their daughter?” And I explained, the reason
                    was compassion and screw up. Yes, the first week was compassion, the second week
                    was because the cable never went through. Well, that's how he started off ...
                    Wasn't it callous? So, he's already planted the seed. Okay but that's not the
                    worst thing he did.</p>
                <p>Another case, during the same period, was of a young man who was traveling with
                    the same restaurant and farm owner who had cultivated the missing couple. But he
                    was traveling in the outback with this young man. He was giving him a ride, the
                    kid had also been to the farm. The kid had stopped taking his medication and
                    died out there in the boonies at this little village where the people are
                    scraping a subsistence living out of the land they cleared in the jungle. They
                    were very poor. Well, what had they done? They put their pennies together in
                    order to provide a decent burial for this kid. This had been organized by the
                    local priest. Well, down there, they don't bury people in the ground, they have
                    above ground structures to hold caskets.</p>
                <pb facs="0077" n="Page0077"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ah, oh, yes. Volts.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: In effect, they're really just slots, places that would accommodate a
                    small casket. Well, that's how they bury there because the water level is so
                    high they can't dig a hole. Well, this investigative reporter is interviewing
                    the family of this boy on camera. Okay. So he's interviewing them. How did the
                    boy do in school? And then he turns to them and there are the two parents
                    sitting on the sofa and he says, Well, do you realize that your son isn't buried
                    in the ground? Well, they went ballistic. “They never told us he wasn't buried.
                    Why didn't the embassy tell us?” They were shocked. That was, I think, the
                    foulest thing I've ever seen. It used to characterize that sort of thing as,
                    what is it, 60 Minutes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: 60 Minutes journalism. It has since improved a bit. That's what he
                    did to these people, and I thought that was the foulest thing that I had seen.
                    The whole program was condemning the embassy and the State Department. I think
                    the title of it was “Passport to Nowhere.” Well, a fallout from that is for
                    several years after that when I would find myself over in Rosslyn at the old FSI
                    site there and I would be riding up in the elevator, I could tell who the most
                    recent recruits were because this film was the first thing they showed them in
                    the A-100 class. [Laughter]. I'd find them looking at me, thinking do I know
                    him? Where do I know him from?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, God.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Okay, so that was really the high point, well the low point, I mean
                    now there's more to it than I can dwell on. Over the years, I've been useful to
                    a great number of people. Many of them wrote to me in Quito when they saw this
                    television program because it's quite condemnatory. Saying, you know, I remember
                    when you helped us, we don't believe the image that this guy was portraying.
                    Several people wrote to me. The other people who accepted what he said wrote to
                    the Department of State or to the Secretary and said “Fire him.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, boy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: So, I forwarded the letters I got from my fans to the State, but it's
                    not the same thing. It seemed self-serving.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0078" n="Page0078"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, what happened? What was the Department's
                        reaction?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: None, in terms of like supporting me or ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Supporting you or not supporting you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, they were neutral. They were neutral. They didn't take a
                    position. They left it to the post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that this dogged you through your
                        career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no. The only follow-up I did send to the Assistant Secretary was,
                    that I think since they're using this film in the training course, I should get
                    residuals. She laughed. But, there was something else to do with this ...Within
                    six months of this TV program, someone came and reported to me that an American
                    girl had been raped in Ba�os. I set Debby, my vice consul to work locating the
                    girl. So, we had her name, so there are all these hostels, these hotels known to
                    us where young wanders stayed. Debbie got on the phone and located her. Why had
                    the young woman not reported it? Because she had seen this film and knew that
                    the embassy wasn't the least bit interested in her problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, God.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Okay. Well, that didn't end there. Debby ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Debby being ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Vice consul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Debby, what was her?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Debby, Debby ... It'll come to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0079" n="Page0079"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: It was her first tour, but she was very capable. And she has since
                    done very well. Got a car, a driver, and Debby went to Banos with our embassy
                    police liaison, a retired Equatorial police captain. He had gone with me when I
                    went to Banos. Three of them drive off, pick up the girl at the hotel where
                    Debby had located her. And they go to Ba�os and light a little fire under the
                    police there. They go out, accompanied by a couple of cops around the hills,
                    because this girl has been hiking by herself in the hills around Ba�os. And so
                    they followed the route that she had and low and behold they find and arrest the
                    shepherd who had raped her. Well, it worked great and I gave the story to a
                    visiting American reporter who was very interested. I had hoped to somewhat
                    balance the bad press we had gotten about the disappearance of the Americans. He
                    got very enthusiastic but it never saw the light of day. And that good story,
                    that happy ending, never saw print.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your reading on this place that was the focal
                        point of this so-called investigative report? You know this Ecuadorian who
                        was befriending these people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, he was a relation to someone of influence because he never got
                    the kind of interrogation that I know the police are capable of, which I could
                    not suggest they do because you don't do that. They hadn't even taken him into
                    custody. So finally we got enough pressure on them. They took him into custody,
                    but still, they didn't interrogate him as they could have. So I feel very much
                    he had some protection. Now, he wasn't responsible for anybody's death, but we
                    just felt that he had to have known more. He could have been more helpful. My
                    personal opinion is that he was not at the farm where these two people
                    disappeared. He cultivated young Americans, or young travelers going through. He
                    was not on the farm so he couldn't be held directly responsible. It may have
                    been that the young woman in Banos attracted the attention of some of the
                    workers out there, they got frisky and the young man objected and she may have
                    gotten raped and the boy killed, and the bodies buried in the jungle. That's
                    certainly a possibility. I can't think of anything else. The young woman might
                    possibly have slipped, there's a fast running stream, running through Ba�os,
                    fast running, really moving. She could well have been wandering around there and
                    slipped into the water and been swept down to the Amazon. That's a possibility.
                    But any violence against her ... somebody in town would have seen it, people
                    would have, there are people in the streets. Now, if the person who assaulted
                    her, if that was an assault, was someone very well connected then that's when
                    nobody would see anything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Did, you left there in '77.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0080" n="Page0080"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the embassy, how did people treat you after the, you
                        know being the focal point of this 60 minute thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, it didn't affect anything. It didn't involve any celebrity
                    because the condemnation was general and the ambassador was also interviewed.
                    The State Department was condemned and the embassy, so we were all on the same
                    footing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '77 where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I went in for a year of language training in Farsi, preparing for an
                    assignment in Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find Farsi?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Difficult, difficult. And I never really accomplished very much with
                    it because, by the time I got there, there wasn't much opportunity for the kind
                    of casual interaction with the local populace by which you build up a language
                    capability. People were as likely to spit on me as to converse casually or to
                    correct my Farsi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you were out there in what '78, '79?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what, when you arrived in Tehran, what was it
                        like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, it really heated up a few months later with riots. Martial law
                    was declared and then it got tight. There was a curfew and you had to be off the
                    street by 8:00. If you wanted to get together with somebody for one reason or
                    another, you had to schedule it for like 5 to get home by 7 or 8. I can remember
                    racing through the streets to get home in time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were doing consular work then ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I was head of the NIV section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That must have been, you know, Iranians have stood for
                        years have been a pain in the neck for counselor officers. I found that up
                        in Yugoslavia and in Athens and other places ...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0081" n="Page0081"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: The consular section was a stand alone facility, but the demand was
                    so great that, that was yet another stand alone facility. It was in one corner
                    of the chancery compound wall. In the main consular section we had IVs, NIVs,
                    Welfare and Protection and Citizenship services.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was in charge of the consular section?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Lou Goelz.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Great.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: You know Lou.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know Lou.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. Yes he was in charge of it when I worked there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how did you find, what were the demands on you
                        because Iran was going through a revolution. There were a hell of a lot of
                        people who were trying to get out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, there was heavy volume, but of course there had been frequent
                    travel to the U.S., so most of them had visas. The middle class all had their
                    visas already. The heaviest of anything was in students and people who wanted to
                    get out. Our volume at the heaviest approached 100,000, which is not heavy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how did you find, how were you looking at, not
                        looking at the visas, a person asking to go to the United States in the
                        middle of a revolution from a very ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There was civil disturbance, but the revolution didn't take place
                    until the Shah left and Khomeini came back then you start talking about the
                    revolution, that's when the government changed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So after, when you first arrived ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: It was pretty non-violent.</p>
                <pb facs="0082" n="Page0082"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, so there wasn't an extraordinary demand then for
                        ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, there was ... and we were busy, it wasn't all that big of a staff
                    and as I said the volume as I remember was approaching 100,000, maybe 10,000 a
                    month at our busiest and that was when the staff was really reduced. So we were
                    busy. Yes, we were under the gun, but it was a very exciting time to be there
                    because nowhere else in the world, as I wrote to Judy Heimann, do we have
                    priests with guns getting their hands in the levers of power and political
                    authority. That was exciting. When the families were given voluntary departure
                    in December 1978, I lost my most valuable colleague, a PIT American Foreign
                    Service spouse.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, was there much discussion within the embassy and all
                        about what was happening?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, yes. There were daily staff meetings, who did what to whom, the
                    political section and the agency were busy with these things all the time, but
                    the Shah was still there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you all feeling ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But there was the unrest and there was marshal law, but what you had
                    was great numbers of people enriched during the economic boom following the
                    quadrupling of the oil price some years before. You had tremendous projects of
                    construction going on in the city. The national bird was the Crane and to supply
                    the labor, a lot of the people, country people came into town and they brought
                    with them their values and their children who were influenced by the big city
                    and going to the university and probably giving lip to their parents and
                    breaking with the old, proper way of doing things. There was this social
                    turbulence going on and hostility to the Westernization that was going on of
                    which the Shah was a leading proponent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then you were saying, you felt uncomfortable getting
                        out in public places as an American, I mean you know, identify yourself as
                        an American.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, not until after Khomeini came back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, when the Shah left, was that, did that sort of pull
                        the plug. I mean were people trying to get out at that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0083" n="Page0083"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. Yes, as I said many already had visas. Well, I followed the
                    philosophy of NIV issuance if they had financial interests in the country, land
                    owners, factory owners, people of substance, for whom there wasn't any question;
                    that is, when things improved, they would return. They didn't want to leave and
                    abandon their goods. Well, I think we had the same philosophy in Beirut, some
                    years before. If they had a reason to come back we would give them a visa. If
                    they don't have a reason to come back, they don't qualify.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, were you, was the volume of applications picking
                        up?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. Yes and our staff was reduced. We had voluntary departure of
                    dependents on December 8th of '78, I guess. Okay. The embassy was attacked on
                    February, early February ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think February 14th ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, was it 14th. My wife left on the 4th of February when she and the
                    ambassador's wife and the last of the wives left. That would have been February
                    4th. 10 days later there was the attack and after and there were several hours
                    of captivity. Soon after that incident the word came down that anybody who
                    wanted to leave could do so. Great numbers of the American staff left, many
                    going to join their families who were already evacuated and so then we struggled
                    along. I became Chief of the whole Consular Section. I still had my local staff,
                    Chief of the Consular Section, except I was the only American officer there for
                    several weeks and then one fellow came back from leave and there were two of us.
                    He was very good because this was the time when young men formed armed groups
                    and the streets were under the control of young men with guns. NIV visa
                    operations stopped except for medical emergencies. You couldn't imagine how many
                    of these, what do you call these, quadruple by-passes surgeries became
                    necessary. What was the name of the doctor in Texas?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: __________</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: It must have made his fortune.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this was a man in ___________ Houston.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0084" n="Page0084"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. And he was. He had to have been a very busy surgeon because
                    suddenly, almost anybody with a good deal of money who didn't already have a
                    visa was applying for a visa on medical emergency because he needed quadruple
                    bypass surgery. But, he had the money to pay for it. Okay, so those guys, they
                    went. For what they were worth, they were confirming medical certs and
                    appointments in Texas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So then were you there, what happened to you when they
                        took over initially on February 14th?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I didn't go to work that day. We hadn't been to work, for 2-3 days
                    before the attack. The Iranian soldiers that were guarding the embassy compound
                    were suddenly withdrawn, so the word went out, don't go to the embassy. Well,
                    two days went by and there were no incidents so a bunch of us got together in
                    one of the officer's houses in the neighborhood and we had a drink to celebrate
                    the fact that we had gotten through 2 days with no difficulty. There hadn't been
                    any soldiers guarding us, but there hadn't been an attack. The next day some
                    people who just couldn't stay away from the office went in and got captured
                    because that's when they came over the walls and took the embassy for those few
                    hours. But, there was still a government that could stand up to the mob and had
                    sufficient clout and prestige to be able to tell them, okay stop that, let these
                    people go half a year later, why that wasn't possible. We had one person killed
                    in that incident, one of the national employees, I think someone working in the
                    cafeteria. And we had one marine shot. He gave up his gun as he was instructed
                    to do and the ham-handed klutz who took it shot him with. But, it was an
                    accident and not fatal. So then those of us who didn't go to work that day kept
                    in touch by phone on what was going on. And then finally the captives were
                    released and we went back to work. That was the same day our ambassador was
                    killed in Kabul.</p>
                <p>During that period, Khomeini came back, and I was still living in my apartment,
                    several miles from the new consulate location in the Chancery. They later made
                    me move to a building right across the street from the back Chancery entrance.
                    Before then I came out of my house one morning got into my car which had a c.d.
                    plate and just got down the street when a car stops me with 4 armed young men.
                    And what do they want to know? They ask me in Farsi, where the American consul
                    lives. [Laughter]. Whoo. In my Farsi, as I said, never became very good, but it
                    was evidently good enough that I was able to tell them, “Gee, I don't know.”
                    Happily we're not dealing with the swiftest guys on the block. They don't even
                    look at the plates. I was driving an American car, which was not that unusual
                    but I had c.d. plates and didn't have a mustache. And I'm sure my accent, my
                    Farsi accent wasn't all that good, but they accepted it, and I drove off. That
                    was as close as I came to being captured.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then, of course the big takeover was when? In
                        November or something ...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0085" n="Page0085"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you were out of there by then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No. I was still assigned; I just went out for a couple of weeks leave
                    to visit my wife.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Uh, huh.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: So we were in the cafeteria of the embassy in Amman, having lunch
                    when someone came in and said there was something going on in Tehran, I think
                    you better go upstairs and check it out and that's when I found out that they
                    had come over the walls again, only this time to stay.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had there been any, in the time between the February thing
                        and the time you went on home leave, I mean on short leave to Amman to see
                        your wife, was there any, I mean were things getting worse and worse?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, yes. Oh, sure. But, even before my wife left, I remember coming
                    home one night when the office was already dark and realized that my wife, in
                    our kitchen, which faced the street, was silhouetted against, the light. So I,
                    next day, I got heavy drapes in so that wouldn't happen because I was afraid
                    somebody might fire a shot at her. They did at our naval attach�, the navy
                    captain and he came very, very close. He was answering the telephone and
                    whatever the conversation was he wanted to make a note of something the person
                    was telling him, but he dropped the pen and as he bent down to pick up the pen
                    the shot hit the wall where he had been. Well, that was the end of his regular
                    tour. We had been in Farsi language training together. But, that's so this was
                    in my mind when I saw my wife's outline in the window. I told you we had a local
                    shot and killed, marine shot, and 2 years before a local consular employee going
                    to the embassy to collect mail was shot and killed. An officer usually made this
                    daily trip. During the last days, we had someone down in the oil field servicing
                    agency in the south killed then we had another American killed, but we didn't
                    know what he was doing, he was kind of mysterious. He was a civilian living off
                    somewhere. The consul in Isfahan was stabbed. But, those were the only physical
                    things, but the fear was always there. In Beirut you had a lot of kidnappings
                    and that was my personal concern.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there an idea before you went on the short leave to
                        Amman, were you still talking about hanging in there ...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0086" n="Page0086"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, we were not only hanging in there, we were building up our staff.
                    We were going to show Khomeini that we could get along. We had turned down staff
                    so low that that I had only one vice consul. An FSO who had retired returned to
                    the foreign service and they said oh you want to come back to the foreign
                    service, we've got a great assignment for you and he came to me. [Laughter]. So
                    that gave me 2 officers, that's all. But then we got a whole bunch of them fresh
                    from Farsi training. All of those people who were aided, and evacuated by the
                    Canadians, except for the Agricultural attach�, all worked for me. We also got a
                    new Consul General, Morefield. He became a hostage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't Kennedy was it, Kennedy Morefield, wait a minute
                        no.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anyway Morefield.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: It was Morefield. And so this was what was going on. We were on our
                    way back up ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were any of you questioning this ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: About leaving or not?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no. The policy was we would show them, we would demonstrate that
                    we can get along. The only way we can do that is to resume normal operations, so
                    I don't know, I don't remember in staff meetings, anyone questioning the wisdom
                    of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And also, we were always, frankly we were enjoying ourselves. It was
                    the most exciting assignment in the Foreign Service at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, sure, yes. I mean of course the Foreign Service sort
                        of blossoms under pressure. What about, were you getting any taste of
                        confrontations or something with the religious types at that point or was it
                        ...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0087" n="Page0087"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: We, well see the religious didn't bother us, it was their
                    anti-Western orientation. The religion didn't matter. Where the religion was
                    showing up was active persecution of the Bahai.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of Bahai?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And there was not anti-Semitic activity to my knowledge. There were
                    some accounts to be settled and one member of the family of a Jewish merchant I
                    knew was killed. And many Jews, and Bahai and Christians lost their property.
                    But no active persecution of any one on religious grounds except Bahai.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you seeing any, how about students, I mean you
                        weren't dealing with students, but was there, were they trying to get to
                        Holdernaut or?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, they may have been, but we were closed to them. When we
                    reopened in October, then of course they turned up again. And, until we shut
                    down ion February the Mullahs who had been hostile to the U.S., and
                    anti-Western, had no aversion to trying to get somebody in the embassy to get a
                    visa for their nephew, not their niece, but their nephew. [Laughter].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what happened to you then, I mean all of the sudden
                        you're, when you're first, when you're dealing with, when you're in Amman,
                        what do they do, I mean were they saying, was there an initial thing saying
                        well this will be over soon and we'll get back together again?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no. There were only separate sitreps. No one offered an opinion
                    or any predictions. My own personal thing is how do we judge the present in
                    terms of the past and so I thought that I'll hang around here for a few days and
                    then go back to Tehran. So my wife and I stayed in Damascus, which was our base.
                    Then finally, I sent cable to the Department, which they didn't answer, saying
                    that I'm here if you need a consular officer somewhere in the area, I'm
                    available. Well, they never answered any of these cables [Laughter] because they
                    had more important things on their minds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what happened to you then?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0088" n="Page0088"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Ah, well I hung around there waiting for things to develop and then
                    spent a lot of time preparing an inventory on the stuff I left back in my
                    apartment. My wife who was living in Rome had visited me in July on her way back
                    from a trip to Hong-Kong, on her way back from Hong-Kong, she stopped off and
                    spent 2 weeks with me during which time she bought 12 rugs. All of which I lost.
                    And that's an unlucky number because I had 1 rug of my own to make 13.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you were saying, you were spending your time
                        inventorying, in Amman.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And also visiting the countryside. This was the time when the area
                    was supposed to be ablaze with anti-American feelings. My wife and I rode public
                    busses around Syria and Jordan and encountered courtesy and consideration.</p>
                <p>Well, as I was saying, this is the time when there was supposed to be a blaze of
                    anti-American, anti-Western sentiment and my wife and I rode public buses around
                    Jordan and Syria with no discomfort whatsoever. It produced some amusing things.
                    One time when we were in this very holy city in Syria, we were going to see a
                    famous old giant waterwheel, and we entered a tunnel and my wife who was ahead
                    of us, I was walking with our driver and we saw a Muslim woman go up and tug at
                    her sleeve. What's going on, we picked up our pace, but by the time we got there
                    the nice woman had left and my wife was laughing because the woman had asked her
                    in broken English if she was an American and Pearl said yes and the woman said
                    well, maybe you know my brother in Kansas City. [Laughter] And that is the God's
                    honest truth. [Laughter].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was sort of the feeling when you were sitting
                        there at that time that this Iran thing, Tehran thing would be settled by,
                        you know in a little while.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Based on our experience in February, I did not believe that it was
                    going to go on as long as it did; we would return and get on with business. The
                    Department following events in Pakistan ordered all dependents out of the Middle
                    East. You could see that they were taking a very serious view of it so I sent my
                    wife back to Paris where she had moved from Rome. Then I caught an evacuation
                    plane with dependents from the Gulf and went to Rome. There I caught another
                    evacuation flight to Washington. It was about 3-4 weeks after the takeover that
                    I left Damascus. I got back to Washington the 19th of December so it was that
                    long that I hung around Damascus and Rome trying to get an assignment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you get everybody out of the country or draw down,
                        sometimes there is a superfluity of people back in Washington, what to do
                        with them.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0089" n="Page0089"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, well what did I do? I got a good assignment in Lima. There were
                    also other possibilities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, ah Medellin?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I chose Lima. After the capture of the Embassy in February '79 we did
                    not have regular army protection. We had some informal kind of militia that was
                    supposed to be protecting us but they weren't really, they were occupying and
                    controlling access to the compound. I had to fight my way into the compound one
                    day because our captors decided we shouldn't work that day. One day I had a
                    couple of visitors from Rasht on the Caspian Sea. These are people who had come
                    to me on their own, they didn't need visas because they both had visas, there
                    wasn't anything I could do for them. They and their families had visas before I
                    ever met them. They came to me and said, “If you ever need to get out of here,
                    if you're in danger, let us know, we will hide you.” Unsolicited, that was on
                    their own. One of my people came in and told me that the leader of the militia
                    had collected a lot of our documents and is carrying them off ... passports and
                    things like that so I charge down the stairs and I catch him and I get a hold of
                    one end of the box he has and he's got a pistol on his hip and his brother is
                    there cradling an Uzi. Well he and I are going back and forth. I'm very angry.
                    Going back and forth tugging on this box and the brother is like [Laughter]
                    sitting at the center line at the net of a tennis match, he seeing us going back
                    and forth [Laughter] and he's still cradling this Uzi and the young man who had
                    come up to tell me about this was translating what I was saying to this man
                    except he was putting it in very polite language. I was calling this guy every
                    foul thing I could think of because I was out of my mind with anger and my clerk
                    was saying, “Mr. Richardson said that you shouldn't do that and those documents
                    belong to the embassy.” And this kid is being very polite and then finally the
                    thug that I'm contending with hears something he can repeat. He doesn't know
                    what it means and asks what means, “Son of a beach!” [Laughter]. At which point,
                    I dissolve in laughter and he was so stunned with my change of mood that he lets
                    go of his side of the box and I won.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, God ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And, well later on that young man made his way to the States and
                    there was a hearing, there was to be a hearing at an immigration court on
                    whether he would be permitted to stay or be deported. Where the hell they were
                    going to deport him to? His lawyer got in touch with me and I was very happy to
                    write up the incident and send it off. Well, the INS accepted my recommendation
                    and his son has just graduated summa cum laude from John's Hopkins
                    University.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How wonderful.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0090" n="Page0090"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. I hadn't I hired him. Personnel sent him to me. And I couldn't
                    figure out why, with the embassy under the gun like it was, any ambitious young
                    Iranian would come to work for us. So I thought he was a spy. I distrusted the
                    young man and he turned out to be my interpreter for the son of a bitch
                    [Laughter]. So that's one of my favorite stories from that period. But also
                    these people, the dentist and the doctor from Rasht, who offered to hide me if
                    need be. Okay, they offered me this choice of posts and I chose Peru and was
                    very glad I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Peru what from ... '80 or?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: That would have been '80.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And so you probably left in '79, you left Tehran in '79.
                        The takeover was in '79.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Then it was '80, I was already in Peru in '80.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, so probably ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Because when the hostages were released, my wife went back to
                    Washington to great them. She had worked with the Department's family liaison
                    group.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, so you were in Peru from '80 to ... how long were you
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: 3 years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '83 then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There was a fairly good sized operation. I had about 22 people
                    working for me including several vice consuls and a local lawyer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your job position there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0091" n="Page0091"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, Chief of Consular Section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There was a complete unit there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Ed Corr. Now, you were asking me about Peru, who was in Peru? Oh, Ed
                    Corr, with whom I had served in Ecuador. When I was in Ecuador, he was the
                    Political Counselor, I was Chief of Consular Section. And we had a great dispute
                    on principle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the principle?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: That he wanted something done to accommodate some contact of his and
                    I refused to do it. So we went back and forth, back and forth, and I was in the
                    right, I had, I had a right to do it refuse it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes, I know, I have any of these particularly Chiefs of
                        Political Sections ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: So it went up to the ambassador and the ambassador backed me. Well, 6
                    weeks later we find out the name of the man who was going to replace the
                    departing DCM ... it's Ed Corr, with whom I had just had this big fight on
                    principle ... well, he's got to be the most decent man in the world, he never
                    referred to the argument. He and I are still friends, it had no effect
                    whatsoever. So he was my DCM and then later on he was my ambassador in Peru.
                    Some years later I inspected El Salvador when he was ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you went to Peru in 1980, what was the situation
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: The situation was also one of a military dictatorship. And while I
                    was there, there was an election and the man elected was the man who had been
                    deposed by the military 10 years earlier so if Rip Van Winkle, a Peruvian Rip
                    Van Winkle, had fallen asleep during his first tenure and awakened after the
                    election, he would have still found the same president in their white house. I
                    always thought that that would have been an amusing idea for a story.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0092" n="Page0092"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now we've gone through some rather difficult periods
                        of Peru with a military that was not vehemently deposed towards the United
                        States and there was nationalization of some international property and all
                        that. How were things at the time you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, by the time I had gotten there, whatever the bad feelings had
                    pretty much passed on, problems if not been resolved, they had been suspended.
                    The military was in control and a lot of military checkpoints on the road. My
                    wife and I were driving from Lake Titicaca back into the country, and we
                    encountered an incredible number of military checkpoints.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, was this the time of, what was it, the Shining
                        Path?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a pretty scary situation, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: We had an embassy bombed at that time. It knocked out, about I think,
                    a hundred windows. They had built a protected area for the marine guard and it
                    had just been completed like a week or 10 days before this bombing and happily,
                    that's where the marine guard was, in his appointed place when the bomb went off
                    so he was not injured. If he had been out of it, he would have been peppered
                    with shards of glass.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was, how did the political events, you know
                        this Shining Path terrorism affect your operations, or did it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: On consular operations?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I would say that there were just general security concerns. I don't
                    know if it was the Shining Path or not. I was threatened once, my house was once
                    threatened to be bombed. Why threatening? If they were going to bomb, they would
                    have bombed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bombed. Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: So, I don't know why anybody would have called up and threatened to
                    bomb my house.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0093" n="Page0093"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was consular work like? ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Now, there was Ayacucho. We traveled quite extensively in the
                    country, my wife and I, by road and air, but there was one city that we always
                    wanted to visit but that was a hotbed of Sendero Luminoso guerilla activity.
                    That's where it started. And so we never got there. But otherwise we traveled
                    quite extensively. Along the coast we used a car, when we went into the interior
                    to Cuzco and Iquitos we flew. I spent a lot of time down in the south performing
                    American services for the copper company employees down there. The company liked
                    that because instead of having the employees come up and lose time, they just
                    had to provide me with transportation down there and a place to sleep. So they
                    would send a plane for me and take me down.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Also the missionaries in the interior. I worked very closely with
                    them, the people who were doing the Bible translations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now, how about, what were sort of the, were you
                        having some of the same troubles you were having in Ecuador about Americans
                        being foot-loose and fancy-free and hiking along the Andes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No. That was pretty mush past, but at one point I had something like
                    22 people in prison, all for drug smuggling. They created some excitement for us
                    when they went on a hunger strike. It lasted a couple of weeks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were these real smugglers or were these kids?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No. These were adults. But not professionals. One guy came down with
                    his golf clubs and stuffed his golf bag with cocaine. No, they weren't very
                    smart. But I also had druggies, people who came down simply to indulge in
                    drugs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, tell me when you get that, were there affects to
                        them playing around with these drugs or were they essentially just sitting
                        there and ...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0094" n="Page0094"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Getting happier and wasting themselves, but eventually they moved on.
                    I didn't have anyone die on me from drug overdose. I don't understand, there was
                    one couple, they came to me begging for help, there wasn't anything I could do
                    for them unless I take them into a hospital which they refused. They were gray.
                    The only gray color I've ever seen on a European type person, she was dead
                    several days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, boy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But, they were gray.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they willing to go back to the States or?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to help that or do they..</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I never had to repatriate any of them, they somehow found their way
                    out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were Peruvian jails?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Terrible, terrible. They, but before I got there, we had negotiated
                    one of these treaties where the person could serve his time in his home country
                    and this was popular with Americans because parole and time off for good
                    behavior were much more liberal in the U.S. Federal system than in Peru. But I
                    had one guy who turned it down. He turned it down. He had a caf� going in the
                    prison with a pool table and regular little rackets he had going on, he wasn't
                    about to give that up to go sit in jail in the U.S.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there many students going from Peru to the United
                        States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Not that many, they, the middle class already had their visas and so
                    they'd have B-1 / B-2's. If they came in for a student, it wouldn't really be
                    anything that we would need to focus on because they came from families that
                    could afford to send their children to the school and if they were from that
                    social class that couldn't afford it, so they didn't get visas. They were just
                    part of the great poor mass because I had a high refusal rate there.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0095" n="Page0095"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But, how about, were there efforts made for Americans to
                        adopt children or anything like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I didn't have that in Peru, I had it in Ecuador when I was there.
                    There was an active child adoption activity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How does that work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: It works quite smoothly, but on a small scale. It wasn't a big
                    business. There was one lawyer who was very active and he gave satisfaction.
                    What he arranged, you know was he selling babies? But nobody talks and nobody
                    complains ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No. That's often the way. Well, how did you find Peruvian
                        society. I mean living in Peru?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I enjoyed it. It's a highly stratified class structure, but
                    it's changing. Can I tell you a story about social-cultural change?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: My wife and I went to a dinner party, it was a buffet and the guests
                    were people of our age. Peruvian wives all prepared plates for their husbands
                    and brought the plates to their husbands. Their husbands never went near the
                    buffet table. Well, everybody's getting fed and you know I'm getting hungry and
                    I know my wife's not going over to the table to prepare a plate for me, it
                    wouldn't have occurred to her. Well, what am I going to do? I'll lose face if I
                    go, but I don't want to go hungry. Well, the men and women are separated, but
                    the food was in the men's room. The women would serve their husbands and prepare
                    their plates and go to the adjoining room. Well, I saw my wife, but she was busy
                    talking. She was one of the last women to go to make a plate for herself. So I
                    saw her filling up her plate and I wandered over by the door way leading to the
                    room where the women were and when she came by I greeted her and said, “Hey,
                    honey, what have you got there.” So she held out her plate like this to show me
                    what she had on her plate and I snatched it out of her hand. [Laughter]. And I
                    went back and rejoined the men. I explained it to her later and she understood.
                    Well, these were people of our generation, our age. A month or two later and it
                    had to have been, it could not have been a longer gap, otherwise it wouldn't
                    have struck me so vividly, we were the oldest people at a dinner party where the
                    guests were the age of the adult children of the previous crowd, they are the
                    age of the adult children and of the same class and we noted that not a single
                    young woman prepared a plate for her husband. Without any hesitation at all
                    every young man went up to the table and filled up his own plate. That was a
                    social cultural change that we observed. I was very, very struck by that.</p>
                <pb facs="0096" n="Page0096"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, fascinating.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: So, a society in the process of change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, were there any major events in the '80-'83
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, the big thing was the election.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fujimori?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, no, no. Famous Peruvian author presented himself as a candidate,
                    but he didn't win, it went to Belaunde who had been there 10 years before. That
                    was one of the biggest things.</p>
                <p>One brief story before leaving Peru. At a large American missionary station deep
                    in the interior I attended a performance, in English, of a French play, Cyrano
                    de Bergerac, by American students of the station school while behind me someone
                    was explaining the action on the stage to a Quechua-speaking woman in full local
                    dress. I have always counted that evening as one of my most notable
                    cross-cultural experiences.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you left there in 1983?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Right, right and I stopped off for 2 or 3 months, did a TDY as head
                    of the Consular section in St. Paolo, which I enjoyed very much. It was a
                    dynamic city. In those days I walked very briskly, and nobody ever passed me on
                    the street in Lima. I got to San Paolo and elderly women were elbowing me out of
                    the way. That's the difference, it was tremendous experience. I loved the city.
                    You couldn't breath however because of the pollution in the air was so foul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Probably much worse now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Undoubtedly. And there is a district there that had a very high
                    deformed birthrate, you know birth defect rate, I forgot the name of the
                    industrial suburb, but other than that it was great, it was a real pleasure. I
                    would have gone back there in a moment if they had offered it to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0097" n="Page0097"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did they offer you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I got back and I didn't have an assignment. I was in the Department
                    without an assignment. I went around knocking on doors, I went to see Dick
                    Morefield.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dick.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Dick Morefield had been my last ConGen in Iran and a hostage. He said
                    well, yes, I've got something for you if you think you can work with a
                    troglodyte.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With a what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: A troglodyte.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, my God.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: And I said well, I don't have any other job. I would not have had any
                    difficulty working with anyone, yes I'll try it. And I did. And so I went to the
                    Bahamas. But, the problem with this is, that person's daughter is now a
                    high-ranking State Department official.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me just turn this off. Well you went to the Bahamas
                        where he was the ambassador, I take it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that, I mean we don't have to, I mean people are
                        people and public officials, you know we don't have to handle this with kid
                        gloves. How did this affect the embassy and consular work in the
                        Bahamas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Consular work, it didn't. This was a political, social-political
                    attitude. But, I'll tell you what affect it had on me. Before I got there, he
                    had kicked out his DCM and had appointed the Head of the Consular Section as
                    DCM. Shortly after I got there, within a year, he kicked out the DCM, former
                    Consul General and a new fellow came in and then after a year, he became
                    dissatisfied with the new DCM and he was trying to get rid of him. My fear was
                    that he would ask for me because I seemed to be the only person of rank that he
                    liked. So that tells you ... it didn't affect the consular work. But, it did
                    cause me some concern.</p>
                <pb facs="0098" n="Page0098"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how, what were the issues in the Bahamas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Drugs. The Bahamas, the only time of prosperity in the Bahamas is
                    when there is a serious shortage of something in the United States. During the
                    Civil War, it was smuggling guns and ammunition, supplies. During prohibition it
                    was booze and since World War II, it's been drugs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I've heard you had Roz Ridgway. She was down there
                        earlier and she was saying this was the port drugs hit.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And this was just when the Bahamas got independence, she
                        was, I think DCM and it was, the big money and all hadn't yet hit and it was
                        a solid, capable young government, but all held ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But it's so corrupt, that type of money is terribly corrupting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, were you concerned about the money getting,
                        corrupting our staff in the consular section.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There was no way the visas were the problem. The Bahamas regarded
                    themselves as the 51st state. They'd go see an ophthalmologist in Miami, the
                    same for gynecologist. And you'd go to Florida to have your baby so there were
                    no serious visa problems for Bohemians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they throwing Americans in jail for drug business or
                        not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, but they were mules.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Peru.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: In Peru. Those were people, obviously they were small time
                    entrepreneurs, they were coming down to buy a kilo to take back to make a little
                    score for themselves. No, these were mules. Welfare mothers, single mothers on
                    welfare who'd be paid to come over, collect the package and bring it back.</p>
                <pb facs="0099" n="Page0099"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what happened to them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: They were, they'd be arrested or better yet they'd be permitted to
                    board the plane and they'd be arrested in the States in the hopes that the
                    information they could give would lead to the person who hired them. One, now I
                    did have one fellow who swallowed a couple of condoms full of cocaine, but this
                    was for personal consumption.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, the plane was on the runway, about to take off, when one of the
                    condoms ruptured and he went into a frenzy, a drug induced frenzy, and died
                    right on the runway with his wife there. Now, whether his wife was privy to his
                    activities or not, I had no idea, but I had one dead American and fresh widow on
                    my hands for the weekend, because I couldn't even get the medical examiner to
                    certify to his death until Monday and this was Saturday. So I took her, I took
                    the widow home with me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: But that's the only drug death, I know I had many other deaths. Over
                    2 million Americans visit the Bahamas annually so they get into all kinds of
                    mischief. I had one tourist, we found him dead at the bottom of the elevator
                    shaft in one of the big hotels. And we don't even know how it happened. How did
                    he get under the elevator? They never found a defective door, you know where
                    they could say oh well, something happened, the door opened and he stepped into
                    a void. They never found that a defective door. We had rapes. Well, these things
                    happen. We had people die on the cruise ship on its way to the Bahamas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do the cruise people take care of these mainly?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. But they unload the body at the first port that they come
                    to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, did, how did you find, were people in trouble with
                        the police, were they helpful?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I always suspected the police were pretty corrupt, but they were
                    courteous and friendly, and you see what we would be dealing with wasn't
                    anything that threatened them in any way. And so they could afford to be
                    gracious. We didn't give them a lot of trouble. We had one person in prison for
                    murder. I visited him regularly.</p>
                <pb facs="0100" n="Page0100"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Robert Vesco still around?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, I think he was in Cuba by that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Much to your relief.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: [Laughter]. Well, where, I did have one bad moment, well of course
                    there had been this man in Colombia had taken over an island for trans-shipping
                    drugs ... I've forgotten his name and that was a big scandal. They'd finally
                    gotten rid of him, that was before I had arrived. But a man came in and had his
                    passport renewed, nothing wrong with it, we did the usual check, everything was
                    clean, he takes his passport and he leaves. The next day I read in the paper
                    that he is the object of an indictment for a multi-million dollar sugar swindle
                    in New Orleans. [Laughter]. But that broke after I renewed his passport.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how was the morale of the embassy with this
                        difficult ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Oh, no problem, it was the DCM's who caught it. And maybe his
                    relations with the Department. But he wasn't difficult for the rest of us. There
                    was one really bright, the Economic/Commercial Officer, his name is now engraved
                    on the wall there at State ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was killed at Grenada.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. And he was impressive, I think it was only his first or second
                    tour. He was impressive. He had just married a local girl, a Bahamian girl, and
                    his next assignment was Grenada and he was visiting the Chief or Police when
                    somebody came in to kill the Chief of Police and he was killed. What a pity
                    because he was, as I said, he was an impressive young man.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Cy this is probably a good place to stop, you left
                        the Bahamas in 1983, where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I inspected for 4 years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then what did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0101" n="Page0101"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I retired in '91.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, we might cover the inspections then, now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: There wouldn't be much to them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Alright.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: We'll cover the inspections. Sure you know what you do in an
                    inspection, you go around, people meet you at the airport and they try their
                    best to get on your good side and occasionally you can do some good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, did you find any real, you know I hate to dwell on
                        the negative, but as an inspector goes, did you find any cases or problems
                        that were interesting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, I got to Fiji, there was a brand new officer, fresh you know
                    from the A-100 course and he'd taken over the consular section, small as it was
                    and we counted the passports and there was something like 23 of them not
                    accounted for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, God.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Well, obviously, he wasn't there long enough to have made a
                    connection to dispose of them, for which I was very glad so, we called that to
                    the Department's attention for further investigation. But, he'll never take over
                    any post again without going over inventory before he signs for it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ah, well one time I had an inspection come when I was
                        Chief of the Consular Section in Belgrade and we seemed to be missing 25
                        blank passports. We kept counting and counting and my predecessor had
                        ordered 75 passports instead of the usual hundred and so we were assuming
                        that you order them in batches of 100. And, again, I was very careful from
                        then on.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0102" n="Page0102"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, well on the, occasionally we could do some good, but there
                    wasn't anything notable. I remember when I left Kinshasa, I noted in the report
                    that they needed closer supervision in the Consular Section because the Consul
                    General was also Supervisory Consul General for neighboring countries. And so
                    she traveled a good bit and when she traveled there was a junior officer from
                    some other agency who was holding down the fort and it was obvious he wasn't
                    paying very much attention to what was going on. Well, later when I was doing a
                    TDY, immediately following retirement, in Lagos the Dutch consul sent me a
                    passport from someone who was applying for a Dutch visa. This person had a
                    Gambian passport containing a US visa issued in Kinshasa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well Zambia was before Anesia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: No, Gambia in West Africa. He's applying for a Dutch visa and she
                    found that he had a visa issued in Kinshasa. She was suspicious.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, you were saying something like a traveling
                        salesmen.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes, he had a visa from some place 2,000 miles away from his home so
                    she brought it to my attention and this convinced me that what I had observed a
                    couple of years before was true. I canceled that visa and shortly thereafter the
                    story broke that the Kinshasa locals had been up to hanky-panky. Not properly
                    supervised, they had a little racket going. And it's weird, it spread so far
                    that somebody would go all the way from Gambia to Kinshasa, 2,000 miles. Not
                    neighboring countries, Rwanda, Gabon, but all the way from there so they had
                    something going, but that's the only malfeasance I detected.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about sexual harassment. It's around this time when
                        people are beginning to pay more attention to that. Was this something you
                        were ever looking for?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: I don't remember, I don't think that we ever asked the direct
                    question and when we would have individual chats with the staff. No one ever
                    brought anything like that up to me. We sometimes had some sexually active
                    officers, but if it's consensual, there isn't much you can do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then you retired when, in?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0103" n="Page0103"/>
                <p>RICHARDSON: June of '91 I inspected and then I retired in '91. But there was one
                    amusing incident, the inspection team arrived in Quito and there was the usual
                    meeting with the nationals. The Chief of the team introduces the other members
                    of the team. Well, I'm at the end of the line, so I'm the last one who was
                    introduced. Well, he mentioned this is Mr. So and So who will be doing,
                    inspecting the political, economic, admin sections. Before he introduced me,
                    well nothing had happened, the nationals just sat there and nodded their heads.
                    He introduces me and there is tumultuous applause. I hadn't been at the post in
                    10 years, but they remembered me. Well, if it had been a lesser time, if it had
                    been 5 years or less I'd have had to recuse myself from the inspection, but at
                    10 years, I didn't have to.</p>
                <p>I cannot conclude this review of my career without mention of a great
                    satisfaction I experienced one day. There were three people at the counter one
                    day when I wandered into the old Foreign Service Lounge. All three of them had
                    started their FS careers with me as section chief and they were all going on to
                    good assignments. One was on his way to the War College, another was to head up
                    the Vietnamese refugee (boat people) operation in the Philippines and the third
                    was going to a very good job in the Department. Mr. Chips could not have been
                    more proud and pleased than I was that day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, gosh. Well, Cy, I want to thank you very much. This
                        has been fun.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RICHARDSON: Yes. It has.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
