<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000083">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Gordon R. Beyer </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR GORDON R. BEYER</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Horace G. Torbert </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 9, 1989</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ambassador Beyer, we are very happy to have you here with
                        us today, and I would like to go over your career, in general. I wonder if
                        you would start out by telling me a little about how you first got
                        interested in foreign affairs and how that resulted in your winding up in
                        the Foreign Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: I was at college at Harvard, and my oldest brother also went to Harvard
                    and to Harvard Law school. He was interested in public service. He eventually
                    did work for the government for a time after he graduated from law school before
                    going into private practice. I suppose it was his influence, more than any other
                    single individual, that got me interested in foreign affairs.</p>
                <p>After Harvard, I went for a year to Northwestern, where I got an M.A. in history,
                    and was thinking, in fact, of not going into foreign affairs, but teaching. The
                    Korean War was still on, however, and I was married and we were running short on
                    money. So I enlisted in the Marine Corps and was eventually commissioned and
                    then sent overseas.</p>
                <p>With my battalion in Japan, which was a training battalion for Korea, I was made
                    the S-2, the intelligence officer. I went to intelligence school at Camp Drake
                    in Tokyo and then went back to my unit. One of the major jobs that I had at that
                    time was talking to Japanese prosecutors about our young Marines who got into
                    trouble. I found that I seemed to work a little bit better with Japanese
                    officials than some officers in our unit. So that interested me once again in
                    going into a profession in which it would be necessary to work with foreign
                    officials. It wasn't that I particularly liked foreign officials; I just found
                    that I did it a little bit better than some others.</p>
                <p>So, after the Marine corps, I came back to Washington, joined the Bradley
                    Commission, the President's Commission on Veterans' Pensions, headed by General
                    Bradley, took a variety of exams including, finally, the Foreign Service exam,
                    passed the written and eventually had an oral exam, passed the oral, and came
                    into the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is the proper way of doing it, but not the easy way
                        as some of the rest of us got into the Service. Do you want to start then
                        and outline generally where you went to begin with, and what your major
                        duties were, and what kind of a life you had for the first year or so? I
                        think you started out by going to Bangkok, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right. After the A-100 course, which all the young officers took at
                    that time, I was assigned to Bangkok, Thailand as our first post. My wife and
                    young daughter, Theresa, and I took off for Bangkok. It was a pleasant trip in
                    those days. We went by railroad from Washington to Florida, to Chicago, to
                    Minneapolis, to Seattle by train, then Northwest Airlines from Seattle to Tokyo,
                    to Hong Kong, to Bangkok. In those days it was a prop plane and we traveled with
                    beds on this plane.</p>
                <p>We arrived in Bangkok and there were three junior officers assigned to Bangkok,
                    Thailand. I was assigned, perhaps in those days considered the least desirable
                    post, as consular officer. In fact, it turned out to be a marvelous job where I
                    was in charge of our little consular section, had an American assistant, an
                    older woman, and two or three Thais. No one, really, was terribly interested in
                    what we were up to as long as things went along all right.</p>
                <p>Two things that I remember are, when I arrived, Mr. Donovan was inspecting the
                    post, and the consular section had had some troubles because a traveling rodeo
                    had gone broke in Bangkok, Thailand. I had been working part-time on the desk,
                    when I was in the A-100 course, with one Mr. Rolland Bushner, who was the desk
                    officer. So I was somewhat familiar with the problems, as seen from Washington,
                    with this rodeo going broke. One of the problems was, that the consular officer
                    did not immediately find out what the Americans were and what their passport
                    numbers were.</p>
                <p>So, as this rodeo went broke, the horses were sold and the Americans dispersed,
                    but there was never a very clear accounting of who was who, and so on.
                    Washington was quite distressed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Donovan, an old consular hand, was very upset. When I arrived, he decided to
                    take me under his wing and tell me how this should have been done so that, if it
                    ever happened again, I would be able to handle it properly. He was a fine
                    teacher. I learned a great deal about consular work from him, and kept in touch
                    with him for many years afterwards.</p>
                <p>So I did that for nine months. I was then assigned to the economics section, and
                    had a pleasant time there, doing a variety of things. Robert Cleveland was the
                    head of the economics section, and I learned a great deal from him about Foreign
                    Service life and the style that we, as young officers, should maintain.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>Then finally, I finished up for the last year or so on our delegation to SEATO.
                    So, in that first tour, I had a good exposure to life in the Foreign Service—the
                    consular business, the economic side of our affairs, and then the diplomatic
                    side and working on our delegation to the Southeast Asian Treaty
                    Organization.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was SEATO, in those days, a viable and growing concern
                        that was really, that you felt, was doing something useful in building our
                        defense posture in that area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: I thought it was quite viable, but it was not a NATO. It didn't have
                    forces assigned to it. It had a disparate membership and, therefore, was never a
                    defense organization as such, as NATO was.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, these were the early days of SEATO. For example, Ambassador
                    Jack Lydman was in charge of the secretariat at SEATO in those days. Mr. Hill
                    was in charge of our delegation—another fine and vigorous officer. What SEATO
                    did do, I think, is it was more of a cultural organization in many respects. It
                    permitted a great deal of conversation between the European members—the U.K. and
                    France—the US, and the members from other parts of the world—Pakistan and
                    Thailand. So, though never a NATO, I think it served a very good function in
                    those days, and it certainly was very interesting for all of us.</p>
                <p>One aspect of life in Thailand in those days was curious. I was, of course, a
                    third secretary. There were a goodly number of other third secretaries who were
                    there, including the today's ambassador from Australia to the United States,
                    Mike Cook, Bruce Harland of New Zealand, and Ali Alatos of Indonesia. Ali today
                    is the foreign minister in Indonesia, and Bruce Harland is up at the U.N. in a
                    significant post.</p>
                <p>But, in any event, we third secretaries decided that, since no one else wanted to
                    talk to us, we'd talk to one another, and we got together for lunch every couple
                    of weeks. It became very interesting because we felt we could invite anyone that
                    we wanted to, and we began to invite people that, I think, our ambassadors began
                    to wonder about.In any event, all of our ambassadors heard about this, after
                    about six months. We were called in and asked what we were doing and what we
                    were up to. [Laughter] We explained that this was just a social club and that we
                    were having a good time.</p>
                <p>The ambassadors that I had there, first was Ambassador Max Bishop who I didn't
                    get to know very well. As I said, I was down in the consular section at that
                    point. The next ambassador in the second year was Ambassador U. Alexis Johnson,
                    and his DCM was Leonard Unger. Both became friends that I kept in touch with
                    throughout my career in the Foreign Service, and both were outstanding
                    officers.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>Mrs. Johnson became very fond of my wife, Molly. Molly wanted to teach English to
                    Thais and asked Mrs. Johnson if that would be all right because, in those days,
                    it wasn't too common for wives to work. Mrs. Johnson said this was fine as long
                    as she attended the American wives' meeting at the residence once a month. That
                    was the only requirement she put on Molly.</p>
                <p>We, of course, in those days, did work very closely, both of us, with the staff
                    of the embassy and the ambassador, and so on. We tried to be as helpful as
                    possible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had, at the end of that period, a couple of years in
                        the Department. What did you do? You did personnel work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right. I was assigned to the personnel operations division. I had
                    been off on a trip up-country in Thailand, and I returned and found that I had
                    been assigned to the personnel operations division. I was really depressed
                    because I didn't think that was a very good assignment. But it was the personnel
                    operations division for Europe, and I found out more about the Foreign Service
                    than I ever had known before or since, and perhaps more than I really wanted to
                    know. But it turned out to be a marvelous job.</p>
                <p>People who I kept in touch with ever afterwards—Galen Stone was the head of the
                    office. Freeman Matthews was in charge of one division, the division that I was
                    in, and Sam Gammon was in charge of the other division. Sam, of course, is now
                    the executive director of the American Historical Association.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You met most of the movers and shakers in your first
                        couple of years, in other words. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right. It was really remarkable.</p>
                <p>I found out a curious fact however. You couldn't see your file in those days
                    except if you were assigned to personnel, because you had to deal then with the
                    files. So I was shown my file, and just before I left Bangkok, Thailand, we were
                    inspected again. The inspector mixed up my wife with another wife and described
                    her as a dizzy blonde.</p>
                <p>As I said to Galen Stone, “She may be dizzy, but she's not blonde. [Laughter]
                    What do we do about that?”</p>
                <p>So we got that corrected right away. Otherwise, I suppose it could have been
                    quite detrimental. But that was one aspect of being in personnel.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>Another aspect of being in personnel and in the operations division—this is the
                    assignments division to Europe—was that I never had so many friends.</p>
                <p>Then there was one last aspect to it. I was in charge of staff personnel in the
                    Soviet Union and Eastern Europe. One of the jobs that we had as personnel
                    officers in those days, when the cold war was at its height almost, was to
                    interview our staff people to see if they really were competent to go to these
                    difficult countries. We also interviewed people as they came out of the
                    countries, and I'd like to tell two stories about that.</p>
                <p>One about a young man who wanted to go as a communicator to Poland. We never
                    assigned a communicator to Eastern Europe in those days if they hadn't already
                    had one tour overseas. This young man had not had a tour in the Foreign Service
                    overseas, but he had served with the military in communications overseas and had
                    an excellent record. So I convinced my bosses that we should assign him to
                    Poland.</p>
                <p>After he had been there about six months, we found that the Poles had drilled a
                    hole into his bedroom, which was up on the third floor of the embassy building,
                    and young ladies of the night came and visited him. When this was found out by
                    the security officer, he was pulled rather rapidly.</p>
                <p>They said, as they looked into this, “How in heaven's name did he get assigned
                    there since we only assign people who have served in other foreign posts.”</p>
                <p>I was to blame for that, I'm afraid. [Laughter] He was a nice young man,
                    though.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you recovered. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: The other aspect of the story that I would like to tell is about talking
                    to people as they came out of post. Poland, in those days, was really one of our
                    happiest posts behind the Curtain. Yet, as I began to talk to staff people as
                    they came out, there were lots and lots of complaints, and these complaints got
                    worse and worse. And I wrote them up, and I sent them first to Bob Falstead, who
                    was immediately in charge of my office.</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, that's interesting.”</p>
                <p>And he sent it back to me.</p>
                <p>I said, “I am really worried about this. Would you object if I showed it to Galen
                    Stone?”</p>
                <p>He said, “No, not at all.”</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>So I showed it to Galen.</p>
                <p>Then Galen called me in and said, “Well, I've read this. It is kind of worrisome,
                    but what do you think?”</p>
                <p>I said, “I don't know. Something is going on over there. I don't know what it is,
                    but the comments from the staff people have gotten very harsh about the post.
                    They are not very happy, and it's a variety of little things, such as, the wives
                    get first chance to go to the commissary. The secretaries and others, who are
                    working, don't get there until after working hours. Therefore, the wives have
                    picked things over. Or the food in the canteen has become more and more Polish
                    and less and less American. These young people are not very happy about that.
                    Thirdly, the service is bad, and so on and so forth. It is a variety of little
                    things that we never used to have as a problem in Poland.”</p>
                <p>So he said, “Well, I'm going to show this to some of our security people and have
                    them check and see if they can find out what's going on.”</p>
                <p>Galen did that. They did check, and this is when they discovered that Mr.
                    Scarbeck, who was the administrative officer, had been compromised.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was, obviously, not paying sufficient attention to his
                        job.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right. Yes. As he got and more involved, he did less and less of
                    his job. That resulted in a decline of administrative service, particularly for
                    the lower-ranking folks in the embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Having never done it myself, I always felt that personnel
                        work, at some point, was a very useful thing to have in one's file. I did,
                        of course, serve on selection boards and things of that sort, so you get a
                        little bit of it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In spite of having been assigning people to Europe, you seemed to have assigned
                    yourself to Yokohama next. [Laughter] How did that happen?</p>
                <p>BEYER: As I had mentioned, I had been in Japan during the Korean War, and I was
                    intrigued by Japanese affairs. I had studied under Reischauer at Harvard.
                    Reischauer was the ambassador to Japan; he had just been named. So I had myself
                    assigned to the Japanese Language Training School.</p>
                <p>Actually, right before I left personnel—one little story if I may. President
                    Kennedy and his whole new staff had come in and, as you may recall, he said that
                    State is in charge of foreign affairs.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>Then three months later he said, “State is not doing the job.”</p>
                <p>Well, it wasn't quite as bad as it sounded, but what had happened is, we had
                    people that worked with the Eisenhower Administration. When the Kennedy people
                    came in, we had people that could work with them, but they weren't in
                    Washington. And so, the effort in personnel was a tremendous turnover to try to
                    get people back into Washington that could work with the new Administration.</p>
                <p>And so the director of personnel asked for a special assistant. We sent one young
                    man up, and he lasted one day and was bounced out. So the director wanted
                    someone else, and he wanted someone talented, and so he talked with Mr. Jova,
                    who was in charge overall of the personnel operations division. I was called
                    into Jova's office, and he told me what they wanted, and he told me that I had
                    to stay up there and I had to do a good job. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>So I went up there, and I became the special assistant. That was a
                    fascinating—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The special assistant to whom?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: To the director of personnel who was Hermann Pollack in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, I knew Hermann well.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: So we did start shuffling people around, trying to get people back into
                    Washington that could work with the new Administration.</p>
                <p>One Saturday morning, when we were involved in doing this, Hermann had all of his
                    staff in, and I was there. The request came from the White House for someone to
                    work closely with the President that the Service had confidence in, who had
                    served in two areas, and was 30 or under.</p>
                <p>So we went through our files trying to find someone like this. We could meet all
                    of their requirements except the “30 or under.”</p>
                <p>So we went back to the White House and we said, “We can meet that requirement
                    except for the '30 and under.' Why is there that requirement?”</p>
                <p>They said, “Well, Bobby is only 32, and Ted Sorensen's 30, so it has to be 30 or
                    under.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>We didn't meet that requirement.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they take somebody, though?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Oh, and the last requirement is “30 or under and had to have been in the
                    Service about ten years.” That was the problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't have anybody.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Actually, it was impossible. Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's touch briefly on Yokohama and what you did when you
                        got there. I take it that, having known Reischauer, you probably had some
                        contact with him, even though you were at a separate post somewhat
                        removed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes. First of all, the school was in Tokyo. So, when I was up at the
                    school, he would have language officers over from time to time, and we would
                    chat with him. I was not the best language officer in the world, and I decided
                    that maybe I didn't want to spend a whole career in Japan. So we were just
                    initiating a six-month course. So I switched with another officer, who had been
                    assigned to the six-month course. I went into the six-month course, and he went
                    into the full two years—Bill Clark by name, who is now Deputy Assistant
                    Secretary in East Asia. Bill was a marvelous linguist and went on to become one
                    of the better Japanese linguists in our Service.</p>
                <p>I went on into the six-month course, and then after that went down to Yokohama,
                    where my first job was as a visa officer and an administrative officer—not visa,
                    passport and citizenship, and administrative officer. And I did that for six
                    months. It was quite a large consulate general in those days. It had nine
                    officers and about fifteen folks—a big place.</p>
                <p>After six months, it was reduced to three officers—a consul general, who lived in
                    Yokohama but worked in Tokyo, a passport and citizenship officer, a shipping
                    officer, and an administrative officer—he did all those things—and me, who
                    became the reporting officer. So the next year I did reporting, and then the
                    third year it was reduced to one person, and that was me. We just did the
                    shipping and what reporting we could.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were gradually being phased out of existence.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>BEYER: That's right. In fact, what happened, of course, is—you probably know—the
                    school was moved from Tokyo to Yokohama. I was all for this because I thought
                    that the young language officers could live in some of the smaller villages
                    around Yokohama, such as Kamakura, or so on, which are very lovely places, and
                    would really get into the Japanese ways and the Japanese society. In fact, of
                    course, what happened is that the language officers lived right in Yokohama,
                    went to the Officers Club, and didn't get involved as much in Japanese life
                    during those days that they were in the school as they might have.</p>
                <p>One other thing that happened in Yokohama, by the way, is—we had a child born
                    there who died after two weeks. That was supposed to be our last child because
                    Molly was Rh negative. This results in having to change the blood of the child.
                    So we had been advised by the doctors down in Yokosuka not to have any more
                    because it would be tough for the mother and for the baby. But, having lost this
                    child—it had a congenital heart disease, lesions in the heart which, in those
                    days, they really couldn't fix and I'm not sure they could have fixed her even
                    today.</p>
                <p>But, after three months, we went back to Yokosuka and decided we would try one
                    more time. The folks in Yokosuka said that they would do everything they could
                    to bring the baby out in good shape. So that is when our youngest was born—Tom.
                    He was brought on after seven months. He had a variety of little things to get
                    fixed up, including a complete transfusion of his blood, and so on. But both he
                    and mother survived, and both are doing quite well today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Isn't that great!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Actually, our second was an Rh-negative one, too, except
                        it was very early in the procedure and they didn't do that complete drainage
                        and oil change that they do now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Of course, I really have to put in a plug for the Navy doctors in the
                    hospital in Yokosuka, which was made available to Foreign Service people in
                    those days. They did, really, just a marvelous job. It couldn't have been
                    better.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember years ago that you told me that you were
                        seriously thinking of resigning from the Foreign Service about this time,
                        until you got this wonderful chance to open a new post in Hargeysa, which
                        always amazed me that you would stay for that. [Laughter] It certainly
                        showed the stuff you were made of. Do you want to touch on that a little
                        bit?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>BEYER: Well, it is true. Every couple of years, I think, in those early days I
                    used to think I ought to resign from the Foreign Service and do something else.
                    The head of Mobil Oil Company in Japan, became a friend. We belonged to the same
                    little club in Yokohama called the “Martini Taster's Society.” It was 12 men,
                    eleven Americans and one Dane. We met once a month, and the only thing that you
                    had to do was to have at least one martini for lunch, which always led to very
                    bad things. But it was a nice group. The consul general had traditionally been a
                    member of this group. So, when it was reduced to one person, they decided that
                    they would invite me to join, and that's how I met this man.</p>
                <p>He called one day. It was in the spring.</p>
                <p>He said, “Let's go play golf.”</p>
                <p>I said, “It is a little difficult for me because I have to get someone to cover
                    here.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, see what you can do.”</p>
                <p>So I called the embassy in Tokyo, and they said, “Yes. Go play golf. We'll cover
                    for you.”</p>
                <p>So, during the golf game, he said, “Why don't you join Mobil Oil Company?”</p>
                <p>Well, two things really had happened. One was this possibility of opening a small
                    post in Africa had come up, which I was very excited about, and I'll come back
                    and talk about that. But also, Molly's parents had died and left a little money,
                    which made it possible for us not to have to worry about schooling of the
                    children. The president of Mobil commented that, working for the Foreign
                    Service, I would not be able to send my children to the same schools that I had
                    gone to because they didn't pay well enough.</p>
                <p>Well, with this little bit of extra money, that burden was relieved, and we were
                    able to look forward to being able to send the children to whatever schools they
                    could get into. So that was important to not leaving.</p>
                <p>Then, after telling him that I wasn't going to leave, he then said, “Well, you
                    know, I don't blame you at all. I wish I had stayed in the Navy.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>He really enjoyed the Navy and wished that he had done that.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>As far as the post is concerned, just a day or so before we had this golf game, a
                    classified telegram had come from Washington, explaining about the opening of
                    this post in Hargeysa, Somali Republic, why they wanted a post there, and so on.
                    Since it was classified, someone had to bring it down from Tokyo because we
                    didn't, by that time, have classified facilities in Yokohama. We were out that
                    evening and when we came back, this communicator had the telegram and left a
                    message for us to come up to his apartment and take a look. Good soul that he
                    was, he had opened an atlas to show us where Hargeysa was and, indeed, where
                    Somalia was. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>We were very eager to do this, and it wasn't until some years later, we learned
                    that five people had turned it down while we had been eager to go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it was a fascinating job, I guess. Anyway, we were
                        delighted to see you when you arrived. I might interject that I was in
                        Mogadishu, so we welcomed you there. How did you get, by the way, from
                        Yokohama? Did you go home in between?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: We did. But, as you may recall, you were very interested in having someone
                    get there sooner rather than later. So, despite having been in Yokohama for
                    two-and-a-half years and three years in Japan, and watching American President
                    Line Ships come in and out of Yokohama, and getting to know the shipping agent
                    for a couple of years very well, who had promised us that—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That you could have the royal suite.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right. [Laughter] The basic first-class suite would be a really
                    good suite. But we didn't take the ship, which is—I mean, it was in those days—a
                    marvelous two-week cruise, we flew back. We flew to Washington and on down to my
                    parents' home in Florida, and then off to Africa.</p>
                <p>Those were wonderful days to travel to Africa. We took, I believe, East African
                    Airways, but it was being run by the British. They'd set the plane up in
                    compartments, like they have on trains in Europe. They gave us a whole section
                    because, by that time, there were five of us. It was just a marvelous trip to
                    Nairobi.</p>
                <p>Nairobi was a lovely city, though I remember Ambassador Torbert saying, “Don't
                    think that the rest of Africa is like Nairobi, because it is not,” which was
                    absolutely true.</p>
                <p>Then we went on to Mogadishu, and we were there for ten days before going up to
                    Hargeysa.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you want to paint a little picture of Hargeysa and what
                        you did there—which was really the end of the world, I must say.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes. In those days, it was quite hard to—it took about eight days to go by
                    truck from Hargeysa to Mogadishu, and it was a fairly long plane ride because
                    Somalia is in the form of a seven. You couldn't go directly because that was
                    going across Ethiopia, and Ethiopia—in those days and, perhaps, until today—was
                    the enemy. So the planes had to go around the corner, and that took quite a long
                    time in these old prop planes—these DC-3s.</p>
                <p>The post had been established in the sense that a house had been found, an office
                    had been found, and so a lot of the tough, basic decisions had already been
                    taken and had been, I think, taken very well by a more senior officer who had
                    done this. But there still were a lot of things to do in the sense that we
                    didn't have furniture for either the house or the office, at that point.</p>
                <p>I still remember Wayne Swedenburg, who was the administrative officer of the
                    embassy in Mogadishu. I talked to Wayne and said, “What should we do about
                    trying to get some things out of Washington for the office, in particular?”</p>
                <p>We had gotten the desk and a credenza—a credenza is, I found out, something that
                    you put against a wall. But we didn't have any couches, or chairs, or coffee
                    tables, or rugs, or draperies.</p>
                <p>So Wayne, being a very practical man, said, “Why don't you go to Aden, which was
                    just across the Gulf of Aden, the town of Aden, buy what you need, have it
                    shipped over?”</p>
                <p>This was far and away the simplest, the quickest, and the cheapest. So I went
                    over to Aden and went to a Norwegian store and bought some very nice things, had
                    them shipped, and put in the office at Hargeysa. The furniture had a wine-red
                    back of cloth and white leather seats, and then light wood on the arms. That was
                    the two chairs and the couch. The table was also of light wood. The rug was
                    gold, and the draperies were, again, wine red. I asked Molly, when this was all
                    finished and set up, to come down and take a look at the office and see what she
                    thought.</p>
                <p>She opened the door, took one look, and said, “Metro-Goldwyn Mayer.”
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>However, the Somalis were lively people, and they heard about this new office.
                    For the next two weeks, I had a steady stream of Somalis coming into the office,
                    for one reason or another, to take a look. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>We also set up a library, and we showed films. So I was very much involved with
                    our United States Information Service people in Mogadishu that first year
                    because they would send us materials, and so on and so forth.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>After that first year, we had assigned to us a wonderful USIS officer, who had
                    been in London, named Savalas. He was the brother of—Telly. The Savalas who is
                    on T.V. He did a marvelous job, and I realized what a good USIS officer can do,
                    which I really hadn't been doing—but we tried. It was fun.</p>
                <p>One other thing that we had to do in Hargeysa which was, I think, a little bit
                    unusual is, the British at that time did not have relations with the Somali
                    government. Therefore, we represented British interests.</p>
                <p>Somaliland, which is what it was called—was a British protectorate before it
                    became independent in the Somalia Republic and joining the south, which was an
                    Italian colony. But many of the Somalis in the north had relations with the
                    United Kingdom in one way or another. They were retired from the Somali Camel
                    Corps, or they'd been in the maritime business and were receiving modest
                    pensions or stipends of one sort or another. So one of our jobs every month was
                    to pay these folks these modest amounts of money.</p>
                <p>After we'd been there about six months, we got a communications from the U.K.
                    government saying, “We understand that you are still paying a pension to the
                    widow of this man who was a merchant seaman, and we figure that she must be
                    about 102. We wonder, is she really alive and do you really give the money to
                    her?”</p>
                <p>Well, I had to write back and say, “No, we didn't give it to her. We gave it to
                    her sons.”</p>
                <p>Her sons were in their sixties and seventies. They were old men themselves. Then
                    the word came back from London, “Well, we appreciate your problem, but you have
                    to see her and see that she is still alive before you give out any more
                    money.”</p>
                <p>So, when her son came in the next month to get his check, I said that I couldn't
                    release it until he brought his mother in. He said, “Do you realize that my
                    mother is a three-day walk into the Ogaden?”</p>
                <p>This is a grazing area in, in fact, Ethiopia, but is inhabited by ethnic Somalis
                    most of the time.</p>
                <p>So I said, “I am terribly sorry, but those are my instructions from London, and I
                    really have to follow them. I realize that this is difficult.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Do you have any idea how old she is?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Yes, I think I do. I gather she is really quite elderly.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Yes. I don't know whether she can make the trip.”</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>I said, “Well, those are my instructions.”</p>
                <p>So he disappeared, and he reappeared about a week later with a woman that he said
                    was his mother, and I believed him. She certainly was the oldest-looking person
                    I have ever seen. So I gave him the check and reported this back to London, and
                    they said okay. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Interesting. Now, at that time we had a Peace Corps, as I
                        remember it. At least we had it for a while until there was some border
                        trouble which came up. During your stay there, you had quite a few border
                        troubles, didn't you, with Ethiopia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes. We had border troubles, but we also had ethnic troubles between the
                    clans. The Habr Awal and the Habr Yunis got into a fight. These were two major
                    Ishaaq clans, Ishaaq being the large clan overall. Two thousand men were killed.
                    I couldn't believe that the Somalis could get in such a fight with themselves.
                    It was just unbelievable to me.</p>
                <p>At one point, a young man came in, who was a teacher, and showed me where he had
                    been shot, and it had gone right through his pants cuff. There was just a little
                    round hole.</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, this is just silly.”</p>
                <p>He said yes, he realized that, but that it had just started and these things did
                    happen from time to time. There was never any reporting in the Western press, to
                    the best of my knowledge, on this kind of killing.</p>
                <p>When we first arrived in Hargeysa, the Ethiopians had just bombed the town. The
                    Somalis did not believe that the planes that were flown could have been flown by
                    Ethiopians. The thought they were flown by Americans. We were, at that time,
                    very close to Ethiopia and had been for many years. Haile Selassie, of course,
                    was a legend in his time, and well and favorably remembered here in the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>I was really received with a certain coolness—indeed, more than coolness, perhaps
                    some hostility. I can remember that the road from the airport into town had to
                    go around a corner where young Somalis lounged at a local gas station and would
                    always shout at the Americans as they went by, sometimes even throwing
                    stones—which was a sort of Somali trait because that's the way they kept track
                    of their herds. So they learned to throw stones very early.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And there were plenty of stones available.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>BEYER: That's right, because in Hargeysa—and, I guess, perhaps the rest of
                    Somalia—it was like Arizona or New Mexico in the sense that it was quite dry. It
                    only got five or six inches of rain a year. That usually came in the big rains
                    in the spring. There were small rains in the fall. Then we'd go for as long as
                    six months with no rain at all. The climate, however, was very nice and very
                    healthy because of this lack of moisture.</p>
                <p>So there was, for example, a large Peace Corps contingent in the northern regions
                    because, of course, the Somalis in the northern regions, being a former British
                    protectorate, the language of instruction in their schools was English. It was
                    English rather than Somali because, in those days, Somali was not written. it
                    was not a written language. It was just a spoken language. So English was used
                    in the schools, and it was very easy, therefore, for our Peace Corps to be of
                    assistance, teaching in their schools.</p>
                <p>There was a doctor assigned, because of the number of Peace Corps folks that we
                    had in the northern regions, but that doctor had really very little to do
                    because, as I mentioned, the kids just didn't get sick because of the nature of
                    the climate. It was a marvelous climate in the sense that, for three months of
                    the year, it was cool enough to wear a jacket, and the summers, though warmer,
                    were very dry. Therefore, you didn't feel the heat so much.</p>
                <p>We had in the backyard in Hargeysa four horses, and so we did quite a bit of
                    riding. There was also an institution called the Hargeysa Club, which was the
                    old British Club in the northern regions. The Club had a place to stay, it
                    served meals, and it had grade-B movies a couple of times a week. It was an
                    interesting facility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I might mention, of course, that Hargeysa was about, as I
                        recall it, 7,000 feet up in the air as opposed to Mogadishu which was at sea
                        level. Therefore, the climate was quite different, indeed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Didn't we have to, as I recall it, evacuate the Peace Corps while you were
                    there?</p>
                <p>BEYER: Not while I was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember doing that at one point. Maybe it was before
                        you came.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Well, that's right. Right before when I came, the Peace Corps, the first
                    group, they bombed Hargeysa. The Somalis were quite antagonistic to Americans.
                    The volunteers in the northern region just scattered, and it was very hard to
                    find where they were because the deputy director, who lived up in the northern
                    regions, was not a consular officer, was not alert to keeping close track of his
                    volunteers. So his volunteers just left the country and never told him where
                    they were going.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>So one of the purposes, I believe, of establishing this branch office of the
                    embassy in Hargeysa was to be sort of a lightning rod for any hostility towards
                    Americans so that they could be hostile towards this facility rather than at any
                    particular volunteer.</p>
                <p>Similarly, we had a somewhat better feeling for how to keep track of folks, and
                    we did that. In addition, there were certain separatist feelings between the
                    north, which was a former British protectorate, and the south, which was a
                    former Italian colony. The northerners were beginning to feel that maybe they
                    shouldn't have been so quick to jump into a republic with the folks from the
                    south, because a lot of the money they felt they were earning for the government
                    was going to Mogadishu and, therefore, leaving the northern regions and not
                    coming back.</p>
                <p>A couple of incidents that were interesting to me at that point—President Aden
                    Abdullah Osman at one point came to Hargeysa. With the other consuls or vice
                    consuls, we attended a dinner with him and had a long talk with him. I thought
                    the embassy might be interested in this, and so I wrote a long telegram, which
                    was classified, and took it down to the local—we had a one-time pad and
                    classified it in that manner—took it down to the local post office, showed it to
                    the telegraph man, and he said, “This is in code.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Yes, it is.”</p>
                <p>He said, “I won't send it.”</p>
                <p>I said, “You have to send it. It's a telegram. You just have to send it.”
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>So he did send it. It got back to Washington, and they spent two or three days
                    trying to decipher it, could not, cost $180, and a rocket came out to the
                    Embassy saying, “Tell that consular officer in Hargeysa not to send anymore
                    classified telegrams. If he's got anything classified, to send it to the embassy
                    by pouch, and they can send it on to Washington.”</p>
                <p>This is what we did from then on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We were, I guess, pretty well cleaned up, up in Hargeysa.
                        By this time, my contact with you had a temporary break because I left
                        Mogadishu, but you later came down to Mog as political officer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right, political officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have anything more to say about Hargeysa?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>BEYER: Just two things. One is that Mohammad Egal, a former minister in the
                    government—and to become a minister again, indeed, to become prime minister—was
                    from the northern regions. We lived in a house of his first wife, and so we got
                    to know Mohammad Egal quite well because he would come up and visit his
                    children.</p>
                <p>At one point, he told me—after he'd been up in Hargeysa for three weeks and we
                    were drinking at the Hargeysa Club bar, which he enjoyed very much—he commented,
                    “You know. You never really do get divorced from a wife.”</p>
                <p>So he still saw quite a bit of Asha, his first wife, and his children.</p>
                <p>The other thing that I remember is, Ambassador Torbert—two things. One, when we
                    first arrived, that little boy that was born, Tommy, you had us to lunch, and I
                    remember we came—this is a very Foreign Service story. You had the whole family,
                    including little Tom, and we had him in a crib, a portable crib. We whacked open
                    that crib and dumped Tom in it. You were impressed by that. [Laughter] The other
                    two kids behaved themselves, but this little guy, we just put aside and he
                    slept.</p>
                <p>The other thing that I remember is, at one point you were worried about the
                    separatist business. We had left Hargeysa to take a boat, believe it or not,
                    from Djibouti down to Mombasa as part of our R&amp;R holiday. We had talked the
                    Department into permitting us to do this rather than going to Athens, which was
                    our R&amp;R post, because we wanted to go to the game parks. We convinced them
                    that this was a significant change in climate, etc.</p>
                <p>As we came down in that Lloyd-Triestino Italian Line, we stopped in Mogadishu,
                    outside in the ocean. People would come and join the boat and be lifted up in a
                    bag. We were watching this operation and, at one point, the bag dropped, and
                    there was Bill Sandals, who was the political officer and quite an impressive,
                    older officer, quite proud of his dignity. Being hauled around in a bag, he
                    didn't enjoy it at all [Laughter]. So I went running down.</p>
                <p>I said, “For goodness sakes, Bill, what are you doing here?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, the ambassador sent me out because he wants to know whether, in
                    your view, there is any truth to these rumors that we're hearing down here about
                    a separatist movement in the north.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, when I left the north—which was about two days before—things were
                    still very quiet, and I didn't think there was anything to those rumors.”
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>So he went down to the deck, and got back into his bag and went back ashore. I
                    still remember that.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The bag actually was a wooden platform with canvas sides
                        that collapsed. That's the way I arrived in Mogadishu. My ambassadorial
                        dignity was somewhat threatened. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Well, it was the way everybody arrives. I didn't see why he should have
                    been so upset. [Laughter] But he was.</p>
                <p>At any rate, after you left, sir, Ambassador Thurston arrived. I was getting to
                    be known in the embassy as an expert, just because I was bouncing around in the
                    northern regions. So he asked that I come and replace his political officer
                    after my two-year tour in Hargeysa, and so I did that.</p>
                <p>Alex Johnpoll was the DCM when I went down, and I learned a great deal from Alex,
                    also. He became a lifelong friend until he passed away. He was replaced by Hal
                    Joseph, who was also a first-rate officer and a good tennis player. He and I
                    used to play tennis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very important there, too. That's one game you could
                        play.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember anything particular from your Mogadishu
                        days? What was going on by that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: I think the thing that I remember the best is what a democracy Somalia was
                    in those days. They had elected a president twice and the parliament three times
                    in open elections. Dalka was the political journal. It was in English and was
                    the first, probably the best, political journal being published in Africa in
                    those days.</p>
                <p>I was at the embassy for a year. In the last days of that tour at the embassy,
                    there was an election. President Mohammed [Ibrahim] Egal became prime minister,
                    and Abdirashid Shermarke became the president. So there was a switch there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Abdirashid, having been prime minister before, then he was
                        replaced by Abdirizak Haji Hussein, and then Egal replaced him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right, and then Egal replaced Abdirizak Haji Hussein.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It seemed quite idyllic.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>BEYER: Right. I remember Ambassador Thurston saying to me—we had a beach house at
                    that point—”I want you to see Egal before you leave and find out what kind of
                    government he's going to have and what he wants to do.”</p>
                <p>So I called Mohammed, and I said, “I'm leaving in a few days. I would be very
                    grateful if I could talk with you, perhaps at the beach house.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Gordon, I'm really very busy. Well, all right.”</p>
                <p>So he came over about 4:30 to the beach house, and just the two of us talked for
                    about an hour or two hours. I then reported this back to Ambassador Thurston,
                    and his policies were very much what we hoped they would be. He became a very
                    close friend to the United States, as did the Somali government, in those
                    days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He shortly thereafter came on a visit to the United
                        States, I remember.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Right. By this time he had married a second time, Edna.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The beautiful Edna, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Who was a lovely gal and a nurse. I remember the headline when he and Edna
                    visited the United States. It said in the Style section of the Washington Post,
                    “Second wife and midwife.” It was an article about Edna. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came back then in 1967 to the Department for quite a
                        long tour.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right—five years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that entirely in African affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes, it was, except the last year. Ambassador Thurston wanted me to go
                    back onto the Somali desk, unbeknownst to me. I guess I'd been considered for
                    the secretariat, which would have been fun, but I didn't mind going on the
                    Somali desk. I did that for a couple of years, and then became the deputy in
                    what was, in those days, called Northeast Africa and included the Sudan,
                    Ethiopia, and Somalia. The last couple of years I was the deputy in that office
                    under Matt Looram. Matt was an outstanding officer, who served in Europe, and
                    then, as a matter of fact, was to be an ambassador in Somalia.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Matt worked for me way back in Western Europe
                        days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: So I did that for four years, and then went to the National War College as
                    a student, which was a great experience in those days—1971-1972. I graduated in
                    the class of 1972. In those days, the students visited for three weeks the five
                    geographic areas of the world, and the Air Force assigned planes so that each
                    group had its own plane which meant that it would leave when you were ready to
                    leave. You didn't have to meet schedules. It would take whatever you bought and
                    just put it on the plane.</p>
                <p>Another officer, Dave Simcox, and I were the only two Foreign Service officers
                    who were selected to go to the Middle East. This was, of course, an area of
                    great interest to the military because they foresaw troubles there. So they only
                    took two civilians, and Dave and I were the ones that got onto this trip.</p>
                <p>There was a great deal of talk about buying things in the Middle East. I wasn't
                    very interested in this, but our first stop was in Tunis.</p>
                <p>All the military folks said, “Well, in Tunis you are supposed to buy bird
                    cages.”</p>
                <p>They were white and blue bird cages. So we went running into town, and I thought,
                    “Well, I might just as well get a bird cage, too.”</p>
                <p>I must say that, once you start buying like that, the bug does sort of get you. I
                    was as bad as they were. But when we came back to the plane, we hung up on the
                    ceiling all our bird cages. So that was the beginning of a plane filled with
                    things—the bird cages all the way down the top of the ceiling. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>Those were happy times, and I regret that the War College is far different from
                    what it was in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We can get into that later when we get to the time that
                        you were there in the management thereof. You then went back to northeast
                        Africa in 1972 as DCM in Dar es Salaam.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right. Bev Carter, who was named ambassador—one of the black
                    officers in the Foreign Service, who had come up through the United States
                    Information Service, USIA, and was then a deputy in AF under Ambassador Newsom.
                    He was assigned to Tanzania and asked if I'd like to go as his deputy. I agreed
                    to do so.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>That was an interesting assignment but, in fact, Tanzania was a difficult country
                    for me. It was the greatest disappointment of any of the countries I think I've
                    served in in the Foreign Service in the sense that—the intellectuals in the
                    academic community of both America and Europe considered Julius Nyerere
                    something of a philosopher king, and I felt like I was going to the philosopher
                    king's kingdom. In fact, of course, as I was to find out, Julius Nyerere was a
                    ruthless, autocratic ruler, who stayed in power by being very tough, indeed.
                    Indeed, I found that the term “disappeared” was a verb—such as, “Mohammad was
                    disappeared yesterday.” This happened often to those who got too close to
                    Americans. We began to realize that, the only way we could have Tanzanian
                    friends, or see Tanzanians, was in large groups so that they could not be
                    identified as being particularly close to us Americans. This made it very
                    hard.</p>
                <p>The first year and a half was a very disillusioning experience. It was really
                    like living behind the Iron Curtain, from everything that I've talked to of
                    folks who have lived behind the Iron Curtain.</p>
                <p>The country was not doing well. For example, they had a policy called
                    “Villagization”—Ujamaa was the term in Swahili, and the effort was to move
                    people into government villages. The advantages from the government's point of
                    view would be that they could provide a modicum of health care, a modicum of
                    education, and clean water. In fact, what it did is it broke the identification
                    of a family or family unit to a particular piece of land and forced them into
                    these villages. Then they would have to walk to these pieces of land, and slowly
                    the identification of that particular piece of property, private property with a
                    private individual, was broken.</p>
                <p>This Ujamaa was not going as fast as it was hoped. Therefore, they decided to
                    speed it up, and they used the Army to transport people and to knock down
                    villages and move people, sometimes as little as five miles, to this new
                    village.</p>
                <p>We found out that this moving of people was going on because I went with the
                    family down to the Selous, which is a game park down in the southern part of the
                    country. As we drove down there, we saw this happening. We saw people—it looked
                    like a picture from the Second World War, with people streaming along the sides
                    of the road, carrying their belongings on their head or their back, and carrying
                    long poles to build new houses in the new village sites.</p>
                <p>I got back to Mogadishu and I said, “We've got to report this. This is just
                    terrible, and we also ought to get some newspaper guy—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You got back to Dar es Salaam.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Dar es Salaam. I'm sorry. Dar es Salaam. And we ought to get some
                    newspaper folks down from Nairobi to report on this. We told reporters in
                    Nairobi about what we thought was happening and that this was really quite a
                    major story.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>They came down to Dar es Salaam, drove down towards the Selous, got about 50
                    miles outside of town, were picked up by the government, returned to the airport
                    in Dar es Salaam, and told they could never come into Tanzania again.</p>
                <p>This was a very efficient way to control the news. As the newsmen said to us,
                    “You know, Tanzania is kind of important in East African political affairs, and
                    to be barred for life from a country is rather severe. It really does restrict
                    our reporting on this country.”</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, the story eventually did get out. There was an article in Time, and
                    so on, and we estimate that six million people were moved in this villagization
                    process. It was really quite harsh.</p>
                <p>The thing my wife remembers the best is going past a village that had been
                    knocked down and burned, and a woman—and the smoke slowly going up—was poking
                    through the rubble, looking for her favorite utensil to take with her to the new
                    Ujamaa village or the villagization policy, the new village.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the total population?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: The total population at that time was about 20 million, so it was an
                    enormous amount of people, just an enormous amount of people—couldn't believe
                    it. All over the country, apparently, this was happening, and we wouldn't have
                    known about it in the embassy except—because we didn't travel that much in the
                    country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you restricted in travel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: No, we were not. We were permitted to go and see this business. The
                    officials didn't like it too much, and we were often questioned rather
                    closely—where we were going, what we were doing. But, since we were going down
                    to the Selous for a holiday, they could hardly keep us from going there. It is a
                    fine game park area. Indeed, Tanzania has, I think, the best game parks in East
                    Africa, but the facilities today are—they were going downhill then, and they are
                    even worse today, I am told by those who have visited. On the other hand, the
                    facilities and the parks in Kenya continue to be quite impressive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kinds of programs did we have going in Tanzania at
                        that time? Were there AID programs of one sort or another?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes. We had a large AID program. It was about $10 million a year.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>Another interesting story to me is, at this time—now this was the last years,
                    this was during the Nixon Administration, Nixon-Ford. An official came out, an
                    AID inspector came out, and he spent a couple of weeks in Dar, talking to folks,
                    and so on. Then he spent another week, traveling around the country.</p>
                <p>He came back, and he said, “I don't think our economic assistance is going to
                    help this country, and I don't think we should be here at all.”</p>
                <p>Because of the socialist nature of the government, he felt that our aid would not
                    be helpful, and he said—Tanzania in those days was getting more assistance per
                    capita from countries around the world, particularly northern Europe, than any
                    other country.</p>
                <p>He said, “If the countries of northern Europe think that they can help Tanzania,
                    fine. But I don't think we can. I don't think we should.”</p>
                <p>That particular report was buried by AID, but I kept a copy for years because I
                    found it so fascinating. Also, the Tanzanians would tell you, “Well, we're doing
                    this in health, and we're building these many schools, and so on and so
                    forth.”</p>
                <p>Then he would go out and look and, of course, the statistics that the Tanzanians
                    would hand out in Dar es Salaam, and the reality out in the field, was not
                    comparable at all. These were just misstatements. They were just errors. They
                    were lies, in fact.</p>
                <p>So the cooked figures of the government departments in Dar es Salaam were just a
                    scandal, and he discovered this. In its own way, it is kind of unfortunate, I
                    think, that we didn't recognize the lesson right there—that there are some
                    countries we can help, and there are some that we cannot. Perhaps Tanzania was
                    one of those countries that we really can't help.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, perhaps our own bureaucracy has something to do with
                        this.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes, indeed. Actually, Ambassador Thurston was opposed to this policy. He
                    used to call it “the policy of 'pays choisis',” the chosen countries. He said
                    that there were some in Washington who didn't want to help Somalia but wanted to
                    help Ethiopia. He felt that this was wrong, and that there were many reasons to
                    help Somalia, let alone that it was an operating democracy in those days. I
                    agreed with him.</p>
                <p>But now, in retrospect, I really think that there are countries that we can help
                    in the developing world. But there are also countries we can't help.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any change in the political situation in
                        Tanzania while you were there? That's when they began to have border
                        difficulties with Uganda, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved in that at all at that time—as a
                        forecast of your future operations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: There was the abortive effort in the southern part of Uganda by Tanzanian
                    troops, and Nyerere pulled back from that. But there wasn't much political
                    change because Nyerere had an iron fist on things in Tanzania and ran a very
                    tight organization. So there was no political change in the three years that we
                    were there, really—except, as I say, that, if anything, things got a little bit
                    worse.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have sort of lost track of things there. When did
                        Nyerere finally disappear as a factor?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: I don't know whether he's disappeared yet—in the sense that he has given
                    up the presidency a couple of years ago and he's no longer president of
                    Tanzania. But he is still head of the party.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He's still ___ machine?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Incredible. I remember that, in my day when we had Soapy
                        Williams and Wayne Fredericks. Wayne was very devoted to Nyerere. I always
                        considered Wayne was a bit of an ideologue, anyway. [Laughter] Never having
                        met Nyerere, I was a little suspicious at the time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Soapy Williams came through when I was the DCM, and because, of course, he
                    is a well-known Democrat, it was given to me to entertain him rather than the
                    ambassador. [Laughter] That was sort of interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Those tend to happen. Eventually you left in 1973.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes, 1975. In 1975, it came up what I would do next and, at this time,
                    Free Matthews was on the Egyptian desk and he was looking for a deputy. Sam
                    Gammon—I had kept in touch with him—was in the executive secretariat. So word
                    came out, “How would you like to go on the Egyptian desk?”</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>I said, “Fine.”</p>
                <p>It was, I think, probably the most exciting job that I had in the Foreign Service
                    in the sense that, in those days, Kissinger was the Secretary of State, Ford was
                    the President, and there was this tremendous effort for the United States to get
                    along with Egypt. We had had a break in relations that lasted about seven years.
                    We reestablished relations in December of 1973. I went onto the desk a year and
                    a half later.</p>
                <p>In that year and a half, the Egyptians were trying to get established here. There
                    was an effort to bring Sadat, who was the president of Egypt, to the United
                    States on a visit. We had never had a chief of state from Egypt visit the United
                    States. He was the first. Because, as the deputy in the old AFNE, and in AFE, I
                    had handled a number of state visits, when it was arranged for Sadat to make his
                    first visit, which was in November of 1975, Free said, “Okay. You handle the
                    administrative arrangements of this thing”—which I did do.</p>
                <p>The only substantive thing that I really added to that visit was, there was a
                    great deal of talk about the peace process—this effort to bring peace to the
                    Middle East—that it was an ongoing thing, that it would take many, many years
                    and, therefore, it was, indeed, a process. The thought was that President Ford
                    would be reelected, but we knew at that time that President Sadat had a bad
                    heart and had had a heart attack. So we thought that he probably would not
                    continue, and the effort to establish peace in the area would fall by the
                    wayside at some point.</p>
                <p>So the thought was, after the official visit here in Washington, I suggested that
                    we get these folks out of Washington—the two principals and the two secretaries
                    of state or foreign ministers and their families—to talk about the future—how
                    things should go forward if either of them falters. So some wealthy Republican
                    contributors in the Jacksonville, Florida area gave up their houses. After the
                    official visit, President and Mrs. Sadat and Foreign Minister and Mrs. Fami,
                    with President and Mrs. Ford and the Secretary and Mrs. Kissinger, went down to
                    these homes in Jacksonville and spent a long weekend. I think it was
                    two-and-a-half or three days. They talked about the future.</p>
                <p>We feel that this did work because, when President Ford was not reelected, the
                    transition, as far as the Middle East is concerned, to President Carter went
                    quite smoothly, and it led, of course, eventually to the Camp David Accords.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you really started that whole process.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>BEYER: Well, no. It was just a part of the whole thing. I didn't really, because
                    there were too many people involved to take sole credit for that, but it was the
                    one little thing that I did suggest and that they did agree to, to talk about. I
                    think that was good because we then saw Sadat here several times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's a note here you were at the US-U.N. in 1977. Was
                        that a full assignment or just a detail?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: It was a detail. We were on holiday up at Cape Cod at a family place. The
                    telephone rang—this is after I'd been on the desk for two years and I was up for
                    an assignment somewhere—and it was the special assistant to Roy Atherton, a
                    fellow named Abington by name, who said, “Roy would like you to go to the U.N.
                    to be with this new delegation that Andy Young is going to head.”</p>
                <p>The Department of State always assigns one officer from each of the geographic
                    bureaus to the U.N. for the General Assembly. The idea of that officer is to
                    meet with the senior members who come for the General Assembly.</p>
                <p>Both Molly and I had always wanted to live in New York, and so we said,
                    “Terrific. We'd love to do that.”</p>
                <p>Other folks said, “Why don't you want a permanent assignment?”—because this was
                    just for the General Assembly. It would only go from September through
                    December.But we said, “That's all right. We get to go to New York and we really
                    want to do that.”</p>
                <p>So we did do it. It was great fun.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By that time they were able to pay your per diem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: They paid marvelous per diem, yes, as a matter of fact. So we didn't have
                    any money problems at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I suppose there was a time there when New York was just
                        another home assignment and you didn't get paid anything.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>BEYER: That's right. No, the per diem was excellent, so we were able to live
                    reasonably. Actually, it was an interesting job because I wasn't reporting on
                    the Assembly. I was supposed to talk to these folks, these senior members of the
                    delegation, and so on. Many of the secretaries would sit all day, waiting for
                    the officers to come back and report on what had gone on at the General
                    Assembly. The officers couldn't get back until the General Assembly closed, and
                    that usually wasn't until five or six o'clock at night. Then they'd come back
                    and dictate their telegram.</p>
                <p>I would come back and forth during the day. I'd run over and talk to somebody,
                    come back, and the girls were just sitting there. So I was able to turn out all
                    this material. Then, when the other fellows came back who were reporting on the
                    assembly, I was done and away. So it was a great setup.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember anybody particularly that you met there
                        that was important or significant?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Two things that were significant, I think, to me. One was—as you may
                    recall, President Sadat went to Jerusalem. Right up to the very day, he got out
                    of the plane in Jerusalem, the head of the Saudi delegation, who I had gotten to
                    know, told me, “Sadat will never go. He simply will not do that.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>Of course, Sadat did do that. Sadat was one of the most unusual political folks
                    that I have ever had anything to do with, and a remarkable man.</p>
                <p>For example, one story about him—Hermannn Eilts was the American ambassador in
                    Cairo in these days. He got very close to Sadat. He used to go with him to his
                    villa down on the Nile, and he said that sometimes he'd talk with Sadat, and
                    Sadat would stop talking and would just think for 40 minutes. He just wouldn't
                    say a word. He'd just sort of go into this haze and just think out a problem.
                    Then he'd start talking again.</p>
                <p>Hermannn said, “I'd just sit there and wait.” [Laughter]He was that kind of
                    fellow. Anyway, that's one thing I remember about him that occurred.</p>
                <p>The second thing that I remember distinctly was, the number two in the Israeli
                    mission had been there for a number of years. People said that he knew more
                    about how the U.N. operated than anyone else. I wanted to get to know him, so I
                    kept working and working at it. Finally, I invited him to lunch at the Harvard
                    Club in New York. I joined the Harvard Club through some friends, and it wasn't
                    very far away. It's 24 West 42nd Street, just on the other side from the east
                    side—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right by the public library.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>BEYER: That's right. Right by the public library, not too far away. Anyway, I
                    finally got this fellow to come to lunch with another Israeli and there was
                    another American there. There were four of us. He had never been to the Harvard
                    Club for lunch. it was quite an impressive place to eat, and he enjoyed it. He
                    talked a lot. When the lunch was over, he was enjoying it so much and was
                    feeling so much at home, that they gave him the check. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was his name? Do you remember?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: I don't remember his name. I'm sorry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you went back for another fairly long spell in the
                        East African—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes. Actually, what happened is, I went back to Washington and Roy
                    Atherton said, “I want you to go out to Cairo to be the political officer.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Okay, I'll go to Cairo and be the political officer, but I would really
                    like some Arabic before going. I just don't think that, you know, I'm so new in
                    this whole Middle East business that I really ought to have at least some
                    Arabic.”</p>
                <p>As a matter of fact for the month of January, Roy and the head of public affairs
                    were in the Middle East, and so I ran that office—the public affairs office.
                    Then when they came back, we talked about what I should do.</p>
                <p>So he said, “Why don't you go to Cairo, and if you want Arabic training, I'll
                    arrange it for you at FSI.”</p>
                <p>Well, it's the best language experience I ever had. I must say, a marvelous
                    teacher, an Egyptian. We would work from eight in the morning until twelve, and
                    then she would say, “That's all you can do. What you should do now is listen to
                    tapes and work on the script. Then we'll go on with it the next day.”</p>
                <p>So I said, “Okay.”</p>
                <p>So I came home at noon, had lunch, took a nap—got in bed, took a nap—then sat up
                    and listened to tapes and worked on the script until about seven o'clock at
                    night. I did this for several months. Molly said, “I don't know anyone else in
                    the Foreign Service who could work things out where they spend all afternoon in
                    bed.” [Laughter]</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>In fact, it was a marvelous language experience, and the language was going
                    better than any foreign language I think I ever studied, even though it was
                    supposed to be a difficult language.</p>
                <p>But, about March or April, the fellows from AF, Bill Harrop by name, came to me
                    and said, “We need somebody to head the Office of East African Affairs—which, by
                    that time, was twelve countries—We don't have anyone to do it. We don't have
                    very many people who know anything about Africa, and if you do this for a couple
                    of years, we'll try to get you a mission at the end of it.”</p>
                <p>So I thought that sounded pretty good. [Laughter] So I went to Roy and I said,
                    “You have a lot of good Arabists.”</p>
                <p>And he did. There were a lot of good Arabists.</p>
                <p>“And I'm sort of Ezzat Arabist, at best. Africa is really hurting, and it seems
                    to me that it is in the best interest of the country and the Service that I take
                    this job. Would you object?”</p>
                <p>He said, “No. We'll catch you the next time.”</p>
                <p>But, as you know, in the Foreign Service there are routes that one gets on and
                    never gets back. So I left working in the Middle East and never really did
                    return.</p>
                <p>The job, as AFE, we had eight officers at that point and a variety of secretaries
                    and, as I say, these twelve countries. The thing that was interesting to me
                    about those twelve countries is, no one really cared about them too much. They
                    just wanted us to have reasonable relations with these folks. But the thing is
                    with these twelve countries is, one of them is always falling off the table. So
                    you are always running to catch it before it went splash. [Laughter] So there
                    was a lot of weekend work, and we were being called often by the secretariat
                    folks to work on one aspect of a country or another. But it was an interesting
                    experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was about to disappear down the drain. Now that
                        included all of the countries of the Horn of Africa except Egypt, did it?
                        Did it include Sudan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes, Sudan all the way down to Malawi and all of the islands—the
                    Seychelles, the Comoros.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some nice vacation spots.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right. Madagascar and so on.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any particular high points of that period that
                        you remember?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: There was one. Right at the beginning, as I mentioned, there was a little
                    extra time before my predecessor left. So they said, “Well, why don't you go
                    visit the area?”</p>
                <p>So the first place I visited was Ethiopia. The tradition in the old days in
                    Ethiopia was on Sunday, to go down to the lake—I forget the name of the
                    lake—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tana?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: No, further south. But in any event, and have a lunch at the hotel, and
                    either do some swimming, or some bird watching or whatever, and come back. So
                    the political officer said to me, “Why don't we do this—even though Mengistu had
                    taken over and our relations with Ethiopia were not so good—why don't we do
                    this? Would you like to?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Yes, I'd love to.”</p>
                <p>They were bird watchers. This is Andre Navez, I think his name was, and his wife.
                    The three of us went down in a big carryall. Well, we had a nice lunch.</p>
                <p>We were driving back, and Andre said to the driver, “Stop. Look at that
                    bird.”</p>
                <p>And there was a little bird, sitting in a puddle. So we got our glasses, and we
                    were looking at this bird. Suddenly, we began to realize that there was a
                    certain hubbub. We looked around the vehicle, and it had been surrounded by
                    Ethiopians. As we raised our glasses up from the puddle, we realized we were
                    looking right down the runway of Debrazite Airbase.</p>
                <p>Now we had given most of those planes to the Ethiopians but, nevertheless, these
                    folks were very unhappy that we had the glasses and that we were apparently
                    looking at the base. So they made a citizen's arrest, and they took us in to the
                    base.</p>
                <p>We were presented to the officer of the day, who was very suspicious of us, and
                    then heard the story. It was so silly that we were bird watching, that he
                    realized it probably was true. He had been trained in the United States. He was
                    a pilot. So he told these folks he would take care of it, and then relaxed with
                    us and was quite pleasant. But we went up the chain of command. Each time, a
                    more senior officer talking, the same sort of thing—initial great suspicion and
                    then realizing nobody but Americans would go bird watching next to a military
                    base with glasses—field glasses are prohibited to the normal Ethiopians—until we
                    got to the head of the base.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>Now the head of the base was a political appointee, and he was a Galla. Now, the
                    difference between the Galla and the Amhara are, as you know, very significant.
                    I mean, one is quite Negroid, as are the Gallas, and the Amhara are not. So we
                    got to this fellow, and he heard our story. He didn't think it was very funny,
                    and he didn't get very warm.</p>
                <p>But he realized that Andre and his wife were diplomats, so he said, “You two can
                    go, but you,” pointing to me. I did not have my passport. He said, “You are
                    going to Addis Ababa, and we will take you.”</p>
                <p>So Andre and his wife took off in the carryall, and got outside of the base, and
                    then waited for me to come out. They put me in a Volkswagen with a trooper with
                    an AK-47 behind me and a driver. We took off, going about 60 miles an hour
                    towards Addis Ababa—a little bit nervous on that drive, I must say. But the
                    driver was a nice fellow. He was, again, an Amhara pilot.</p>
                <p>So we got up to Addis Ababa, and there was a large wall to this facility and a
                    big, metal gate.</p>
                <p>I said, “Is this where all the government people were killed a few months ago,
                    eight or ten months ago?”</p>
                <p>And he said, “Yes, as a matter of fact, this is where it happened.”</p>
                <p>So the gates opened, we drove in. Andre was behind us. He had to stop. They
                    closed the gates, and Andre took off for the embassy to alert them.</p>
                <p>I, meanwhile, went in and talked to the officer in charge. Eventually—he again
                    was an Amhara—told the story. He said, “Oh, my God! You've just come out from
                    Washington and they've arrested you! We'll never get our relations with this
                    country going in any better way.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>I said, “No, you shouldn't be upset. They did exactly what they should have done.
                    It did look very suspicious, and no one but Americans would go buzzing around
                    this country with field glasses, looking at birds. It was probably not a very
                    good thing for us to have done.”</p>
                <p>So he said, “Okay. Well, you'll be meeting with the foreign minister tomorrow.
                    I'm sorry this incident happened.”</p>
                <p>By this time, of course, it's about 11 o'clock at night. “But we'll drive you
                    back.”</p>
                <p>So I said, “Thank you very much.”</p>
                <p>They opened the gate, and there was Andre. So they put me into his car, and we
                    went back to the charg�'s house. The ambassador was not there.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>He said, “What are we going to do?”</p>
                <p>And I said, “I don't know. It's your post.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>I don't know whether they reported it or, if they did, how they reported it.</p>
                <p>But the next day, the foreign minister was very apologetic, and once again I
                    said, “It really was my fault, not yours, that we got into this scrape.”</p>
                <p>After that, we had really quite a pleasant talk.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Great. What a way to break the ice! We haven't got much
                        left on this tape, but let's see if we can get you started in Uganda. I take
                        it that they made good—a rare experience in the Foreign Service, perhaps,
                        that they made good on their suggestion that they find you a post.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes. Quite a credit, and an interesting assignment, really.</p>
                <p>Well, we had selected a man to go to Uganda. He served primarily in Europe. He
                    had never served in Africa, and he had cleared all the hurdles that one does in
                    the Department of State.</p>
                <p>His name had actually gotten over to the White House, when he decided, “I don't
                    think I want to go to Uganda.”</p>
                <p>He had found out enough about Uganda that he decided that he didn't want to go to
                    Uganda. So, suddenly, we were without an ambassador to go to Uganda. The
                    assistant secretary at that time was Dick Moose, and this was about six months
                    before my two years was up.</p>
                <p>He said to me, “You have told me that you didn't want to go someplace dull and
                    boring in Africa. How would you like to go to Uganda?” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>I had never thought of it, but I said okay. Actually, I had picked the fellow to
                    get us started out there, Dave Halstead, who had been there as a junior officer
                    and was doing a fine job of getting the post started. So that's how I—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The post had been closed for how long?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: The post had been closed for about seven years. Dave opened it with just a
                    couple of folks, and then slowly we were building the post up.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Amin had already left when you got out there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you get—you got there in 1980, what time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: June of 1980.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the state of play? They changed presidents or
                        prime ministers about every three weeks.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: This was the third government, I guess, and it was called a military
                    commission. It was to hold elections. That was its only job was to hold
                    elections.</p>
                <p>The one thing that I thought was sort of interesting about that particular
                    appointment is, I was asked by one of the fellows on the political side of the
                    White House if I would like to talk to the President, call on the President.I
                    said, “Oh, yes. We would be very pleased to do that.”</p>
                <p>And so he said, “Would your wife like to do that, too?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Yes.”</p>
                <p>It was just a photo opportunity, obviously, but we thought that would be quite
                    fun. So he arranged it. We met—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was still Carter.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: This was still President Carter, yes. We met in Ham Jordan's office, and
                    he showed me the briefing paper that he'd sent to President Carter so I would
                    know what the President might ask, which was very generous of him. Then we went
                    into the President's office.</p>
                <p>So we talked a little bit about Uganda, and I was astounded how much he knew
                    about Uganda, I must say—very bright.</p>
                <p>At the end of it, he said, “Well, I want to wish you well and, because you are
                    part of my family, I want you to know that, if you ever get into any trouble
                    with the Department of State, and they are not being responsive, I want you to
                    come to me directly.”</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>I was astounded to hear this, because it wasn't in the briefing papers.</p>
                <p>So I said, “Well, thank you very much.”</p>
                <p>Then he kissed Molly, shook my hand, and off we went.</p>
                <p>So this fellow—his name has slipped my mind—said to me, “Did you get that
                    business about the family?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Yes. What is all that about?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, you may not remember this, but a couple of years ago, when he
                    first took power here and I came to the White House to work, I called you over
                    to give me a brief—Beard was his last name—to give me a briefing on
                    Somalia.”</p>
                <p>Tom Beard, I think it was. He was on the political side. He had raised money for
                    President Carter and the Democratic Party.</p>
                <p>He said, “I called you over because the Italians in New York were putting
                    pressure on us to do something for Somalia. I called you over to talk about
                    Somalia, and you did. You gave me a very good briefing on Somalia. At the end of
                    that, you told me about the problems that Hermannn Eilts had had in the sense
                    that the Libyans had sent an assassination team to kill Hermann, and between our
                    people and their security folks, they were caught, just after they crossed the
                    border. You said to me, 'Get Billy disengaged from the Libyans. They are really
                    bad folks.'”</p>
                <p>Tom said, “Well, I sent a note to this effect to the President and, as you may
                    recall, Billy disengaged from the Libyans, and it caused very little trouble to
                    us. That's the kind of thing the President never forgets, and that's why he
                    added this little comment to you so that you'd know.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was interesting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes. It was interesting, wasn't it? Actually, I needed—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ambassador Beyer, when we were so rudely interrupted by
                        the end of the tape, we had just finished your interview with President
                        Carter on your way out to Uganda. Do you want to get yourself to Uganda, and
                        tell a little about the hard situation you found when you got there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>BEYER: Well, I should begin by saying it was our favorite post, Molly and mine.
                    It was difficult in the beginning in the sense that security conditions were
                    really quite bad. We had a dusk-to-dawn curfew for our staff, and that lasted
                    for a year and a half. I am pleased, if not proud, that in the three years that
                    I was in Uganda, despite the mayhem going on, we did not have one person injured
                    or one person killed in those three years, despite the fact that, in all of the
                    countries surrounding, Americans were hurt or killed. We feel quite proud of
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have special security precautions that were
                        responsible for this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: No. We just had a disciplined staff. Indeed, a newspaper reporter at one
                    point came, after we'd been there six months or a year. We were in the back of
                    the British High Commission Building—quite a large building—and we occupied the
                    back half of it, on an alley.</p>
                <p>He said, “I don't understand this. Nairobi is a big embassy. It looks like a
                    fort, and it's got lots of Marine security guards. Why don't you have any Marine
                    security guards?”</p>
                <p>And I really didn't know what to tell him. But, having been a Marine officer
                    myself, I knew that we could not handle young men, young Marines. They just
                    didn't have the discipline that was required to live in that situation.
                    Obviously, I didn't want to tell that to the press. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>So I would say such things as, “Well, when we get into permanent quarters, maybe
                    we'll have Marines then, but we don't have them now. We are in, after all, what
                    is a British building, and it wouldn't look proper to have Marines.”</p>
                <p>The real reason was, we felt that it was too dangerous a situation to have Marine
                    guards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what did you have for security?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: We had a security officer from the Department of State, who was a
                    first-rate fellow. His wife was the GSO, as a matter of fact. All the women at
                    Uganda worked, either in the embassy, for USIA, or at the international school.
                    It was called the Lincoln School.</p>
                <p>Indeed, my wife taught at the Lincoln School, and the wife of the USIS officer,
                    who had at that post—his name slips my mind—Mary Lee was the head of the school.
                    It was about 60 per cent Ugandan and about 40 per cent foreign. Our folks were
                    helping it get back on its feet.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This all was taught in English.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>BEYER: It was taught in English because that's the official language in Uganda.
                    Uganda has very strong tribes, and I use that advisedly in the sense that you
                    can look at a person, you can look at a Ugandan, and tell what part of the
                    country they come from because the Nilotics of the north are very black and very
                    Negroid in feature, and kinky hair, and so on. The people from the west, the
                    Ankoli, are Semitic in origin like the Masai. They are tall, light colored,
                    straight hair, and aquiline features. Then those of the Baganda around Kampala
                    look like American Negroes. So the differences are really very distinct.</p>
                <p>One of the reasons that we were as safe as we were—I talked to Bob Keeley, who
                    closed our post, when I was going out there. Bob was Deputy Assistant Secretary
                    in African Bureau.</p>
                <p>I said, “Bob, how dangerous is it?”</p>
                <p>He said, “I don't think it's too dangerous if you identify yourselves as
                    Americans. The Ugandans have tried, because it was a British protectorate, not a
                    colony, to keep foreigners out of their political problems. Therefore, they
                    always considered that those who came to the protectorate, whether it was
                    teachers or administrators or medical folks, have come just to help. Therefore,
                    they have no antagonism towards you as an American. You are quite identifiable
                    because you're white.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Thank you, very much.”</p>
                <p>Actually, that was a principal aspect of our security—indeed, to the point that I
                    told Washington I didn't want any black Americans assigned to the post. That
                    didn't go down too well in Washington, needless to say.</p>
                <p>But, at one point, they did assign—Eddie Dearfield, the head of USIA, when he
                    went on leave, they assigned a young man from Howard University, who is black.
                    When he came into the office, I told him why I didn't want him there but, since
                    he's here, make sure he identified himself as an American so that they would
                    know that he is an American and not a Ugandan. He said he would do so. He was
                    very careful.</p>
                <p>But, after a few weeks, we had a plane that brought in supplies and the pouch
                    every week, and we had people go out on that plane to Nairobi for holiday or for
                    a few days' break. So he said he'd like to take the pouch and have a few days in
                    Nairobi.</p>
                <p>We said, “Fine.”</p>
                <p>He didn't have a lot of money, so he decided to stay in an Indian-run hotel in
                    Nairobi. That hotel happened to be near the radio station, and that was the
                    weekend that there was the attempted coup in Nairobi. He spent most of that
                    weekend on the floor, as the rebels tried to take the radio station and were
                    firing right through his hotel.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>So when he came back, if anything, he was a few shades lighter and said that it
                    is even safer in Kampala than it is in Nairobi. [Laughter] At any rate, he did a
                    fine job and left at the end of the summer when Eddie came back. He had done a
                    good job.</p>
                <p>But service in Uganda was interesting. I looked at the residence, and I thought
                    it was the worst residence I'd ever seen because it had been used as a French
                    school and had run down terribly. We fixed it up, and Molly worked very hard on
                    it. By the time we left, we considered it one of the best residences we'd ever
                    served in because it was a real, working house, built on the side of a hill,
                    actually near the top of the hill. We could see Murchison Bay from the house. We
                    could look down on the rest of Kampala. It was really quite lovely.</p>
                <p>Kampala, of course, is built on hills, much like Rome, and is a very lovely city.
                    It has a climate which, I think, most people forget about. Because it is high,
                    just under 5,000 feet, it seldom gets colder than 65 or warmer than 85, so it's
                    a climate somewhat like Southern California.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We spent some time up there, so I'm familiar with it. It
                        is one of the glory ports of the world, that African highland.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: It really is. Yes, just lovely. The one thing that I do remember is, I
                    arrived a week before Molly. So I arrived on Friday, and on Saturday I was
                    invited out to the Gayaza Girls' School. The Gayaza Girls' School is a boarding
                    school, out about 15 miles from Kampala. They were celebrating their 75th
                    anniversary.</p>
                <p>So I went out there and was put with the rest of the ambassadors and started to
                    chat with the fellow next to me. It turns out that he was the ambassador from
                    Burundi.</p>
                <p>He said, “You know, sometimes the reason the Ugandans are so difficult is just
                    because of this thing.”</p>
                <p>I said, “What?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, here we are, celebrating the 75th anniversary of a girls'
                    boarding school. You know, in Burundi we are lucky if we have a school that is
                    ten years old.”</p>
                <p>That was really quite true. The Ugandans were very highly educated, Makerere
                    University, one of the biggest, one of the best universities in Africa and of
                    long standing. It was a fine school which Amin ran into the ground, but they
                    were building it back up when we were there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the government situation as you got there and as
                        you progressed?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>BEYER: When I arrived, the military commission had just taken over. Their job was
                    to hold elections. I appealed to Washington for assistance, and they flew in
                    ballot boxes to help. The economic conditions that I mentioned, I think, were as
                    bad as the security conditions. The black market was rampant, and so on.</p>
                <p>At one point, I talked to the head of the military commission, and I said, “You
                    really better do something about the black market because it is impossible for
                    an American to do business here, or anybody, to do honest business here.”</p>
                <p>He said, “I realize that, but that kind of a decision, what kind of an economy we
                    have, we have to put off to the new government. That is a decision they will
                    have to make.”</p>
                <p>The political parties were reestablished. The Uganda People's Congress was the
                    party that [Milton] Obote headed, and the Democratic Party, the other major
                    party, was headed by Paul Semogerere. Then there were two other parties, the
                    Uganda People's Movement, UPM, which was headed by Yoweri Museveni, and who is
                    currently the head of the Uganda Government, and the Royalist Party, which also
                    didn't do very well.</p>
                <p>Museveni's party only won two seats, and he himself was not elected in the
                    election. The election was close. It was disputed. The Democratic Party
                    maintains that the UPC stole the election.</p>
                <p>Obote said, “If I was going to steal the election, I wouldn't lose all the
                    seats,” which he did, except one around Uganda.</p>
                <p>I think, in fact, that probably the UPC did win the election and, though a
                    disputed election, it was probably a better election than Mayor Daley ever ran
                    in Chicago. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Out of that came what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Out of that came Uganda People's Congress government, headed by Milton
                    Obote. He, as president, was elected. It works like the British system. They
                    elect people to the parliament, and then the parliament elects its officials.
                    Obote was elected by his party as president. There was also a prime minister and
                    a vice president.</p>
                <p>Paul Muwanga, who had headed the military commission and was a Ugandan, was the
                    vice president. The prime minister was from the north, and his name slips my
                    mind.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Baganda is the tribe around Kampala?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>BEYER: That's right, and a very wealthy, and a very highly educated tribe, as a
                    matter of fact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you began to run—for instance, I note that there was
                        a rocket attack on the Kampala barracks in 1982. Was that a significant
                        event, or was that just something that happened to hit the summary that I
                        read about what went on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: The significance of that attack is, the government maintained it was from
                    the Catholic Church, which overlooked the barracks. The rocket
                    people-guerrillas-went into the Catholic Church and used that grounds to fire
                    from. The government couldn't respond to the fire because they were afraid of
                    hitting the church. So they were very unhappy.</p>
                <p>Uganda is rather like Ireland, in the sense that I've never been in a country
                    where religion is as much a political factor and where it is so identified with
                    parties. The Uganda People's Congress, the UPC, the party of Milton Obote, is a
                    Protestant, Church of England, party. They have those colors. Anglican officials
                    are part of the party, and so on.</p>
                <p>The Democratic Party is a Catholic party and, of course, the Democratic Party was
                    the party of opposition, and they also felt that they'd lost the election
                    unfairly, so on and so forth. So you had this thread going through Uganda.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are those two Christian elements the vast majority?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Those are the vast majority.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In other words, there are no animists—well, there must be
                        some Muslims out there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: There are some Muslims. The Arab ambassadors maintain that their Muslims
                    in Uganda were about 22 per cent. Paul Muwanga, for example, the vice president
                    of the UPC, maintains that it was less than ten per cent. So I am not really
                    sure.</p>
                <p>But Yoweri Museveni, when he established this new party, this UPM party, Uganda
                    People's Movement, he wanted it to be non-sectarian. He wanted to get away from
                    this political party being identified with a religion. He talked to his father.
                    He was from the west himself. He was an Ankoli. He talked to his father, who was
                    a sub-chief out in the west, to join UPM.</p>
                <p>His father said after a long time, apparently, but right before the election,
                    “Yoweri, I can't join your party because I don't want to give up my religion.”
                    It was that kind of a feeling. It was really quite strange.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My wife would say the Christian church has a lot to answer
                        for.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: It was curious in Uganda because the largest number of foreigners were not
                    British or Asian. They were Italian, and they were Italian because they were
                    brothers, and fathers, and sisters, and so on, who taught in these various
                    schools. It was that kind of a difference, too, because the Anglican schools
                    maintained that they were training people to lead the government. The schools of
                    the Roman Catholic Church were schools to teach trades. So there was that kind
                    of a difference—almost a—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Proletariat.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes, between the two. Very, very strange. Very curious.</p>
                <p>One thing that I did want to mention, though, was about this business of
                    President Carter making this comment about help if I needed it. When I was there
                    just a couple of months, the director of AID, who had a very good reputation,
                    was married to a French woman and had a farm in France. So he took off for his
                    farm in France and did not administer a $3 million program to assist some folks
                    who were starving in Uganda in the far northeast of the country. These were very
                    primitive folks, but we had gotten this money but he didn't administer it.</p>
                <p>I was very upset, so I sent an eyes-only telegram to the head of AID saying,
                    “This officer is the kind of fellow who puts off until tomorrow what he should
                    have done yesterday.”</p>
                <p>This telegram made the circle in Washington and created a great brouhaha, to the
                    point where the deputy director of the Foreign Service sent me a telegram saying
                    that I had to apologize to AFSA, to AID, and so on—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To AFSA!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes, AFSA got into this because the AID folks in AFSA said, “You are
                    disparaging all of AID people and, therefore, this is really very bad.”</p>
                <p>So they said that I had to—finally, the deputy director general of the Foreign
                    Service sent this telegram, saying I had to apologize. I had decided that I
                    would resign rather than apologize. So I wrote a long letter to Tom Beard, not
                    to the President, to Tom Beard. I outlined the situation.</p>
                <p>I said, “This is what happened. I will not apologize and I will resign, however,
                    if this is what I should do.”</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>But I said I felt really badly about this because I don't know how many people
                    died as a result of not administering this program, but probably thousands and
                    maybe tens of thousands.</p>
                <p>I said, “That's pretty hard to live with.”</p>
                <p>The next thing I knew, everything stopped. I didn't hear anything more from the
                    Department. I didn't hear anything more from AID. I didn't hear anything more
                    from AFSA. It just stopped.</p>
                <p>So, eventually, I came back when the new administration came in. They wanted to
                    see who this fellow was, if he had two heads, or whatever.</p>
                <p>So I saw Tom and I said, “Tom, what did you do?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, I got your letter. It made sense to me. I went in to see the
                    President, told him the story. He said, 'Tom, take care of that for me, would
                    you?' So I just called the Secretary of State and the head of AID and told them
                    to knock it off.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>I said, “Thank you, very much!”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I must say, that's quite a story—how to have a little
                        backside protection. I take it this AID director was the only AID official
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: No. There were other officials, but he did leave within another month or
                    so. He quit AID, got a job working on the Ivory Coast as a consultant, for over
                    six figures—or high six figures, I was told.</p>
                <p>I was then very fortunate to get a young AID director named Buck, who was simply
                    first rate and did a marvelous job in the three years that he was there—just a
                    wonderful officer, and we worked very closely together. I was very lucky.</p>
                <p>As a matter of fact, one of the things that surprised me most when I left the
                    Foreign Service is, the people in Uganda—in AID, USIA, and the embassy were very
                    close. We depended on one another for safety and security. Every night, in those
                    early days in particular, we were on the radio, checking with everyone to make
                    sure everyone was okay.</p>
                <p>That kind of closeness and that kind of support extended even into the American
                    community. There were a group of missionaries there. We were all very close. As
                    a matter of fact, I was able to convince the American community—once we got the
                    pool working. It took us a year and a half to get the pool at the residence
                    going—to use the pool, and they did so.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>But when I left the Foreign Service and went down to this lovely place in
                    Lexington, in this lovely museum and research facility and library, and so on, I
                    couldn't believe how the people didn't get along. Here it's this idyllic
                    situation, and they couldn't get along, and yet in a place like Kampala, which
                    particularly for the first year and a half was wild, they got along fine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think you can tell a lot of stories about this. The more
                        danger it is, the better—or the more isolated it is, or the more
                        rundown.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: But also, part of it is the Foreign Service, I think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Depending partly, but also it is true that it is much
                        easier to coordinate things in the field than it is to get them to
                        coordinate it in Washington, which goes on. How did our relations with
                        Uganda develop over these years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Well, I was fairly close to Obote, because he had been exiled in Tanzania
                    for nine years and, during that period, I was there in Tanzania, also, for
                    three. So we used to talk about our experiences in Tanzania.</p>
                <p>When he took over the government in late December of 1980 and from then on, we
                    expected that we would see a form of African socialism. He was, after all, one
                    of the original African socialists. He did a 180-degree turn, however, and
                    became a free-marketeer. He got the government out of all these parastatals and
                    various economic activities. He would either sell them or just give them up, and
                    he would encourage the Ugandans to produce as much as they could and sell
                    wherever they could.</p>
                <p>Of course, by that time, selling food just to a place like Kenya was lucrative.
                    So the economic development in those three years that I was there—the two and a
                    half that he was in charge—it was a miracle. Talk about an economic miracle,
                    that really was one, and it was a marvelous thing to see.</p>
                <p>Obote maintained that it wasn't as big a change as we thought it was.</p>
                <p>He said, “You know, when I took over in 1962, when I was first president—prime
                    minister of this government—the economy was controlled by the British and the
                    Asians. The Africans were nowhere to be seen. I had to do something to get the
                    Africans into the economy, so I would just nationalize some industries and give
                    them to Africans, give them to Ugandans, and let them run it.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>“When I came back, Amin had taken this policy and distorted it to the extent that
                    he had driven the British out. He had driven many of the Asians out. He had
                    confiscated their property. And I realized that we needed those people to come
                    back to help us because we needed their skills.”</p>
                <p>This goes back to what Bob Keeley had said about the need for skills, that the
                    Ugandans were not unhappy about having foreigners come and help them.</p>
                <p>So Obote said, “That's why I pushed through parliament a law to give back to
                    Asians, and the Brits, and anyone else who had had property confiscated, we
                    would give it back to them. We knew we wouldn't get everybody back, but we did
                    get some”—which was true. He did get some.</p>
                <p>“We opened the economy because now it was not a question of getting the Africans
                    in the economy. There were too many of them, and they weren't very efficient.
                    What we wanted to do was to get them off the government rolls. We tried to do
                    that.”</p>
                <p>There is an interesting story, I thought, about this whole business. After the
                    new government took over, Buck and I, the AID director and I, met with the
                    acting minister of finance and the head of the commercial bank. These two men
                    were close to Obote and gave economic advice to Obote.</p>
                <p>So Buck and I said to these folks, “You've got to get rid of the black market,
                    and you've got to get a team to help you get going. Wouldn't it be a good idea
                    to bring in someone, perhaps, of a name who might do this?” [Robert] McNamara
                    had just resigned as head of the World Bank.</p>
                <p>I said, “Maybe it would be wise to get someone, if you could, like McNamara to
                    come in and be sort of an economic czar and run this place, to help you get
                    started.”</p>
                <p>They said, “Yes. That sounds reasonable.”</p>
                <p>So we agreed that they would report it back to the president and I would report
                    it back to Washington. So I reported it back to Washington, and I sent a copy to
                    Bill Harrop, who was the US Ambassador in Kenya at that point. Bill sent a
                    rocket saying, “It's unreasonable to get the Americans so involved in Uganda.
                    This is a bonkers idea.” [Laughter] Well, Washington felt the same way.</p>
                <p>They said, “Really, what you ought to try to do is get an IMF/IBRD team out
                    there, to give them advice.</p>
                <p>So I said, “Okay.”</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>So the next week we had our lunch again with these same two fellows—Buck and
                    I—and I said, “Well, Washington really thinks it would be smarter if you got a
                    team from the IMF or the World Bank to give you a hand rather than a well-known
                    American or a well-known anybody.”</p>
                <p>They went, “Whew! I'm glad you said that because that's the same way the
                    president feels.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>So they did get a good IMF team to come out, actually, headed by a Frenchman but
                    had a good reputation. That team would meet with ambassadors from donor
                    countries about every six weeks, as well as the key economic officials in the
                    government. They would explain what they'd done, and then they would ask donor
                    ambassadors if they couldn't coordinate their programs to support this overall
                    plan, which we did do.</p>
                <p>The result was, it wasn't very much money that we put in, but it was in key
                    areas, it was coordinated, and it was coordinated with some of the other things
                    that the bank was doing. The result was this sort of boost to the economy really
                    worked. The economic development just went forward very rapidly, and it was a
                    terribly exciting thing to see. It really was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there a little longer than Obote. You weren't
                        ousted until after Obote was ousted, I take it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: No. I left in June of 1983, and Obote was toppled by the military the next
                    year. Then the military was overthrown by this guerilla group that Museveni
                    headed.</p>
                <p>There's a story to that, really, because things were going along very well. Even
                    the security situation was getting better. The Army, which was a rag-a-tag
                    outfit was slowly, slowly coming into shape. We were all working on it. The
                    Commonwealth had a training team, headed by a British colonel, who had served in
                    East Africa, knew the Africans well. We were training folks, and so on.</p>
                <p>The Army was headed by a fellow named Ojite Ojok, who had gone to Sandhurst and
                    was not politically oriented at all. He was from the same tribe as Obote, so
                    Obote trusted him.</p>
                <p>When I left in June, they had almost overcome the insurgency. The Army was almost
                    back in reasonable shape. Then in September, Ojok died in a helicopter
                    accident.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was Ojite Ojok?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>BEYER: Yes. It wasn't until a couple of years later, when I was in Rome—we were
                    staying with the Italian ambassador who was the Ambassador in Kampala when we
                    were there. This Italian ambassador maintained that Ojok had been killed by the
                    East Germans. I don't know whether that's true, but the Italian Ambassador,
                    Niechele Martinez, was convinced.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why by the East Germans?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Because they had supplied the helicopters, or had supplied some of the
                    people that worked on maintaining the helicopters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sounds like an Italian conspiracy theory.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes, it does, and I don't trust helicopters, anyway. But what it suggested
                    to me is just how important one man can be, and with his loss, everything began
                    to unravel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Has it unraveled since? I'm not up to date.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As we leave, as the sun sets over the prairie and as we
                        leave beautiful Uganda—which is beautiful because I've been there—do you
                        have some thoughts about the possibilities of solving some of the insoluble
                        African problems, and whether what we've been doing—trying, and making some
                        progress, and then falling back—is worthwhile? You've already said that
                        certain countries probably can't usefully use our aid. What are your
                        recommendations for future generations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: I've written on this because, as I've gotten to know more about the
                    Marshall Plan, I've begun to see that there were certain basic principles in the
                    Marshall Plan which, if we apply them in our AID program, I think they would
                    work.</p>
                <p>One of them is, you have to let the people decide what they need and how to go
                    about implementing it. They can take advice from an IMF team, or from donor
                    ambassadors, organizations, their AID people, etc., but they eventually have to
                    decide what is required.</p>
                <p>Then secondly, I think that, if a country doesn't follow a free-market system—if
                    it isn't a market system that provides for private enterprise—I'm not sure that
                    our aid is going to work. But I know that it does work in Africa. The market
                    economy and private enterprise work in Africa and, if we follow that kind of
                    line, I think our aid can be effective. If we don't, I don't think our aid
                    works. It may work for somebody else.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>I was talking to one official in the African Bureau, and he said, “Well, in
                    Africa, most of the countries are going for market economies and private
                    enterprise. Now we've just got to make sure it works.”</p>
                <p>There are reasons sometimes why aid doesn't work. I mean, the reason Uganda isn't
                    working today is complicated, but Museveni has gone back to a socialist
                    organization and to supporting the consumer rather than the producer, and on and
                    on—not following what really were the basis of the Marshall Plan. So there are
                    some principles there, I think, that, if we follow them, they will work in some
                    developing countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Museveni is still the president, is he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Yes. Nice guy, actually.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The other problem that I have always felt we had was the
                        inability to think in 20- to 30-year terms, and to finance it, which is,
                        because of our budget system—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Well, I would disagree there, also. You know, the Marshall Plan was for
                    only four years.</p>
                <p>Truman said, “I do not want this program to get involved in the 1952 election.
                    Therefore, I want it to end before 1952.” Actually, the program ended in
                    December of 1951.</p>
                <p>I think that five years is a reasonable period to assist a country economically.
                    We were only on two-and-a-half years in Uganda when I left, and two-and-a-half
                    more years of that and they were going to be able to be on their own. They
                    weren't going to need any more help from anybody. Maybe something from the World
                    Bank or something, but certainly not from any individual country.</p>
                <p>I think our people would put up with a program that's limited—five years and
                    we're out—but enough of a program to make it work. I think that that should
                    be—in most countries that have any wealth at all—enough.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's get you just briefly back, because you left Uganda
                        and you went for a couple of years to the National War College.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>BEYER: Yes. I was the international affairs advisor, which is the number two slot
                    over there, and deputy to the commandant. The issue there was, when the college
                    was established, George Marshall was the Secretary of State, and he was very
                    instrumental in getting the National War College established. Kennan was the
                    first deputy over there.</p>
                <p>He established it because he said, “In the Second World War the Army didn't know
                    what the Navy was doing, and neither knew what the diplomats were up to.
                    Therefore, we ought to have a senior school, in a very relaxed way, where these
                    three elements can get to know one another—the Army, the Navy, and the
                    diplomats.”</p>
                <p>Now, of course, it includes the Air Force, and it includes some intelligence
                    folks, and so on. But that was the idea—not very structured, study national
                    security, travel together, and live together, and get to know one another so
                    that, when you become generals and admirals and ambassadors, you will be able to
                    talk with one another.</p>
                <p>After three years—maybe four—no foreigners were sent to the National War College.
                    Brits and Canadians were there the first three or four years, and then
                    Ambassador Durbrow said, “No. We're not going to have anymore foreigners, and
                    we're not going to have them because we want this to be an environment that is
                    open and free—where a speaker can come and talk about classified things, and the
                    students can talk about classified things, and not have to worry about having
                    foreigners there.”</p>
                <p>So there were no foreigners from that time, when Ambassador Durbrow was there,
                    until I was the number two there. In the second year, foreigners were
                    introduced. Well, I was very unhappy about that and wrote memos, and talked to
                    the folks in the Army, talked to the folks at the National Defense University,
                    talked to the people in State, and failed in getting the foreigners removed.</p>
                <p>Indeed, at one point, I ran into Ambassador Durbrow and—he's only about that
                    big—he got very excited and chewed me out for about 20 minutes for failing to
                    get the foreigners out of there. After 20 minutes, he sort of leaned back and
                    said—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Took a breath—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right. He said, “You know, I haven't been that angry in a long
                    time.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But he can be way off. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>BEYER: At any rate, I did feel unhappy, and I just couldn't get folks—either in
                    the military or in the Department of State to listen. The reason was that our
                    people wanted to send our best officers to the senior seminar, and the folks in
                    the military wanted to send their best officers to the Army War College in
                    Carlisle, to the Navy War College, and the Air Force War College. Therefore, NWC
                    is no longer getting the best and the top folks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't true in my day, and I don't think in your
                        day.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: That's right. So it was very frustrating. Indeed, not the year I was
                    there, the year after that, three officers who had opened their windows, did not
                    get promoted in the senior service and had to leave the service. There are
                    people at the National War College. I couldn't believe it, but that was what was
                    happening.</p>
                <p>Of course, today, increasingly, officers don't want to go to any of these senior
                    schools because they don't want to take that time out from getting through to
                    the senior service.</p>
                <p>So I'm not sure what the future is. I gather that at the NWC, there is thought of
                    changing it to become a research center and not a school at all, which maybe is
                    where it should go, frankly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This may bring up some questions of the talk, now that
                        it's time to take another hard look at the Foreign Service Act, and some
                        changes. Do you have any thoughts on this which, I think, has something to
                        do with this because a lot of the things like the senior service, and the
                        merit pay, and merit awards, and a lot of things of that sort, are in the
                        Act now and, perhaps, should be reexamined.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: I'm sort of a mossback in this kind of business. I still believe that
                    language training and area expertise is important. I still think that it is a
                    good idea for young officers to serve in various divisions in the
                    embassy—consular, admin, economic, and political. I still think that our best
                    officers are going to end up in reporting jobs, and that that's where they
                    belong.</p>
                <p>I don't believe in cones. I don't believe an officer should be stuck into a cone,
                    that he should, indeed, be able to go into various areas, and I believe that he
                    should get his administrative experience as he goes along, by running little
                    places. Therefore, I think that little consulates, small consulates, are a good
                    idea because it gets your best people out into the country in which they are
                    serving.</p>
                <p>Certainly, after two years in Hargeysa, when I went down to the embassy,
                    everybody thought I was the expert about Somalia. Well, maybe I was. You know,
                    there weren't many people that knew much about Somalia.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right. They've been out of touch with some of the
                        Somalis.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: And get out, running around in the country. I remember you encouraged me
                    to take trips. You know, every couple of months, get out and travel. So we tried
                    to do that, but I think that, therefore, the Service, as I knew it, was a much
                    better place to serve and work in then than it is today, where you get into
                    these cones, where you have this merit-pay business.</p>
                <p>I don't have any problem with the wives working, but there are lots of things
                    that they can do overseas. My wife worked in her first post, as I mentioned,
                    when Mrs. Johnson said, “Sure. You want to teach English to the Thais, go
                    ahead.”</p>
                <p>I think that wives can find interesting and good things to do, and the tandem
                    assignments, of course, is a problem, but it is not an insoluble problem. There
                    are some women I know who were very fine Foreign Service officers, got married,
                    decided—when they had kids—that it was more important to raise their kids, even
                    though they were outstanding Foreign Service officers. Maybe one day they'll
                    come back. I don't think the Service is as attractive a place to serve as it was
                    when I was in there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you say a little something about what you've done
                        since you left the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Sure. It was a year and a half that I was at the National War College when
                    I got a letter from Andy Goodpaster, who was in charge of the search committee
                    for the Marshall Foundation.</p>
                <p>He said, “Would you like to be considered for the head of the Foundation?”</p>
                <p>I had never thought about it, and maybe that's the best way to get a new job.
                    But, as I mentioned, I was having troubles at the National War College because I
                    couldn't get anybody to listen, and I was thinking, “Well, maybe I'm out of step
                    with this new Foreign Service. Maybe I should be serious about this.”</p>
                <p>The more I found out about the Marshall Foundation—I had some interviews, and so
                    on—the more I became intrigued with it. Ambassador Fred Hadsel was the director
                    who I replaced, though they changed—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Another old Somali hand.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>BEYER: That's right, another old Somali hand. They changed the organization
                    somewhat because they wanted the president to live in Lexington and be the
                    senior person, paid employee, at the Foundation.</p>
                <p>So, when they offered the job, I said, “Okay.”</p>
                <p>Since I've been down there, it's been fun, but it's also been very lucrative. It
                    is very hard to leave now. You get used to this substantial pension plus a very
                    substantial salary and, of course, they provide a house, and an entertainment
                    allowance, and a travel allowance, and all sorts of things. So it is pretty hard
                    to go back now. I'm not sure, also, that I could get up to speed to the pace
                    that the Foreign Service officers work at.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, on the other hand, it sounds, from what you've been
                        saying, that you have been able to augment your Foreign Service experience
                        with a little historical perspective here, and it's been a substantively
                        useful thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: It's been very useful because retired Foreign Service officers, or even
                    some still on active duty, have been very supportive to our programs. They've
                    come down to speak, they've come down to run round tables. So it's really been
                    very helpful. Having had some experience in the Foreign Service, so that you
                    could call these folks and ask if they'll give you a hand—because we don't pay
                    them anything to speak of—is really very useful. So it's been good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kinds of programs do you run down there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BEYER: Well, we have two aspects. One is sort of research and the museum, an
                    archives of two million papers, a current library of political and military
                    history, which we keep current with 25,000 books.</p>
                <p>The other side is outreach programs to younger folks, and we run the Marshall
                    ROTC Award Seminar in which we take the top Army ROTC cadet from the colleges
                    and universities around the country and bring them to Lexington for four days.
                    There are about 318 of these folks, and we have 20 round tables, and so on, and
                    major speakers.</p>
                <p>Then in the fall, we have the Public Service Leadership Conference, to which we
                    bring in former Truman scholars, former Marshall scholars, and some Europeans,
                    and then this fall some Asians, to study various problems.</p>
                <p>Then we have an undergraduate program where we bring young folks from surrounding
                    colleges and teach them to use original sources, which they've usually never
                    done, to write a paper.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>Then we have programs for high school kids and elementary school kids. For
                    elementary school kids, the program is called “try on a piece of history,” and
                    we use some of the materials from the museum, and we let them try on shakos and
                    jackets, and so on. Then we give them a tiny list of things to find in the
                    museum. In this way, they learn a little bit about a museum, what it does, how
                    it works, and so on and so forth.</p>
                <p>So these are the outreach programs to younger Americans. The idea is to try to
                    keep vital in American society Marshall's way and his ideals, and some of the
                    things that he stood for. He was quite a remarkable public servant. I think many
                    people feel he was one of the best, if not the best, public servant in the
                    twentieth century.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you very much, indeed, Ambassador Beyer. I think
                        this is going to be a major and most useful addition.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
