<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001647">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Ambassador Leonard Spearman </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2010-03-16"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2010-03-16"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR LEONARD SPEARMAN</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Ronald Palmer</p>
                <p>Initial Interview date: September 22, 1999</p>
                <p>Copyright 2007 ADST</p>
                <p>[Note: This interview was not edited by Ambassador Spearman]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is an interview with Ambassador Leonard Spearman of
                        Texas currently working at Coppin State College in Baltimore. Why don't you
                        tell us what you're doing at Coppin State, Mr. Ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Thank you very much, Ambassador Palmer. After a number of years in the
                    academic and several small</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's address that. You started as an academic and got
                        your Ph.D. at the University of Michigan, and what year was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: 1960.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then after that what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I was Professor of Psychology at Southern University in Baton
                    Rouge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's the period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: 1960 to 1970. I lectured at Queens College in New York during that
                    period, I lectured at Rutgers for a summer as a Martin Luther King Scholar
                    during that period, but basically I spent 10 years at Texas Southern as
                    Professor of Psychology.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had said that you were at Southern University?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I'm sorry, at Southern University. There are two because I
                    wasubsequently you will discover that I was President of Texas Southern
                    University in Houston.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So 1960 to '70, you were at Southern University in Baton
                        Rouge?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: In Baton Rouge. During that period I became completely engaged in a
                    number of social programs in that period, the Head Start, the Upward Bound
                    programs. My interest in the social psychology aspects dominated my thinking,
                    and I became involved in how to increase the numbers of minorities involved in
                    post secondary education and as a result became quite associated with programs
                    such as Upward Bound, such as Talent Search, special services for disadvantaged
                    college students, and the reshaping of federal student aid as it pertains to
                    minority students. I left Southern in 1970 to come to Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was in the Nixon administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes. I came here as Director of Student Special Services and remained
                    here 10 years as Deputy Associate Secretary for Higher Education.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was in the government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: In the federal government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see, so you were in the Department of Education?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: It was then the Department of Health, Education and Welfare, and of
                    course my last year here or the last year and a half here was when the change
                    was made separating out Education from Health, Education and Welfare. I have
                    served under five different secretaries during that period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Perhaps you could take us year by year, because this is
                        also an interesting insight into the evolution of the Department of
                        Education at the national level. You came to Washington in 1970, and what
                        was your initial job and how long did that last?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: My initial job involved three programs. The programs were designed for
                    the disadvantaged in higher education. If you recall, during the '60s, many of
                    the programs that focused on minorities and Appalachia and so forth came out of
                    the old Office of Economic Opportunity. Congresswoman Edith Green and Senator Ed
                    Brooke, I think, ought to be credited with moving many of these programs into
                    some kind of institutional arrangement within HEW rather than lose them. So Head
                    Start, Upward Bound, the Council for Legal Education Opportunity, the National
                    Defense Student Loan programs, all were brought into the U.S. Department of
                    Education.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Into the Department of Health, Education and Welfare?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Correct. Health, Education and Welfare, and we were the “E” in that
                    Health, Education and Welfare. Education had its Commissioner of Education at
                    that time, and our titles were nowe did not have the secretarial level rank, we
                    had the Deputy Commissioner, Assistant Commissioner.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what was your job title then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I came in as a director. There were five directors in Higher Education,
                    and I was one of five.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would be the GS designation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I came in as a GS 16.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were a super grade?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes. I was promoted to a 17, and that gets into another part of the
                    evolution which occurred during the Carter administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: First of all, let's kind of continue with the Nixon.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: In a year and a half, 18 months after I arrived, I was called in and
                    told that I was now in charge of all student aid administered by the U.S.
                    Department of Health, Education and Welfare.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your boss at that time? Who was the Secretary at
                        the time? Robert Cohen? No, he was a democrat.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: No, from New Hampshire or Massachusetts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll get to that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, because the number is unbelievable, from Casper Weinberger to
                    Califano, you name them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anyway, I am sorry, I interrupted.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: It's a very interesting story. There were two other minority directors
                    in higher education, the eminent Fisk scholar, Preston Valian, and the former
                    president of the All Women's College in North Carolina, Willa Playa. So there
                    were three minorities at that time who were directors in higher education all at
                    the super grade level and all having earned their doctorate degrees during that
                    period.</p>
                <p>After 18 months as a result of a reorganization, Peter Muirhead, who was
                    Commissioner of Higher Education, called and said I would like for you to take
                    over all of our student aid programs, all of our higher education programs
                    including student aid. This gave me approximately 21 discretionary grant
                    programs including the massive student aid programs with a budget of about $2.5
                    billion at that time.</p>
                <p>I stayed for 10 years, from President Nixon to President Ford and through two
                    years of President Carter, at which time he introduced what was knowand that's
                    why we go back to this GS 1at that point I am now a GS 17, then we were moved to
                    the Senior Executive Service category. When I left the Department of Education,
                    what is now the Department of Education</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What year? What year did it become the Department of
                        Education?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: '79, I believe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the Carter administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: In the Carter administration. And Patricia Roberts Harris is now the
                    Secretary of Health and Welfare and Education during this split period, and
                    Califano comes in as Education secretary and Patricia Roberts Harris takes over
                    the other “H” and “W” part of the operation.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is perhaps an insensitive question, but presumably
                        you came into the Nixon administration because you were a Republican?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: No, the actual fact is that I was a bureaucrat. I was simply a high
                    level bureaucrat, but the determinatioI was not a political appointee in the
                    federal government. So I came here really as the direct result of academic
                    qualification and experience in the field rather than any political
                    appointment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it's not unusual therefore that you transited the Nixon
                        to the Ford to the Carter administration because you were a civil service
                        employee?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I was a civil service employee, yes. I believe that when I was
                    interviewed it had absolutely nothing to do with the Nixon administration. In
                    fact, my political leanings did not occur significantly until after I was in
                    Washington but had little, if anything, to do with my appointment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did being a minority have anything to do with your
                        appointment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I wouldn't rule it out, but I think the fact that the programs which I
                    had dealt with at Southern were directed toward the disadvantaged, toward
                    minorities, I had worked with migrant workers in Texas, Florida, Mississippi, I
                    had worked with the Outward Bound program, I was on the board of Head Start in
                    Baton Rouge, and so much of the focus of five years had been directly involved,
                    so I could not deny that being black or being a minority was a determining
                    factor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The reality is that you were a deeply experienced
                        professional educator?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, I think that'you see, you asked the question what year did I get
                    the doctorate, but I had already spent 10 years in the academic arena while
                    earning the doctorate. I was on the faculty at the University of Michigan</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you get your BA?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I got my BA in 1947 from Florida A&amp;M. I was 18 years of age. I took
                    a master's at Michigan at 21 years of age and returned to Florida for four years
                    where I taught as a lecturer and an instructor in psychology. I then went back
                    to the University of Michigan. A part of this life that does not show itself is
                    that for three years I was a therapist at the University of Michigan Children's
                    Psychiatric Hospital working with severely disturbed children and also a
                    lecturer in the School of Education at the University. So 10 years had passed
                    between the time I took my master's degree and the time I took my</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you took your master's in what year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I took my master's in 1950 and returned to the university in 1954. I
                    completed my doctorate while I was working with a family with three children,
                    and I did a Ph.D. thesis at the University of Michigan and then went to Southern
                    University.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the title of your dissertation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: A Profile Analysis Technique for Diagnosing Severe Reading
                    Disability.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's extremely interesting. Now you left the Carter
                        administration in 1979?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: 1980 to be exact. I left the Carter administration in 1980 and on to
                    Texas Southern as President of Texas Southern University where I remained.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this the first time you had been solicited as a
                        potential university president?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: No, I suppose I haI am flattered, but let's see, I was asked to
                    consider any number of presidencies prior to Texas Southern. I hesitate to
                    mention names of institutions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why don't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Well, at one point Tennessee State made very strong overtures toward
                    me, Shaw University, Savannah State College, one of the institutions of part of
                    the University of California system had asked me. I have been offered at least
                    five or six presidencies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did you choose Texas Southern?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I think in 1980, my disenchantment with the federal government had
                    reached an apex. I came to thI felt that in 1970 when I arrived in Washington,
                    there was a moment of high creativity operating in the federal government, and
                    those of us who ran programs had a chance for a great deal of input.</p>
                <p>By 1977 or '78, we had become a completely legalistic organization, and every “i”
                    that was dotted, every “t” that was crossed, had to be legally approved, and
                    that was just stifling of intellectual people. It was not so much money, it was
                    not so much the salary, even though the salaries were low. People were beginning
                    to say, I can't take this lack othat is, people with an academic background who
                    were not born into the bureaucracy began to feel stifled. And so I began to
                    respond more aggressively, I suspect. The offers had occurred prior to that, and
                    I had passed them over.</p>
                <p>But all of a sudden a very distinguished elderly gentleman from Texas walked into
                    my office. His name was Ernest Sterling, and he was Chairman of the Board. Rumor
                    has it that he was very wealthy but in terms of a self made man and so forth. I
                    listened to him very carefully about the needs of Texas Southern University, its
                    location in Houston, and he said we need you. And I said, well, let me discuss
                    this with my wife and with my family and see what happens. I accepted the
                    position in a short period of time and went to Texas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you became president of Texas Southern University</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: July 1, 1980.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kinds of problems did you see when you went to the
                        university?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Well, Texas Southern at that point was in the midst of strong civil
                    rights issues as most Historically Black Colleges were involved. Texas Southern
                    had been neglected by the State of Texas. Texas Southern was founded after most
                    of your Historical Black Colleges. I'm not sure that you know that Texas
                    Southern was founded in 1947.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: And it has been called “The House that Sweat Built” because there was a
                    black man named Human Sweat who applied for law school at the University of
                    Texas. Through a series of actions on the part of the University of Texas to
                    keep Human Sweat out and finally to permit him to take classes alone with
                    teachers coming to him, the State of Texas decided to solve the problem of black
                    folks by creating a university. And they said it will be a university of the
                    first kind. We will offer pharmacy and engineering and law and all of the sorts
                    of things that were clearly pie in the sky promises. And after having created it
                    and its enrollment having expanded tremendously, there was this period of
                    neglect.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many students when you came?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: When I came to Texas Southern University, there were 9,600 students. In
                    fact, at that point it was the largest single campus, state supported
                    institution in the United States with one third of its students basically from
                    foreign countries, and most of these were from Africa or Iran.</p>
                <p>Texas Southern had been a victim of state neglect on the one hand and a failure
                    to provide competent management in some instances on the other. I came to Texas
                    in 1980 and embarked on a number of issues to reshape education at Texas
                    Southern University.</p>
                <p>The governor of the state was Bill Clements at that time, and Governor Clements
                    appointed me to a blue ribbon panel of four people to deal with the civil rights
                    issues. This was an extraordinarily tricky assignment because it dealt with
                    representing both Texas Southern and Prairie View. I guess my strongest ally in
                    this was a black woman who was in the Texas state legislature named Wilhelmina
                    Delco.</p>
                <p>Although a Democrat, Wilhelmina was interested in Prairie View having a greater
                    stake in the Permanent University Fund which everybody knows provides millions
                    of dollars each year to the coffers of the University of Texas and Texas
                    A&amp;M. Prairie View was this isolated little black college over here that was
                    a part of the A&amp;M system but was not a recipient of the goodies that were
                    part of the state coffers, and Texas Southern was the independent institution.
                    So as a result of this action, I think we made great progress in improving both
                    salaries, physical facilities, image, and so forth. And for the next seven and a
                    half years, I think that the campus of Texas Southern University changed, the
                    faculty's morale certainly increased considerably, the students sought in record
                    numbers attendance at Texas Southern University. So I had a great time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a moment that we ought to record for history. You
                        have modestly pointed to achievements. Let's be specific.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I suppose if I had to list</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your achievements?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Well, I think two or three things occurred at Texas Southern
                    University. I think the facade of the campus completely changed as a result of
                    our work at Texas Southern University. More buildings were constructed during
                    that period, renovations occurred, the interior of the campus was completely
                    modified. Academically our law school became accredited during my
                    administration.</p>
                <p>Our school of pharmacy not only regained its accreditation but was expanded to
                    include the offer of a doctor's degree in pharmacy. We became the third
                    historically black institution to receive accreditation for the Master's Degree
                    in Business Administration outside of Howard and North Carolina AMT during that
                    period. Our School of Education was accredited. We submitted the first clean
                    audit to the State of Texas that had been submitted in 10 years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is a clean audit?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: A clean audit means you have balanced your books and you can account
                    for all of the funds that you have received and expended. Every year of my
                    presidency from the first year, the state applauded Texas Southern as having met
                    all of the state requirements in terms of providing an up to date audit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to increase the number of PhDs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, we increased the number of PhDs . We also increased the salary
                    both at the base level of our PhDs and at the clerical and support level. I
                    suspect that was the thing that increased my popularity more than the faculty,
                    that secretaries and janitors were able to </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to establish an endowment?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, but very small. Here again it's extraordinarily difficult. Texas
                    Southern was 35 years old when I was president; Howard is 120; Florida is 100.
                    Any of the institutions, even Coppin State, where I currently work, is 100 years
                    old this coming year. When you have an institution which is an inner city school
                    and most of its students come directly from Houston, when you say you were able
                    to establish an endowment, it's a modest effort when you compare this to where
                    you have a long list of alumni and supporters. But during that administration,
                    we established a chair in the School of Business funded by TENECO. The radio
                    stations, the television stations united behind my administration as well as the
                    state representatives, the Texas legislature. I think more than any other
                    president in its history, I probably had greater support from the governor on
                    down. I think I may have been the first president in which the governor of the
                    state delivered a key note address on its campus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you know, I'm very grateful that we're having this
                        discussion because it provides insight into the types of qualities that were
                        perceived when the Reagan administration began thinking about choosing
                        ambassadors and so forth. You must have then been a prize choice for them
                        given your background?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Well, I think there were perhaps three things that elevated me to the
                    attention of the Reagan administration. I think the first has to be credited to
                    George Bush who I had known for a long time and incidentally whom I had
                    supported for the presidency when he was running against Reagan, as you would
                    expect, we were Texans, we were solidly behind him. But he had never lost the
                    relationship with me, and my first commencement speaker for Texas Southern was
                    George Bush, and he does hold an honorary doctorate degree from Texas Southern
                    University.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Wonderful.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I think George Bush kept in contact with me and I kept in contact with
                    him, and when he and his lovely life Barbara visited Houston, my wife and I were
                    often part of their company. And so we watched the Bushes grow, the older
                    Bushes, but we watched the children, the Bush children, in a sense grow up and
                    became to some extent familiar with them. We even flew with Barbara and
                    President Bush to the launching of the nuclear attack sub, “Houston.” So I have
                    had a number of opportunities to visit with him.</p>
                <p>There were two other factors. If we're leading to the issue of why the
                    ambassador's appointment, there were several things that occurred. When I was in
                    the federal government, most people did not know that Ford had sent me to Asia
                    to interview troops in both Japan and Guam and to help shape legislation to
                    provide for education of these soldiers upon their return. And if you recall
                    that war, many of the blacks were ill trained in the Vietnamese conflict.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ill trained or ill educated?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Ill educated, period. And so Sidney Marlin and I undertook the
                    responsibility of looking at these troops and talking with them and their
                    commanding officers and trying to find out what kind of programs we could put
                    into the federal government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is 1975?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, we're back in the '70s. I'm not regressing but I think it's
                    important to know how you get to a certain point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Secondly, I had represented our government at the UNESCO deliberations
                    on higher education in Paris.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: 1974 75. Thirdly, I had been appointed as chairperson of the
                    International Education Committee for the U.S. Department of Education while I
                    was president, and so the great picture with Senator Jim Bunning. He's a member
                    of Congress right now, he's been up for the Hall of Fame two or three times, and
                    he's a congressman from Kentucky. He was on that committee along with a number
                    of distinguished educators and so forth, and I ended up having to chair the
                    Committee on International Education for now the U.S. Department of Education.
                    And finally, President Reagan through Vice President Bush's nomination, had
                    nominated me to serve on the Board of International Food and Agriculture
                    Development. So I didn't exactly walk off of the streets in a sense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't descend from the heavens?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes. Now admittedly I had no idea that I would ultimately be appointed
                    or even nominated to be an ambassador, but I didn't come into it without some
                    knowledge, some awareness.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Exposure?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: And exposure. Let me also share something else with you. President
                    Reagan had asked me to be on the delegation to the 25th anniversary of the
                    independence of Kenya and the 30th anniversary of the independence of Ghana. The
                    State Department had also sent me earlier to Egypt to pair many of the
                    Historical Black Colleges of the United States with Egyptian universities in a
                    research effort. So when this pattern of apparently isolated international
                    exposures had taken place, it did not take away from the surprise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One might say you were a Bush rather than a Reagan
                        republican?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, I think that would be fair.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you a registered republican?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, but I was trying to answer the question about the 1970s when I
                    arrived in Washington versus the 1980s. At the 1980 level, yes, I was and remain
                    a registered Republican, so it perhaps made it easier for President Bush because
                    the line was certainly shorter in terms of the selection of individuals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean precisely that there are not that many
                        experienced</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I mean that there are just not that many, period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:black republicans.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: As I said humorously to Governor Clements one day when he was up for re
                    election, “Governor, if you want me to have a fund raiser for you, two cases of
                    beer and a phone booth would be sufficient to have all of the Republicans that I
                    know,” which is kind of interesting because the thing has changed in Texas
                    considerably since those early days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll come back to that. So, when were you approached for
                        the position in Rwanda which was your first African post?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Well, it's kind of an interesting story. One of President Bush's good
                    friends, but also a friend of mine in terms of support who happens to be the
                    president of a bank in Houston, we were leaving an affair one night, my wife and
                    I and his wife, and we were walking along with our little black suits on and our
                    bow ties, and he saiI was no longer president at this time</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were no longer president of</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Of Texas Southern at this time. And this was in the spring of '87. And
                    he said, “You know what your next assignment is going to be?” And I said, “No.”
                    And he said, “You're going to be appointed a United States ambassador.” And I
                    said, “Yup, and I'm also going to fly on the Apollo mission, and I'm going to do
                    a moon walk for you.” And he says, “No, no, I'm serious. I just left a vacation
                    spot with Vice President Bush, and you're going to be nominated for an
                    ambassadorship.” I kind of smiled and said, “Great, tell me this is a good way
                    to placate a warrior, the lone black Republican,” and my wife and I just got in
                    our car and left.</p>
                <p>Subsequently Clements was reelected. My son went to work for Clements, my oldest
                    boy went to work for Clements in Austin, and we called the governor, my wife and
                    I, and said we would like to come up and just say thank you for employing our
                    son and to congratulate you on your re election to the governorship of the great
                    State of Texas. The secretary said, “Oh, he would love to see you.”</p>
                <p>So we put on our Sunday best, we drove up to Austin, and we walked in, and the
                    Governor said to me, “How is Africa?” And I said, “I suppose Africa is in the
                    same place it was yesterday, it's doing well.” He said, “What do you mean,
                    you're not ambassador?” And I said, “No, Governor, I live just south of Houston
                    about 15 miles on a golf course.” He said, “No, no, you've got to be kidding. I
                    only wanted to see you because I wanted you to tell me about Africa, and I
                    thought you were home on some kind of R&amp;R.” And I said “No.” He picked up
                    the phone, and he called the Office of the Vice President of the United States
                    to find out what the mix-up was. And it seemed to me that my name had just
                    slipped with all the things they have to do.</p>
                <p>And shortly after, Ambassador, I have to tell you it was less than a month, less
                    than three weeks, I was sitting in my office on the campus doing what we as
                    professors do, and a gentleman stepped inside of the door and presented his FBI
                    credentials, and said I am here to interview you, and so the process began. It
                    ended with me coming to Washington to attend the language school, the Foreign
                    Service Institute</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had no French?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: As an undergraduate in 1944, I mean you know, that French.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the language study?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I think this is probably one of the finest parts of the Department of
                    State. I applauded every moment that I spent in the school, and while I did noI
                    probably would not have passed the examination at a 3.5 or 4.0 level, I think
                    that without it, I would not have been a very effective ambassador without
                    having some clear understanding of what the language was all about from a
                    speaking point of view and a listening point of view. I would hope that the
                    State Department never relinquishes that part of its operation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I trust that there is no danger. The Foreign Service
                        Institute is one of the best institutions for language training in the
                        world. But we're ahead of the game here now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, I'm sorry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were nominated?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: President Bush, then Vice President Bush, recommended me obviously to
                    Reagan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is '87?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: This is '87, late '87, because it goes over into the winter of
                    clearances, of Foreign Language Institute training, and things of that sort.
                    When everything was cleared, I was standing on the golf course at Country Place,
                    and my wife who never comes to the golf coursshe doesn't want to hear all the
                    foul language and see how much we're bettincame racing out to the golf course
                    and said, “The President of the United States has just called you,” meaning
                    Ronald Reagan, “and they want you to return the call at three o'clock and its
                    two o'clock.” So she didn't say anything to the people that I was playing with.
                    So I raced over to the car and got into the club house-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is what month?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I left in March or April, so this has to be in a cold month like early
                    February or something like that. Has to be in this period of time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you raced to the phone?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I raced to the phone, and my wife said, “You didn't tell me they want
                    you to be ambassador to Rwanda. Where is Rwanda?” And I said, “Well, let's get
                    an atlas.” And I picked up the phone and called, and they said just a moment,
                    and President Ronald Reagan came on the phone. To be absolutely precise, it was
                    during the time of the Bork hearings because I engaged the President in a
                    discussion about Bork's capabilities, at which point he discovered my academic
                    background.</p>
                <p>I said to him, I was a graduate student at the University of Michigan, and if you
                    had talked with me during the '50s, I was a Freudian buff. I read, I absorbed
                    everything that Freud and Jung and Ranke did in this business, but by the time I
                    completed my degree, I was no longer a Freudian. And I said our positions change
                    academically, and I felt that the treatment of Bork was a kind of political
                    witch hunt of an academic who has the right to change his mind. I don't
                    necessarily have to agree that I support Bork, but I do have to support the
                    academic respectability and freedom of an individual to write earlier a series
                    of articles of which he has the right to change. My wife was sitting there
                    looking at me saying, “You're talking to the President of the United States,”
                    and the President was sitting there saying, “I appreciate your comments, now
                    what do you think about this?” So this conversation went on I'm sure much
                    longer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long would you estimate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Fifteen to 17 minutes, I suspect. The tape will show that we had a very
                    good conversation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had not met him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, I had met him. Yes, I had not only met him, but I rather modestly
                    will share with you that we were also his guests at a White House dinner for the
                    President of Brazil. Again, George Bush haI was president of Texas Southern at
                    the time. And so we had been to the dinner. I had met him then. I had also met
                    him at a luncheon for the Historical Black College presidents. Did he know me?
                    The answer is probably not. But the answer is I did meet him. I also met him
                    when he was running for the presidency.</p>
                <p>I would like to just share that real quick story with you. I think it's an
                    interesting story. I was about to come to Washington, and I was at the airport
                    when my assistant, Dr. John Lash, called, and said the governor wants you to
                    call him. And he said call before you get on the plane because he has an
                    assignment for you.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>So I called the office, and the governor said, “Yes, President Reagan is coming
                    to Houston for a fund raiser and we want you on the program to deliver the
                    invocation.” And I said, “Governor, there are a lot of things that you may want
                    me to do, but prayer is —” He said, “And there are a lot of things that you may
                    want in life that a good prayer won't hurt a college president to deliver.” So I
                    prayed individually for all of the Republicans as they lined up, I prayed for
                    Phil Gramm, and I prayed for George Bush. I did individual prayers all the way
                    down the line because I wanted to be sure that the Lord heard our plea for
                    this.</p>
                <p>That was one of the cute little things, but the great highlight for my wife was
                    the night that we were invited to the President's. I believe Jonas Salk, I
                    believe one of the Huttons was at our table, and we had a chance to</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This for the President's</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes. So anyone who says, “Oh, if the President invited me to dinner, I
                    wouldn't go,” would have to be telling the biggest untruth that I have ever
                    heard. It was a marvelous experience for us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I appreciate what you're saying with regard to being
                        invited to the White House or indeed being addressed by the President of the
                        United States. It's a very special situation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Anyway, so you were sworn in as Ambassador to Rwanda when, in 1981?</p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: No, 1988, spring of 1988.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And when did you get there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: April. Prior to going now, the entire family went to the White House.
                    One of our colleagues said to me, the only advantage that we non career
                    ambassadors have is that we get an invitation to visit with the President and
                    get cuff links while you guys spend all of your time studying to be ambassadors
                    and you have to go straight to post. But the non-career ambassadors are invited,
                    and so my wife and my three children all walked in, and President Reagan greeted
                    us. An absolutely fantastic memory, the man's abilities and training from the
                    movies, plus his own natural instincts are unbelievable. He greeted us as if we
                    all went to college together, and with individual names and the warmth that was
                    so evident of Reagan. But, yes, I arrived at post and I lefdeparted for Kigali
                    and arrived in early April 1988.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is 1988?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had the troubles in Rwanda begun by then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: No. They started shortly afterwards. For the first year and a half or
                    so, outside of some conflicts that had occurred between the Burundi Tutsi and
                    Hutu, which lefshortly after I arrived, there was an insurrection in Burundi,
                    and that put about 100,000 people in refugee camps, and we had to address that
                    matter immediately. And now this experience in the Foreign Service Institute
                    becomes very important because the Germans, the French, the British, all of us
                    were working together to try to address some very critical problems that
                    occurred.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel comfortable- (End of tape)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>All right. This is the second iteration of an interview with Ambassador Leonard
                    Spearman. We had to break off the last interview because he went overseas to
                    South Africa in his capacity as special assistant to the president of Coppin
                    State College where he is at the present time and pursuing his interest in
                    energy matters. After South Africa, he then went on to West Africa, and we will
                    try to pick up his contemporary activities later, but today let's focus on your
                    experience in Rwanda. When did you go to Rwanda, Ambassador?</p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I was confirmed by the Senate in the spring of 1988 and got to post in
                    April 1988. This was toward the end of the Reagan years, and I was asked to
                    assume the post at that particular time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you left Rwanda when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I left Rwanda in December of 1990.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the troubles in Rwanda began when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Well, actually they began in September of '89. An interesting anecdote
                    on that, without boring you, is that President Habyarimana and I were both in
                    Washington at the Grand Hotel, and there was a reception in his honor by the
                    Rwandan citizens and the embassy here. During the course of the evening, Irving
                    Hicks, who had served as ambassador on two different occasions and was Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary for African Affairs, walked up to me and quietly passed me a
                    note and said, “Go home, your country is at war.”</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>I was absolutely flabbergasted. While there were many telltale signs that the
                    conflict was brewing, I don't think any of us expected it at this point. The
                    next morning, of course, I departed on Air France, we kind of bypassed the Fly
                    American rule, and I flew Air France to get the connection and go straight to
                    Kigali.</p>
                <p>But it didn't work out that way. When we got in Paris, we were joined by of
                    course the Libyan ambassador, the foreign minister, the French ambassador. All
                    of us were trying to speedily return to troubled Rwanda. We got to Nairobi, and
                    Air France took us to Bujumbura, and I had to spend the night with Ambassador
                    Cynthia Perry.</p>
                <p>The next morning the Belgians flew a flight over and picked about 15 of us up who
                    were virtually stranded. I mean, here we were generals without troops, separated
                    from our troops and our families. So after a path was cleared, we were able to
                    land successfully in Rwanda to discover that the Tutsi rebellion had marched
                    into Rwanda from Uganda.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You spoke of telltale signs, what were the telltale
                        signs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Well, there was a considerable amount of unrest among the Tutsis. The
                    Tutsis in Rwanda are indeed, were at that time indeed well trained, well
                    educated, but were really afforded second class citizenship.</p>
                <p>There were two major telltale signs. The first, the Soviet ambassador, Ambassador
                    Sakharov, asked me to come to his residence one day where he presented me with
                    photographs of the unloading of semi armored vehicles at Entebbe which were all
                    pointed south. The Ugandan explanation for this was that it was in preparation
                    of the summer bivouac. The Rwandan government under Habyarimana had very little
                    confidence in the Ugandan government, so Foreign Minister Bizimungu approached
                    me and told me that there was really evidence that there was going to be an
                    attack.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When was this approximately?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Oh, these events were occurring from February through September of
                    '89.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is of '89?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Of 1989. I can recall vividly him asking me whether I would intercede
                    on his behalf to ask President Bush if we would send a Stealth plane over to
                    monitor. And I said while there is a very strong Texas connection between
                    President Bush and Leonard Spearman, it is unlikely that I would be able to do
                    that.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>But what he was doing was appealing for help at that point. They were aware of
                    the military power of the</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “He” is the</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: He, meaning Foreign Minister Bizimungu.</p>
                <p>A third signal was my wife and I were invited to a private party at one of the
                    President's homes away from Kigali. There were only three people present, the
                    President, the Foreign Minister, and me, and our wives, of course. During the
                    course of that evening, the President expressed grave concern about several
                    things: one, the brewing pressure of democratization on him to create a multi
                    party system; two, the growing concern about the Tutsi rebellion which was
                    stirring in southern Uganda; and, three, a very real concern that the United
                    Nations had not responded positively to eliminate much of the pressure and
                    suffering of the Tutsis who were in refugee status in Uganda.</p>
                <p>It was interesting becauslet's take the first one, the growing pressure of
                    democratization. President Habyarimana was reeling under very real pressure on
                    both sides. The West was saying create multi party systems, create democracy,
                    eliminate the green cards, and open the society.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Green cards?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I use green cards here to mean identification cards. “I am a Tutsi and
                    I carry my card” kind of thing.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, his hardliners were saying, can't you remember? Don't you know
                    who these Tutsis are? These are the same people who 50 years ago kept us in
                    bondage and kept us suppressed and kept us on our knees and told us that we were
                    farmers and told us that we were nothing, if anything, and they were the sons
                    and daughters of kings and queens. So here was this dynamic president saying, I
                    really want to respond to the West because I need your bilateral support in the
                    sense of aid to our country, but on the other hand, I do know that these
                    hardliners are telling me that the Tutsis are going to take us over. Well, he
                    was nervous, he was not sure even of Museveni's role.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Museveni?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: The President of Uganda. President Habyarimana was a man on a hot wire.
                    Every move he made to accommodate the West and democracy was interpreted as a
                    weakness on the part of his own hardliners. So the Arusha Conference became an
                    absolute disaster for him because he was thinking, “I don't know where to
                    go.”</p>
                <p>I think this is the part of the thing, Ambassador Palmer, that fuels the
                    speculation of who killed him. I mean, who shot the plane down? Was it his
                    hardliners who said he's going too far, he's giving away the store? Was it the
                    Tutsis who said we have got to do something? I think I grew up diplomatically
                    during these discussions and during these crises that occurred as to the kind of
                    philosophical, moral pressures that were operating in the society.</p>
                <p>So there are those who say that Habyarimana was a benign military, not the</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Benign authoritarian?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Benign authoritarian is the more appropriate expression. Well, surely
                    enough, the conflict did surface. The Soviets had alerted me, the Soviets werI
                    don't think that they thought that they would be involved in it. I felt that
                    they were simply saying, this is a western problem, and I don't know how to go
                    to the Belgians and the French on this, and in a sense, I thought Sakharov was
                    reading us as his closet ally to say something is going on over there and you
                    guys are better equipped to get into it because our role here is limited. We
                    train mathematicians and physicists and engineers, but we don't want to get
                    involved in the dirty linen of armed rebellion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's worth reflecting on just for a second, the fact
                        that by the late '80s, the Russians had had their fingers burned here and
                        there in many places in Africa, and I just don't recall that they had a
                        particular policy. They were dragged into Angola, as it were, by the
                        Cubans.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In any event, I think history would welcome your insights on how this boiling
                    anger erupted. What was behind it? You said before that the Tutsis had this
                    memory of being kings and queens and the Hutus of being serfs, of being
                    servants.</p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Well, without pretending to be a Rwandan scholar, there are certaithere
                    were certain exposures and certain information that I was privy to. If you look
                    at the society prior to 1900, the Germans were present. The hierarchthere was a
                    balance here. The Tutsis said, we will provide cattle and military support, and
                    you provide us with grain, and we'll try to get along.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “You” being the Hutu?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, you meaning the Hutu, and we'll try and get along. The Germans, of
                    course, came in, and stayed until roughly 1915, and they began to paint the
                    Tutsi as a superior group. Anthropologically, they had the thin lips, tall, the
                    thin noses, as opposed to the squatty, short anthropological or anthropometrical
                    types.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Bantu?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: The Bantu groups. And so the Germans orchestrated this in a way in
                    which there was this three tier caste system. We're at the top, the Tutsis are
                    here. And so the Belgians, who reluctantly accepted this trust territory, said,
                    hey, if it's working for the Germans, let's maintain the same system. So the
                    Hutus worked their backs to the bone to provide corn and vegetables and fresh
                    fruit which were really taken off the top through their Tutsi
                    representatives.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it a feudal system?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: It was clearly a feudal system. Some people claimed that the
                    introduction of money contaminated the system completely, that it was a feudal
                    system, but it was a feudal system based on mutual jobs rather than the presence
                    of wealth per se. But when wealth and dollars, when francs got into the picture,
                    the system of course became more and more corrupted.</p>
                <p>In 1955, '56, '57, the Hutus appealed to the Belgians for equality and equal
                    treatment. The Tutsis rejected their request and said that they were the sons of
                    kings and queens and these were squatters and peasants and were condemned
                    forever to toil the soil. After two or three years of attempted negotiation, the
                    Hutus struck back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is 1960?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: This is 1957 through 1960, and please forgive me on my times, but this
                    is in the late '50s. They struck back with machetes, and because they constitute
                    85 percent of the population, they virtually decimated the Tutsi population,
                    driving them into Tanzania, to southern Uganda, to Zaire, and some fled into
                    Burundi. At this particular point, the military role of the Hutu became more and
                    more confident and ultimately took over the government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the early '60s?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: This is the early '60s. Habyarimana, I believe, was the second elected
                    president of Rwanda. Kayibanda was the first one, the airport in Kigali is named
                    after him. And so there was always this uneasy peace. “We in Uganda are truly
                    Rwandans, we are coming home one day. We want to come home.”</p>
                <p>On the other hand, Rwanda, the size of the State of Maryland, 7.4 million people,
                    growing at an extraordinary rate of 5 to 6 percent a year</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Five to 6 percent a year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes.is saying what are they coming home to, what are they coming home
                    for? Why doesn't the Ugandan government... Well, at first the Ugandans had
                    welcomed them because Idi Amin and the others had capitalized on this tremendous
                    brain power and prowess of the Tutsi warriors and military leaders. They were
                    excellent teachers, they were good businessmen, and things of that sort. But now
                    the Ugandans</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is the period here, is it the 1960s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: We're in the '70s now. The Ugandans apparently were growing a little
                    weary that their refugees had remained a long period of time. So they probably
                    were under great pressure to rid themselves. I would not be surprised that they
                    were under some pressure to say that these people are taking our jobs, we want
                    them to go home. They are really Rwandans. And Habyarimana is saying, no, I
                    don't want you back because we are fearful of the retribution and the skill that
                    the Tutsis have, and we are doing pretty well here, we've got a nice peaceful
                    society, and everybody is in place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I just find that note, a nice peaceful society, what is
                        very difficult to make sense of is the violence, is the hatred, is the
                        extent to which the Hutus really apparently tried to eliminate, took
                        genocidal action against the Tutsis. How do you explain that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Well, I think you have to put both countries together. I think you have
                    to put Burundi and Rwanda together. I think you have to ask yourself, here are
                    two mirror countries, Burundi at the south, Rwanda to the north. In the south,
                    the Tutsis were the dominant military power and the dominant power. Even though
                    they were only 15 percent of the population, they controlled 85 percent of the
                    Hutus in Burundi. Now, right across the border, this is a split territory, here
                    is Rwanda, it's 85 percent Hutu, but now we are on top and the 15 percent</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “We” being the Hutus?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: We being the Hutus. We do not want that to occur to us. We are refusing
                    to go back to a system in which 15 percent of the people up here will control us
                    again. So there was this fierceness, there is this hatred, even though there had
                    been intermarriages, and anthropologically you could not tell in many instances
                    the Hutu from the Tutsi, but they knew.</p>
                <p>Now secondly, it's very difficult for us to see as Americans the closeness with
                    which seven million people live in an area the size of the State of Maryland,
                    which means that there is no place that you can turn that there are not people,
                    even though as you travel along the highway you say to yourself, there is nobody
                    here, stop, just stop, get out of your car, and then 50 people will be there
                    before you know it.</p>
                <p>I turned over in a vehicle on my way to a golf course on a slick, sandy road. It
                    appeared that before the roof could touch the ground, they had turned the car
                    back over. It didn't occur that rapidly, but the point is, it was almost as if a
                    wrecker, but it was a human group of men who said, ah, and I knew just enough
                    Kinyarwanda to say I'm in trouble, and the car was flipped over. But there was
                    no one as I turned that curve. That's the point I'm making.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this is an important point. The effect of
                        demographic pressure, population density, and that thing where sometimes as
                        in animal experiments you have species biting, fighting, killing each
                        other.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Well, listen, here in the United States, an increase in violence occurs
                    as you decrease the amount of space. What we have got here are people who are
                    here together, who are afraid. The radio is the primary means of communication.
                    Now a few zealots get on the line and say these Tutsis are coming back, you must
                    destroy them. These cockroacheis the proper term for which they used to refer to
                    thethese cockroaches will take us over, they will maim our children and so
                    forth. You must destroy them. If I repeat this on the radio village by village
                    by village, and I have got this tremendous, as you point out, demographic issue
                    of population density, how long does it take a group of 25 Hutu to destroy with
                    machetes and stones an entire village of helpless people? The answer is it
                    doesn't take very long.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, we're going to pass on now to your next post. But I
                        want to just reflect on the fact that we have just seen, as it were, tribal
                        violence in Kosovo, we saw it earlier in Bosnia, and it's useful to remember
                        that these types of killings have taken place here in North America,
                        specifically vis a vis the Indians. Unfortunately it is a part of our
                        inheritance, not to mention the 30 Years War and what happened in that
                        period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>So you left Rwanda in December 1990?</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I left Rwanda in December. I came back for confirmation hearings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were assigned to</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Lesotho. I had received a very lovely message from President Bush
                    stating that we had been without an ambassador in Lesotho for 18 months, and he
                    was afraid that this was conveying the wrong message and that he would
                    appreciate it if I would remain in Rwanda until a successor was confirmed
                    because the war was going on at this point, and as soon as that occurred, then
                    he would like for me to prepare to move.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your successor?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Robert Flaten. I came home in December, spent Christmas with my family
                    and the grandchildren, and then in January we were off to Lesotho.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: January 1991?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, and if we can think of the date in which the American forces, the
                    United Nations forces invaded Iraq to push back the Iraqis, it is the same date
                    in which we were flying.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was the launching of Desert Storm?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Desert Storm. I always remember it by that. And off to Maseru we
                    went.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Broadly, how would you compare, maybe first impressions,
                        but how would you compare Lesotho with Rwanda, both of them being
                        agricultural societies?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Well, both are small. Lesotho, of course, is more mountainous. Maseru
                    is about 5,000 feet above sea level, and the entire country gets up to in the
                    northern part about 11,000. It's rocky in terms of its terrain, less population
                    density, only two million people in the entire country as opposed to seven
                    million people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is the size of Lesotho?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Roughly the same as the State of Maryland. But the population of
                    Lesotho iI mean, the size is not much greater than the State of Maryland. It is
                    located in the belly of South Africa. That is, you can't go into Lesotho or out
                    of Lesotho without traveling into South Africa. It is extremely influenced by
                    South Africa because its economy depended owhile the French and the Belgians had
                    a great deal of influence in Rwanda, now I'm moving to South African influence,
                    British influence.</p>
                <p>I am moving from a Francophone country to an Anglophone country. I'm moving to a
                    country with no television, and very strict rules of Catholicism regarding the
                    conduct of women and young women under President Habyarimana to a mora little
                    bit freer society because of access to television, access to local hotels, there
                    were more bars and restaurants available, and while there was limited travel out
                    of the country, people were able to go out of the country even though that
                    travel was limited to perhaps Swaziland or Botswana or South Africa.</p>
                <p>The National University of Rwanda was largely a Catholic, self contained
                    university. The National University of Lesotho was formerly the BLS, the
                    National University of Botswana, Lesotho, and Swaziland. So the education of
                    these people took on a little broader scope, and, interestingly, Lesotho had the
                    highest, among developing nations, has the highest rate of literacy among women
                    of any country in the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why is that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: The phenomenon is probably caused by the fact that men ritualistically
                    enter into the mines at an early age in South Africa. It is kind of expected
                    that you will go across the border into the gold mines, the diamond mines, the
                    coal mines, to earn a living. After all, 76 percent of the gross national
                    product of Lesotho at the time I arrived came from South Africa. So it was, “I
                    hate you, but I can't live without you.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just a quick insert. It's interesting that it would
                        suggest that the women had to be trained up, had to carry on activities in
                        the country, which reminds me of the Vikings. The Vikings periodically went
                        away and the women had to take on roles of the men.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: It's the same. That's an important point because it's wortthe students
                    at George Washington who want to understand the nature of mining and so forth,
                    or any students for that matter, to visit because these camps are
                    extraordinarily complex and elaborate operations, with dormitory facilities</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is in South Africa?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: In South Africa.with pool halls, with tennis courts, with everything
                    that you want to see. And on Fridathese workers must work two weeks rotation
                    before they go home. Now I'm looking at the South African side because I'm
                    looking at the men at this particular point. Now as unprecedented as this is,
                    these men really have to struggle to get home with their money because the
                    prostitutes are lined up on the outside of the place. They know when payday
                    comes, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was going to ask, with so many other needs taken care
                        of, what the situation was with regard to the sexual needs of the
                        workers.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: This is a big business out here. If you drive up to these camps, from a
                    distance they look like a huge institution of higher education, except that you
                    see the mounds and mounds of dirt that have been removed from the depths of the
                    earth. And I fortunately have had the experience of going deep down into a gold
                    mine a mile below the earth. South Africans weren't comfortable with having an
                    American Ambassador down that deep, but we did participate in that.</p>
                <p>Now you've got to get back over here. Here is the problem, because this is an
                    important point. As the squeeze on apartheid and the squeeze on the exportation
                    of diamonds and gold from South Africa</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because of the sanctions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Because of the sanctions. Now you have a problem. The South Africans no
                    longer need all of these workers from Swazi and Lesotho, and so between 1991 and
                    1993, I saw the gross national product of Lesotho that depended on South Africa
                    drop from 76 percent to 51 percent.</p>
                <p>Now, in the meantime, the women are at home. Sure, they get more education, they
                    do the farming, they do the rearing of the children, they are primarily
                    responsible for that. But Lesotho was changing. There was gambling in Lesotho's
                    hotels, which is allowed by law but not South Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The South Africans ran these enterprises?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Of course, the Sun Enterprises is in all of the free states in
                    essence.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I met the man who is responsible for the Sun Valley
                        Enterprise because he also owns casinos in Mauritius. I can't think of his
                        name now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I didn't mean to get off onto that, but the point is, when I arrived,
                    General Lekhanya was the military head of the government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a military government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There had been a coup?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, there had been a military government in Lesotho. Lekhanya
                    haGeneral Lekhanya had taken oveall right, this gets a little complicated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's all right. He had taken over.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: It's a monarchy, you have to remember, King Moshoeshoe. The prime
                    minister was running the country, Lekhanya. The king kept interfering allegedly
                    into the operation of the government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is the period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: We're dealing in the late '80s. So the King had been exiled on one
                    occasion, and finally they said to the king, you have to go to London, you have
                    to leave. The king left, he left his wife, the queen mother, and a son, which
                    gets very important. And I'm going to have to edit this thing, but Lekhanya was
                    unpopular with the South Africans. Lesotho was also a stopping off place for
                    members of the ANC who wanted to get out of South Africa. South Africans had
                    butchered in the early mornings thousands of Lesotho while they were sleeping,
                    looking for ANC refugees.</p>
                <p>Lekhanya militarily overthrew Leabua and took over the government and created a
                    military cabinet of generals. When I arrived it was in place. Lekhanya is short
                    in stature, not necessarily a very attractive man, buit's almost a
                    contradiction. He was so bright that he appeared to be attractive. He was
                    articulate, yet he had only worked in the mines, he had dropped out of school.
                    He had traveled widely, he clearly loved music from the classics to jazz, could
                    fly a plane, extraordinarily literate, and loved the social event.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did he get into the military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Came out of the mines. And men joined the military. Almost every one of
                    those generals sitting on that podium has been in the mines. So his ritual and
                    now the person who succeeded him, both are graduates of the diamond or the gold
                    mines in essence. And so you had this experience, you don't want to go back to
                    the farm. In most developing countries, the military has the largest budget, and
                    to be an officer in the military is of course prestige.</p>
                <p>I made very good friends with Lekhanya. I got there in January, and we began to
                    relate and to talk. Lekhanya came by my house and I said to him one day, “You
                    know that the street that I live on, the American residence, is muddy, and
                    therefore I can't keep my car very clean out here, and I have noticed that all
                    of the other ambassadors have paved streets. Is there some reason that you don't
                    love the Americans?” We got into a lovely discussion, and he says, well, you
                    Americans are so rich, you can pay for your own street paving. And I said,
                    “Well, I will only pave it up to the point at which I turn into my house.” And
                    so in a few weeks someone came by and began to put some gravel and tarmac the
                    area for me. But we developed a very warm visiting friendship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the human rights situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: In a sense, the military controlled things. We didn't have very good
                    protection of labor laws, environmental protection laws, but you didn't have a
                    great deal of abuse. It was not like you couldn't speak out on television or you
                    couldn't write articles. Lekhanya had been to the United States, and he had made
                    a commitment that he wanted democracy, and he welcomed me to shepherd him
                    through how do we get to it, to this process, and it was important to him that
                    we move toward a democratic reign. But it was important to him that Moshoeshoe
                    not return, because he felt that the biggest block to democratization in Lesotho
                    was the presence of the king who wanted to run everything with an iron hand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The presence of the monarchy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: The presence of the monarchy, and so he was not popular with the
                    monarchy. He also had gotten himself into a little bind because he had killed
                    someone from his role as the military head. He killed a young man at a dormitory
                    at a university and had been exonerated, but he retained the power of office.
                    And so he was looking for redemption, he was looking for a way to come out of
                    this.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>But he had a strong team around him, and the people were upset with the team, and
                    the military was upset with the team that included the foreign minister, the
                    minister of finance, and one of his generals. And so I met with Lekhanya, and I
                    said to him, “You are going to have to make a decision, General. Do you wish to
                    stay in office because there is going to be a coup to overthrow you.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You knew that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I knew this. “You can avoid this coup if you will dismiss three
                    people.” And he said to me, “Mr. Ambassador, I can't do iI am a military man,
                    I'm a loyalisuntil you can give me some evidence.” I said, “It is not for me to
                    give you evidence, it's for you to ask the question, but here is the moral
                    dilemma which you face. You have a vision of a democratic order for Maseru. Are
                    you willing to give up that vision or delay and defer that for three people? You
                    have to make that moral decision, not the American ambassador. I am here to
                    assist you in getting to it, but here is the dilemma. You will be overthrown.”
                    “Do you have any idea about when?” “Yes, in less than two or three months. So
                    you have time to think about it, to consult with your family, and I'm
                    available.”</p>
                <p>Whether he believed me or not, whether he became bullheaded and said I can
                    overcome this, I'm not sure. But the records do show that I advised him. And he
                    was overthrown by his own military. He was under arrest, he was taken to the
                    radio station, he was asked to give up hihe did.</p>
                <p>He was not brutalized, he was not beaten, he was not placed in jail, contrary to
                    reports that came out. He was treated with every ounce of respect as a general.
                    This was in 1991, the spring of 1991, and I'm going to guess about April if my
                    memory is serving me right.</p>
                <p>Another general, Phisoana, but the military remained in power. It was kind of
                    interesting. I think that more than any other time in my diplomatic career,
                    having moved from Habyarimana to Lekhanya and now to a third leader, and I was
                    older than all of them, I think there was this</p>
                <p>Three military people. There was this difference to me. I felt like, and my wife
                    would say, “Wow, they want to talk to you all the time about issues and things
                    of this sort.” And I think it had to do with the fact that I was older and the
                    developing world's respect for the graying hairs, I think it was partly that. I
                    think it was that they didn't think I had any ulterior colonial motive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q. You had no agenda?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I had no agenda except to try to see could we help you where we
                    possibly can, can we get to where we want to go, and can I work with the other
                    embassies in marshaling the support to get there. But anyway, the transition for
                    me was not a difficult one even though Lekhanya kept visiting me.</p>
                <p>But there is one little anecdote in here that I have to share with you. Lekhanya
                    went away quietly across the border, and many of his older military people
                    convinced him that the time was right that he could retake hiwell, he failed.
                    His coup of coups or his recouping, as it were, failed, and Lekhanya knocked on
                    mabout 1:30 in the morning, my guards notified me that someone is on the
                    outside. “It's 1:30 in the morning, who is on the outside?” “General Lekhanya.”
                    Lekhanya came in, and I said, “General, can I help you?” And he said, “Well,
                    I've got to get out the country and I need your help.”</p>
                <p>Well, I'll skip a lot of the particulars in this, but we did manage to get him
                    across the border into South Africa, and he is noI have seen him since then, I
                    visited him two years ago. He's an extraordinarily rich and successful
                    farmer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In South Africa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: No, in Lesotho. He has got a lovely home up on top of a gorgeous hill,
                    and he's got peach trees, and he sits out on the veranda, and he has got a
                    trailer sitting out there. So be it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In any event, the interesting thing is, at a certain
                        point, the king did come back.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, okay. We went through a period of time, and I became dean of a
                    small diplomatic corps.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: 1992?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: 1992. And in 1993, we carried out our first democratic elections in
                    Lesotho. That was my pride and joy. I think if I had to look back at it,
                    carrying them through their first democratic election in 27 years was indeed a
                    highlight. The establishment of an American school, the Lesotho American School
                    and the Rwanda American School, were two of the highlights for most people, but
                    from an educatioas a professional educator, you know that there is a certain
                    amount of satisfaction you see in having 57 different kids from 25 different
                    countries sitting in a class singing to you. It's a real warm feeling.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>Yes, the king, back to your question. The king's son was the king. He was sworn
                    in with all the trappings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How old was he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: 29. He was a frequent visitor in our residence and often asked me to
                    come over to his. And the queen mother had my wife and me to her country home on
                    more than one occasion for dinner and we chatted. She felt very comfortable
                    talking to the Americans. She had visited the United States on one occasion.</p>
                <p>But she loved her husband. The son was a reluctant kinKing Letsie was a reluctant
                    monarch. Following democracy, following the elections</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What month were the elections?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Elections were probably in February because by this time</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: February of 1993?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Right. Because by this time, President Clinton was in office, and all
                    of us had to resign posts, the typical State Department procedure, and there was
                    a critical issue — the records and so forth, and they would make a final
                    decision on it, and the prime minister agreed to abide by the verdict of this, I
                    believe, three-country tribunal in essence. And they agreed that Moshoeshoe was
                    officially the king to the delight of the son Letsie, and Moshoeshoe did return
                    to regain his thrown.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was before or after the elections?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: This is after the elections.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The elections were for a parliament?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, the elections were for prime minister and a parliament. They
                    established a prime minister.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. And following the elections, there was an effort to
                        restore the monarchy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Restore the monarchy. Well, the monarchy was never destroyed, but to
                    restore the king to the throne of the monarchy, the father of the king, the
                    rightful king. But they wanted certain concessions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: The government wanted concessions, I'm sorry, the newly established
                    government wanted concessions from Moshoeshoe. “Yes, you may return, but once
                    again we're going to tell you, there is a separation of the monarchy from the
                    operation of the government. Please do not dictate to us.”</p>
                <p>Well, that was the problem. He would have never been exiled, but he had such
                    powerful influence in appointments in government and appointments in the
                    military and appointments every place, so it became extraordinarily difficult,
                    that is, the perception of the government, that it became extraordinarily
                    difficult for them to run the government because the king was running the
                    monarchy and the government. And so they were in essence saying, do the rituals,
                    grow the goats and the sheep and so forth, but do not deal with the operation of
                    the government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is extremely interesting because what the politicians
                        and the parliament, the newly elected parliament, were asking, was that a
                        king give up his traditional powers, authority, influence, hierarchical
                        status and remake himself into a constitutional monarch.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: That's correct. But he had a number of years to practice this. You see,
                    Moshoeshoe had been elected as president 27 years ago. They had exiled him to
                    Holland on one occasion. And so it kept going, going, going. This is an
                    extraordinarily brilliant man, Moshoeshoe. His writings are superb. His legal
                    training in London is phenomenal. This is not a
                    I-grew-up-in-the-wild-come-to-office king. This is an articulate, skillful man
                    who with a pen is as uplifting as deadly.</p>
                <p>So the Moshoeshoe line going from the founder, he comes from a very distinguished
                    line, King Moshoeshoe who founded the country of Lesotho. This man is a — in
                    American terminology — is a blue blood descendent, and he is very well-educated,
                    as is his son King Letsie, who is also a lawyer.</p>
                <p>So Moshoeshoe is a threat to a military government based on mine workers, mine
                    graduates, as opposed to the elite.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the mine workers would typically be people who had a
                        primary education?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Right, primary education. And so his rhetoric and his pen made them
                    extraordinarily nervous, of course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say that he had time to practice becoming a
                        constitutional monarch.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I say that only because Leabua, who was the prime minister, had run
                    into difficulties, so it was not his first time being exiled under General
                    Lekhanya. He had been exiled once before. But when he returned, he always
                    resorted to the same. Now, would he have done it a third time, I have no idea,
                    because he was killed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The king?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: The king. He was in an accident off of a cliff. He and the driver were
                    driving up early in the morning. Whether there was fog, whether there was foul
                    play, no one seems to know. Everybody seems to have reduced it to a sheer
                    accident.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And that was in what year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: 1996. Now, I'm out of there at this particular point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Looking back, I was exposed to people in 1991 or so who
                        were very interested in the hydroelectric potential of Lesotho and the
                        possibility of selling electricity to South Africa. Recently there has been
                        a great deal of criticism of corruption in the awarding of contracts and so
                        forth. Do you have any comment on that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Well, the Highlands Water Project really began during the time that I
                    was there. In effect, to be candid with you, I would try to get there early
                    enough to welcome American bidding into the process because it was strictly a
                    European contest. And so the Highlands water project began during that
                    particular period.</p>
                <p>It was extremely complicated because here is a country that is being suppressed
                    by South Africa, preparing to award a dam which is being funded by South Africa
                    to provide water into the Orange Free State to assure that there are no
                    droughts, because Lesotho's wealth is the water in the northern part of the
                    country. So a massive project began. I am not at all surprised that there are
                    stories of corruption involved in this. After all, the selling of water is like
                    the selling of diamonds or like the selling of gold or like the selling of
                    arms.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One cannot look too closely at the history of water in
                        California.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: That's correct. So the promises that were made that we would rebuild
                    houses, build schools up in the north, for people who were being displaced, the
                    opportunity, the insertion of controls to block off the diamonds which might be
                    swept through by the water, all of these give great opportunity for hanky
                    panky.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Speculation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: That's right, speculation. And so, yes, I have heard, I'm aware of
                    this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Speak for a moment about diamonds. This is the great
                        export of Lesotho, isn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Lesotho has some diamonds, but there has been no really heavy diamond
                    markets identified with Lesotho. What they were doing when they did the water
                    dam was that they had to develop some kind of elaborate mesh that ran through a
                    certain area in which if diamonds were flushed out of this area, they would stop
                    there. A number of companies have said that they tried to go into Lesotho to
                    mine diamonds, but their veins do not appear as prosperous despite its close
                    proximity or they would have pulled them out a long time ago to try to alleviate
                    some of the poverty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But there is diamond smuggling, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, yes.</p>
                <p>All in all, it's been I hope that I tried in my two terms' appointment to
                    dissipate the notion that all non-career ambassadors are not well trained, not
                    well schooled, have no understanding, are political puppets of the President.
                    But rather, we took this very seriously because, in the first place, how many
                    people get tapped by the President of the United States to serve as an
                    ambassador, whether it is career or non-career? And, two, you represent the most
                    powerful nation in the world, and what you say at a dinner party, what you say
                    at a cocktail party, and of course of your conduct, when your wife's affairs
                    translate into what America is all about.</p>
                <p>As a black American, I began to understand a number of things. I was never called
                    an Afro American, I was never called a black American, I was called an American
                    and perceived as such. Secondly, there was another notion that I think is
                    important as you all put this together. I had heard rumors that African leaders
                    did not respect black ambassadors because they felt they had no power to effect
                    change. I think that's an abusive statement</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's not true.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: It's an untrue tale.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To respond to it very bluntly, African American or Irish
                        American or Jewish American or female American ambassadors have as much
                        power as their ability. There are good, bad and indifferent, and that's the
                        answer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Of course, yes. I had someone say to me when I was in Texas, oh, you
                    will be home in three or four months because you won't be able to make the
                    adjustment. Well, here it is 1999, going into the millennium, and I am still
                    traveling backwards and forwards to Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would like to just stop there for a moment as we begin
                        to bring this interview to a conclusion. You are presently the Special
                        Assistant to the</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: No, I'm Distinguished Professor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Distinguished Professor at Coppin State College. So what
                        are those responsibilities, and how is it that you continue to go back and
                        forth to Africa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Several years ago, we created a nonprofit organization called Renewable
                    Energy for African Development. The object of our organization is to stimulate
                    the use of clean energy technologies or solar technologies in the rural
                    villages. We are aware of the fact that roughly 60 to 70 percent of the world's
                    population is without electrification, and the rural people suffer. And while a
                    great deal of work is moving forward in India and Asia and South America, very
                    little is being directed toward Africa in terms of adequate electrification. Our
                    organization, with support from the U.S. Department of Energy, some from the
                    USAID-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a for profit organization?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: No, no, it's nonprofit. We receive funds, we solicit funds in order to
                    go in and train and to persuade government to embrace solar technology in its
                    energy sector and to find more economical ways to expand this energy to rural
                    areas, to increase education, to increase health, to slow down the migration to
                    urban cities. Why did we do this? Because the SADC ministers, we met with the
                    SADC ministers</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: SADC is the South</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Southern Africa Development Cooperation. And we said, what is your most
                    pressing problem, and the answer was, the need for electrification in our rural
                    villages. People are moving into the cities. We have a fragile infrastructure,
                    we cannot take care of them. We have to do something. We can't get teachers out
                    in the rural area. Well, through a series of grants since 1994, we have
                    trained-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From the Department of Energy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: From the Department of Energy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How much annually?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Roughly $200,000 to $250,000, depending on the year. Currently, I am
                    operating out of a $250,000 grant with the Department of Energy. We have trained
                    professors, we have trained NGOs or local nongovernmental organizations in the
                    installation, we have modified energy policy by getting into the government, we
                    have helped governments establish funding mechanisms for rural
                    electrification.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How much progress is being made in solar energy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Oh, unbelievable, Ambassador, when you consider the fact that it costs
                    between $15,000 and $20,000 per kilometer to extend the grid of those electric
                    lines that run up and down the street. That's what it costs in developing
                    countries, whether it's in India, Malaysia, and so forth. The cost is
                    prohibitive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again, what was the cost?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Between $10,000 to $20,000 per kilometer. Now you've got to do this in
                    a way in which you don't destroy the village atmosphere of the people. So big
                    companies like ENRON have now created solar components. British Petroleum bought
                    SOLAREX right outside of Gaithersburg here. Shell has gotten into the whole
                    solar thing. ESCOM, the great power utility company of South Africa, has a whole
                    section now, all of this since 1994, in solar technology.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So in addition to being present at the creation, it sounds
                        to me as if you have found a vocation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Yes, I suspect thawell, the Department of Energy and many of the people
                    in South Africa and Botswana have now seen me as a forerunner of the expansion
                    of solar technology in their countries. So the new Minister of Energy in South
                    Africa has called on me, and for your information, I may have made this point to
                    you once before, the ambassador from Tanzania was the former Minister of Energy
                    in Tanzania. The ambassador from Botswana was the former Minister of Energy in
                    Botswana. So people kind of wonder, what does Palmer do, what does Ambassador
                    Palmer do other than be an ambassador, and they never know that you're an expert
                    in Asian studies and Asian affairs, but we do have lives outside of
                    diplomacy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bless your heart. I know that you have to go and we're
                        going to conclude. But just a few words about your work at Coppin State
                        College. Is it a Historically Black College?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: It's a Historical Black College that was created about 1900 for the
                    primary purpose of educating women for teaching established by Fanny Coppin. Its
                    president is Calvin Burnett who has been there 28 years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A distinguished educator.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: A distinguished educator, a Washington University doctorate who has
                    really identified himself strongly in Jewish Black relations in Baltimore and in
                    his ability to maintain a liberal arts atmosphere in a state supported
                    institution located in a troubled neighborhood of Baltimore. We have less than
                    4,000 students. We have about 120 faculty members, all of whom are extremely
                    dedicated, it appears to me.</p>
                <p>When I sought to retire and devote all of my energies to our new organization,
                    Renewable Energy for African Development, and my wife and I had agreed that we
                    would settle here in Washington, someone approached me and said, well, there's
                    Coppin over there, and you ought not put yourself out to the field too early.
                    President Burnett welcomed me with open arms and said I would like for you to
                    bring your organization, Renewable Energy for African Development, headquarter
                    it here at Coppin State, and begin to involve us in the process. And so I now no
                    longer write proposals for Renewable Energy for Africa, I write them for Coppin
                    State College, Sub-renewable Energy for African Development. They were kind
                    enough to permit me to continue to pursue this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you teach?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>SPEARMAN: No. I lecture at the request of various people on the faculty who ask
                    me to come in and discuss international affairs. I meet with student groups to
                    talk about opportunities and careers in the foreign service. I host a
                    distinguished lecture series at Coppin State in which Ambassador Palmer does not
                    know it, but he is going to be my spring presenter. We do this with no
                    funds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would love that. Let me accept.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Ambassador Jeter has already spoken; Ambassador Marguay has already
                    spoken.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Palmer is different.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: I know Palmer is different, I know that. And I will do a seminar on
                    October 25, we will do a seminar at Coppin State on financing strategies for
                    clean energy projects in Africa, and five African ambassadors will be present.
                    And I chair the International Education Committee at Coppin State.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I would like to suggest that perhaps Coppin State
                        and George Washington could do something together.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>But let me bring this interview to a close by expressing on behalf of the
                    American people our gratitude for you, a man full of years, who went overseas to
                    difficult destinations, Rwanda and Lesotho, and not only comported yourself with
                    honor and dignity and professional achievement, but as you suggested, did
                    everything you could and successfully to demonstrate that non-career ambassadors
                    can be just as good if not better as career ambassadors.</p>
                <p>I would like to say, finally, that we the American people are delighted that you
                    found a vocation in thihow old are you now, Ambassador?</p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: 70.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, given your energy, you appear to be a much younger
                        man. I think you should look back on your experience not as rejuvenating but
                        as one that will open up new paths for you. Thank you very much,
                        Ambassador.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SPEARMAN: Thank you for having me. I think what you're doing is absolutely
                    splendid, and I am glad that I had the opportunity to share my thoughts with
                    you.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This ends the interview of Ambassador Leonard O. Spearman, distinguished former
                    Ambassador to Lesotho, 1991 1993, and to Rwanda, 1988 1990.</p>
                <p>Thank you very much, Ambassador Spearman.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
