<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001405">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with George McFarland</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2007</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Foreign Affairs Series</p>
                <p>GEORGE MCFARLAND</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Lewis Hoffacker</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: August 3, 1999</p>
                <p>Copyright 2000 ADST</p>
                <p>[Beginning of tape blank; beginning of interview not recorded]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, would you like to continue?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Pearl Harbor occurred when I was 11 years old. I was subjected to all
                    the wartime information, patriotic writing, not to say propaganda and I
                    succumbed. I was in ROTC in high school. It was compulsory for all boys. We wore
                    a uniform four of the five school days of the week and learned to drill and to
                    shoot and saw training films on combat. This was within the umbrella also of
                    public attitudes toward the government that we no longer know, an attitude of
                    enormous respect. It was the US Government that had brought the country out of
                    the Depression. It was the US Government that helped decisively win World War I.
                    Then, as time went on, we won World War II. So the thought of working for the US
                    Government was one that involved considerations of respect and feeling honored,
                    of associating with a worthy cause. And besides that, the country was repeatedly
                    in danger. People forget how nearly we were all overrun in World War II. If
                    Hitler had gotten that atomic bomb first, we would all be speaking German now,
                    at least all of us that survived. And then immediately after the war, of course,
                    we went into the Cold War and another sense of danger.</p>
                <p>At any rate, I came out of my growing up with several results, one being this
                    intense concern with the country's security and interest in the military, a
                    feeling that success in battle or a good report of one's actions in battle were
                    to be very highly esteemed. I suppose another influence on me must have been all
                    the World War II veterans who came back, all those stories about their
                    participation in combat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you at SMU at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I entered SMU in 1947. I graduated from high school at the end of May
                    of '47 and entered SMU, rather against my will, but at my parents'
                    insistence.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you a day student?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I was a day student. I lived at home and commuted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course. That saves money. Money was important.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was a child of the depression, too. I know what you're
                        saying to us.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, people simply didn't have it, and among the student body there
                    were perhaps eight per cent who had cars. Now, I suppose, almost everyone. But
                    parking was not a problem on the campus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you take your degree in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I took my degree in journalism. I had started out majoring in biology
                    and found that I just couldn't overcome the math requirement. My brain simply
                    doesn't function when confronted with math problems. Maybe it was a childhood
                    fear, but my intelligence is all verbal. And I worked on the student newspaper
                    briefly while I was in school, and then took a part-time job as a reporter for
                    the Dallas Times-Herald, sort of big thing to make the journalism scene for a
                    time. For the last year and a half I was in school I covered the campus for them
                    during the week and then on Saturdays worked as a regular reporter. It was
                    terribly valuable experience. All the other people in journalism envied it. I
                    was getting a leg up on a future journalism career, and I also was a stringer
                    for United Press and International News Service, which later merged, and for
                    Time Magazine. I got two or three squibs in Time Magazine, which invariably got
                    me in trouble with the university authorities because it was not good public
                    relations for SMU. But that was a time, by the way, of greater control over the
                    press and greater respect on the part of the press for official secrets.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No leaks. If there were leaks, the press respected the
                        source.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: The White House correspondents during Roosevelt's time did not publish
                    the fact of his obviously declining health, for example. They simply took the
                    press releases that came out of the government at face value and embroidered on
                    them as best they could. A great deal has changed. I'm a child of another
                    era.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Privacy of the President, oh, my. They didn't prod him for
                        that, or if prodded, they didn't print it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: The only thing that came close, a colleague of mine at the
                    Times-Herald told me that the Texas press had helped to undo Governor Pappy
                    O'Daniel simply by quoting him directly. He had complained, it seems, that some
                    newspaperman had misquoted him, so they took to quoting him exactly in all his
                    inelegant, garbled, ungrammatical speech, and that finally killed him, or so the
                    journalists thought. That was as close as it came to “investigative reporting.”
                    At any rate, I was all set to become a journalist, and I hoped to become a
                    foreign correspondent. I didn't realize what form my foreign correspondence
                    would eventually take. I was in ROTC at SMU, Air Force ROTC, the only kind they
                    had. Obviously, the draft had begun again in 1948, when I was a sophomore, and
                    my father had thought it was good insurance to have a commission promised along
                    with my diploma. Of course, you didn't have to worry about being drafted as long
                    as you were a student, but nonetheless, I'm sure that he was right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your father was a strong influence and he imposed a
                        discipline, which was normal in those days, maybe not so normal now, but you
                        listened to your father and did often what he recommended. That is the way
                        it was, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I felt as if I had no real choice, and I didn't want to hurt him or my
                    mother either. My mother governed by the tactic of “Don't hurt me.” Wonderful
                    woman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They both lived a long, rich life, I hope.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, they did. They lived, my father until '93, my mother until '91, I
                    think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My goodness, it's great for you, your longevity.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: But they lived very regular lives. They never stayed out late, and
                    they didn't drink. My father smoked.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't a vice in those days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, for my mother it was. She insisted that I never take up the
                    practice, and I have since been very grateful to her.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, good for her, good for you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: But at any rate, I had the choice on graduation, starting before
                    graduation, of taking a 21-month tour of active duty as a supply officer or
                    public information officer or training of that sort or signing up for pilot
                    training with a four-year commitment. Well, naturally, given my background, we
                    were discussing, World War II, pro-US Government, pro-military and so on, I
                    signed up for pilot training. I was one of five, I think, in a class of
                    something above a hundred cadets to volunteer. The others had more sense, just
                    as the others had had more sense in sticking to business. I'm sure they've all
                    prospered since then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was the training?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I was assigned first to Bartell Air Base in Florida. It was a contract
                    fly school. The Air Force had faced a sudden tremendous requirement for new
                    pilots along with their infusion of money for new aircraft and the requirements
                    of the Korean War. Truman, as you might recall, had cut the armed forces to the
                    bone and into the bone in the late '40's, so that we had very, very few military
                    resources to throw into Korea when the war came, and those that we had were in
                    some cases decimated. It's rather sorry. We were almost thrown out of Korea by
                    the North Koreans. But the shock of the Chinese intervention, apparently, in
                    November-December of 1950, decided Truman that he did indeed face a dangerous
                    enemy and he must build up the military. This was just in time for me. There
                    were several contract flying schools, primarily what was then called basic
                    flying school across the country. The people in our ROTC detachment at SMU
                    seemed to have influence, so our group went to Florida. And about half of our
                    entering class of second lieutenants - we were matched also with cadets; we had
                    a group of cadets going through on the same program - but about half of our
                    class came out of West Point, and they had to be among the top 10 per cent in
                    order to get into the Air Force because there was so much demand for Air Force
                    commissions in West Point. There was no Air Force Academy. The Naval Academy
                    had, of course, Naval Air Corps to offer its graduates who wanted to fly. Some
                    of the Naval Academy graduates did, in fact, enter the Air Force, but they were
                    not at the level of West Point by then. These also were people who had been
                    brought up in the glory of the military during the '40's and again in '47,
                    graduated in '51, an example of the level, the caliber, is that one of my five
                    apartment mates was Buzz Aldrin. And it was Buzz who started modifying my Texas
                    English into something approximating standard East Coast English.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you didn't lose it all. You have a little bit.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: My Texas accent has begun to come back now, with renewed residence in
                    the State.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh the Foreign Service modified it too, I would
                        think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, and living in the East generally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sure.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: You tend to become standardized. Lyndon Johnson never did, and I've
                    known other people who never lost a deep southern drawl.</p>
                <p>Q: LBJ, I was amazed, his mother gave him elocution lessons, so obviously she
                    spoke the way he did. Elocution requires a certain diction. I learned that out
                    at the LBJ family home. She gave elocution lessons to the kids around there,
                    including him, but it didn't seem to make a difference.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, maybe he deliberately rejected that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, there you are in flight school.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I suddenly found that I had to try very, very hard, harder than I
                    had ever tried before in my life, and I've survived. About 30 or 35 per cent of
                    our class got washed out, including the pitcher of the West Point baseball team.
                    That was a terrible injustice.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a heavy percentage.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, it is very wasteful. By today's terms it would not be tolerated,
                    but those were early days of the contract flying schools, and some of the
                    instructors thought that it was to their credit if they washed out more
                    students. The others felt more protective and thought it was to their credit if
                    they passed more students. I did well enough to get by, but then, to my great
                    distress, was sent to multi-engine flying school for the second half of my
                    flying training, and I had wanted to fly fighters. I was terribly disappointed.
                    But on my final check ride, I got in with this check pilot who had this terrible
                    reputation, and I just choked up. I was too tight on the stick. I passed, but
                    barely.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>Well, anyway, I came out of multi-engine training, again asked for fighters, and
                    I graduated, by the way, on August 2nd of '52, which was 47 years ago yesterday,
                    and was assigned to be trained as a copilot in B-29's, although in the
                    nomenclature of that time, I was a pilot, and the pilot was the aircraft
                    commander. I was sent to Randolph Air Force Base at San Antonio. I teamed up
                    with a series of World War II veterans, captains, majors, lieutenant colonels,
                    and finally got settled down with a red-haired major who was an alcoholic. He
                    had been a sort of a hero in World War II and had even been on War Bond tour, I
                    think, because of his exploits in flying B-17's out of Egypt. He had, after the
                    war, been unable to adjust to peacetime and his marriage broke up, and he turned
                    to alcohol. He broke down after our 16th mission, on my birthday in 1953, and
                    just after landing, while still on the runway, went into convulsions. I was
                    teamed up with yet another one. But at any rate, I flew a total of 20 missions
                    from February of '53 until the war's end, I believe it was the 27th of July,
                    1953. And we just passed that anniversary also. Those missions gave me an idea
                    of what modern war is all about. It's very impersonal, even though we were
                    flying outdated equipment, we were still using machines for the most part to
                    carry on the fighting. We flew at night, in the dark of the moon, with our
                    bellies painted black and altitudes to avoid contrails. All these were things
                    that had been learned from attacks by the MIG-15's, with which the other side
                    had linked up. These were day fighters, and they had no radar on board. They
                    depended on radar guidance from the ground, which could, of course, easily be
                    jammed. So we were never hit. We would see the fighters going by and turn on
                    their running lights in the hope that we would fire at them and then they could
                    see where the fire was coming from and attack us. And before I got there several
                    airplanes had been shot down by MIG's that flew up their condensation trail.
                    That's why we avoided those altitudes where you leave contrails. But otherwise
                    it was an easy war. As I was saying about the machines, we dropped bombs using
                    Sure Rans. These are short-range aid to navigation. There were several of them
                    in South Korea, and the planners of the mission would pick two, one that would
                    provide and arc - that is, if you flew a constant distance from the station,
                    that would be your bomb run, and then when it reached a certain distance from
                    other station, the bombs would fall. So it was carried out mechanically -
                    primitively but mechanically. And we also had basic World War II type defenses
                    such as searchlights. But the flak was scary at times, but never touched us.
                    They had no radar. They had to use barrage flak, which is much less
                    dangerous.</p>
                <p>Q: You got through the war.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: We got through the war. I could only imagine later the damage that we
                    caused below, all the innocent people that had died, all the unnecessary
                    destruction of the environment, of houses, of crops, and so on. But it was so
                    impersonal that I began to think I was just part of a team that began with the
                    taxpayer. But I learned several other things. One of the most important was the
                    essentiality of training and discipline. You don't send a bunch of barroom
                    brawlers to combat. You send nice boys that are willing to accept discipline,
                    and you train them and train them and train them until, even if they're being
                    shot at or even if they're on fire, they go on doing their job. And that was
                    essentially our approach to combat. You may see films of World War II crew that
                    were not so trained panicking - wild things. But we were supposed to be
                    professionals. And we did have a higher level of experience. We had all those
                    field-grade officers as aircraft commanders.</p>
                <p>Well, back from the war, I was assigned to Carswell Air Force Base, and I was
                    adjutant for a year and a half, I suppose, until June of '55. I had been
                    transferred to headquarters 8th Air Force, Massachusetts, Westover Air Force
                    Base. Carswell's been shut down; Westover Air Force Base has been shut down.
                    These were all big investments at that time for the Strategic Air Command. I was
                    in the headquarters in Massachusetts for the next three years, which is why I
                    took the exam for the Foreign Service in Hartford, Connecticut.. I had meanwhile
                    accepted a regular commission in the Air Force with every intention of making it
                    my career, and yet I had this nagging doubt that I really wanted to spend my
                    life practicing to do the unthinkable, or helping others to prepare for the
                    unthinkable. I felt that I had something more to offer in the intellectual area
                    that was not in demand in the Air Force.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could it have been that you would like to prevent war? Was
                        that part of it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's normal. When you've been through what you've been
                        through, then you just would like to do something to prevent it.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: That was one of my principal objectives. I had had this experience,
                    and the Strategic Air Command, you know, was dedicated to the nuclear
                    destruction of the Soviet Union and had an elaborate system at that time of
                    bombers and tankers for refueling, forward bases that bomber or tankers would
                    fly to and shorten the distance. There was a huge armada, and perhaps it helped
                    to keep the peace, or perhaps it was just a great waste. I don't know, but we
                    had something like 70,000 men and 8,000, I believe, were officers, and the 8th
                    Air Force alone, which is one of the three numbered Air Forces in the Strategic
                    Air Command, these were the days of Curt LeMay as SAC commander, the glory days
                    of SAC, and SAC had got anything it asked for. And mainly what it asked for was
                    more aircraft and more bases. We built up Westover and supervised the building
                    up of new bases throughout the Northeast, including the bases up in Newfoundland
                    and Labrador, which were the advance bases for tankers. I had this experience
                    that stamped itself upon my memory during the Suez crisis in 1956. I don't know
                    how many people were aware of it, but we went on alert, a full alert. I went
                    into the control room of the 8th Air Force to watch as symbols were moved across
                    this gigantic map, and one after another the B-47's and B-52's were announced:
                    combat ready, cruising aircraft ready for take-off. The tanker units were flown
                    to the far bases, some of the B-47's also, until finally all the symbols were up
                    and ready to start. It was like that, a hammer on gigantic pistol being pulled
                    back, and the end of the world, at most, a good part of it, was very, very near.
                    It would have happened in the next few hours if they had ever gotten the order
                    to go. I thought that was an impressive sight.</p>
                <p>At any rate, I was more and more interested in the Foreign Service. I had thought
                    of becoming an Air attach� and had been told, no, that's not the way to advance.
                    Everybody wanted to just move forward and make that general. I did terribly
                    well, I must say. I had a string of outstanding efficiency reports, in large
                    part because I could write and nobody else could. But also I had a lot of energy
                    and I learned to fly, 22 years old.</p>
                <p>Well, maybe it was because of the New York Times. They were so pro-Foreign
                    Service, and George Kennan set a powerful example. Foreign Service officer -
                    develop the greatest strategic idea to govern our foreign policy for years. And
                    I finally decided I wanted to try for the Foreign Service exam. I had been
                    reading a great deal and improving my knowledge of history, foreign affairs,
                    economics, and so on. I got in touch with a professor at Mt. Holyoke. My wife at
                    that time was trying to get a master's in history from Mt. Holyoke. She later
                    dropped out. Anyway, this was a very bright guy, and he told me what I should
                    read to prepare for the written exam, and I had a few discussions with him, he
                    suggested questions to prepare for especially. Not really a cram course, but it
                    was a great deal of help. So I had an order about three days before the written
                    exam to fly down to El Paso, Texas, and I got back at about two or three in the
                    morning of the exam. I had about two or three hours sleep and got up, into the
                    car, and drove down to Hartford, where the exam was being given in the State
                    House.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was all day, too, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, this was after the change. This was the exam that lasted, I think,
                    three hours or so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Three hours, but intense.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, but I should backtrack and say that the exam was changed in the
                    mid-'50's, I think, with the express desire of eliminating the cram courses and
                    if possible moving the geographical center of the Foreign Service a little
                    farther to the left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you came in at the right time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: At any rate, I got to the door fairly in time, and just as a New
                    Englander at the door said, “You're late!” I could have hit him, but I didn't. I
                    just did get in with hundreds of other applicants in the exam and was later told
                    that I had passed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You passed? Good for you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And later I had to drive down to Washington to take the oral and
                    passed that. The oral was given by these people I really admire. They obviously
                    were educated. One of them combined all the virtues - the brains, the decency,
                    the helpfulness to society, service to the government - even through one of them
                    gave me a hard time - he was the bad cop - I got by them. And then began the
                    year - I guess this was in early '58 - again, the year I refer to later as the
                    year of the long sweat, because I had to find out whether I'd passed the oral
                    exam, excuse me, all the other exams - security, health, and so on. And then,
                    when was I going to be appointed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They made you wait, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And they had no funds. Finally in the summer I was told by the Air
                    Force I was about to be transferred to SAC headquarters. They liked me too much.
                    And “Sorry, but I'm resigning and going into the Foreign Service.” I was already
                    a captain by that time, and I was willing to accept to go back to second
                    lieutenant with the whole junior officer routine to work through again in order
                    to be in the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were motivated.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I was. And in those days they didn't have much compensation. The
                    best they could offer me was the top level of the entering - the top pay grade
                    of the FSO-8, as it was then called.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So how old were you at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I was 28 at that time. I became 28 in 1958.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's when I came.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: You were also 28 or so when you began?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, 27, I think, but then I'd had three and a half years
                        military experience, which set me back.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: What service were you in?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Army.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Where?</p>
                <p>Q: Second World War, Pacific.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Pacific?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. So they were looking for people who'd had experience
                        other than academic, even then. They were looking for people other than
                        Northeasterners.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, and they liked, as I said, my maturity and my Air Force
                    background.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And your experience in the Air Force - yes, those were big
                        pluses.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And I suspect the fact that I already had security clearance and there
                    was no question about my patriotism. In those days so many people's patriotism
                    was questioned for so little reason. Even though, during the oral exam, I had
                    advocated opening relations with Red China on the grounds that it was better to
                    negotiate it.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How'd the board take that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: They passed me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They passed you, yes. Good.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I think they were trying to see whether I could defend myself. Perhaps
                    they marked down positively for intellectual courage; I don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't waffle.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No.</p>
                <p>Q: The important thing is you don't waffle. The Board of Examiners -</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: You served on one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I didn't, but I have the idea you don't try to fool
                        them. They like a straightforward answer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes. One of them began, the bad cop, began to ask a question, “If you
                    were a resident of England, would you vote for the Labor Party. . . “ and then
                    he retracted the question. And I must have said something smelling of socialism
                    because one of them asked me, “In the Air Force, you are meant to live on base
                    in a very managed society, you know what socialism feels like, don't you?” “Yes,
                    I do, I do. I don't like it.” I thought a perceptive comment on his part. I had
                    thought that many times, but I didn't expect a civilian to make the point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So there you were. You resigned from the Air Force.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I resigned from the Air Force.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you still didn't have your commission.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And there you were.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: But I had to get out before the Air Force moved me, and also I wanted
                    to be instantly available just in case the State Department decided, yes, we've
                    got money.</p>
                <p>I was married just before going to the Korean War. December of '52, I took time
                    out to marry a girl who seemed to be an ideal mate, Phi Beta Kappa, interested
                    in the same things I was. Her name was Peggy Nichols. We had a honeymoon in New
                    Orleans, and then I suffered a great deal when I had to leave her to go off to
                    war. I returned, of course, in late '53. We had our first child, Stephen George
                    McFarland, born in December of '54, in Fort Worth, at Carswell Air Force Base
                    Hospital. It's strange that with all the moving around I've done, three of my
                    four children have been born in the United States, two of them in Texas. My
                    second child, Anne Seymour McFarland, was born December 23, 1958, in Austin,
                    after I had moved to Austin preparatory to entering the Foreign Service. One
                    other point, backing up, about the Foreign Service oral exam - the examiners
                    seemed to be quite impressed with my knowledge of United States geography, which
                    apparently most Americans lack. I had gained that, or course, from flying all
                    over the country. This was a tremendous benefit that the Air Force gave me. I
                    knew exactly what the country looked like from sea to sea, and I had also, of
                    course, had to drive over a good part of it, moving from base to base. I was
                    quite a citizen of the United States then, preparatory to becoming a citizen of
                    the world.</p>
                <p>Well, moving on, back to the period after September of '58, I arrived at the
                    University of Texas campus just in time to enroll for the fall semester and a
                    number of courses that would help me prepare for Foreign Service work. The most
                    outstanding of those courses was an international relations seminar led by
                    Professor Jim Roach, and I also took two courses in Spanish hoping to pass the
                    Spanish exam. At that time all Foreign Service officers were on probation until
                    they had passed either the written or the oral exam in a foreign language.
                    Thanks to this study, I was able to pass the written exams shortly after
                    entering duty in the State Department. The long wait, or the longs sweat,
                    finally came to an end in early December of '58, when I got a letter, not a
                    phone call, but a letter from the State Department saying that they still didn't
                    have money in their budget to hire new FSO's, but they did have money to hire
                    extra people for the Passport Office during the spring rush, and they would like
                    to use this money to bring in 20 people from the top of the list for FSO-8.
                    Would I be interested at all? I was rapidly running out of money and said, yes,
                    yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's interesting that the Passport Office should need 20
                        people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: But they did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a woman who ran the Passport Office.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Frances Knight. She was entrenched with barbed wire in terms of
                    Washington politics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Powerful.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that directly across the street from the Executive
                        Office Building? We called it Old State, remember?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, it was down -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now it's called the Executive Office Building. She had her
                        office opposite that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: We were on 19th Street at that time. It was not far from Old State.
                    Perhaps they had been at Old State earlier on.</p>
                <p>Q: It's not important. But anyway, you were going to the Passport Office.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, they brought us in, and I instantly realized, from being with
                    these other people that I had changed environments. I was among people who
                    laughed at the same jokes I did. The Air Force officers I had known were good
                    men, responsible men, brave men, good at what they did, but they were not
                    overwhelmingly bright - in other terms. I don't know that every Foreign Service
                    officer could get through pilot training. I don't think every pilot could pass
                    the Foreign Service Exam. I learned that distinction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did both.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: But it was an elite. There were a few exceptions in our entering
                    class, but most of them were very, very bright. One of them was Tom Pickering. I
                    had Buzz Aldrin in my flying class; I had Tom Pickering, the current
                    undersecretary for political affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But this wasn't the Foreign Service beginners' -</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, we were put into doing this work that any high school graduate
                    could have done under the supervision of -</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you were still a class, were you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: We were already a class.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were already a class, but you hadn't gone into the
                        Foreign Service officer orientation. That's unique. I never heard of it
                        before. You did it. How long did that last?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: This lasted from the 2nd of January - actually, I arrived in
                    Washington as Fidel was arriving in Havana. I just got that on the radio as I
                    was driving from Austin to Washington. And of course Fidel at that time enjoyed
                    tremendously good press in the States, and I thought it was a very auspicious
                    moment. How was I to know? The first of many ironies. I quickly found that I had
                    exchanged membership in a fairly proud club - Air Force captain, regular
                    commission, on a flying status, well respected - and suddenly I was thrust into
                    this assembly-line job where we were taking on passport applications, looking
                    them over to see if everything was in order, stamping them, and moving them on.
                    And we were given quotas for the day. The only thing useful that came out of it,
                    apart from my association with my colleagues, was that I gained quite an
                    appreciation or knowledge of citizenship law.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That didn't last too long, I hope.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: This was from January to July.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, half a year. They finally got money.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you got into the regular class.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: They did finally find out. . . . Those were the days of July 1 - June
                    30 fiscal years. The did finally find they had money for a class at FSI starting
                    in May, but they already had us employed, and they used that for sort of another
                    group. And we started in July and at that time became FSO's. Until then we'd
                    been FSR's, which ain't the same. The letters change. But we were all greatly
                    cheered up to be out of the horrible Passport Office.</p>
                <p>Q: How long was the orientation course? Was it three months?</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It seems to me there was about two months. Do you remember? Perhaps it
                    was three. I'm not sure. It was an excellent course. We gained, I think, three
                    more members by then, the A-100, and we were all quite pros.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's inevitable. I guess they've all retired by now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: A number of them resigned. Two were thrown out as a result of
                    conflicts with supervisors in the first assignment - three, I think. Those were
                    the days when you were on probation the first two years, I think, till you made
                    FSO-7, and they kept us all at grade eight, with the exception of one guy who
                    was 5/5 in French, but the rest of us stayed FS whatever it was. I was making
                    $5,885 a year, and that's the way it stayed. I think it was for two and a half
                    years, and I was finally promoted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were waiting for your first assignment.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: This was two and a half years plus the seven months or so that I had
                    spent in the Passport Office, so it was a long, long time, and I really
                    suffered, and my wife was just getting down. That was when her depressions
                    began.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The uncertainty?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, not having enough money. She had come from a wealthy family, and
                    she missed her mother. This was actually, I'm being unfair - it actually started
                    in the Air Force, at Westover Air Force Base. She loved being close to New York;
                    she loved New England; we traveled a lot through New England. But she was far
                    from home.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was she prepared for the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: She was intellectually. She was very much supportive of my decision to
                    go in, but the reality was something else. She couldn't take it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were waiting for your first assignment.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I passed the written exam in Spanish, but then they decided that we
                    should all be fluent in a language, and I had wanted to be trained in some other
                    language, especially French. I really wanted to learn French. I already had
                    Spanish. They assigned me to Spanish. I think I got a 2+ in speaking, but they
                    needed 3, so I was sent to four and a half months of Spanish training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At FSI?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: At FSI. After completing A-100, those three months including the
                    consular segment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they brought you up to three in the -</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I think I was S3 or 3+.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's fine. So you got your language requirement
                        out of the way.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And then went on and polished it up, and when I came back from my
                    first post, Costa Rica, I was more advanced.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So Costa Rica did that? Did that please you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: The assignment initially struck me as awful. I wanted someplace where
                    things were going on. And yet, it turned out to be almost an ideal first post.
                    You could make almost any mistake, I think, and then you would have been
                    forgiven, and people were friendly, and you could see how things work in an
                    embassy and in an overseas community.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about relations between Washington and Costa
                        Rica?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Extremely friendly. The Costa Ricans - I think if we had wanted
                    another state, they would have signed on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you had enough Communists to watch.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, this was Cold War time, and the Cubans were working there. But
                    there were also some Cuban exiles by this time. This was February of 1960, when
                    I arrived. And Cuban exiles began arriving I guess before May.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you working on your first assignment, political,
                        economic?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, my first assignment was consular work. I was vice-consul in a
                    two-man section. But it was easy consular work, in the sense that we did not
                    have a long line of visa applicants that you do now. It was not a visa mill. I
                    had a mixture of visas, welfare and whereabouts, and citizenship papers. And the
                    consul went off on delayed home leave, I think it was, leaving me in charge for
                    a couple of months. In September, I believe, an aircraft carrying three
                    Americans disappeared somewhere in Costa Rica. There was an airplane overhaul
                    facility near Costa Rica which a number of the US airlines used, cheaper to have
                    their aircraft overhauled there than in the States. Two of the chief pilots of,
                    I believe, Eastern Airlines had flown an aircraft down there and had time to
                    kill and met an American rancher from Costa Rica. He invited them to see his
                    ranch. He would fly them there the next day. They had to sleep off their
                    hangovers, so it was after lunch, I think, before they took off, and this was at
                    the time of year when Costa Rica every afternoon was covered by rainstorms. The
                    rainy season in Costa Rica starts usually in April, and the showers begin late
                    in the day and gradually advance, so that by late September one o'clock is sort
                    of a bad time to take off. But these were two senior pilots of Eastern Airlines
                    and a guy who had come to that area and thought he knew the country. They
                    disappeared. I was the consular officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was your case.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: The Costa Rican civil aviation authorities mounted an air search. We
                    should have been setting up a grid and checking each square in the grid. And
                    that was declared over in about three or four days. The family was going out of
                    its mind back in the States and sending telegrams and phoning and so on. After a
                    week or so, I got a message from some other American living way out in the
                    hinterland that he thought he might have seen a crash out there, so I got the
                    AGS people to lend me a helicopter with crew. The American Geodetic Survey. It's
                    an army outfit that operated - and still does operate in many Latin American
                    countries - mapping or helping the local authorities to map. They took me down
                    to this man's ranch, and we checked out the area thoroughly, and then I chewed
                    out the rancher for a false alarm, and we came back. I did get in a little
                    experience in the helicopter. Then after another week or so and many more
                    frantic telephone calls, I got word from some people back in the jungle that
                    they had seen way off in the distance something on some trees, and maybe this
                    could have been the airplane. Well, we had nothing else to check, so I asked the
                    police to provide me a patrol, and I borrowed a jeep from the army attach�, a
                    Jeep station wagon, and headed with the patrol back into this area. Well, we
                    stopped for the night at a beaten-up hotel and had dinner there, and dinner must
                    have been loaded with bad things. I got sick that night, and we drove on out
                    anyhow and started out into the jungle with a couple of local guides. We made
                    camp, and the next morning I was just debilitated. I tried to keep warm, and I
                    was holding up the others. So I sent them on alone, and this guide took me back
                    to his hut where his wife was living and put me in a storage room to sleep. They
                    came back without finding anything.</p>
                <p>But six weeks later, which is the normal incubation period, I believe, for
                    hepatitis, I came down with hepatitis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You picked that up then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It must have been.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the crash?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: We never found any sign of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could it have gone in the ocean?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I think that's probably what happened. This would have been a
                    reasonable thing to do. It was too dangerous to let down. . . . They may have
                    got caught in the clouds, and without navigation equipment. Under those
                    circumstances, it would have been reasonable to fly west over the Pacific a
                    decent time and then let down very, very slowly and hope to see the water, and
                    they turn back in and at least find someplace to land. But these were
                    superheroes, so maybe they did it some other way. But we never found a trace. Of
                    course, if they'd gone down in the jungle, they could have gone without a trace,
                    too, because there are, as in Vietnam, three levels of foliage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then the families finally had to accept that reality.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, but I kept getting calls right as I was getting sick, and -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Congressmen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, they didn't go to congressman. They just bugged me periodically.
                    Q: And hepatitis is no fun. You were laid up for -</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, when I got it, I was out of action altogether. It's a lazy man's
                    disease. It's not all that painful. The beginning's like flu, of course. You
                    have fever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But bed rest, that's the only thing you can do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, that's the only thing. They put me in the hospital and put me on
                    intravenous feeding and kept me quiet. I couldn't move even to go to the
                    bathroom.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any damage to your liver?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, I survived without that, but I was off duty for quite some time. I
                    think I came down with this illness in mid November, let's say, six weeks after
                    the search, and I finally started back to work in January, but only half days. I
                    found that I couldn't handle visa work or anything else that imposed a strain on
                    me. I just emotionally had no stamina, emotional stamina. I just sat there. I
                    didn't break down and cry; I just didn't handle it. It was sad, so I was given a
                    chance to do political work - and that's what I really wanted to do anyhow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, good for you, but you were able to do it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, so I came in half days for the political section, then full days,
                    and I even got some plaudits from the Department, which in those days reacted to
                    reporting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that was the pattern, I guess. It was in my case.
                        They wanted to be sure you were in all sections of the embassy in the first
                        couple of tours. So you had consular and political.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, and then - I was trying to arrange my own rotation - they had a
                    junior officer job that opened up in the economic section, an economically
                    inclined junior officer assigned to it. I said, “Look, let's work out a rotation
                    so that he goes to consular and gets his rotation in consular work, I go to
                    economic, and now we've got a rotation schedule for junior officers, those two
                    positions.” And that was accepted. So I spent my second and final year out of
                    two and a half in Costa Rica in economic work.</p>
                <p>And then during that year, I was trying to decide what hard language to sign up
                    for. You may recall that in those days the Department had a very grown-up policy
                    that all officers should have a “world language” and a “hard language.” And I
                    was sucker enough to believe in it, I guess. It was a good choice.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you choose?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I chose Turkish, at the urging of my DCM, who had been a very
                    promising Turkish language officer. I had though about Japanese, but my older
                    brother was already a specialist in Japanese religions. He went into academia,
                    and I thought two brothers in Japan to be one too many. I thought about another
                    Far Eastern language, because the Far East interested me. I hadn't been there in
                    three and a half years. And I considered Russian, but what I heard about the
                    problems of living in Russia and being under constant surveillance didn't
                    encourage me much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Turkish limits you to Turkey, of course. You
                        couldn't use it anywhere else.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, no, my first post was Cyprus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that was before it was divided.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes. It was when it was divided.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, so you saw some of the fireworks.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Oh, I should say I did. I finished up the Turkish course in May or
                    June of 1963, and went on the Cyprus Desk for three months waiting for a job to
                    open up in Cyprus. It turned out to be the consular job, but it was only a sort
                    of part-time consular work. There wasn't that much to do in consular affairs in
                    Cyprus, and the rest was supposed to be political, and I was being sent there as
                    the first Turkish-speaking officer in the Embassy. And it was otherwise and
                    overwhelmingly a Greek-oriented embassy. All the other language officers were
                    Greek language officers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember the ambassador at the time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, that was Fraser Wilkins, when I arrived.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. I know Fraser.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I arrived there in September - so many things in my life seem to
                    happen in September - and had about three months to get my feet on the ground
                    and meet the Turks and start taking Turkish lessons to keep my conversation
                    going, because I had to live in the Greek Sector. It turned out I never found a
                    house. We were looking all over the island and couldn't find a place that suited
                    my wife. We stayed in the temporary apartments that were right across the street
                    and a half block beyond the embassy, just a vacant lot between us. The embassy
                    was in two joined apartment buildings or office buildings, with a slight break
                    or dip between them. And the night that it all broke loose, I was embassy duty
                    officer, which was just, I think, three nights before Christmas. It think it was
                    December 22nd of '63. It was at 11 or 12 o'clock at night I heard a tremendous
                    siren go off, and I figured it was from the police stations. Other sirens, then
                    BOOM! BOOM! Grenades and gunfire. It was pretty loud. I quickly jumped into my
                    clothes and ran across the street to the embassy and notified the ambassador. He
                    asked me to get the country team together - that was everybody - so I started
                    calling them, and I was interrupted by a fellow from the Tourism Hotel. “What's
                    going on here?” This was for me the definitive instance of the fog of battle. I
                    didn't know what was going on, and I had to tell him so. I didn't know that this
                    many years later we would still have a Cyprus problem. No one is quite sure yet
                    what set off that incident that developed into full-scale fighting between the
                    paramilitaries of the two sides.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You don't know who fired the first shot?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No. Apparently a Greek police patrol was pressing the Turkish
                    Cypriots. A Greek police patrol was in the Turkish Cypriot area of north
                    Nicosia, and fighting broke out, but I don't know who fired the first shot or
                    why. But the two sides had been getting visibly more tense for some time, since
                    I had arrived there. And the Greek Cypriot police had been searching for hidden
                    Turkish arms, trying to round up Turkish Cypriot paramilitary. Well, in the next
                    couple of days, some 104 Turkish Cypriots were killed. Only five of them were
                    from battles. And then the next three or four months, the Turkish Cypriots, who
                    were then 18 per cent of the population, were driven back out of their villages
                    into about five per cent of the Island's area, where they've stayed for the next
                    10 years. This, today, would be called, of course, “ethnic cleansing.” In those
                    days, we couldn't see it that way.</p>
                <p>We had, of course, an element of adjusting to the initial shock, responding in a
                    variety of ways. The British had forces on the island who did a very good job of
                    moving in and interposing themselves and talking truce and getting the fighting
                    to stop within about two days. But it wasn't sure how long the peace would hold.
                    So that on Christmas Day, I organized a convoy to go into the Turkish Cypriot
                    sector and bring out American and any other foreigners that were cut off there.
                    We knew there were about 17 Americans that were cut off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So essentially, the island was divided.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was divided just almost overnight.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was before the Turkish forces arrived.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, that was another thing here later, 10 years later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But it's the British that interposed, because there was no
                        UN presence at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: The UN forces came in a few months later, and the Brits continued to
                    be part of the UN force. They were the largest contingent, but there were
                    Canadians, Norwegians. . . . It was a big operation. It was, I think, the first
                    UN peacekeeping force. UNPECYP, it was called.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You as a Turkish-speaking officer, were you suspect?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I was suspect, of course. They Greeks thought that I was
                    pro-Turkish, and the Turks were quite pleased initially to have me as eighth man
                    in the embassy, and then they began thinking, Hey, he lives in the Greek Sector.
                    He's coming over here to spy on us and going back and telling the others. So I
                    was suspected by both sides. And that corresponded with my own attitude, which
                    was “a plague on both your houses” - get along, as you used to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there for the US national interests, nobody else.
                        You weren't trying to be a partisan in the conflict. Just Uncle Sam's
                        interest required you to be that way.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Exactly, that's right. But the Greeks, especially, whose initiative
                    had set up the whole thing, were paranoid and bloodily paranoid. They were
                    willing to kill. They had shot an American member of the embassy in the late
                    '50's, when they were trying to get the Brits out. Somebody went to the man's
                    door, and when he opened it, someone fired six or so shots from a revolver and
                    it was only because he fell to one side he lived - I mean, he was badly hurt,
                    but he survived. And we had repeated threats against us, because we were trying
                    to keep the Greek Cypriots from going out an completing the job of wiping out
                    the minority Turks. And the Turks, meanwhile, “We have the right of intervention
                    under the 1958 agreement, and we could exercise it.” “Oh, no,” the United States
                    Government said. Britain said, “you would set off a war with Greece.” “Greece
                    would fight Turkey?” Well, this became our policy - that we would avoid Turkish
                    intervention. The Turks should not intervene; they should sit by and let their
                    community sit and be squeezed, besieged, by the Greeks. The whole thing, of
                    course, had started out of the desire of Greece, and especially the Greek
                    Orthodox Church, to reunite all the regions where historically Greeks had been
                    present and where actually there was a large Greek population. This was enosis
                    of Greece, and in another term it might be called Greek territorial expansion,
                    or territorial ambitions. I don't think we came out so strongly against Greece,
                    but we had called a spade a spade, and it was their ambition, and not any
                    ambition of Turkey's on Cyprus, that caused the problem. The Brits, as a
                    historical footnote, had offered Cyprus to Greece in 1914, that Greece would
                    join the allied side in World War II. Athens then had a lot of German influence,
                    and Athens refused. It was a terrible mistake. After World War II, after the
                    Italians had been forced out, Greece wanted to continue expanding, and they saw
                    the successes of nationals elsewhere against the British Empire and got curious.
                    They sent they young monk Makarios to Cyprus after training him in the US with
                    the specific mission of uniting Cyprus for Greece. The Church was a direct
                    inheritor of Byzantium. A great many people make the mistake of considering
                    Greece to be the inheritors of Pericles. That's not Greece. So that Makarios did
                    what he could to carry out his mission. He had accepted the London-Zurich
                    Accords, not happily, but he had accepted them, dividing the government of the
                    island, but keeping the island whole and integrated. He became the first
                    president, and the Vice-President was a Turkish Cypriot, Dr. K�c�k, a medical
                    doctor. I don't know if you've found this. There are a great many medical
                    doctors that rose to prominence in politics in very small countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any feel for the Greek lobby in this country?
                        Was it powerful?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Oh, terribly powerful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Turks were separate.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I heard personally from it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the Turks had no lobby, really.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the Greek lobby is powerful on the hill. You felt that
                        in the early days. It was always there pressuring the White House.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes. This, I suppose, was a basic reason for our taking such a pro
                    -Greek stand on the issue. Another part, of course, was the threat of the Soviet
                    Union. Greece could have been torn loose from its association with NATO, could
                    have opened the door to their co-religionists in Moscow. That's possible. I'll
                    concede that as a possibility. But at any rate, we were not concerned with
                    righting injustices against minorities; we were just concerned to keep the lid
                    on, don't explode.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And it was Cold War time. Everything related to the Cold
                        War. A Communist threat was always there. And for 25 years I dealt with the
                        Communist threat, as you did. That was our main preoccupation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Precisely. Everything was oriented toward basically our national
                    survival and the contest, in any case, with the Soviets, the KGB, and all its
                    many fronts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they must have been pretty busy on the Island.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: They had a Communist Party there and a Communist trade union which was
                    quite powerful.</p>
                <p>Q: Did they have an embassy also.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Oh, yes, there was a Russian embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they ran a powerful operation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The CIA had to watch them very closely.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Of course, they watched the CIA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any problems with the CIA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, I didn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were there. They were going about their
                        business.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: The CIA people that I knew were Eagle Scouts. They were all close
                    friends. We even lived. . . . Most of the families were moved out - several of
                    us shared an apartment. There were two CIA officers and two State officers,
                    buddies. This was not the CIA of myth; this was the CIA of good, highly
                    patriotic people. They simply had a different method of operating than we did,
                    but the same goals. Q: So you had two years in Cyprus.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I had two years in Cyprus. I should point out some of my adventures
                    there. I was living, as I said, not far from the embassy, in clear view of the
                    embassy. In early February we got a warning that a small fanatic group of Greek
                    Cypriots led by Makarios's personal physician, who had sworn to attack Americans
                    - the British intelligence put this out and passed it on to the CIA, which
                    passed it on to everyone. Everywhere around the world (the rest of my Foreign
                    Service career I was getting at least one threat every six months, I think) -
                    but this was specific and time-related, and it was confirmed by later events.
                    The evening of the 4th or 5th of February I was standing out in front of the
                    temporary apartments talking with a neighbor who was a communicator and saw this
                    sand colored Land Rover with several people inside pull up to the side gate of
                    the embassy, about 30 or 40 feet from the embassy itself. The gate, of course,
                    was unlocked. There were no guards outside. These were the early days. Somebody
                    got out, unloaded something from the back of the Land Rover, pushed the gate
                    open, walked up to a permanently closed side door, entered - it was the wrong
                    building - set down the package, struck a match, and lit the fuse, and at that
                    moment converted himself into an enemy of my country. I got his description. He
                    ran back to the Land Rover, which tore off. I couldn't see the license plate as
                    I ran. I ran to the embassy and told the Marine guard to get everybody out of
                    the building, and the bomb went off. And with the Marine behind me, I ran around
                    the end of the building to check to damage, and someone, some person we had
                    evacuated, called from behind to look out, there may be a second one in there.
                    He saved my life. I ducked around the corner of the building, and - KABOOM! -
                    the second one went off, knocked down the Marine, who miraculously was not hit
                    by these flying fragments of pipe that had been put inside a threaded pipe so it
                    would break up into shrapnel. One piece went through the side of a car, and
                    another one cut down a small cypress tree. They were picked up all over the
                    place. And just after the first one went off, just after I'd ducked around the
                    side of the building, the ambassador, who lived on the top floor of an adjoining
                    building, the penthouse, called down, “What's going on down there?” because I
                    hadn't had time to notify him. And I said, “One small bomb, Sir.” BOOM! - the
                    second one went off. “Correction: two small bombs, Sir.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you knocked on the ground by the second one?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, I was around the corner from it. The Marine was knocked down,
                    though, and I was okay. Nobody's hit me yet. A lot of people have tried, though.
                    So the ambassador called a country team meeting and decreed evacuation. So I
                    spent the rest of the night as consular officer organizing my share of the
                    evacuation. We got all of the families off the next morning for Beirut.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's the evacuation of the embassy. What about the other
                        Americans on Cyprus? Did they leave voluntarily?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: There were not many other Americans. We had already had a cutting back
                    of the official presence to essential personnel, so the Peace Corps left, most
                    of the AID mission, and so on. The Americans who remained were in the station
                    that I can't refer to in greater detail and the cadre of the embassy. And let's
                    see, the UN force came in. I was the principal go-between with the Turkish
                    Cypriots. I kept in constant touch with them. I had finished the Turkish course
                    with an S4/R4, which at that time was a record, I think, and in fact led them
                    to... There was a couple with an S4/R4 in Hindi that Tony Quainton achieved. Our
                    success motivated FSI's hierarchy to proclaim that henceforth nobody would get
                    S4 on the basis of 10 months of language training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Rather arbitrary, I would say.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: But anyway, the linguists thought we were both deserving of it. At any
                    rate -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your family had gone.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: My family was gone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you send them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Beirut. And they stayed there until May. My wife had an operation and
                    then went back to Texas to recover. The children were with her. I was all alone
                    in Cyprus until December, when they returned. Things had settled down by that
                    time, and there was no longer a threat to Americans. I finally found a house,
                    where we stayed for seven months or so.</p>
                <p>And let's see, what other stories can I... Oh, yes. Let me continue what I
                    started, this critique of US policy. The Greeks made a flagrant attempt at
                    annexing Cyprus in July of 1974, when the Greek junta was in power, which
                    impelled the Turks this time to invade. And many casualties and considerable
                    destruction. This could have been avoided if Turkey had been permitted to
                    intervene in 1964 on the outbreak in December of '63, and the intervention would
                    have been to restore the status quo ante, the London-Zurich Accords, that is,
                    the combined government -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they had a right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: They had a right under those accords, which we prevented them from
                    exercising, we and the Brits. And furthermore, this would have prevented the
                    partitioning of Cyprus, that would have meant to the Greeks great advantage.
                    And, yes, we couldn't do that. It was a major shortsightedness of policy.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>Q: Whether the Greek lobby is to blame for this?</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I'm not aware of it, but I simply say that it was a major failing, and
                    I think it bears relation to the policy over Yugoslavia. This Greek-Turkish
                    problem in Cyprus was, in fact, our first Balkan War of the second half of this
                    century, and the same elements present in Yugoslavia were present there,
                    especially the incitement of ethnic anger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Makes sense.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And the fight over holy land. Well, so much for our policy. I
                    continued to carry it out as an embassy officer. I had to defend it at one
                    point. I was invited by a Turkish Cypriot friend to visit his club one evening.
                    I arrived on schedule and was shown into this conference hall where about 50
                    Turkish Cypriot men, obviously the educated type, were assembled, and I was
                    shown to a seat at a table facing them. I thought I was there as a guest. It
                    turned out I was there as an object of questions, and for an hour or an hour and
                    a half I carried on in Turkish defending the United States position. It was, I
                    guess, the roughest time I ever encountered with people who were under siege as
                    a result of United States policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you allowed to write that up when you went back to
                        the embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I wrote it up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You wrote it up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I believe I did. I think it's on the record. Although the people in
                    the embassy were so pro-Greek, they thought they were bending over backwards. I
                    was kind of like the token Negro. Although the ambassador did later make a point
                    of meeting with the Turks every week. Fraser Wilkins lasted only until about
                    March of '64. He began drinking rather heavily under pressure. George Ball came
                    out on a peacemaking effort and was not well impressed and had him withdrawn. He
                    never again had an ambassadorial job. He was inspector general later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who replaced him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: He was replaced by Toby Belcher, Taylor G. Belcher -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. I know Toby.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND:- a great guy. We were all friends, and he had this instinct for -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Energetic.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND:- diplomacy, and particularly for a trouble spot or a hot spot. He knew
                    where to send people and what to do, how to get things done. And I ran afoul of
                    the Turks, in particular, one instance which I frustrated an effort by a Turk in
                    their embassy to set off a Turkish air strike. He was the, I suppose, USIS
                    equivalent. He sent off a false report to the Turkish radio station in Ankara to
                    the effect that Greek Cypriots were attacking a Turkish village in the north of
                    Cyprus. We picked this up on, what is it, the -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: FBIS?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND:- FBIS, yes, thank you, almost immediately. It came in as a flash
                    message. I quickly checked with the UN. “Has there been any attack on this
                    Turkish village West Akron?” Because he had reported artillery shelling. “No,
                    it's all quiet there.” “Are you sure?” “Yes.” I reported, put in the
                    ambassador's support, “Tell the Turks, don't react.” They had sworn that they
                    would send in fighter bombers next time a Turkish Cypriot village was attacked.
                    We frustrated this. And I was pinned with the responsibility for this in the
                    Turkish eyes, and this particular Turk sent off a message which I later heard
                    about thanks to CIA saying that I was CIA. I was supposed to be an operative. It
                    discredited me, but another Turkish Cypriot told me that this man had confided
                    to him that “I have prepared a pilaf for Mr. McFarland, and he is going to have
                    to eat it.” Well, I didn't have too much difficulty eating that particular
                    pilaf. But this must have been in May or so. In late July or early August, after
                    working seven days a week for about seven weeks straight, I took a few days off
                    and went down to Tel Aviv to rest on the beach and see something of Israel, and
                    the first morning I was there, I picked up the newspaper: “Turkish Jets Bomb
                    Cyprus.” Oh, God! Just when I was away! I tried frantically to get a flight back
                    there. The embassy in Tel Aviv couldn't have cared less. I had to wait until my
                    scheduled return. Meanwhile, other people had handled it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: People were hurt.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: People were hurt, and then the Greek Cypriot armed forces got hurt.
                    They had attacked Turkish Cypriots and tried to extend their . . . and the Turks
                    responded.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By air. So you were due to leave. You were there more than
                        two years?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I was there not quite two years. I arrived in September and left in
                    July.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Theoretically you were ready for a Washington assignment,
                        were you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, I was sent on to Istanbul. That was my reward for Cyprus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So this is three overseas assignments in a row.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, of course, separated by Turkish language training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So Istanbul.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It had changed from your time even then. They had built some new
                    highways and torn down parts of the city to open up traffic. It was then about
                    1,300,000, probably not much change from your time, but certainly far smaller,
                    about a tenth of the size that it is now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes - 12 million. I was there a couple of weeks ago,
                        12 million in Istanbul.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND:Really, wow. Well, anyway, I loved Istanbul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The consulate, when I visited a couple of weeks ago, they
                        have a big wall right on the street to close the street between the two
                        buildings. It's just a solid wall, and they've taken bombs, rockets into the
                        garden. I went inside. Remember what a wonderful building, the two of
                        them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In a cage of concrete.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I wouldn't want to see it.</p>
                <p>Q: It really broke my heart.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, my heart was already broken by what they did after I left. When
                    I was there I had the greatest most beautiful office I've ever had. Maybe it was
                    your office too.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Second floor?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Marble fireplace. You went in the front door of the old main
                    building.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The main building?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: The main building. Over on the right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I wasn't there. I was in the other building. You were
                        in the main building?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, the consul general was at the back on the left side, and we had
                    the ballroom upstairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, it's a different place. Were you political then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I was assigned there as a political officer. My consular days
                    were finally over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, good for you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And I had not been doing all that much consular work in Cyprus. The
                    weirdest case, I suppose, in Cyprus was this woman who came in one day, an
                    American citizen, bar girl type, with a scarf around her neck and dyed hair and
                    so on, tall woman, and brought this American passport. She had spilled hair dye
                    in her purse, and it had unfortunately gone right across the identification
                    page, and she filled out an application for a new one as Roberta such and such.
                    Well, of course, that was presumptive fraud, and we had to send down the
                    application to the Department, and back it came and “Roberta” was actually
                    Robert. He/she had been working as a bar girl in the bars frequented by all the
                    UN people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Nicosia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: In Nicosia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Isn't that cute.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And then on top of that became destitute. I had to arrange a loan from
                    relations she had in the States and then finally issued a passport good only for
                    return to the United States in the name of Robert. And he/she objected to this
                    wildly. “I'm going on the airplane representing America, and how do you want me
                    to look? Nice, dressed up, like a pretty girl, or looking like a god-damned
                    queer?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She wore a dress, did she?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, bar girl, you know. Well, sorry, but this is you - you're Robert
                    and this is the only thing I can do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a sex-change, as far as you could tell?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: He or she claimed to have had the preliminary operation for a surgical
                    change of sex. I was at the end of the chain of command.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You got rid of her; that's the important thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I had various other consular adventures. There was one that I
                    couldn't have gotten away with now, but there was this paranoid Greek American
                    who had flown back to Cyprus and had run out of funds; at the same time he was
                    causing problems with his behavior. I think he may have been
                    paranoid-schizophrenic, the most dangerous kind. He had worked in a restaurant
                    in the States. He was a big strong guy. And we finally issued him a passport
                    good only for return, and got some sort of clearance to get him on the next
                    flight out. And then when we went looking for him at his hotel with the navy
                    corpsman and ambulance driver and ambulance, and the navy corpsman and I found
                    him sitting outside his hotel. The people there had shoved him out. And we each
                    grabbed an arm and got him into the van, by force. As I say, we couldn't do that
                    these days. And once he was in the ambulance, we shot him with something or
                    other and calmed him down and put him on the plane. But it sure solved the
                    problem of his misbehavior and his safety in a dangerous situation. He could
                    have done some wild thing, and the Turks would have shot him dead.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He could have gone berserk.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: The sides were not that far apart, you know. There was just the Green
                    Line, as the British named it. It was a green line because they had chosen the
                    green grease pencil to draw to draw on the map. That's the origin of the term
                    green line.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But your relations with the British were cordial.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Oh, yes, very cordial, and probably the UN troops. They were all
                    excellent people. The Irish had a particularly outstanding contingent there.</p>
                <p>We had a good time in Istanbul. I loved the city, but life there was considerably
                    duller, without conflict except, of course, that the resentment against the US
                    stewed and stewed, and one of my regular chores was to go to Taksim Square and
                    count the number of people who were engaging in the latest demonstration against
                    the United States. And I nonetheless met a lot of Turks who really became
                    friends, and I was sorry to leave them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was consul general?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Lansing Collins. He was a Princetonian who had served in Ankara some
                    years before as counselor for pol-mil affairs. This was his last post. I think
                    he retired after that. It's often used as a retirement post. I had been promoted
                    fairly rapidly. After I got into Istanbul, I got the old Class 4, which would be
                    Class 2 now. So I caught up with my colleagues in the Air Force, who were making
                    lieutenant colonel about that time. Unfortunately, the second year I was in
                    Istanbul, my wife had sort of broken down in depression and so on and had to go
                    back to the Untied States again. The deputy consul general's wife invited me to
                    dinner. And I had something else going on at the time I took the call, and
                    failed to write it down, and I failed to go to the dinner. She got extremely
                    hurt. Her husband took extreme exception. It wasn't an excusable thing to do,
                    but it wasn't worth the penalty that I suffered, because I got an efficiency
                    report out of him that Lansing Collins tried to counteract but couldn't. There
                    were the days before you could argue, and so on. I spent 10 years in that
                    grade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My goodness, that was devastating.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It was devastating. I didn't “get along well with other Americans.”
                    That's all. And in Cyprus I had been given some report to the effect that I
                    should be promoted to old Class 2 by age 40, in a position to make the grade by
                    age 40, rapid riser, and all that. And he said I should be kept in grade at
                    least until about 1975, I think, or '72. Anyhow, I was promoted in '66 and
                    promoted the next time in '76 or 7.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because of that one supervisor?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes. Well, that plus I went to the Cyprus Desk, where I thought I did
                    a brilliant job, but there was this durn - darn Bob Folsom, who was put in over
                    me as Cyprus country officer, director of Cyprus affairs. And this same one who
                    had given me the bad efficiency report in Istanbul had moved to the Turkish Desk
                    for this time, and he poisoned this guy against me, and this happened to be the
                    time when efficiency reports included a secret annex which could not be shown to
                    the recipient, and he said in there that I had been promoted too fast and was
                    too young or something.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's -</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And in all due immodesty, I had run circles around the man. And -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Nasty, that one dinner party did it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND:- anyway, it was unbeknownst to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Istanbul was not a happy place. Your wife had her problem,
                        and you had your problem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, but that was only the second year I was there, because the first
                    year I got promoted. And I really liked Istanbul, I was happy, and I enjoyed not
                    having my wife there, once she left.</p>
                <p>Q: The kids, what about them? Did they go with your wife?</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: They went with the wife. My life in Istanbul was kind of idyllic in
                    retrospect, because I enjoyed the language, I enjoyed the people, with the
                    entr�e I had I could go anywhere in the city at any hour of the day or night.
                    All of the waiters in the good restaurants knew me. Life was cheap.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you live?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I lived in Bebek.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, my.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I had a partial view of the Bosporus, not the greatest, but I drove or
                    took the bus or a bulmus up and down the Bosporus to go to work. And it was
                    always a drive through history, and the Bosporus of course, was constantly
                    changing its moods.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I had lunch in Bebek last time I was there, a couple
                        of weeks ago. It was the restaurants, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, I understand that it's now a very expensive place to live.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. I wouldn't want to live there, not at all. So you
                        had two years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I had two years in Istanbul and then was sent to the Cyprus Desk in
                    Washington. Well, Jack Horner was the one who asked me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, Jack Horner.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND:To go there, but he retired after I had been there only about a month
                    or so, and Bob Folsom, then, who had been consul general in Salonika, was
                    brought in as the country directory.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this is still GTI, isn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Sir?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it GTI? Greece, Turkey, and Iran?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: At this point they had broken up GTI. It had been GTI when I was on
                    the Cyprus Desk before, but then they had reorganized with these country
                    directors with the idea of eliminating one layer so that in effect the deputy
                    assistant secretary became the office director with the Turkish country director
                    and the Cyprus country director and the Iran country director underneath him.
                    Stuart Rockwell was the supervisor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. I remember him.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And I again arrived just in time for a crisis. This was a crisis
                    engineered by a General George Grevis, formerly of the Greek army, who decided
                    to take some armored cars into a Turkish village and start shooting things up.
                    This determined the Turks to intervene. This was, I think, in late November or
                    early December of '67. And that was when Cyrus Vance was sent as mediator. I was
                    handling the whole crisis and almost lost control to the Rostow brother, not
                    Eugene, but there was a Walter?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Walter, Walt. The one who was here in UT.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Oh, maybe it was Eugene. I'm sorry, but one of them was in State.</p>
                <p>Q: Yes, Walter is the economist, I think. Well, they were both in State, I guess,
                    at one time.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Anyway, he was moving to take over this crisis when there was a crisis
                    in pound sterling, and he moved to that instead, so the pros handled it and did
                    all the work, and it went very well. So twice in a row we were able to keep the
                    Turks from intervening. But the first time - I should have mentioned this while
                    I was still on Cyprus - there was the Johnson letter (this was, I think, in June
                    or July of '64), which I believe George Ball said was “the crudest piece of
                    diplomatic writing every developed.” It was written by a woman that made me a
                    great favorite of hers. Formerly she was the head of GTI, Kay Bratman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember Kay.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I looked it up in the files later, and found that she was the drafting
                    officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For LBJ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And LBJ signed. Indeed, it was from Lyndon to Inonu.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “Crude,” you say.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Oh, it threatened that if the Soviet Union intervened against Turkey
                    because of Turkey's actions against Cyprus, we would feel under no obligation to
                    come to Turkey's support. That was its principal proviso. And to Inonu, who was
                    frankly - founded his relationship as Atat�rk's chief lieutenant - was frankly
                    like Mohamed, a sacred figure in the cult of Atat�rkism.</p>
                <p>Q: What was his response?</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It was a terrible thing to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the response? The Turks did not invade.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, the Turks did not invade. They did not intervene.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they resented it deeply.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: But they resented it deeply.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you consider Johnson pro-Greek? I know he spent time
                        in Greece.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I don't know. I don't know if he was or not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, anyway, you would have known if you were on the
                        Desk. I know he visited Greece at least once. I know that he never was in
                        Turkey.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, there wasn't - and he didn't do anything particular for Greece
                    at the time I was on the Desk.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But he was President then. I think he went to Greece
                        before, when he was Vice-President.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: We used to send over these snippets for the President's evening
                    reading but had little hope that they would ever be read.</p>
                <p>Q: Vietnam was there anyway.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: There's only so much presidential time available during the day.
                    Anyway, we got past that second crisis, so we stopped the Turks from intervening
                    twice. Now once by threat and once by mediation. To advance a little on my
                    story, in July of 1974 - I was by then acting political counselor in Ankara -
                    the Greek junta tried to depose Makarios and set up a Cyprus for Greece. I
                    cannot understand the prime minister in Greece in those days, Ioannidis. He had
                    spent his life as a neighbor of the Turks. Their prime intelligence target must
                    have been Turkey, and surely should have understood how the Turks would react.
                    And yet he thought that “our great, good friends, the Americans, who had stopped
                    them twice will stop them a third time, and it is their duty and responsibility
                    to do so.” (Of course we couldn't.)</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Turks marched.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: They had a division earmarked for Cyprus. It did a miserable job of
                    command and control, but it got ashore. Then there had to be a second invasion.
                    But Makarios survived. He escaped their attempt to arrest him and fled to the
                    Brits, and the junta wound up being deposed themselves. They paid heavily for
                    their mistake, just like the Argentine junta.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did they do on the Island? A new line was drawn by
                        the Turkish troops?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, they came in the first time, they saved the airfield and a small
                    area around Farinya and then around Alistim. It wasn't a large enough holding,
                    so the Turks reorganized, sent in more forces, and reopened the battle a few
                    weeks later. And it was that second intervention which brought international
                    opprobrium on them, and the first one was considered to be within their rights
                    under the London-Zurich treaty. But the second one just seemed to be gratuitous,
                    and it was on that basis that the United States, in its wisdom, cut off all
                    further supplies of arms to a NATO ally, Turkey. And that was what I suffered
                    under in Ankara. I spent a good deal of time defending that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Explaining that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Defending the US and explaining its policy, and fighting with people
                    in Washington. I think I must have had to spend as much time arguing in
                    Washington as I did talking to Turks. But anyway, my only contribution to the
                    Cyprus Desk, really, apart from day-to-day forecasting and handling that event -
                    must say, I made accurate forecasts; I only missed once - I developed a proposal
                    for standby mediation, based on the success of the Vance mission. The US would
                    have a mediator briefed and ready to step in, and this proposal was accepted by
                    the ambassadors in all three countries involved, and we took it to Joe Sisco,
                    who at that time was assistant secretary for the UN. Joe Sisco vetoed it. No,
                    Cyprus is a UN concern now. We cannot take this down the road. Better let the UN
                    handle it. And Stu Rockwell okayed my idea, which essentially has come out now
                    with a special coordinator for Cyprus affairs. Well, but nonetheless, this would
                    have been further along the lines of policy that I have seen now as mistaken,
                    the idea of keeping Cyprus as an undivided whole, undivided except for the Greek
                    lines around the Turks, and subject to future trouble.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>I don't know if I spelled out my position adequately to begin with, but the
                    problem is that the core of the Cyprus problem is Greece's desire for Enosis,
                    opposed by Turkey's concern that Greece will then control its entire coastline.
                    All the approaches from the Mediterranean and Aegean will have to pass close to
                    Greek Islands. This is anathema to Turkish security planners. Atat�rk felt that
                    Turkey must be a secure territory, with no expansion, just secure territory.
                    Turkey, apparently, has no real ambitions for territory in Cyprus. The reason
                    for the partitioning of Cyprus is to prevent Enosis, as I see it, not to breed a
                    terrible financial burden and drain on Turkey of having a separate Turkish
                    Cypriot state which can't support itself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So there are Turkish troops there, and it's a
                        republic.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, recognized only by Turkey. The rest of us seem to want to have a
                    unitary Cyprus once more. Now a unitary Cyprus would simply be another target
                    for the Greeks to try to capture, which would set off more conflict. The best
                    long-term solution for Cyprus is what we've got now, the division, the
                    partition, which is resented by Washington and, or course, most of all by
                    Athens, because it makes Enosis impossible. It's better to make Enosis
                    impossible, and then let's get on about the business of living.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the UN has a substantial force there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes it does.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To avoid conflict.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I doubt that there would be any conflict if the UN force left.
                    There might be some shooting by hotheads. It would depend very much on the
                    leadership of both sides. I read in the newspaper that fighting was going to
                    start again. I doubt that very much. That depends very much on the mainland
                    countries. The problem with Greece's attitude toward Turkey is that as a small
                    country it does not have the power to overcome Turkey, so it keeps sticking its
                    finger into the big guy's eye, provoking Turkey without a rational hope of
                    accomplishing any good end.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Pure nationalism.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, and bravura. I understand it in the Greek psyche and the Latin
                    psyche, but it's just not rational, and we should not let ourselves be captured
                    by it as we have let ourselves be captured by it. We went into Yugoslavia, I
                    think, initially with the idea that there should be no partitioning and found
                    that good fences do make good neighbors, or at least neighbors that are some
                    sort of peace. And I'm afraid that that's the only solution for Cyprus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Greece is part of the Balkans.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Greece is part of the Balkans. And Turkey is. Turkey was the Balkan
                    power. But this is another Balkan war that's best settled by partition - which
                    we've got in place. There's not been any fighting since partition was
                    established in 1974. Before that there was fighting periodically. They could
                    live on their own without Uncle Sam I'm quite sure. I would hope that Greece and
                    Turkey would little by little withdraw their own forces.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Greece doesn't have any forces there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Oh, yes, they do. They have 10,000 or 12,000 troops, and Turkey has
                    more than that. I think they have most of a division. And they've even
                    established a university around Famagusta.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A Greek university?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, a Turkish Cypriot university.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I see what you mean.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: A friend of mine in Ankara has gone there to teach. He retired from
                    teaching at Ankara University and moved down there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, is there a Greek Cypriot army or police force?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I'm not sure what their arrangements are now. They had a police
                    force, which rapidly was converted into infantry at the time of the fighting.
                    And there was a small army, but they depended mainly on the Greek army
                    contingent. Under the London-Zurich agreement, both the mainland countries were
                    permitted to position contingents. And they fought. One of the last incidents of
                    the time when the Turkish invasion occurred. Turkey's difficulty was in
                    communications and maintaining command and control. In Ankara we were contacted
                    by the Turkish General Staff who said, “Our aircraft has reported a Greek
                    destroyer to the north of Cyprus steaming toward Cyprus. This is within an area
                    that we consider unacceptable. Please inform Athens to turn that ship around, or
                    we're going to sink it.” We quickly got off a Niact, Flash, whatever it was
                    forwarding a message to Athens. They contacted the Greeks and came back with the
                    response “that's not our ship. We have no destroyers in the area. If you think
                    it ought to be sunk, go ahead and sink it.” Well, the Turkish Air Force was
                    unable to contact the destroyer. It was of course flying a Turkish flag on its
                    stern, but of course those perfidious Greeks would do that. And using their US
                    training they peeled off and put bombs onto it. It sank. About a week or so
                    later, crew members on a lifeboat were picked up by a passing freighter, and the
                    truth came out. The Turks had bombed their own ship. They didn't have common
                    frequency between ship and air.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's inexcusable.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Lack of information, lack of communications, planning, and discipline.
                    It was the Turks' first time in combat since Korea, and Korea was sort of an
                    exception. They were fighting under our command, and it was just a brigade. It
                    was not all branches. The Turkish Air Force had never been in combat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how did things go on the Cyprus Desk in
                        general?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: The thing is, once that December crisis cooled off and I'd tried to
                    get my paper accepted, things became very, very dull, and I began running out of
                    things to do, and I thought about getting on another desk and thought there was
                    a chance here to write a paper. I asked for a year of independent study. It was
                    run by FSI, and I went to the Library of Congress and then to the State
                    Department library. This was during Vietnam times, and I wrote on the subject of
                    consulting the electorate in making foreign policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Consulting -</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND:- the electorate, the US electorate, because it was felt at the time
                    that there wasn't enough consultation. Studies of McNamara had shown that, yes,
                    there's plenty of consultation, and the public did support the initial
                    investment in Vietnam, and only then turned against policy. But anyway, I spent
                    a year working up the paper, which, again, was not published. I thought I had a
                    lot of good ideas, and in effect, the ideas were carried out later - not that .
                    . .I had advocated sort of direct consultation with individuals. We were already
                    in consultation with lobbying groups, of course, but what happened was that
                    Congress started asserting a greater role in foreign policy making.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So your paper was not published.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, it wasn't published.</p>
                <p>Q: It's in the archives somewhere, is it? It has to be.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND:It may be. I have a copy of it, at least.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If you did it under FSI, it would be part of the FSI
                        archives, wouldn't it be?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I guess. I don't know. I have a copy of it still, about a 50-page
                    paper, 50-60 pages. It was too long to be an article and too short to be a book.
                    I think that was it's main problem, and by the time I finished it, of course, I
                    was ready to move to a new post and thinking about that and didn't want to take
                    the time to shorten it or lengthen it. Toby Belcher, my ambassador in Cyprus,
                    was reassigned to Lima, Peru, and asked to have me transferred there to his
                    political section. And he tried, he wrote a letter to Cyrus Vance with a copy of
                    this, urging that Cyrus Vance get it published in Foreign Affairs, but nothing
                    further happened.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>Anyway, I moved on to Lima, Peru. My marriage, by that time, had been growing
                    worse and worse and worse. My wife was in tears almost all the time. My
                    firstborn, my son, was delighted with the prospect of moving to Lima. I had
                    thought that he would want to finish his high school in Bethesda, Bethesda-Chevy
                    Chase high school, where he had just started. But no, he was delighted to go. He
                    had learned Spanish in Costa Rica, where he'd gone as a child, and so off we
                    went to Lima. It was then run by a military dictatorship which was very
                    anti-American. They had started out their r�gime by confiscating, nationalizing,
                    American oil companies, International Petroleum. This was in '68. It was
                    actually registered in Canada but American-owned. And nationalization without
                    compensation went down crosswise. This had become a big nationalist issue in
                    Peru, and foreign exploitation of their sacred oil, as it was in so many
                    countries. I arrived just about six weeks after the great Peruvian earthquake in
                    1970. I got there in July. I guess it happened the end of May. There was a kind
                    of international competition to provide aid to the survivors. About 70,000
                    people were estimated to have been killed, most of them up in the mountains, a
                    great many of them in one mudslide that simply covered an entire town. That
                    first weekend, I took a shared taxi and went up close to visit the destruction.
                    There, typically, relief efforts which were largely being carried out by the
                    Catholic Church, with a great many foreign priests. The next weekend, I borrowed
                    an embassy jeep in terrible condition and drove up this makeshift road to the
                    disruption of the mountains, and found the international fair of relief efforts.
                    The Russians were there with one effort; the Cubans had sent an entire field
                    hospital and were busy infiltrating. A number of other countries. We had been
                    the first to send in help. We had a navy carrier in the vicinity. They sent
                    helicopters to get over the mountain ridges and into this valley. One of the
                    helicopters crashed just below the ridge line. I think it got caught in a
                    downdraft. I passed by the wreckage. And then the Soviets tried a long-range air
                    support operation and dropped an AM-24 into the North Atlantic. They stopped
                    their air bridge at that point. They had a small airport there with airplanes
                    from all over. I reported on that, the political aspects of emergency
                    assistance, competition.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that a big political section?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, I was the number two, and there was a junior officer and a labor
                    officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Toby was ambassador.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Toby was the ambassador, and Ed Clark was the DCM.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, I remember Ed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: He retired from there. He was another Princetonian. We had a happy
                    embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's good. But you were a bachelor when you
                        arrived.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No. As I was saying, my marriage broke up finally in February of '72.
                    My wife had gone off to visit her mother yet again, and I made the decision to
                    be cruel and decide finally that we had to seek a divorce. My two children had
                    been staying in Lima and were quite happy there. The older of the two decided to
                    stay in Lima with me and finish high school there. He was then in his senior
                    year about to graduate, and the younger of the two, a daughter, stayed with her
                    mother and had a very bad time, as it turned out. Divorce is, I guess, always
                    wrenching and traumatic for all concerned. It was just an unfortunate situation.
                    I had put it off for as long as I could. I wanted to let the children get as old
                    as possible so they could handle it better, but still, it was difficult. At any
                    rate, my son did finish at the Roosevelt High School, it was called, the
                    American Field Service school in Lima, in July of '72 and went on to Yale. One
                    of the happiest moments of my life was getting his acceptance letter from Yale
                    and getting him out of school to read it to him over the phone. After he left, I
                    was all on my own in Lima. I should say that my brother came down for a visit,
                    and he and my son and I went off to the jungle on an expedition, away. I happen
                    to like the jungle, and I traveled all over Peru. I took my son to see as much
                    of it as possible, and he loved doing it. And of course his Spanish became
                    excellent by studying with Peruvian friends, having all that exposure to life in
                    Peru. But October the 7th of '72 my present wife, whose full name is Maria
                    Rosario S�nchez Moreno, and now is de McFarland, but everyone calls her Rosario.
                    She's 15 years younger than I. At that time she was 27 and I was 42. I met her
                    at the birthday party of a Peruvian friend. It was her birthday also, and she
                    dropped by with some girlfriends, and we met. And my life has been constantly
                    happier since then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good for you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I had great resistance to marrying again. I wanted to make sure that
                    this time I had an adequate person, particularly a strong person. She, I finally
                    realized after a few months of going out with her, was exactly the person that I
                    had in mind. I was crazily lucky to find her. She's the daughter of a good
                    family there. Her father was a doctor for the Ministry of Public Health, had his
                    own clinic. Her older brother was a doctor also. She had studied in a school run
                    by American nuns. She spoke English and was a leader among people, a great gift
                    for getting along with people, charming them and at the same time very down to
                    earth, unassuming, great personal dignity and strength and courage, and just
                    made a simply terrific wife and mother, a terrific diplomatic wife as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I could see that, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Accustomed to entertaining and accustomed to dealing with people from
                    other cultures. She had none of the class attitude that characterized Peru, the
                    curse of Lima, in fact, an inheritance from its days of being a viceroyalty with
                    an extreme classism, which looks like racism but is in fact classism-racism,
                    because the lower classes usually are darker, they just automatically confer
                    higher class to a person who's lighter skinned. We were married after I was
                    transferred to Turkey after my divorce came through. At any rate, nothing much
                    happened in Peru in the time I was there except that I had to learn how to deal
                    with a really closed political society and a semi-hostile government.</p>
                <p>Q: It was a junta.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, a military government which was at the same time a socialist
                    government. They were appropriating socialist ideas apparently with the idea of
                    uniting the populace behind them. This was a very big theme, the unity between
                    the people and the armed forces.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were trying to look like populists, were they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, they were populists.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were populists.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Military populists, if you will, and they held rallies in which they
                    transported people in from the shanty towns on the edge of town, and they
                    demonstrated. But they became the first Latin American government to become
                    recipients of Soviet heavy military equipment, including tanks and artillery and
                    aircraft. And they established relations with Cuba, one of the few Latin
                    American countries to do so, and they had in short order a Soviet embassy, a
                    Cuban embassy, I believe a Chinese embassy, and a North Vietnamese. And money,
                    of course, was flowing from their intelligence services, into various groups
                    around the country, but under the close eye of the Peruvian armed forces. At the
                    time, I was astonished that there was no resistance to the rule of the armed
                    forces. They carried out one nationalization after another. The nationalization
                    of the petroleum company was followed by the expropriation of farms and ranches
                    above 150 hectares, and sometimes those even smaller. This was agrarian reform.
                    It was badly handled. It was at the time a focus of a great deal of admiration
                    on the part of the American academic community. And the military learned to use
                    terms that were in vogue among American academics, such as social mobilization.
                    They even had an agency, which was social mobilization, and there were great
                    hopes for the agrarian reform. It turned out a disaster. Probably, though, if
                    they had contented themselves with the agrarian reform and had concentrated on
                    that and making it work and making it just, on ending the corruption that was
                    involved - because generals were arranging deals by which they would benefit in
                    return for not taking quite so much of a person's holdings - if they had
                    concentrated on that, they might have gone down in history as a government that
                    did something to advance Peru. As it was, they were responsible for the “lost
                    decade,” in which Peruvian income dropped, Peru turned from an agriculturally
                    exporting country to an importing country - in sugar. Grace had invested heavily
                    in developing sugar production for a new industry. It never existed before Grace
                    came in there on a large scale. They confiscated Grace's holdings. In return,
                    Grace decided to end all its investments in Latin America, where it had been a
                    pioneer, you know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And henceforth we're going to invest in Europe. We know it's stable.
                    By the time I left, the talks were well advanced to the impasse over our
                    compensation for IPC, and that issue was settled shortly after I left. There
                    were other issues: the 200-mile territorial sea limit. Peru was a leader in that
                    movement, and saw an international settlement that negated their position. They
                    had been seizing our fishing boats. We had a continual source of friction
                    between us also. But it was only when I returned in the '80's that I found
                    Peruvians were not passive after all. They can be violent, but at that time no
                    one wanted to take on the military government. There was no sense of shared
                    interest among the conservatives, among the landholders, among anyone else that
                    was affected. The military government practically ran its course. Velasco had a
                    serious illness, was weakened, and was finally ousted in '75 by other generals.
                    It seemed that his whole purpose in mounting this series of reforms and trying
                    to bring the populace behind him was to have support for a new war with Chile.
                    Chile in the War of the Pacific in 1879 had taken away a large part of southern
                    Peru, and he wanted to be ready to mount a new war in 1979 to redeem the lost
                    Peru and with full popular support. The other generals weren't having any, and I
                    got fragmentary reports from people who were around that tend to confirm that
                    objective of his. Anyhow, he was dumped, and another general, Morales Berm�dez,
                    who had been his finance minister and saved him from a number of bad mistakes,
                    took over as president and led the country through a very bad time and finally
                    turned over power to an elected president in 1980.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Soviet military, was it substantial?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: The Soviet military?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Soviet military aid?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It was substantial. It was a substantial price tag.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What they paid for it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It was aid only in the sense that it was on somewhat concessionary
                    terms, but the Peruvians ran up a bill - I've forgotten whether it was two
                    billion or three billion. It doesn't make much difference which because given
                    their economy it was irrelevant. It was simply not an expense that Peru needed
                    to burden itself with at the same time that they were sabotaging their own
                    economy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We cut off military aid to them, I guess, at one stage -
                        for good reason.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, the one problem was that before I got there we had decreed that
                    we would not sell any more sophisticated aircraft to South American countries if
                    they did not did not need it. Peru took a violent reaction to this. This was, I
                    think, one of the grievances that the Peruvian military had. They got their
                    high-powered military equipment -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they paid for it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND:- and it was absolutely useless.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, they never used it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Some of it later was used against Ecuador, but that, again, was
                    useless.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: One result of the Peruvian military's adventure in government, was
                    that the military was absolutely corrupted and was almost ruined as a military
                    institution.</p>
                <p>Well, I was invited to go back to Turkey in '73, to the Political Section. I of
                    course had not been promoted. I had to go out as number two in the political
                    section. I'd been number two in Lima, not advancing. By that time I should have
                    been political counselor. And there I was. I accepted and went back, arrived
                    there in 1973, and I was married the following June. Rosario came over with her
                    sister and stayed there a few months working as secretaries in Latin American
                    embassies and when the divorce came through we got married. I had to take over
                    as acting political counselor in April, just after my divorce. My predecessor
                    left me with zero political contacts. He had only a few of his own, and he
                    didn't turn them over to me. He was not a Turkish speaker, number one. I had to
                    set about rebuilding political contacts, and in fact, I was approached to report
                    him. The ship was dead in the water. Furthermore, I had a useless officer,
                    graduated from Harvard - I don't know how - but he was absolutely useless.</p>
                <p>Q: You were on your own, really.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, and I was bearing down -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: The ambassador was Bill Macomber, William B. Macomber -</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I remember him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND:- who had been deputy assistant secretary for management, and he
                    started us on the Cyprus force over on the side of management and
                    administration. At the time he came out with this I had written memos to him
                    taking issue with the view that managers and administrators are a dime a dozen
                    in the United States, and people who can interpret overseas political events are
                    in extremely short supply, and our essential role is interpreting what's
                    happening overseas, not in administering. But he had his marching orders from
                    Lyndon Johnson, as he told me later, which was for a State Department that could
                    manage in doing a good job over there in Vietnam. We were never, ever
                    predictably going to have another Vietnam situation with all those people. And
                    the need for greater ability to manage, which is altogether under-emphasized in
                    the Foreign Service compared to the military, but still, we didn't need to go
                    overboard, as we did, which added to the length of my time in grade, because
                    they started promoting administrative officers and consular officers and making
                    up their quotas. But I got along well with Macomber after the first year or so.
                    I was acting political counselor for several small crises - an Aegean crisis
                    between Greece and Turkey, then a crisis over Turkey's opium production. This
                    was in late June of '73. Macomber was pulled back to Washington in protest of
                    the Turkish Government's attitude. And then for the Turkish invasion of Cyprus,
                    for which Macomber was returned very quickly. He was very under-confident of his
                    ability to handle political issues, and overcompensated by browbeating, by
                    keeping us all awake. At the start of any mini-crisis he would call everybody
                    together at the residence, but nevertheless, he and I became friends when he
                    began to see that I had ability that he could count on and ability that perhaps
                    he didn't have. But we went through a rough time. He initially began addressing
                    me simply as “Goddammit,” and it got around the embassy that this was my other
                    name, Goddammit. And then as his exasperation rose in step with the increasing
                    tensions over Cyprus and the invasion and so on, I reached my highest point. I
                    became “Jesus George,” as in “Jee - zus, George, do I have to do all the
                    thinking around here?” After that he decided I passed the test, and we were
                    friends, and we still are friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they bring in another political counselor over
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, yes. I was acting until about August, when they brought in
                    another one. Nobody wanted to work for Macomber; he had such a bad reputation.
                    And the job, after all, was and FSO-1 job, not an FSO-4, and now the minister
                    counselor. And they found an FSO-3 who had some connection with Turkey and was
                    willing to try it, and he lasted I think just under three months, and the
                    alcoholism that he had under control before took hold again, my second time to
                    be involved with an alcoholic. He fooled me. Other people knew. The secretary
                    knew and so on. I didn't until one day he arrived late, and the Marine guard
                    found him holding onto the rail of the stairway unable to climb, and he was
                    evacuated. And I was again acting political counselor. And then Macomber decided
                    to think big. “That's where you should be anyhow. You're the political
                    counselor, and you're entitled to the political counselor's quarters, a
                    beautiful place, the top apartment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you got the job.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I got the job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's something.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: A three-grade stretch.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that promoted you then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, no, no, no.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't understand.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: But that summer while I was still acting, I had gone through all these
                    crises, but that year they were promoting on the basis of cones. There were only
                    about, I think, five political officers promoted, of whom three were from
                    Kissinger's own staff, who he saw to it. So the other two. . . . I missed. There
                    was an economic officer in Istanbul who had done nothing. He got promoted, and I
                    didn't. An inspector came through after I was political counselor and
                    recommended me for a double promotion. Well, they didn't do it. But at least I
                    finally did get promoted after demonstrating over and over again that I could do
                    the job three grades higher and under pressure and conflict and a big embassy.
                    We had people there from just about every agency, and they liked me. I enjoyed
                    it, good time there. And the other embassies had good people there too.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>I knew a couple of people in the Russian embassy, not that I was on good terms
                    with them. I set up a carefully planned reporting program, and by the time I
                    left, visitors told me that we had become one of the outstanding reporting posts
                    in Europe. Of course, by that time Turkey had been transferred over to the EUR,
                    Turkey, Greece, and Cyprus. And as the EUR hands complained, we brought them
                    their first war in 30 years - not counting the Greek Civil War, I guess. At any
                    rate, we had a good time there, traveled a lot on weekends and so on, whenever
                    we could. I had to work long, long hours.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was your honeymoon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I got three days, and Kissinger got five. But from there, of
                    course, I was overdue for a Washington assignment or for a DCM-ship. What I
                    really wanted was a DCM-ship. I wanted to catch up, make up for lost time, and
                    as an O-3 I was eligible. But I was offered DCM-ship in Cyprus. Think again.
                    There's a Greek lobby in your town, isn't there? And do you imagine what they
                    would say, and can you imagine what the Greek Cypriot Government would say to
                    having a Turk - in their eyes - as a number two in the American embassy? And
                    they called me back the next day and said, “You're right.” They also offered me
                    deputy office director for Turkey, Greece, Cyprus. I mean, they had reinstated
                    by this time the offices, and I made the same point. With the Greek lobby it
                    would never wash, and it didn't. And eventually all they could offer me was
                    Turkish Desk officer - well, good Lord! I was going down from two stars to O-3?
                    I couldn't take it. What was the stretch all about? So I instead opted for
                    senior training, and I was offered a year at Princeton, at that wonderful
                    Woodrow Wilson School. It was a great year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's great.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And we got into New York frequently, and I renewed my acquaintances
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What, did you write a paper?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, I went to seminars. I wanted to get out of Turkish things and into
                    a more general preparation. I wrote some little papers, but nothing big. And I'm
                    rather sorry now that I didn't specialize more on Turkish matters, but I was up
                    to my ears at this point in being with the Turks. I could have taught a course,
                    I guess.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, but Princeton was pleasant. It's a nice -</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were no midnight cables no Niact's. You know what I
                        mean.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: They let us live in junior faculty housing. By this time we had a
                    daughter, the first of the second generation. She was born in Turkey. What a
                    great gift. And the first flowers that arrived in the room were from Bulent
                    Ecevit, who is now the prime minister, who was then the recently ousted prime
                    minister, a great political figure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's great.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Maybe now's the time to bring it in. I should have gone back to
                    Turkey.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right, go ahead</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND:As DCM, seven years later. I was EUR's candidate. I was the person
                    indicated. I had far more qualifications than anybody else. By this time I had
                    become a senior officer, FE/OC in current terms, and the then ambassador was a
                    political appointee, Strausz-Hup�. He was an Austrian financier who had
                    emigrated to the States just before World War II and had gone into academia and
                    become one of the founders of the Institute for International Relations. And
                    during the Nixon Administration, he had been appointed ambassador to several
                    places - Sri Lanka, or Ceylon, as it was then, and married a Sri Lankan, and
                    Sweden, I think, and then USNATO. Anyway, when the DCM he inherited had to
                    leave, whom I knew, he had the problem of replacing him. I was number one on the
                    list, and he preferred somebody he had known in USNATO who had no Turkish, no
                    Turkish experience. He knew that he wasn't a threat. And somebody who counseled
                    him or had the basis for sending him up said, “There is no way that he would
                    have brought in a Turkish language officer as his number two.” He was afraid I
                    would show him up. Of course, I wouldn't have.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, of course not.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I know what it is to be loyal to your chief. I would have helped him.
                    I had great respect for him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But he didn't know you. He knew the other guy, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: He knew the other guy, and this was the reason for my retirement - I'm
                    advancing considerably in my story. This was probably the principal reason for
                    my disillusionment.</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Or at least consul general in Istanbul or Ismir - would
                        that have been satisfactory?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, I wanted a DCM-ship. I wanted real policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And I just lived there with the idea to bring my knowledge of Turkey
                    and Cyprus to bear on US relations, and I think I could have made a
                    contribution, and it was never made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: They did fill it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Beg pardon.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, I stayed in Ankara a total of five years, summing up, a total of
                    seven years in Turkey plus two years in Cyprus plus two years on the Cyprus Desk
                    plus a year studying Turkish. It was a considerable investment. That was my real
                    specialty. And that was the reason why, I think, EUR and the State Department
                    plumped for me as the DCM. Ron Spiers, who succeeded Macomber as ambassador and
                    made me - I thought he made me - a prot�g� at least, told me after I had
                    retired, when he was undersecretary for management, that my case had been among
                    several that motivated a change in the DCM-ship selection procedures, where
                    ambassadors were no longer allowed a completely free hand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But in the meantime.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It's a hard issue to settle, but I was deeply disappointed. Okay, well
                    after I went on from Turkey to Princeton and then started looking for an onward
                    assignment, I didn't want to go back to Washington because the jobs there just
                    weren't adequate. There was nothing good at all, so I started looking around
                    overseas, and there was an opening as political counselor in Brasilia, which was
                    at least equivalent to what I had had before and was still a stretch assignment.
                    The only problem was that I had never been in Brazil, and I had no Portuguese,
                    but I had had previous South American experience, and I had been political
                    counselor in a Class I post, a far more challenging post than Brasilia, for that
                    matter, and I had gotten an A in the course. But Robert Sayre was the ambassador
                    there, and for some reason, over the overwhelming contrary advice of everyone in
                    the Brazil Office, he asked for me as his political counselor. And then when I
                    began challenging him on various thing he may have regretted it, but anyway, we
                    moved to Brasilia and it was another quiet time in another military
                    dictatorship, but this time I had what turned into an excellent political
                    section. It wasn't so great at first. I had inherited this same zero quantity
                    from Harvard that I had been taxed with when I started in Ankara, but I
                    persuaded him to move on, and people came in of top quality. I had three Ph.D.'s
                    working for me at one point, having one who moved down from INR. My number two
                    after a year or so is now an ambassador in Africa. I helped both of them. I gave
                    both of them great reviews.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about your Portuguese? Did you have time to
                        study?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I was given five weeks to adapt my Spanish to Portuguese.
                    Unfortunately, FSI was not well prepared to do this, and -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's not much time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It's not, no, and I came out of it with a basic knowledge of
                    Portuguese, but without fluency. I was slow in speaking, and once I got to
                    Brasilia, there were other things to do besides participate in Portuguese.
                    Anyway, in a year or so, I had enough to function in the embassy. And Portuguese
                    and Spanish, you know, don't coexist very well in a person's mind unless he uses
                    them constantly, and even then. I spoke Spanish at home with my wife and
                    Portuguese with the Brazilians, but the two would cross over into one another.
                    Even the native Spanish-speakers had that problem.</p>
                <p>Q: Buy you and Sayre got along eventually.</p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, not really. Sayre was a very cold fish. He didn't go out and mix
                    with the Brazilians. I picked up an excellent contact high up in the Foreign
                    Ministry, and he decided he liked that, and that was his contact in the Foreign
                    Ministry from then on. And he had certain ideas that were his and were fixed and
                    he was not going to be talked out of them, and I had the temerity to tell him
                    so. For one thing, he insisted that the military government was really a nest of
                    democrats, in effect, and while he was off on home leave, I wrote a report on
                    the corruption in the military, and when he came back he was just about ready to
                    sack me. He demanded an immediate explanation. I had undercut all of his work
                    for the two previous years convincing people in Washington that the military
                    were outstanding people, and, well, they were moving towards an “opening,” as
                    they call it, toward democracy, but it was still a directive government,
                    authoritarian with just the dressings of a military controlled parliament, but a
                    military president and so on. And I fortunately was able to go back and give him
                    a memo citing exactly the inverse, picking up all of this, that, and the other.
                    And I didn't hear any more about it, and I wasn't sacked, but he was president
                    of the Promotion Board. And it was only after Tony Motley arrived, a political
                    appointee, that was far, far superior to Sayre, better than an FSO ambassador,
                    and I finally got promoted in the senior service. By that time I was into my
                    early 50's. I think I was 51 or 52. It was a little late. I should have had that
                    promotion ten years earlier if I was going to do anything with it. And I suppose
                    before I left Brasilia I was already seriously thinking about retiring. I asked
                    for Ankara, which I thought I'd be a shoo-in, but just in case I asked also a
                    DCM-ship in Lisbon. I had Portuguese by that time, fluent at it. And Lima, where
                    I managed on a previous tour and then my wife's connection. And in each case it
                    went to a favorite. And I was thoroughly disillusioned. And all the other jobs -
                    a political-military advisor - I didn't care all that much about them, but they
                    didn't happen anyhow. So I was thinking about having to go to Washington and
                    writing another paper for a year waiting for an onward assignment and worrying
                    about what this would do to my children, to be jerked around from post to post.
                    And a job opened up, well below my grade, as DCM, but actually charg�
                    d'affaires, in Antigua, in the Caribbean, with responsibility for Antigua, and
                    St. Kitt's and Nevis, which became a republic two months after I arrived, and
                    the three British Crown Colonies, Montserrat, and the British Virgin Islands. I
                    thought it would be wonderful. And it sounded like the chance to be in charge of
                    a post. And it was better than going to Washington, I thought, better than
                    writing a paper and just killing time waiting for something. It turned out, by
                    the way, that if I had gone to Washington, I would have been in Ankara a year
                    later, because the DCM went out on time in grade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But did you get to Antigua?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I did go to Antigua in 1983, after my four years in Brasilia. I had,
                    by the way, a total of eight years as political counselor in two Class I posts
                    from two different areas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now who was your ambassador. Did you report to an
                        ambassador in the Caribbean?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, Antigua was under the ambassador in the Bahamas, and I can't
                    remember the name.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's to hell and gone, not even close.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, it's a long way away, 800 miles or so. I'm sorry, not the Bahamas.
                    Barbados.</p>
                <p>Q: Oh, Barbados. Okay.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: But it's still -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But did he, in effect, supervise you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: He wanted to, and he was very sensitive to competition and rivalry
                    between the two posts, which actually began with his own embassy down there in
                    Barbados. He had the idea they were a big embassy, and yet they were very small,
                    but they had strange ideas and very, very competitive. Anyway, he was a
                    political appointee from Nebraska, and he visited Antigua just once or twice, I
                    think - not a bad guy. Actually, I was in charge. His visits were only to show
                    his face. The -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you charg� d'affaires then? On the diplomatic
                        list?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, there was not a dip list in Antigua, it's only 2,000 people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:I know, it's only a little spot in the Caribbean. But you
                        had a title of some kind.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I was charg� d'affaires. I was always introduced as the American
                    charg� d'affaires or American charg�. I appeared on televisions all the time. I
                    was Mr. United States down there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the ambassador came to town, and then I guess you
                        weren't called charg�.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: That's right. I was temporarily his DCM.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you appeared on the, I guess, the diplomatic list in
                        Barbados, or did you? No?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I don't know. I never saw it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I never heard of such an arrangement, but anyway it
                        worked, as far as you were concerned.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It didn't work. It was a problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The embassy was crowding you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, they were needlessly competitive, got us out on things. I would
                    find an AID officer puttering around town without notifying us. The USIS also,
                    when I asked for things, they wouldn't necessarily supply them. I did have. . .
                    . Well, we had the Grenada operation while I was there. We lined up support from
                    the governments in Antigua and Montserrat, that were in my district, and
                    notified the State Department, and this was a beautiful case of intervention in
                    terms of diplomatic support. We had a request for intervention from all the area
                    governments, unanimously. And my father died just about this time, and I had to
                    leave and go home, and returned after the intervention was well underway, and
                    the embassy in Barbados had charge of that.</p>
                <p>We had a lot of administrative problems. I had written the ambassador there about
                    them. I sent him a message to send on to Washington. Well, he didn't send it on.
                    The inspector who came through later said I should have sent it directly to
                    Washington, and therefore it was my fault.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it didn't work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It didn't work. And I spent a lot of my time straightening out
                    administration.</p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>I think the most rewarding thing I had to do there was handling a drought on the
                    island of Antigua. The prime minister waited until the island's reservoir had
                    gone completely dry during the long drought, summoned me to a meeting of his
                    cabinet and said, in a deep voice, “I want the United States Government to give
                    us $1 million for drought relief.” I fortunately happened to have a visiting AID
                    representative, who reminded me that I had authority to pledge $25,000 on my
                    own. There was a certain shortfall. I did organize the island's response. I got
                    one of the prime minister's sons, who was a minister, to handle the Antiguan
                    side of things. AID sent in a water engineer, from whom I learned a great deal
                    about hydraulics, such as the meaning of the term “total dynamic head” and the
                    interesting bit that most old water systems leak up to 60 per cent of the water
                    that's put into them. We were able to help Antigua in buying water from other
                    countries, but they had to pay for barging it in. The Seabees, very helpfully,
                    sent in a detachment which worked on repairing water mains and rebuilding water
                    storage tanks, which would receive the water from the barges, and in fact
                    installed a floating water line to connect from the barges in the harbor, such
                    as it was, to the storage tanks. These were very impressive people, just
                    couldn't get enough work to satisfy them. And we got through the water
                    crisis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have the impression that it's a very corrupt government,
                        a family.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, well, all the Caribbean governments tend to be more or less
                    authoritarian one-man r�gimes, and this in particular. But the prime minister
                    was a venerable figure, but anyone opposed to him had already long since left
                    the island. There was a token opposition, but out of 72,000 people, you couldn't
                    have too much discontent. The island later became a haven for gun-running and
                    drug smuggling, but not during my time. We had a navy station and an Air Force
                    downrange rocket observing station and, in addition, an AID representative and a
                    Coast Guard representative. So I had a decent-size country team, despite the
                    small size of the embassy. I had a serious problem with the administrative
                    officer that was sent, an African American who had made a career out of suing
                    the United States Government for discrimination and had invested his winnings in
                    his own defense fund. The inspectors cited him for a serious administrative
                    misstep, and on that basis, I asked the Department to reassign him. He instantly
                    applied to the Equal Employment Opportunity Office, was granted unlimited time
                    to prepare his own case. He disappeared for approximately two and a half months
                    and returned in an extremely combative mood. After I had retired, still I had to
                    answer questions and make depositions about his conduct there. I understand that
                    he was eventually removed from the Service, but it was a sour note for ending
                    the Service.</p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>I took retirement very early, the 2nd of January of 1985 and moved directly to
                    Lima, Peru, with my wife and two small children. I should have mentioned that my
                    second child of the second generation, a boy, was born at Princeton just before
                    I left there. I moved to Lima largely for family reasons, not because I had any
                    employment lined up there. In fact, there was none to be found at a decent wage.
                    Peru was in the depths of a very long recession with no end in sight. I was not
                    interested in trying to go into business for myself, not having had business
                    experience and after considering the general reputation of Peruvian business
                    practices, which are not terribly open and legal. And I settled down to write
                    novels. I dedicated several years to writing novels and finished two, and
                    finished them, in fact, several times after rewriting, but was unable to get any
                    published. It's possible that I was too far away from the United States to be in
                    touch with publishing trends or I didn't have the right connections. It's also
                    possible that the manuscripts just weren't good enough. But it was a very
                    disillusioning experience, because I had thought that my only real gift was in
                    writing. It turns out that novel writing amounts to more than writing, though.
                    The two children adapted well to Peruvian life, growing up surrounded by a large
                    and very caring, close Peruvian family. I benefited from that, too. This family,
                    like most Peruvian families, has a sense of “family-ness” that goes well beyond
                    anything practiced for the most part in the United States. For example, to this
                    day, I get birthday greetings from nieces and nephews in Peru and not one from
                    my nieces here in the States. I traveled around taking the children to see most
                    of Peru with my four-wheel-drive pickup, and we did a great deal of camping up
                    in the mountains, in a largely unvisited area, probably Valley of the Volcanoes.
                    From north to south, wherever we could go that was safe, we went. We wound up
                    camping a great deal on the beach because in the mountains travel became very
                    risky because of the terrorist threat, Sendero Luminoso, Shining Path,
                    Hispanicist operations. It was a, quote, Maoist organization, a phenomenon in
                    South America because it was without dependence on outside support. They
                    charged, in effect, taxes to people whom they could threaten, who were within
                    their reach, and they ruled by fear.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How Communist are they, or were they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Totally. They were Pol Pot types.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In other words, they went by the book?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: By the book. By the Maoist book.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They weren't just... Well, that's a long time ago. Even
                        China has evolved.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Until 1992, roughly, and there are some of them operating. In 1992,
                    after they had started trying to move into Lima, and had set off a car bomb that
                    devastated a whole block of downtown Lima, the police got very serious about
                    catching their leader, which was the objective that President Fujimori had set,
                    and they caught him - and within a mile of our house, a middle-class area where
                    you would never have expected him to be hiding, was his house.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fujimori did it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Fujimori gave the right strategic directions - go for the head of the
                    organization.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you care to talk about Fujimori?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Certainly. He's a remarkable figure. He has already overstayed his
                    fame, his moment, in Peru. He took office in 1990, after two decades, 22 years,
                    really, of decline, when Peru reached a point well below what it was in '68 when
                    Velasco had taken over. Fujimori succeeded APRA president, American Popular
                    Revolutionary Alliance, named Alan Garcia, who had been a very credible, very
                    promising young politician when he ran for office in '85, and was elected
                    overwhelmingly, and promptly betrayed all hopes by becoming one of the most
                    corrupt presidents on record, not only he but all the people with him, only a
                    few of whom have actually been charged but were generally on the take. He has
                    been living in exile ever since 1990 in one luxurious setting after another,
                    which you can't do simply on the retirement pay of a former president. He
                    obviously has millions. He's living in Paris right now in a luxury apartment
                    with his own security force, and previously spent a long time in Bogot�. If
                    there was anything Peru did not need at that point it was betrayal, and he
                    betrayed it. The reaction against him resulted in Fujimori's election.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Pardon the interruption - is Fujimori anti-corruption, or
                        is he also a taker?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, he's got his own thing, now, apparently. But he was anti APRA
                    corruption because politically -</p>
                <p>Q: But he's vulnerable to the same Peruvian disease.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: He is now, but it's not known. I mean, it's only surmised.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, all right. I just thought I'd ask.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: But in the case of Juan Garcia it was quite obvious, and in fact was
                    attested to by one of the Italian executives of a company who worked on building
                    an electric railway through Lima. It never got beyond the point of building a
                    series of gigantic concrete pillars in one street, several miles worth of
                    pillars - no train. He apparently made quite a lot of money off that, and off a
                    deal that Peru had ordered I think it was a little over 18 Mirage fighters. Now
                    they didn't really need them. Of course they didn't. And these were greatly in
                    demand at the time, and Alan worked out a deal by which another country would
                    buy them at a much higher price. Peru would recover whatever it paid for them,
                    and he would take the rest. As I say, he lives well in Paris.</p>
                <p>And of course, this gets into the question that was posed by a Brazilian at the
                    time. It's not just him, it's all of us. They people who pay bribes are no less
                    guilty than those who accept them. But in this case, it wasn't Peruvians who
                    were paying bribes. It was a sharp operator who was making money off his
                    country. But there is a very, very strong tendency among Peruvians. Do we sell
                    out whatever crook we're working for?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now, you as a retired government employee living in
                        that environment on a limited pension, how did you faire in that
                        environment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: The first year I saved more money than I had been able to save on
                    active duty, but after that the cost of living began to rise and rise and rise.
                    It's not quite clear why. After Fujimori came in, he began privatizing the
                    state-owned enterprises.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that a good thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes. And bringing in investment in a variety of things. The money came
                    in. There was also a great flood of unacknowledged narco-dollars from drug
                    smuggling. Peru is a tremendous source of cocaine. It's the largest coca-growing
                    country in the world. It's not clear just what proportion of Peru's total dollar
                    supply comes from that. I suspect that a much larger proportion comes than what
                    they acknowledge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have drug lords there as you do in Columbia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are they known</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, they stay more out of sight, and they're not so well known.
                    There's great suspicion, though, that a great many of the top people in the army
                    are compromised. The problem, of course, comes back to our requirement. I had
                    never professed to have a solution to the drug problem. I can see in both ways.
                    I'm horrified by drugs. I am equally horrified by the cost of the drug war. And
                    one of the costs has been that by making drugs illegal, we have raised the
                    profits of the drug lords, for all the smugglers, and because they are making so
                    much, it's nothing to them to pay off police, army generals, judges, governors,
                    whoever. In all the producing countries, this is having a terrible effect on the
                    fabric of society, on the civil authority, on people's confidence in government
                    - not that they had much confidence previously. That's been their historical
                    experience. Their governments were not to be trusted much. That is one reason
                    for the election of this son of Japanese immigrants, Fujimori, to be president,
                    because the little people have had it with the traditional ruling group. They
                    have been one failure after another, even though the army was not really part of
                    the traditional ruling group, they tried that experiment. The Peruvians actually
                    had tried all the varieties of political organizations just about, except
                    out-and-out Communism, but they picked this Japanese as someone who was wily and
                    smart and yet not a European type. And his first term was a great success. He
                    brought security to his country after this long reign of terror, and he
                    acknowledged involvement and investment, even though very little of it trickled
                    down. But the poor people seem to have infinite patience. They felt that after a
                    while they'd begin to get theirs. The trouble is, now, being seated on a second
                    term, he closed down congress at one point and fired the supreme court justices,
                    made way for himself for a second term, and now in his second term people are
                    thoroughly fed up him. The economic policies have not resulted in greater wealth
                    farther down. Even the people at the top are beginning to have problems. And
                    something like 30 or 40 per cent of Peruvians live in extreme poverty, by which
                    I mean not having enough to eat and not having adequate clothing or adequate
                    housing. People in the United States don't understand, on the basis of US
                    experience, what it is to be poor, as you know very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: They know what it is in Peru, and one of my brothers-in-law remarked
                    to me years ago, “We live in a poor country,” and I caught his whole meaning:
                    that its poverty had an impact everywhere you looked, people's attitudes, and
                    the way people lived, from the top to the bottom. And everything is relative. By
                    standards of Bill Gates and, indeed, by the standards of a good many
                    millionaires around Austin, I'm poor. By the standards of poor people in Lima,
                    I'm terribly rich.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, there are a few rich ones at the top, a few families
                        that are rich, is that it? Is there a middle class of some dimension and
                        then a heavy lower class? Is that still the pattern?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, for many years, there was this land-based aristocracy, the
                    hacendanos. Hacienda? - that was the owners, the families, the owners of
                    hacendados. And they pretty well ran things, especially outside Lima, in their
                    own districts. They were like squires or barons or whatever. And if there were
                    votes, their people voted the way they wanted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they had serfs on their land.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, not really, but something -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you call them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: What, the peones?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Peones? Were they sharecroppers, or did they pay?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: More or less, they were sharecroppers. That's right. Or they were paid
                    minimal wages. It depended on the landowner. Some were quite enlightened and
                    treated their people well, and then others were brutal. But that was the old
                    system, and that was broken up by the agrarian reform of the military
                    government. That's what I was saying - if they had stuck with that, they might
                    have had a place in history that was more favorable to them; but they broke it
                    up, but they didn't really introduce anything good enough to be viable in its
                    place. They were all wary, I think, of carrying out agrarian reform. Japan did
                    it. Israel did it. But in Peru they didn't catch on. And it had difficulty
                    feeding itself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Relations with Washington are better with Fujimori?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, they were for a time, but we became critical of his human rights
                    practices.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Prisoners, and political prisoners.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, yes, and. . . . It's not quite fair. There's something on both
                    sides. It's a question of due process. During the worst of the terrorism, as
                    they called it - it's fair to call it an insurgency - the police were on the
                    point of being undermined and corrupted by the influence of the Sendero
                    Luminoso. The police, after all, live in these same slums where a lot of the
                    revolutionaries live. Their families were hostage when they were off, and they'd
                    restore them at night and on weekends. Their loyalty was not entirely
                    unquestioned. The army also, drawn mostly from up in the mountains, by forced
                    levies - there was enough of a draft of them, mainly enforced just against the
                    poor and powerless, because the sons of the wealthy could always buy their way
                    out. If you really wanted somebody you had to go to the villages and pick them
                    off the streets without even letting them notify their families. So they weren't
                    sure of the army either. That's why there was an elite force that went in and
                    got this leader of the Sendero, an elite force from the police, not from the
                    military. The military never won its war. But I've lost my thread.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm sorry I interjected. You were living in Lima now, and
                        you lived there for, you say, 13 years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: 12 years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then you moved to Austin.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes.</p>
                <p>Q: For good reason. To be close to family.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, by the time I left, the insurrection was, for all practical
                    purposes over. That was just before we left. Another small guerrilla group,
                    MRTA, Movimiento Revolucionario Tupac Amaru, stormed the Japanese embassy during
                    a diplomatic reception.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I remember that. That's a very dramatic incident.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: That was just before Christmas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes. Early December, I guess, and took all these hostages. We were
                    still there, but we were not close to it. We'd had dinner near it a night or so
                    before. But we were by this time moved out of our house and were in a furnished
                    apartment we'd rented to stay there during Christmas, and then after Christmas
                    we'd planned to move on. At any rate, that was the only security problem, apart
                    from just plain crime. Peru suffers from the problem of respect of government.
                    We have never really suffered from it, but we are starting a trend toward lack
                    of respect toward government and lack of respect of laws, for authorities,
                    generally. It started during Vietnam, I think. It's at a far more extreme state
                    of development in Peru, and I hope it doesn't get that far here. But in Peru
                    there's practically no respect for authority. The police are corrupt and forfeit
                    all respect. You get pulled out of the car for going through a green light, and
                    the policeman claims it was red and wants to be paid off.</p>
                <p>Q: Does this compare with Mexico? Do you know enough about Mexico?</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Mexico is worse. The police there are actually carrying out a large
                    percentage of the crimes. In Peru they may be conniving with the criminals, but
                    they are not themselves the criminals, in most cases. In Mexico there was all
                    these.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you came to Austin for other reasons, returned to
                        Austin.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, I was fed up with Peru for a good many reasons. One person asked
                    me what I most missed about the United States, and I said, “I miss the
                    bureaucracy and the police.” And that's absolutely true. People complain about
                    the bureaucracy and the police here, and they don't know how good they are.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because here they are service organizations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Here they provide services.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To the taxpayer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And if you're not satisfied, you can complain.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, and you can throw the rascals out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: That's right, and there, to begin with, you can not pay a bill by
                    check through the mail, first, because it would be stolen by the post office
                    employees, and second, because even if remotely enough it did arrive they
                    wouldn't honor it, they wouldn't believe it. Nobody there writes real checks.
                    There's no point in trying to cash it because it would be returned without
                    funds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's very hard to live with a pocket full of - whatever
                        they are, dinars.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: So you go to the bank or to the government office involved or for some
                    things, like utility payments, you go to drugstores and make your payments
                    there. But everything has to be done in person, so there's an awful lot more
                    traffic on the streets and millions of man hours lost. And then the bureaucrats
                    themselves are extremely whimsical. I understand that France has the reputation
                    of the worst bureaucratic country in the world. Well, these people must have
                    taken lessons in France. They have the same whimsicality I've heard about, and
                    that's every bureaucrat making his own decision, variation on what the rules
                    are. Maybe you catch him in a good moment, and maybe not. I remember, the last
                    several years my wife had to do all of her dealings with the government offices
                    because I became enraged. Another thing is the traffic. I am a safe driver, a
                    careful driver, and I frankly regard it as a threat to my life when somebody
                    runs through a red light at me or fails to honor a stop sign when I'm crossing
                    the street and come close to hitting me. I grow irritated. And so my wife
                    started doing all the driving in the city. And it's not only Americans who get
                    road rage there. I had a Peruvian spit from his Volkswagen at my pickup as we
                    were both snarled in a traffic jam and shouting insults at me, which I couldn't
                    hear - just as well - and finally the little man got out of his Volkswagen
                    taxicab and drew this enormous screwdriver from behind the seat and was
                    apparently challenging me to a duel. What he didn't know was that I had a 380
                    automatic. I was returning from the beach, and I always went armed when I went
                    out of the city because of the danger of highway robbers. And of course I didn't
                    draw it; I didn't do anything. If he had had a pistol and had drawn it and fired
                    it at my family, I would have shot him as quickly as that. I'm a good shot. And
                    I was psyched up to fire if we were attacked, but only if we were attacked.</p>
                <p>Q: That's a difficult situation.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, it's hard to train, but I trained myself well. And you don't draw
                    unless you're attacked. You don't show your weapon. I had that bit of insurance
                    just in case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now you don't have that here. I mean, those are things you
                        left behind. Those things you described you left behind. You're here, and
                        you're content.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes. There is a sense of safety here. People complain about threats.
                    This is a far safer and more trusting society. In Peru you simply cannot leave
                    things outside, even a garden hose, much less a bicycle. People will run off
                    with it. They'll occasionally steal bicycles here, but not garden hoses, not
                    lawn furniture. Even plants. And perhaps that has something to do with the stage
                    of economic success that we have. It's just not worthwhile. But there it is
                    worthwhile.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are you glad you did 26 years in the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In retrospect, are you glad you made that decision?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It was the overwhelmingly good decision of my life, and the worst
                    decision was leaving it. I'm sorry I retired when I did, although I had only
                    about four or five more years to go before mandatory retirement, but I wish I
                    had stuck with it. Still, it would have been at high cost to my children, and I
                    balanced those things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also, if you'd taken jobs that weren't interesting, you
                        could have spent your five years in the Service, but you didn't want to take
                        uninteresting jobs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No, the -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And I didn't either. You know, I saw, after I was named
                        ambassador, then I got two other assignments which were worthy - they were
                        worthwhile - but I had the feeling that maybe they wanted me to move on,
                        make room for others, so I moved on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I had that feeling also.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, but I could have walked the corridors for another
                        five years, but I didn't want to. I wanted a second career, and you chose a
                        writing career. I chose an oil company. So you come. . . . I think we're
                        similar in that regard - 25 years in the service, and then another period of
                        productive work of one thing or the other. And so a second career, in our
                        society, is a normal thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, it is.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Two or three careers, as a matter of fact, nowadays. You
                        don't just stick with one till you die. And I didn't want to die, you know,
                        at my desk. I just wanted to die somewhere else. But anyway, I'm putting
                        words into your mouth - or not putting words into your mouth.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Those are good observations, though. I -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then you're in environment, as I am -</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I think that -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:- now, which I like. I like Austin, for a lot of reasons.
                        This is a good place for this phase of my life. I'm content, and you're
                        content, so that's why you live here.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Well, I'm very content to be here, and -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you have family considerations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And I'm glad that they had the experience in Lima that they did. That
                    was a great gift that I gave them. And I don't regret that. It's just that I
                    think I became over-dedicated or over-accustomed to that life, and there was
                    really nothing else that I wanted to do. I didn't have a second career lined up,
                    as I said. I should have done that. I should have planned my retirement more
                    carefully than I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You can't do it over again. But you've had happiness of a
                        different sort.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: That's right, mainly with -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:- family and friends.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you're alive.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: And I feel good about helping out with the children.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And there are plenty of volunteer jobs around, if you need
                        them. I'm involved too much in them, but not too much because I like them.
                        Well, do you have anything more you'd like to say?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I could backtrack perhaps.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, do you want to go back to Rodger Davies?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, I think so. I'd like to continue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why don't you do that, and we'll probably end this and the
                        secretary will await your instructions on that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Yes, well, we'll move back to the Ankara period and the consequences
                    for the United States of the Turkish invasion of Cyprus. The Greeks in Cyprus
                    and in Greece simply were infuriated that the United States had not saved them
                    from their own folly in provoking Turkey at that time to get rid of Makarios and
                    make Cyprus part of Greece. It had been quite clear that Turkey would not be
                    held back a third time, but the Greeks wouldn't see that. Well, anyway, a few
                    weeks after the invasion of Cyprus, there was a mass demonstration around the
                    American embassy in Nicosia, and two members of Greek Cypriot organizations,
                    carrying rifles, without any opposition from the Greek Cypriot police, entered a
                    building next door to the American embassy, went to a window that looked
                    directly into the windows of the ambassador's office from about 50 or 70 yards
                    distance, and opened fire with AK-47's. The staff of the ambassador was in the
                    DCM's office. They were covered down the hall in an area where there was a
                    change of level in the halls. The ambassador was the last to take refuge, and as
                    he arrived where they were, a bullet caught him right in the chest. He fell, and
                    a Foreign Service national, a Maronite Christian in Cyprus, a girl, reached out
                    to catch him and had the back of her head blown off by a second bullet. I had
                    known her while I was there, and I had worked with Rodger Davies for a time in
                    the State Department while he was deputy assistant secretary for Near East. Some
                    time later, in December of '75, I believe it was, I was on home leave in the US
                    when I got the news that my good friend Richard Welch, who had been station
                    chief in Athens and whom I had worked with in Cyprus and in Lima, had been
                    assassinated by three Greek nationalists in Athens, right in front of his
                    residence and with his wife watching. His wife still has not recovered. We
                    stayed in touch with her. This was a very high price to be exacted for
                    irrational expectations of US behavior.</p>
                <p>Q: Yes, it tempts you to generalize about the character of a people. I'm not
                    asking you to do that, but these were Greeks who were killing Americans for no
                    good reason. Are there many like that, or would you find Turks doing that?</p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I would hesitate to generalize on the mass of Greeks, but Greece does
                    include all too many psychopathic killers, psychopaths who kill Turkish Cypriot
                    noncombatants, shepherds out in the field minding their sheep. Greek Cypriots
                    stop in the road in their cars and pick them off. There was entirely too much of
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a Balkan disease.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It does seem to be so, doesn't it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, it's certainly not Pericles. Well, do you have any
                        further thoughts or footnotes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: Perhaps I will add them when I review.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you get the text, you can add and subtract.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: I had a great many. . . . Oh, yes. There's another story I should tell
                    about the Greek attitudes to Turkey. My wife and I in 1977 visited Athens with
                    our baby daughter and traveled - this was at Easter time, or just before Easter,
                    I'm sorry, just before the Greek Orthodox Easter, not the Western Easter - and
                    from there we traveled up to Thessaloniki. I have another story about that. I'll
                    have to backtrack yet again. Bob Fulsom, the one I worked for on the Cyprus
                    Desk, had been consul general in what was then called Salonika, and a friend of
                    mine who worked for him, went the story, came in one day and told Fulsome that
                    the Greeks called this Thessaloniki; they don't call it Salonika. I think we
                    should do the same. And Fulsom said, “You're absolutely right.” He sent off a
                    recommendation to Washington, which was adopted, and as a result, it is now
                    called Thessaloniki, and we had to spend, I think, about half a million dollars
                    in redoing navy charts and air force maps with the new name.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Folly, folly.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>MCFARLAND: That was Bob Fulsom's great gift to the world. But at any rate, we
                    visited Salonika-Thessaloniki and went on to cross the border with the intention
                    of being picked up on the Turkish side by a consul general car from Istanbul and
                    go on from there, see more of that part of Turkey. And we got to the Greek
                    border post at the river which is known in Greek as Maritsa and in Turkish as
                    Meric. The two border posts are separated by a bridge about a kilometer long,
                    and the Greek border post was decorated with posters that were strongly
                    anti-Turkish - Turkish atrocities and whatnot. I had heard that the entire
                    border was mined on both sides. They were nothing if not fearful, angry, of
                    course, and demonstrating, but fearful. And he stamped our passports, waved us
                    out the door. There was no taxi that could take us over to the Turkish side. We
                    had a kilometer to go with the baby in a backpack and about 70 pounds of
                    baggage. And I stood on the Greek side and looked across this bridge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No taxi.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: No taxi. And the Turkish driver could see us, but he couldn't come to
                    get us.</p>
                <p>Q: So the bridge really was no man's land.</p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: It was no man's land. We started across, I felt like refugees.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were heading in the right direction. You were heading
                        for Turkey. Funny last kilometer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MCFARLAND: A wonderful way to treat an American diplomat, right? And to
                    demonstrate their feelings. Their NATO ally was their most bitterly hated enemy.
                    I honestly think that if it hadn't been for their war against the Communists in
                    the late '40's, they might well have allied with the Russians. Maybe that's
                    another factor in our pro-Greek stance. But anyway, we struggled across the
                    bridge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, if you have any other thoughts, just give them to
                        the draft. It's been a pleasure. I've enjoyed this, and I appreciate your
                        giving us the time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
