<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001012">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Leonard J. Saccio </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR LEONARD J. SACCIO</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Melbourne Spector </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: September 30, 1990</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is an oral history interview with Ambassador Leonard
                        J. Saccio. It is a part of the oral history project on the Marshall Plan and
                        its immediate successor agencies, and it is also a part of the regular
                        program of the Association for Diplomatic Studies; that is, the Foreign
                        Affairs Oral History Program. This oral history program is located at the
                        Lauinger Library at Georgetown University. The portion of the Marshall Plan
                        and successor agency studies is being financed by a grant by John J.
                        Grady.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador Saccio has had a distinguished career in government, in private
                    industry, and in academia. His career in the government is especially
                    interesting from our standpoint, because he served in very high positions not
                    only in the Foreign Aid Agency at the headquarters and abroad, but he also
                    served as an ambassador.</p>
                <p>My name is Mel Spector, and I am the director of the Marshall Plan Project. I had
                    the pleasure of serving under Ambassador Saccio when he was the deputy and
                    acting administrator of the Foreign Aid Agency.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ambassador, I'll take the privilege of addressing you informally, if I may,
                    based on our own friendship. Why don't we begin at the beginning, sir, and tell
                    me how you got into all of this?</p>
                <p>SACCIO: Back in 1954, I was director and general counsel of a manufacturing
                    company in New Haven, which was on the way of being sold or closed because of
                    economic conditions in a product that it manufactured and sold. This being the
                    end of the second year of Mr. Eisenhower's administration, I thought that that's
                    the place I'd like to go to. I asked for some support from the people that I
                    knew in politics and political affairs. And I got it very readily, particularly
                    from Senator Prescott Bush, who interviewed me and said, in effect, “Yes, young
                    man, perfectly willing to do so.” He got a few letters from his major
                    contributors, so it was no real problem.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>I just went down to Washington and looked around. And one of my supporters, who
                    had been the speaker of the house in Hartford, sent me to two fellows. I
                    couldn't understand what they were or what their position was. But it turned out
                    that they were in that group of people who serve senators and
                    representatives—staff aides—who knew the Washington setup inside and out and
                    were not particularly dedicated to any particular representative. They would
                    move from one job to another, working with a senator from one state or a
                    representative from another state.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They really are career people, aren't they, on the
                        Hill?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: They are, on the Hill. They always get some sort of job, and they have no
                    worries about advancements or things of that kind, because this is what they do,
                    and besides being awfully amusing in the way they spoke about what was going on
                    in town. And after chatting with them, they picked up the phone and said, “We
                    have an interview for you up here and one there.” The one they emphasized was
                    the Foreign Aid Program.</p>
                <p>At that time, it was a separate institution, headed by former-Governor Stassen.
                    And I walked into the place, and there was a young fellow by the name of Levine,
                    I think his name was, who was in charge of personnel, and he just said, “Okay.
                    What kind of a job do you want?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, I'm a lawyer, and this is where I want to do something.”</p>
                <p>He said, “I think we have an opening.” So I became deputy general counsel within
                    15 minutes.</p>
                <p>My wife was seated in the park waiting for me, and I walked out and I said,
                    “We're all set.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this your first interview? This was the first agency
                        that you went to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I think so. I don't think there was any other. Well, at least they knew
                    where the openings were and said, “Anybody who's a friend of So and So, is a
                    friend of ours, and we'll see what we can do for you.” So it was as easy as
                    that. Strangely enough, the lady who was in charge of personnel, her name was
                    Pryor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Helen Pryor?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Helen Pryor. She later was assigned to South Korea as the administrative
                    officer there. When Levine said, “We have this job,” I got interviewed by Chris
                    Herter, Jr.. And he looked at me and he looked me over, and he said, “Sure, it's
                    just fine.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Chris Herter was in the Foreign Aid Program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. Chris Herter, Jr.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jr., of course.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He was general counsel, and I became his deputy. The joke was that my
                    title of deputy general counsel was more resounding to people than general
                    counsel was. People would say, “Well, deputy general counsel, that's pretty
                    important.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It has a ring to it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: For some reason or another, I went into Helen Pryor's office and said,
                    “Here I am.” She gave me the cold shoulder. She let me wait in this small office
                    before she let me into her office and then swore me in! It wasn't the same day,
                    but when I finally came down. We packed all of our stuff here. We lived in
                    Bethlehem up the road here, and we got all our things in our station wagon and
                    just drove down. We got there, and she said, “Raise your hand,” and swore me
                    in.</p>
                <p>When Chris Herter heard about this, he was furious. “That's not the way to swear
                    a man in. You'd think you are a clerk or something.” But I later discovered and
                    became, of course, great friends with Helen Pryor, and she was one of my great
                    supporters around the place. Her son-in-law whom I have known for years lives
                    down the road here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Does he really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: But she was cold to me because I was a political appointee. I mean, I
                    walked in and, by gosh, it didn't matter whether she had anything to say about
                    it or not, I got the job.</p>
                <p>On the program itself, the first interesting thing that happened was that the
                    agency was subjected to an investigation or a review. If you will recall, the
                    so-called Second Hoover Commission had a subcommittee on the Foreign Aid
                    Program, and the subcommission was manned by one top man from a very important
                    accounting firms. I can't remember the name now, but it's the big one and it's
                    still the big one. And on it was Hollister. He was one of the members.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: John Hollister.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>SACCIO: John Hollister. We were invited down. I just tagged along, you see,
                    because Stassen was going to be a witness there, of course, as counsel. I don't
                    know whether Chris bothered to go to it, but just to get educated, I sat down,
                    and Stu Van Dyke was one of the witnesses.</p>
                <p>The object of the commission was to investigate the extravagant use of
                    counterpart money in Europe. Now, travel. Everybody was all over the place. And
                    I think the subcommission took a little trip to Europe and came back absolutely
                    astounded because of the palatial facilities and quarters that were built on
                    counterpart funds, particularly Germany, which I saw myself a couple of years
                    later. My gosh! I had a bedroom bigger than a conference room.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By any chance, did they see Henry Tasca's place in Rome,
                        the one he had? I will tell you about that off the record.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Stu Van Dyke, in his very calm and collected way, testified and he made
                    his statement. He just went along and didn't try to contradict the commission.
                    They were peppering him with this and that. All these people who were jumping on
                    airplanes and spending a lot of money going back and forth. We had all kinds of
                    commissions; people who were delighted to be on a commission because they got a
                    free trip. These are not employees, but friends of whoever it was were put on a
                    commission to take a little investigation here or there, as I remember it.</p>
                <p>So I said to Stu, “You just go along. You don't say anything. You don't
                    contradict them.”</p>
                <p>He said, “You got to go through this. It's the old story.”</p>
                <p>In other words, we were going through something that was known to be, and I soon
                    discovered, that the whole AID program was a place where people got jobs as
                    easily as I did because of background or political connection. I mean, if you
                    were a halfway decent lawyer and you were a Republican and you knew somebody and
                    had served the Party in one fashion or another, it was fine. The Congress, at
                    that point, was Democratic, and most of our time seemed to be spent on answering
                    questions or going before congressional committees, aside from the presentation
                    itself.</p>
                <p>At least one operation—two operations—were based just on a committee getting
                    after the Republican administration. One was Senator McClellan's committee, the
                    Senate committee whose counsel was Bobby Kennedy. And the other was Porter
                    Hardy, who decided that he was going to investigate Bill Warren, who had been
                    the mission director in Iran, and at the time that he was being questioned by
                    Porter Hardy, was the so-called economic coordinator in Korea. Senator McClellan
                    was from Arkansas.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>The business with Bobby Kennedy—I say Bobby Kennedy because he was the man who
                    really wanted to investigate. McClellan was chairman, but he let Kennedy run the
                    show as far as I could see. Bobby would just go up to him and say, “We want to
                    do this,” and “That's perfectly all right.”</p>
                <p>The big issue was whether there was any corruption in buying silos from an
                    American company for supply to Pakistan—the famous Pakistan silo case. And the
                    issue, as far as I could figure out, was why did we pick this company. There
                    were apparently no bids. It happened to be a Midwestern company, which, of
                    course, you could associate with Stassen's background and Bobby Kennedy was
                    after getting the facts in order to criticize Stassen and his organization and
                    the administration of the program.</p>
                <p>The issue came to a point where he got a subpoena for two of our people in that
                    division who were doing all the work in connection with the contract, whether
                    they were in the contract section or in the—well, two men who they asked to come
                    down to talk to the committee. And for one reason or another, there was some
                    doubt as to whether they would go or not, so Kennedy got a couple of subpoenas
                    “appear before the committee and we want to question you.”</p>
                <p>At that point, Stassen was out of town. Chris Herter was out of town for one
                    reason or another, and these fellows said, “What do we do? We got subpoenas; we
                    got to go.” So Dr. Fitz said, “Well, go, but you got to go with them.”</p>
                <p>So I said, “Okay.” So I went down, and we went into the committee room where I
                    knew the senator held hearings. And before long, some young fellow came up to us
                    and said, “We want you down in the office.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, the subpoena is returnable to the Senate committee.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, that's all right. Just come on down and talk with Mr.
                    Kennedy.”</p>
                <p>So we went down in the room, and he came out of his office and he said, “I want
                    to talk to these two fellows.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, you want them in your office. The subpoena is returnable to the
                    committee, not to your office.”</p>
                <p>And he said, “You will have to check this with your authority.”</p>
                <p>I called Dr. Fitz right from the telephone in the hallway there and Dr. Fitz
                    said, “Well, it's okay, but you've got to be present.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were their attorney. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: So I went back and said, “The agency is perfectly happy, but I have to be
                    present.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Absolutely not. I want to talk to them.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Absolutely not. If you want to talk to them, I have to be present.”He
                    said, “You just wait a minute.” Just as plain as that. The next thing you know,
                    he leaves, and a message comes back, “Come on up to the committee.”</p>
                <p>And then the thing bust out. “How dare you deny the counsel the right to question
                    them.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Senator McClellan...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is right before the Senator now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No, the whole committee was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, you're before the committee now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: When Kennedy talked to the senator, he said, “He doesn't want me to talk
                    to them, but we're going to do it because he insists that it's returnable to
                    Senate.” So they pulled out an alarm, and every senator on the committee showed
                    up, including “Scoop” Jackson and the famous rural Shakespearean. What was his
                    name? The senator who quoted Shakespeare all over the lot and came out with some
                    Shakespeare, “What does this man feed on that he dare?” [Laughter] Irwin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Irwin. Oh, the great Senator Irwin.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I got blasted. I said, “This is a subpoena returnable to the
                    committee.”</p>
                <p>And they said, “What right have you to talk? The subpoena is there. You're not
                    their lawyer; you're the lawyer for the agency.”</p>
                <p>One of the fellows—I've forgotten his name—he was cute. He looked up and he said,
                    “He is our lawyer.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good for him. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>SACCIO: He was streetwise. He said, “We make him our lawyer; that's it.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they didn't have to pay your fees, either.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Oh, well. They had a session and said, “Well, we can't have this.” So
                    they immediately appropriated some money to hire a lawyer to represent them so
                    there wouldn't be any conflict.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I was kidding! That's terrific.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: They did. It was great, though.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I believe this is the subcommittee on appropriation,
                        because McClellan was the head of that. It was a very important
                        committee.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Oh, obviously. But at any rate, it had subpoena authority to investigate;
                    that's what it had. It didn't have to go back to the Congress to ask for it.</p>
                <p>And they sat there, and the issue became, “Can these people testify?” “Because,”
                    I said, “these people are advisors to the director of the aid program, and what
                    they say to the director is privileged.” And this is the first time the
                    executive privilege came up in recent times. And “Scoop” Jackson, you know,
                    started blasting me up and down. Where was he from?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The state of Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He said, “The district attorney has the right to issue a subpoena.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Look. The district attorney has a right to ask a man to come to his
                    office, but he cannot subpoena him. He can only subpoena him before the Grand
                    Jury. Excuse me. I've had plenty of experience on this, because I was a
                    prosecuting attorney in Brooklyn, chasing after corruption in Brooklyn.”</p>
                <p>Well, he raved about that. But at any rate, it all came out and finally Stassen
                    had to come before them. These fellows got their attorney, who was somewhat
                    previously associated with the program.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But was then in private practice?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: That's right. At any rate, it became a great issue all over the place.
                    Finally, in matters of this kind, it always breaks down so there is some sort of
                    compromise, and they got the facts. And as we left the hearing with Stassen and
                    Chris Herter and everybody in this big limousine that we were traveling, and he
                    said, “Well, we can't do it this way. We'll just use their plans.”</p>
                <p>I said, “You can't use their plans because, after all, they belong to them. You
                    just can't appropriate the plans of this company to make silos.” So we dropped
                    the whole thing.</p>
                <p>The other thing, of course, was Porter Hardy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Pardon me a minute, Len. Was this early in your career
                        that you had to go into this meeting? Had you been in the agency very long
                        when you...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Two months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Two months. So this was your baptism by fire?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: It was. It was that. And, fortunately, I had had some seven or eight
                    years of experience as a prosecuting attorney, and I knew the procedures. And
                    Bobby Kennedy didn't know the first thing about it, because he was not a
                    criminal lawyer and he was recently out of law school. But he obviously was
                    furious. And to a follow-up, when he came through Argentina when he made that
                    famous trip down the west coast of Latin America and around to Argentina, when
                    he came off the plane, there was Ambassador Ed Martin to greet him and I was
                    there, too. And he looked at me and said, “I remember you.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>But the other was Porter Hardy. There were other committees there who all wanted
                    to do something and get something. There was one committee, the name of which I
                    forget, sent in a request to have copies of all correspondence going on between
                    Washington and the various missions, and they wanted them every day as they came
                    in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, my God!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, this was the kind of atmosphere. And, obviously, Stassen himself
                    was the target, being a political, well known, and having ambitions—everybody
                    knew that—and they were trying to get at him in one way or another.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>Porter Hardy was after what he considered a mess in Iran. Iran was quite a post,
                    because in addition to a mission director, a more fancy “economic coordinator,”
                    as Bill later was in Korea. He had ten regions, as I remember, each with a
                    deputy director, spread all over Iran, and they were doing all kinds of
                    things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Bill Warren was the only holdover from the Truman
                        Administration, the only holdover, because John Foster Dulles and Allen
                        Dulles talked to Stassen and said, “This man has to stay.” And Loy Henderson
                        of State said, “This man has to stay. He's too important.” So it's
                        interesting that he would be a target later, even though he was a holdover
                        from the Truman Administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, Loy Henderson had been ambassador in Iran. Is that the
                    connection?</p>
                <p>At any rate, here again it was on and off, and Bill in no way wanted to cooperate
                    with Porter Hardy. He considered him a lowly sort of politician, unimportant
                    Congressman from the southern part of Virginia, and obviously trying to make a
                    name for himself. And as we go up and back, I stuck with Bill all the way. I
                    said, “Bill, why don't you answer his questions?”</p>
                <p>“Forget it. I'm not going to give him the satisfaction of doing anything. I'm
                    going to sit there and just let him spiel away.”</p>
                <p>Well, this went on, but it indicated the atmosphere of the place where more time
                    was being spent, aside from the Presentation every year...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The regular Presentations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: The regular Presentation. The other things in the first period: there was
                    my own questioning as to what the program was about and, of course, learning the
                    rules. I discovered, as everybody else did, but to me it was new, that the aid
                    program was so infested with protecting the interest of everybody in the United
                    States, aside from giving aid to other countries. Good old Reg 1 was so full of
                    things. You had to protect the farmer, you had to protect small business.
                    Everything was up and down the line, and before you could say that this man was
                    qualified to have a job or a contract of one kind or another, you had to go
                    through Reg 1.</p>
                <p>It was so complicated and so long that of the ten or 15 lawyers we had in our
                    office, only two—Peter Morse and a fellow by the name of Rothschild. Peter Morse
                    was really absolutely the best lawyer we ever had in the place, and they were
                    bound up on this thing. We had another lawyer, who used to be in Dulles' law
                    firm, who was devoted solely to, I think it was Section 401, which gave the
                    director of the ICA a means to cut through regulations in a case of an emergency
                    or an important operation.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A very important piece of legislation. It's very nice to
                        have that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: And it was used, and I've forgotten his name, but he was an elderly
                    fellow. I shouldn't be saying that, but 30 years ago, he was elderly. And he was
                    very careful. Absolutely he had to have everything in line, because he had to
                    have a perfect record so that if there was any question, you know, “this is why
                    we did it.”</p>
                <p>The exceptions were that when Mr. Dulles wanted something, he got it. He said,
                    “Write me a 401.” That's all it was, you see. He didn't have to produce all the
                    little things that everybody else had to produce, which is understandable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was 401 used sometimes for what we would say “political
                        reasons”? I don't mean domestic political, but political vis � vis country X
                        over what was considered to be a true economic problem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, obviously you couldn't separate them, because that was the basic
                    thing—I can get to that right now— that made it difficult for the aid program to
                    work with the State Department, because they were two entirely different
                    concepts. You can't separate the political from the economic. But the State
                    Department, in its foreign policy, so to speak, wanted something done, and they
                    didn't care whether it was economically sound or was really helping the country
                    as far as its economic standards were concerned. Whereas the guys in the aid
                    program wanted to see results in the way of production, increased food,
                    technical assistance of one kind or another.</p>
                <p>The assistant secretary in charge of the area, as in one case, Tom Mann, who was
                    assistant secretary for Latin America at one point, turned to me and he said,
                    “You know, when I was down in Salvador, those aid people gave me a lot of
                    trouble.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Why?”</p>
                <p>“Well, they needed a fire engine down there, and I wanted them to give it to them
                    and they wouldn't do it.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>And when there was some problem with—well, most of that, obviously, was a great
                    problem. I got a call from one of the Secretary's' immediate aide and said,
                    “Len, we want a shipload of wheat to go to—I think it was—Iran. Have you got
                    any?”</p>
                <p>I said, “What do you mean?”</p>
                <p>“Yeah. We want it right away.”</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>So I called Dr. Fitz and said, “What do you have on float?”</p>
                <p>He said, “There's a ship going to Egypt, but I won't give it to them.”
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That sounds like Dr. Fitz; I know.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He was furious. So I put out instructions to divert the...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At this point, you were no longer in the general counsel's
                        office. You were the deputy administrator, probably.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I'm not sure, because Chris Herter left pretty soon after. When Hollister
                    came in and Stassen went out— I forget, Stassen became “Secretary of Peace,” and
                    they put Hollister in, there was bad blood between Chris Herter and Hollister.
                    They couldn't get along nohow. Hollister was a prominent lawyer from—what was
                    it—Cleveland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From Ohio.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He came in. He had been a member of that Hoover subcommittee and knew all
                    about the program, and his job was given on the theory that he would run it
                    efficiently and not with all these expenditures all around the place. And before
                    you knew it, the whole darn agency was stuck in the State Department, and it
                    became a part of the State Department instead of a separate agency. The “white
                    telephone” was pulled out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, then it became ICA. It was FOA and it now became the
                        International Cooperation Administration, and it was a whole new setup.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Later I'd like you to talk a little about that setup and
                        your relationship to the State Department coordinator.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I think I became deputy later on, but I can't place that Egyptian's cargo
                    as to whether I was. At any rate, I was the man they turned to, that's all. And
                    I may have been deputy by that time, but I'm not sure.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>That was the major thing that made it so difficult. And the other major thing, to
                    my mind as a comparative newcomer, was whether this aid program was really doing
                    something aside from giving plenty of dollar currency so these people could live
                    and import industrial products.</p>
                <p>One fine day I called up Dr. Fitz and I said, “This sending of tons and tons of
                    food to Pakistan, what's going to happen when we stop? You know, the whole point
                    is you are feeding them, but the moment you stop, they have no resources.
                    They're agriculture is minimal.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Len, I know, but we have to do this.”</p>
                <p>I said, “I can't understand it.”</p>
                <p>I should mention here that the one thing that Hollister did to the program as far
                    as the substance was concerned, otherwise he was a good administrator, he
                    created the worldwide malaria program. He did that job, and it was an essential
                    plus to the substantive results of a good aid program.</p>
                <p>I made the silly—I guess it wasn't so silly. I said, “What's the whole point of
                    this? They haven't got any food and you're going for a malaria program without
                    giving them the means of working. You're just making them better and you have to
                    feed them.” I was being very neo-Malthusian, I suppose. And this fellow's clever
                    answer was, “They still make babies when they have malaria.” So that was my
                    answer. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, were you made deputy under Hollister?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Under Hollister, yes. That was an interesting thing, and it's just an
                    interesting anecdote. Let me see. Who was the deputy? Somebody left who was
                    deputy, and I forget who it was. Oh, no, that wasn't it. The Hollister affair
                    was when Chris left as general counsel, Hollister looked around from among all
                    his law acquaintances looking for a general counsel. He had some friends in
                    Philadelphia and some good lawyers. He offered them the job, and they said, “No
                    way. We're not going into that.” So he finally turned to me. He called me up and
                    he said, “I asked So and So and So and So, but I want you to be general
                    counsel.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Thank you very much. I appreciate that.” And they arranged a swearing-in
                    in the big conference room we had in that building.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Maiatico Building.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: And I called up Senator Bush's secretary and said, “They want to make me
                    general counsel, and I'd like the senator, if he has time, to officiate at the
                    swearing in.”</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>“Fine. He'll be there.”</p>
                <p>When Hollister found out, he said, “I didn't know you knew Senator Bush.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, I do.”</p>
                <p>“Why didn't you tell me? I would have...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Given you the job right off the bat. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I think that's under what circumstances I became general counsel. But at
                    any rate, Hollister left and I would say that he had no background or direct
                    interest in the substantive part of the program. I mean, he was just in love
                    with Jack Ohly and his analysis, which were quite complicated, as you probably
                    remember. Jack Ohly was his right arm. They would sit and talk about this thing,
                    but there wasn't anything that came out of it that added something, or at least
                    made a difference.</p>
                <p>The program was pretty much settled between defense support, economic
                    development, and technical assistance, and there was no great variety or changes
                    while I was there for six years. And most of the time, the general counsel, and
                    I as the presenter—I became presenter when some fellow who was a big shot in a
                    law firm in New York—I think his name was Levin—came down and he insisted on
                    putting up a big plaque over his door, just like the State Department assistant
                    secretary's. Was it Strock &amp; Strock &amp; Lavan, I think, or a firm of that
                    kind. He was there for two weeks and, “You mean I got to do all . . . This is
                    too complicated,” and he quit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was in the aid program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes, that's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And which job did he come down to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: The presenter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, to be the presenter. And he had a sign above his
                        door?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. He had the rank of assistant secretary.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But he took one look and left?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He was there for a few weeks, you know. He'd stride in. And, here again,
                    you see, I was taken in, just “Who else would do it?” My wife never forgave
                    me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You'd go up there for days at a time, wouldn't you, to
                        present?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Oh, yes. On one occasion, I got a call at 7:00 in the evening. We were
                    entertaining a Latin American diplomat who was with the Latin American Bank, I
                    think, and we got a call at 7:00, “Otto Passman will see you now.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. And Gerald Ford was a member of the committee, as I remember. He
                    would sit in and then leave. And I went up there with a 25-page statement, you
                    see. I forget what the specific subject was, but I was defending the . . . His
                    committee was, in effect...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I believe Otto Passman took over from Porter Hardy. He had
                        the same committee, but Otto Passman succeeded Porter Hardy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I see. And he was a subcommittee of the Appropriation Committee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Correct. That handled the foreign aid program.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: And Douglas Dillon, at that point, was either under secretary or top
                    economic man in the department. And he would go before Passman and give the
                    opening statement, and we would follow up with the details. An interesting
                    incident: Otto Passman pulling out a clipping of that columnist.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Drew Pearson?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Drew Pearson. Relating that a group of these guys from the aid program
                    went off on a separate plane with their wives to review the situation in a
                    number of stations of the aid program. He asked Mr. Dillon, “How come they're
                    going off with their wives?” as if it were a junket.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>And Mr. Dillon said, “Mr. Saccio will be able to answer that question well
                    enough.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>Well, I went up there with Johnny Murphy, and I forget what my answer was. He
                    wanted to know, you see; he waved the clipping. And I gave a very quick answer
                    which amounted to the fact that we were going out to places where no superior
                    officer of the agency had been, and that there had been no contact with the
                    people out there and we knew nothing about how the families were getting on and
                    I wanted to take my wife. And the reason why Mr. Roseman's wife was there was
                    because he was one of the important officials and had been a director of the
                    program in Cambodia before, and she knew what it was about.</p>
                <p>There was some other remark I made which—oh, he, Passman, had been criticized by
                    somebody, and I just said, “You know, like these people who criticized you.” So
                    what did he do with it? He threw it away. [Laughter] Well, the best statement I
                    ever made before the Passman thing...</p>
                <p>The statement I made was when Passman just said, “All this stuff is just dollar
                    diplomacy,” I said, “I know about dollar diplomacy. I've studied our history.
                    Philander Knox was the guy who invented that word, and this is not.” And I
                    pulled out a speech about all the good that was being done. We weren't just
                    bribing people. And Gerry Ford looked at me and did a little chuckle, and then
                    he left.</p>
                <p>Passman was a funny guy, because in one way or another, he was just always
                    political. One of his “clients,” was Greece, and if we wanted to get our bill
                    through, we had to put $25 million into Greece, regardless of anything, and that
                    was it. It was just, unfortunately, a man who was more interested in picking up
                    things on trips and getting counterpart, and as long as he got what he wanted,
                    he was very lush on the amount of money he spent on his clothing, shirts, ties,
                    and cuff links.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I remember cuff links, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Let me stop here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Len, I'd like to ask you about your relationships with
                        Douglas Dillon and whether or not your relationships with the State
                        Department were modified or changed in any way after he took over as the
                        coordinator.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No, no. I don't think there was any change. He was a lot more
                    sophisticated about the operation, being a banker himself and former ambassador
                    to France. He knew what we were doing, and there was no real question as far as
                    being contrary to our objectives.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>I know he was very deeply involved when we had the problem with the Suez...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Suez Canal?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No, no, with the famous dam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, the Aswan Dam.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: The Aswan Dam. Because that's when he, I think, really had a real tough
                    time, because there was no question, you see, we people in the aid program had
                    nothing to do with that sort of thing. And we may have been critical because we
                    had some very direct interest in the dam itself, and to have it go over to the
                    Russians—not that we were happy about building the dam, because there was
                    certainly a lot of technical opinion that it wasn't a wise thing to do in view
                    of the fact of the whole agriculture was based on the flooding of the Nile in a
                    regular season. But that was nothing that we would have a voice in, and properly
                    so. There was no point in our talking about that. This was really a fight
                    between the Russians and ourselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Essentially it was a political matter.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. And whether the dam was to be built or not, it was really secondary
                    to the issue we had with Egypt.</p>
                <p>No, the relationship with Dillon was far superior than it was with the assistant
                    secretaries, because he had a much broader view of things and he understood what
                    we were doing. And he wasn't being contrary or telling us we had to do it. He
                    would just nod, and that was it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He'd once been a mission director himself under the
                        Marshall Plan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He had?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: France.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, he was made ambassador eventually. In those days, the mission
                    director, of course, was from a separate agency; it was not from the State
                    Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were other people in Dillon's office, I believe.
                        There was Jack Bell, Graham Martin, other people like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: There was another fellow—let me see—who worked with us. We have very good
                    relationships. Phil Claxton, a wonderful guy, and his—I'm trying to remember the
                    name of the fellow he worked with. We worked very closely. We really had no
                    problems, and we were, on both sides, sophisticated enough to say that you've
                    never resolve this problem. It's to whether you're doing it for aid or you're
                    doing it for State.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Correct.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: And one of the jokes that we had at one point were preparing the
                    Presentation. One of them said, “Let's refer in our basic statement to
                    Jefferson.”</p>
                <p>I said, “You know those guys up there. They don't know anything about Jefferson.”
                    And we all started laughing. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>One important thing happened with the Mossadegh trouble. He was in Iran when the
                    Shah was kicked out. The present revisionist history in effect said we did the
                    wrong thing not letting him in, because what could he have done? We could have
                    contained him just as well. Putting the Shah in, you know, you did the wrong
                    thing, because what you did was make a guy a multimillionaire.</p>
                <p>But that's revisionist. The point was that Dulles asked the Congress immediately
                    for $250 million as an emergency fund, and they passed it like that. It was
                    true, you see. They would go in there, counteract Mossadegh and put the Shah
                    back in.</p>
                <p>But that was the issue. And the interesting part of it was that Mr. Dulles called
                    in a bunch of advisors of his, including “Wild Bill” Donovan, who was always
                    available for that sort of thing. We sat down around the table. I was seated
                    next to Mr. Dulles, and Mr. Dulles was going to explain to them what he wanted
                    them to do in connection with the threat in the Middle East.</p>
                <p>Incidentally, one of the questions I had when I first got on the program was that
                    I learned that Iran was making $200 million a year as royalties on the oil, and
                    my question was, “Why the hell are we giving them aid?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When they're making that much money.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: That's right. $200 million dollars was a heck of a lot of money then.
                    It's probably equivalent to $4 billion dollars today.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Correct.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: “Wild Bill” Donovan looked up at Dulles and said, “Here we are. We're
                    your trained seals. What do you want us to say?” [Laughter] Of course, he had a
                    heck of a lot more clout than Dulles did from the point of view of long
                    experience and as the originator of the OSS. The famous guy in the trenches in
                    France.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: True, in World War I. Yes, a famous man.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: On Armistice Day, he rose—I read his biography—and said, “We are now a
                    world power.” That was the attitude.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, there must have been someone at that meeting from
                        the Central Intelligence Agency. Or do you recall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No, but the people he brought in were from outside the government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, these were outsiders?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes, a commission. A quick operation in which they backed Dulles' request
                    for $250 million. Three or four years after, we were revising the statute of the
                    aid law, and one of the juniors sitting around with Doug Dillon running the show
                    as to what we should put in and take out, and one of the fellows said, “We
                    better take out this little $250 million authorization that we got some years
                    ago. We don't need it anymore.”</p>
                <p>I looked at him and said, “Don't touch it. Do you want to create a little problem
                    up on the Hill? They're going to ask you why you did and who did it. Leave it
                    there. They won't even notice it.” The whole point was I was concerned that
                    anytime you take anything out, you're bound to have a hearing on the subject.
                    Why did you do it, and was it successful?</p>
                <p>Nothing was said after I made this remark. And the next day I got a call from
                    this young fellow, or somebody who was at the meeting, and he said, “Do you
                    really mean that we should keep it?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Damn right you keep it. Don't touch it. Let it go through.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Mr. Dillon asked me to call you.”</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>We're not going to have much time for more anecdotes. But the Presentation was a
                    rough job, and 80 percent of the time was devoted to just responding to
                    Congress, and it was very difficult. Now, you can't downgrade it, because it's
                    an essential thing. You have to do it, but neither side, the Congress or the
                    executive, are free to really consider the basic problems. You get just an
                    overall idea that if you send a couple of people, like our farmers down there to
                    teach them how to plow, and give them some food and give them some public
                    security, send a police team down there, and give them some money to build
                    roads, and that's it.</p>
                <p>And this, of course, is hindsight on my part, except that I did ask questions
                    about what happens when you stop feeding them. But none of that really
                    penetrated, except that in the technical assistance program, we did things which
                    were really very basic and they were worthwhile. And the other part of the
                    technical assistance participant program—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The participant program, which is the training program
                        here in the United States.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: People come in and they're required to go back, and they could not return
                    for at least two years. Indicating how important it is, was the experience I had
                    in India, where I was the economic minister and the AID director in India.</p>
                <p>A little old lady, gray haired, came in the office and said, “I want to see you
                    and talk to you about what I have in mind. I want to have a conference with all
                    the past participants that are in the area around Calcutta.”</p>
                <p>I said, “What?”</p>
                <p>She said, “Yes. This is what I do for the AID program. I go around and invite all
                    the past participants, and we have a session and we talk and so forth to see how
                    things are going.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Calcutta? Do you know what that is? That's the Bengali Reds. I mean,
                    that's run by the communists there. Won't you be afraid?”</p>
                <p>“Oh, no,” she said, “I do this, you know, regular.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, I'm really concerned about you going there.”</p>
                <p>She said, “I've been to Calcutta, and I know what it is and I've studied it. The
                    Ford Foundation is doing a terrific job there making studies and studies and
                    studies.”</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>So I finally said, “Okay, if you feel it's all right.” I mean, she had—I forget
                    how many—they were in the hundreds. They came to the conference and they had an
                    absolutely wonderful time, because they really appreciated what had been done.
                    And these were people who had stayed in the United States long enough to get a
                    feel of what it was like.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's wonderful. That's really one of the best things we
                        did, isn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. And the funny part of it is, you know, some of these participants
                    who come back, they can speak English and so forth, and they're hired by the oil
                    companies to run the gas stations because they're so good.</p>
                <p>Well, you're going to have things like that. The other thing we did in Colombia
                    was create a high school system, which did not exist. You had just the lyc�e
                    type of secondary education, which was open only to the well-to-do, who were
                    students going on to college. In the combination of the British and ourselves,
                    we built up a construction business to build the schools. They built schools—I
                    forget the number, but they were in various parts of Colombia—and installed a
                    comprehensive curriculum so that everybody could go. For the first two years,
                    everybody had the same course, and in the next three years, they branched off
                    into whatever they wanted to do—go to college, learn a trade, or what have
                    you.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why don't we get back to when you were deputy director of
                        AID, and then we'll go into Colombia later as we go along.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Very good. The funny part of becoming deputy director—I forget who was
                    leaving, and I think Jimmy Smith came in as the director.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, director or administrator. I forget what the title
                        was in those days. He didn't stay very long, Smith, did he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No. He really wanted to be the assistant secretary of the Navy, and when
                    he didn't get that, he quit the AID program.</p>
                <p>Well, there was nothing special about being deputy, except Ed Riddleberger didn't
                    do anything. He just sat there and was furious at the fact that they appointed
                    him to become the director or the administrator.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He didn't really want the job?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>SACCIO: He didn't want the job, and then he had a heart attack and he was out. We
                    never got anything from any of these administrators beyond administering, that's
                    all. They brought in a fellow by the name of Fitzgerald, who got his job, I
                    think it was essentially Grady's job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, William Fitzgerald.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: William Fitzgerald, who got his job by, you know, making a $1,000
                    contribution. He came in and he loved to go out on inspection trips.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I had to deal with him in Mexico.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He would concoct a little junket of chartering an airplane to go to the
                    box fight in New York. And he'd invite various congressmen and say, “We're all
                    going up and have a great time and see the fights.” This got so bad, he would
                    wander all around the Hill talking to people. He had some connection with French
                    bankers of one kind or another. His wife was French, a charming lady who
                    couldn't drink anything. I mean, she'd touch whiskey, and for some reason, she'd
                    get woozy right away. She was a very conservative French, a lovely person.</p>
                <p>He became so much of an annoyance that Dillon said to his staff, “I think we have
                    to get rid of Fitzgerald.” So the question came as to who's going to do it.
                    Dillon said, “Len will do it.” [Laughter] I was informed that I supposed to fire
                    Fitzgerald. Well, I was furious, because they never consulted me when he was
                    hired.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But then you got the job of firing him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, I didn't let him get away with too much. He was an awfully nice
                    guy, but he was a floating...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, as I recall, towards the end there, in '59 and '60,
                        there was a pretty good team there. It was you—you were really running the
                        agency—and you had Jim Grant, Johnny Murphy, and Dr. Dennis Fitzgerald. And
                        this team really ran the agency, and you brought some stability to the
                        agency that it hadn't had.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, thank you. Jim Grant was absolutely wonderful. Murphy was terrific,
                    and because of his long service in the AID program, was highly respected on the
                    Hill. As a matter of fact, when the time came that we had to have an inspector
                    general, the Hill said, “We'll take Johnny Murphy.” No questions asked.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>Jack Ohly was the constant philosopher and prober and really a great steady
                    influence on everything we did. Jim Grant was a go-getter if there ever was one,
                    because he thought out things and he and his staff—I don't know what they call
                    them, the program director or the policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I believe so. Policy and program, something like
                        that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: As an example of his foresight, when we took this trip that I told you
                    about that Passman criticized, he had in his pocket a plan which he worked out
                    with me in Washington of accelerating the grants to Taiwan and telling them
                    that, if they did certain things, instead of giving them an annual cut, he would
                    combine five years of grant money committed to Taiwan, if they carried out their
                    plan of land reform and family planning and all that sort of thing.</p>
                <p>And this is just wonderful. We stopped there, and we were wined and dined. And we
                    didn't see the president, [Chaing] Kai-shek, but we saw the vice president, and
                    we were going to explain it to him. And I explained it to the vice president.
                    The vice president had his interpreter there, and he would nod his head, saying,
                    “Yes, yes.” Jim stopped it in midair. He said, “Len, this interpreter is not
                    interpreting correctly. He's not getting the story over.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jim spoke Chinese?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes, so he pitched in. No, it was a darn- good team. The only thing I
                    regretted was that we couldn't continue on that basis, because Jimmy Smith
                    really did nothing; Riddleberger did nothing. Labouisse came after I left;
                    Kennedy put him in. He couldn't stand it any longer, and then they had this last
                    one, Fowler Hamilton.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you went to Brazil.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Right. Now, to be frank about my going to Brazil, was that I turned to
                    Dillon, after Riddleberger came back, and I said, “I can't stand this.” I mean,
                    he's no great operation. I thought, you know, that he would resign for illness,
                    but he wasn't going to resign for illness because he still wanted to be in the
                    Foreign Service. I was no great name in Washington. I mean, I was a guy from
                    Connecticut as far as the politicians were concerned. That's what they wanted,
                    somebody of that caliber, reputation, and so forth, because if you put somebody
                    in there, people say, “Okay, we trust that man, and we know him.” I was a young
                    guy from Connecticut, that's all, who had nothing more than the local political
                    connections, which were perfectly all right and useful.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>So I said to Dillon—we were alone, clearing up some business. The next thing, he
                    talked to Loy Henderson, and they decided that the best thing to do was to send
                    me overseas and put me in the Foreign Service Reserve. Obviously, they wouldn't
                    make me an ambassador. I didn't have the kind of experience, and they knew if
                    they did, I'd be fired the next day anybody else came into the White House.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was getting towards the end of Eisenhower's
                        Administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. So they said, “We'll send you to Brazil and make you the economic
                    minister and the AID director combined.” And I think Cottam, who was my
                    predecessor there, had the same standing, but he was in the regular Foreign
                    Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Howard Cottam.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: So I went down there, and this was in September.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is September of . . .</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: '60. And this, of course, was an entirely different operation, as far as
                    my experience was concerned. Except as an administrator, I presumably had the
                    help of everybody else to run a program.</p>
                <p>On our way down, we were on board, I guess it was, the Brazil or the S.S.
                    Argentina. We took a ship down, and we had to get an exemption for that, because
                    you flew down to your post and you didn't just take a cruise. And everybody knew
                    that, but they said, “You've been working so hard, absolutely.” But at any rate,
                    we cruised down, and on the way down, the election took hold in Brazil, and
                    J�nio Quadros was elected. There were great cheers from the Brazilians on
                    board.</p>
                <p>Now, on the AID program, before Quadros was elected, Dillon had been working very
                    hard to create some understanding with Latin America. He understood the
                    problems, and he had been working with Kubitschek in Brazil, who had proposed
                    what he called “Operation Pan-Americana.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Kubitschek did?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. And Dillon was working with him on that basis. As a matter of fact,
                    even before that had been established, because of our special relationship with
                    Brazil—I'll explain why it was a special relationship—that created a joint
                    U.S.-Brazil Economic Committee to work with Brazil on its economic problems.
                    Now, this wasn't doing very much, I assume, for the simple reason that
                    Kubitschek made this proposal, and he talked, if I remember correctly, of a $30
                    billion operation. Behind that was the famous, highly respected Ra�l
                    Prebisch.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ra�l Prebisch from Argentina.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: And he had proposed, you know, the only way to help Latin America was to
                    put in resources. And they started this thing, and it was in stream when Kennedy
                    came in, and Kennedy converted that into the Alliance for Progress.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But there had been a lot of new emphasis on Latin America
                        in the latter days under the Eisenhower Administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Definitely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In fact, the Inter-American Development Bank, I think, was
                        created.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. I should go back and mention one thing that Stassen did, was create
                    what came to be the IMF. Aside from the World Bank, he put $100 million as
                    capital for a bank that would loan on business, loan money out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To business?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: To business, for the less-developed countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, is that OPEC?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No. I think it was the predecessor of the IMF.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Predecessor of the International Monetary Fund?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>SACCIO: Right. That's something when this came about, of course, the idea of the
                    Latin American bank was broached and it was created while I was still in
                    Washington. The treasury man was the United States representative there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tull, was his name.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes, that's right. But at any rate, when I got to Brazil, I found a
                    massive mission there. For instance, the device used was the—oh, gosh.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Servicio?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Servicio. What it consisted of was representatives of the United States
                    and representatives of the country working together on technical assistance, and
                    you would have a servicio for agriculture, one for education, and one for public
                    safety, although I don't know whether they called it that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One for health.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Health and education and so forth. And these were all working on the
                    basis of trying to put in technology into a developmental mold for the country.
                    The work at the AID Mission was tremendous, as far as paperwork was concerned,
                    on and on, preparing for everything to be sent up to Washington for the
                    presentation. And you had a whole staff there. Bob Herder was there. He was the
                    deputy, and he had been in public administration in Iran and he was the mainstay
                    of the operation when he was Cottam's deputy and he became my deputy.</p>
                <p>But we couldn't find just how to do this thing. It was a slow process. I had to
                    recognize that right away. And the situation there as an agricultural country,
                    it wasn't able to produce its own food. Its cattle was out on the range for
                    years before it could ever be brought in to be packed. The agriculture servicio
                    bothered me more than anything else. I think we had about 15 Americans on that,
                    who had their offices over at the Department of Agriculture in town, and what
                    they were doing was going out and seeing what people needed in the way of
                    equipment, things of this kind.</p>
                <p>I talked to the Brazilian head of the servicio and found that he had absolutely
                    no authority in the Department of Agriculture—it was entirely different—and the
                    Department of Agriculture was not producing anything but bureaucrats who got
                    jobs in the Department of Agriculture. And I beefed like all heck to Dr. Fitz
                    over the phone saying, “Look, these guys are not . . .” But any rate, Cabot, who
                    was the ambassador...</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, John Cabot.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: John Moore Cabot, yes.</p>
                <p>I said, “Look, what are we doing here?” Bob Herder said “calma.”</p>
                <p>They sent a former congressman down, who lost his job as a congressman, to take
                    care of some social program. I've forgotten his name, but I guess he was half
                    Italian, so he thought we were buddies or something like that. He was one pain
                    in the neck, and I would get so mad at him, I would shout him out of the office.
                    And my secretary would come in afterward and say, “Look, you know, they hear you
                    out there.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Let them hear me.” He was just imposed on us, but he became so
                    fascinated about it, he started his own participant program. But before that, he
                    was just looking for the job. We got people time and again coming down—Stan
                    Grand and all these people—looking for my job. It was a good job in that famous
                    3,000 job pamphlet that's always issued for new administrations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. Stan Grand came down there before the election,
                        or maybe during the election?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I forget. But he was down with a team regularly, and we became friends,
                    of course. He and I got along fine, but it was obvious what he was doing. Dillon
                    came down for the new administration. He was now Secretary of the Treasury and
                    Kennedy's man and he came down at the most important time. There was an
                    Inter-American Bank conference, and they had a whole outlay there. J�nio
                    Quadros, of course, was president.</p>
                <p>We had a very elaborate procedure of committing PL 480 currency. You know, we
                    gave the food, but they had to put up their local currency for it. And it would
                    be used, but it had to be used very carefully. Project-wise, you had to justify
                    it. It was no joke. It wasn't just shoved in the bank. And you had to get all
                    kinds of permission to do it, because, otherwise, it would be wasted.</p>
                <p>So right in the midst of this conference, Doug called me up and he said, “Len, we
                    need so much in reserves.”</p>
                <p>And I said, “We got to go through all this processes.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Len, we need it. Would you kindly commit it?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Yes.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, he was down in Brazil at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In this conference?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And he needed that much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes, it's part of the deal. “Here I come. (U.S.) I'm going to work with
                    you.” (Brazil)</p>
                <p>Well, this seemed to be the practice for practically everybody. In the first days
                    of the Kennedy Administration, we had people come in all over the place. But a
                    good example of how it operated was—well, Tad Szulc had written these
                    devastating articles of starvation and the drought in the Northeast.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tad Szulc, he was the New York Times correspondent.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: That's right. Everything was going. And Stevenson came down, and we had a
                    whole session with J�nio Quadros. In his team was Lincoln Gordon, the obvious
                    successor to Cabot. He wasn't yet made, but everybody knew that. And Dick
                    Goodwin, who took the trouble of staying behind after the delegation left the
                    president's office up in Bras�lia, to tell the president that Cabot was going to
                    go out and that Mr. Gordon was going to be the ambassador.</p>
                <p>No, no. It was Goodwin who told the president that it was Gordon who was going to
                    be the ambassador, and he downgraded Cabot like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cabot had no authority after that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. The example I was thinking about is Senator Young. I don't remember
                    his first name and what state he came from, but he was in charge of some
                    committee. And with this brouhaha about the northeast, he was going to come down
                    and look at it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Northeast Brazil?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>SACCIO: Northeast Brazil. Because of all these people coming in and out, we, in
                    the embassy, decided—the ambassador, of course—that we would oppose any more
                    visits to the northeast. He said, “All we are doing is creating more problems,
                    because what else can you do?”</p>
                <p>So I happened to be on consultation up to Washington, and so was Lincoln Gordon,
                    and Senator Young came to the State Department and wanted to talk to Lincoln
                    Gordon before they went down.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Gordon then ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Oh, yes. He was ambassador. And he said that he was at the White House
                    and could not be with him because he was tied up, but Len Saccio was around to
                    talk to him. So I got invited into this room with three Air Force generals and
                    God knows what. They were going to fly them down, a whole Air Force planeload of
                    three or four senators. And Senator Young turned to me and said, “We want to go
                    down, and we're flying directly to Recife and want to see the place. We
                    understand that we got a message from your deputy, the Charg� Bond—Niles
                    Bond—that there was a problem, that we should consult with the ambassador up
                    here.”</p>
                <p>I said, “I was not surprised that Bond had responded that way, because that was
                    the agreed position of the embassy.”</p>
                <p>And he turned to me and he said, “Why can't we go down there?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, the embassy feels that it's counterproductive. You're creating all
                    kinds of situations there.” They have a feeling that, during the war, we were
                    able to do anything, you see. We built a whole town. We built roads and so forth
                    and all that and it was the point where we sent the planes across to Africa, and
                    we'd do anything. Well, what the hell are we waiting for up in the
                    northeast?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why couldn't we do the same thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Why can't we do the same thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Develop the Northeast.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>SACCIO: We had already committed $150 million down there. I said, “You want to
                    get briefed? The place to get briefed is in Rio, where the office of the
                    Northwest agency is. Where Mr. Furtado, who is the head of it, will brief you.
                    And to fly this big plane down there,” I said, “this is the wrong thing. You
                    come down to Rio and you get briefed, and then we'll fly you up in a small
                    chartered plane so you can go see it for yourself.”</p>
                <p>So we all got back to Brazil, and they show up, and Gordon had a big briefing
                    session in the ballroom of the embassy. And when it was all over, the senator
                    got up and they said, “Mr. Ambassador, have you any objection of our going up to
                    the northeast?” The ambassador said, “No.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they held you responsible for their not going to the
                        north?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Before you know it, we had a whole team come down from Washington to
                    reinvestigate under the charge that I was running the embassy. And poor Linc
                    Gordon tried to get out of it. He said, “No, no. Len is a...</p>
                <p>The Senator Young example is only an example of just how we ran the AID program,
                    because they all came down. For instance, the first time the group came down,
                    headed by Adlai Stevenson, and they went down and talked to J�nio. And A.A.
                    Berle, the old assistant secretary, came down, and at a conference in Itamaraty,
                    which is the foreign office palace in Rio, he got up and made a speech in
                    Portuguese. He had been ambassador to Brazil for a long time and he had learned
                    the language. And he ended off by saying, “To give you a good start, we are
                    immediately appropriating $100 million to the program.” There was dead silence.
                    Niles Bond was in that conference and I was there. As we walked out, he said,
                    “What a lead balloon.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>Well, at one point Fitz said, “What do we do now?”</p>
                <p>I said, “What you ought to do is invite Furtado, who is the head of the northeast
                    agency, up to Washington to see the President, because, after all, it's the
                    Alliance for Progress.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Wait a minute, Len. That sounds good.” So he called up, and he said,
                    “Okay, set it up and you come up.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Okay.” And we went up there. It was beautiful. We stayed at the same
                    hotel. I had breakfast with Furtado, and we went to the White House. And before
                    we got into talking to Kennedy, Dick Goodwin looked at the briefing paper on
                    Celso Furtado, and there was a line there, “he has communist . . .” So he took a
                    pencil, and he crossed off all this business about something like communist
                    leanings.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>Obviously, he was perfectly right in doing it in the sense that Celso Furtado was
                    no more a Marxist than—he was a Marxist only because he read about it. He was
                    not a capitalist, put it that way. He believed in government planning.</p>
                <p>We finally walked in, and the President was his usual gracious self. And Furtado
                    said, “There's a province up in the middle north which we can really develop,”
                    whether it was Piaui or another one. It's inward, way inward, from Recife.</p>
                <p>And he turned around to me and he said, “How big is Piaui?”</p>
                <p>Boy, I caught it. I wasn't going to be dishonest. “It's very big,” I said. I
                    should have said it was bigger than Texas— that would have been historic—but I
                    didn't.</p>
                <p>At any rate, we smiled and we had a nice session, and they sat down and planned
                    it all. And they decided to send a separate mission director for that area, and
                    I can't remember the guy's name to save my life, but he was of Italian
                    extraction or Italian, but an American citizen, and he was related to Gardner,
                    who became...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bruno Luzzato.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was the father-in-law of Richard Gardner.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: That was fine. That was the end of my direct authority up there. We had
                    some very good guys in education who I got to know when we traveled up there in
                    various parts of northern Brazil, and they were really hard workers and they
                    were creating a very good education program. Well, Luzzato came along, and,
                    before long, one man that we knew, a Brazilian top engineer who was in charge of
                    one of the big dams, the building of a whole series of dams in a major river to
                    create a great source of power, and he said to me, “Do you know this fellow,
                    Luzzato?”</p>
                <p>I said, “No. The State Department thinks he . . .”</p>
                <p>“What a character!”</p>
                <p>I said, “What do you mean?”</p>
                <p>“He's a big talker.” I think he used some Brazilian words that would mean about
                    the same what we would say.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>I said, “Oh, my gosh.”</p>
                <p>He said, “You got to be careful of that guy.”</p>
                <p>So he established himself up in Recife, and immediately he pushed everybody aside
                    and worked closely with Furtado, and they created a big plan of how to develop
                    this entire area in the northern part of Brazil. I said to Furtado, “Now, look.
                    Before you go up there, find out something about it.” This was not my idea,
                    because one of our AID men said, “You know, that's a tropical jungle. They
                    better find out something before they start building cities and roads and all
                    that.”</p>
                <p>This is the attitude, you see. They had a diagram, actually, with a center and
                    housing all over, hospitals, roads, and so forth, and pure, you know, Thomas
                    Moore utopia. It was all laid out. But Furtado said, “Well, I've already
                    committed myself. I made an announcement on it, so we're going to do it.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, you make the announcement, but have somebody go and take a look
                    there. I'll lend you a couple of our guys who know Brazil and know something
                    about the place.” And surreptitiously, we included a man from United Fruit, but
                    we wouldn't tell anybody he was from United Fruit because that would damn the
                    whole project.</p>
                <p>He finally consented that they go up, but he would not withdraw the program. So
                    they went up, and they came back. “The place is just absolutely dismal, because
                    it's got all kinds of refugees up there who went out there on their own. And as
                    far as getting any wood out of it, it's all teak and it sinks in the river. You
                    can't even get it out.”</p>
                <p>So what could you do? He and Luzzato sat down and signed five agreements,
                    selected money for health, education. I said to him, “What are you doing with
                    these agreements? I mean, they're just agreements; they're paper.”</p>
                <p>“Well, this is what we got to do.”</p>
                <p>I said, “This is not the way. You can't just build. You have to start off with
                    training people and getting yourself people who'll go in business and so forth.
                    You're just feeding them.”</p>
                <p>Well, I couldn't do very much. I explained this all to Lincoln Gordon, who,
                    incidentally, he and I became great friends. When he first came down, he was
                    cross-examining me, to see if I was a fit person for the job, but, you know, he
                    did it politely. He first met me at a conference of mission directors and
                    ambassadors in Lima, Peru, and I went up there representing Brazil. He, of
                    course, was on the way to Brazil to take on the job, he stopped off there first.
                    And that's where I made my remark to the famous Murrow, who was head of
                    USIS.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Edward R. Murrow.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Edward R. Murrow. And they sat the mission directors with the
                    ambassadors, which was a big mistake, because every time the board up there,
                    with Murrow and assistant secretaries and so forth, said something, a mission
                    director would say, “Hey.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The mission director would speak up, is that correct?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, it happened when I was bold enough to make the remark, “You know,
                    the Pope had issued an encyclical on the subject of help and development. Why
                    didn't we respond to it?” I forget what it was. It had to do with helping the
                    less- developed countries. And I said, “Our USIS didn't do a darn thing
                    about.</p>
                <p>There was shock all over the place, you see. Finally, Mr. Murrow addressed me,
                    and he said, “Our President doesn't want to get into the position of seeming to
                    deal with the Vatican.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, Lincoln Gordon came up to me and said, “Why did you do that?”</p>
                <p>I said, “You know, our USIS fellow thinks there's communists under every bench
                    around this place.” His name is Allejandro. He was a typical, you know, public
                    relations man, and that was the pitch—there are communists all over the
                    place.</p>
                <p>Well, we really didn't get very far in doing anything, except we had a very good
                    system in Sao Paulo, a business school. We did a great deal in public safety.
                    There's no question about that. The whole thing was, really, transferring wealth
                    into the area in one form or another—food, etcetera. They had an agriculture
                    which could not even support a poultry industry. We said, “You know, it's easy.
                    You know, a little farm.” “But where are we going to get the seed?” They would
                    have to import the seed!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To feed the poultry?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. And that's a big business. I mean, they had no Purina, or whatever
                    we call it, where you could go and buy the bags full.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: May I ask you at this point, you were the minister
                        consular for economic affairs, as well as the AID mission director,
                        correct?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. Really, at that time, they called me minister. They changed that
                    later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you also were responsible for the economic reporting of
                        the embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Right. That situation was pretty depressing, anyway. There was a man from
                    the treasury there, and he was the real man, Herb May. We had a commercial
                    attach� and we had an economic man from the State Department. Herb May
                    maintained the relationship. Our commercial man was afraid to take American
                    businessmen to the commercial office of the Brazilians, because “we don't do
                    that sort of thing.”</p>
                <p>The other fellow would clip the newspapers, and because of his wife's condition,
                    would take all Friday off to go to the commissary to stock up their apartment
                    with food. I mean, there was nothing there that amounted to anything except Herb
                    May, who was a brilliant economist and knew his stuff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the treasury representative?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes, that's right. And he'd draw up a plan, like everybody else, which
                    would require $2 billion, and “this is the way you do it.” It served its purpose
                    without any question. The special relationship with Brazil goes back to World
                    War II. They fought with us in Italy. It's true we supplied them, we trained
                    them, we gave them everything to do it in, but this was very close and we wanted
                    to continue it.</p>
                <p>And it was a democracy. We were afraid communists would take over the office when
                    Goulart came in, and they fired him and the military came in. Quadros quit
                    because of his weird nature. He quit on the assumption that they would
                    immediately call him back and say “Come back,” the way he did in the state of
                    Sao Paulo when he got mad and quit, and then they put him right back in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So he thought he could do that as president?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. It didn't work. It was a sad case, he had close relations with the
                    spirits. The cartoon was of a table under which he was with his hand up, getting
                    a whiskey bottle.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>There was a definite prejudice against outsiders, foreigners. They had a pamphlet
                    out which said, “Every time you press a button in your house, you are paying
                    five cents to a foreign utility company.” You press a button, you're paying for
                    oil. You press a button, you're paying for this. And they used to call their
                    very competent and highly praised ambassador, Roberto Campus—Bobby
                    Fields—English for Roberto Campus.</p>
                <p>We were not making any great progress except to placate them in some fashion or
                    another. As an agricultural country, it was primitive. They had coffee, and that
                    was growing wild. And they were spreading it all over the southern part of
                    Brazil and they were making fortunes on it, but nothing as far as the
                    development of agriculture, as such.</p>
                <p>The Kennedy Administration came in with land reform, and it never got started.
                    The areas where they had plantations working were not small, little plots. The
                    Germans down in southern Brazil knew how to run their show. They didn't need
                    land reform or anything like that. Well, getting back to Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you have left Brazil, and you've come back to
                        Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. I went to see Dillon and I said, “This is what happened.” He talked
                    to George Ball, and they sent me to Salvador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you became the DCM in Salvador. And the ambassador was
                        who?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Murat Williams.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Murat Williams, a career Foreign Service officer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He had had a very difficult situation there for two years. We went down
                    in 1963.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It says '62.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He was there for two years with the declaration of the Alliance for
                    Progress, which created an absolute panic situation in Salvador. The so-called
                    14 families—oh, I see what the trouble is here. The appointment date is '62.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you went in '63?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>SACCIO: In January of '63. I remember we spent New Year's Day en route, and we
                    drove down.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Drove the whole way?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. We were warned about getting through the gap there, but I wasn't
                    going to fly. Not that I was afraid of flying, but we wanted to see the country
                    and we visited my daughter's husband's family living in Arkansas on the way
                    down— her husband's family, because she was then living in Washington; we left
                    her. We drove all the way down—Mexico and so forth—and the famous gap, which is
                    a very dangerous thing to drive, because it's just a canyon going right through,
                    with little crosses on the roadside where the deceased workmen were buried.</p>
                <p>We got down to Guatemala and stayed with Jack Bell, who was the ambassador there,
                    and went on to Murat Williams and worked for him. But he had gone through the
                    whole period of the initiation of the Alliance for Progress.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Murat Williams.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Which was highly advertised as a land reform operation, and, you know,
                    getting down to the level of distributing the wealth evenly. And the 14 families
                    who owned the coffee plantations and the rice and whatever else they grew, they
                    were afraid that the communists would take over. There was no joke about
                    this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To them, this meant communism would take over?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Oh, no question about it. And, of course, there was an element of
                    leftists, without any question, whether they were Marxists or what have you. The
                    university was just full of it. When I got there, things had calmed down
                    considerably as far as I could see, and we were working with a new president,
                    Julio Rivera. He was a big stocky guy, about six foot, and of Indian extraction.
                    Obviously, there was white blood in him, a mestizo. But he was enormous and big
                    and the smartest, nicest guy you could work with, and he was absolutely in love
                    with Jack Kennedy.</p>
                <p>Jack came down and met all the Central American presidents in Costa Rica. He
                    invited them all there and they talked, and they came out with stars in their
                    eyes. And we worked with Rivera, and the program there was the usual program.
                    Herder was the mission director. He had gone to Salvador.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bob Herder, the man who had been with you in Brazil.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: It was something. We just drove down arriving in the evening. We drove
                    around looking for a place to get information. We drove up to a house, knocked
                    on the door, and there was Bob Herder and his wife. They were expecting us, but
                    we hadn't known how to get there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you just happened to...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Hit the place just luckily. But at any rate, the program was a good one,
                    a decent one, and we were making a heck of a lot of progress in developing
                    industry. At that point, they were working on the plan of a Central American
                    common market, not so much market, but in which the five nations in Central
                    America would work together and allocate various industries or functions or
                    services, one or the other, so they would be working as an economic group, just
                    like the Andean operation in South America, which would have connected
                    Venezuela, Colombia, Ecuador, Chile, and Peru. The whole idea of trying to have
                    it just like Western Europe.</p>
                <p>There were no great disturbances. There was constant, at least public, arguments
                    with the leftist students, but they were kept in rein. There was no terrorist
                    activities on either side. They were allowed to speak, and they did. And the
                    high point of this was that the candidate for president to follow Rivera had a
                    debate with the top man of the student organization, and he beat the pants off
                    him on the radio. He was able to actually show how silly this guy was and all
                    the things that he was saying about the economy and what he had done. The
                    justification was that it was a poor country. There's no question about that.
                    This is the whole situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did Rivera relate to the 14 families?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He was not related to them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I didn't mean it in related, but how did he get along
                        with them. What was his relationship with the 14 families?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, the relationship was the law and order factor that he maintained.
                    It wasn't a terrorist or CIA type. It was that there would be law and order, and
                    nobody was going to take any land from anybody. They resolved that fairly
                    quickly. I don't think they ever really got to a point for the simple reason
                    that the nature of the land would not lend itself to that sort of thing. It was
                    rocky and it gone through various ups and downs because it was a one-crop
                    operation.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>In the middle of the 19th century, the one crop was indigo, and they were
                    developing it for the dye that the Prussians needed for their uniforms. Now,
                    when the Prussians stopped using and when they invented chemical dyes, they
                    didn't have that resource anymore, and the top people in Salvador were the ones
                    who introduced coffee and made a go of it.</p>
                <p>As a people, the Salvadorans are hard workers. They're noted for being the
                    hardest workers and the best workers in the building of the Panama Canal. Many
                    of them went down. And, you know, this business of Asians going to Kuwait and
                    the immigration isn't new, because that went on, as you know, in history all the
                    time. Where the jobs are, people go. Whether you have immigration laws or not,
                    they get there.</p>
                <p>But it was sad, because you'd go out to these villages and they weren't starving,
                    but they certainly weren't . . . One of the great things that Churchill and I
                    experienced—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Churchill, that's Mrs. Saccio.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: We went to a little village where there was a Peace Corps girl 65 years
                    of age. I don't know what her background was, if it was a teacher or
                    something...and she had a little section of a house—very simple, a cot and a
                    water well—and we said, “What do you do here?”</p>
                <p>“Well, I work with the town. We're trying to get things going.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, what are we doing?”</p>
                <p>“Well, for one thing, we got them a water supply.”</p>
                <p>“A water supply? You mean they didn't have a water supply?”</p>
                <p>“Well, there was a little trickle of a stream coming out of a rock on the main
                    road into this town, and they would go and fill their pails. But,” she said,
                    “that's ridiculous, carrying all this, and when water isn't there, you just
                    don't have any water.”</p>
                <p>So she got the engineers out of a Salvadoran ministry, told them to come up with
                    a design to build a little cubicle dam right there. On one side, showers for
                    men; on the other side, showers for ladies, where to get your water and so
                    forth, and this is kind of problem. It so demonstrated how difficult it is when
                    you don't have—I've been reading the history of the American Indian, and this is
                    the problem. The technology is so little and their natural resources are so
                    minimal, that you really . . . I mean, in Asia, you'll build bridges and you'll
                    have rice and so forth, but a place like Salvador, the biggest project the
                    Salvadorans said he wanted to put into effect was a tree farm up in the
                    northeastern part of the town.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who, the president?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No, no. This was a Salvadoran technician. He said, “This is where they
                    used to grow their indigo, and it's no longer possible. We'll have a tree
                    farm.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Do you understand what that means? How long? I mean, I don't know
                    anything to speak of, but this is a major long- term operation.”</p>
                <p>Now, in this same town where we saw this Peace Corps lady, we walked around the
                    town and Churchill mounted a donkey. But we went out in the country on
                    donkeyback, and we did this on the suggestion of our Peace Corps lady. “You
                    think this place is poor, just go up there.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you, as the deputy chief of mission, got on a donkey
                        to go up there? [Laughter] That's good.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: The crazy thing I did was when there was a fire with the circus down in
                    Miteroi, across the bay from Rio, we sent down a lot of medicines, and I was
                    stupid enough to get into the helicopter to fly it over. My State Department
                    guys thought I was . . . “Well,” I said, “they need this medicine? Of course,
                    they need it. But how do you advertise that we're giving it to them? We'll fly
                    and get our pictures in the papers.”</p>
                <p>Salvador was really great, and it was being managed well, considering that the
                    army was in control, the country police were in control. But there was no
                    fighting, no bombs, no terrorists, nothing like that. And this candidate that I
                    told you beat the student leader in the debate, he became president and carried
                    on, but what happened after that, I don't know. I mean, really that was the
                    golden age of Salvador, those two and a half years we were there. It was really
                    very good, and it was a decent program, well run.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately, that common market idea, well, the whole roadway from the airport
                    to the center of the city was just crowded with people who would come in with
                    little plants, cigarette makers, and things of this kind, which was fine. But
                    before you knew it, they had two refineries in Central America, where they only
                    needed one. It's very difficult.</p>
                <p>And these five countries are so different from the other. Guatemala is 60 percent
                    Indian—real Indian, not just mestizos. Costa Rica is European, very little
                    mixture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, in Rio, you'd been minister and you had
                        responsibility for the economic. Now in Salvador, you're DCM, so you've got
                        responsibility—or did you—for the political and economic, as well as for the
                        whole operation.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>SACCIO: Oh, yes. I was just the deputy to the ambassador, that's all. I ran it
                    for a good number of times because he was away.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were the charg� when he was gone.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you enjoy that, being the charg�? That was your
                        first.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Oh, well, fine. We had a good political officer. We had an excellent CIA
                    man, who was a human being, who understood the problems and kept me advised and
                    contacts with the old-time politicians, not the army, but the old-time—Osorio
                    and people of that kind.</p>
                <p>You know, the W.R. Grace Company became ITT. It was just absolutely disgraceful
                    in the way they kept the port on the Pacific. The pier was rusty and they were
                    still using the tide as a source of power, and the piers were rotted. And when I
                    saw the representative of the Grace Company, I told him. I said, “Instead of
                    getting out—(which they were doing. They were sick and tired of being in Latin
                    America; they were pulling everything out)—why don't you do something over there
                    that means something?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No way.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No. I don't know how long they had been in Latin America—years and years.
                    It was an old fruit transport company. They were mostly fruit traders and
                    freighters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now, how did you find the, they say, career Foreign
                        Service officers? Did they accept you as DCM? Did you find any problems
                        dealing with them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Oh, there was a problem. Do you remember Roy Kohler?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>SACCIO: I forget on what occasion it was, but I was up in Washington, and they
                    were having a get-together of the Foreign Service officers. And I walked in
                    there and I put out my hand to say hello to Roy, because I had worked with him
                    as the representative of the AID program in the Secretary's staff meeting every
                    week and Roy was a chief political officer. He was top man, I guess, for Europe.
                    He snubbed me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because you weren't an FSO?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I was already, but he was taking it out on me. The career officers' last
                    defense against political appointees is the assignment of DCMs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, by that time you had become an FSO?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Oh, yes. I said, “What the hell is the matter with this guy?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then after Salvador, you went to Argentina?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. Well, in Salvador, when Murat Williams left, because he was anxious
                    to become the ambassador to Israel. This was his great desire.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Israel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. He was fascinated with the kibbutz and he wanted to go back. He had
                    seen it and how it worked and so forth. And they said, “We'll make you a career
                    minister.” He said, “You can do anything you want, but I want to go there.” So
                    he resigned from the Foreign Service. I knew of his great interest in Israel,
                    and he kept saying...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Later he probably would have become ambassador to Israel.
                        He was a first-rate ambassador, I thought, Murat Williams.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's one thing unusual about that mission that I want
                        to put on the tape. In the succession in a mission, it's usually the DCM
                        becomes the charg�, and then if the ambassador and the charg� are out of
                        town, then the head of the political section. In Salvador, Murat Williams—I
                        don't know whether you had anything to do with this—wanted a different
                        succession. He wanted the AID director to be charg� in case you and he were
                        out of town, and Ed Martin approved it. It was the only time it was ever
                        done. So Bob Herder would become charg� in case you and the ambassador were
                        out of town.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, I can understand that, because Murat didn't like the political
                    officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: The prime example of his beef about him, I think, our famous vice
                    president, the man from Minnesota.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, Hubert Humphrey.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Humphrey came down, and the congress of Salvador invited him to speak to
                    them, and Humphrey went off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He loved it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: And this fellow—whose name I don't remember— said three words for 15
                    sentences spoken by the Vice President. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The political officer was doing the translating?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. The only man we had. He was a jumpy guy, and he had good contacts
                    and so forth, but he and Murat never . . . that's why. And Herder always worked
                    very closely with the ambassador. Herder was the salt of the earth, and just
                    between you and me, he made fun of Murat, who was, you know, the Ivy college,
                    the Virginian counterpart of the good families and all that. But they worked
                    very close together. Now I'm reminded of that. I didn't realize. Well, this is
                    getting too lengthy.</p>
                <p>Before we continue chronologically, I'd like to cover the business of the CIA and
                    my experience with them, and it goes back to my being in Washington and in the
                    five posts. In Washington, it was, strictly speaking, with the Vientiane. John
                    Tobler was the AID director there. Do you remember him?</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I was on that around-the-world trip in which we did a good number of the
                    missions. Incidentally, we had President Truman's old plane, with the poker
                    table and all. The stop there was very disturbing, because John was very
                    concerned of the situation there, and his ambassador was very concerned. They
                    were working together and they felt that they had no say or that the CIA was
                    running the whole thing, and they didn't know what the hell was going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is in Vientiane, Laos, right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. He and the ambassador got together with me and Jack Bell. Jack Bell
                    was the State Department man on the trip. And we sat down in this dark little
                    room, and they let out their fears and concerns, and as far as they were
                    concerned, Laos was finished. There were very concerned. I think they felt that
                    the CIA was not really meeting the problems of the country or they felt that it
                    was more a secret operation than anything, without the ambassador or John, with
                    his AID program, knowing anything about it.</p>
                <p>They spilled their guts to us, and we realized, both Jack and I, that they were
                    in a state of almost panic. And we said, almost simultaneously, “Now, look here.
                    We're going to save this country, and we're going all the way. Don't assume that
                    we're getting out of here.” And Jack, as the policy man, you know, laid it on.
                    And we left the room, shook our heads, and said, “My gosh. These fellows are
                    absolutely scared.”</p>
                <p>When I got back to Washington, I told the CIA, “You're not paying any attention
                    to the ambassador or the AID director.” They sent their top man over to my
                    office to brief me for a whole hour. They wanted to satisfy me, because I didn't
                    hesitate to say that there's something wrong there.</p>
                <p>I say that because I found as going through here, the six years in Washington and
                    then overseas, the State Department had created a situation where it used the
                    CIA and would not acknowledge it and denied that it knew anything—denied
                    publicly, of course—that it knew anything about what was going on, and this
                    happened time and time again in my service. I happened when the Chile thing
                    broke.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>I saw that Charlie, the assistant secretary, the Sears man—Charles Meyer—went
                    before a congressional committee and said he knew nothing about what was going
                    on. When Oliver came down when I was in Argentina, first of all I had to
                    convince him to come down to Argentina, because he was reviewing a couple of
                    other countries and they said, “Why are you skipping Argentina? I mean, this is
                    an important country.” And he finally consented to come down.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is Covey Oliver, then assistant secretary for Inter-
                        American affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I was the charg� and took him around. We talked to the foreign ministry,
                    and Herb Thompson did the notes, and it was very good. And in the car, he
                    obviously was interviewing me, and he asked me what kind of an ambassador would
                    I be. Would I want to know what the CIA is doing, or are you like— who is that
                    slick ambassador we had in Brazil for a while with the two dogs? He had
                    plastered hair, very neatly European in his dress, and all that. He was
                    kidnapped, wasn't he, at one point?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I can't remember his name. You're not talking about Rob
                        McClintock?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No, no. He certainly and coolly outsmarted his kidnappers. At any rate,
                    when he was briefed to go down to Brazil, they asked him whether he wanted to
                    know what this CIA was doing. He said, “Absolutely not. I don't want to know
                    anything about it. You can tell my DCM, but not me. I don't want anything to do
                    about it.” And Covey put that question to me. He said, “Would you?”</p>
                <p>I said, “For Christmas sake. I would lie for my country just as well as anybody
                    else. You mean to say I'm not going to know what these guys are doing, with my
                    experience with this fellow I had in Argentina? Who is running the goddamn
                    embassy?” And the fellow in Colombia, when I finally got there, my god, my
                    political officer would go to him and ask him to get some information for
                    him.</p>
                <p>The State Department allowed itself to become a tool of the CIA, because they
                    relied on it to do this, do that, and Kennedy was one of the greatest violators
                    of that if there ever was. With his counterinsurgency program—this is Bobby
                    Kennedy—and the whole idea that the CIA was an instrument, as if he were
                    fighting in the street fights of New York or in Boston. It was incredible.</p>
                <p>And when I came back once, I said, “My CIA man is spreading stories about the
                    fellow who is candidate to become the president of the Latin American
                    Organization.” It was some prominent Latin American who was not very happy with
                    the United States. The CIA man was spreading stories about his weaknesses or
                    whatever, misinformation or something, so I said, “Jack”—this is Jack Crimmins,
                    isn't it?</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, John Crimmins.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He worked with Charlie Meyer on Cuba. I said, “What is this guy going
                    around telling these stories for?”</p>
                <p>He said, “We told him to.”</p>
                <p>I said, “For Christ's sake, Jack,” and I walked out of the office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They told him to, but then he didn't let you or the
                        ambassador know that he told the CIA man what to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's terrible.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, I had my problems with this guy, who had been there for four or
                    five years with a number of ambassadors and he was running the show. Stevenson
                    was my deputy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is now in Colombia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. He came in. You know, we had the adjoining offices. I've forgotten
                    this CIA man's name. He said, “He's brought in somebody to help settle this
                    strike.”</p>
                <p>I said, “What strike?”</p>
                <p>“Well, there's a strike out there, and he's brought in a man to help it,
                    apparently as least disturbing as he possibly can be.”</p>
                <p>And I said, “What!” So I went back to my office and called my secretary, “Tell So
                    and So to come on down here.” And I said, “You brought in somebody to work on
                    this strike?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Yeah.”</p>
                <p>“Who the hell gave you authority to do this?”</p>
                <p>“Well, I mean, this is, you know, anti-communism and so forth.”</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>I said, “The next time you do it, you're going to get out of here. You dare do
                    anything like that again, you're out.” And I wrote one of those messages, “Eyes
                    Only,” and bypassed him, which is a joke, because the guy up in the...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Works for the CIA.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No. He was from the National Security, but he came and told me, because
                    he didn't like him, either. [Laughter] It was a joke.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some of those station chiefs have more authority than the
                        ambassador.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Tasca was a famous example.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're talking about the CIA.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Do you remember Tasca's first name?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Henry.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Henry Tasca. He was made ambassador to Greece during the—I think they
                    call them “the colonels” who are in charge—and he was there for some time, a
                    couple of years, perhaps three. At one point, the station chief gave a reception
                    of one kind or another, and he invited all the people he knew. And everybody who
                    was anybody—the military, everybody that was important—came, and Henry was so
                    embarrassed that he walked out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. Well, this I read, but it happens to be exactly the experience I had
                    with our station chief in Colombia. He had a party and he had a magnificent
                    residence. There was no question about it. They were all, as in Latin America,
                    small villas in the city, of course, walls and beautiful large, expensive
                    entertainment rooms, the dining room or the assembly room of one kind. And, by
                    gosh, they were all there, all the people that he had on the payroll.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>His payroll may not have been very expensive, but it was a precious thing because
                    he would get anything that these people wanted into the country for them in the
                    way of books, newspapers. Not silly things, the things a writer would want or a
                    newspaperman would want. And there was one fellow who was a maniac about
                    collecting books. In fact, his whole house was an empty shell of three stories
                    lined with shelves of books of every kind, and he would boast, “Name me a book,
                    and I have it.” And everybody would try it on him, and he'd have it.</p>
                <p>Our station chief was able to do all these things. They knew where to go when
                    they wanted something or help. Now, this was not necessarily nefarious, but it
                    was beyond the control of the embassy or the State Department or anybody like
                    that, because it would be a situation of non-accountability. The only person he
                    was accountable to is back home in the CIA. If he did something wrong, well,
                    they'd take care of it themselves.</p>
                <p>But the situation there in Colombia, in Argentina, was the same. We had one guy
                    who was actually brought up in Vietnam as an officer, working there. He had this
                    entire perspective of working against the leftist, the communists, or what have
                    you, and he brought it to Argentina. He was looking for things all over the
                    place.</p>
                <p>One of the things he did was to try to put the foreign minister on the payroll in
                    Argentina. He went to see him and said, “You know who I am? I'm very much
                    interested in what you do. And if there's any help you need or anything you
                    need...” And the foreign minister told the ambassador, Ed Martin. This foreign
                    minister was the type, you know, the old families, maybe not necessarily
                    terribly wealthy, but well off, and he was very much interested in foreign
                    affairs. He was a partial paralytic and had to use canes, just like FDR; he was
                    a proud man.</p>
                <p>Then they tried to buy the one famous columnist they had, who would you say was
                    on the same level of Walter Lippmann in the United States. They wanted to work
                    with him.</p>
                <p>Anytime you ask them, “Now, where do you get this report? What's your basis?”</p>
                <p>“We have it. We have it.”</p>
                <p>And I said, “Now, look. I just can't believe this in one instance. You have a man
                    who got this information from a reliable source. Bring him in; I'd like to talk
                    to him.”</p>
                <p>He brought him in. He was an American, and he looked like an ordinary fellow. He
                    didn't look like a tourist or anything like that. And I asked him to tell me.
                    Well, the story didn't come out exactly the same, but they had summarized it so
                    beautifully that it sounded like nice, clear information.</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>Now, when Dick Nixon came into office, the first thing he did, you will recall,
                    he wanted the Foreign Service, no matter from what department—State, Commerce—he
                    wanted cuts, and he put out an overall cut of 10 percent. And as far as the CIA,
                    I cut them down 25 percent.</p>
                <p>But my concern became, and always was, that we were working with these fellows
                    who just did not have the background of working with other governments on an
                    open diplomatic basis. They were all geared up on the business of terrorists,
                    secretive operations, conspiracies, and so forth. And they were using their
                    judgment, and whatever came from Washington, there was no question.</p>
                <p>And most of the Foreign Service, I learned, particularly the senior boys who had
                    been in the business for a time, decided they wouldn't have anything to do with
                    it, because they didn't want to get in the position where they would have to
                    say, “I did know about it, and it was justified.” No. “I did not know one
                    thing.”</p>
                <p>And I said so when I got back to Washington. I said, “The State Department is
                    just absolutely dependent on these fellows, and they shouldn't be. You could get
                    all this information they give you just as easy as the Times reporter would get
                    it. And you have a Times bureau chief in any of these countries. He has three or
                    four stringers with him and so forth. He could tell you just as much as these
                    guys can, outside of deep mysteries or conspiracies. But as far as the general
                    situation in a country is concerned, they were writing economic reports and they
                    were writing political reports, of course.</p>
                <p>Once I called the station chief in, who came after I had his predecessor moved.
                    Oh, I have to tell you that I fired him; I got him out of there. I said, “Why
                    are you sending in these reports on economic situations?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Those are my orders.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Let me see your orders.” He went back in the office and pulled out his
                    instructions. “We want you to report on all these things, everything.”</p>
                <p>I said, “For Christ's sake. You don't have to report on that. We'll take care of
                    that. What do you think we are here for?”</p>
                <p>He said, “I'm sorry. These are my orders.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, you just forget them, because we want our people to do their work
                    and not come to you and ask you questions,” which they were doing before.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>It was a sorry business, and I didn't mind telling anybody in Washington, because
                    when I had this fellow removed, he had been there for quite a long time.
                    Obviously, everybody was close to him, including the Colombians, our people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I ran into him once when I was there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Did Christian Herter go back and become assistant secretary for
                    Inter-ocean Environmental?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Something like that, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: And he had a deputy who was ambassador to Peru, who was instructed to
                    make a critical speech by Washington. And, of course, he was kicked out by the
                    Peruvian government. They had to reassign him, so he became deputy to Chris.</p>
                <p>I told them that I wanted to see this matter cleared. I don't want this guy
                    running around, particularly since there was an election coming up. It's a
                    perfectly good election. If the Liberals win or the Conservatives win, it will
                    make no difference. It's just the same people. They're nice on one side, nice on
                    the other, and they have their faults.</p>
                <p>Allen Dulles made a big joke of that. When he was station chief in Geneva, he
                    advertised that he was with the CIA because he wanted to have people come talk
                    to him. [Laughter] That's what he said. They all knew.</p>
                <p>Well, so much for the CIA, because I felt that it corrupted our policy. I mean,
                    what happened in Chile, what happened in Guatemala, I didn't have any direct
                    part in it because I wasn't there. But it was obvious that any amount of leftist
                    indication of anybody was suspect. And the only case I know where an ambassador
                    overruled this attitude was our good friend who was ambassador Portugal. He
                    became director of the CIA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, Frank Carlucci. Well, Frank's a very able guy. He is a
                        tough guy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: When they overthrew the dictator there, and the democratic parties were
                    fighting among themselves as to what to do, Washington became concerned that the
                    Socialists would take over. And he just raised holy hell, “What's wrong with the
                    Socialists? I mean, they're all Socialists here.” Do you know Carlucci?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I don't. I just know that he's a very able person, one
                        of the best we've ever had.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>SACCIO: When Bob Stevenson left and went to Washington, I got a fellow by the
                    name of Allen—I can't remember. At any rate, he was an old Latin American hand
                    who had been shoveling around and nobody would give him an advancement. And when
                    they asked me who I wanted for DCM, they offered me him, and I didn't know
                    anything about him. And I just asked, and I got the usual State Department
                    statement, you know, “Good man. He has experience,” and so forth. He was
                    suffering from eye trouble, but he was getting over that, so he came down.</p>
                <p>He made a mess of the operation. They didn't tell me fairly that he was not,
                    because from my private experience in business, I found that interviewing people
                    was really, as far as I was concerned, not very effective. You just got to know
                    the guy, and you never could get an answer clearly from anybody that he was no
                    good or what. They wouldn't say anything like that. He said, “He's a fairly good
                    guy.” You have to learn how to interpret that, but being new on stateside, I
                    took it, and he was incredible. I asked him to be removed, and I asked for Frank
                    Carlucci, and they laughed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were smart. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: They laughed. I said, “Yeah, I've seen him up in Brazil where he was
                    assistant to the ambassador,” so it was just temporarily. Well, I made a short
                    trip to Brazil at one point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You could see that he was very able; a very good guy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: But he was a Foreign Service officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. He's a career Foreign Service officer—was until
                        he became Secretary of Defense.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I don't know that there's much to say different as far as the operation
                    of embassies in any of these places. India was, here again, a sad matter,
                    because they appointed Senator Keating. He was senator and he was the man who
                    claimed that he had the pictures of the missiles in Cuba, and then he ran as
                    chief justice of New York Court of Appeals. Of course, he claimed he got more
                    votes than anybody else in any office that ever ran in New York state, because
                    he was the only one running. And, of course, they had to vote for him, no matter
                    whether they voted for the Democrat or the Republican.</p>
                <p>I don't know why they sent him to India, except that you had Nixon there who gave
                    him that job. Let me see, I got to Delhi, India in '69 or '70. No, who would
                    have sent him there? I was appointed to Colombia in Nixon's Administration.
                    Wasn't he elected in '68?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, they sent Keating to India, and he had no know-how or understanding
                    of India. He was following Bowles, who was very close and sympathetic and
                    empathetic of the whole Indian operation, and his wife went around in saris and
                    sandals and rode around on bicycles And when Keating came in, he said, “I want
                    you people to get dressed as Americans. None of this stuff; no sandals. And I
                    don't like beards.” Some of our AID people . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you had that nice AID building by the time you got
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Right next door. And we had enough trouble with that, because everything
                    had to be secure about the embassy. But people who wanted to come to see me as
                    the AID director, they would go into the AID building without any trouble. The
                    man in charge of security would shake his head, “How did this guy get in? You
                    keep controls with the embassy.” But they were joined, you see. What could we
                    do? You could go down the basement and come up from the other side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, we had that underground passage.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: But he was a sad case for an ambassador if he was to have any influence.
                    But aside from that, our policy was pretty poor stuff, because we never made up
                    our mind whether we were going to be with Pakistan to support their prejudices
                    against India and building up their armaments, or be on the Indian side, or be
                    on both sides, or try not to be involved, and Mrs. Gandhi was against the
                    Americans, anyway, just culturally. She was brought up in London School of
                    Economics, and palsy-walsy with the Russians and had a whole combination of
                    military assistance and plants and all that kind. There was no way that Keating
                    responded to any of that, because he didn't know, and he wasn't helped by
                    Washington in any way. Anytime we sent something to Pakistan, we had a
                    crisis.</p>
                <p>When Churchill and I first got there in 1969, we were invited by the minister,
                    who was my counterpart on the economic side. His daughter was getting married,
                    and they had these cottages, as you well know, with the gardens all around. I
                    think it was the first day we were there, the second evening. We went there
                    dressed up to the garden, and there was Mrs. Gandhi seated on one of those awful
                    stuffed chairs that they have in all these Latin American or less-developed
                    places. I don't know why.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, a symbol of affluence.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. Nothing clean, no nice stuff. Just big, fat furniture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which, in that climate, is the worst thing; it's so hot.
                        The big stuffed, served you out in the garden.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. And rugs on the lawn. And we passed the reception line, the bride
                    and groom. The minister took us and introduced us to Mrs. Gandhi, and she smiled
                    and he left. Apparently, people were doing that. They were going first to the
                    reception line and stopping and chatting with her. And we were all alone at that
                    point, nobody with us, and she wanted to know who we were.</p>
                <p>And I said, “I'm the new minister in charge of the AID program.” She froze,
                    looked the other way, and there we stood, both of us. We didn't know what the
                    hell to do. We were saved, but not too soon, by somebody coming along. We sat
                    down in front of her, not knowing what to do, and then somebody came along, and
                    we decided to move on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why do you think she acted quite like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Because she was definitely against the U.S.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Against the U.S. or against the AID program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Against the U.S. and the AID program. She didn't mind the money. She
                    didn't refuse our aid. She didn't refuse the food. It was on the aftermath of
                    President Johnson putting the screws on India in one of the successive monsoon
                    failures in which he laid down the law, “You either do something about your
                    agriculture, or we're not giving you any food.”</p>
                <p>There were freighters coming in every day in the ports of Calcutta and Bombay
                    with food, and he imposed this on them. Obviously, he had to do it, because he
                    was talking to the head of the state. And the stuff came in. PL 480 poured in
                    and created the billions of rupees and the funds that nobody knew what to do
                    with, because all we needed was $50,000 to take care of the embassy needs at
                    that point.</p>
                <p>There was still a grudge, except there were some knowledgeable Indians who said
                    “President Johnson did the right thing. Now we have a growing agriculture. We're
                    doing rice, we're doing this, we're doing that, and we're doing malaria.” But
                    she was against us, just like any Latin American leftist would be, prejudiced
                    against the capitalist nation. Because she was brought up as a socialist,
                    educationally, as well, and that was it.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>Well, the aftermath of that was that I told the people in the embassy, “We know
                    that; we expected that.” Nobody warned me about it. Why would they warn me? They
                    didn't know we were going to the reception or I didn't ask.</p>
                <p>The man who they put as my counterpart was the top-level civil service. You know,
                    they talk about the steel structure. He was very close to Mrs. Gandhi; a great
                    economist. One of the better Indians who didn't go into politics for money. He
                    eventually moved over to the United Nations and became one of their officers.
                    Either that or the Bank. I think it was probably the World Bank.</p>
                <p>I would sit down and review the week with him, and we'd describe what's going on,
                    what had to be done, running through all the programs. And he appointed a
                    secondary man from his office and said that, on the day-to-day matters, you can
                    work with one of his aides, which I understood perfectly. He had other things to
                    do. And we worked on the population program all up and down, and some of the
                    boys in the embassy said—oh, Funari, who became my deputy, was there when we
                    arrived. He told the Indian native help in an assembly hall, introducing me as
                    the new director, he said, “His name is Saccio, my name is Funari, but you're
                    not going to have spaghetti every day.” They laughed. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>He told me that Mrs. Gandhi had a secretarial aide who took notes on every
                    meeting and was her calendar scheduler. He identified the man so I knew what he
                    looked like, so when the AID director, the former head of Michigan State...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hannah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: John Hannah came on a visit. We made a call on Mrs. Gandhi with the
                    ambassador, and they sat right in front of her and I sat on the side. I was
                    supposed to go with them. And she talked, and she turned around to me and
                    smiled. Oh, there goes my good friend; he must have said something. [Laughter]
                    Because, you know, we were working entirely on a non- political basis.</p>
                <p>There were two crises. One, Keating's alarm clock did not work, so he didn't get
                    to the airport to see her off to the United States. He blamed his Foreign
                    Service officer, who was a gal, who was his immediate aide, and who he tried to
                    screw at any chance. You know, he was 79 or something, but he wanted his women,
                    just like Gandhi, as a matter of fact. And he blamed her, you see, because she
                    had not awakened him or something, as if she were living with him, which, of
                    course, was not so. She hated him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he living then in Roosevelt House, in the main
                        residence, or was he where Bowles used to live?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>SACCIO: Not where Bowles used to live, because he was in the mansion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, that's right, because he wouldn't do that. I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: The other small crisis came when she made a speech down in the southern
                    part of India and “all these Peace Corps people and all the CIA spies” and all
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She said that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: In a speech.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, my lord.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: And Keating was unable to handle it, because, being brought up the way he
                    was, he would not even admit there were CIA people in the country. In a staff
                    meeting, he asked the CIA guy, or anybody else who was in there, “What do I say
                    if they say we have CIA?” And there was dumb silence, even from the station
                    chief. He was adrift, you see. Nobody had briefed him, and he didn't have sense
                    enough to realize everybody knows that we have agents all over the place. But in
                    those days, you would cover here, cover there. It was a lot of nonsense. But any
                    rate, he had a real rough time.</p>
                <p>But the program was a good one, but an almost impossible one, because back in
                    1920, the population was 150 million. When we were there, it was 500 million,
                    and it is now 850 million. The international conference just the other day of
                    aid-giving people, the industrialist stated, “The developed countries ought to
                    do something about this. Give aid to the less-developed countries.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the field of population, is that correct?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No, everything. But the whole point was, they said in that—whether
                    explicitly or otherwise—they said the population is just taking over. When you
                    have a situation like in Indonesia, India, China, what have you, the Chinese do
                    something about it. The Indians try to do something, and one of the reasons Mrs.
                    Gandhi was considered a tyrant was because she went around with vasectomies and
                    all that all over the place and was very brutal, at least according to critics,
                    of pushing people out of Bombay and out of Calcutta. It was, “Get back in the
                    country- side.”</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>They wanted to build an atomic bomb and nuclear capability, and they wouldn't
                    take any advice or guidance of the United States. And when they opened their
                    first atomic nuclear plant outside of Bombay, the ambassador wasn't even
                    invited. I mean, this was a national operation and the Diplomatic Corps was all
                    invited, and we had helped with some of the materials and so forth. And Stone,
                    who was the DCM—what was his name, Galen Stone?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Galen.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Galen Stone moved heaven and earth and said, “He should be up on the
                    platform, not sitting on the first row or the second row of the audience.” So it
                    was an impossible case of nobody liking anybody, and only the people at the
                    technical level, let us say, had contacts that meant anything, some of the
                    political officers and so forth.</p>
                <p>The CIA would never open its mouth in a meeting. The guy would sit there and
                    listen to us. Once I burst out, and Galen Stone said, “Keep quiet, Len. Keep
                    quiet.” I said, “What the hell are you fellows sitting in here listening to us,
                    and you won't say a damn word or what's going on? I mean, why the hell are you
                    here, spying on us?” I told them so. When the ambassador was away, and I was in
                    charge, I made it quite clear in the open meeting. I said, “You got anything to
                    report on?”</p>
                <p>Well, we were doing some quite good work. But I tried to find out what projects
                    had been in operation in India over a period of years to see what had happened
                    when somebody was talking about a milking operation, a dairy operation. Going
                    back to Washington, it's impossible to get the archives.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really. There weren't good records right there in New
                        Delhi nor in Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: If there was, they said that it's too difficult to get at that sort of
                    stuff and dig it out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I think it's notorious that the institutional
                        memories of both State and AID are some of the worst in Washington—I mean,
                        the worst in the U.S. Government.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, there was no permanence of responsibility. They put out, four years
                    late, the book on diplomatic correspondence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And even that is badly censored. That isn't a good
                        record.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: It's criticized all over the place.</p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let me ask you one thing that I haven't brought up.
                        We've discussed your general opinions of working with the State Foreign
                        Service, the AID Foreign Service, and the CIA. What about USIA? What's your
                        general feelings about USIA? You must have worked with them in all these
                        countries, of course.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, I can run down the line. In Brazil, Alessandro, a typical case. I
                    mean, there was counterinsurgency, communists all over the place, that sort of
                    thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The United States Information Agency?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. He was the head of the USIS. He would not find opportunities to put
                    ourselves forward. It was just this whole operation of fearing that the leftists
                    were taking over, and they bought it hook, line, and sinker. I mean, they didn't
                    make any distinction between what was said in Washington, public consumption,
                    and what they had to do at that level. I mean, there was nothing into that.</p>
                <p>A guy like Jack Crimmins would work on coffee and the economic part, on which he
                    did a terrific job. They had to get a coffee agreement of one kind or another,
                    and he had shipping inside and out. But nothing about the basic relationship
                    between the countries to make them better or understand why we were not being
                    accepted.</p>
                <p>Then, at one point—I think I told you about messing up on the Pope's encyclical,
                    and I raised that with Murrow at that Lima meeting. Well, he didn't take
                    advantage of it. What the Pope said was so much of what we were trying to do, at
                    least saying that we were trying to do it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you're dealing with a Catholic country, a Catholic
                        continent. This isn't India, where you've 14 different religions. You've got
                        one basic religion—Catholic.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: In Argentina, we had Jack Knight.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jack Knight. We're talking now the USIA in Argentina.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>SACCIO: Now, he had that position in Rome when Clare Boothe Luce was there, and
                    he said that Clare Boothe gave him a free-hand on public relations things. And
                    he worked on it, and he expected that I had nothing to say about what he was
                    doing. I mean, my idea of a DCM is not waiting for the ambassador to tell me
                    something or I'm supposed to be the administrative officer at the top of the
                    whole thing to see that people work very closely related to the substance, not
                    just how many reports you have.</p>
                <p>At one point, Washington wanted a report on the progress of the Alliance for
                    Progress. He wrote a long—it wasn't a telegram; it was a letter. They had two
                    types at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: An airgram.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: It ran three or four pages, all the Argentines were doing under the
                    Alliance for Progress. And I said to him, “Where do you get all this stuff? They
                    were doing this anyway. What does it got to do with the Alliance?”</p>
                <p>“Oh, well. It shows that they are progressing.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, you don't say so here. This is the great work of the American AID
                    program here.”</p>
                <p>And I called up the AID director, and I said, “You believe this stuff?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, I cleared it, but . . .”</p>
                <p>I said, “You're not going to send this stuff. It's a lot of public relations
                    stuff.”</p>
                <p>Well, Knight was that kind of a fellow. First he said, “Mrs. Luce let me do
                    anything I wanted. I'm a newspaperman:” and so forth. And there was nothing
                    there, except on the surface.</p>
                <p>The one thing that he and I did together which was worth something was when Ill�a
                    was kicked out and Ongan�a took over. The military took over practically
                    everything and put the clamps on the universities. And there was an American
                    professor in there, Ronald Zone, no relation to anybody in our government, and
                    he got kicked out. So we discovered where he was, in a hotel in the middle of
                    Buenos Aires, so we took it on ourselves to go down and talk to him. It showed
                    up on the front page of the New York Times. [Laughter] But we did a good job of
                    showing that we're not going to take any of this kicking around of people.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>In that connection, it's interesting that Ed Martin wanted to take a vacation,
                    and he asked all concerned—the CIA, the political officer, and me—whether this
                    was a good time to go away; maybe something would happen. And I said, “Well, do
                    you remember my interview with Alsogaray?” Alsogaray was a famous economist of
                    Argentina, and his brother was the chief of staff of the Argentine army, but the
                    second Alsogaray was not a military man. He was an economist, true and simple,
                    and at one point, he had been the economic minister, whether he was under
                    Frondizi or somebody else, and he put the country through a hard winter. You
                    know, the old thing of squeezing in order to get back to a sound currency. And
                    they hated him.</p>
                <p>They had an elected president, who was either a doctor or a dentist, I forget,
                    and whose hobby was studying maps. He would say, “Look, do you see how different
                    Argentina from the United States? The rivers don't run down from the mountains.
                    We don't have any strong rivers, like you have Mississippi and so forth.” When
                    Mr. Ford came down to talk to him, he offered him an antique Ford as a gift. He
                    said, “We have plenty of those on the streets of Argentina.”</p>
                <p>He was useless. His idea of the separation of the powers of the state was very
                    simplistic. He made a big speech at the beginning of the congressional year, or
                    the fiscal year it to Congress. He said, “I'm the executive. I'll take care of
                    this. You're the legislature. You pass the laws, and I will enforce them.”</p>
                <p>And I said to Ed Martin, “Just imagine a President of the United States waiting
                    for the legislature to pass the necessary laws that this country needs, and then
                    enforce them.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This president, what was his name?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Ill�a. Well, obviously the country was sick and tired. I mean, they had
                    Frondizi, who was pretty active and was trying to do something, and he was full
                    of vim and vigor and had a big fight with Kennedy about the hoof and mouth
                    disease and how to get meat into the U.S. But Ill�a was just a nice guy who
                    didn't seem to have what some people say Mr. Bush doesn't have, and, of course,
                    they're wrong. He had no vision at all.</p>
                <p>So I went to see the economist, Alsogaray, at one point. I called him up and he
                    said, “Meet me in my private office.” Well, his private office, like many of the
                    Argentines and Latinos usually have a little office. There's not a damn thing in
                    it. A desk and a chair, but no books or papers. I went there and I sat down with
                    him and talked to him for an hour, and I put the question to him, “What's going
                    to happen?” Everybody is talking about a golpe. What is the military was going
                    to do.</p>
                <p>So he said, “Well, in six months, about June, we will take over, and this is the
                    program we're going to institute.”</p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>“Thank you very much, se�or.”</p>
                <p>I went back and gave it to Ed Martin. He smiled and said, “Let's send it in,
                    that's all.”</p>
                <p>And time passed. I guess that must have been in the early part of the year.
                    Things were going on just the same as ever, and Ed Martin wanted to take his
                    leave. He asked the country team. We said, “We can't tell you it's not going to
                    happen or that it is going to happen. You know just as well as we do of all the
                    talk, but when would be the time for you?” So he went.</p>
                <p>So, sure enough, in June, it was, '66, they took over. It was a beautiful job.
                    Oh, I have to remember one thing. One of our colonels who was in the military
                    assistance program had his office in the Argentine secretary of war, and come
                    around 4:00 in the afternoon, he was fiddling around with his papers, and one of
                    his counterparts said, “John, I think you better go.”</p>
                <p>He said, “What do you mean?”</p>
                <p>They said, “Well. I think everything's taken care of. It would be a better idea
                    that you go off early.”</p>
                <p>“No problem. No problem.”</p>
                <p>So John almost had a heart attack running to the Embassy to tell me, Ed Martin
                    being away. He said, “It's going to come. It's going to come.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Okay. Put it out. Get the boys in.” The political officer—what was his
                    name? “Pete.” He had a funny first name, but his nickname was “Pete.” And I made
                    the mistake of calling him Peter once, and he said, “Hey, that's not my name.
                    'Pete' is my name.”</p>
                <p>Well, we all got ready and, by gosh, things began to rumble, and just then, the
                    Soviets had their annual reception. We were listening to the news and I said, “I
                    better go there. Maybe I can find something out.” And I got there and most of
                    the other guests had disappeared already. The caviar gone. There was nobody
                    there associated with the Argentine military. I went right back and said, “Keep
                    going.” And, boy!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: It happened, and there was an announcement, “The government has been
                    taken over. There's no problem. Just for the next four days, do not drive your
                    car around the four blocks of the presidential palace, Casa Rosada, and there
                    won't be any problem.” There it was. It was done.</p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>So, of course, under our Latin American agreement, which said that we will not
                    support—collectively, Latin American countries will not recognize any government
                    that takes over forcefully from a duly-elected government. This was a sort of a
                    development from the Alliance for Progress idea of working together and that
                    democracy was important, as well as land reform, popular government.</p>
                <p>After 18 days, some reporters went in and talked to Ongania. The essence of it
                    was, Ongania said, “We will work our way to a democracy and we will have an
                    election. We just got to get things in order.”</p>
                <p>Martin was up in the United States at some Beach, and he immediately got hold of
                    the State Department and said, “Grab this. Because if we don't recognize this,
                    this uneven status of not having recognition, it's troublesome. We're not going
                    to be able to do anything about it.” So they took that as a ploy to say, “Yes,
                    he's going toward a democracy, and we're all ready to go.”</p>
                <p>So I got instructions to go to the foreign ministry to tell them that, “You're
                    nice boys now. We'll work with you.” And this new man made me wait exactly 18
                    days, corresponding to the 18 days that had passed since the golpe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Eighteen days. He wouldn't see you for 18 days, because it
                        took you 18 days to recognize the government. That's terribly
                        interesting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: But, unfortunately, Ongan�a came in. He had a bunch of businessmen as
                    economic ministers, and they had no different vision than anybody else as to
                    what had to be done specifically. It was still a country relying on one-crop
                    agriculture, meat, and wheat, and in competition with us in the world markets
                    for cereals, a heavily loaded bureaucracy in every business—telephones,
                    railways. A labor union set up, which they inherited from Per�n, where
                    everything had to be accounted for. If you had a little inflation, you had a
                    little sort of wage raise. And you kept doing that, and it went around in
                    circles.</p>
                <p>They claimed to have tremendous resources, but that was wrong. They had no coal,
                    they had no oil, they had no water power. They were considering building a power
                    line all the way from the Andes to Buenos Aires, which is over 2,000 miles. This
                    was the basic problem of what do you do with a country whose technology is so
                    poor and whose desires, whose idea of a standard of living, is as high as
                    possible in an industrialized country, and blaming it on the foreign
                    capitalists? Because the military is not capitalist, it's not free enterprise,
                    and the labor unions aren't and the leftists aren't.</p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>They all are suffering from the same thing that Eastern Europe is suffering
                    today. We want to be free, but we also want our social security, we want our
                    wages, and we want to be able to work on a farm from 9 to 5 and go home. We had
                    a whole bunch of farmers come down from the midwest of the United States,
                    practical guys who ran farms. Whether they were the big corporations or not, but
                    they were farmers of the American style.</p>
                <p>We put them at one end of the semi-circle of Buenos Aires, which has one-third of
                    the population of the country. The other 16 million are all over this vast area,
                    the Pampa. Up in the north is the wheat country. The Pampa is the meat-growing
                    country land. And they went through that whole area and said, “My, gosh, we
                    could create a tremendous food-producing area here” And what are they doing?
                    They're at the mercy of just one crop. They could sell beef and they could sell
                    wheat, and they have to compete with us because we could outsell them anytime
                    with our subsidies and quantities.</p>
                <p>We never could tackle that problem. And when finally the military got out after I
                    left, they put in some free enterprisers who had the silly idea of opening
                    everything. Before you knew it, all their money was being spent abroad. They
                    didn't have a protective tariff of developing their own industries, which we did
                    in our early period of the republic. But it didn't become necessary. There was
                    no point to it, after all, because we were producing as much as we could import.
                    In fact, we didn't even rely on importations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Have we left India?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, India, I think, is pretty much here our inability to work with
                    socialist countries shows up, as elsewhere. You just recall the word
                    “socialist,” and then you close your mind. The fact is that we're just as
                    socialist as any of them, because we have all kinds of safety nets, economic
                    safety nets.</p>
                <p>Of course, this is 20-20 hindsight, because I've been reading much more about all
                    these things since I retired, having to teach international law. We have no
                    concept that we can work with these people, even though they are socialists, in
                    theory and in theology. Leave out the communists. We have government-owned
                    operations all over the place. The S&amp;L, of course, is an example.</p>
                <p>That's what I considered one of our failures, and that's because domestic
                    rhetoric is always against us. We cannot say anything good because we have to
                    base it on freedom, freedom of the individual, the open market, things of this
                    kind. Again, I say this after the fact, but this is what became very difficult
                    to deal with in these countries. Now, I understand AID has gone for attempting
                    to develop entrepreneurship in business, which is very important, and that would
                    be the way, I imagine, to resolve some of these problems. And poor old Gorbachev
                    is now faced with it, because how do you create a body of people like that right
                    off in 500 days?</p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>We had a debate between AID and State about assistance to Africa, and we were
                    bound up by the European policy not to interfere with the colonies of Western
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was when you were with AID in Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: That's right. I was deputy. Jim Grant was working on that, and Jack Bell,
                    too, on his side. One day the Secretary was away. I forget who it was. Dillon
                    was chair of the Secretary's staff meeting, and Jack Bell and I just called in
                    and said, “Look, this is silly. We were being stopped from doing anything in
                    Africa on the basis of we can't touch the colonies of our friends in Europe. And
                    it isn't working, and it's going to lead to all kinds of trouble.”</p>
                <p>So Dillon said, “Let's make a study about it.” Jack Bell really was strong for
                    it. And that guy started it, we're talking about with Jim Grant. And it was a
                    great pleasure for Jack Bell, in the same meeting, hauling away. So we had a
                    quick study, and we set up a whole thing with myself, as chairman, and
                    Satterthwaite coming in and making the basic political statement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Satterthwaite, he was assistant secretary for Africa, is
                        that correct?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I think that is right. Joseph C. Satterthwaite, assistant secretary of
                    state for African affairs.</p>
                <p>So we wrote a very good paper, and the White House called, a little time after,
                    “What are you guys doing about Africa?” And Joe responded like all get out that
                    he had a report, which we had shoved him to do. He was not very happy about it,
                    but he got instructions from Dillon, and he had to go through. Boy, did he have
                    a piece of paper.</p>
                <p>Ted Achilles was really a wonderful guy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, first-rate. He's one of the really top Foreign Service
                        officers, I felt.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Roy Kohler was the control officer when the Soviet Party Secretary came
                    over and went to Disneyland—do you remember—Khrushchev.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>SACCIO: He was reporting the trip, and he told us just how shocked the Russians
                    were when Hollywood gave them a performance of the cancan without panties. The
                    good, old conservative Soviets were shocked. And then we were talking about the
                    forthcoming election, and there was talk about that and everybody was quiet, and
                    Ted Achilles said, “Well, what did he say about the elections?” Everybody
                    laughed, because these State Department guys want to be in touch with politics
                    but not say so.</p>
                <p>Moscoso, I mentioned the fact that he was the guy who had to tell me of new faces
                    and that's why we wanted to change things down in Argentina. But, interesting
                    enough, he was a member of a party that went down to see Castro three years ago.
                    Bob White is the head of this International Development Study, and he invited a
                    number of people, including myself and ex-ambassadors, to go down. And there he
                    was. We became close friends, working together and pushing for the things we
                    wanted to know. We weren't taking any stuff.</p>
                <p>I said, “Look. I want to see something about agriculture. I mean, I'm not here
                    just to go to these institutions.”</p>
                <p>“And I want to see industry,” he said. But we were never able to get them to
                    change their program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you did go to Cuba?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: We did. We got there. We spent five days there. We were given these new
                    accommodations in the Royal Hotel and went to various things, and we were quite
                    impressed with the fact that it's a fairly simple economy, obviously poor, but
                    it has its hospitals, it has its education, and it has all these things. There's
                    no overbearing traffic. The buses are used. The hospitals are good. The local
                    sanitariums are good, things of this kind.</p>
                <p>Every time we asked him about freedom of expression, he said, “Well, that's . .
                    .” We asked him about their experiment of giving farmers the right to go on the
                    market themselves, and he said, “We couldn't have any of that. Here's a man
                    making $50,000, and his wife buying up everything in the stores, so we cut it
                    out. We can't have that.”</p>
                <p>Bob White was trying to get some sort of understanding saying, in effect, there
                    are differences, but there's no reason why they should be in the camp with the
                    Russians and the Soviets. We can deal with them, and we don't want the whole
                    idea of making a deal with the devil, as long as he's on your side. Your enemy
                    is my enemy.”</p>
                <p>And I kept saying—I think I was the only Republican—I said, “Look, you're never
                    going to get away with anything unless, on the surface, this is a free country.
                    Why don't they hire a public relations firm?”</p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>“Well, what's the point of that?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Look what the Israelis do. Look what everybody else does. They go and
                    they talk to the congressmen. I mean, no matter how good or bad they may be,
                    they have to tell their stories. Of course, public relations people are going to
                    tell you right away you could lose; clean your act up. You can't have anybody in
                    jail just because he disagrees with you.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's going too far.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, Bob is doing a terrific job of maintaining the contact in there,
                    but you're up against a stone wall of—well, you see how Castro turned down
                    Moscow for years. I mean, he doesn't agree with them, and when they got into
                    glasnost, he said, “It's not for us.” He had his experience with that.</p>
                <p>When we finally got to see him personally, and we started at 10:00 and ended off
                    at 3:00 in his beautiful office. It wasn't tremendously large, but it was a
                    beautiful architectural, simple job. Nice offices and nobody around. There was a
                    clerk at the desk and one policeman at the door, so you didn't have any problems
                    with anything.</p>
                <p>We sat there and he talked. We tried to interrupt and say, “But, what about . .
                    .” And he told us what he's being doing, how he goes out in the field and he
                    corrected a drainage problem. And he worked in a shop where a girl was putting
                    in needles, and he figured out that this was ruining her eyes and that there was
                    an easier way of doing it, so he fixed that up. And then he went to a hospital
                    to decide various questions about services, and on and on.</p>
                <p>We couldn't get very much, and Bob White put in a question once in a while, but
                    he, very obviously, was maintaining a relationship. He was not cross-examining
                    anybody.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He wanted to keep this thing going.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: It was a very worthwhile thing. Well, that morning—it was morning before
                    we got to bed, 4:00 in the morning. I couldn't sleep. We had a couple of
                    scotches with the leader, and he gave us a cigar. So I sat up in bed. He was
                    kind enough to give us single accommodations. We didn't have to sleep in the
                    same room, so we could put on the radio if we wanted to without disturbing the
                    other guy.</p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>I put on the television and, believe it or not, the five hours of what he talked
                    about was on television. It was on television in the sense that it pictured what
                    he was doing and what he told us was already passed. I mean, he had done it
                    already, all five items that he covered—his trip out in the drainage area, the
                    factory, the hospital, and so forth. And I had insisted with Bob White that we
                    get together in our conference room in the hotel before we left, because I
                    wanted to get some conclusions of what we thought. He said, “Okay, if that's
                    what you want.”</p>
                <p>We had a fellow by the name of Joseph, who had been a Peace Corps executive and
                    now head of New York City University. He's resigned from the head of City
                    University recently. He had been a Peace Corps man, so he knew a lot about that
                    sort of thing. We had a Franciscan priest. We had Bill Attwood, editor of
                    Newsday. We had three of our former ambassadors. I don't remember their names;
                    and Moscoso. We got together that morning before we left, and I told them what I
                    had seen. I said, “You know. What we got from Castro was just a repetition of
                    what he had done in the past week or so, going from place to place.”</p>
                <p>I was obviously impressed by the fact that there were no crowds, no flag-waving,
                    no military. He was in one car and there was an escort car, and that's it. He
                    would stop at all these places, and the cameraman would take everything. He'd
                    walk in and say, “Television's working nice now,” to the lady of the house.
                    “What are you going to do about the roof?” It's just wonderful. He is enamored
                    with the ordered society, without any understanding that if you educate people,
                    you find you have an intelligence on your hand, like Mr. Gorbachev has.</p>
                <p>I've never seen such a group of people who are so well dressed, so well fed,
                    showing up on screens in Moscow and Leningrad. I mean, Sir Isaac Berlin points
                    out in his comment that the people you're really dealing with, the
                    intelligentsia that was created in the 19th century in Russia, they're not
                    Marxists. They're educated, they're not brilliant, they're the basic core of the
                    intellectual middle class. Not intellectual in the sense of book readers, but
                    what the Europeans call intelligentsia. And that's what you see on the
                    television. Well, where would you get a guy like Boris Yeltsin? If he were a
                    dictator or a communist. And they're all over the place, once you give them a
                    little food.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And freedom.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: They want the rest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Gorbachev gave them freedom.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: That's right.</p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>With Al Roseman and his wife. We stopped there. Cambodia. I forget his name, but
                    a fellow by the name of Mann was the mission director.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Charlie Mann.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: A very good guy. And the ambassador was Ambassador Trimble. Al and
                    Charlie took me aside and said, “He's scared stiff; he won't do anything. He's
                    impossible.” (He had autographed pictures in silver frames of all the people he
                    knew in the State Department.)</p>
                <p>“We have direct contact with the Cambodians, and we know them.” I think they
                    called him “Shnookie,” the prince.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sihanouk.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: And, here again, the boys in the AID program knew, had the guts, and were
                    close, while the ambassador was . . . I didn't meet anybody in the embassy, such
                    that I recall, but Trimble was . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He didn't have much to do with the Cambodians, or feel
                        that he could have any effect. Is that it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: That's right. And he was frightened about what was going to happen there.
                    Well, it finally did, I suppose, but there was no feeling of “we have a chance,”
                    as far as I can make out.</p>
                <p>John Connally's trip when he was Nixon's man:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Secretary of the Treasury.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He made that worldwide trip. It was all advertised as a preview to
                    succeed Nixon as president before the ceiling came down. We were in Colombia at
                    that point. Just to indicate the arrogance of we “Americans,” they, in effect,
                    said, “We're going to take this trip, and it's going to be on our terms. They
                    ought to be happy that we're coming.” And they laid out the schedule.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Without taking it up with the Colombians? (???)</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, they told us, “This is what we propose to do,” and there was no
                    real choice. And it was all advertised worldwide what was happening, and they
                    got it out to the newspapers just as fast as we got it by telegram. They were
                    stopping at Venezuela and then flying over to Bogot� and then on down, and the
                    press was all keyed up to the idea that they were trying him out, just like in
                    the case of Nixon.</p>
                <p>He (Nixon) was a private citizen when he came down to Buenos Aires. But when he
                    became president, boy, you should see everybody calling me up and saying, “I was
                    at that meal. Do you have a photograph of that?” USIS brought out all the
                    photographs and we sent them to the various guys who had become ministers. It
                    was all fun.</p>
                <p>On Connally, I was notified exactly when he was coming, and he expected to call
                    on the president. They would come on a certain day, and they were off; the plane
                    would take off. I said, “I'm not going to go to the president and tell him that
                    lunch has to be at a certain hour, because you are coming in at a certain hour,
                    and that's what we have to do.” Absolutely not. What the hell do you think the
                    President is a hotel manager? So I couldn't get through to them, so I called
                    John Irwin. He was at the top of the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, he was under secretary.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: John Irwin. On the phone, I said, “Hey, this is a hell of a thing to do.
                    I'm not going to go tell the president when he is to meet with them because they
                    didn't want to be sleepy when they arrived; they wanted to make the lunch later.
                    Absolutely not. You have communications with them. You tell them that they have
                    to come at this time, and that's what I'm going to tell the president.” And they
                    took it. They changed it. They came in droopy-eyed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they did it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: But they did it; there were a few murmurings around the place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, do you think this is endemic that the department
                        just doesn't understand the field? This was a case, perhaps, that a very
                        powerful man had said he wanted to do a certain thing, and the department
                        just caved.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>SACCIO: Oh, yes. The department couldn't do anything about it. It's like Bobby
                    Kennedy coming around making his trip. He sent two kids—and I mean kids—as
                    advance men, and he wanted to do it his way. And what he wanted, they came into
                    my office. I don't know where the ambassador was. He was either meeting him or
                    on the way simultaneously. And this was a couple of weeks before they arrived,
                    and they said, “We want all the people in the embassy to be dismissed, go home
                    and get their family, and bring them to the residence and meet with Senator
                    Kennedy.”</p>
                <p>I said, “What do you think you are? They're not going to do that.”</p>
                <p>“Well, this is what the senator wants.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you told the Kennedy advance people...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: So, I had the political officer, Pete with me, and we sat there. They sat
                    on the lounge and I was kind enough, protocol wise, to get from behind my
                    desk...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And sit in a chair.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Not sitting behind the desk. You have to be very careful when somebody
                    comes to visit you. If he's important enough, you don't sit behind your desk,
                    like Luzzato did to me when I came back from Washington. We went into a bare
                    room where there was some furniture, and immediately he got behind the desk.</p>
                <p>I said, “No soap. We're not going to do that. Do you know where these people
                    live? They're way out in the country. The family can't come in on their own.
                    They have to go back and get them.”</p>
                <p>They said, “Send them out.”</p>
                <p>I said, “No soap. I'll tell you what I'll do, though. When Senator Kennedy comes
                    to the embassy here before he goes to the residence or after he gets to the
                    residence, he comes to the Embassy and visits with the ambassador officially and
                    we have a talk about plans. We're on the eighth floor. When he gets through with
                    that, we'll have everybody on the eighth floor at the elevator and say hello to
                    the senator. Then we'll stop the elevator on the seventh floor, and we'll have
                    everybody on the seventh floor to say hello to the senator. And we'll go down to
                    the sixth floor, and everybody on the sixth floor . . .”</p>
                <p>“Okay, okay. Well, maybe that will do it,” he said, “He'll meet everybody,
                    because you're all here.”</p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>So we did it that way. Ed Martin and I and the senator moved toward the elevator.
                    All the political officers and the CIA boys were all collected on the eighth
                    floor. They came out from wherever they were on the ninth. And they all said
                    hello to the senator, very politely, “It's good to see you.” Then down to the
                    next floor, the economic and commercial. The sixth floor, a little more of
                    this.</p>
                <p>On the fifth floor, it began to go bang, bang. The Argentines (nationals employed
                    by the Embassy) had gotten so excited. On the fourth floor, bang away. On the
                    third floor, . . . Before he got down to the bottom, it was chaos. And he walked
                    out in the street— and this is a narrow street—and he got up on top of the
                    ambassador's limousine, and the place was jammed. The entire block was full. He
                    said, “I seem to notice that I get more applause the further down I go.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Argentines. This is because they liked the Kennedy
                        family.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: That was the whole thing.</p>
                <p>On university contracts, I can go back to India, if we have a little time. I
                    found that some of these contracts were just shells. We had a man there. In some
                    cases, we had three or four professors, and they were teaching some course or
                    something. But they were not integrated. They were not in management positions
                    and they were not in administrative positions.</p>
                <p>On the basic top-level university which devoted to agriculture, we had a
                    professor there. He and his wife, nicely settled, retired from some state
                    university. We went up there and he had breakfast for us, and I asked him what
                    he did. He said, “Well, I'm looking into the development of peas.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Do you sit with the faculty or the board?”</p>
                <p>“Well, once in a while they call me in.”</p>
                <p>I said, “For Christmas sake. What the hell are you . . .” Here we have a contract
                    with the university, and we have one man who could just be one of the
                    professors, but nothing more. Maybe one of the research men, but nothing having
                    to do with the whole plan of the university, the education, the effect on
                    development, all that sort of thing. And I said to the very nice guy who was the
                    agricultural chief at the AID program, “What's this guy doing?”</p>
                <p>“Well, you know, you can't . . .”</p>
                <p>“My gosh.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, whose fault do you think that was? Was it that it
                        wasn't planned well by the AID mission, or the person wasn't adequate for
                        the job that was chosen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No, no. Apparently, at this point, whatever they did for the university
                    had...</p>
                <p>I can't say of anything before, because I don't recall getting in any deeper. But
                    I said, “This man has to leave, because he has no purpose here.”</p>
                <p>And they said, “Well, look. His wife is here, and the situation at home.” You
                    know, personal things like that.</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, I'm sorry. He stays to the end of the whatever term there is, and
                    nobody goes in.”</p>
                <p>One fellow, who was the contract man for the university—I forget whether it was
                    Illinois—with Orissa, a state of India off on the Bengal side. I had an
                    interview with him when I first came. I said, “How is it going.”</p>
                <p>“Well, we're having problems.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, what are they?”</p>
                <p>“Well, we recommend that the faculty be permanent and not part time or slipshod,
                    that they be given salaries, that they have a fixed curriculum, and that they
                    have to follow it.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Would you kindly write those down on a piece of paper?”</p>
                <p>“Sure, I'd be delighted.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Now, you go back and tell them if they don't do this, you're going to
                    cut out the contract. Because we're not staying here just for you to be
                    frustrated and not doing anything.”</p>
                <p>“Well, you know, they have problems with money.”</p>
                <p>I said, “I know they have problems. And if you're going to do anything for them,
                    you have to tell them that this is what we suggest. And if they don't do it,
                    there's no point in your being there or saying we have an AID program.”
                    Incidentally, it worked.</p>
                <p>Another instance in the AID program, we had a very good guy on economics and
                    statistics. He was the brother of the opera conductor, Rudel. His name was
                    Rudel, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yeah. I knew him. Rudel. I see him every now and then.
                        He and I live about ten blocks apart. Julius Rudel is his brother.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He told me how it was set up, and he had about 15 Indians working in his
                    office maintaining statistics showing where the possibilities for shrimp
                    development for small business, for export to make dollars. And they kept books
                    over the period of months and years and so forth, showing how things would be
                    developed and how they were going. I said, “Well, what do you do now?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, we continue to do this.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, what about the Indian government? What are they going to do?”</p>
                <p>“Well, we're going to try to get them to do the same.”</p>
                <p>I said, “You could advertise that you have this. If they're going to do it, I
                    want you to transfer the whole bunch of Indians over to the ministry and put
                    them over there.”</p>
                <p>“Oh, that would be catastrophic, because they won't get paid.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>I said, “I don't care. You can't have these guys here. They're beautiful, they're
                    lovely, they're having a great time, and they obviously want to continue to work
                    for the United States embassy. What greater prestige and what greater pay would
                    they get?” And, of course, we were paying out rupees, of which we had
                    millions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hundreds of millions.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: That professor from Columbia came down to report what we had there. So
                    Rudel said, “No, that's impossible.”</p>
                <p>So I said, “Well, I have to see the economic minister, and I'll just tell him.
                    Would you kindly arrange for my appointment?”</p>
                <p>So we had an appointment for a fixed time, and we went in there and he made us
                    wait literally three-quarters of an hour in the small anteroom. Whether it was
                    small or big, didn't make any difference, but there we sat. They sent out a
                    messenger, “Pretty soon,” and so forth.</p>
                <p>Finally, he had me come in. I think I had somebody with me, one of the
                    officers—maybe Rudel. I told the Minister this work had been going on very
                    nicely, it's very important, and I thought it's at a stage that we ought to
                    transfer it over to him.”</p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>He looked at me and finally got around to apologizing for making me wait out
                    there, because he had to be briefed. “You know, here in India, we're slow. We're
                    not as fast as you people are.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Oh, I can understand that. But we would like to make this transfer and
                    put these people in your ministry and make them continue to work and make it
                    useful to your people.”</p>
                <p>He said, “We can't do that.” And this went on.</p>
                <p>So I laid down the law. I said, “If you don't, we'll dispense with the whole
                    operation. Do you want it or you don't?”</p>
                <p>We became great friends, because he was one of the top civil servants who went
                    from the head of one agency to another. He went from agriculture to be the civil
                    servant of defense, which is no small job in the way of prestige. He wasn't very
                    happy, but we did become friends after he became secretary of defense, because
                    we weren't transferring our soldiers to him. [Laughter] But the difficult of
                    moving this sort of stuff on is...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you feel that we aren't tough enough on this, that we
                        keep things going too long?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: It's hard, because, obviously, it was a very difficult problem to switch
                    15 people and put them in an Indian ministry, pay them the same as they've been
                    paid, considering what the rest of the guys in that ministry were getting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. They were getting a lot more working for the AID
                        mission.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Of course, and it was steady. I'm sure the other guys had steady jobs,
                    but they had to have those little chips in order to get jobs.</p>
                <p>Great things. The business school in Sao Paulo, the comprehensive school system
                    in Colombia. Certainly Taiwan was a wonderful job. Korea was a terrific job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you mean this is where we've had successes?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>SACCIO: Yes. Whether it was through technical assistance or economic development
                    money where they could import things. Mostly on the basis, the successes were on
                    the base that would accept it. In China, you would get it. In Taiwan, you would
                    get it because you had a bunch of Ph.D.s, and it was embarrassing to walk into
                    that room with Ph.D.s from Princeton, Harvard, and all, sitting around me, with
                    my little J.D. from Columbia University. I mean, they were all good. They knew
                    their stuff, and they weren't just scholars. They were in the government. And
                    you had that.</p>
                <p>Korea, I imagine it was the same thing, possibly because they were trained by the
                    Japanese all during the long occupation; they were working with them and it was
                    an industrial country to a certain extent, even before they were freed of Japan.
                    In Brazil, you have a lot of intelligent people, but it's not so set up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you. You served in Salvador, you served in
                        Brazil, you served in Argentina, you served in India. You saw a lot of what
                        happened in Korea. Why is it that Latin America, frankly, does not develop,
                        and I think quite a few of their elite have gone to our best schools? And
                        yet, places like Korea, Japan, Singapore, they do develop. I would like to
                        say, and I'd like to test this, that I think it's cultural. There's a
                        different culture.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: You take the Chinese: They have a sophisticated culture of five, six,
                    seven thousand years, with scholars as the key to their culture; scholarly exams
                    to get into the government, competition of a high order, enough base in
                    practical science, and no competition from the outside to undercut their
                    production.</p>
                <p>You take Latin America. The moment that the tin pots from Manchester came in,
                    home craft went out the window, because you could buy a tin can or tin pot for
                    nothing. They came in from Manchester, which the British wanted to sell, and
                    they would get food in return. And that's what you got from the Latinos.</p>
                <p>The economic minister of Colombia in the 19th century said that. “We are in a
                    wonderful position, because we can get all their goods and just give them food.”
                    And they said it in a book, with no recognition that industrial production is
                    the heart and soundness of your currency.</p>
                <p>If you can't produce anything, why would the government give you a dollar for
                    anything unless you produce something for it. I mean, if you read Galbraith's
                    little book on money, the government doesn't put dollars out for nothing. It's
                    got to get something in return.</p>
                <p>Well, the Indians used wampum as exchange. It was only good as long as there were
                    beaver. The moment the beaver disappeared, the colonists weren't interested in
                    it. They wanted hard cash. And where did they get the hard cash? By shipping
                    goods to England. That's where they got paid.</p>
                <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                <p>Bernard De Voto pointed that out years ago. The two cultures that came together,
                    the European and the Indians, were ice ages apart. The stone ages and the
                    European modern culture, they came together, and it was perfectly easy for the
                    poor Indian to take what he could get. They would give them instruments made out
                    of iron and steel, not the stones, and they wanted it and they were willing to
                    pay. They went out hunting for beaver. When the beaver ran out, they weren't
                    getting anything. So he pointed out simply. When you get this sort of thing, how
                    do expect them to live together without clashing? That's it.</p>
                <p>Thomas Jefferson was willing to say, “Now, if we teach these Indians to mark out
                    their land and grow their food, they will be so interested in selling their
                    product, that the land becomes worth something, and they will become suppliers.
                    As long as they don't care about the land, they don't have any interest. And
                    this is the only way,” Mr. Jefferson said, “we're going to civilize these
                    people. Make them realize that the land is worth something, and that we're
                    willing to pay for it.”</p>
                <p>One thing in Colombia that I want to point out. About the time I was leaving, I
                    went to pay my call on the ex-president, who did a great job for Colombia,
                    Lleras Camargo.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're talking about the president of Colombia—the former
                        president of Colombia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: The former president when I was leaving.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lleras Camargo.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I went to pay my respects, saying I was leaving the Colombia. He was in
                    his little place in the country. And it was interesting, because as I learned
                    Colombians were not the kind that amassed great wealth. They were very modest in
                    their material resources. He lived in a very simple house, and when he quit the
                    presidency, he went to this little place in the country where he bought a little
                    house with just, you know, 100 x 50. He said he made a big mistake because he
                    didn't ask the farmer for the field out there so he could keep the view. He
                    couldn't get it from him now unless he paid him a fortune.</p>
                <p>But the thing he said was really something. He had done a job for Colombia in
                    getting it somewhat straightened out economically— coffee and so forth. And he
                    turned around to me and he said, “You know, if it hadn't been for your AID
                    program, I would never have been able to do it.” This was the first time I ever
                    heard anything like that. And my political officer said, “My, God. This is the
                    first time anybody has said that.”</p>
                <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                <p>When I arrived in Colombia, the foreign minister did not know anything about our
                    AID program. I said, “Se�or Ministro, we have a program here of $100 million,
                    the largest per capita program in the world, for 20 million people.”</p>
                <p>He said, “I didn't know that.” The next time I met him with another minister, he
                    said to the other Minister, “Did you know that they have a program here of $100
                    million?” He said, “They do?” This is incredible!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was USIA in all this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: So I called them in. I said, “What's this? The foreign minister doesn't
                    know how much we're doing here.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, it's not our policy to embarrass them.”</p>
                <p>I said, “You mean to say that?” President Nixon delivered a speech at that point,
                    and he had a whole section about helping the Latin Americans. And the best paper
                    in Colombia, La Prensa, I think it was, “Promesas, Promesas, Promesas,
                    Promesas.” A nice editorial. They always promise, and what the hell do they
                    do?</p>
                <p>So that's when I called the AID director. I can't remember his name. He became
                    ambassador to Costa Rica.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Marvin Weisman.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I called him in with the USIS director, who was a tough kind of
                    character, pretty knowledgeable and all that. I said, “Hey, what's this here,
                    'promesas, promesas'? I want you to write a letter saying what we're doing for
                    this country, and I'll answer that 'promesas, promesas.'”</p>
                <p>They said, “You don't want to do that.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Yes, I do.”</p>
                <p>“Well, you know, we don't like to...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Blow our own horn? Something like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                <p>SACCIO: Stick their nose in. I said, “Okay. You go back and write that letter,
                    and I want you to review it very carefully and put everything that we're doing
                    in this country. And come back, we'll review it, and if it's okay, I'll sign
                    it.”</p>
                <p>They did. They got up a very good letter on what we were doing in the country.
                    That being done, he said, “What do you want me to do with it?”</p>
                <p>“What do you want me to do with it! Take it to the damn editor and tell him to
                    print it!”</p>
                <p>“Well, you know the editor.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Oh, yes. I know the editor. Just go over and do it.” It was on the front
                    page of La Prensa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they did publish it on the front page? Very good.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Then they wrote another weak editorial, “But, you know, you're not doing
                    enough.” All in the same vein as the meeting of a bunch of Latin American
                    economists in Caracas at one point. The headline came out of the conference,
                    “The foreigners have invested $8 billion in Latin America, and they took out $9
                    billion.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Okay, here's your chance. If you put $100 in the bank, do you only want
                    to take $70 out?” Come on. Tell them that money makes money. That's the whole
                    point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Both of you are supposed to profit from it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I did the same thing in Brazil. I went down to Sao Paulo and addressed
                    the American Chamber of Commerce, and I told them what we were doing in Brazil.
                    I came back and Lincoln Gordon said, “Why the hell don't you write speeches like
                    that for me?” Because he was asking his political officers to write his speech.
                    I said, “Well, that's my job. I went down. You knew I was going down. I had to
                    make a speech.”</p>
                <p>The interesting part about it is when they published it, the radical press was
                    sure not to have my picture up there. I had an address where we were giving some
                    aid to the aviation industry, and they had pictures of everybody except me. I
                    mean, they cut it right off. I asked them, you know, “I was the principal
                    speaker, wasn't I? Why isn't my picture there?”</p>
                <p>“Well, that's what they do.”</p>
                <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                <p>Another problem that we had. We have gold mines in northwest Colombia—private
                    enterprise, American They've been there for years. It's in the jungle, and like
                    in any underdeveloped country, wherever you have a plant or an operation or a
                    project, it attracts immediately. Just as if you were a tourist stopped at a
                    side road in Mexico or in India, before you know it, there are kids there, and
                    they would talk to you or ask you for something. And the attraction of the
                    native Indians, whether native Indians or mixed blood, were all there. They want
                    food, they want shelter, and so forth, and the criticism is, “Look at all the
                    money they're making, and they're talking it away and this is our land.”</p>
                <p>I wrote to Jack Ohly about the same situation in the far north of Brazil, where a
                    couple of Brazilian entrepreneurs had created a chemical factory. They had to
                    build a fence so tight to prevent people from getting in. Because where there is
                    a company commissary; there was food, there is housing, and it just breaks your
                    heart to see how the people all go there trying to get in and break through the
                    fence.</p>
                <p>The same thing in India. I observed it. We went to one plant there, which was
                    being inaugurated with our help. All around it, they had high fences and guards
                    so that nobody could get in there, because they all came to the place.</p>
                <p>The gold mines in Colombia, they said, “Look, this is ours. They're taking it
                    away.” And I said right back to the guy, “Why don't you buy it. Why don't you
                    take it over. We'll advertise these mines for sale. Why don't you buy it? Why
                    don't the Colombians? You have rich men, rich people. Why don't you buy the
                    mines? Because I looked into it. They're making 14 percent on their investment.
                    It isn't very much, but they keep going.”</p>
                <p>“Well, we won't be able to make enough money on it.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not enough for them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No, because they're in a risky business working in those places, if you
                    don't make 25 percent. And it's natural. I mean, this is true of what's true in
                    our country. If you don't make a substantial investment in the development of
                    the country, the risks you take are such that you demand a high price for your
                    money.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're talking about land reform. You were saying about
                        land reform?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: As far as I know, it never worked in Latin America. Mexico started quite
                    early on the whole idea, but sensibly divided agriculture between what they call
                    the ejidos and private enterprise farming, and much of the Mexican wheat is
                    grown by the private people. When the Brazilians went to do the same, they
                    recognized that they had to have large-scale farming.</p>
                <pb facs="0077" n="Page0077"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Otherwise, it won't compete.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: So that was no solution. Family planning, they were all interested in
                    trying to do something about it, but it's hard to get a grip on the thing where
                    people have no recourse. They have no reason themselves to control births. They
                    need kids to help them do what they need in the way of work. It's only when they
                    reach a certain level of affluence that they say, “Well, we can't have any more
                    kids, for the simple reason that I don't want to become poor.” And I think the
                    administration ought to have its head examined in stopping the family aid
                    programs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The family planning programs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: They should know. The sophisticated white people in this country have a
                    low opinion of the blacks, the minorities, and so forth, who produce kids by the
                    dozen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As we wind up, let me ask you a couple of questions. Let's
                        take Colombia. You were going there as ambassador. What kind of briefing or
                        preparation was offered to you by various agencies in Washington? I mean, I
                        don't want the details, but generally, did you have good briefing or what
                        before you went to Colombia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, I met with bankers and a whole group of industrialists in New York,
                    and we just pleasantly talked of the general knowledge of the bad situation
                    there and the whole idea. They seemed to be in favor that we ought to do
                    something, as any good businessman wants to do business, wants people who can
                    pay for their food and pay for their products.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about your briefing by the department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: I don't recall that it was anything more than the usual, you know,
                    population and how much was there, how large the program was, who was there
                    before. I found out a lot of facts myself. I came across myself the amazing fact
                    that in “compensation for taking Panama,”—I'm quoting T.R.—we took it. The
                    United States Congress felt so much about it after the canal was built and
                    everything was going fine, in the '20s they gave Colombia $25 million in a sort
                    of gesture. That was a bonanza that Colombia was just so grateful for. It lived
                    on that $25 million, and it was just absolutely great.</p>
                <pb facs="0078" n="Page0078"/>
                <p>Another odd fact was that when there was a first Pan-American Conference in
                    Washington back in '98,(???) I think it was, we invited all the Latin American
                    countries up here and had all of the stuffed shirts of the presidents and
                    diplomats. And one of the things that we offered the delegations was a trip
                    through the United States railway system. The Argentines, “No, we have
                    railways.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Argentines did not accept.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No. They wouldn't go on it. It was demeaning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you meet with any other people who had been in
                        ambassador to Colombia, other U.S. ambassadors who had been ambassadors to
                        Colombia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: My only meeting with Spruille Braden was across the argument table.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Spruille Braden?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: You don't remember Spruille Braden?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember Braden. I didn't know he had ever been to
                        Colombia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He was ambassador there, one of the early ones.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is before he was ambassador to Argentina?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: No, it was Colombia he was ambassador to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Colombia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: He may have been in Argentina, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think Spruille Braden was an ambassador to Argentina and
                        was taken out because he had gotten involved in the local election before it
                        happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0079" n="Page0079"/>
                <p>SACCIO: I thought it was Colombia, because I had heard all kinds of stories about
                    him there and the difficulty of getting his car from the east coast. You might
                    check that. But he and I had an argument across the table in the Senate Finance
                    Committee. And I forget what the argument was about. But he mentioned my name,
                    and he thought I was wrong or something else, and I thought he was wrong.</p>
                <p>And I met up with Willard Beaulac. He came around. He was ambassador to Salvador.
                    He died recently. He's the one man I remember—I'm sure there were others who
                    said the same, and I think McClintock was probably one of them—who said, in
                    effect, that we've got too many people abroad. All the embassy needs is a good
                    ambassador, a good political officer, a good administrator, and that's all. Not
                    these hundreds all over the place.</p>
                <p>And one guy will never forgive me for kicking him out of Argentina because, in my
                    opinion, he was surplus. He represented the Treasury, and he had been there a
                    little longer. He had great friends all over the place, particularly in the
                    financial sections, and I was the guy who had to go to the foreign minister and
                    urge him not to sell us out on gold. And they were so kind to me. It was
                    Christmas, and they said, “We can't deny what you're asking. It's Christmas.”
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Always go on Christmas.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, he was an awfully nice guy. He was under Ongania. He was the
                    economic minister. And I told him about the tax situation, how terrible it was,
                    that they ought to do something. Because what these Argentine's were doing was
                    letting the inflation take care of it, then pay it with the same worthless pesos
                    years later. And I said, “You've got to really do something if you're ever going
                    to get out of this thing.”</p>
                <p>He said, “I know. I know what happens. There's a little notice that a computer
                    has come to town on a freighter, and immediately they start paying their
                    taxes.”</p>
                <p>“That's the idea.” I forget what it was I asked him to do. Do you know who he
                    called? One of the military officers before he would act.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He called the military officer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Well, as we wind this up, do you have any general observations or concluding
                    observations you'd like to make about this business called foreign affairs?</p>
                <pb facs="0080" n="Page0080"/>
                <p>SACCIO: Well, I worry about this time and again. I've gone from the one end of
                    the spectrum of saying let them alone, let them figure their own way out. Help
                    them some, but don't get in there. To maybe not the other extreme, but the other
                    level of operation, of getting into the U.N. and working from there with the
                    idea that you must recognize the individual sovereignty of a country, even if
                    you don't like what it is, and help them as much as you possibly can with
                    training, education, possibly investments, wisely made, without regard to
                    whether they're pink, black, or white.</p>
                <p>The thing that impresses me is that's what the present administration is doing.
                    It's talking about the sanctity of a country, and it cannot be invaded by
                    another. And if you have this, you cannot have a democracy in the UN, because it
                    means that the General Assembly will vote themselves everything they want.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All the little countries will outvote.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Sure. So you have to have this system, and you should have the court
                    which resolves technical or contractual questions and not decide that you don't
                    have to go in if you don't want to.</p>
                <p>But studying the Constitution as I did because of the bicentennial we had—Forest
                    McDonald, he is one of the great scholars; he wrote a very good book on it—it
                    became so evident that the Constitution was based really on the experience of
                    the people of 150 years of colonial self-government, and they knew where they
                    had to compromise and that the judiciary could not be in the pocket of the
                    executive nor the legislature could not run free of any restraint. And one of
                    the participants in the convention said it. This is not Locke who's telling us
                    to do this, or Montaigne and so forth. This is based on the compromises we know
                    we have to make. And when you hear these people say, you know, “The Constitution
                    gave us liberty.”</p>
                <p>The other conclusion is that the document has to work itself out. It is not
                    self-administering. And all of our people, when they wrote this Constitution,
                    knew it. They said it's going to be God or luck that this really works out. We
                    don't know it is. And you had all kinds of crises, like Jackson telling the
                    court to go fish, the bank, and you had the Hartford Convention wanting to get
                    out. You had all kinds of things, but it still kept going, because it was based
                    pretty much on, say, 2,000 years of British government. It's hard to realize
                    that there was 150 years of experience, 1620 to 1776. And 150 years, the
                    colonies was so damn prosperous for the first 50 years, it wasn't even funny.
                    After the Revolution, they had a little trouble.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really from 1620 to 1787, to the Constitutional
                        Convention.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0081" n="Page0081"/>
                <p>SACCIO: It was a long period after King Phillip's War, where New England went
                    down like this, because it destroyed itself in that war. They came in, and they
                    had a free ride, because the Indians had been devastated by disease, by the
                    fishermen who came down from the north and the dealings with them. They found a
                    population of 20,000, where there was 80,000 before. The trails were built, the
                    farms were built, communication systems were all there, and it was so easy for
                    them. Before you knew it, they were prospering like all get-out. They had a good
                    relationship with the Indians because the Indians wanted what they saw, and the
                    colonists were willing to pay for it in their wampum.</p>
                <p>Now, the result is that it is hard to impose one culture on another, no matter
                    what you do. And the whole idea of the UN is that these various cultures can
                    work together, if you don't assume to dictate one on the other. You have to have
                    some order. And the order, when you talk about there's a moral content in our
                    foreign policy—I'm sure there is—the moral content is they're doing something
                    that works out, and not something because you think it's liberty or democracy.
                    We love it. We're getting less of it because we're becoming a crowded nation,
                    and we need all the rules and regulations. It's going to get more and more
                    difficult.</p>
                <p>But look at the way a guy like Tom Wicker turns around, the New York Times
                    columnist. He wrote a column about referendum in California, rule by the people.
                    He's a liberal; we know that. He's quite a liberal, and what he said about those
                    damn conservatives and supply economists, he wrote a column and said, “This is
                    crazy. You can't pass legislation like that. There is no considerations of the
                    difficulties, of the nuances, that you have to think of in passing a law. You
                    just say, 'No tax over two percent and that's it.' Look at what the hell it's
                    done to California.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you very much, sir.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SACCIO: Not at all.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
