<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000088">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Jack R. Binns </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR JACK R. BINNS</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: July 25, 1990</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Please tell us a little about your background.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: I am a West Coast person. I was born in Oregon, raised largely in Spokane,
                    Washington. I came east in 1952 when I accepted an appointment to the US Naval
                    Academy. I graduated from that distinguished institution in 1956 and began a
                    career in the Navy. I served in the Navy until 1962, when I entered the Foreign
                    Service. While serving in the Navy, I was assigned to “foreign shore duty” in
                    Yokohama, Japan.</p>
                <p>I had become interested in the Foreign Service through a friend, who retired
                    10-15 years ago and became a professor at Michigan University. I took the
                    Foreign Service entrance examination in San Francisco, before leaving for
                    Yokohama. While there, since I had received notice that I passed the
                    examination, I went to see the Consul General to introduce myself. The people
                    there were quite interested in me and were very helpful. I met a number of
                    people there, two of whom are still close friends—one just retired and the other
                    will be retiring shortly.</p>
                <p>When I entered the Foreign Service in 1962, my class was reasonably large. It had
                    between thirty-five and forty people. For much of our work, we were divided into
                    two sections. A number of my colleagues have been quite successful in the
                    Foreign Service; some left the Service and became successful in other endeavors.
                    At age 29, I was one of the two or three oldest people in the class. Most of the
                    class had had relatively little work experience; many were just entering from
                    graduate school. The class was predominantly male—one woman; no blacks or
                    Hispanics. In the sense that it was male and white, it was much like its
                    predecessor classes. But it was not predominantly Ivy League. There had been a
                    clear effort made to reach out to get geographical and academic
                    representation—it went beyond the Ivy League, Stanford and Berkeley.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your first assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>BINNS: My first post was Guatemala from 1963 to 1965. In those days, when you
                    entered the Foreign Service, your first two year tour was a “rotational”
                    assignment and you spent, in theory, at least, six months in the main sections
                    of an Embassy—political, economic, consular and administrative. That was my
                    first assignment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were our interests in Guatemala in the early
                        1960s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Our interests were largely economic and security. This was after Castro's
                    coup and there was a perception, indeed a reality, that he was fermenting
                    revolution in the Central America region. The US had major investments in
                    Guatemala, at least relative to other Central American countries. We had a major
                    economic assistance program—The Alliance for Progress. We saw the development of
                    Guatemala as an inoculation against communism and it was therefore a
                    priority.</p>
                <p>Socially, Guatemala at that time was a panorama of extremes. There was a
                    substantial wealthy community which controlled the economy, controlled to a
                    large extent the political scene although it by no means had a monopoly on it.
                    Then there was 90% of the population living at or below the poverty level. The
                    majority of this group was ethnic Indians,many of whom did not speak Spanish. It
                    was clearly a polarized society.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How well did you and your Embassy colleagues feel that the
                        Alliance was working?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: We felt it was a very positive effort and thought we were having quite a
                    bit of success. That was certainly true from the microeconomic perspective and
                    from the social development point of view. We built over two thousands schools
                    over a relatively short period. I remember that we would always try to send
                    someone from the AID Mission or the Embassy to dedicate these schools as they
                    were completed. We had two or three people on weekends cutting ribbons.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did these buildings remain school buildings?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: I am sure they are still being used as schools. We build two thousands of
                    them, mostly small ones with four to five classrooms largely in remote rural
                    areas. They were built for primary education. The question was that beyond that
                    level there was not much of an infrastructure, not much government investment
                    nor much economic interest in pursuing more than just rudimentary education. The
                    poor rural families, once a son reached the age of ten, put him to work because
                    the child could contribute more to the family by working in the fields than by
                    staying in school.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were in Guatemala, how important did you
                        consider American business interests?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Except for the United Fruit Company, American business was not
                    particularly influential. Even the United Fruit Company's star was waning at
                    this time. Because if American anti-trust legislation, the Company had been
                    forced out of the railroad business—at one time it had owned the only railroad
                    in Guatemala. It was forced to sell it because of American law. The same law
                    broke the Company's monopoly on sea-borne transport in Guatemala. Until the
                    early 50s, United Fruit owned the only deep water port in Guatemala. There was
                    no road linking the port to Guatemala City and other major population centers of
                    the country. There was only the railroad. So United Fruit controlled the port,
                    the railroads as well as large banana plantations which was the basis for one of
                    the principal export products of the country. It had a lot of power.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your Ambassador was Jack Bell, I believe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: That's right. I was most impressed by him. I thought he was extremely
                    intelligent man; one who did a superb job as Ambassador from my point of view as
                    a newcomer to the Service. His major interest is economic development. I
                    remember most vividly that during my second year, while I was probably working
                    in the administrative section, I was pulled out of the section to study what
                    progress the Alliance for Progress had made. So an AID junior officer and myself
                    were given the task of designing indices which would allow us to objectively
                    measure the progress that was being made in meeting then specific goals of the
                    Alliance. The Treat of Punta Del Este set up ten specific goals for the
                    Alliance. One for example, which was easy to measure, was a sustained growth
                    rate of two and half percent per annum above the population growth. There were
                    others which for the most part did not lend themselves to quantitative
                    measurement. So we had to device other indices. For example, for the eradication
                    of literacy, it could only be done through a thorough census, which was beyond
                    the capacity of Guatemala to conduct. We used instead the number of schools
                    built, the number of children attending, the number of people attending adult
                    education, the amount of investment the country was making in education from its
                    own resources, the number of teachers being trained and so forth. There were a
                    long series of measurements which while not addressing the issue directly, could
                    provide a feel for where the program had been, where it was currently and how
                    far it might have to go to meet the objectives. We spend several months doing
                    this. It became clear that we were making more progress in some areas than
                    others, but there was a general feeling that progress was being made across the
                    board. In no case, to the best of my recollection, were there any objectives
                    that were achievable in a ten year period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Castro appeal was very strong at this time. Did we do
                        anything to counter it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>BINNS: We were providing military assistance to the Guatemalan Armed Forces. We
                    had a “Public Safety Program” through the AID mission which was intended to
                    train the police. We were, as I mentioned, trying to inoculate the country
                    against Castro's siren song by improving the lives of the Guatemalan citizens,
                    especially for those at the lower end of the income scale. These were all
                    activities to counter Castro. Not all were of course being conducted solely for
                    that threat, but they served that purpose as well.</p>
                <p>If you know Guatemala, its history is strewn with government over-throw attempts,
                    usually by the military. Shortly after my arrival, the existing
                    democratic-ostensibly democratic-government under Presiden, was over-thrown by
                    the military. It stayed in power throughout my tour, but shortly after my
                    departure, conducted elections which were free and open in which the opposition
                    party won. The new President was allowed to take office and served his full
                    term.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your next assignment was Bolivia in 1965. What were your
                        responsibilities there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: I went as Executive Assistant to the Ambassador. It was a newly created
                    position in the Embassy, in response to the Administration's desire to have
                    closer linkages between program activities and budgetary requirements. During
                    this period, programming budget in the Department took the form of CCPS
                    (Comprehensive Country Programming System). I was sent there along with some
                    twenty-five other relatively junior officers around the world, to run the CCPS
                    and to serve as a staff aid to the Ambassador. The CCPS required the
                    identification to a considerable degree of precision the policy objectives that
                    were to be achieved in the country by the US elements. In that sense, it was a
                    very useful exercise. We had to disaggregate these policy objectives into
                    discrete lines of actions or strategies designed to attain those objectives.
                    Then we had to relate somehow the priorities assigned to these objectives to
                    budgetary allocations. The idea of identifying your objectives more precisely
                    and the idea of disaggregating those objectives and the idea of designing your
                    strategies and course of actions quite carefully to meet the objectives, seemed
                    to me and everyone else a great improvement on previous practices. The system
                    however broke down on the assumption that there was a linkage between the
                    objectives and the resources devoted to attaining them. I drew the conclusion
                    that sometimes the most important objectives might be political—for example,
                    sustaining a democratic government in the face of hostile military or subversive
                    threat—which might be sustained the best by just having the Ambassador talking
                    to two or three key people and stopping the undermining. The resources involved
                    would be nil. On the other hand, your fifth most important objective might be
                    the development in Bolivia of the Chapare unsettled Region which might be a very
                    resource intensive goal—building roads and other infrastructure, moving people
                    into the area. So there is no correlation between how important an objective
                    might be and the resource allocations. The assumption behind CCPS that there was
                    such a correlation was just wrong.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There are a lot of things that can't be quantified. But in
                        the sense that it forced people to look at what they were trying to achieve,
                        it was a very valid exercise.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Another aspect of CCPS was that, at least in theory, you would be able to
                    identify the presence of individuals and agencies of the US Government in the
                    country that were not really contributing to our foreign policy objectives.
                    Those positions could be eliminated and the people returned to the United
                    States. Indeed, as recently as 1977 or 1978, in London the State Department
                    inspectors discovered 17 or 18 people in the British Defense Department who were
                    completely unknown to the Embassy. It could have been that 20 years earlier or
                    whenever the program started, the Embassy may have been aware of their presence,
                    but over a period of time, lost track of the program while these US government
                    employees continued to go along merrily doing whatever it was they were
                    doing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Bolivia in 1965-67 when you were
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: As always in Bolivia, the situation was extremely poor. The country
                    depended largely on its earnings from its tin mines. The political situation was
                    that the Bolivian revolution, which began in 1952 and was a real
                    revolution—changed land tenure patterns, changed land ownership, gave rights to
                    the rural campesinos, who had been essentially disenfranchised and treated as
                    serfs—was ended by a military intervention in 1964, when the military threw out
                    President Victor Paz Estenssoro. The military closed his political party and
                    took over. It was initially at least a stressful period because they overthrow
                    of a democratic government was seen as a set-back for the Alliance for Progress.
                    Over the near term, the Bolivian military agreed to return to democratic rule,
                    had elections which brought, not surprisingly, a military officer, to the office
                    of President.</p>
                <p>Our Ambassador at the time was Doug Henderson, who was very good. He was a first
                    class human being. That is also true of Jack Bell; both were extremely able and
                    admirable people. We had an enormous AID mission in Bolivia in the mid 60s. We
                    were putting in big bucks in development funding for direct budget support of
                    the Bolivian government. There were two types of budget support: one was direct
                    allocation of US appropriated dollars that were given to the Bolivian government
                    for mutually agreed upon uses to permit them to carry out their functions and
                    the other was called “extraordinary government budget support” which was
                    entirely funded from local currencies accumulated by the US government from the
                    sale of PL 480 food sales and distributions. We basically fed the country of
                    Bolivia for a long, long time and generated enormous amounts of local currency.
                    We used that currency for developmental ends; much, but not all, went to the
                    Bolivian government to fund programs that both they and we considered essential.
                    At one time, the AID Director, Irving Tragen, said to me that we controlled over
                    60% of the Bolivian currency. Here was the United States controlling 60% of
                    another country's currency.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, that kind of situation also has great dangers.
                        What was the view of the Embassy in having all this power?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: The view of the upper levels of the Embassy and the AID mission, which I
                    got to know pretty well through my CCPS assignment (all resource related
                    questions used to come to my desk before going to the Ambassador, at least in
                    theory, which gave me as a junior officer an unusual broad overview of the
                    Country Team and US inter-agency operations) had a concern about our deep
                    involvement. When I arrived, we were in the process of phasing out the direct
                    budgetary support and the local currencysupport. The direct dollar support was
                    being phased out at approximately 20% per year under what was known as the
                    “Sullivan” plan. It was totally phased out in 1967. With it, there was a major
                    restructuring of the Bolivian government.</p>
                <p>The local currency support was a little trickier because we still owned the
                    money. We could either burn it or spend it. The question was how we were
                    spending it. It was hard to find developmental ways to spend local currencies
                    other than directly supporting government programs—wages, etc. So the phase out
                    of that program took a little bit longer until the local currency was
                    exhausted.</p>
                <p>There was a concern at the Embassy that its role was too big and clearly Irv
                    Tragen, who was in my time in the Foreign Service during which I associated with
                    a lot of AID programs, was by far the best mission director I ever encountered,
                    both conceptually and in dealing with governments and people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tells us about the Bolivian miners.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: They would occasionally be unhappy with the central government, usually as
                    result of their wages not being increased as rapidly as the inflation or that
                    the government had taken some action to close down the less productive tin
                    mines. That would bring as many as 50,000 miners to La Paz where they would
                    march down the streets with their mining gear and sticks of dynamite tucked into
                    their belts. It was quite a dramatic scene. In La Paz, at least, they rarely set
                    off the dynamite, but tales of their dynamite activities at the mines are
                    legion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we during your tour in Bolivia very much involved in
                        the drug issue?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: It was not a significant matter. Later, during the 1972-74 period, I was
                    the Bolivian desk officer when the drug issue was a major one, calling for White
                    House interest. There were special task forces to deal with the narcotic issue.
                    Needless to say, most of those efforts were fruitless and the situation
                    continued to deteriorate simply because the market for the products grew and
                    grew.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After nine months of international labor training, you
                        went to El Salvador and were there from 1967 to 1971. What was the situation
                        in San Salvador when you arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Politically, the military, essentially reform minded, under Julio Rivera,
                    who had just left the Presidency when I arrived, had assumed power. Power had
                    flowed from the traditional oligarchy to the military, which pursued development
                    and other strategies which the oligarchy did not like very much. It tried to
                    dull the cutting edge of the military's reform process, usually with some
                    success. Nevertheless, there was still a feeling of reform progress. The first
                    several legislative elections under President Rivera were by all accounts free
                    and open. The Presidential elections for his succession which brought Fidel
                    Sanchez, another military officer, to the office was probably the most open
                    Presidential election ever held in El Salvador up to that time. The Christian
                    Democratic Party, which was a new party in existence only three or four years,
                    claimed it had won that election, but I am not sure that even it believed it. It
                    was nothing like 1972 when there was blatant and open fraud which everybody
                    could see. So essentially while I was there, it was a very hopeful period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were our interests in El Salvador at this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Economic development was our overriding interest. We didn't have a great
                    deal of investment; it was not a large market, but we felt that El Salvador
                    needed help, needed the inoculation against Castro's subversion. El Salvador was
                    also a country that was marked by sharp economic differences between a small
                    elite and a mass of people at or below the poverty line. You had cautious
                    movement toward reform, but at the same time, it was a repressive society—less
                    repressive than five years earlier and much less repressive than it had been
                    thirty years previously, but still a repressive society.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the accusations against the Foreign Service and the
                        Department that has been with us for a long time is that we tend to deal
                        with the elite group at the top, ignoring the large masses below. How did
                        the Embassy work in a situation such as El Salvador?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>BINNS: When I went there, our Ambassador was Raul Castro, a political appointee.
                    He later became our Ambassador to Bolivia and then Governor of Arizona and later
                    became our Ambassador to Argentina. He did quite a good job in El Salvador, less
                    good jobs in Bolivia and Argentina. I felt that in El Salvador we were too close
                    to the ruling party; not too close to the oligarchy because for the most part we
                    didn't have much to do with it. To the extent that the accusation you mentioned
                    might be applied to El Salvador, it is incorrect. But we were close to the
                    ruling political party, which was in some respect influenced by the oligarchy,
                    but only as one of several factors. My job was that of Labor Attach�, which
                    required me to establish contacts with trade unions. I supervised a labor
                    development program which was conducted by the American Institute for Free Labor
                    Development and financed by AID. So I worked for the Embassy in a political
                    position and for AID as a program director. I persuaded the Ambassador that we
                    needed to improve our contacts with the Christian Democrats; I persuaded the
                    Ambassador that we needed to reach out beyond just the trade unions that were
                    affiliated with the regional democratic labor movement and reach out to the
                    Christian Democratic labor movement with which we had no contacts. We had to
                    establish at least lines of communications with a communist affiliated trade
                    union center. So I was out a lot talking to people who had had no previous
                    contact with the Embassy and to whom the Embassy had previously not paid much
                    attention.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador did not have the Christian Democrats or the labor leaders over for
                    dinner, but he would certainly include them in larger functions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why couldn't the Christian Democrats be invited for
                        dinner?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: I didn't say they couldn't be invited; I just said that the Ambassador
                    didn't. The two principal leaders of the C.D. Party—Napoleon Duarte and Abraham
                    Rodriguez—were distinguished leaders. But the Ambassador was basically a
                    conservative, even though a Democrat. He felt more comfortable with the upper
                    middle class which was predominantly affiliated with the ruling National
                    Conciliation Party.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any problems with any parts of the US
                        Government in your role as Labor Officer?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>BINNS: In our goals and aims, there was consistency among all agencies—to the
                    extent that I was ever aware of what others were trying to do. On the other
                    hand, there was a real egregious case in which the CIA attempted to enlist a
                    leading labor leader with whom I had worked with very closely. They put him on
                    their payroll; it caused him lots of problems and didn't help us. Prior to that
                    time, he had been very willing to work with us. We gained nothing from the
                    Agency's efforts except to gain some unvarnished intelligence about what was
                    going on or what his views of the labor movement were. It was a dopey action for
                    which we and the labor leader paid a price. But basically, all agencies were
                    pursuing the same goals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that just points out that putting foreigners on US
                        payrolls does not give you information that you couldn't get in overt
                        manner.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: There was another probably even more egregious case. CIA Had a very good
                    penetration of the Christian Democratic Party. They were paying a senior member
                    of the Party, who I am pretty sure I know who it was. After some time, I was
                    able to build up very good relationships with Duarte, Rodriguez and other senior
                    party leaders, including Fidel Chavez, now the Presidential candidate, but who
                    at that time was a young man who was a good friend. We were getting more
                    information than we needed about what the CD Party thought about issues, their
                    aims and strategies. At one point, Duarte said to me that if we wanted to give
                    them money, it would be welcomed. He said they would take money from anywhere.
                    It was not a plea for recruitment, but just his reflection on the US activities.
                    Senior members of the Party knew that one of their members had been become a CIA
                    agent because he had told them so. They used that channel as a way to get their
                    message to the Embassy. From their point of view, it was a perfectly legitimate
                    approach under the circumstances.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the Embassy view the “Great Soccer War”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: There were some very interesting side aspects. Basically, the demographic
                    pressure in El Salvador was so great that over a period of approximately twenty
                    years, large numbers of Salvadoran had migrated illegally to Honduras, which had
                    a lot of land, almost free for the taking. It had employment opportunities; it
                    had banana plantations which paid much better than any employment in El
                    Salvador. There were probably between 100,000-200,000 illegal Salvadoran in
                    Honduras. The Hondurans viewed the Salvadoran as taking the best jobs because
                    the Salvadoran have a deserved reputation as being extremely hard workers.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>In 1969, for reasons that I still don't clearly understand—partially due to
                    domestic politics, partially conscious effort to divert popular attention from
                    domestic problems toward the presence of the Salvadoran immigrants, partially
                    because of the football (soccer) rivalry in the World Cup preliminaries—tension
                    between Honduras and El Salvador rose after a game in El Salvador which hosted
                    the Hondurans. The Salvadoran stayed up all night screaming in front of the
                    hotel where the Honduras team was playing so that no one could sleep. It was
                    trivia, but shortly after that, riots broke out in Honduras where Salvadoran
                    were dragged out of their homes, beaten, driven off jobs, brutalized. Obviously,
                    the Honduran government sanctioned those mob actions. Literally thousands of
                    Salvadoran immigrated back to El Salvador, including some who had lived in
                    Honduras for as long as twenty years. Many were in bad physical condition
                    because they had been beaten or because they had to walk fifty or hundred miles
                    to the border. It was a very, very bad situations. Tensions were rising
                    dramatically. Both military groups were making noises about the each other's
                    barbarity. Finally, in July 1969, the Salvadoran armed forces launched a
                    military attack on Honduras, driving twenty to thirty kilometers into the
                    country. They repelled the Honduran army's counter-attacks. Then they literally
                    ran out of gas and couldn't move forward. Within 100 hours, the OAS had
                    intervened and a truce was established. Ultimately, the Salvadoran withdrew.
                    Interestingly enough, in the days preceding the outbreak of the war, we were
                    extremely concerned about the possibility of a Salvadoran incursion into
                    Honduras. There were a lot of reasons why we didn't want that to happen, but
                    suffice it to say, our efforts to avoid the war were unsuccessful.</p>
                <p>Our Ambassador at the time in El Salvador was Bill Bowdler, who at every Country
                    Team meeting and in between was asking for the best intelligence available on
                    what the Salvadoran army was doing. He encouraged the members of the MilGroup to
                    circulate among the military, particularly in the outlying areas to see whether
                    there were any signs of mobilization. He wanted daily meetings to bring all the
                    intelligence together. The same injunction was placed on the Defense Attach� and
                    the Political section. The key was the military. During the prewar period of
                    several weeks, our MilGroup people would return and report that saw no sign of
                    any movement whatsoever or any signs of mobilization. They reported that the
                    Salvadoran army was not doing any of the things that one might expect from a
                    military force preparing for action. On the other hand, we had political leaders
                    saying to us that war was likely and that El Salvador would attack Honduras. Our
                    military officers could not corroborate this prediction. CIA could not get any
                    corroboration, because their key liaison contact was a senior military officer
                    who was involved in the mobilization plans. But he was a liaison man; CIA had
                    not penetrated the military.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>The most interesting aspect, which we discovered only later, was that the
                    commander of our MilGroup and the chief of our Army MilGroup section, were
                    meeting daily for long periods with the general staff of the Salvadoran armed
                    forces, planning their mobilization and their attack on Honduras. It blew our
                    minds, but it absolutely true. As far as we know, these American military
                    officers were on their own and not under Washington instructions, as far as we
                    were able to ascertain. They were involved in Salvadoran activities without
                    knowledge of the other members of the MilGroup and certainly without the
                    knowledge of the Embassy. One could argue that the other members of the MilGroup
                    might have suspected something or were pretty stupid.</p>
                <p>The way we discovered this atrocious negligence of duty was even more
                    extraordinary than the fact itself. When the Salvadoran attacked Honduras, they
                    immediately violated the Security Assistance agreement by using the equipment
                    and munitions that we had provided for something other than self-defense and
                    against a non-Soviet or communist power. We were required by law and by reason
                    to suspend our military assistance program which meant withdrawing all our
                    advisors from all Salvadoran units and breaking all relationships with the
                    Salvadoran military. That was very politically heart-felt in Washington because
                    the whole incursion came as a great surprise. The Embassy, except perhaps some
                    of the MilGroup, recognized that the suspension of assistance was the only right
                    and proper response that could be made. So we stopped all supplies. That mean
                    for example that all Salvadoran planes were immediately grounded for lack of
                    spare parts.</p>
                <p>This greatly upset the Salvadoran. They called the Ambassador in and told him
                    that they were very upset. He told them that his hands were tied; they had
                    violated an agreement and our law was quite clear. We didn't have any choice.
                    The Salvadoran President said that to show his government's displeasure he would
                    declare persona-non-grata the MilGroup commander. The chief of the army section
                    and the chief of the air force section. We considered unfortunate, but weren't
                    overly upset since there was not to be a military assistance program for a while
                    anyway. The Salvadoran gave our military officers a week to pack up and go home.
                    Soon after the President's action, the MilGroup commander came to the Ambassador
                    and said: “Mr. Ambassador, it is very unfair that I being declared p.n.g. It is
                    not fair. Nevertheless, I would like to pay farewell calls on the chiefs of
                    staff of the armed forces, the Minister of Defense and others. But since I can't
                    have anything to do with them, would you grant me an exception?”. The Ambassador
                    agreed that it was decent thing to do.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>It turned out that the MilGroup commander, who was a colonel and a graduate of
                    West Point, didn't speak a word of Spanish. So he took with him a Puerto Rican
                    officer, a major, as a translator and note-taker. When they returned from the
                    farewell calls, the colonel instructed the major to prepare memoranda of
                    conversation. The major sent the drafts to the colonel, who cut them to bits so
                    that nothing that had transpired was left in memoranda. In fact, the MilGroup
                    commander put in a lot of stuff that had not transpired. The major, who was not
                    too smart, went to his superior, who was the number two in the army section.
                    That officer read the originals and the corrected versions. In the original
                    there was comment made by the colonel to the effect that the problem between the
                    US and El Salvador was the American Ambassador and his failure to perceive and
                    support legitimate Salvadoran aspirations. Furthermore, the Ambassador's
                    unilateral decision to suspend assistance was unwarranted. The colonel was
                    blaming the Ambassador for everything that the US government had done to punish
                    the Salvadoran. All that was in the originals of the memcons. The colonel had of
                    course scratched all of that out and had put in other stuff. The number two in
                    the army section was also a West Pointer couldn't believe what had happened; he
                    took the two documents home, slept on them and at 7:30 the next morning went to
                    the Ambassador's residence with the papers. He said that his commanding officer
                    had done this; that it was unconscionable and that he couldn't support it and
                    thought that the Ambassador should be aware of what had transpired. The colonel
                    was then given twenty-fours to leave. Subsequently, the chief of staff of the
                    Salvadoran armed forces, at a party, approached the Ambassador and said:” One
                    thing about that war with Honduras that always confused us was your strong
                    reaction when in fact you helped us plan the mobilization”. He then proceeded to
                    describe the activities of the American military officers, still puzzled why the
                    Americans had helped to plan the invasion and then had cut off military
                    assistance when it happened.</p>
                <p>The whole story was unbelievable. Bowdler actually laughed. He had an opportunity
                    when the versions of the memoranda of conversations were brought to him and the
                    subsequent immediate despatch of the MilGroup commander, there had been a lot of
                    cable traffic with Southern Command, whose commanding general wanted to
                    court-martial the colonel. SouthCom took the matter very seriously, but Bowdler,
                    being more decent than I would have been under those circumstances, decided
                    against that on the grounds that a court martial would raise an unnecessary
                    uproar. He recommended that the colonel just be put out to pasture and be
                    permitted to retire in a year or so.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Washington was appalled by the whole incident. It was the most egregious thing I
                    have ever seen. At that time, out bilateral military assistance agreements for
                    the most part required the host country to pay for all the expenses related of
                    the American military—rental allowances, some contributions to the US government
                    for salaries and other expenses. The officers were provided cars by the host
                    government. So many of the MilGroup officers came to view themselves as much, if
                    not more, agents of the host government's military because that was who
                    supported them—financially and in other ways. They had allegiance to the
                    Embassy, SouthCom and the host government's military establishment. I have seen
                    similar attitudinal problems in Bolivia where a MilGroup commander was removed
                    by Ambassador Doug Henderson, basically for articulating his views on his
                    relationships; he felt that he was responsible to the Ambassador for certain
                    things and to the Bolivians for others. He said that he always had to chose
                    between the two. Henderson said that he admired his frankness, but that under
                    the circumstances, it was best for the officer to leave the country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell us a little about Bill Bowdler, who was a very
                        important figure in our Central America policy development.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Bowdler was a lot different from Raul Castro. He did have Christian
                    Democrats, labor people and others to his house for dinner. He was more informal
                    and thoughtful. He was profound. He did act decisively after the MilGroup
                    incident, but he was much less forceful than Douglas Henderson. He was more of
                    an intellectual. He had trouble with US military elsewhere as well. He had an
                    Air Attach� in South Africa who acted contrary to existing US government and
                    Embassy policy and got us into a big flab with the South African government by
                    flying the Embassy airplane over the South African nuclear site, took
                    photographs and then left the camera in the plane, where it was confiscated by
                    the authorities. There was no intelligence that he could have collected that
                    wasn't already available to us. The South Africans knew where he was because
                    they watched him and he violated existing inter-agency procedures on how you get
                    approval for intelligence missions of that sort. It was a royal screw up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left El Salvador in 1971 and were assigned to ARA.
                        What were your responsibilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: I started out on the Inter-Departmental Group (IG) staff. That staff is
                    now know as the Regional Policy Office in ARA. One of our functions is to
                    coordinate our policy in the region and oversee its conduct. In the Johnson and
                    Nixon Administrations, a lot of power was given to these inter-departmental
                    groups, which were chaired by the State Department's Assistant Secretary. The
                    IGs made resource allocations and other policy decisions. The inter-departmental
                    process reached its zenith during Henry Kissinger's term as National Security
                    Advisor. The process eroded somewhat after he moved to the State Department
                    because he didn't need that elaborate system there to influence what was going
                    on. In the Reagan period, you had anarchy—there was no process, certainly as far
                    as Central America was concerned.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>I was dealing with all of Latin American when I was on the IG staff. Ever since
                    the beginning of my tour in El Salvador, I had the feeling that the region was
                    being neglected by the top policy makers. For example, in the Johnson
                    Administration, you could observe the steady decline of economic and security
                    assistance levels and other resources allocated to that region.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were our major interests in Latin America in the
                        early 70s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: I would say that the major interest of the IG staff was to get Henry
                    Kissinger's attention to a policy review paper on Latin America—called a
                    National Security Study Memorandum (NSSM) at the time. Shortly after taking
                    office, Kissinger sent out a NSSM directing ARA to conduct an inter-agency study
                    of our policy toward Latin America. He wanted to know where we should be going.
                    The study process was underway when I got to the IG staff. It was still going on
                    twelve months later when I left the IG staff. It would be scheduled for an NSC
                    review and then something else would arise to take it off the agenda. Three
                    months later we would get a new NSSM telling us to redo the study, which we
                    would do. Then we send it back to the NSC, but it never got on the agenda.
                    Kissinger had a bipolar world view.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you looked at Latin America, how did Mexico fit
                        in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Mexico has a unique role because of our inter-dependence and the many
                    faceted relationship that we have with that country stemming from its proximity.
                    It doesn't therefor fit very neatly with the rest of the Hemisphere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1972, you moved to be the Bolivian desk officer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Yes. By the time I arrived, Che Guevara had already been done away with.
                    Development and the restitution of democracy were the big issues. President
                    Renhad been killed in a helicopter accident. He was succeeded by his
                    Vice-President, who was extremely weak with no political base. He was hand
                    chosen and seemed to be the kind of Vice President selected by a number of
                    political leaders around the world. But he couldn't hold on and the military
                    took power. We objected and tried to push the Bolivians toward democracy. There
                    were more coups. We just tried to get our relationships with the Bolivians
                    straightened out. Narcotics had become an issue, but it was not yet anywhere
                    near the top of the agenda—maybe it was third or fourth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of ARA after your tours in the
                        field?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>BINNS: Whenever we thought that we weren't getting the proper amount of top level
                    attention, we would look at the Bureau of African Affairs and felt better.
                    Clearly, we weren't the Bureau of European Affairs, which was the glamor bureau
                    and the Bureau of Near East and South Asia Affairs, because of the region's
                    volatility probably get the lion's share of resources. The Bureau of Far Eastern
                    Affairs had a war. The Reagan administration changed all that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you had a major change of pace. How did that
                        happen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Thanks to Henry Kissinger and his GLOP theory. He reputedly, after a
                    hemispheric OAS Foreign Ministers meeting in Mexico, where he met with all our
                    Ambassadors in Latin America, was appalled by their alleged lack of
                    understanding and appreciation for the great bipolar issues of the day and felt
                    that they were very parochial; he felt that this was a problem in the Foreign
                    Service and in his usual insightful, but in the short term probably stupid, was
                    decreed that 60% of all assignments made in the next period would be made to
                    areas outside an individual's area of specialization. Hence, if one were a
                    Chinese language officer and an East Asian expert, he could expect to be
                    assigned perhaps to Africa or the Middle East or Latin America. A Europeanist
                    could go anywhere, but 60% of all officers were not to go to their areas of
                    special knowledge and experience.</p>
                <p>I had been scheduled to go to Guatemala as chief of the Political Section. That
                    was never consummated because of GLOP and the Office of Personnel proposed that
                    I go to Madrid as Labor Attach�, which would have been a natural. As it turned
                    out, there were problems with my acceptability to the AFL-CIO for that
                    assignment. Because in the delay in getting that clearance, Personnel, assigned
                    me to London in the Political Section, where a vacancy had unexpectedly
                    developed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me pursue your comment about the AFL-CIO. Was that
                        procedural problem or a policy problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>BINNS: I am not sure what kind of problem it was. Labor Attach� assignments are
                    referred to the Department of labor for approval. It checks with the AFL-CIO. If
                    the latter has an objection, for whatever reason, it will make it known to the
                    Department of Labor, which in turn will then not concur in the State
                    Department's proposed assignment. The Director general has the authority to make
                    the assignment anyway. In this particular case, we had a pusillanimous Director
                    General and Personnel staff which didn't want to do that. Part of the problem
                    was not so much that they disliked me, but they had someone they liked better.
                    The Labor Department blamed it on the AFL-CIO; my few contacts there said it was
                    not the AFL-CIO which had vetoed the assignment. My own guess is that the jerk
                    in Labor Department, who was former Foreign Service officer whom I didn't like,
                    made little effort to do anything. It turned out that the Madrid assignment was
                    made in Solomonic fashion with neither of the contenders getting there in the
                    end by extending the officer then in Madrid for another year. In any case, I did
                    very well by the snafu.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You served in London from 1974 to 1979—five years. What
                        was your assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: I started out working on the Labor Party, the Northern Ireland issue, the
                    Scottish and Welsh national issues and I was the resident expert on Latin
                    America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lets' start with Northern Ireland. What were we doing on
                        this subject?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Kingman Brewster, who was my Ambassador at the end of my tour in London,
                    put it best. He said: “In law, you have to distinguish between a problem and a
                    fact. The problem you can resolve; the fact you have to accept. Northern Ireland
                    clearly appears to be a fact”. That sums it up precisely. What we in the Embassy
                    tried to do, not always with success, was to try to keep the United States out
                    of it. We had no business in it; we wished both sides—the Irish, the British,
                    the Ulstermen Protestants and the Catholics—well. But it was not our problem or
                    our fact. There was and still may be, although less so, a tendency particularly
                    in the Irish-American community, top try to get the United States involved in
                    the resolution of what they perceive to see as the “Northern Island problem” as
                    opposed to the “Northern Ireland fact”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any pressures from people like Senator Kennedy
                        and Speaker Tip O'Neill, both of whom represented large Irish-American
                        communities, on behalf of the Northern Ireland Catholics?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>BINNS: In 1974, when I went to London, Ted Kennedy had made some statements that
                    upset the British. They were outraged by his involvement which they felt was
                    based on ignorance of the situation in Northern Ireland. They thought that his
                    statements were unhelpful. In case of O'Neill, during my five years there, I
                    don't remember anything that he did that drew British outrage or even concern.
                    In that same period, Kennedy's activities became less obnoxious to the British;
                    he may have gained a better appreciation of the situation in Northern Ireland
                    and what the two governments were doing. In my last year in London, I became the
                    Political Counselor—chief of the Political Section. I had four different
                    Ambassadors while I was in London—Walter Annenberg, Elliot Richardson, Ann
                    Armstrong and Kingston Brewster.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the Northern Ireland case, we were not trying to play
                        the “honest broker”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: That was certainly the institutional preference. The State Department
                    didn't want to touch it because it was and still is a “tar baby” and something
                    over which have we really have no influence and no ability to affect.</p>
                <p>There was one compelling issue which to some extent is still an issue—or a
                    collection of issues. I refer to the fund raising by the IRA in the US, illegal
                    arm shipments from the US to Northern Ireland in support of the IRA, extradition
                    of people that the British want and who live in the US Those issues are always
                    with us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this period, how were we dealing with these IRA
                        problems and how did the British Government perceive our efforts?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: We condemned the IRA as government. Certainly there were members of
                    Congress—and not all were Irish-American. There were some Italian-Americans who
                    were very vocal—pro IRA. We supported the efforts of the Irish and British
                    governments to resolve the problem. We supported direct rule and power sharing.
                    There was a power sharing government for the first time in 1973-74 that
                    ultimately collapsed in the face of popular opposition. Power sharing called for
                    Catholic and Protestant politicians who formed a single government for the
                    Northern province. But it lacked popular support and was brought down by a labor
                    strike by Protestant workers. They closed the economy of the province and the
                    government collapsed and direct rule from Westminster followed—no local
                    Parliament, no local government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the status of the Welsh and Scottish
                        nationalities issues at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>BINNS: There was a major interest concerning Scotland. The national problem of
                    Wales is basically non-existent. There was an opportunity in 1979 for the Welsh
                    and Scots to vote on what the British called “devolution”—essentially the return
                    of powers from the central government to regional governments, which at the time
                    didn't exist. The regional governments would have to be established. In Wales,
                    about 70% of the people voted against devolution. In Scotland, of the people who
                    bothered to vote, about 60% voted in favor, but the referendum was so drafted
                    that in order to be approved, it required the support of 60% of registered
                    voters. In Scotland, the vote fell short of it. So there was no devolution there
                    either. However in Scotland, nationalism is alive although not well. In Wales,
                    it is a dead issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As a political officer and subsequently Counselor, what
                        were your main concerns?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: It was a matter of avoiding problems. We tried to have the British
                    government to continue to support our strategic interests in NATO and other
                    parts of the world. The British, through the Commonwealth, an historical
                    association with and influence over areas of Africa, the Middle East and South
                    Asia that allow them to do things that we can't do. They can gain information
                    which we couldn't collect on our own. So they are very helpful to us. The
                    preservation of that collaboration, the preservation of their commitment to
                    NATO, the preservation of their position vis-a-vis the Soviet Union were the
                    main interests.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any major point of conflict with which you had
                        to deal?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: There a number of them, none of them earth-shaking. One thing that was of
                    concern was the leftward drift of the Labor Party, which, if it had continued,
                    might have threatened the British commitment to the alliance, threatened their
                    participation in European affairs and our collaboration in other areas of the
                    world. Michael Foote was identified with this left-wing strain in the Labor
                    party as was Neil Kinnock, the current Party leader. In fact he has brought the
                    party toward the right. What concerned us most was what we called “entryism”
                    which because of the Labor Party's structure, permitted extreme left wing
                    groups—usually Trotskyites—to enter a constituency party organization and with
                    twenty or thirty people who were willing to dedicate time to the effort, could
                    take over that organization. A Labor Party constituent party in Dorking, England
                    is no threat to the United States, but what they did, when they took over the
                    party, was to determine who the party's candidate for Parliament might be from
                    that constituency. Theoretically at least, if they were able to make this
                    “entryism” program stick, they could control and dominate the Parliamentary
                    party, which is, of course, when Labor wins an election, is what runs the
                    government.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>I arrived just after Ted Heath had lost the February elections. So Labor was in
                    power when I arrived and when I left in July 1979, Margaret Thatcher had just
                    come into office. So I served my London tour entirely with a Labor government.
                    Harold Wilson was the Prime Minister initially and he was followed by Jim
                    Callaghan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a book written about Wilson's overthrow. What
                        was that all about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: According to the person who advanced this theory, MI-5, which is the
                    domestic intelligence organization comparable in some, but not many, respects to
                    our FBI, felt that Wilson, for a long, convoluted and not very persuasive series
                    of reasons, was an agent of influence for the Soviet Union. Some people say that
                    helped contribute to his resignation and in turning the plot over to Callaghan.
                    The plot was that the MI-5 people and their cohorts were going to make this
                    public and that threat caused Wilson to step down. I don't believe a word of
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we comfortable with a Labor government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Quite. They were extremely supportive not only in NATO but also vis-a-vis
                    the European Community, etc. We might have a discrete problem here and
                    there—e.g., shipping arms to Chile—but no major issues. There were extensive
                    consultations on all issues, global as well as local. Our level of foreign
                    policy cooperation and consultation was closer with the British than any other
                    foreign country. Not because the British were better allies than for example the
                    Germans, but because the British through the Commonwealth and their historical
                    connections, had a greater reach than others.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to contact anyone in the British
                        government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: It was a unique experience for me that a foreign government was so open.
                    People were extremely open with us. It was almost like working in Washington,
                    maybe even better.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find it a problem to keep on top of all the
                        relationships between the Embassy and the government? Or of telephonic
                        conversations between Washington and the British government?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>BINNS: I think that was true in the U.K. and some other posts. A lot of it has to
                    do with who the Ambassador is. Clearly during the Annenberg period, the British,
                    while many liked him personally, did not consider him to be a “serious”
                    representative. As a consequence, the British began to conduct more business
                    through their Embassy in Washington than through us in London. I think that
                    changed with the advent of Elliot Richardson, who was probably at that time, at
                    his peak of fame. He was regarded as a “serious” person and politician and was
                    extremely connected in the US; Annenberg's departure coincided almost with a
                    change in the U.S. government. I think then the Labor government was more
                    comfortable dealing with us than with unknown persons in the State Department
                    and other agencies in Washington. Later, they solved that perception by changing
                    their ambassador in Washington. But clearly the change of our ambassadors in
                    London shifted the burden of dialogue from the British Embassy in Washington to
                    the American Embassy in London.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was Anne Armstrong regarded?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: She was extremely well liked and earned everyone's respect—British as well
                    a s Embassy staff—because of her intelligence and her ability to pick up very
                    quickly on an issue. While her appointment initially was not greeted with a
                    great deal of enthusiasm, she won the respect of all through her intelligence,
                    diligence and the seriousness of her approach to her job. Both Richardson and
                    Armstrong had rather brief periods in London—a year plus. That of course
                    increased the burdens on the Embassy's professional staff. We were blessed
                    during this period with Ron Spiers as the DCM—an extremely able officer who had
                    had a distinguished career. He was followed by Ed Streator, who was also a very
                    able and distinguished officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Brewster had a much longer tour. He had been President of
                        Yale. How did he perform?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: He was an outstanding Ambassador. He was the best that I served, partly
                    because he had a longer tenure, but also because of his relationship with Cy
                    Vance, the Secretary of State. They were close personally and Brewster could
                    reach Vance at any time and essentially get anything he wanted out of the State
                    Department. Unless you have witnessed such a relationship, you don't realize how
                    helpful it can be, whether you are talking about resources, policy issues or
                    anything else. Brewster could make things happen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is an interesting point. It is often assumed that a
                        political appointee has automatic access to people in power. This is not
                        always the case. But it is certainly helpful an Ambassador who has direct
                        access to the Secretary of State instead of some White House staffer.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>BINNS: That is certainly true. There are many issues that are resolved by the
                    White House, either through the NSC or through a staffer to the President.
                    Rarely, although I am sure it happens, the issue is resolved by a direct call to
                    the President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did Carter relate to the British?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Callaghan had a very strong and close relationship with Henry Kissinger.
                    They were two different types, but they struck it off very well. They were
                    personally close. For example, when Callaghan was named a “free man” of Cardiff,
                    Wales, which was quite an honor, Henry Kissinger came from the United States to
                    participate in the ceremonies at Callaghan's invitation. That was a personal
                    gesture; it was not a policy matter; the two just liked each other considerably.
                    That did not happen in the Carter period, in part because Vance was not the same
                    type as Kissinger. Callaghan had become Prime Minister; David Owen was the
                    Foreign Secretary and the same chemistry that existed between Kissinger and
                    Callaghan did not flow between Vance and Owens. On the other hand, the Labor
                    party liked Jimmy Carter a lot and particularly were pleased with is emphasis on
                    human rights. The decision on the neutron bomb, for example, blind sided the
                    British, who felt that it was handled very amateurishly.</p>
                <p>In NATO, we had mooted the possibility of deploying an advance nuclear weapon
                    that had the advantage of destroying targets by radiation—it killed the men
                    inside a tank, but not the tank. It could be dropped on an occupied village for
                    example and not destroy it, although the occupying army would be killed.
                    Unfortunately, it would also kill any civilians in the village as well. There
                    would be no long term radiation effect. It was believed that it was a partial
                    answer to the West German and other continental European concerns about the
                    possible destructiveness of nuclear war in Europe. We labored long and hard to
                    persuade our allies that this was the weapon of the future and necessary for the
                    defense of Western Europe. They were not easily convinced; in fact, the Germans
                    were never convinced at all. Others went along with varying degrees of
                    reluctance and agreed with the decision. At the last minute, without previous
                    consultation—which was the key—, the Administration decided not to deploy the
                    neutron weapon. Because a lot of people had their arms twisted and had been
                    forced to agree to decision to deploy—a decision with which they were somewhat
                    uncomfortable and which was unpopular in their countries—they felt they had been
                    left out on a limb and that Carter then sawed off the limb. If he had consulted
                    with them, they could have scrambled back to safety.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the US view Thatcher's election at the time it
                        happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>BINNS: As George Brown once said, after he had lost his Parliamentary seat:
                    “Democracy is democ”. We are democrats and we think democracy is a great thing,
                    so we were happy to deal with her. Personally, I never liked her. I found her
                    very hard edged, opinionated, not open to reason and argument in my limited
                    contacts with her at dinner parties and social events. For the Embassy, it was
                    business as usual.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your next assignment came in 1979 as Deputy chief of
                        Mission in San Jose, Costa Rica. You were there for a little more than a
                        year. How did you feel about that assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: It was a great assignment. I lobbied hard to get it and I got it. After I
                    got there, the Ambassador stayed for a couple of months and then went on leave,
                    returned briefly and went on to another post. So I was Charg� for nine of the
                    thirteen months I was there.</p>
                <p>Costa Rica was a dramatic change from my previous assignments in Central America.
                    Costa Rica is absolutely atypical for Central America. It is a social democracy;
                    there is relative economic equity; the wealth of the nation is spread relatively
                    evenly. The literacy rate was somewhere in the 90 percentile. There was no
                    abject poverty. It was a very delightful place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any particular problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: I got to Costa Rica about a week after the Sandinistas had taken power in
                    Nicaragua. So most of our efforts were related in one form or another to
                    Nicaragua and to Cuba, as well. The Costa Ricans had agreed to allow Cuba to use
                    their country as the resupply point for the Sandinistas during the last year
                    before they took power. They had gained considerable ground in Costa Rica and
                    had unusual relationship with the President and his family. They paid
                    substantial amounts of money to the President's son in order to get the supply
                    base rights.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the US role in Costa Rica while the Sandinistas
                        were using the country as a base?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: We certainly voiced objections. We felt that it was an unwise thing for
                    the Costa Ricans to do. I was not in Costa Rican during this period. But I know
                    that we thought it was improper according to international law; we thought is
                    was a short-sighted Costa Rican policy—probably senseless; we thought that
                    rather than supporting the Sandinistas, they would have been wiser to support
                    our efforts and those of the OAS to force Somoza out and replace him with a
                    transitional government. They didn't agree and being a sovereign state, they
                    conducted themselves accordingly.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you arrived in Costa Rica, the Sandinistas were
                        establishing themselves in Nicaragua. How did that impact US-Costa Rican
                        relationships?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: After the fact—and perhaps even before—, the Costa Ricans realized that
                    there was a risk with the Sandinistas—being Marxists-Leninists— might not be
                    democratic reformers. They certainly liked to think that the Sandinistas were
                    the latter; there were some reasons to believe that. Thee were some people in
                    the Sandinista movement who were legitimate democrats. When I got to Costa Rica,
                    we were in a pragmatic mode. The Cost Ricans had approached us and told us that
                    they could have some influence with the Sandinistas; that the Sandinistas owed
                    them a lot and that the Costa Ricans would try to use that influence to get a
                    viable democracy established in Nicaragua. We told them we would be most pleased
                    to cooperate to achieve that end. We started to put joint programs together,
                    discussing ideas on what might be done to keep the Sandinistas “honest” and
                    force them to hold open and free elections for Somoza's successor. They were
                    unsuccessful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you see the Sandinistas and the Nicaraguan
                        situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: I viewed the situation with considerable concern, but not alarm. I tended
                    to feel, based on my experiences in the region and in London where we exchanged
                    a lot of views with the British, including the Labor Party and the socialist
                    International—both supported the Sandinistas—, about the Sandinistas. There was
                    considerable hope that the Sandinistas could serve as a basis for democratic
                    regime as opposed to a totalitarian leftist government. That was ultimately
                    proven incorrect in part because it was self-fulfilling prophecy. There were
                    people who said there was no choice, that they would become totalitarian and
                    therefore we should treat them as such from the onset. If you would talk to
                    Larry Pezzulo, who was in the best position to know because he dealt with the
                    Sandinista government for a couple of years as our Ambassador, he would tell you
                    that had we adopted a different policy, events might have turned out
                    differently. There was some role for American influence; to be sure, less than
                    we would have hoped for, but there was some.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>For example, shortly after the Sandinistas took power, they asked the Costa
                    Ricans to help them with their educational system. They wanted to replicate the
                    Costa Rican experience; they wanted to educate their people. They asked the Cost
                    Ricans for any surplus teachers—e.g. retired—who would be willing to go to
                    Nicaragua to put a program together. Both countries became interested in the
                    project, but neither had the money for it. So we were asked to fund it. We told
                    the Cost Ricans we would review it. It was not a project that US could fund, so
                    we went to the World Bank, which was willing to fund something like 400 teachers
                    on a grant basis. It never happened because it turned out that this was not what
                    the Sandinistas wanted. The same situation arose with the Peace Corps. We
                    offered them a Peace Corps program; they voiced an initial interest, but never
                    made the decisions or took the steps necessary to start the process of
                    developing a Peace Corps project. We did provide Nicaragua economic assistance.
                    The Costa Ricans, along with the Panamanians, offered assistance in customs and
                    immigration procedures. Those were initially accepted and twenty or thirty Costa
                    Rican and Panamanians went to Nicaragua and started to work with what was left
                    of the Somoza custom and immigration services. Within four months, they were all
                    expelled and replaced by Cubans. Same with the teachers program; it became a
                    Cuban project.</p>
                <p>Before leaving my Costa Rican experience, I should mention the “Maria” boat
                    crisis. These were Cubans who wanted to flee Cuba and Castro was willing to let
                    them go. They could take small boats and anything else that would float were
                    allowed into Cuba to pick up those who wanted to leave and some who Castro
                    wanted to expel—whom we did not want in the United States. There was also an
                    airlift and many people were seeking asylum in various Latin American Embassies
                    in Havana—all who ultimately were permitted to leave Cuba. But the US didn't
                    want them and we were looking around for other havens. The Costa Ricans offered
                    temporary asylum for up to 10,000 escapees. We put together a so called
                    international conference on the issue; we got lot of inter-American
                    participation; not much European. The conference was held in San Jose which
                    didn't do a lot, but it was an issue with which we were dealing with and the
                    Costa Ricans were being very helpful. The Costa Rican offer was largely
                    self-generated; we were canvassing all the Latin American nations to see the
                    level of interest—Peru, for example, was very helpful. Once we had made the
                    request to Costa Rica, without any arm twisting, Carazo, the C.R. President,
                    agreed almost immediately.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your next assignment was as Ambassador to Honduras. How
                        did that come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>BINNS: I am not exactly sure. Bill Bowdler came to Costa Rica and said to me:
                    “Jack, you know you haven't been here very long, but I have a proposition to
                    make. I don't know whether you'll find it acceptable; I don't know if I were in
                    your shoes that I would accept it”. That piqued my interest. He said that the
                    Department had been watching what we were doing in Costa Rica and some of my
                    messages had reached the Seventh Floor. They thought I had done a real good job
                    and besides the Seventh Floor remembered me from London days. So Bowdler had
                    asked Harry Barnes, then Director General, if I could be considered for
                    Ambassador to Honduras, even though I was still in a relatively low rank.
                    Bowdler said if I accepted the offer, my name would be forwarded to the White
                    House for approval. I really didn't want to leave Costa Rica because it first of
                    all a very nice place and I was enjoying it immensely and secondly, I had a
                    daughter who was senior in high school, who would have to move for a third time
                    during her high school years, which would not have been a good thing for her.
                    She was very happy in Costa Rica and as it turned out, was very unhappy in
                    Honduras for a number of reasons. But after a family confab, we agreed that the
                    Ambassadorship was an opportunity that couldn't be passed. So I accepted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have problem being confirmed?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>BINNS: There were attempts to block the appointment from two quarters: a) the
                    right and B) and some non-Congressional Democratic opposition. The right
                    considered me too liberal—I was caught in one of the usual contests between
                    Senator Helms and the Department of State concerning Frank Ortiz, for whom Helms
                    wanted an Ambassadorial assignment which State didn't want to give (there were
                    some twelve Ambassadorial appointments that Helms was holding up at the time).
                    Ultimately, the Department did something for Ortiz and my appointment was
                    approved. The other problem stemmed from a Presidential Commission that Carter
                    appointed while I was in Costa Rica. It was supposed to study agriculture in the
                    Hemisphere to see what we could do to advance it so that Latin Americans could
                    feed themselves. It was headed by the former President of Florida University and
                    was composed of a distinguished group of farm experts, academics and some people
                    interested in economic development—one former AID Mission director, for example.
                    That Commission came to Costa Rica first for some reason and we scheduled to
                    talk to Costa Ricans knowledgeable in agricultural matters. It became clear
                    after the first couple of days that the Commissioners were almost unanimously
                    opposed and made no secret about it to land reform as was being proposed in El
                    Salvador at the time. Without exception, including the President, the Costa
                    Ricans favored land reform. When the Carter Commission left, I sent a NODIS
                    (very limited distribution to high ranking officials in the Department only). I
                    made a mistake of including other US Embassies in Central American for
                    distribution because the Commission was supposed to go to those posts. I sent
                    the cable because this was an American Presidential Commission ostensibly on a
                    fact finding mission that appeared to have predisposition against one of our
                    principal policies; i.e. the support of land reform in El Salvador. I thought
                    the Department and the White House should be made aware of this as well as my
                    colleagues in the posts that the Commission would visit. It happened that the
                    Commission went from San Jose to Guatemala where our Ambassador showed them the
                    cable. I am told that they hit the roof when they found out that I was reporting
                    their prejudices before the report was written. One of the members of that
                    Commission subsequently tried to stop my appointment. He stalled it, but didn't
                    stop it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Honduras from 1980 to 1981. What was the
                        situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: There had been a military rule in Honduras almost uninterruptedly since
                    1963. Briefly, there had been a popularly elected government in the early 70s
                    that served about eighteen months before the military replaced it. In light of
                    the events in Central America, especially Nicaragua and El Salvador, the
                    Honduran military had gotten religion and decided to get the problem of
                    governing off their hands and to return to democracy. We of course had been
                    twisting their arms and trying to force them in this direction for almost
                    fifteen years.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>The Honduran military had announced that it would hold elections and turn
                    governmental power to a democratically elected government. Basically, therefore,
                    my instructions were to do everything I could to make sure that those elections
                    took place and that there would be a peaceful transition to a constitutionally,
                    democratically elected government. It turned out that way. The election in
                    November 1981 was very close. There was an almost-coup in September of that
                    year, but it didn't occur.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What tools of influence did we have?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: The principal tool we had was the Honduran people, especially after the
                    military had announced that they wanted an election and a transition. The
                    political parties geared up. Popular sentiment supported the transition to
                    democratic government. We used every means at our disposal to underscore our
                    support of elections. Every speech I made—I made a lot of them—, every interview
                    I gave and in almost every meeting I had with Honduran officials or members of
                    the private sector, I underscored the importance we gave to the elections. I
                    also pointed out the potential consequences of not following their commitment by
                    pointing to El Salvador and Nicaragua. We were able to make to push the door
                    further open.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would you judge the ARA Bureau? What policies was it
                        pursuing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: It was trying to inoculate Honduras from the same disease that had
                    infected Nicaragua and El Salvador and potentially Guatemala; i.e. civil war. We
                    didn't need another communist-backed insurgency in the region and the best way
                    to do that was to make our best efforts to allow the people of Honduras to
                    determine their own future through a democratic process.</p>
                <p>During my period in Honduras, the Sandinistas were not much of a problem. Their
                    activities to spread the romance of revolution were couched more in evangelical
                    terms than in actual subversion. They were using Honduras as a base to provide
                    material—weapons and ammunition—to the insurgents in El Salvador. But they did
                    not actively try to subvert Honduras.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you receive instructions to try to stop the
                        Sandinistas from using Honduras as a transfer point?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>BINNS: Yes. I was trying to gain Honduran cooperation to make arms interdiction
                    more effective. We spent a lot of time on this issue and the Hondurans made one
                    seizure. The problem was that the Salvadoran insurgents and the Nicaraguans had
                    a pretty good apparatus. None of the seizures and very little of our successes
                    were based on any intelligence that shipments were coming. The evidence tended
                    to be circumstantial. The big shipment that was stopped came as the result of a
                    low level policeman seeing a warehouse that seemed to hold very suspicious
                    material. He went into one day when no one else was around and found a
                    semi-trailer, without the truck, with its top pulled back. That struck him as
                    very curious; he reported it and the police came and investigated the warehouse
                    and found a concealed basement that was filled with arms—several hundred US
                    combat weapons and munitions. When they looked at the trailer, it had once upon
                    a time been a refrigerated van. The cooling coils had been stripped out and the
                    space was used to store munitions and bring them to the warehouse. From there,
                    the shipment would be broken down into smaller quantities and smuggled to El
                    Salvador. This was not an intelligence coup, but the result of good police work.
                    One interesting aspect was that after the police had made the discovery, they
                    cleaned the place up and staked it out. One day, a pick-up truck driven by a
                    Salvadoran, pulled up and the police grabbed him. Within twenty-four hours,
                    throughout the US, Mexico and El Salvador, there were screams about the
                    Hondurans arresting one of the principal insurgent leaders. Our intelligence
                    people went to the Hondurans to check the story and were told that the Hondurans
                    had never heard of him. They wanted to know who he was. After a couple of days,
                    it became clear that the Salvadoran driver was the leader in question. He had
                    been traveling with two passports, both of which were fakes. The truck he was
                    driving had been constructed so that rifles and ammunition could be hidden in
                    it. So a Salvadoran insurgency leader was captured by sheer accident. That was
                    typical of the kind of success we had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the human rights situation in Honduras in the
                        late 70s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: We of course were involved in that issue, but there weren't many problems
                    in Honduras on that score. One of the interesting thing about the Honduran
                    military rule and Honduran society in general did not condone repression and
                    therefore there wasn't much. There was some, but not much. The military had
                    never been violent against their own people, One did see the kind of repression
                    in Honduras that you saw in Guatemala, El Salvador or Nicaragua.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That suggests that these countries are much more different
                        than is usually thought.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: That is right. If you have been there and have spent any time in more than
                    one, the differences are clearly greater than their similarities. In the macro
                    sense, their similarities are strong, but at the micro level, dissimilarities
                    prevail.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>I might just mention the Contra issue as it manifested itself toward the end of
                    the Carter administration. When Somoza fell, much of the National Guard left
                    Nicaragua, especially the leadership. They went to Costa Rica and Honduras.
                    Initially, in the latter country, there were about three thousand former
                    Guardsmen in holding camps. The Honduras left it pretty much to international
                    organizations to support these refugees. Some went to the US; some filtered into
                    the Honduran society and became legal immigrants. Eventually, all the people in
                    the camps dispersed and they were closed. So we had about one to two thousand
                    former National Guardsmen in Honduras. Many settled in the Choluteca area which
                    is the south corner of Honduras. Some of them staged raids across the Nicaraguan
                    border, which according to our information, were not so much military actions
                    than they were just harassment. For example, they would rustle cattle to bring
                    them back into Honduras. These incursions were not significant or effective
                    either militarily or politically. In Tegucigalpa, there were a number of former
                    Guardsmen or Somoza supporters who were running around telling everybody that
                    they were the leaders of one Contra group or another which was fighting in
                    Nicaragua. Most of that was illusory; most of these individuals were pretty
                    seedy.</p>
                <p>I thought I was on the same wave-length with the CIA, although near the end of my
                    term, there were some events that caused me to raise my eye-brows. It was not
                    entirely clear what was going on. I only put the whole picture together later
                    when more information was revealed. Indeed the CIA was preparing for a Contra
                    movement, but during my time in Honduras, I think there was a consensus in the
                    Administration that these guys were little better than criminals. In many cases,
                    the organizations they claimed to represent were penetrated by the Sandinistas;
                    that is to say that some of the people in leadership position of these
                    organizations were suspected to be either Sandinista agents or at least
                    sympathizers. That came from CIA intelligence as well as from the Hondurans. So
                    we did not take these organizations seriously. On the other hand, these groups
                    were constantly trying to push the Embassy in one direction or another. I think
                    they were trying, by being seen with us, show that they US support. At one
                    point, I issued a policy that the Embassy staff have nothing to do with these
                    people—they were not to be invited to our parties, we were not to accept their
                    invitations. If they came into the office on legitimate business, such as
                    consular, the policy was to deal with them in a business-like fashion, but to
                    avoid any public contact with them. I had a couple of Embassy officers who were
                    a problem in this matter; that is the reason I issued that policy directive. In
                    one case, the officer had served in Nicaragua and was sympathetic to the Contra
                    cause on a personal basis and was opposed to the Sandinistas.</p>
                <p>But the Contra movement at that stage was not a serious matter. I advised the
                    Department of my policy and never received any disagreement. My view was
                    supported by our Embassy in Managua because both of us felt that we should not
                    appear to be favoring the anti-Sandinistas.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>In the Summer of 1981, there was a growth in lawlessness in Honduras which became
                    a concern. Bank robberies increased dramatically, super market and payroll
                    robberies increased; there had not been much of this before. Than there was a
                    kidnaping of the child of a wealthy Nicaraguan Somoza supporter who was living
                    in Honduras. We suspected that the bank and payroll robberies were being
                    conducted, in part at least, by former National Guardsmen and so reported to
                    Washington. The kidnaping, as it turned out, was conducted by former National
                    Guards elements—Contras. They were holding the child for ransom to finance their
                    movement. We reported this event since the information reached us through
                    liaison channels. Ultimately, the child was released and the Contras were warned
                    by the Honduran authorities that “enough is enough” and that either the crime
                    would cease or that they would be expelled to Nicaragua. That stabilized the
                    situation in a hurry. It was clear that certain Contra elements were engaged in
                    criminal activity. We reported all this in both State and CIA telecommunication
                    channels. The Agency instructed the Station Chief to stop that kind of
                    reporting, or so he told me. That was a straw in the wind. He also received
                    similar cautions about reports of human rights violations by the Hondurans.</p>
                <p>When I arrived in Honduras, we knew that there was a group of between 10-12
                    Argentine military officers working with the Honduran G-2 (Intelligence). We
                    didn't know why or what they actually did. They kept to themselves and neither
                    our MilGroup or defense Attach�s were able to get any information on their
                    activities. You will recall that at this time Argentina was under a forceful and
                    repressive dictatorship. It turned out that these officers were training the
                    Contras with the knowledge of the Honduran military, if not the whole
                    government. Subsequently, in the Reagan Administration, we approached the
                    Argentines, got them to increase their staff in Honduras and used them to train
                    the Contras, before we had authority to get involved on a large scale
                    ourselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did US politics influence your activities? At this
                        time, the US was close to the election which brought Ronald Reagan to the
                        White House.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>BINNS: It played in a number of ways. We have already talked about the Contra
                    issue, although that didn't flower completely until after my departure. Another
                    aspect was in Honduras itself. There were two parties contending for the
                    Honduran Presidency: the Liberal and the Nationalist. The former was marginally
                    to the left of the latter, but not as far left as, for example, the Christian
                    Democrats. The Liberals were pretty much a centrist party that had won the two
                    previous electoral outings, although their governments never completed their
                    terms. Their presidential candidate wa. The Nationalist Party was led by Zuniga,
                    who had been a major player in Honduran politics since 1963 when he was Minister
                    of Interior and a key advisor to General Lopez, who took power in 1963. Zuniga
                    had been in and out of powerful positions since that time and had always been a
                    power behind the throne. He was widely discredited; believed to be very
                    pernicious, influenced by many people, many of whom were unsavory. He was a man
                    who had attempted on various occasions to manipulate and indeed remove American
                    Ambassadors for real or perceived interventions. John Jova was entrapped by
                    Zuniga; he purchased some antiques, which had been stolen, unbeknownst to John
                    of course. Jova had been set up by the Ministry of Interior. Fortunately, John
                    had already been named to another position, but Zuniga took credit for having
                    the American Ambassador removed. He had running feuds with a series of
                    Ambassadors; he felt that I was a leftist and mounted a campaign even before I
                    got there trying to discredit me and thereby weaken my influence. He did develop
                    close relationships with the extreme right—the nutty—wing of US politics. Among
                    his contacts was Senator Jesse Helms and members of his staff. That staff was
                    perfectly capable of being disruptive even in a country like Honduras.
                    Immediately after the US election, rumors were floated that I would be relieved
                    immediately. Fortunately, I stayed on for another eleven months so that the
                    rumor proved unfounded. But Zuniga was constantly stirring up the waters and I
                    became an issue in the American campaign. Once Reagan had been elected, Zuniga
                    was able to play more cards. There were at least two people from Helms' staff
                    who would come now and then to Tegucigalpa. One of them is now the Under
                    Secretary of State for Economic affairs—Dick McCormack and the other was Chris
                    Manion, who I think is still a member of the Helms staff. McCormack was a loose
                    cannon and a fool. He was convinced the Liberal Party candidate was a cat's paw
                    for the Sandinistas and that he and his Party had received financial support
                    from the Sandinistas. McCormack was sure that if he were elected, he would tilt
                    dramatically toward the Sandinistas. In fact, the reverse occurred. He allowed
                    us to run the Contra support operation from his country and was very helpful to
                    our pro-Contra policy. McCormack, on a couple of occasions, has said to me that
                    I had been absolutely dead right in my judgement and that he had been wrong. In
                    any case McCormack and Manion were in Honduras trying to undercut what I was
                    trying to do. Zuniga was involved in trying to prevent the elections because he
                    felt that he would lose, which indeed is what happened.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When Reagan was elected, was there a feeling that there
                        would be a major change in our policy in Latin America?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>BINNS: There was that perception immediately among the right wingers in Honduras
                    and the Contras. These people had been in touch with their American friends and
                    allies throughout the election period. They had been told that as soon as Carter
                    was out, so was the concern of human rights and that real politik was in. The
                    Honduran Democrats would be back in and the bad guys would be thrown out. The
                    change in Administration was used by Zuniga particularly in Honduras in support
                    of his efforts to frustrate the electoral process. He kept pointing out that the
                    new American administration was different from the last one and that therefore I
                    no longer represented the Administration and that no attention should be paid to
                    the Honduran election—this was all said privately, not publicly. Publicly,
                    Zuniga was campaigning for President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The inference I have gotten from other interviews that the
                        change in ARA leadership was more of a “hostile take-over” than just a
                        change. Did you have that impression in Tegucigalpa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Indeed. Bowdler was tossed out unceremoniously to say the least. It was
                    one of the worst examples of personnel management in the Department that I have
                    ever witnessed. Bowdler has served several administrations loyally. He was
                    literally given until noon of January 20th. to clear his desk and get out of his
                    office. Unheard of!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that impact on you and your Embassy staff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Well, we still worked for the Department. There was still some one in
                    charge of ARA—John Bushnell as acting Assistant Secretary. He was “acting” for
                    quite a while. I also had friends on the Seventh Floor who were feeding me
                    information. They knew that I was on the so-called “hit” list that the
                    transition team had prepared. I was also told that Haig had thrown that list
                    away and that I was not in immediate jeopardy. Then I was told that I would be
                    replaced; Enders, the Assistant Secretary-designee, called me and told me that I
                    would be replaced. Then he called and said a problem had arisen with my
                    successor and that I would have to stay for a while. Indeed, during my last week
                    at post, he called and asked me to stay for another two weeks, but that was
                    after all my farewell activities and I said: “No way!”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your effectiveness damaged by the rumors and what was
                        going on in Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>BINNS: There were a number of agendas being carried out by different people;
                    there was a State Department agenda—at this time it had not yet taken the
                    decisions to support the Contras, but was certainly considering it—was to hold
                    the Nicaraguan government's feet to the fire to insure that there would be an
                    election. Vernon Walters made two trips to Honduras to talk to President Paz and
                    senior military officers about holding those elections. We did not want the
                    Hondurans to think that if they didn't hold the elections, business would
                    continue as usual. In terms of my principal over-riding objective, there were no
                    differences between the Embassy and the Department. We had the largest economic
                    assistance program in Latin America, which in fact grew after my departure. As
                    far as military assistance was concerned, the new Administration wanted to
                    provide more money than I thought could be reasonably absorbed. Despite that,
                    the Hondurans got more; what we were trying to do in the military sphere
                    doubled, much of it ill-advised. For example, in mid-February 1981, my MilGroup
                    commander came to me to tell me that he had just received notice from SouthCom
                    that it had been tasked to develop a plan to interdict the arms flow from
                    Nicaragua to el Salvador. SouthCom was putting together some recommendations
                    which including the assignment of over 200 American troops to Honduras to assist
                    the Hondurans in this interdiction effort. These Americans would lead small
                    combat teams to cut all the trails through the mountains, etc. which might be
                    used as infiltration routes. I have never seen anything about this plan, but I
                    got this information. I sent another NODIS cable to John Bushnell in Washington,
                    asking what was going on. I said that I had not been consulted and that it was
                    nonsensical idea. I pointed out that we were working on the issue with the
                    Agency through different means and this involvement was the silliest thing I had
                    ever heard; it was counter-productive at best. Little did I know that the
                    decision to task SouthCom for those recommendations had been taken by a very
                    small group; there were allegedly only four people in the Department who knew
                    anything about this. So I was blowing the news all over the Department, even
                    though I had sent the cable NODIS. Bushnell was incensed that I sent the cable.
                    I told him that I had not known anything about it and that I had received this
                    information which I thought should be passed on to the Department. I repeated
                    that I thought it was a stupid idea. It never reached fruition, but they found
                    other ways to accomplish their aims.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you returned, did you see the new emphasis on the
                        Nicaragua and el Salvador threats as over-blown?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>BINNS: In regards to Nicaragua, it was mindless. The notion that a rag-tag bunch
                    of individuals—the Contras—, who were mostly former Guardsmen and hated by the
                    Nicaraguans, could enter their country and overthrow the regime, even a
                    totalitarian one, which was supported by at least 75% of the population, was
                    sheer non-sense. The idea of doing it covertly was even crazier. I happen to
                    think that there are occasions when covert operations are appropriate, but one
                    has to be extremely careful and select the situations very carefully which will
                    permit a country to have “plausible deniability”. You can't be totally
                    inconsistent with international law and practice. Most importantly of all, you
                    have to have a political support base in the United States. None of these
                    conditions had met when the operation started against the Nicaraguan regime. We
                    should have continued to try to co-opt the Sandinistas, even if the chances in
                    the short run were not very good. That was what Pezzulo was trying to do and I
                    supported his efforts wholeheartedly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you returned to Washington, how were you viewed by
                        the new leadership?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: There was no way they would let me back into ARA. That is not unusual; you
                    become a non-person. You don't have a job. I was sent for a year as a Senior
                    Fellow to the University of California at Berkeley (The Institute for
                    International Studies). I was there five or six months when I got a call from
                    EUR asking me to come back as Director of the Northern European Affairs Office.
                    I accepted with alacrity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did EUR undergo any great trauma under the new
                        administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: No, no great trauma. There were some differences and ironies as well. One
                    of the policies I was resisting when I was in Tegucigalpa was the militarization
                    of the central America problem. One of the leading instruments of that policy in
                    the Department was the Director of the Politico-Military Affairs Bureau, Rick
                    Burt. I had served with his two principal deputies in London—Bob Blackwill and
                    Jim Dobbins. He had become the Assistant Secretary for EUR. So I was I back
                    working for my old nemesis. The other irony was that two years later, Tom
                    Enders, who had been the Assistant Secretary in ARA and who had sacked me before
                    he was sacked himself, asked me to be his DCM in Madrid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was you principal concerns in the Northern European
                        Office in the 1982-84 period?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>BINNS: The state of our relationships with Great Britain and nine other
                    countries. The greatest stresses were due to our decision to proceed wit a major
                    anti-trust prosecution of a number of British airlines for restraint of trade in
                    setting Atlantic airfares. Among the alleged culprits was British Airways which
                    Mrs. Thatcher was determined to privatize. She felt that our action in addition
                    to a potential suit by Freddie Laker for putting his airline out of
                    business—which might have triple damages—might endanger the financial health of
                    British Airways. Ultimately, the prosecution was killed by a Thatcher to Reagan
                    phone call. That was the major tension during my term.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You then went to Madrid as Deputy Chief of Mission to
                        Ambassador Enders, starting in 1984 and stayed there until 1986. Was the
                        offer to be his deputy come as a surprise?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: You could have knocked me out of the chair with a dust feather. Enders was
                    a good guy to work for because he was open to reasonable arguments; you could
                    talk to him; you had to make a pretty persuasive case if he had other views.
                    There is a theory that I would subscribe to that Enders is very good to work
                    for—he encourages the people who work for him, he reinforces their efforts, he
                    rewards psychically at least, he is bright and exciting—but does not work well
                    for others. His problems, as illustrated by experiences in ARA, were with other
                    people—the White House (which really didn't know what it wanted to do), the
                    Seventh Floor, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Spain and what were you
                        particularly involved in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Spain had a socialist government. A couple years before an attempted coup
                    d'etat by some elements of the military was defeated, probably through the
                    intervention of King Juan Carlos. The whole military did not support the attempt
                    and therefore democracy was saved.</p>
                <p>This socialist government had been in power for about a year and half when I
                    arrived. We wanted to get Spain into NATO. The Spanish popular opinion did not
                    support Spanish membership. We also had the problem of renewal of base
                    agreements. We also had to deal with Spanish entrance into the European
                    Community.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>We certainly felt quite strongly that Spain remain a part of NATO. They had
                    started the joining process under a previous government and we wanted them to
                    continue. We encouraged the Germans particularly and the British and the French
                    to use whatever persuasive efforts they had to convince Spain in its membership
                    drive. In some sense, we may have been pushing on an open door. Early on, Felipe
                    Gonzalez had decided that Spain was going to be come part of Europe. This drive
                    towards “Europeanization” included membership in NATO. He viewed the presence of
                    US bases in Spain as somewhat of an anachronism which he didn't particularly
                    like. On the other hand, he recognized that there were some valid strategic
                    interests for those bases—especially the Rota Naval Base near Gibraltar. So he
                    decided early on, as any good politician would, that he would try to serve as
                    many ends as possible with the same initiative. He felt that by keeping Spain in
                    NATO he would strengthen Spain's European credentials, please his European
                    allies and his colleagues in the European Community so that they would accede to
                    Spain's membership and would get rid of at least part of his “bone in the
                    throat” over the bases. He saw staying in NATO as a means of reducing our
                    military presence in Spain which he didn't like.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the bases a major problem for the Embassy during this
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: They were not a major bone of contention. It was a problem largely of our
                    making in that we tend to approach negotiations on those issues is to make
                    everything high priority and do not ourselves engage in a determination of
                    importance of each of the issues. The Defense Department's position in any base
                    negotiations is to get everything and, if possible, get a little more. That is
                    not a very realistic way to approach negotiations, but in a highly charged,
                    ideological administration, to suggest otherwise would have undermined one's own
                    credibility and standing. Felipe Gonzalez told Tom Enders early on that he would
                    do everything he could to stay in NATO; he thought he could bring it off, but
                    the price would be that we would have to close the Torrejon Air Force base, just
                    outside of Madrid. That was the home of the 401st Tactical Fighter wing, which
                    in a crisis situation is moved to a forward base in Turkey on NATO' s southern
                    flank. That is how the Spanish Prime Minister viewed the situation evolving. He
                    had to turn popular opinion around in Spain—which reflected a 70% opposition to
                    NATO. He also had to swing his own party around which had a long standing
                    position of opposing Spanish membership in NATO. So he saw the base closing and
                    Spain's membership in NATO, and therefore Spain's integration into Europe, as
                    trade-offs.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>Enders understood that position. We had to be very cautious, as I suggested
                    earlier, how the issue was framed to a very highly ideological administration.
                    It didn't want the facts; it just wanted to accomplish what it wanted. It was
                    hard to address because Enders was fearful that if the issue was addressed
                    frontally and openly, the Defense Department would tag Enders as a “liberal
                    whose loyalty to the administration has been in question and whose judgement has
                    always been dubious”. Such a DoD attitude would have killed any chances of
                    finding a solution before the bargaining had even begun. On the other hand, the
                    European Command understood what the situation was and was willing to try to
                    find a compromise and to address the issue in a rational way. But they never
                    prevailed on the civilian side of DoD—the Richard Perles of this world—who
                    wanted everything we had and a little more.</p>
                <p>While I was there, Spain held a referendum which Gonzalez played like a fine
                    violinist plays a Stradivarius—with loving care with a good melody. The
                    Spaniards reversed themselves and voted in favor of Spanish membership in NATO,
                    with certain qualifications, such as that military forces would not be
                    integrated into the NATO command structure. We tried not get involved in the
                    internal debate. The US position was quite clear and we didn't have to announce
                    it repeatedly. It became somewhat screwy because the Conservative Party in
                    Spain, which had traditionally supported NATO, now urged voting against Spanish
                    membership in the referendum because they viewed a favorable vote as a vote of
                    confidence for Gonzalez.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Does Spain's membership make much of a difference?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BINNS: Does Luxembourg matter? Germany contributes the land upon which the battle
                    will be fought and a substantial army. Spain has a good air force; it has a
                    small, but respectable navy; the army isn't much but in view of Spain's
                    geographical location, it is hard to see why a large army could be maintained.
                    Strategically. if you look at armed combat on in Europe, Spain would serve like
                    the U.K. in Northern Europe-a reserve depot logistic support base. That made
                    sense strategically and militarily as well as politically because the way you
                    helped preserve democracy in Spain is to link Spain ever closer to Western
                    Europe. You institutionalize that democracy. Belonging to NATO is another
                    element binding Spain to Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left Spain and retired in 1986. You were still young.
                        Did you feel that you had served in Central America and had incurred the
                        enmity of Jesse Helms and others that you had a limited future in the
                        Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>BINNS: There were two decisive factors. One was the one you just mentioned. The
                    other one was that I had thirty-five years of governmental service and had
                    nothing to gain from staying on from a retirement point of view. The more
                    decisive reason was that the Foreign Service was no longer fun for me. I had
                    served in it for nearly twenty-five years and enjoyed really virtually every
                    minute of it. I never served with an Ambassador I couldn't respect and in most
                    cases. respect enormously. I have seen a lot of situations—in one case, it
                    happened to me—where an officer had an immediate supervisor that he or she
                    didn't respect. I know a lot of colleagues that served with impossible people
                    and in intolerable situations. I never experienced that. I was very lucky. I
                    always had good jobs and I enjoyed tremendously what I was doing. In Spain, for
                    a variety of reasons, including the political one that you alluded to, it was no
                    longer fun. One of the more decisive elements was the way the Administration was
                    treating Enders.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>That is a long and involved story, but it may be illustrative. I got a call in
                    about July 1984—soon after I had arrived in Madrid—from a friend on the Seventh
                    Floor who was very close to Secretary George Shultz. He called me from a phone
                    in a city other than Washington and his remarks were very indirect. The thrust
                    was that President Reagan had told Shultz that he had been getting comments from
                    sources accusing Enders of being disloyal to him personally and politically.
                    Reagan thought that Enders should be replaced. The person who called me said
                    that he had told the Secretary that he had a source in Madrid who would give him
                    the straight and unvarnished truth on this allegation. Since I was that source,
                    I told my friend that whatever had been told Reagan was a lie; I thought Enders
                    was more loyal than the Administration deserved after they way it had treated
                    him in Honduras. I said that Enders was basically a believer in what the
                    Administration was trying to accomplish and he had never, never done anything
                    except to support the Administration in every respect. My Seventh Floor friend
                    said he would take my comments to the Secretary. He also told me that I was not
                    to mention this conversation to Enders unless he called me back within a week's
                    time top tell me that the issue was dead. Then I was permitted to tell Enders.
                    My friend of course didn't want Enders to stir up the waters any further. After
                    the week went by without a word, I called my friend and reminded him that I was
                    supposed to get some information. I was told that the rumor had been killed and
                    the Secretary had managed to allay the President's concerns. So I proceeded to
                    tell Enders about the events. He was astounded. He couldn't figure out the
                    source that had tried to knife him. Then in September or October, I received
                    another call from the same person on the Seventh Floor, informing me that the
                    same issue had arisen again. He asked me to inform Enders, but asked that Tom
                    not do anything because the Secretary believed that he had it under control. My
                    friend thought however that Tom and I should be aware of the situation. In
                    December, Enders returns to Washington—he was taking a Christmas holiday—for one
                    day. While there, he discovers that someone else has been nominated by the
                    Department to the White House to replace him. Of course, no one had told him
                    about it. The reason given to him was this pernicious allegation of disloyalty.
                    So Tom went to talk to the Secretary and was told that the charges of disloyalty
                    had been raised twice. He didn't know the source, but the pressure was coming
                    from Mrs. Reagan. That was the reason why, when the Secretary thought he had
                    matters under control, the rumor and the pressure kept recurring. Shultz told
                    Enders that he didn't believe one word of what was being rumored and that he had
                    his full support, but that the situation was reaching the point where he
                    couldn't continue to defend him without ruining his own credibility. Shultz said
                    he would look for another assignment for Enders. He also told Enders that he
                    wanted to go to the White House to straighten this issue out, he was most
                    welcomed to do so.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>So Enders went to the White House and had an interview with Michael Deaver,
                    Reagan's special assistant and very close to both the President and Mrs. Reagan.
                    Deaver said that he would examine the issue and would conduct “loyalty”
                    hearings. Unbelievable. Enders called me from Washington to explain all this to
                    me. He wanted to collect all his speeches and press conferences and other media
                    coverage because he had to return to Washington in two weeks with all this
                    material for the hearing. I told him that I thought he was crazy and he
                    shouldn't have to put up with all this nonsense. If I were in his shoes, if they
                    didn't believe in my loyalty, I would tell them to go to hell. He obviously
                    didn't take my advice—it may not have been good advice, but it felt good. Enders
                    went back to Washington in January for the “loyalty” hearings. Deaver said that
                    he was convinced that the rumors were all specious and he didn't know where it
                    came from, but that he would give Enders his full support and he thought that
                    the rumor could be killed. But it didn't die; Deaver was in Madrid in March or
                    April, advancing a Presidential visit scheduled for May. He told Enders he had
                    tried to kill the rumor, but it was still floating around. He said that during
                    the visit, he would set a private meeting between Enders and the President
                    during which Enders could reassure him that there were no foundation for the
                    accusation of disloyalty. The matter dragged on and on even though the President
                    accepted Enders' statements. It was still alive six months later, when Enders
                    was being considered for the post of Ambassador to Australia primarily to get
                    him out of Spain and out of the President's eye-sight. That was for me an
                    enormously souring experience even though it hadn't happened to me personally. I
                    finally told Tom that I didn't know how long he would stay in Madrid, but that I
                    was getting out. It was no longer fun, particularly the way he had been treated.
                    There was nothing left in the Reagan period that I could aspire to and therefore
                    I was going to retire.</p>
                <p>I stayed until January, 1986. Enders was going to be replaced in July and began
                    to look around for a second career. He is now with Solomon Brothers and I
                    understand that he has not regretted for a moment his decision to retire and I
                    haven't regretted either.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever find out the background of all this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>BINNS: One thing that came out at the “loyalty” hearing was an indication from
                    Deaver that the sources who were talking to Mrs. Reagan were Mr. Rosebush, her
                    private secretary and some friends in the New York social set, particularly the
                    publisher of Women's Wear Daily”— a fellow by the name of Zipkin. Their contacts
                    in Madrid were feeding this disinformation to the White House—Mr. Rosebush—who
                    was relaying to Mrs. Reagan who then passed it on to the “old man”. We found out
                    that among the things that were used to buttress the specious argument of
                    disloyalty were little squibs planted in gossip columns in the Madrid press. For
                    example, one column suggested that Enders was very close to the Socialists. The
                    Madrid gossip press, not unlike that of many countries, was quite corrupt and
                    you could get almost anything printed if you were willing to pay for it. It was
                    a campaign originated by the right wing in Spain for unknown reasons except
                    perhaps to discomfort the Ambassador. Obviously, they were successful. It
                    subsequently became clear when in mid- or late-1985, I got another phone call
                    from a friend in the NSC who asked me if I knew the Countess of Romanones. I
                    said that I knew her. She was an American married to a Spanish nobleman. They
                    were very right wing—openly and avidly Francoists. They were on the outside
                    since Franco's demise. They were excluded from the royal court—they were
                    unacceptable to King Juan Carlos. My friend then asked why the NSC would get a
                    request from the East Wing of the White House for the Countess to have an
                    appointment with Bud McFarlane—then the NSC Advisor. I said that I couldn't
                    imagine any reason for such a request and I advised the McFarlane should not
                    meet with her. I asked that I be kept posted. I then went to Enders to tell him
                    of the call. He told me that before he had arrived in Madrid I had been advised
                    by Wells Stabler, the former Ambassador, to stay away from the Romanones because
                    they would try to take American Ambassadors as social hostages. Enders further
                    said that when he arrived in Madrid—it was on a Wednesday—his social secretary,
                    without asking him or my wife—had accepted a dinner invitation extended by the
                    Countess for Thursday evening. He then told my secretary that she would have to
                    call up and get him out of it; he was just not prepared on the first night in
                    Madrid to accept such an invitation. After that, the Countess was out to get
                    him. In any case, eventually my NSC friend called back and said that upon his
                    recommendation, Bud had decided not to see her. A second request was made by the
                    East Wing; McFarlane then agreed to see her and was then asked by the Countess
                    to appoint her as the US Ambassador to Spain to replace Enders. And that's how
                    the campaign to discredit Enders got started. Unbelievable! The Countess has a
                    residence in New York and travels in those social circles and through them, she
                    sabotaged Enders. She paid for the articles to be published in the Madrid gossip
                    columns; they would then be clipped and sent to Zipkin who then sent them to
                    Rosebush. That was bizarre!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do when you left the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>BINNS: I came home with the idea of getting into the antique importing business.
                    I started that and I also had a consulting business. Shortly after I retired,
                    while in Spain on an antique buying trip and other commercial work, I got a call
                    from the Department's Bureau for Diplomatic Security which wanted to know if I
                    would be interested in becoming a consultant on crisis management exercises.
                    This is the way the Department practices its emergency plans and trains Embassy
                    personnel in crisis management. I did for about four years. I have been doing
                    other consulting work as well. One of the companies that I consulted for has
                    asked me to join them on a permanent basis in Tucson, Arizona.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you very much for this interview.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
