<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001658">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Mr. Jacob Walkin </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2010-04-10"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2010-04-10"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>JACOB WALKIN</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: March 30, 2000</p>
                <p>Copyright 2009 ADST</p>
                <p>[Note: this interview was not edited by Mr. Walkin prior to his death.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is March 30, 2000. This is an interview with Jacob
                        Walkin done on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training
                        and I'm Charles Stuart Kennedy. Mr. Walkin, can you tell me when and where
                        you were born and something about your family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1917 and my family was Eastern
                    European. I guess there were many such families at that time of Jewish origin,
                    who emigrated from Czarist Russia just before WWI. I have an older brother who
                    was born in 1910 and a sister who was born in 1913. I was born in 1917 in New
                    York and the only member of my family born in the United Sates. My father was an
                    ordinary laborer and remained an ordinary laborer all his life. They were only
                    semi-literate, and never fully learned English; the family language was Yiddish.
                    Although my parents both spoke Russian, they only used it when they didn't want
                    the children to know what they were talking about. The distance between me and
                    my parents was so great that I could say in some respects that it was perhaps my
                    older brother who really helped bring me up and helped me adjust to the world
                    around me, because the first language I spoke at home was Yiddish, not English.
                    But, as soon as I was old enough to talk with my brother and sister and to get
                    into the streets, I began, of course, to speak English.</p>
                <p>The natural evolution of a family like this is that my sister got no farther than
                    the ninth grade before she had to be put to work. My brother got through high
                    school and then got a B.A. right away and a law degree at night, both at night;
                    I was the only member of the family who could go to college during the daytime.
                    I had a very fine high school, Thomas Jefferson High School, in east New York.
                    Afterwards, I went to a very fine school; I couldn't have gotten a better
                    education, I think, than I did at Cornell at that time, not only because we had
                    Carl BeckeI don't know whether you know the name?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I know the name. He was a very famous historian,
                        American historian.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>WALKIN: Very famous historian and a very fine lecturer. I thoroughly enjoyed his
                    lectures. We also had Phillip Moses, who completed his studies at Harvard and
                    joined the Cornell faculty in 1936, at the beginning of my junior year; I
                    started Russian History and Diplomatic History with him. We also had a famous
                    medieval historian, Karl Stafforsen. I feel, in retrospect that between the
                    three of them and the other faculty members, that I had as good a bachelor's
                    education as anyone could have gotten anywhere, in the field of history</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What other subjects were you interested in? Not history,
                        but other subjects.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I took Latin, because I had had Latin in high school and I happened to be
                    a good student in Latin. I took French, because I studied French in high school.
                    I took Calculus, because I understood enough mathematics, because of what I had
                    had in high school. I had the usual array of courses in English; I guess that
                    was it. I had to take one science course, and I choose geology. By the way,
                    geology also happened to be the department where I worked. I had to work my way
                    through; I couldn't have done it otherwise. They had this program of the
                    National Youth Administration whereby college students worked in a college
                    department. I think it was for 50 cents an hour, up to a certain limit of hours;
                    and I never waited on tables. I worked through my college years for the Geology
                    Department on this NYA program; that is how I earned the money which enabled me
                    to get through. So I had this fine education and a Phi Beta Kappa election; but,
                    afterwards, I could get nowhere at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You graduated at 1938?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: ?1938?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it at the end of the Depression?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Yes, the Depression was just ending and the best I could get was taking
                    the Fulton Street El to downtown New York and delivering Women's Wear Daily to
                    customers in the downtown area. But, I did finally get a job. It was with the
                    Civil Service Commission in Albany. I spent six months in Albany, from June 1939
                    to November 1939, where I got a slightly higher salary, and a more interesting
                    environment. Later, I got a job with the National Labor Relations Board in
                    Washington. My title was messenger. This with my Cornell Degree, but I gradually
                    moved ahead, both in the National Labor Relations Board and then lateafter I had
                    become a CAF-16, I think it wain the War Production Board, which of course,
                    nobody has heard of now, but it was a major institution during WWII. I worked my
                    way up. By the time I was drafted, I had the title of junior economist. So,
                    although I was a GS-7 and had a professional title, I was drafted. However, even
                    there, everything worked out to my advantage.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What year were you drafted?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: 1942.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1942?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Yes, I was discharged in late October 1945.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you take your basic training?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Camp Lee, Virgininot very far from hernear Petersburg. I was there for
                    three months in the fall of 1942. This was, and I think still is, the
                    quartermaster training center. I had very poor eyes, and I was limited. This was
                    only because I lied about what I could see and, because, well, they needed
                    people like me anyway. So I took my basic training at Camp Lee and then was
                    assigned, as would be natural, to a quartermaster regimenot as a truck driver, I
                    couldn't drive, but because I was a good typist.</p>
                <p>I had learned typing at home. My brother had bought a typewriter and then was
                    smart enough to give me a guide on learning how to type. Typing is what I had
                    done throughout Cornell. I typed so well for the geology department that they
                    used their own funds to employ me for more hours than the NYA allowed at the
                    time.</p>
                <p>So I was assigned to a quartermaster truck regiment where I worked in the orderly
                    room. As a result, just about everybody got to know me. Some of the sergeants
                    began to give me driver training. I couldn't possibly afford a car at that
                    point, but I learned driving well enough. In one exercise, our first destination
                    was Camp Shelby which was just outside Hattiesburg. It was an exercise which was
                    done on the gulf shore between Biloxi and Gulfport, if you know that part of the
                    country. I was, of course, sitting around. I wasn't supposed to be a truck
                    driver, but the opportunity came for me to get into a 2 and half ton truck, I
                    forget if it was Biloxi or Gulfport, and to drive it alone to the final
                    destination, where everybody applauded when they saw me bring it in and bringing
                    it to a perfect stop. I was given, of course, a license to drive a two and a
                    half ton truck. But something was wrong there. This part is peculiar but really
                    interesting. The head of the group was a first lieutenant who for some reason
                    took a dislike to me, not because I couldn't do the work; I still have no idea
                    why. I ended the war, by the way, as a third grade sergeant. There was no
                    occasion for me to go to?.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: OCS (Officer's Training School)?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>WALKIN: OCS. I just didn't think of it. But I did, I think, do work in the army,
                    which the army took notice of, when I was finally discharged. I will get to that
                    in a minute. But, what happened initially was, I think, unusual and changed the
                    whole course of the war for me and made it more dangerouno question about that.
                    But, the fact is that I was not wounded, I got through. I worked in the first
                    army headquarters as a typist. But, I had other skills as well, and I think my
                    whole army record looks good, but not the part with this quartermaster truck
                    regiment. I stayed with that regiment through Camp Shelby, and then we went to
                    Camp Monroe in North Carolina, and to Fort William Henry Harrison just south of
                    Helena, Montana. But, by this time, I was getting disgusted with the way I was
                    being treated. Well, there is no need to prolong this; I just didn't like the
                    way I was being treated. I had enough information; I don't remember what was
                    now, that made it possible for me to transfer myself away from them without
                    their permission, while I was in Montana, I put through the necessary papers for
                    this transfer, and I was transferred to Fort Belvoir, Virginia, for about three
                    months. But now, I was open to assignment. Fortunately, First Army Headquarters
                    was looking for people and I was assigned there. This was in the summer of 1943.
                    So, I moved from Fort Belvoir to Governor's Island and prepared to go overseas.
                    I spent the rest of the wa21 monthwith the First Army overseas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the commander of the First Army?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Omar Bradley, until the First Army grew. Then we had another general, a
                    southern general, with nowhere near the reputation of Omar Bradley's. He saw me
                    paying attention once and I saw him; this was in England.</p>
                <p>Prior to that, our preparation in the U.S. was in Governor's Island. We got on a
                    ship that no one knew anything about, the Queen Elizabeth I, and crossed the
                    ocean to Scotland. Our first stint was actually in Bristol, in western England,
                    where we planned Operation Overload. I did not have the highest classification.
                    I knew we were going to be in Normandy, but I did not realize we were going to
                    land there and eventually break out from there. Well, it was all fascinating for
                    me, a history major who had studied French and Latin and here I was in Europe. I
                    could site a number of instances where I could have been hurt or killed, but I
                    wasn't. I got through the War, going all the way, as I say, from the beaches of
                    Normandy to Weimar, Germany, where the war ended. I got two tours of the
                    Buchenwald Concentration Camp. I could tell more stories about that, but I
                    won't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The First Army was where in the line, that was next to the
                        British?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: There was a First Army under Bradley and a third army under ?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: George S. Patton?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>WALKIN: Patton that was the basic army that moved, as I say, from the Beaches of
                    Normandy to Weimar in what was to become East Germany. But we had nothing to do
                    there. For very good reasons, I decided not to go back to the United States at
                    that point but to stay in Europe. I was assigned to the G-5 section, the
                    military government section, in Luxemburg City, where I was in the summer of
                    1945. I developed some eye trouble there and as I had already been over there
                    with the army for three years, I was just sent back. I spent the last months of
                    the war in the eye center outside Philadelphia. I don't think it is an army camp
                    any longer, but they treated all the eye ailments over there. Of course, I know
                    that name but I can't remember it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's alright.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: It doesn't matter. Anybody who was in the army at that time would know
                    this general hospital outside Philadelphia.</p>
                <p>When I was discharged after three years and two months in the United States Army,
                    there was no question about what I would do. I went to graduate school and got
                    myself a Ph.D. in Political Science. I studied Russian at Yale, too, so that I
                    could write a dissertation on Russia. I wrote what I knew would become a book
                    eventually and would really establish me as a figure in Russian History, even
                    while in the army. The book was published in 1962, while I was in Indonesia. It
                    was important that when I finished, both my Master's degree and my Ph.D., the
                    deputy head of the intelligence division came out to California to recruit and
                    found somebody who had studied Russian and who the professors were praising to
                    the skies. He eventually guaranteed me a job. I did get my Ph.D. when I left
                    Berkeley in June. I was immediately hired by the State Department, and worked
                    for four years on Soviet intelligence. I read Soviet papers everyday. As a Ph.D.
                    student, I read thousands of pages of Russian, pre-revolutionary Russian. I can
                    show you some of the books I bought in that period that I still have in Russian.
                    But, this experience in State Department intelligence...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in State Department intelligence from when to
                        when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I joined them in June and I left them when I was sworn in at Fort Meyer
                    here and then assigned to Camp Lee, that was August 1942</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you got out of the army, you went back? Where did you
                        go for you Master's and Ph.D.?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>WALKIN: Oh, I went first to Yale, from 1945 to 1947, to the International
                    Relations Department, but, International Relations was not my subject. I got my
                    best grades in other subjects, like the Russian Seminar and Russian language.
                    Also, at Yale there was a former Englishman, Cecil Driver, who had had a
                    commonwealth Fellowship and had remained in the United States as a professor. He
                    taught Comparative Literature. I think the Russian History seminar, the Russian
                    language graduate seminar, and Driver's course in Comparative Government are
                    what I really got out of Yale. Well, I was not a particularly good International
                    Relations student. I got my highest grades in these other subjects, and I think
                    wisely, choose Berkeley to continue my Ph.D. Now, it's important also that I
                    mention my relationship with George Renonski. He oversaw my dissertation from a
                    distance. Every time I finished a chapter, I would give it to my committee at
                    Berkeley, but also send it to Renonski in Yale.</p>
                <p>When I was finished, my Ph.D. was entitled something like State and Society in
                    Old Russia. It was an analysis of the institutions of the state and the
                    institutions of society just before the Revolution, basically during the reign
                    of Nicholas II. I still get compliments on it. It was never, by the way, a
                    paperback, but it will eventually be, I feel, when full attention is turned to
                    that whole subject. Of course, I have a deep interest in the history of Russia
                    and in their future and in what influence Russian history will have on this
                    future. By the way, it was important that one understood the distinction between
                    Tsarism and Communism, and I was perfectly positioned to do that.</p>
                <p>I spent four years in the State Department intelligence service [Intelligence and
                    Research, INR]. It was then the main producer of intelligence reports on Russia.
                    I was promoted there, by the way. My later promotions were in the Foreign
                    Service, but I was initially promoted there from a GS-9 to GS-11. We had a whole
                    group of Russian speaking people and we all go to know what was going on in
                    Soviet Russia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now this was after the war, after you got your Ph.D.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: That's right, in 1952, which is when I joined the Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were the leaders in Russian research in the
                        Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: The head at the time was Moss HarveI think he was a southerner; the
                    deputy head was Boris Carson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: His son is, I think, in the historian' office now.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>WALKIN: Oh, that could be. Moss Harvey and Carson were the heads of the whole
                    division. I was in the Soviet Internal Division and the head was, I forget his
                    name.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's all right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I will remember it, of course, in due course. None of us were
                    particularly well known. We were producing the reports on what was going on at
                    that time, in the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression, at that time, of the information
                        we were getting from our Embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Oh, they were good. I was reading all the classified materials. I got the
                    impression that they were quite good, but I have a different impression now.
                    Actually, it is too long to talk about. I do want to mention to you that I,
                    along with all my fellow researchers, really got to know, , what was going on in
                    the Soviet Union at that time. We understood Russia, and we understood all the
                    mistakes that were made about it outside the United States Government at the
                    time and are still being made. I will give you one example of how it came out.
                    One of my colleagues was in the Foreign Branch and was assigned to Moscow and I
                    was in Soviet Internal. I don't know why I was not assigned there; most of our
                    people went there. They needed somebody in Belgrade at a time when I was
                    available, so I went to Belgrade. But I am glad of it, I don't regret that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now when you were in INR, during the early fifties, did
                        you feel that there was any problem in the unit you were with, with
                        McCarthyism at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: A few. I got into INR in the middle of McCarthy era, in 1952. I don't
                    intend to brag; but even at that time, I knew that I had a special aptitude for
                    current history. I knew it in high school. I got into no radical movements,
                    which are all in the dustbin of history now anyway. My history teacher said to
                    me, “Why didn't you become a socialist?” I didn't know what to answer him. I
                    think socialism was and is a largely theoretical and empty ideology; and, it
                    will never be revived again, I think. But, I had not been in any radical
                    organization and I was left alone. We had no serious problems in intelligence.
                    Some people, who may have been in minor-leftist organizations, maybe were looked
                    into. But, I don't recall, at least in the division of research for USSR and
                    Eastern Europe, that anybody got into serious trouble because of McCarthy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the impression that your group of analysts had of
                        George Kennan?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>WALKIN: Oh, that is a long story. I went to see Kennan in Princeton before I went
                    to Belgrade, which was my first foreign assignment. Kennan was a very peculiar
                    man in my opinion and illustrative of the peculiar weaknesses that people have.
                    It doesn't matter what you have accomplished. Peculiar weaknesses can show up in
                    anybodanywhere, at anytime. Kennan, of course, was one of my idols, while I was
                    in graduate school and I read his article. I forget what it was called.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mr. X article, I think it was called Mr. X.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Yes, it was written by Mr. X, right. I read that article many a time and
                    I found it, of course, a first rate article, as all of us in INR that were
                    working on the Soviet Union and reading Soviet papers every day did. But he was
                    a man, apparently, of a very peculiar mental construction. He gave us, well,
                    what is that name of his theory?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Containment.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Containment Theory. He writes a wonderful article, then he joins a group
                    which opposes everything that Containment called for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Oh, you were aware of that? Everything that Containment called for, he
                    opposed after he joined this group. How do you rate him? I don't know how to
                    rate him. He was, on the one hand, as far as I am concerned, a very brilliant
                    man and on the other, well, to put it frankly, a jackass.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, he is a mixture.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: There are more than just me who are aware of this. Well, that is the way
                    it is, it was very peculiar indeed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did he tell you about Yugoslavia before you went
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: No, I saw him in 1952.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I see. He did not reach Yugoslavia until 1961. But you
                        talked to him before you went to Yugoslavia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Yes, but that was 1952.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he have anything to say about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: No, I forget what we talked about. I probably should have had in my head
                    some idea of just what I wanted to discuss with him, but I was just not built
                    that way. I forget now what we talked about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you got to Yugoslavia in 1952, what was Yugoslavia
                        like, when you got there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: It was not the Soviet Union. I knew the Soviet Union. I started to tell
                    you about how all of us who worked in INR, at that time, learned it. One of my
                    colleagues went to Moscow for three years. Afterwards, because he had worked on
                    Chinese-Soviet relations, he was assigned to Hong Kong. So, here is my old buddy
                    from INR in Hong Kong and he didn't know anybody and I knew everybody, so I
                    arranged a cocktail party at his house and just introduced him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is in Hong Kong?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: In Hong Kong.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's go back to Belgrade. Let's talk about Belgrade.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: To Belgrade and how different it was. It obviously was not what I had
                    been taught about the Soviet Union, which I started to tell you, that we all
                    knew so well since we read Soviet papers everyday. And there was no doubt about
                    what we were reading and reporting, but Belgrade was entirely different and it
                    is important by the way that you know and understand the distinction which a lot
                    of people overlook between Totalitarianism and Authoritarianism.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would you define the distinction?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>WALKIN: Yugoslavia was not a Totalitarian state. Anybody could go abroad and come
                    back, as they did in the millions reallif they didn't get work at home, they
                    sought work in Western Europe. Then, when they had enough money, they went back
                    home and no stigma was attached to them. You knew the Soviets; you know enough
                    about it. Well the best illustration of the difference between the Chinese,
                    which was also an open system, and the Russians at the same time, was that the
                    Chinese were sending some 30,000 students a year to the United States and the
                    Soviet Union were sending 30.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: And that in part is the difference between Totalitarianism and
                    Authoritarianism. I got a good taste of that, by the way, in Indonesia, because
                    all sorts of things were going on in Indonesia which I knew would never happen
                    in the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was your job in Belgrade?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Initially I was in the consular section, issuing visas. After a year, I
                    was to be transferred to the political section. Everybody knew that I had a
                    Ph.D. in Political Science, what my academic background was, and all this work I
                    had done in the Department. Well, nobody really knew much about Yugoslavia at
                    that time.</p>
                <p>There was a USIS library. Anybody could go there. Nobody took your name. Nobody
                    followed you. Nobody told you not to go. You could go there and read whatever
                    you wanted to. There was nothing like this, of course, in the rest of Eastern
                    Europe till years later.</p>
                <p>The embassy had a military section. They gave the most cocktail parties, I think,
                    and, of course, I went to a whole host of cocktail parties in Belgrade. But they
                    were there and they remained there until shortly before I left two years later,
                    giving military help to the Yugoslavs. This obviously had nothing to do with the
                    rest of Eastern Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: They had a USAID section. They worked in the open. Everybody did.
                    Everything was open and well, I looked around and said, “This isn't the Soviet
                    Union.” I did not hesitate, when I met this girl, with whom I decided I would
                    sleep and eventually marry. But I won't go into details on how this was
                    discovered. The Ambassador knew that I was living with a Soviet woman and that I
                    had a daughter. It got to SY but nothing happened, except, well nothing
                    happened, because there was no compromise.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: James W. Riddleberger...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Oh, he was a tremendous man. I liked Riddleberger greatly. He was
                    replaced by Karl somebody. You may know?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think he came from China, Karl Rankin.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Yes Karl Rankin. He had been in China. I think you are right. I was with
                    him for a very short time, but I was much more impressed with Riddleberger than
                    with Rankin. There were stories of Rankin sitting in the library sorting books.
                    I don't know how true they were. I was not on that floor. I remained in the
                    consular section, but this did not hinder my later promotions, I think, because
                    of the fact that everybody knew that I knew more about issuing visas than anyone
                    else. When a new head was put in, I remember all that vividly. Everybody turned
                    to me for an opinion on what the Department would approve of or disapprove of.
                    So I did not do any political work in Belgrade, but when I left the Foreign
                    Service, knowing what I did, I felt that it would be much more pleasant to
                    specialize in Yugoslavia than Russia. Well, I knew that when I went to Belgrade,
                    I could speak Russian fluently. I haven't used it for years, but I could get it
                    and Serbian back at any time. I can learn languages naturally and Maria
                    Angelooch...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, wonderful lady.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I am sure you know her.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She was a delightful woman.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: A delightful woman. She used to tell me that I was the only officer that
                    had not gone to FSI for 8 months and could speak Serbian better than they
                    could.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes; I am sure there is aptitude.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>WALKIN: It was while I was on duty. I and one of my colleagues, and one of two
                    locals, went on a two or three week trip, basically along the coast from one end
                    pf Yugoslavia to the other. What is that port city at the entrance to
                    Yugoslavia?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, there is Rijeka.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Rijeka is what I am thinking of. I should remember it because of the
                    name. We went from that end all the way to Montenegro. We also drove from
                    Montenegro back up the hills toward Belgrade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They weren't very good roads.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were bad roads.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: They were dirt roads, but passable, as I recall. We had no unusual
                    experience. I spent three days in Sarajevo during the Spring of 1958, during my
                    last years there. The man in chargI run into him occasionallhe says nothing to
                    me, nor I to him, but it doesn't matter. I know I made trips to Zagreb, when my
                    former associate Robert Kaiser was Consul General there, but I also got a
                    scholarship later on, what is this group?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fulbright?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: No, it was not the Fulbrighit was the other Eastern European
                    ScholarshiTelex or something like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It doesn't matter.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: What they did was to put American students in Yugoslavia at a university
                    to study whatever topic they wished and would give them rubles periodically from
                    the university bursar so that the whole thing cost them nothing. I got one such
                    fellowship and made six study trips to Yugoslavia after I left the Foreign
                    Service; the best one was one I paid no money for.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I want to go back to a time you were in Yugoslavia in the
                        early 1950s. How about giving visas to Yugoslavs? Wasn't there a problem
                        because many were associated with a Communist Organization?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: No, it wasn't that so much; it was the fact that they had relatives in
                    the United States and were not likely to come back. We were not so much
                    concerned with subversion, but with the possibility that once they went there as
                    tourists they would not want nor be likely to come back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were going to Gary, Indiana and places like
                        that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Yes. There were a fair number of students. Yugoslavs could go wherever
                    they wanted to study or work freely, with no suspicion necessarily falling on
                    them, and that hit me as soon as I got to Belgrade.</p>
                <p>I often went to cocktail parties and met all these people from the United States.
                    And we, of course, had a huge delegation there. And, as I say, I did something
                    which, if this were Russia, would have forced me out of the Service immediately.
                    But, as I said, there was no compromise. I was sent a mild reprimand from the
                    then Director General. But there was no reason for them to throw me out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you get married?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: In Belgrade. After I was ready to leave, my wife and daughter came to
                    Belgradmy wife, of course, with a visa. I had had my daughter legitimized in
                    Atlanta. Somebody from passport tipped me off on this. Georgia is the only state
                    in the Union in which you can get an illegitimate child legitimized. One of my
                    family's neighbors in the Georgia complex in which they lived, was a lawyer; he
                    got this done. My daughter was legitimized under the laws of the state of
                    Georgia. My daughter was also in conformity with the Immigration and
                    Naturalization Act, once I married her mother. And she was under 18, so INS gave
                    her a certificate not saying where she was born, but saying that she was an
                    American citizen from the time she was born. On the basis of the legitimization
                    given in the State of Georgia. What I got from the State Department was an
                    acknowledgment saying that she was my dependent. So my daughter moved around
                    with a diplomatic passport as my dependent, and she came to the United States
                    with a diplomatic passport to live permanently as my dependent</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go? You left in 1950?when, 1958 from
                        Yugoslavia? Where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>WALKIN: Home leave, of course, with my family base being in Atlanta at that time,
                    and then I was sent as far away from my transgression as possible, Hong Kong.
                    But I wouldn't change my years in Hong Kong and Indonesia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's alright.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: This was a kind of punishment, but I am delighted that I spent two years
                    in Hong Kong and four years in Indonesia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We will pick this up the next time, when you were in Hong
                        Kong and you got there in 1958 until 1960. Great, we will do that then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>A little announcement here, today is the 21st of April, 2000. You were telling me
                    something that happened with the military in Weimar, I think</p>
                <p>WALKIN: Well, no. I spent 21 months of the military as a draftee with the United
                    States First Army, most of it in Europe. We were initially based in Bristol,
                    where we were planning Operation Overlook. Eventually, I wound up with the
                    closed company, First Army, in Weimar, in what was to become East Germany.</p>
                <p>What particularly struck me in those months in Europe was an incident in Paris,
                    actually Versailles, where we were based for some months in September 1944, just
                    a few weeks after the First Army entered the Paris area. I worked in the G-5
                    section of the First Army. The officer I worked for had some mission in
                    Versailles, and since my work was apparently up to date in the office where I
                    was working, he asked me to drive him there, which I did. When I got there, he
                    went off somewhere. I was left to wander around Versailles, which I was doing,
                    when two French women passed by and started talking to me. They were utterly
                    astounded that I could answer them. I had had three years of French in high
                    school and a year and half in my first years as an undergraduate at Cornell,
                    where I took my Bachelor's degree; and, by that time I could speak French. When
                    the women addressed me, I answered them in French. They had never met a GI who
                    could speak French and they stopped and started to chat with me. Other people,
                    coming by and hearing that we were talking in French, also stopped, until I had
                    a crowd. It was fifty years ago, but it seems to me that I had a crowd of about
                    30 people?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good heavens!</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>WALKIN: Standing around and us chatting for, I don't know 20 or 30 minutes in
                    French. I have never forgotten this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course not.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: It was quite an impressive affair, and they must have talked about it for
                    days on end. It was probably one of the finer contribution I made as a GI
                    stationed in Western Europe during that critical period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's move on. In 1958 you went to Hong Kong.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I was assigned as general investigator of Chinese fraud. There were quite
                    a few of us, and this is what I did for one year. I made periodic trips into
                    Kowloon and talked to various Chinese. I learned Cantonese, by the way, while I
                    was there and that is what I did for one year. But they had a security officer
                    who proved to be a drunkard, and they just sent him home. The Consul General at
                    the time, Jerry Lewis Holmes, had to pick somebody to replace him. I thought
                    nothing of it at the time, but it so happens that he picked me to replace him.
                    That is what I did during my last year in Hong Kong. I was the security officer
                    doing all the same jobs that security officers do, including, by the way,
                    lecturing to newcomers on particular security problems that we had in the
                    consulate general.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the major security problems that we were
                        concerned about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: There was a general question of general security and Chinese spies for
                    the area, but also the usual security officer duties of investigating particular
                    employees, and employees to be, to ensure that they were not spies or working in
                    any way for the Chinese communists. I also gave periodic lectures on the
                    particular problems affecting us in the Consulate General in Hong Kong. I got
                    quite a crowd. It is worth mentioning that when we were through, they just
                    didn't want to leave; they wanted to hear more of what I had told them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean the people who were being told the security
                        problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Yes. The particular security problems to watch out for because they had
                    come to work for the Consulate General in Hong Kong.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you working on American and/or Chinese employees in
                        the Consulate General or were you working on the visa/fraud side?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>WALKIN: No, I was not in the visa/fraud side as a security officer. I did the
                    general investigating work of a security officer, and, as I started to tell you,
                    this lecture I gave periodically to newcomers on the particular security
                    problems that they should look out for while they were employed in Hong Kong. I
                    certainly remember the fact that this grouI don't know, there were quite a few
                    people in my office listening to me talk about the particular security problems
                    of Hong Konthey just didn't want to leave. They wanted to hear more. I did
                    general security work and I continued to make trips into Hong Kong. I caught the
                    attention once of Holmes when I reported back to my reporting officer, who was
                    Sam Gilstrap, the Deputy Consul General, about an incident concerning an
                    American Chinese in Kowloon who had probably been sent there as a secret agent
                    to check on potential spies. He spoke Cantonese fluently. I probably started
                    talking to him in Cantonese and when he learned that we were Americans, we
                    started talking in English. He had been sent there without the knowledge of the
                    Consulate. I reported this to Sam Gilstrap when I got back. When he reported it
                    to Holmes, Holmes immediately sent for me. I told him in detail just what I had
                    learned: that this guy was an American, and had been sent by some agency other
                    than State and was working secretly there. Holmes exploded, because he had not
                    been told about this. He just listened to me and I know that I never saw that
                    young man again. He was probably withdrawn immediately.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we concerned at that time with attempts by the
                        Communist Chinese to place employees in the Consulate General?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Oh, no question about that. Before anybody could be employed, I as the
                    security officer, engaged in long investigations of individuals and wrote
                    reports on individuals who had applied to work in the Consulate General</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we get much support from the British?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Oh, yes. I personally didn't have much contact with the British, but I am
                    sure we did. We were generally sympathetic to them and their own administration
                    of Hong Kong as a colony of theirs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you did this until 1960 and then where did you
                        go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I had home leave and then I was sent to Jakarta.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>WALKIN: I was in Jakarta from March 1961 to December 1963; then I was moved from
                    Jakarta to Surabaya.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation like in Jakarta in 1961?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: It was a fascinating situation for me. Here I had been, as I think I told
                    you, for four years in INR, working on the internal political conditions of the
                    Soviet Union through reading communist papers everyday. We all had a pretty
                    clear idea of the situation. Or, at least, we thought we did. This assessment
                    was not done by the CIA at that time; it was done by this group in INR that did
                    the basic intelligence on what was happening in Communist China which was one of
                    their principle missions: to assess the situation actually in Communist China;
                    something which the political section could not do since our Diplomatic Mission
                    was rather restricted. A good deal of work was done through reading the
                    Communist press right there in Hong Kong, instead of making contact with the
                    local Chinese. But, what I was getting at, was the fact that our relations with
                    the Chinese were limited on the mainland in that a good deal of the political
                    work was being done there in Hong Kong. Now, I had no direct connection with
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now in Jakarta, in 1961, what job did you have when you
                        came there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I was chief of the Consular Section and I sat with the chiefs of other
                    sections every morning with Ambassador Jones, for example.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, Howard Jones was the Ambassador. What was your
                        impression of Howard Jones and how he operated?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I find that difficult to answer because my actual contact with him was
                    limited. What I am bound to remember is his particular attitude toward Sukarno
                    and his readiness to continue relations with Sukarno, regardless of what he did.
                    I happened to be in Jakarta in the spring or summer of 1963, when Sukarno
                    ordered the British Embassy sacked.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, it was sacked and burned.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>WALKIN: Well, it was rather disturbing to all of us. We didn't know whether we
                    would be next or not. I remember that day quite vividly. Well, we were not
                    touched and I guess that I started to tell you that being assigned to Indonesia,
                    Jakarta first and then Surabaya, I got an idea of the contrast between a
                    totalitarian state, like the former Soviet Union and an autocratic state, like
                    Indonesia, where all sorts of things happened that couldn't conceivably happen
                    in a place like the Soviet Union. So my being for four years in Indonesia was a
                    fairly enlightening experience for me, and also frightening at times, because,
                    as I think you know, Sukarno declared us a mortal enemy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Wasn't this the year of living dangerously?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I confirm that. We could never be sure whether there would be a mob
                    pounding rocks at us at any time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the other officers at the embassy? Did
                        you find a split between the other officers at the embassy and Ambassador
                        Howard Jones?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I wouldn't put it that way. Everybody understood this problem though
                    Jones was more tolerant of somebody like Sukarno, who had basically declared
                    political war on us in the summer of 1964, than we were prepared to accept. A
                    typical example is what happened after the sacking of the British Embassy. We
                    were all, of course, enraged with Sukarno; but not Jones. And, since we were
                    enraged, and this was not the policy that he wanted the Embassy to carry across
                    to Sukarno, he set up a cocktail party at which all of us met with Sukarno and
                    shook his hand. I have a picture of me shaking his hand. It is a good thing that
                    it shows the back of my head and not my face, because I am sure my face would
                    have been contorted while I was shaking Sukarno's hand. That problem was endemic
                    during all of the Jones years there and until he was replaced by Marshall
                    Green.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As chief of the consular section, what was your main work
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I guess it was basically issuing visas. I have no exact recollection of
                    doing anything else. We had a small consular section, and I was the chief.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was wondering if you had any Americans in jail or
                        something like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: We had no particular problems that I can recall that I worked on.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this was not a time when Americans were going to
                        Indonesia as tourists and all.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Well it was, until Sukarno declared, more or less, war on us, and
                    declared us one of the principal enemies of mankind, more or less in the manner
                    of the Communist Chinese.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you went to Surabaya from what, 1963 to 1964?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: 1965, I left in November of 1965.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many Americans were in Surabaya?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I'm not sure I can give you a figure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Probably just a few.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Yes, just a few. The visitors I can remember the most were those I met
                    due to the fact that I, as the Deputy to the Consul, had a government house with
                    a guest room. Americans from the region used to stop by and I would meet them
                    and give them this guest room and also breakfast in the morning. That was my
                    principle meetings with Americans. I did not see too many Americans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have many dealings with the Indonesians while you
                        were in Surabaya?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I knew quite a few of them, particularly since I spoke Indonesian. I had
                    parties for them, that was something I was supposed to do. I went to cocktail
                    parties whenever I was invited; that was also something I was supposed to do. I
                    had a very pleasant relationship with a group of Indonesians in the Foreign
                    Office back in Jakarta, where I had been for more than two years. Incidentally,
                    as Consul in Surabaya and as an American there who did political and economic
                    reporting, I achieved a certain reputation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a period where we were looking very closely at
                        what Sukarno was doing, whether he was going to turn the country over to the
                        Communists or not. You must have been doing reporting on that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>WALKIN: I certainly was. I was the only one doing reporting on that. When two
                    inspectors came out there, I guess they publicly commented on the fact that I
                    was the only one doing reporting on that. But I also got compliments later,
                    which I would have to repeat here that the political counselor in Jakarta at the
                    time was Ed Masters, who later became ambassador. Marshall Green was at that
                    time the Ambassador, and Jack Lydman was Deputy Chief of Mission. Masters was
                    the third in line there. When I retired from the Foreign Service and went to
                    teach at Auburn, I went to Washington every year and one of my first years, when
                    I went from Alabama to Washington in the summer, I met with Ed Masters, who was
                    back in Washington at that time. Later, of course, he was appointed Ambassador.
                    But during the course of our luncheon, he said, “No one before or since you were
                    in Surabaya has reported on East Java the way you did.” And this, by the way,
                    also led me, when I returned to the Department later, to take the dispatches
                    that I had written, remove the classified information - I don't think any were
                    classified more than confidential - and wrote an article which I called, “The
                    Muslim Communist Confrontation in East Java, 1964 1965”, which was eventually
                    published with the approval of the Department. I got quite a compliment from the
                    editorial board of the publication, Orbis, which is still a quarterly journal of
                    international relations based in Philadelphia. They sent me a letter when I sent
                    them a copy of the article: the editorial board unanimously and enthusiastically
                    accepts your article.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you run across Bob Martens?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Oh, certainly. I met him here, too. He's been here. He sat for you.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I interviewed Bob Martens, and also Dick Howland, who
                        I think he was there a little later.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I think a little later. I would know all the names of those who were
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there the last day of September and the first day
                        of October 1965?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I was. The article that was published was based on the fact that I was
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened in Surabaya, when there was this coup?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I remember many publicly monitored stations and of course I was talking
                    to anyone I could as well as reading the local press. I also watched the
                    Communists and Muslims in the marches they did in the streets of Surabaya. I
                    deliberately left my post to go out and watch them. Remember that I could speak
                    Indonesian fairly well. I had this opportunity, not just to see what both groups
                    were doing and to see their street demonstrations, but to talk to many
                    people.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When Marshall Green came to Indonesia in early 1965 or in
                        summer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: That's accurate, early 1965.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did that make a difference, do you feel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Not to me, working in Surabaya, no. I had had very cordial relations with
                    Howard Jones throughout and I continued to have them with Marshall Green. When I
                    gave them a copy of my article, after I had retired and a couple of years after
                    I returned to Washington, he was quite grateful. He was, I guess, himself
                    writing about that period, and he accepted my article with considerable
                    graciousness, for a man of his office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your orientation on the leaders in Surabaya? Were
                        they on the Communist Sukarno side or on the Nationalist side that joined up
                        with Suharto?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: They were on the Nationalist side. I don't really remember talking to too
                    many pro Communist people. I have no recollection of it now, but I probably
                    did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When Suharto took over, was there any fighting in
                        Surabaya?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Not in Surabaya, but you probably have heard of the killings of the
                    Communists that took place, and the accusations against Bob Martens, that he
                    instigated it. I really saw nothing of it from my position in the Consulate. I
                    knew it was going on, of course, from reading the local press avidly, every
                    day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you left there in 1965, where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Back to the Department. I was assigned to the Office of Migration and
                    Refugees and I remained there until I formally - this was the beginning of 1966
                    - left the Department in September of 1969 and became a professor of Political
                    Science at Auburn University.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what were you doing in Refugee and Migration
                        Affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>WALKIN: I was in charge of the Far East. In retrospect, when you ask me 30 years
                    later, what I was doing, I say, I was in the refugee business. There were some
                    very close relations I had with some Tibetans. I helped them stage some sort of
                    reception at the National Gallery and I talked to the head of the Tibetan group
                    in Washington quite a bit. I was also monitoring letters on refugee questions
                    sent by Congressmen, that usually came to me from the political bureau. They
                    were the ones monitoring this, and they were routinely sent to me personally,
                    because I was the one who looked over Congressional replies on refugee problems
                    for the section. My boss part of the time, was Graham Martin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, boy. How was he as a boss? He has quite a
                        reputation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I think he was a remarkable man. One of the reasons is that I didn't
                    realize at the time how much of a liking he had for me. Once, in 1969, I think
                    it was, while testifying on the budget for the section in a Congressional
                    subcommittee, he specifically mentioned two names as being outstanding officers
                    under his command: me in Jakarta and I forget the name of my associate then in
                    charge in Geneva. He mentioned these two names publicly. I have the volume of it
                    somewhere here. If you like, I could call you when I find it. I am a research
                    person. I have all sorts of material here, and can't find most of it myself. But
                    I probably will find it and I'll call you if you want to see it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, good.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I'll be glad to call you and actually show you the volume in which he
                    mentioned me.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>My feeling is that I met two Foreign Service giants through my 10 years overseas:
                    Julius Holmes in Hong Kong and Graham Martin in the Department. A number of us
                    ate in the State Department cafeteria, which was and probably still is, open
                    until seven, because there are people there all the time. A number of us used to
                    eat our dinners there. Whenever Martin came down there and saw me sitting alone,
                    he always came to sit with me. There were a number of my associates who could
                    confirm that, particularly Henry Heymann, who was also in Jakarta in that time.
                    Well, I think it was a great privilege to know Graham Martin and to have been
                    admired by him. If I had been conscious of how much he admired me... I don't
                    regard it as anything unusual, but I just failed at that time to grasp the
                    extent of the admiration he had for me. But then it was too late when I finally
                    spoke to him in his hometown: Winston Salem, North Carolina. If he had been well
                    enough, he would have invited me to his home to watch me spar with faculty
                    members with whom I disagreed. I, of course, have been a hardliner on Soviet
                    Russia throughout my life; you wouldn't expect me to be otherwise, especially
                    after working four years on Soviet intelligence. He would have loved to see me
                    taking apart faculty members with whom he used to meet periodically. I would
                    have had an opportunity to talk to him about Vietnam, because I followed Vietnam
                    quite a bit; I do not agree with the public statements made about it now, and I
                    know he would not have agreed with them either, if he were alive. But, I reached
                    him near the end of his life. It was such a trip to Winston Salem. It just never
                    became possible, though I would have enjoyed it immensely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved at all, when you were in Refugees and
                        Migration, with this sort of American domestic politics involved in that
                        bureau or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: No. I have no recollection of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, the main exodus from Asia during the time you were
                        responsible for, was the result of the Chinese invasion of Tibet, was that
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: Yes, I vividly remember my association with the chief of the Tibetans in
                    Washington and the party we gave together at the National Gallery. I was busy
                    and even talking to Graham Martin every day, but I have no strong recollection
                    of exactly what I did during the three and a half years I worked at the State
                    Department. My work in INR was at the old SA-1 building, across the street from
                    the main building. But I was now in the main building when I came back from
                    Indonesia and was assigned in the Bureau of Migration and Refugee Affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left the Department of State in 1969 and you went to
                        Auburn. Auburn is where now?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>WALKIN: It's in Alabama. It is the old land grant institution and the sister
                    institution of the University of Alabama. It is located in the Eastern part of
                    Alabama, about 35 miles west of Columbus, Georgia and Fort Benning. The
                    University of Alabama in Tuscaloosa was the liberal arts college in the old
                    days, while Auburn was the agricultural and engineering college; it was
                    completely integrated by the time I arrived there. The rivalry between the
                    University of Alabama and Auburn is, of course, well known throughout the
                    South.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You started there in 1969 and this is the height of the
                        anti-Vietnamese protests; but, you were in the heart of the Deep South,
                        which was not particularly strongly protesting, from what I gather.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: That is correct. I have very strong views on Vietnam because I followed
                    it. I think that what is publicly statethe Lehrer program [The NewsHour with Jim
                    Lehrer, Public Television program] the last three dayis one-sided and, well,
                    useless. This sort of traditional way of looking at Vietnam is not the way to
                    understand it. Put briefly, I would put it this way: no President in office
                    would have allowed the North Vietnamese to intervene in South Vietnam and ensure
                    that the South Vietnamese Communists won. If we did it in one country, we would
                    have done it in all the countries. No President would have accepted this,
                    including Kennedy. There is overwhelming evidence that Kennedy did not accept
                    it, even though there are people who say that he was ready to get out. This is
                    nonsense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course it's nonsense. Well, you were at Auburn from
                        when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: The fall of 1969 until I left to come here, which was July 1993. We
                    stayed there after I retired, because it was really a pleasant community and I
                    was strong enough to live there by myself, which I did. My daughter took my
                    place in the State Department. Have you seen this poster I have here on
                    Milosevic?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I will take a look at it in a minute.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>WALKIN: She got some copies for me. I stayed at Auburn because it was a pleasant
                    community in which to do my research and writing; I also had the help to be
                    there alone. I could be visited alone by my daughter there. I guess it was she
                    who realized that she could not take care of me properly while I was there. In
                    1992 to 1993, we arranged for me to move to this apartment as a “condominium
                    home,” if you know the lingo of senior living communities. Incidentally, I was
                    not actually discharged from the Department when I left in 1969. They told me
                    this and I know no details, “We are going to put you on leave without pay,”
                    because this would increase my pension. I don't know what the details were, but
                    I was not formally separated from the Department until February 28, 1970,
                    although I actually left in September 1969. When I got to Washington as an
                    Auburn professor that first summer of 1970, in which I told you about the
                    luncheon with Ed Masters, I had been formally separated from the Department. But
                    I was on leave without pay from 1969 to the end of February in 1970.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you certainly had an interesting career.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I did. I regard my career in my old age as having been unusually
                    successful. The key to it, probably, was the fact that I was drafted in World
                    War II and spent over three years in the United States Army. I knew nothing
                    about the GI Bill, I did not object to being drafted. I felt it was proper to
                    serve in the Army, but I had four years of eligibility under the GI Bill. For
                    the first time in my life, I could go to graduate school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So many of us owe our future to the GI Bill. I have a GI
                        mortgage on my house. I got a master's degree because of the GI Bill. I met
                        my wife because of the GI Bill. So the GI Bill was very useful.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WALKIN: I would regard it as an essential part of my career. I could not have
                    become either a Foreign Service Officer nor a professor without it, without my
                    advanced degrees, and I made the right decisionwith that I had a very successful
                    career.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I'll just sign off here. I want to thank you very
                        much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
