<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000903">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Frank Pavich </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>United States Foreign Assistance Oral History ProgramForeign Affairs Oral History
                    Collection Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training</p>
                <p>An interview with Frank Pavich</p>
                <p>Interviewed by W. Haven Nort</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: March 26, 1998</p>
                <p>Introduction</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is an interview with Frank Pavich. Frank, how many
                        yearwere you with AID?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I was with AID for thirty years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you start?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I started in 1966.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you retired when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I retired in Cairo, Egypt in June of 1996.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Give us a thumb nail sketch of your career so we have the
                        wholpicture before we go into the specifics.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I came to AID in the early '60s when the program opened up in Vietnam and
                    they were looking for provincial advisors. I came in at that point and was in
                    Vietnam for six and a half years and then came back to Washington for two years.
                    I then went back out to Ethiopia, the Yemen Arab Republic, Somalia, Ghana,
                    Pakistan, and finally to Egypt.</p>
                <p>Early years and education</p>
                <p>Q: Okay, let's start out with where you grew up, your early education, and
                    whether there anything during this time that suggested you might get into
                    international development type work.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>PAVICH: I was born in 1933 and grew up in San Francisco, California. San
                    Francisco was an international port and I was always intrigued by that. There
                    was a coming and going of ships and people. My father was from Yugoslavia, my
                    mother was Italian-Irish and our friends were Europeans, a mixture of first and
                    second generation Americans. I graduated from high school in San Francisco and
                    was fortunate to get an athletic scholarship to the University of Southern
                    California. I started out as a physical education major, because that seemed to
                    be a natural for a jock.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your sport?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I was a football player. I wondered at the time why I should play
                    football for three quarters of the year and then continue to learn the same type
                    of thing about sports and athletics. I wasn't that much into the sports. So, I
                    switched from physical education to Public Administration (PA). One of my
                    friends at the time was in PA, and we talked about it and it seemed to me if I
                    wasn't interested in business I was interested in doing something that seemed to
                    be useful and felt that government would be the proper place to do that. So, I
                    got a Bachelor of Science degree in Public Administration in 1955. Then I went
                    into the Marine Corps as an Infantry officer for two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you serve overseas in the Marine Corps?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No, I was U.S. based. It was just at the end of the Korean War and I was
                    fortunate. But I did get my first introduction to how a big organization worked
                    and the management dynamics that are present in that kind of environment and
                    what it takes to work with people and be either a leader or a follower. Some of
                    the experience from the athletics carried over into being a Marine officer. It
                    certainly was a rewarding experience.</p>
                <p>After the Marine Corps I went to work as a city planner in San Francisco. This
                    was only a short term assignment. I was filling in for people who were on
                    vacations. I was there for about six months. However, I got my foot in the door
                    and got some exposure to the business of city planning, working with a
                    commission and the public and thinking about urban problems. After San
                    Francisco, I took a job in Mountain View, California, where I was Assistant City
                    Planner. I worked there primarily in annexations, which was a big thing in
                    California in those days. This was bringing in all the unincorporated territory
                    around the cities into the cities to broaden their tax base and develop. I was
                    working in what is now Silicon Valley. I watched that coming from way back.</p>
                <p>Joined the Peace Corps - 1962</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>In 1962 my boss at the City Planning Commission called my attention to a program
                    that had just been initiated by President John Kennedy, the Peace Corps. He
                    thought I might be interested in it, although I don't know why he thought so. I
                    applied and was accepted to join either the program in Tunisia or the program in
                    Iran. It turned out to be the Iranian program. Our group was the second Peace
                    Corps program in the field.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why were you interested in doing that at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The idea of traveling had been on my mind since I was a kid swimming in
                    San Francisco bay. This seemed to be a legitimate opportunity for getting into
                    something that would take me there and I could learn something at the same time.
                    So, I went to Iran for two years. At first I worked with an Iranian university.
                    Ironically, I was a basketball coach. Then I graduated from that to the Iran
                    Municipal Association, where I was taken on as an Assistant City Planner. I
                    worked there with five Iranian architects and engineers. We did basic city
                    planning for some of the provincial cities, although we worked out of Tehran. A
                    lot of it was design work which wasn't my field. So, it was interesting for me
                    to work with these architects who were doing urban design.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did you do that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: For two years. I left Iran in the middle of 1964 anaccepted a fellowship
                    to the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find working with the Iranians at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Oh, I found it to be very interesting and rewarding and a lot of fun.
                    They were very nice, friendly, warm people and good to work with. I enjoyed the
                    experience very much. I learned a lot there. Things that carried me through
                    situations later on when I was working with AID.</p>
                <p>I left Iran to go to the University of Pittsburgh to study public and
                    international affairs. It was a new school and new field. I stayed for a year
                    and got my masters in public administration. Then I preceded to look for work
                    overseas. I went to New York and looked at the UN and some of the voluntary
                    agencies like Catholic Relief and CARE. I went to Washington and talked to USAID
                    and they didn't have anything at the time. So, I went back to California and
                    began doing a job search there for work in urban renewal or development.</p>
                <p>First years with USAID in Vietnam - 1966</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>One morning I had an appointment in Oakland, California to interview for a job in
                    their urban renewal office. I got two telegrams at the same time. One was from
                    AID and one was from CARE. Rather than reading them I stuck them in my pocket
                    and went across the bay to Oakland to do my interview. I didn't want to be
                    distracted. It was a good interview and I got a job offer. I came out of the
                    Oakland City Hall and walked down the street and opened up the telegrams. The
                    one from CARE invited me to take a job in Yugoslavia or Egypt. I opened up the
                    other one from AID and it said they were starting to recruit people for a
                    program in Southeast Asia, Vietnam, and would I be interested.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was what year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: This was in 1966. I continued walking down the street and I saw a sign
                    that said Western Union. I reached in my pocket, pulled out a quarter, flipped
                    it, and it came up AID. I then sent two telegrams, one to AID saying yes, and
                    one to CARE saying no thank you. That was how the decision was made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you have believed the quarter if it had come out the
                        otheway?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, in hind sight I think I made the right decision, but at the time I
                    really didn't know. I had worked a little bit with CARE in Iran and I was rather
                    intrigued with what they were doing.</p>
                <p>I came to Washington and joined a group at FSI for preparation to go to Vietnam.
                    We were in language training, area studies and were told to play soccer because
                    they thought our counterparts would be playing soccer. They took us down to the
                    Marine Corps base at Quantico and we qualified on the pistol, semi and automatic
                    weapons and were advised to buy a small arm for ourselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your understanding of what your job was?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Provincial Representative somewhere in Vietnam. They suggested we all
                    have a personal weapon. I mulled that over and didn't buy one at the time. I
                    remember a group of us went out—a mixed group of male and female. We had nurses,
                    former Peace Corps people, people just out of law school, graduate school. I
                    remember one night over a couple of beers we were talking about what was going
                    to be our greatest challenge of this career we were about to set off on. We were
                    all new to this. It was almost like the Peace Corps again. We thought about the
                    danger there and that we might get killed or captured, as some did. Or, we might
                    step on a land mine, or something like that. I thought our biggest problem would
                    probably be our own bureaucracy. I don't know why that came to me at that time.
                    However, for me, throughout all of my career, it has been a battle between
                    myself and the bureaucracy. There has been a sort of give and take on that. I
                    often wonder what made me think of it then. I knew Public Administration before
                    I went into the Marine , which was my first taste of bureaucracy, and I could
                    see the problem.</p>
                <p>We went to Vietnam and the next thing I knew we were being interviewed by John
                    Paul Van, who was the Provincial Coordinator at that time. We were given our
                    assignments. I was assigned to go to Plei-Ku province in the Central Highlands.
                    One morning at sunrise in Saigon I got on a small aircraft and headed for a
                    place called Nha Trang, which was on the coast of Central Vietnam. I got off the
                    plane and went to the regional headquarters and met a man named Hatcher James
                    who was the Deputy Regional Director at that time. He was a former Green Beret
                    and he said, “Okay, Pavich, you are going out to Plei-ku. We are going to send
                    you out to Cheo Reo and Kontum [and one other place which I don't remember], to
                    stay with the Special Forces B Team for a couple of nights just to let you know
                    what you are getting into. If you have any doubts or questions about what you
                    are getting into this will be a good test because the B Teams are small teams
                    out on the frontier. They will have around five Americans and 70 or so
                    militiamen who are defending the out-post.” I went out there and sat around for
                    a couple of days. We didn't go out very much because it was dangerous. We got to
                    know the U.S. Army Green Berets who were there and talk to them about what they
                    were doing. I looked at the fortifications and learned about the Vietcong.</p>
                <p>Then, I got to Plei-ku and worked with a gentleman named John Rogers, who was the
                    Provincial Representative. I was his assistant “Prov. Rep.” We had programs in
                    health, agriculture, fisheries, education and in two or three other areas. These
                    programs were provided through a special budget that was funded by USAID. The
                    purpose was to supplement and improve upon what the Government of Vietnam was
                    doing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How big a population was there in this area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I can't remember. Plei-Ku Province is basically a Montagnard province so
                    the population of Vietnamese is very small and the population of Montagnards is
                    probably not even known because they are not settled.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>My job was to work with the provincial service chiefs on thimplementation of the
                    development programs in each one of these areas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the objective?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: To improve the service. To provide the people in the province with the
                    kind of services that they needed in their agricultural development and the
                    education of their children and the health of their families. In some cases
                    where there were refugees coming in from the jungle areas where there was a free
                    fire zone, our goal was to house them and care for them and protect them until
                    they could return home or be resettled.</p>
                <p>This meant traveling out into the districts, which we did and this is where the
                    exposure to the U.S. Special Forces was good, because in all of these areas
                    there was a Special Forces Team and you coordinated with them before you drove
                    down any road to make sure it was clear. All the major roads were cleared every
                    morning at a certain hour. You would find out when they were cleared and safe
                    and then go out there, or, you would go up to a Special Forces camp and use one
                    of their helicopters and fly out to the district.</p>
                <p>We were doing water projects with the Montagnards, building small dams around
                    springs and putting plastic pipes in the wall of the dam so that you had a spill
                    of water going onto a concrete apron in front. People used the apron for washing
                    and bathing. It was very popular. They did the work, we provided the material.
                    We also provided material for building schools.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many in the AID team were doing this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: There were two of us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were expert in all of these fields?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. It was administration. We didn't have to be substance experts
                    because the Vietnamese service chiefs were. We spoke enough Vietnamese to get by
                    and it really wasn't a technical problem, but more of a question of
                    resources.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any problems or events that you remember from
                        thatime?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>PAVICH: There were attacks by the Vietcong and if you were in a district there
                    would be problems of being cutoff from transportation out and being stuck there
                    for a while. You flew across the plains in helicopters at about 40 feet and
                    sometimes you were shot at. The helicopter pilots liked to fly low, they called
                    it contour flying, because it was hard for anyone to know you were coming until
                    you were there. If you were up high everybody would know you were there and
                    could shoot at you.</p>
                <p>I spent a year and a half there and then I had an opportunity to go to Saigon to
                    work in the AID Public Administration Office. There I worked with the Director
                    General of Reconstruction and Urban Planning and the Director General of Housing
                    as an advisor and program manager.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: In the government. I was physically located in the office of the Director
                    General of Reconstruction and Urban Planning. I was the only American there. I
                    had a staff of about 21 young Vietnamese architects. Our basic program was a
                    Land Use Study which is an inventory of the use of land in the Saigon
                    metropolitan area, which had a 10 million population. We had aerial photographs
                    and maps and checked each parcel of land in that whole area, and categorized it
                    in terms of its use. It took us two years to do this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was for planning and laying out development of all
                        kinds?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Planning for infrastructure, for utilities, etc. Almost everything you do
                    is based on the population and the use of the land. It was also to assist them
                    in determining a zoning program and to decide where they wanted and didn't want
                    to put industry and things like that.</p>
                <p>I was there for pretty much three years doing this work and other assignments. We
                    did some housing development plans for relocating people who were burned out of
                    their houses in the TET offensive in 1968.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there in the TET offensive?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, I was there. Actually, I missed it by one day, but I was there for
                    the rebuilding of these areas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a lot of destruction?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>PAVICH: In certain districts where the Vietcong had come in. They would come into
                    areas where there were a lot of squatters. In these areas, there were no
                    facilities like fire hydrants or water. Once a fire started there, there was no
                    way that you could get a truck in because there were no streets, just lanes for
                    bicycles and people, and the area just burned to the ground. There were several
                    thousands of people who were displaced and had to be resettled somewhere else.
                    We were doing a housing program. That pretty much kept me busy until I left
                    Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find working with the Vietnamese?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The professionals I worked with were very good. They knew their business.
                    They were very cordial and welcomed what assistance I could give them on the
                    development side. They were very friendly and always polite. I enjoyed their
                    company very much and made some very good friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you feel about your efforts to do all this
                        developmenwork in the environment of war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I believe it was making a difference, otherwise the Viet Cong (VC)
                    probably wouldn't have attacked Saigon the way they did. I think there was a
                    point where the business of winning the hearts and minds, for whatever reason,
                    was going our way. There were jobs, lots of money to be made. It might have been
                    a false economy, but still it provided work for people and money for people. I
                    think that was probably the reason that the VC did some of the things they did
                    which were probably not in the guerilla warfare book of tactics. So, I think
                    what we were doing did have an effect.</p>
                <p>Q: Was it lasting, or was it all sort of lost when the Vietcong took over?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, I think like in the “Cold War” it is a question of who won and who
                    lost. It was pretty clear that the Communists lost almost every place. Who won?
                    I think that is still to be determined.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about in Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I would like to go back and see.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You haven't heard much about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>PAVICH: No. My wife is Vietnamese and she has been back. Mchildren have been
                    back. But, I have never been back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did they find things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It is very poor. There wasn't much of an economy and the people had very
                    little. They were not very happy with the way things were. The government was
                    every bit as corrupt as it always had been, but I think in Asia as it is
                    apparent these days, corruption is part of the socio-economic fabric.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You saw this when you were working with the government
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. It was quite common.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What form did it take?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: There is always a certain amount of rake-off that happens. You know it is
                    going on but you can't really put your finger on it. They know you know. You try
                    to control it. You couldn't wipe it out, but it was possible to keep it to a
                    minimum because that is the way things worked. People in countries like Vietnam
                    and other developing countries who work in government are paid very low wages
                    and have to have a second job. This means they don't pay much attention to their
                    primary job, and are often taking bribes. As they say, “If you break the rice
                    bowl (the means of livelihood), nothing is going to happen.” It is a choice. You
                    want something to happen or not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You finished there in 1972, before the end of the war.
                        Where diyou go from there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Joined USAID's Housing Office in Washington - 1972</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>PAVICH: In 1972 I came back to Washington to a job which vanished somewhere
                    between Tokyo and San Francisco. I ended up working in the Population Office.
                    They were doing a Population and Urbanization Policy Project with Johns Hopkins
                    University. I worked there for about six months helping to develop the
                    frame-work for the program. This wasn't quite hands on enough for me, so I
                    talked to Peter Kimm, who was running the Office of Housing, telling him that I
                    would like to work in his program. I was invited to come and work for the Office
                    of Housing. I became a Housing Guarantee Loan Officer. My projects were Taiwan,
                    Korea, Thailand, Vietnam and Iran. I actually got to go to Iran ten years after
                    I left there when I was in the Peace Corps, and was able to see what was going
                    on. I was in the Office of Housing mainly processing the loan applications which
                    meant a lot of technical work in putting together plans and getting the loans
                    approved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find working in that unit, which is kind of a
                        uniquunit in AID?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I liked it because it was an urban development program and that was my
                    field at the time. Although, again, it wasn't quite hands on enough for me.
                    Being a loan officer wasn't really what I wanted to do, but working in urban
                    development was, so it was a compromise. I stayed there...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember any of the projects particularly that
                        stood out in your mind?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, we did several projects. We did them in Taiwan and...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of projects were they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was a middle income housing project. All of them were middle income
                    housing projects. We did start to think about low income housing, but it was
                    tough because the Office of Housing was a unique organization. It paid its own
                    way, there wasn't a subsidy there, only a guarantee by the U.S. government. The
                    money came from private investors. So, you couldn't get into programs like low
                    income housing where you needed a big subsidy. You had to find things that would
                    pay for themselves. So, we did middle income housing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did it work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, it did work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You thought it was quite successful?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, it was, particularly in Korea later on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember the scale of any of these projects?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: These were 50, 70 million dollar projects. This was in thlate '60s and
                    early '70s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This wasn't sites and services only?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No, the whole thing was housing. At that point we were trying to figure
                    out how you could do the sites and services. Subsequently, after I left, they
                    did do sites and services but I don't know on how big a scale.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any typical issues that you had to
                        address?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Issues were pretty clear cut. Could they qualify for the loan? Did they
                    have a good plan? Was the rate of return sufficient to pay back the loan?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't have problems with private business?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: You did have administrative problems where they were slow on the paper
                    work or something like that. Or slow on construction, not getting things built
                    on schedule or cost over runs. That sort of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved with local institutions and their
                        housininstitutions?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>PAVICH: I did in Iran. They had a particular problem in Iran which was typical
                    but I guess hard to understand from the Washington perspective. The housing
                    project was in a city named Isfahan and was far behind schedule and beginning to
                    go over budget. So, three of us went to Isfahan to try and troubleshoot the
                    situation. To see what was going on and what could be done. The Shah of Iran had
                    brought back a number of young Iranians who had gone to the United States and
                    received their training and settled here. They were engineers, architects, and
                    other professionals. He brought them back to Iran and put them into sort of
                    special organizations within the government that paid a higher salary than the
                    normal. It was sort of a hybrid organization. The head of this new organization
                    was not one of the young returnees. You had these young Iranian professionals
                    who had been educated in the United States who had worked in the United States
                    and were used to a different way of doing things, back in a culture where the
                    patriarch always had the final word, right or wrong. There was constant fighting
                    among everybody on their team, no one agreed with anybody because they were back
                    in the old system and nobody could make decisions, only the “old man.” Nobody
                    would fess up to the problems with the head of the organization because that is
                    not the way things are done in the Iranian culture. The only way we found this
                    out about the cause of the problems was through interviews with each of the
                    young Iranians. They told us that they couldn't do anything because of the
                    system. They were stuck in the old system, “we think in a different way but have
                    to do it in the old way and the “old man” doesn't know what we are talking
                    about. We are fighting among ourselves and he is not settling the differences,
                    so, nothing is happening.”</p>
                <p>That was pretty much as we left it. We tried to get them step-by-step to make
                    some decisions and I think probably very painfully they did, but I don't know if
                    the overall problem was resolved because I left the Office of Housing to take an
                    assignment in Ethiopia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What year was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Transfer to USAID/Ethiopia in Rural Development - 1975</p>
                <p>PAVICH: In 1975.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right after the coup.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Right. Haile Selassie was under house arrest. Teferi Benti was the
                    chairman of thDergue which was a secret organization that ran the country. It
                    was a very tense time. There was a lot going on there that wasn't very nice.
                    People were getting killed at night. There were mass executions. It was pretty
                    bad. I was assigned to the Rural Development Office. My job was drought relief
                    in the four southern provinces of Ethiopia.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which ones were these?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Bale, Sidamo, Gamo-Gofa and Harar. It was an ideal job fome.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you supposed to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: There were thousands of refugees who were stuck in the huge area of
                    southeastern Ethiopia called the Ogaden. These people were Somalis, and Oromo
                    peoples. Because of the drought their livestock were dead and they were starving
                    to death. Our job was basically to organize a group to go out and find them, get
                    them settled, organize a program of relief for them and try to find ways to put
                    them into productive work to grow their own food or do something for
                    themselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You worked with the Ethiopian Relief Commission?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I worked with a very wonderful gentleman, Shamalis Arjuna. Because USAID
                    had the capacity, we would put together four or five vehicle safaris to the
                    drought stricken areas about once every six weeks. We would send the vehicles
                    out to jumping off points. The travelers would fly out there and join the
                    vehicles and go for five or seven days into the Ogaden to the areas where the
                    refugees were located. We would have medical people, relief people and other
                    donor agency people with us. We would do an assessment, file a report. Based on
                    the report findings, regular relief mechanism would take over, consolidate the
                    refugees into staging areas, settle them, feed them, get them back to health.
                    Once the refugees were taken care of, we would try to put them into agriculture
                    or road work cutting new roads so relief vehicles could get into isolated areas
                    with food and medical supplies, or redoing the regular roads which were in
                    pretty bad shape.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your job was mostly the reconnaissance aspect?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: My job was to organize our trips and coordinate them with the other
                    agencies and do a trip report. Then I would work on follow up things like a
                    project to provide whatever assistance the U.S. could to support refugee
                    development activities. It was pretty interesting. It took me all through
                    southern Ethiopia. There were some wonderful areas that were pretty primitive
                    and wild. It was camping out. It was a good experience. People were paying
                    thousands of dollars to go on Safari to do what I was doing every six weeks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had an Ethiopian team you went with?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. I had two Ethiopian assistants and a team of drivers that did the
                    driving and cooking. Some agencies and donor offices didn't have the capacity to
                    go to the field, so we provided this service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you took them along with you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. We took UN and World Food Program people along and anybody who had a
                    legitimate reason to go. You didn't go there on your own because it was
                    dangerous. There were bandits who would rob you and kill you. If you broke down
                    and you were alone, you were at risk, after the jump off point there were no
                    more gas stations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was the jump off point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: There were a number of them. We would take a truck full of 55 gallon
                    drums of gasoline. Often we would send it ahead and stash it at the police post,
                    so we could go there and get our gas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was the situation in Ethiopia at that time? It was
                        gettinrather difficult wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was pretty difficult and probably the worst it had been. Teferi Benti,
                    who was the chairman of the Dergue, was murdered in a staff meeting by Haile
                    Mariam Mengistu and there was a reign of terror. They were throwing people out
                    of windows and doing all kinds of terrible things. It was very bad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it dangerous for you and your family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: There was a curfew and you just didn't go out after that time because
                    that was when all these terrible things happened. It was secure during the day.
                    (End of tape)</p>
                <p>So the development program there was really in agriculture and we did get
                    involved a little bit in that trying to work with the drought victims. In the
                    Western part of Ethiopia we were doing road projects, pretty much putting roads
                    in areas where there were no roads and working with some very primitive people
                    who were basically pastoralists who were also affected by the drought, but not
                    as seriously as the people on the eastern side. One of our main programs was the
                    roads program. We would go out and do the survey work for the roads and develop
                    a project to do the roads and bring in technical assistance.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have to work with the government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, with the water authority, road authority, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Pretty good. The Ethiopians liked us. There were a lot of AID people
                    there who had been there for years and were running these agencies and had been
                    taught their trade by an American technician. I can remember sitting on the
                    banks of the Omo river in Southwest Ethiopia with these old water engineers
                    around a camp fire and they were telling us about Mr. So-and-so their AID
                    teacher. They would do their water business during the day and at night the AID
                    technician would teach them their job, help them understand new methods while
                    sitting around a camp fire. They were still doing the same work, the way they
                    were taught by the AID technicians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the politics at the moment making it more difficult to
                        worwith them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: What do you mean?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were hostile toward AID at one point weren't
                        they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, they were, but once you got out of the city and away from the
                    provincial flag pole, people were people and a lot of them were in bad shape and
                    needed help. They didn't mind the Americans, in fact, they liked us. Quietly
                    they would say, “Can't you do anything about this?” Unfortunately, there wasn't
                    much we could do.</p>
                <p>There was a reign of terror going on in the country. The government had organized
                    what they called “Kabellies,” or cells. Everyone was in a Kabelli and had to
                    report to somebody. There was always somebody in the system who was accusing
                    someone of being a traitor to the revolution and the next thing you knew after
                    curfew that person would be taken off and sometimes never seen again. A lot of
                    personal vendettas were worked out that way. It was a bad time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The AID program had to phase out at some point didn't
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It phased out because the Ethiopian government defaulted on a loan. I was
                    in the United States in the Development Studies Program and was told that we
                    couldn't go back.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was what year now?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: This was 1977. For me that was really a sad situation because I looked
                    forward to going back to Ethiopia, I loved the work. It was incredible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to get people settled and back into
                        productive lifat all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The Horn of Africa has always been a problem. The area went from drought
                    to floods so we went from drought relief to flood relief. Then there was a war
                    so there were refugees. It is still going on today and I guess it will always be
                    going on. It is a very bad situation because the area is over populated and the
                    people and their animals can't really support themselves on the land any more,
                    and there isn't any industry. Agriculture is sparse. It is a very problematic
                    area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to develop a sort of permanent indigenous
                        capacitto address these problems as opposed to having outsiders do it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The nomadic people have been coping with disasters for ages, they could
                    learn very little about survival from outsiders. They needed food and medicine
                    when the situation got very bad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean Ethiopian government or private institutions.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No. There was a certain amount of capacity in individuals, but the longer
                    they labored under that kind of regime the less effective they could be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about this relief and rehabilitation commission?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The “RRC” did all right. They were helping the people. The reason that
                    they brought down Haile Selassie was that he was not able to take care of the
                    people during one of the droughts. So, the RRC was under pressure to do a good
                    job or the same thing might happen to them. They did a good job and had a lot of
                    help from the outside. Unless there was an on-going World Bank or FAO project on
                    the area, there wasn't much going on in terms of government service in any
                    sector.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved in any of the long term development
                        projects?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which ones?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I don't remember the names but they were agricultural mainly. There were
                    some test farms and seed farms and developing different crops that were drought
                    resistant. That was pretty much it. We did have a pretty big agricultural
                    program there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any contact with the agricultural
                        university?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I personally did not. My relationships were basically witthe relief and
                    rehabilitation people and the water and roads people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any contact with the embassy at all at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. They were always interested in what we were doing because we were
                    out in the field, the frontier. Sometimes I think we were across the frontier.
                    We were sometimes the embassy's eyes and ears in the eastern and southwestern
                    parts of Ethiopia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were getting reports from you about what was going on
                        ithese areas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: They always read our reports and if there was something elsthey were
                    interested in they would call and ask questions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the AID mission shrinking at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was a large mission.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the director?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: John Withers and then Princeton Lyman. It was a great working setup. Some
                    of the people who were there went on to bigger and better things.</p>
                <p>I left in 1977 and went to the Development Studies Program aftewhich I couldn't
                    go back to Ethiopia.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>Attended the USAID Development Studies Program - 1977</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the development studies program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was very good. That was really my first formal introduction to
                    development economics and population dynamics and other subjects.</p>
                <p>Q: Anything stand out in your mind from that course?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, as a matter of fact. They sat us down when we first got there and
                    had each one of us write our theory on development. Then a few days later we got
                    together and made brief presentations of our theory. What they said and what we
                    found out is that there is no one theory of development. There are many theories
                    of development depending on your perspective. After we had done the theory, they
                    divided us up into groups, mixing the various development theories. So we were
                    mixed with people who had different views of development. When we did our on
                    site development training, which was in North Carolina, we went as a team and
                    did a development study of an area and tried to solve some of the development
                    problems. There were people there who had a social, economic, and administrative
                    perspectives on development. It was very good.</p>
                <p>I learned at that time what my perspective on development was. It had to do with
                    consensus building, planning and management, and getting people to participate
                    in developing the consensus and decision making. That is how I saw development
                    because of my planning and administration background. That is what I had been
                    doing, even as a Marine officer. And that was my work in drought relief. It was
                    always a matter of getting people to work together to define a problem and find
                    a technical solution for it, and then doing the things that needed to be done to
                    get the program on the ground and running, then monitoring the process and
                    making changes as you gain experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very much a kind of from bottom up sort of process?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, bottoms up approach. All of the good words that were said about my
                    performance had been that working with people was my strong point. I was able to
                    relate well with people I work with and get something done in that context. The
                    principles are pretty much what guided me. But, at that point I really learned
                    something more about development because it doesn't happen in isolation. I could
                    see my theory developing through experience, trial and error, as it related to
                    the others and how it supported other approaches or how it could be
                    supported.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember what some of the others might have
                        been?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Obviously there is the economic approach. The social, anthropological
                    approach which was pretty much coming from the people depending on who they are
                    and where they were coming from, perspective, vision, context.</p>
                <p>Of course there were more, there was quite a mixture. It was the pull of
                    leverage. You pull it towards economy. How do you get things moving.
                    Consequently, I have learned to work in all of these during the balance of my
                    experience after the development studies program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long was the course?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was about three months. After that I went to the Yemen Arab Republic.
                    I was assigned to the Rural Development Office. I was the Rural Development
                    Branch of some other division.</p>
                <p>Rural development in Yemen Arab Republic - 1977</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Yemen at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, the president, Al-Hamidi, who was in office when we arrived was
                    shortly afterwards assassinated. Then there was an attempt to assassinate Ali
                    Abdullah Saleh. I think he is gone now too. So, politically for Americans in
                    Yemen it was okay, but politically for the Yemeni it wasn't okay, there was a
                    lot of outside influence trying to gain control over Yemen, particularly the
                    Libyans. We almost got run over by Qadhafi one day walking downtown. He came to
                    town and allegedly bought one of the military divisions. Shortly thereafter,
                    there was an attempted coup, which was thwarted. There were a lot of stories
                    about that which were very intriguing.My job was basically to design a project
                    for development using local resources. Now this has got to be a laugh because
                    this is before the days of computers and we typed cables on stencils. My job was
                    to write the entire project paper, every part of it. I didn't type. I wrote the
                    thing in long hand and then it had to be transcribed into typed pages and I had
                    no one to help in the beginning. Fortunately, after working on the project for a
                    while, we had a team of technical people come in. A fellow named Norm Nicholson
                    was one, who later came and worked with AID.</p>
                <p>We all (the team) went to the field and looked over the situation and then tried
                    to decide what the problems were. We had a seminar and invited some of the
                    Yemeni NGO people and some of the government people and some U.S. and European
                    NGO people to talk about the problems of rural Yemen and what could be done to
                    support them. Basically it was water, roads, agriculture, health and education.
                    It didn't take much to guess that.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>Norm Nicholson arrived and we drove out one day with a Yemeni colleague to one of
                    the distant villages. We talked to some of the people there and coming back we
                    designed the project. We pretty much developed the concept of the project. After
                    they all left I put it together. It was very rough because I was writing things
                    I knew nothing about. I had to write the social part, the economic parts and all
                    of the different sections. Fortunately my wife was out of the country so I could
                    work all day and most of the night. When I would pack it up at night a guy named
                    Harry Johnson, who was The Program Officer, would come in after I had gotten the
                    draft together and typed. He worked from about 3 in the morning until about 8 in
                    the morning on the draft. And, we got it finished.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were under pressure to get it done, I would
                        guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. We got the thing together and I came to Washington and talked to Jim
                    Dalton, one of the old timers, a rural development guru. We had a presentation
                    and they basically approved the project we had to do. We had to clean up the
                    writing a bit to make it fit the format at the time. And, that was it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How big a project was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was $15 million, which was big for Yemen. There was a young
                    anthropologist who had just come into agency as an IDI [International
                    Development Intern], Diane Ponasik, who is now a regular AID officer assigned to
                    Haiti. She helped me with the project in Washington. We worked with Jim Dalton.
                    After approval I went back out to Yemen and Diane came out and worked for me in
                    her first field job. We got Cornell University and Chemonics to come out and do
                    the project.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the basic strategy of the project?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Basically the strategy was to improve access to isolatevillages which
                    were high in distant mountains in Yemen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a special area that you were concerned
                        with?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>PAVICH: There are three areas in Yemen. There is the Tihama, which is the lowland
                    area on the Red Sea, that runs into a mountainous area that then becomes a
                    plateau. Both of the villages that we were working with were in the mountainous
                    area. They were really pinnacles, on tops of mountains, because that is the way
                    they built them for security reasons. We went up to these villages and talked to
                    the head of the village or chief of the district. They didn't have office hours.
                    The only way you got to talk to them was from 4 until 7 in the afternoon in the
                    “Mufraj,” which was a big men only room, where you sat on cushions along the
                    walls. The chief sat at the far end, in the center, and the honored guests sat
                    to his left. Everybody else sat around him. They smoked water pipes and chewed
                    “quat,”which is an amphetamine. You had to go in there and do what they did. Q:
                    I suppose they didn't speak English?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: No, we had a translator. We would go in and sit there for a couple of
                    hours just watching the scene and watching the business transactions. All
                    business was transacted there. People would come in and shout or write little
                    notes and wad them up in a ball and throw them across the room at each other.
                    That is how they communicated with each other. We would be sitting up at the far
                    end on the left of the chief and would be given an arm full of quat to chew. So,
                    typically, Diane and I and our interpreter would sit there and chew until around
                    6:00 pm and then we would tell the chief what was on our mind. He would say yes
                    or no or maybe or whatever. And then we would go back and do some more work on
                    it. That is how we negotiated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There weren't any documents exchanged?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No. We did have a government agency in town to sign the documents but
                    each one of these areas was sort of owned by a Sheikh who ran it March 23, 2001
                    and you did what they did. That is why you had to go to the “Mufraj.” Never mind
                    going to the office because nothing happened in the office, it was just there.
                    Nobody paid any attention to it.</p>
                <p>I can remember taking Doug Bennett, our AID Administrator at the time, and a
                    Senator, up to the “Mufraj.” The village really wanted a water project very
                    much. Water projects were not a great problem, but the fact that the villages
                    were on top of mountains was a problem. There was about 3,000 feet of lift
                    involved bringing the water up from the river. It would cost a fortune and we
                    kept telling them no, no, no for a year. On the way up there, it took three or
                    four hours to get there, it was all off road stuff, up mountains, through
                    rivers, etc. We kept telling Bennett not to mention water because they would ask
                    for a water project and he should stay away from that subject. We got into the
                    “Mufraj,” sat down - I don't know what happened, but the first words out of
                    Bennett's mouth were “I hear you are looking for a water project.” That was it.
                    We had a good stay there, they were very happy, but then we spent the next year
                    wiggling out the water project.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't do a water project?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, we did but we didn't do it all. We did part of it, I think the
                    pumps and somebody else did the pipes and the rest of it. But, that was funny. I
                    wish I could remember the name of the other gentleman who was there because that
                    was just about the time that I was thinking about my next assignment. Things
                    were happening in the Straits of Hormuz and I wanted to go to Oman. I was
                    talking to Mr. Bennett and said, “If you are ever going to do anything in Oman,
                    I would be interested.” He said, “We have no intentions of doing anything in
                    Oman.” About three months later we were there!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were some of the projects that you did that worked in
                        Yemen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Programs in animal husbandry and agriculture, particularly horticulture
                    with orchards and vegetable crop production. That was what they could grow in
                    these wadies. You didn't need a lot of land but you needed water and good soil.
                    We did water and tried to do some training in health and roads maintenance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this involve a lot of local participation and
                        organizing youphilosophy of development and that approach?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, it was all that. It was getting the people to commit to a project
                    and to invest. They had a lot of money. Money wasn't the problem. Half the
                    population was working in Saudi Arabia and sending back money. They would take
                    their money to a dealer and say they needed pump. No specifications. So, when
                    they took the pump back they discovered it wouldn't work. They lacked the
                    technology. Through various projects we were able to help them decided what they
                    wanted to dowhat they wanted to do with the water, what kind of pumps they
                    needed and what kind of access was required, etc. They paid for half of the
                    project.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the role of Cornell and Chemonics?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Cornell provided us with Joan Swanson and Mary Abers who were two Arabic
                    speaking anthropologists. They worked basically in the project area full time.
                    Mary and Joan worked with the Confederation of Yemeni Development Associations,
                    which was basically the government, although it wasn't the government, it was an
                    NGO, but it was the only form of organization they had. They were able to get
                    into the community structure and understand who the good guys were and who the
                    bad guys were and what was going on with this project, etc. so it was pretty
                    clear what was happening. What was needed basically was to go in and do a social
                    survey and find out what the needs were. We had other people who could look at
                    agriculture or use Yemeni technicians for that. We would go there pretty much
                    once a month and stay with them for a few days and go around and look at
                    projects, talk to the people and keep the enthusiasm up and do the endless
                    troubleshooting that you have. There was always a problem. The money is not
                    getting there in time. There is a problem in Sanaa, the capital city. There is a
                    problem with the district chief. There is a problem with this one and that one.
                    Somebody is always not doing something. Our job was going in and out of the
                    situation and reminding people what the commitments were, what had to be done,
                    etc. and try to get some leverage from the head people.</p>
                <p>Chemonics provided us with technical people who worked in thdistricts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many people all together on the project?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Oh, we had two teams. One in the highlands and one in the Tihama. I would
                    say there were about seven Americans and probably twice that number Yemeni.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you train Yemeni technical people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: We weren't doing training per se. We were training peoplin the villages
                    to drill wells.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean people to work with you in agriculture and
                        wateprojects. Were they already available?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, there wasn't any government so you were working with a group of
                    farmers. If you introduced a new seed variety or a new insecticide or fertilizer
                    or you helped them to decide what they needed, or go with them to the market and
                    buy the right stuff and not the wrong stuff, that was on-the-job training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said there were Yemeni on the projects, itself.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>PAVICH: We had Yemeni who had been trained. The first Yemeni college graduate was
                    about 47 years old and in the government. There weren't many people who were
                    qualified to do any thing. It was really the “Wild West” and you were working
                    with some pretty basic systems and basic skills. No lack of intelligence, just
                    lack of education.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you training people to carry out this work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The people who worked for AID got good training in project development.
                    This was back in 1977, I know a lot more has been done in training the
                    government people since then, because the young man that worked for me, a Rough
                    Neck on one of the water crews, whom I grabbed and put to work as an assistant,
                    eventually went to the United States and got his degree in public administration
                    at Fresno State University. He is now a deputy minister back in Yemen. I met him
                    playing volley ball one day and he spoke English and struck me as being a good
                    kind of person. He worked for me a couple of years. I later discovered his
                    father had been the minister of education. He had a good background but was just
                    doing the manual labor for the money.</p>
                <p>The snack bar for our office was called a camp because it literally was a camp
                    outside of town that had a huge packing box. They had cut a window in and put a
                    stove and refrigerator in it. There was one man in there who was cooking stew,
                    making sandwiches, coffee and tea for the whole mission. He always had one hand
                    in pocket and was doing his job with the other hand. We wondered for the longest
                    time what was going on and finally learned he only had one hand. He had been
                    caught stealing and his hand had been cut off, according to their law.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of accommodations did the mission have?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Very meager buildings with electricity and kerosene stovebut no
                    phones.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you live?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: In town. The housing was pretty good. But, we had to do our washing in
                    the old washing machines with the old fashion rollers. We had two kids in
                    diapers and used the rollers quite often. We couldn't get Pampers or anything
                    like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was food available generally?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Food was very short. We could get chickens and eggs and some vegetables.
                    It was kind of tough. In those days we had a consumable allowance to bring in
                    consumer items and Peterson Justesen (a European mail/shipping order firm) came
                    to the rescue often.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any consideration of how to maintain your
                        projects ovetime or were they dependent on our being there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: There was a Peace Corps project there that had been developed to work
                    with the water authority to do water projects in the villages. The Peace Corps
                    people had been there for over a year, but and they had done nothing because the
                    Yemeni didn't want them because they didn't think they were qualified for the
                    job. They Yemeni couldn't accept the concept of volunteerism. “Why would
                    somebody come to Yemen and work for nothing? Anybody who comes to work for
                    nothing doesn't have any talent. So, we don't want them.” It was a very sad
                    situation because the young people were talented and they were just languishing
                    because they had nothing to do.</p>
                <p>We worked out a deal with the Peace Corps and the government of Yemen and some
                    U.S. universities that we would recruit engineering students in their last year
                    before they graduated and bring them to Yemen through the Peace Corps. They
                    would work in these villages as engineers. The Yemeni recognized them as being
                    qualified and the universities recognized that the students were applying their
                    skills and were given credit for their time in Yemen. They learned to speak
                    Arabic. It was one of the most successful Peace Corps programs I have ever
                    seen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a Peace Corps project with the university's and
                        AIsupport.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Right. It was an outstanding project. That project went ofor years, at
                    least four years after I left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mostly in water?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Mostly in water. Water is essential. Without water yocouldn't do
                    anything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mostly drilling for water?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Drilling for water, water distribution, water related health. You can do
                    a lot of things with water. You can even get into family planning and
                    sanitation. It goes on and on.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they had a fairly broad approach to it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. The first thing was to get the water. Once you did that then you had
                    a real basis for working with the community because you had a frame of
                    reference, the water which you helped them get. In that society you help them
                    and they appreciate it and there develops a very strong bond.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many volunteers were involved in such projects?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The first group, unfortunately, was 9, 10, 11 people who were pretty much
                    out of it. The second group was about the same number, and I think it got larger
                    as it went on. I talked to people who were there after that and it became a very
                    good project. We had a contractor involved, so it was actually with AID, Peace
                    Corps, a U.S. university and a contractor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which university was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was a university consortium.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was our role? Were we financing supplies and
                        equipment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: We were bank rolling it. We hired a contractor to come in and provide the
                    back up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, the volunteers had a technical and supply support
                        system. They weren't just out on their own.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Having been a Peace Corps volunteer and working with them in Ethiopia and
                    other countries, I learned that the more successful volunteers are the ones who
                    have good back up. I have seen volunteers out in the middle of nowhere who just
                    had to survive. I was one of those for a while. That is no fun. But, once they
                    had a little back up through an agency like AID or even the World Food Program
                    or UNDP, they could do much more. I don't know if that is a lesson they have
                    learned but I hope it is.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It sounds like the right approach, but I know the Peace
                        Corpused to resist such connections.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>PAVICH: They had some strange ideas. I know what it is to be a volunteer and I
                    can say that that is silly. If you can get support then you can do something.
                    Just sticking somebody out there who has to just live from hand to mouth and
                    beg, that is stupid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any other projects in Yemen that you were involved
                        in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: We had local resources for development and the wateproject. Those were
                    the two main projects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you think the lasting effects of those programs
                        might be?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I know AID is worried about the sustainability. In a place like Yemen at
                    that time it is difficult to think about sustainability in terms of fixing up a
                    government that is going to work and having the government establish an
                    equitable tax base that is going to generate money to pay for maintenance. That
                    just wasn't feasible when I was there. I don't know where they are now in that
                    regard. But, politically, what we were doing for those people was important and
                    they liked us and respected us for helping them. We got into political problems
                    later on, but I doubt seriously that any of the people that the Peace Corps and
                    AID worked with in the Tihama and in those isolated villages in the mountains
                    disliked the American aid. I think they appreciated it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any recognition from the government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No, I think the government was too busy sort of selling the country every
                    day. The country sort of went up for bid to anyone who wanted to buy it. The
                    government was a joke. The Sheikhs would come into Sanaa led by Toyota pickup
                    trucks with 50 caliber machine guns mounted on them. Then, we followed in their
                    Toyota land cruisers and then trucks full of armed guards. That was law and
                    order. Those were the people who ran the country, the sheiks.</p>
                <p>Once my assistant, Khalid, and a driver, blew a tire in the middle of the Tihama
                    and went into this village where Khalid happened to know somebody, he knew the
                    Sheikh. He told the Sheikh what happened and was told they, the party, had to
                    stay the night. The next morning when they got up the Sheikh had put four new
                    tires on the land cruiser, so they continued their trip up to where they were
                    going. When they came back and reported to the mission director. The director
                    invited the Sheikh in and gave him a set of dishes, the USAID hospitality kit.
                    So, in exchange for the tires we gave him a set of dishes and that was fine.
                    That was the way you did business in Yemen in those days. I would be very
                    surprised if it has changed a hell of a lot.</p>
                <p>So, sustainability, how do you measure that? I don't know.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>There are villages in Yemen where people speak only American English and most of
                    the people carry American passports because they were born in Detroit or
                    migrated to Detroit and came back to Yemen. So, you will go in there and a young
                    man will come up to you and start speaking American English to you and you just
                    do a double take because he is standing there in his skirt with his dagger and
                    turban on and just doesn't look like someone who would speak English with a
                    Detroit accent. So, Yemen is a very interesting place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Yemeni keep your projects going on their own at
                        all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Technology is what they need. If you can impart technology to a technical
                    person in the government or a person in a village, to somebody, that is what
                    they need and it will sustain itself. Money they have, but they need
                    technology.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is there any other dimension of your experience in Yemen
                        that yowould like to note?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, the people were very friendly. My wife worked for a Yemeni company
                    and we made some very good friends. They were very good to us. We have fond
                    memories of the Yemeni and our AID comrades there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you work with the embassy there at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, we did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was their role in this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: They were always interested in what we were doing because we were always
                    out there where the people were. They wanted to know what was going on and what
                    the people were thinking. We had the entree to some of the important Sheiks.
                    Skip Gnehm, the DCM [deputy chief of mission] in Kuwait, was there then and I
                    can't remember who was the ambassador at that time, but they were both fluent
                    Arab speakers and got along famously. The Yemeni really liked us but couldn't
                    understand why we did things sometimes. They would say, “You are the biggest,
                    strongest country in the world so why do you take all this crap?” What could we
                    say?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You finished up in Yemen when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>New assignment with USAID/Somalia and refugee programs - 1981</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>PAVICH: I finished up in Yemen in 1980 or 1981. I took an assignment in Somalia.
                    I remember my colleague, Diane Ponasik said, “Why do you want to go there? It is
                    such a problem.” I thought to myself that that was where I want to be, where
                    there are problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did she think Somalia was a problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Because there were starving refugees there. This is after the war between
                    Ethiopia and Somalia when all the Somalis were chased out of Ethiopia and
                    clustered in district capitals all over the country and starving to death. I
                    like that kind of action because there is something going on there that you can
                    do something about and feel like you have done something at the end of the tour.
                    That has always attracted me. If you look back on my history so far, I went to
                    Vietnam, etc. and there has always been that element in it for me. So, we went
                    to Somalia.</p>
                <p>The USAID Director at the time was Jim Kelly. My title there was Rural
                    Development and Refugee Assistance, something like that. There were somewhere
                    between a million and two million refugees out there in 15 or 17 camps. My job
                    was to go and visit the camps and talk to the officials to find out how many
                    refugees were there and make sure the food was being delivered and distribution
                    was being managed properly and that our contractors and grantees were doing the
                    job. We had a contract with CARE to do distribution of food and we were doing
                    some development things.</p>
                <p>We were in the process of developing two projects for development with these
                    refugee people. One of the projects was basically in forestry and the other one
                    was in rural development. I worked on the design of both of those projects. We
                    had people coming in from our regional office in Nairobi and other places to
                    help us do the studies for the design work. Here was a situation where I wasn't
                    doing it singlehandedly, but with a lot of good help. Basically the first year
                    was designing the projects. We got them approved and began the programs. The
                    work was managing the projects and the camps.</p>
                <p>Then I was invited to leave AID and go to work for the State Department in the
                    embassy as the Refugee Coordinator Officer (RefCord). I was first secretary for
                    refugee affairs, or something. That struck me as being very interesting because
                    I had been around embassies a lot but never worked inside. This was an excellent
                    opportunity to do so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why would the State Department need someone when they had
                        the AImission and you there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Because State (Department) had a $60 to $80 million program for refugee
                    relief. All the money that was going into refugees was coming through the State
                    Department.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't run by AID?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was refugee money, I suppose.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. They needed somebody with AID experience to work on it. So, I was
                    the refugee coordinator. I left AID and went into the embassy. I still had some
                    contacts with AID but was under the direction of and being rated by the DCM.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the function of the refugee coordinator?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, we had a major program with the UNHCR [United Nations High
                    Commissioner for Refugees], with the World Food Program and other UN agencies,
                    and a whole string of private volunteer organizations. So, it mainly was
                    coordinating.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The U.S. was to be the coordinator of all this and not the
                        UN?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, the U.S. wanted to coordinate its part.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there some overall coordinator?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The overall coordinator was the head of the UNHCR, but the United States
                    didn't always agree with UNHCR on a lot of issues. I was the liaison with the
                    UNHCR person and other UN agencies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were some of the issues?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: How many refugees there are? How much food they are getting? Where is the
                    money going? Are the health programs being managed effectively? Are other kinds
                    of programs, including education, effective? Are the refugees being taken care
                    of properly? The big one was how many refugees are there?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather that was a political issue with the
                        government?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, very political.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Each refugee was issued a ration card that entitled the refugee to a
                    certain amount of grain, sugar, blankets, etc. So, anybody in Somalia who had a
                    ration card was rich. If you had two ration cards you were doing pretty well. If
                    you had 10, 15, 20 or 100 ration cards, as some people did or had control of,
                    you had a lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Through their family or clan or individually?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Every way you can imagine. Through family, clan, individuals, the
                    administration. People who were loyal party members in the government, working
                    in a refugee organization, got ration cards or had control of ration cards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who gave out the ration cards?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The government. Well, the UNHCR gave them out to the refugees. So, then
                    you had the question of who was a refugee. In a line of 20,000 people, how many
                    of them were refugees? Twenty, 18, 5? That was the question. No one could really
                    tell.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you settle this question?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was never really settled. I had a young woman working for me, Michelle
                    Savoy, and she and I would go the camps and walk through every compound and look
                    in every hut and determine in our own minds based on our experience whether that
                    hut was inhabited or not. You could tell if it was inhabited because there would
                    be three stones where the people were making their fire, cooking utensils
                    around, clothes hanging on sticks, dogs hanging around, etc. There would be
                    others that were not inhabited. There may be the three stones, but no ashes. The
                    more often you go through the more you learn about whether it is inhabited or
                    not. You would just divide up the camp into sections and determine what percent
                    of each section was inhabited.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many people do you count per hut?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Probably between six and eight. Mom and dad, three kids angrandma and
                    grandpa.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The people weren't there to count?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No. I did this for five years. At the end of a year, or so, we had a
                    pretty good idea who was there and who wasn't there. We would be told those not
                    around were out with the goats. Well, they weren't suppose to have goats. If
                    they had goats they wouldn't be in the camp. There was a continual argument with
                    the camp officials about how many refugees there were.</p>
                <p>And then we would go to town, to the market and look around and find a rebagging
                    facility where individuals were rebagging all of this food that was given out as
                    rations. They would put it back into the same bags they had emptied, sew them
                    up, put them in a truck and take them into Mogadishu to sell at the market. We
                    would spot it, go back and tell the district officials who were astonished that
                    this was happening. Of course, they knew it was happening, but would go and
                    close it down immediately. Three weeks later we would come back and find another
                    one and we would go through the same exercise.</p>
                <p>Remember that movie Casablanca where they had the illegal gambling in the back
                    room, where the police officer would go in and close it down and then pick up
                    his winnings? Well, it was sort of like that. It was a constant thing.</p>
                <p>One day we were counting refugees. The counters would dip the finger of the
                    refugee in a pot of ink when we counted them. Later on, they would take some of
                    the chlorine that they used to purify the water and wipe the ink off their
                    finger and come back through the line. Of course, they could never get all the
                    ink off and we would catch them and report them to the camp officials who would
                    pretend to beat them and send them off. Then you would find them coming back
                    again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many people were in these camps?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Thousands. Twenty or forty thousand in each camp.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you counted them all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, we did. There were allegedly two million refugees and we were saying
                    there were not more than a million and probably it was more like 700 thousand.
                    We would go back and forth on how much food to bring in so we would have
                    control. But, they had control too because you would find starving people and
                    they would say it was our fault, we hadn't brought in enough food. It was a
                    constant tug of war.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the definition of a refugee?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Someone who had come across the border from Ethiopia and was a resident
                    of Ethiopia, who had left the place where they lived. They were pastoralists and
                    didn't live in one place. All their animals were dead and they were completely
                    destitute.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How could you tell the difference between them and the
                        regulaSomali?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: You couldn't. Some of these people were starving to death,were dying.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I suppose they weren't necessarily refugees. The Somalis
                        mushave been effected by the drought.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: These people were war refugees, they were chased across the border. Some
                    of the clan was on both sides of the border. You would have say 50 percent of a
                    family in Somalia and 50 percent in Ethiopia and both would be in camp. So, how
                    to you figure out who is and isn't a refugee? That was the question.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were some of your other major problems besides the
                        numbers.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Relief people were getting beat up. The major programs werhealth,
                    rehabilitating people, giving them food.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you rehabilitate them? I suppose the main
                        objective wato get them back across the border?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Feed them so they could regain their strength. Getting them to the point
                    where they could get some more animals and go back out on the range.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would they go back out?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, they wouldn't go back to Ethiopia because they would get shot at.
                    They were at war. That was the problem and I'm sure it still is. There is really
                    no law and order because people did what they wanted to do and if you pushed too
                    hard you were likely to get beat up or something. You weren't in a town but out
                    in the bush where there was nothing except refugee camps. The only law out there
                    was the army if they were around and the camp officials. It was kind of
                    tough.</p>
                <p>In terms of development, we tried to get some to grow some cropalong the river,
                    but that was pretty meager.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about health and education programs? PAVICH: All of
                        that was done through voluntary agencies.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of programs were you carrying out in the health
                        area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Mother and child health, nutrition, special feeding programfor
                    malnourished kids and primary education for kids.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were receptive to having those programs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Oh yes, sure. Being in a refugee camp was considered probably the best
                    place to be because you had the best medical assistance in the country. You had
                    doctors and nurses there who were fully equipped with medicine. If you were
                    going to get sick, you wanted to do so out in the bush, not in town, because all
                    the doctors were out in the bush.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's go back to the projects. What were the two
                        projects?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was trying to get those refugees who could, who had some experience in
                    agriculture and who wanted to settle on the land. Trouble was, most of these
                    pastoral people didn't want to have anything to do with being settled. They
                    wanted to be taken care of until they could go back to the range landBut, there
                    were those who were willing to go into agriculture so we could provide them with
                    work with the Somali agriculture extension person in that region to get them
                    started with seed, etc. Or, get them into doing some reforestation activities.
                    Or give them some chickens and into poultry production. Or give them some goats
                    and try getting them back on the range to the limited extent that they could. To
                    keep them busy mainly, and to the extent possible, productive.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was all for the refugees not the regular
                        Somalis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: There weren't any regular Somalis out there. The mission had agricultural
                    programs but they were big ag programs on the big rivers, Juba and Shebeli. It
                    was sort of a stock aid agricultural program and we, on the refugee side, didn't
                    get much involved in that because we were away from those areas. It was just
                    refugees and trying to figure out how many there were and getting the government
                    to take care of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned reforestation by refugees.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: To some extent we were trying to get them to plant trees. It was kind of
                    meager because there wasn't much they could do. They couldn't go far from where
                    they were and had to do whatever they could do around the camp area. The camps
                    were just bad. They were needed mainly to make the logistics of caring for the
                    refugees easier to manage, but the camps were a bad situation because they
                    created a dependency. Without the camps people couldn't do anything, or didn't
                    feel disposed to do anything so long so they were being cared for by the
                    government and the donor countries.</p>
                <p>We had a rehabilitation program where we got road crews filling up pot holes. The
                    roads were just tracks. It was pretty basic stuff. I did that for five
                    years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any special events during that time, any revolution or,
                        was ipretty much the same from beginning to end?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: There was a crisis every week. Somebody was starving, a ship wasn't
                    getting unloaded, food got stolen, the refugees were rebellious, an outbreak of
                    cholera, etc. There was never a dull moment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any sense of progress in terms of beginning to
                        minimizthe population by people moving away?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: They couldn't move away. The only possibility was to gethem being
                    productive where they were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this before the drought problem or was this at the
                        same time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Same time.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>Q: One had the sense that for a while there was a very serious problem but after
                    a while when food was getting to them you didn't have such a serious
                    problem?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, there was always the problem of how many refugees there are.
                    Everybody wanted to be a refugee, to get into a camp and get a ration card. So,
                    there was this constant tension of keeping the numbers at a controllable
                    level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But, there wasn't any real change over the five years in
                        terms onumbers or conditions of people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The health of the people improved. We saved lots of lives, something that
                    doesn't seem to get recognized. People focus on the corruption and all, but a
                    lot of people were dying. So, lots of lives were saved and brought back to
                    health. This doesn't happen overnight. Between these times there were outbreaks
                    of different diseases.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But there weren't permanent solutions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, peace would be one such solution as well as finding something
                    productive for these people to do off the range lands because the range lands
                    were getting smaller and the population was getting bigger. It is a dilemma.
                    They have the exact same problems today (1988) in the Horn of Africa as were
                    there ten years ago, nothing has changed. And, it won't change. It is going to
                    be a maintenance problem for the rest of the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are the refugee camps pretty much still there as they were
                        wheyou were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I don't know. I haven't been back. After all the differenwars they have
                    had there it is hard to know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you having clan fights while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No, the president, Siyad Barre, pretty much had the population under
                    control. But a lot of these camps were used as bases for military operations.
                    There was a very strong group of armed people who were under the control of the
                    government who sort of kept things under control in the camps. The refugees did
                    pretty much what they were told to do by the government, including getting
                    ration cards when they weren't refugees.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were talking about the UN agencies, etc. How did
                        yoformally function as a coordinating effort?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: So much of what I had done in Somalia was outside the normal AID context.
                    I felt my main contribution was in facilitating with and between the United
                    States and the government of Somalia and UN agencies (about 25 agencies that
                    were working in the area). The way that I did that was to be at and contribute
                    at the meetings. As I learned from Ambassador Oakley (ambassador at the time) to
                    “say it as I saw it” and not pull any punches. I let them know I knew what was
                    going on. I tried to get the good things done and do things about was not being
                    done properly. As I said earlier, every week there was a new crisis. It wasn't a
                    tranquil situation, it was a five year crisis, at least for me, as well as
                    everybody else there including both sides of the government and among the UN and
                    private agencies. So, communications between all of these diverse groups and
                    having the interests of each group represented fairly at a meeting was
                    important. Quite often the U.S. would be heavy handed on some food issue whereas
                    the government was not always wrong or corrupt, so the good had to be brought
                    forward. It was the same between other agencies as well. Communications was a
                    constant job, finding out what was really going on and what were really the
                    issues. Developing a rapport with these people was important. They relied on you
                    as being fair, not being just the American mouth piece. Somebody who would
                    represent the situation as you saw it. That was important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you meet formally regularly?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Monthly meetings with all of the voluntary agencies, thgovernment and the
                    donors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The government came to these meetings?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. This is the forum where we discuss what was going owithin the
                    voluntary community, and in camps.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who chaired that general meeting?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>PAVICH: There was a former State Department person who was working for the UNHCR.
                    He was an old Asian hand and in Vietnam at the same time I was. He was a good
                    chair. Everybody liked him because he ran a one hour meeting and would never
                    allowed it to go beyond an hour. He kept it moving along.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many people would be involved in these meetings?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Easily 100-150 people. It was a big program. There were 40 different
                    voluntary agencies in addition to all the UN agencies and the donors and the
                    government. There were lots of people there. They all had a stake in the program
                    for one reason or another.</p>
                <p>There was also a food aid meeting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who chaired that meeting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The World Food Program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was a smaller group I guess?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was a smaller group but a very important group becausthat is where the
                    level of food was negotiated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They negotiated numbers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The government was involved in that too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Everybody was there. And then there were meetings between the American
                    embassy and UNHCR, the American embassy and the Relief Commission, etc. Most of
                    the time the ambassador was representing the U.S. and that was about as high
                    level as you could get. We had a good ambassador there who was a very strong and
                    determined man.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ambassador Oakley.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. Then we had Ambassador Bridges, too. He had the same strengths but a
                    different personality. So, there was a lot of very hard negotiating meetings
                    that went on on all sorts of issues. Stealing of food, stealing of trucks, how
                    many refugees there were, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have big transport problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Oh, yes. CARE was running the whole operation. They had hundreds of big
                    trucks. Sometimes they would lose a truck which would be full of food and driven
                    out into the bush and just disappear. You would have to chase that down.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I understand they had an Indian group that did that work.
                        Ithat right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The Indians did a remarkable job. Nobody could have done what they did.
                    They stood out in the blistering sun every day in those refugee camps and
                    managed the food distribution for years, and no one can do that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were the CARE people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Right. It was the most difficult job that I have ever seen because there
                    was nothing good about it. There was lots of hostility towards them because they
                    were the monitors. The weather was hot, hot, hot and there wasn't any shade. It
                    was just dusty and dirty. They did a wonderful job. We were lucky we had
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did any of the other agencies stand out in your mind?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: They all stood out. From my perspective they all did a heroic job. They
                    lived in the camps in tents or lean-tos. The same kind of housing the refugees
                    had. They cooked out every night under the stars. There was nothing comfortable
                    about it except when somebody like me would drive in with a container full of
                    cold beer. That was the main luxury.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any idea how large the PVO community was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Private Voluntary Organizations</p>
                <p>PAVICH: There must have been at least 40 PVOs and about 20 peoplwith each PVO. So
                    there would be 800 or more.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From all countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. There were Czechs, Japanese, Europeans, Islamigroups, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were all part of this group you were
                        coordinating?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. I would go to Geneva, to Rome and Vienna on trips to coordinate
                    things. It was a wonderful out-of-AID experience for me, more of the diplomatic
                    end of development.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the average dollar value of food we were bringing
                        in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Oh, you are talking about hundreds of thousands of tons of food and
                    millions and millions of dollars. The annual food budget was about $40 million
                    or something like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved in programming and calling forward that
                        kind ofood?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, that was part of my function.</p>
                <p>When I worked for AID the Food for Peace Officer worked for me and wmade the
                    allocation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He worked quite closely with the AID mission?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, he was part of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else you would like to talk about? Any
                        personahappenings securitywise, etc?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, being part of the embassy at that time, I was involved in selecting
                    the refugees who were immigrating to the United States, which was a new twist. I
                    was working with the consul on that aspect by coordinating the interviews. Many
                    of the refugees went from the camps to the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What criteria did you use as to who should go and who
                        shouldn't?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: If they were political refugees who could not go back to the country they
                    came from and they met all the other criteria that INS sets up, they would
                    go.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How do you determine who is a political refugee in that
                        kind oenvironment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Through extensive interviews and background checks. Some of them were
                    pretty obvious because they were political figures before and they were known at
                    the embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there other areas of your activity that we haven't
                        touched on? Five years is a long time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. My kids were with me. There was a very, very high level of comradery
                    between the internationals. Much more so than any other place I have ever been.
                    Our circle of friends was Ethiopians, Somalis, French, Italians, etc. a real
                    good mixture. Everybody was working very hard and every night was sort of open
                    house to come over and chat and have dinner or do something together. There were
                    lots of kids. So, in a situation that was very grim, there was a side of it that
                    was very good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any place where people could congregate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The beach on the weekend was the big thing. There weren't any clubs or
                    bars. There was one international club but it really wasn't very much. There
                    were a couple of restaurants, but most of the time people would come to your
                    house and you would entertain at home.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were living conditions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: They were better than Yemen. We had a regular washing machine. However,
                    we still had to bring in a lot of the food. The school was pretty decent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about communications?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Communication was okay. There were no telephones but we haradios.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was food always available?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>PAVICH: We could go to Nairobi and buy food. We had food that we brought in and
                    there was a lot of seafood. My wife would go to the market and they would be
                    slaughtering a cow or something and she could buy just what she wanted right
                    there. My wife is Vietnamese and coming from her environment, that wasn't
                    unusual, so it worked out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After five years in Somalia where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: What I didn't realize when I took the assignment with the State
                    Department for all the good I did, and I did get formally recognized for what I
                    did, along with a lot of other people who worked in that emergency, it did my
                    AID career no good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Because I was basically out of the “mainstream,” the scalled career
                    path.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were not seconded but actually transferred to the
                        State rolls?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. So, the conventional wisdom was once you take an assignment like
                    that, that is pretty much it for your career because you are out of the
                    mainstream. But, as I look back on my career, I was always out of the
                    mainstream. When I came back from Vietnam the agency really did try to get rid
                    of the people they had in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why do you think was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Maybe the Agency felt guilty. I don't know. But, a lot of good people who
                    served in Vietnam, sacrificed their lives to support the U.S. government policy
                    and programs, were not welcome in the Agency. I think that was bad. A few did
                    survive. I did because I had the Public Administration background and AID had
                    that kind of a program. Others were just pushed out. That is the side of the
                    bureaucracy I am not proud of.</p>
                <p>Trying to come back into AID I had missed the bidding process so I had to call my
                    State Department boss in Washington to get me back to Washington so I could find
                    myself a job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What position was that person in?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>PAVICH: He was deputy head of the refugee office in the State Department. I had
                    to leave Somalia where there were no phones and go to Nairobi where I used the
                    phone of an AID colleague. I was on the phone most of the day calling and
                    explaining I had no onward assignment and I didn't want to return to Washington
                    without a job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your assignment to Somalia had come to an end?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. I asked if I could be brought back to Washington on consultation. To
                    make a long story short I was told, “Yes.” So, I went back and went into the
                    system and found a job. My next job was in Ghana.</p>
                <p>Transfer to USAID/Ghana - 1986</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was in what year now?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It would have been 1986. At that point in Ghana our program had sort of
                    hit bottom, politically and otherwise. The U.S. government and the Ghanian
                    government had a falling out over incidents in the embassy where some of the CIA
                    people were compromised and some of the Ghanians who were working for the
                    “Agency” were compromised. Politically our situation was bad which meant our
                    program was being cut back. It was the worse time for the Ghanian economy. There
                    was nothing on the Ghanian market. It was very bad and that is when we got
                    there.</p>
                <p>There were only six of us in the mission. I was head of the Rural Development
                    Office but also had food for peace, education and whatever we were doing with
                    agriculture. We were doing some private enterprise activities. We were trying to
                    privatize the Ghana seed company and one of my main jobs was to work with the
                    people in the government who were running the company. That was a long
                    process.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did it work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Eventually it worked. I was there for two years and ididn't work until
                    the year after I left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the problem of getting it to work?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>PAVICH: It was a problem because it was staffed by 3,000 people and they probably
                    needed 150. That was one problem. They weren't producing or marketing any seed.
                    They were pretty much defunct. The only seeds they were selling were seeds they
                    had received through the AID program. They had a brand new seed processing plant
                    that was capable of producing seed but they didn't have the wherewithal to make
                    it produce. So, we had to go through a long process of finding all this out and
                    developing a strategy for the government to divest its interest in the seed
                    company and convince the government that nobody is going to want to buy 40
                    percent of it because as long as the government has part of it is not going to
                    be any good. If they really want it to survive as a company they pretty much
                    have to give it away at what the equipment is worth, which was about a million
                    and a half dollars. We worked on that for quite a while.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you have some interested outside investors?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: We were trying to put together a package that would be attractive to
                    outside investors. Eventually we did, but it wasn't during my time.</p>
                <p>We were trying to design a new project that would sort of continue the divestment
                    of state-owned assets and do retraining for the redundant employees and get them
                    back on the job market.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you go about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: We did a lot of feasibility studies. We brought in experts who could look
                    at the economy and try to figure what the value of these organizations were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember which organizations you particularly
                        worked with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: There was a list of about 20 different companies. The ones I got involved
                    with were for branches of Pepsi Cola and Star Kist Tuna. We had to look at them
                    and see what they were doing. Those two were doing well, mainly because they
                    were franchises. These companies were franchised. If they didn't do what they
                    were supposed to do, then the franchise would be cut and they would be out of
                    business. So, they were able to do well. But, most of the other companies that
                    were operated by the government were not doing well at all for the same reasons
                    the seed company wasn't doing well. They were overstaffed, mismanaged and not
                    generating a profit. So, it was a long process of bringing people in and talking
                    to the government and negotiating what needed to be done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the government positive about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, our relations with the government were at a low ebb.</p>
                <p>Q: So, it wasn't very welcomed.</p>
                <p>PAVICH: No, they weren't very anxious to talk with us. We really didn't have very
                    much to offer because the program was getting smaller, not bigger.</p>
                <p>We had residual programs in education and agriculture that we were running. And
                    we managed to work up a program with the Peace Corps and the government and
                    local voluntary agencies to do reforestation and conservation work and
                    developing kitchen gardens and things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It worked pretty well. One of these programs turned oupretty well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were local voluntary agencies or international
                        ones?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Both. The Peace Corps organized a meeting in Kenya of Peace Corps and
                    voluntary agencies. They invited six or eight African countries from East and
                    West Africa, and Ghana was one. So, we went and brought some of the volunteer
                    agriculture and Ghanian government people there. We went through a team
                    organizing exercise and once we got that developed we went into the problem
                    solving process and developed a framework of a plan to do something about
                    reforestation, conservation, kitchen gardens and something to do with watching
                    out for forest fires.</p>
                <p>We had virtually no program money but began to work with the group we had taken
                    with us. Then the World Bank eventually contributed $100,000 and got things
                    started.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not AID?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No. The only thing that AID could provide was food through the Catholic
                    Relief Agency.So, the program developed and we brought in somebody who had been
                    at this conference to facilitate the next stage of our team development which
                    was to broaden the base, bringing in more local people. We developed a program
                    to do this and we did bring in more donors. We managed to get a million
                    dollars.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From AID?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>PAVICH: No. Then I left, but the program continued. I got feedback years after
                    that that it continued, had finally got some money from AID and was doing
                    well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You must think positively about that process for getting
                        thinggoing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. This is a facilitation process that I am discovering has always been
                    a part of what I have done. I realized a few years back that when I went to
                    school at the University of Pittsburgh, I did my masters thesis on urban
                    community development, which meant city, county, state, federal, local
                    organization and people involved in development process. What I developed in my
                    mind then while studying and writing about it was a development theory which I
                    came to practice all through my career. I was so happy when Brian Atwood came
                    forward with his 12 principles of participation, which were exactly what I was
                    trying to do. For me it was very interesting and gratifying.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who ran this group or did they just run themselves?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: They ran themselves with a self-selected committee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who chaired it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It revolved. There was a core with some of the volunteer agriculturalists
                    and AID. The World Bank was in there occasionally and some of the UN agencies
                    came in and out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The government was not involved?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, they were always part of the core.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they didn't lead it or dominate it at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No, no.</p>
                <p>Another thing we did there was to set on paper the beginnings of an environmental
                    protection agency. Everybody in AID has acquired some back ground in
                    environment. I have some background in government and organization with my
                    public administration experience. We put together the framework of an
                    environmental protection agency with the government because they asked for
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did it come to be?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I don't know. This was my last year. It took about six months to write up
                    the table of organization and describe the function of each part of the
                    organization and then decide what help they needed from the outside to develop
                    the parts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't clear where the million dollars came from. Guess
                        missed that point.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The million dollars came from a combination of the World Bank, UN
                    agencies, AID and the World Food Program. I can't remember where else. But, we
                    went from virtually nothing to a million.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a common program or strategy? How did the
                        program get characterized?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The framework, the strategy began in Kenya.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you have to work with in Ghana?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The same thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What defined the program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: What defined the program initially were the activities that were defined
                    in Kenya. Subsequently, in Ghana, they gained substance and funding through
                    various donor agencies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The agencies did their own thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, the Peace Corps was involved in the villages and the volunteers
                    were involved on the ground in the villages with the Peace Corps and the
                    government. There were two volunteer agencies...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the same village?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they worked together in the villages?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. It was the same approach that was taken from Kenya to Ghana and then
                    into the villages. It was the same groups.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the principal activities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I don't remember exactly what the conservation things were but there were
                    kitchen gardens and I am sure there was some reforestation, seedling programs
                    and caring for them. Firemen from the United States came in to them with the
                    fire program. Range fires are a major problem there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you all worked on the same projects pretty much in the
                        samlocations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: We all worked on the organization and then as it left Accra, the capital
                    of Ghana, it became teams of people doing things. At this point I am gone, but I
                    am sure they weren't doing exactly the same thing at each place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But there were teams for each place?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. The organizing principle was Peace Corps, AID, NGinvolvement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Create a team for a particular area.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would there be any particular team leader in that
                        process?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It just depended on the teams. The funny thing is I was just in Tanzania
                    and I ran into one of the people who was in on that project. He is working with
                    Catholic Relief and was a team leader.</p>
                <p>Q: Any other dimension of your work in Ghana? How did you find working with the
                    Ghanian people?</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>PAVICH: It was a great country to work in because the people were very friendly
                    and happy. In their poverty they were so happy. I don't see how they could do
                    it. They had little more than their shirt on their back. We had lots of friends.
                    My wife being Vietnamese could relate with the local people more easily I think.
                    She is a very outgoing and gregarious person. So, we always had lots of
                    friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you relate to the government given the
                        circumstances?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Again, there were a few people you could really talk to and a lot of
                    people who were just there with no pencils or paper. There was no air
                    conditioning so it was really hard to stay awake in the very hot, humid climate.
                    The only air conditioning in the government offices was in the ministers'
                    offices or their deputies. Everybody else sat there and roasted. It was
                    difficult. Our relations when I got there were bad, although by the time I left
                    things were beginning to improve a little bit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the program expand while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. Subsequently the program did expand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But that was after you left?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. I was AID rep for a while after the mission director left and AID
                    didn't bring a mission director back, until another AID rep came in. Eventually,
                    I think a year or so after I left, the mission was upgraded and the AID rep was
                    made director.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You are saying the program amounted to very little?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was about $12-$15 million, but most of that was food aid,Title II.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was the food going?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: To the poor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it monetized or commodity aid?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Most of it was monetized. Food for work programs, feeding programs,
                    education. We did bring in some other food which came in through the World Food
                    Program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what do you think about PL 480 Title II as an
                        AIinstrument?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I have seen it be very successful. Of course, you can see where it has
                    been abused. I went out with the Peace Corps and monitored Title II and saw them
                    just throw it away. It has to be monitored very closely. There has to be a
                    distinct start and finish, and concrete outcome after it has been used. You just
                    can't throw it out there because it makes more problems than it solves. But, it
                    can be used effectively if it is done properly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you think are some of the more effective uses in
                        thGhana situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Giving the food to organizations like the Catholic Relief, where they
                    monetized it and used the money to train people and take care of poor people
                    working with the churches. The priests knew who the needy people were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it mainly school feeding or something else?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: There was an element of school feeding, but most of it was social welfare
                    activities and training. Training women to sew and get into small businesses,
                    etc. There were just lots of things you could do that way. You have small
                    amounts of money but you have to have people do it who you can rely on. There is
                    no way that you can hire people to do that, they have to be volunteers and this
                    is where the volunteer agencies can do a good job. And, the local people helped
                    as they became volunteers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else you want to touch on concerning your
                        Ghanexperience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: There is a lot more to be said but it doesn't fall into AIinterests.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The social life, what the mission was going through, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You can certainly comment on that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>PAVICH: The mission had a small staff, small budget, small program.The government
                    was not receptive which didn't help the morale.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You found the mission had very low morale?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Among the Americans, I think it was high, but in terms owhere things were
                    going it was kind of depressing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the Ghanian staff, what was their
                        situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: They were concerned. I'm sure losing their job was on theiminds, and some
                    of them did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they have difficulty getting food or did we help them
                        out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Everybody did. We did too. If we had to live on the market we would have
                    been in bad shape. But, we brought things with us and we could drive to Lome for
                    food.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you helping to feed the Ghanian staff too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: A little. There was always some way you could help. Not giving them money
                    but having them over for dinner, going to the beach with them, having a
                    barbeque, having an office party, etc. AID people get very close to the people
                    they work with. I think we have more opportunities than other agencies not only
                    with our mission staff but people who work in the ministries and in the
                    villages. I think that pretty much finishes Ghana.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your next assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Chief of the Rural Development Division, USAID/Pakistan - 1988</p>
                <p>PAVICH: My next assignment was Pakistan from 1988-93. In Pakistan I was the head
                    of the Rural Development Division. We managed a number of very large rural
                    development projects in three of the provinces in Pakistan: in Baluchistan and
                    the North West Frontier.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before we get into those projects, what was the situation
                        iPakistan at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>PAVICH: The situation was that President Zia of Pakistan was killed along with
                    our ambassador in a plane crash. They suspected that it wasn't an accident, that
                    there was something in the plane that went off and brought it down. A few years
                    earlier they had burned the American embassy and there was still some of that.
                    It wasn't overt, but people would talk about it now and again with some concern
                    about what could happen if the political situation got out of hand in
                    Pakistan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the economic situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The economic situation was pretty good, I think. It wasn't as good as it
                    could have been but it wasn't bad. There were a lot of people who were
                    undereducated and poor by most standards and who weren't getting much help, but
                    there were a lot of productive areas in the economy and there was a lot of money
                    in the country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the rural area that you were working on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The rural area was going through a slow change of modernization, mainly
                    in agriculture. There were different crops, application of fertilizer, and basic
                    modernization. There were programs to support the environment, conservation.
                    There were major problems with soil erosion and major programs to deal with it.
                    Pakistan at that time was, I think, the third largest AID recipient in the
                    world, after Israel and Egypt. So, there was plenty of money there and lots of
                    things going on. It was not as big as the program in Egypt, but it was big.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the director then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I was there for five years and Jim Norris was the director for three of
                    the five years. John Blackton was the follow on director. It was a big mission
                    and had big projects. The rural development division had a major share of the
                    money. We had close to $300 million in projects. A lot of it was in area
                    development projects which were primarily designed to do opium poppy abatement
                    in the North West Frontier and to a lesser extent in tribal agencies. We also
                    had projects in Baluchistan. We had offices in Karachi, in Baluchistan, in
                    Peshawar and throughout the North West Frontier and the tribal agencies. Big
                    program. We had lots of staff, something in the area of 25-27 professional
                    Pakistani engineers and other kinds of professionals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the American staff?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>PAVICH: There were only three of us. Because of the geographical dispersion of
                    the projects, the head of the division resided in Islamabad, the capital city,
                    and my colleague, John Tucker, resided in Peshawar, which was the jumping off
                    base for activities in the tribal agencies and the North West Frontier. We did
                    have a FSN in Baluchistan and Karachi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have American contractors?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: We had a number of contractors working for us doing these projects. At
                    the time I got there we began a changeover. We tried to turn the projects back
                    to the Pakistanis and reduce the number of contractors. Development Alternatives
                    Incorporated had a big project there in the North West Frontier and the tribal
                    agencies and DMJM had a big project in Baluchistan. They did roads, agriculture
                    and other kinds of infrastructure like utilities and training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For crop substitution or reduce the poppy
                        cultivation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Not in Baluchistan. It was just a straight rural development program
                    there. In the North West Frontier we were working in what had been very high
                    opium production areas. The object was to get the farmers to switch over from
                    opium to other cash crops. We were very successful at that. The main reason we
                    were successful was because the farmers didn't really make a lot of money
                    growing the poppies. The real money was made by the middle man and the people
                    who take the poppy gum and refine it into the basic product. And, the farmers
                    were not all that interested in producing something that obviously was harmful.
                    So, when there were opportunities to raise different kinds of wheat varieties
                    and vegetables, they were willing to go along with it. The other incentive, as
                    part of the package, was the development of roads, the establishment of schools,
                    etc. So, it was a good package and worth it for the farmers to go along with the
                    program. In earlier times the government just wasn't there so they had no
                    compunction about growing the poppy because that was the only way they had to
                    make a living.</p>
                <p>When I say we were successful, I have to qualify it. We were successful in
                    getting the poppy out of the North West Frontier, but it moved into Afghanistan
                    where there were no programs and no law and order.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a specific strategy that you were following for
                        ruradevelopment in Pakistan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Basically it was infrastructure because there was none. It was to get the
                    infrastructure and get the public services in. Get the schools operating and
                    follow that with the agricultural extension with the reforestation. That was
                    basically the strategy. We were working with women's group to develop them
                    economically.</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were their any particular approaches to the people in
                        thcommunities in carrying out this kind of program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. When I got there the mission was calling for a change in our
                    approach. The change was basically (1) to move from a model where the project
                    provided everything to a model where the government provided basic
                    infrastructure and sources and the people contribute their labor and skills and
                    (2) reduce the number of subsidies that had been developed on certain crops an
                    incentive. Our approach was to work with the government and the local people to
                    develop a strategy for basically reducing and zeroing out the subsidies, and to
                    get the local people to make a greater contribution for maintenance of
                    infrastructure. And get the government to fulfill its responsibilities in terms
                    of doing maintenance on roads, providing teachers for school, medical people for
                    clinics and continuing their programs for reforestation, etc. To some extent we
                    were doing training programs with local people to develop the skills in order to
                    reach their objectives.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We talk these days about local participation. Was there
                        anparticular approach to that involvement and commitment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, we developed a number of approaches. It is interesting today when I
                    go out on some of these jobs I see a lot of people using workshops and focus
                    groups, which we basically were doing in 1988. We would encourage people just to
                    talk about the issues they confronted. Or talk about what they understand about
                    the government program. All of these programs were government programs in spite
                    of the fact that AID was paying most of the costs. To get them to talk about
                    their concerns, identify issues and ask questions about the programs so that
                    basically they would be better educated. From that process to develop a priority
                    agenda of what needed to be done in that particular area. It wasn't the same in
                    every area because in some areas they were more interested in getting teachers
                    in the school or medical people in the clinics or getting some kind of
                    sanitation system in the village. It varied from place to place. We encouraged
                    these meetings.</p>
                <p>This required a lot of training of our USAID Pakistani staff as well as the
                    Pakistani government and local people because they had not been exposed to this
                    approach. The approach they were accustomed to was mainly from the top down. The
                    head man telling somebody what to do; everybody sitting there not doing anything
                    until someone told them. Well, we tried to develop a more dynamic process were
                    people could interact and come up with an action plan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they responsive to this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, they were. We had something that we called the “Three Year
                    Workshop.” We contracted out to an organization, Coverdale Organization, a
                    company which set up in the North West Frontier to do basically seminars in
                    training. Whatever kind of training or workshop we needed they would set up and
                    subsequently provide certain kinds of technical assistance are not found on the
                    local market. They also hired local experts to come in and work with a group to
                    solve a particular problem.</p>
                <p>We used that approach in everything we did. In agriculture, the conservation
                    work, and the road work to develop an understanding between the local people and
                    the government about what was involved in having a road and the requirement for
                    maintenance. Building the road is the easy part, keeping it maintained is the
                    hard part.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You spoke of a three year cycle.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was the Three Year Workshop, because we continued to have it in
                    Peshawar, in Karachi or somewhere in Baluchistan, or anywhere where you had to
                    do it. We would get the local people and put them through sort of a basic
                    program learning how to work together in ways that they probably weren't used
                    to. Learning to work without one person giving directions. Once we got through
                    that process, then we would move into another phase where we actually got into
                    rural case studies. What are your problems, etc. In Baluchistan they wanted to
                    be more responsive to the business community but they didn't have a good idea
                    how they should approach that. So, we put them through the training for the
                    first three days and the next three days they worked on developing their own
                    action plan. It worked very well.</p>
                <p>It was the same basic approach we had used in Mombasa and to Ghana, working
                    together with different groups, bringing them together to identify problems and
                    organize a plan of action. It was very effective, I thought.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you find that it became integrated into the government assistance, that
                    they picked up on it and used it themselves without the contractor?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: We did this several times with the government. They were very happy with
                    it. They would come and ask us if they could borrow our facilitators so they
                    could do it with their other staff. I would suspect that once the project lapsed
                    a number of those people who were our facilitators probably went right back to
                    do this kind of work. There were one or two firms in Pakistan that did this kind
                    of workshop facilitation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you really introduced technology through this process
                        intPakistan.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>PAVICH: I felt we did. At the time I was pretty proud of it. Of course, you never
                    realize these things until long after you do it. Another thing that we did using
                    the same process was to develop a workshop between Pakistani government
                    officials at the provincial level and the federal level as well as UN and other
                    donor people at the provincial and federal levels about the drug problem. There
                    is a real division in Pakistan between provincial and federal government because
                    provincial government in Pakistan has everything, it could be a self-contained
                    government. They have their own assembly and all the rest. There is a federation
                    with the central government but the working relationship with the federal
                    government isn't always that great. The central government controls the money,
                    so naturally it has the leverage.</p>
                <p>But on the drug issue, which was very complex because you were dealing with the
                    production of poppies, the processing of the raw materials, drug addicts, law
                    enforcement, etc. there were a number of agencies, Pakistani as well as
                    international, who needed to get together to develop a common frame of
                    reference. So, again we used our Coverdale group and had a number of workshops
                    at the province level to develop clear ideas of where they thought they were,
                    what they thoughts the problems were with regard to the drug issues, and what
                    their problems were with regards to working with international organizations and
                    the federal government. Then we brought them all together and each reported what
                    they thought about the situation, the issue, the opportunities for problem
                    solving. They all got the other's perspective. The process produced a
                    coordinated action plan. I believe we were able to develop a better
                    understanding of the needs and stimulated some measure of greater participation
                    than was there before we started. I am sure that some of the antagonisms between
                    the government agencies are still there, but I think we did get them to make
                    some headway.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the problem of sustainability. Were your
                        resultmaintained?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I would say yes. We were doing was very basic like roads, water,
                    agriculture, and conservation. I think what the people learned in the decade or
                    more that AID was there about roads, the costs and maintenance, and who has the
                    responsibility to maintain them. The same thing with the water. I think that
                    there was enough of an increase in economic growth there that they could go out
                    and buy or rent a rig to drill a well and get it producing water and all the
                    rest. A lot of the rest they had been doing for centuries. I think in terms of
                    sustainability, yes, the skills were sustainable but the levels of funding were
                    not because AID was putting $100s of million into Pakistan at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the Pakistan government people to work
                        with?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Wonderful. They were highly qualified, well trained, probably too
                    bureaucratic for our tastes, but they were very good at what they did. There
                    were problems, they would only do so much. There were lots of opportunities for
                    corruption, particularly from the drug money. That was always a problem. You
                    never quite knew what impact that was having on the decisions made. But,
                    technically, I thought they were very good. The engineers were good, the water
                    people were good, the agriculture people were good and well trained.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are you familiar with the Aga Khan project participated in
                        by AIand other international agencies up in the Northwest Frontier?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It had some special characteristics didn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: We worked quite closely with the Aga Khan Foundation. The Aga Khan asked
                    AID if we wouldn't create an NGO, a non-governmental organization. They didn't
                    want to do it themselves. They had good people who would be involved in it. We
                    worked with them on the charter, got the NGO properly organized and eventually
                    were able to give them a grant to do projects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember what it was called?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: SARHAD. I think it means sunrise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I understand there were some unique features to the
                        project thewere running in the Northwest Frontier area.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: They were up in an area that is contiguous with the Chinese border. It
                    was the old “Silk Route” that came down from China into Pakistan. They had an
                    approach that was very participatory where they would go in and do a dialogue
                    with the people. I was fortunate enough to go and spend several days with them
                    and sit down with them and go through the dialogue. It was of very inspirational
                    speaking with the head of the Aga Khan Foundation at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: About that project?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. He would say that you have to find the “Activists” and the only way
                    you can do that is through the dialogue. Eventually the Activists will make
                    themselves known in one way or another and you work with those people because
                    they are the movers and the shakers. He was right.</p>
                <p>The only reservation I had about the Aga Khan was the big money. They had a fleet
                    of vehicles and helicopters, and without Aga Khan they couldn't sustain anything
                    like that.</p>
                <p>Q: I understand there was a tough line of approach to the village in a sense that
                    the people really had to produce in order to get the support.</p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, that is right. They were rigorous about making peopldo what they had
                    decided to do. They were doing some major things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they successful?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well we tried to borrow the best aspects of the NGO but we couldn't
                    provide a fleet of vehicles or helicopters. We helped set up the organization
                    and they used the dialogue approach in the village. It worked very successfully.
                    I worked with it for three years from the beginning to when they could pretty
                    much take off on their own. I understand they are still in operation.</p>
                <p>My approach to that one was sort of benign neglect. I didn't want to get too
                    involved in it because I knew if I did they would depend on it. I tried to stay
                    out of as much as I could.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The NGO?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. I tried to stay out of it and spent a lot of time going up into the
                    areas where they were working.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they just working in the north?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: In the Northwest Frontier, yes.</p>
                <p>Q: Some people say that such a group depends on a particular personality. Did you
                    find that was significant because you can't replicate a personality?</p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>PAVICH: There was another older gentleman, in his '80s, named Aethar Hamid Khan,
                    who was the grand “Guru” of rural development, and began his work with the
                    Camilla project in East Pakistan. It is interesting because when I was at
                    Pittsburgh I was working with a local organization that was run by a Mr. Bernard
                    Lashbaum who had been with the Ford Foundation in India. He had worked with Mr.
                    Khan in the first rural development program. He brought the approach they were
                    using back to Pittsburgh. I got involved in this urban development thing and
                    found out Mr. Lashbaum had studied under Mr. Khan who I came to meet many, many
                    years later and who is the grand guru. I mean that in the strictest sense.
                    Anytime I, or any of my senior staff would go to Mr. Khan they would literally
                    drop to their knees and kiss his feet and sit on the floor and he would talk to
                    them. I was always there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: His main tool was the dialogue technique?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: He would dialogue. I was rather skeptical about it in the beginning, but
                    I felt that over a period of about three years that what he said made a lot of
                    sense. Of course he had written books too. It was not only what he said, but he
                    sort of provided spiritual guidance. This was the charismatic leader. But, he
                    was also producing people who I am sure eventually are going to be like him -
                    highly dedicated, fixed on principles and discipline. That was his approach.</p>
                <p>Q: This was in the NGO community rather than in the government?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. It doesn't belong in government it belongs in either the NGO
                    community or local organizations.</p>
                <p>I could talk for hours about this man. I guess I was a convert. I have to say
                    that Pakistan was an incredible experience, personally in so many ways. Just the
                    physical beauty of the country and the incredible responsibility that I had. We
                    are talking about $280 million in projects. There are many missions that don't
                    even come close to that. We had a huge staff all over the country. I had never
                    had comparable responsibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How can two people keep their hands on a big program like
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It required a lot of traveling. Fortunately in Pakistan you can fly a lot
                    of places and wherever we flew there was one of our staff that could pick us up
                    and drive us the rest of the way. We had good staff and gave them good training.
                    We had regular meetings and they were some of the best people I ever worked
                    with.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they on the AID payroll and then integrated into
                        thgovernment? What happened to them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The ones I just mentioned were AID staff. But, we had a close
                    relationship with a lot of the district government people because we worked very
                    closely with them. We also had a good relationship with some of the higher level
                    people in the government. In fact, I took the Chief Secretary of the Northwest
                    Frontier, the highest level of civil servant in the Northwest Frontier, he is
                    not political, on a trip to the United States where we visited the Appalachians
                    to see some of the NGOs that were working there. We went to New York and looked
                    at a drug rehabilitation program and NGOs that were doing neighborhood work. We
                    were together for two weeks.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you find a lot that was relevant to the work in Pakistan?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. In 1988 when I got there there weren't any NGOs except the Aga Khan
                    and the government wasn't interested in them. They did become interested in
                    them, however, because they saw what they were doing in Afghanistan, relief
                    work. While there weren't any in the Northwest Frontier when I got there, there
                    were lots of them that lived in the Northwest Frontier but operated across the
                    border in Afghanistan. So, we eventually got the Aga Khan clone NGO which was
                    the first one. After that we worked with several of the community groups who
                    were in these poppy abatement projects and brought them into NGOs. AID had
                    sponsored a number of women's training centers and we spent about two years
                    developing those people in those centers to take over the centers and run them
                    as an NGO. We worked also with several local villages to prevent a take over of
                    what they had been working on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they get their funding mostly from the
                        government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: AID set up a $40 million revolving fund for NGOs. So, there was a lot of
                    money there. It got hung up for a couple of years because the government was
                    managing it and they were afraid of spending it and they weren't very well
                    organized. It took a couple of years to sort that out and they finally were
                    moving the money.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you mean by revolving fund?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Money would go into a fund where it would accrue interest.They would use
                    the money for grants to some of these NGOs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: AID was able to set up an endowment type operation at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes.</p>
                <p>Q: With local currency or dollars?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: That is a good question. I think it was dollars, but now I'm not certain
                    about that. But it went through a long period when nothing happened because the
                    Fund's Board of Directors was not functioning and they didn't really understand
                    what they were supposed to do. But, once everything was sorted out it began to
                    work. There were other problems after that because they were running it all out
                    of Islamabad and I thought what they needed to do was to allocate chunks of it
                    for different regions and set up an office in that location as opposed to making
                    everybody come to a small office in Islamabad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any particular features of your sector work
                        that waunique or special?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I have mentioned the three year workshop.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right. But, in terms of the technology that was used
                        iWashington, education, etc?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, using the workshops in a participatory methodology waunique at the
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved in curriculum developed or materials
                        oanything of that sort?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No, we didn't do that. AID had a huge education program.We were working
                    at lower levels.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were doing the basic facilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, rural development program.</p>
                <p>Q: Were there any techniques involved in doing construction work? There was this
                    F.A.R. technique which was supposed to be reimbursed after people built it.</p>
                <p>PAVICH: We used the Fixed Amount and Reimbursement system and I think it worked
                    very well. Mainly it worked well because the government understood it and knew
                    how to work with it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They had the capacity to manage it and the resources to
                        ....?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>PAVICH: But AID had the largest staff of AID engineers of anywherin the world
                    just for that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For working with you on these projects?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: They were working for us on our projects but it seemed liked the head
                    engineer wanted to run them and there was always sort of a bureaucratic tug of
                    war concerning who they actually worked for. They were working under rural
                    development projects and should come under some management, but it didn't always
                    work out that way. That sort of stuff went on in Islamabad, but once you got to
                    the field it didn't matter. Once you got out somewhere you are all AID. But, we
                    did have to have a lot of engineers. We only had one or two U.S. engineers but
                    maybe 14-15 or more local engineers, Pakistanis who would go out and check these
                    jobs. They had to have that or otherwise the FAR wouldn't work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are there other dimensions of your life in Pakistan?
                        Anparticular events or things that happened during that period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, working with the United Nations on the drug issues was important. I
                    think the high point of this work was a week long narcotics workshop that we put
                    together. I felt that was a milestone, getting that organized and having it come
                    off successfully.</p>
                <p>The privatization of our rural development projects, breaking them up into small
                    NGOs as opposed to big AID projects, was another break through.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So there was a big shift to using NGOs. Was the business
                        sectoinvolved in that at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: To some extent we were working with the business community, the small
                    holders. We were trying to encourage some growers who could to produce
                    strawberries for export to Europe, flowers for export and that sort of
                    thing.</p>
                <p>Another thing we worked on was the elimination of the subsidies and turning
                    things over to the government which was a major accomplishment. I think we did a
                    successful job. The mission was phasing out at this point. It closed down two
                    years after I left. That was it. I would love to go back to see what is
                    there.</p>
                <p>Q: I get the impression that maybe it was through the AID resources that there
                    was this sudden growth of NGO community or was there some other factors
                    involved?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: I think it was a combination of things. I think we pioneered parts of it.
                    We gave the Aga Khan approach a new life in a new area. I think it proved
                    itself.</p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there other factors that facilitated its growth?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, there were so many things that went on. For example, one group of
                    people came down for one of our basic training courses. They came from a very
                    remote area in the Tribal Agencies to Peshawar. They were there for five days.
                    We gave them a per diem, a small amount of money. They saved their money, didn't
                    spend the per diem, and went back and used the money to build a bridge. It is a
                    small thing but significant because they learned how to organize themselves in a
                    way they probably wouldn't have known how to do (if it were not for the
                    training). Most rural people know how to get together to do things, but probably
                    it was that they were always waiting for somebody else to do it. But, we gave
                    them the inspiration to do it and not worry about the government until later on.
                    You decide what needs to be done, find your resources where you can and do
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else you would like to mention about your
                        Pakistaexperience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No, I think we have covered it all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, after five years in Pakistan where did you move on
                        frothere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: After five years in Pakistan it was Egypt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What years was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>A new role in USAID/Egypt - 1993</p>
                <p>PAVICH: Egypt was 1993-96. I retired from AID in June, 1996.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Egypt at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>PAVICH: At that time politically Egypt was beginning to play a slightly stronger
                    role in the Middle East peace process. There was a lot of local opposition to
                    the government, particularly from what people called the Islamic fundamentalist
                    groups, terrorists in some instances. I remember the first day I walked into the
                    office I heard an explosion. Someone had set off a bomb right around the corner
                    which killed a number of people in an attempt to assassinate the leaders from
                    the Ministry of Interior. The target might have been the minister of interior,
                    himself. That was my introduction to Egyptian politics. Mubarak was the
                    president. He was a strong man running a pretty tight ship, I guess, in order to
                    keep all actors under control.</p>
                <p>The atmosphere was pretty friendly. You would sense sometimes a certain amount of
                    hostility towards foreigners, depending on where you were in town. This would be
                    offset in other places with friendliness and camaraderie. Egyptians are great
                    cosmopolitan people, at least the ones you meet in Cairo. They were very easy to
                    work with and well qualified.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the mission like at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Huge. I guess it was the biggest AID mission. It was likworking in
                    Washington with lots of bureaucracy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the director when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Hank Bassford was the director when I got there. He was a very effective
                    director. He was a hard nosed kind of man. He was demanding of his staff and he
                    could be as demanding with counterparts in the government. In a program like
                    that where there is so much money involved, it is not a question of if they are
                    going to get it, but when. It is a tough game to play. I think Bassford was
                    probably one of the more effective mission directors they ever had out there in
                    doing that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: My title was Supervisory Special Projects Officer. I was in the office of
                    institutional development support, which was the democracy office. They called
                    it institutional development support because you could not say democracy in
                    Egypt at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was not a rural development program?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>PAVICH: This was different. Back in Pakistan I realized that the old rural
                    development was rapidly becoming a thing of the past and there were other things
                    developing that were also interesting and have parallels to everything I had
                    been doing up til then and democracy was one of them. It was new and AID was
                    trying to establish itself in this field. They had begun to do some things in
                    Pakistan which I tried to get involved in but the mission wasn't really pushing
                    it too hard. However, it became clear to me that this was an area that had
                    growth potential and required certain kinds of skills that I had many of. For
                    example, working with local government, working with local groups, understanding
                    the basics and principles of government from my Public Administration
                    background. The only areas I didn't have experience in at that point was the
                    political side, the development of political parties and things along that line.
                    But, I thought that there was an opportunity in Egypt to do that, to become a
                    democracy officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this a big program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. Moneywise it was probably the biggest democracy program in the
                    world. We had a number of activities that we were just starting. We had an
                    activity that was to work with the Ministry of Justice to develop the justice
                    system and improve the judicial process, to reduce the caseload burden and
                    upgrade the skills of judges and advocates and make it work and user friendly.
                    We had a lawyer, Ana Klenike, on our staff who was in charge of that.</p>
                <p>I was responsible for two activities. One was with the Parliament and the other
                    was Civil Society. We had a project that had been designed that needed to be
                    tightened up, more focused. That was when I got there and worked with a young
                    woman, Connie Peraskova, to develop a request for proposals, an RFP, for bids on
                    this project. In order to do that we had to go back into the project and define
                    more clearly what the mission wanted. That was one part of it.</p>
                <p>The other part was negotiating with the Parliament, the Speaker of the House and
                    the two Secretaries General. They have the Parliament and the Shura assembly
                    which was a religious group that worked with the Parliament. I was to work with
                    the Secretaries General and basically educate them about the USAID programs and
                    procedures. They had never, never had any kind of bilateral program. This was
                    high profile for the Egyptian politicians, they didn't want to have very many
                    meetings with USAID and we couldn't use the term democracy. It was a very
                    delicate process. In the beginning, and I think all through out, it is still
                    going on now, to tell them what AID does and assure them this wouldn't infringe
                    in any way on their sovereignty, and to help them in whatever way we could to
                    persuade the political powers that this was okay to do. There were lots of stops
                    and starts, advances and retreats. The Egyptian press was taking pot shots at
                    the project saying the Americans were coming in to run the Parliament, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get something done?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>PAVICH: We did eventually.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Eventually we got a project together to work with the staff of the
                    Parliament, to upgrade their skills, to work with the Library of Parliament to
                    develop the capacity of the library to provide the kinds of information decision
                    makers needed. To introduce information technologies by establishing a network
                    of computers so people in the Parliament could connect with the web and get
                    information that way. We brought people in from the outside to discuss
                    Parliamentary procedures, political processes and a number of things like that.
                    We had the U.S. Library of our Congress involved in a project. We had Syracuse
                    University involved in the program in bringing in people and training them. We
                    brought people to the United States and other places to see how Parliaments work
                    and our Congress. In fact, I just talked to someone who works on the project
                    just the other day and they had been doing well, but now they have another
                    political problem so things have sort of stopped for a while.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Political in the sense of sensitivity towards
                        Americaorganizations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Too much American influence. People don't understand that we are not into
                    politics but involved in the organizational development. But, how can you not be
                    involved in politics?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hard to separate them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, in that case. We made some good relationships. I think everybody in
                    the Parliament we worked with were converted. But, by now a lot of them have
                    moved on and there is a new bunch in there. They are the ones who are asking the
                    questions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were working with the elected people rather than the
                        staff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: We weren't working directly with the elected members, but they were
                    working with the staff. It could be they have a new Speaker of the House, that
                    could be the problem, but I'm not sure.</p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>The other activity that we were working with was developing civil society and
                    that was a little more difficult. AID had in Egypt its largest rural development
                    program in the world. It was the Local Development Project (LDII). It was a huge
                    billion dollar project that went on for ten years. I mentioned Jim Dalton to
                    you. He sat with President Sadat. President Sadat said that he wanted to see the
                    AID handshake in every village in Egypt and in that way they will be local
                    development projects. So, it was everywhere and did everything. Everywhere you
                    went you saw the USAID logo. It was very effective. It was criticized widely
                    because there was such a large amount of money that was being given out and AID
                    didn't have enough control over the money, so accountability came into question
                    at times. I guess there were other economists who could argue that you could use
                    that money in different ways and have a greater effect. But, let's face it, it
                    was a political thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the money used for specifically?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Infrastructure, education, health, everything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this go through the line ministries in the
                        government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. It was much the same as what we were doing in Vietnam with the
                    establishment of the budget at the local level. A sort of supplemental budget
                    that the local governments had access to for virtually anything. At the same
                    time it trained local governments in upgrading their skills and developing their
                    capacity to administer the program. Once it got rolling it was doing
                    everything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it countrywide?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All parts?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, all parts. It was very effective. When I got there Hank Bassford
                    went to the government and told them LDII was over. I remember he said the
                    government has to be more transparent in the operations, that is, include the
                    citizens in the planning, and privatize state owned enterprises, a number of
                    other conditions. That was the environment when I got there.</p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>The Egyptians were all expecting another LDII to come along. But the mission's
                    maximum amount of money USAID was going to provide for new activities was
                    probably be around $20 million as opposed to a couple hundred or more. So that
                    was the atmosphere. But, before that we had to define our terms, or what are we
                    talking about. Civil Society, what is that? Participation, what is that? So, I
                    kind of applied one of the methodologies that we developed in Pakistan, the
                    workshop approach. We got a group of missionary people and Egyptians together
                    and had a one day workshop to define “participation.” You got a whole range of
                    definitions from the Americans and from the Egyptians. There was a lot of
                    misunderstanding. Now, this was in 1992. This is pre- cursor to Brian Atwood's
                    “Twelve Principles of Participation.” These things were new, sort of cutting
                    edge stuff.</p>
                <p>I don't think we really came up with one clear definition of what is
                    participation. I think what we did do, at least within the mission at that
                    point, was to establish a common understanding that participation means a range
                    of things and here is the range. We wrote this up and talked about it a lot.
                    Participation was definitely going to be the main theme of our Civil Society
                    approach.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a core concept of participation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The concept was participation and development bringing local groups and
                    government together to work on development problems. That was the theme.</p>
                <p>Then I was fortunate enough to get a license to travel, to go out and see what
                    was going on in Egypt. I took about four months going out to the different
                    provinces and interviewing people in the government and the NGO sector to see
                    how things were running and if the government people had any idea of the change
                    that had just been made, that the big local development program was finished and
                    there wouldn't be another one but something new would be coming along. That was
                    a very difficult job because nobody believed it or wanted to believe it. We
                    would spend an hour talking about the change and where AID thought their
                    programs should be going and they would return to the question, “When do we get
                    our next LDII block grant?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean that program just came to an end and
                        stoppeconstruction?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It didn't leave things hanging but gradually phased out.</p>
                <p>Our problem then was convincing the government at the central level and the local
                    level that there was no more LDII and we needed to come up with something
                    different.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the government react to these new ideas? Did
                        theconsider them fairly revolutionary or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, the major problems there were two. One, they just didn't want to
                    accept the fact that there was no more LDII and two, they were not willing to
                    think of anything that smacked of decentralization. What I didn't mention was
                    that we wanted to develop an activity that would be based at the local level not
                    based at the central ministry level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it a fairly central government situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Very, even with the provincial level. Egypt is a big country but the
                    people are packed into a small area. Going back and forth between places is
                    quick, by plane or train. The central government pretty much runs it all. I
                    thought by putting people at the local level who could work government and with
                    local organizations to facilitate...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were local organizations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: There weren't a lot of engineers but there were organizations. You really
                    don't need an organization, you just need a group of people who want to do
                    something. I have to say that in the three years I was in Egypt the first year
                    was spent mainly on getting the project up and running in the Parliament. We had
                    to send out bids, select a contractor and mobilize them on the ground. While we
                    were doing that we were negotiating a little bit with the government about what
                    they can and can't do, defining an activity that everybody in the mission would
                    agree to as an alternative to the old program and visiting the local government.
                    That pretty much took up the first year.</p>
                <p>The second year was trying to get something on the Civil Society side negotiated
                    with the government, pulling together a critical mass of Egyptian and
                    international NGOs to start thinking about the process. What we wanted to do was
                    to pull them all into a process of defining the project. By this time
                    “re-engineering” had just started and the 12 Principles of Participation had
                    been promulgated by USAID/W. So, this fell in line with all that. We would take
                    all of the stakeholders, bring them together and design a project. If we could
                    get the government to agree to let something like this happen, we could do
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who in the government were you relating to about this sort
                        othing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Mostly Minister of the Interior and a Deputy Minister oInterior.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they really interested in this kind of change?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: This is what happened as I see it. In this year and a half that we spent
                    telling the government that there was not going to be another LDII (Local
                    Development 2), they would have to think in different terms. During that period
                    they came up with a scheme of their own, called Shrouk. Shrouk was the Egyptian
                    version of LDII. Just about the time I thought I had negotiated the other (new)
                    concept with the people I was dealing with in the Ministry of Interior, a new
                    person came on the scene who was in charge of the Shourk project. That was the
                    end of Frank Pavich.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because you weren't supporting it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It wasn't that I wasn't supporting it, I was supporting mission policy
                    and they didn't want it. This person had the backing of the Minister and Mubarak
                    and that was it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they get an LDII project?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No. As far as I know, even today, I have talked to peoplrecently and it
                    is still up in the air.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, that project never got off the ground?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No. I think we were able to salvage some things working with the NGOs but
                    I don't think we ever got the government to come around.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were working against a very tough odds, I guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. The Agency let me down a little bit in this one because they jumped
                    off one band wagon and jumped on another band wagon and sort of left me in the
                    dust. This was a disappointment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did they shift to?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, it wasn't so much the whole mission, it was more or less
                    individuals that saw an opportunity in something the government really wanted
                    that we could go with it and forget the other thing. That upset me because I
                    thought the other thing was based on every principle that AID was trying to
                    develop at that point. I can appreciate that if the government doesn't want it
                    you have to go with what they do want. The Egyptian man with whom I was
                    negotiating with sensed immediately what the situation was and just said that
                    there was no need for Mr. Pavich to come to the next meeting. And that was it. I
                    was pretty much out of it. What disappointed me was that my people in the
                    mission didn't say, “You can't do that. He is the person in charge of this
                    project. If we decide to change our strategy, it is the mission's strategy, not
                    his strategy.” But it didn't work out that way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You would have identified with it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I would have identified with it. It was a good lesson. don't feel too bad
                    about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the mission was bought into it at that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, they bought into Shrouk. We tried not to have it that way. I
                    continued to work on it but I just couldn't go down and be up front with the
                    Ministry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But it was the same program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, it wasn't the program that the mission had approveand I was trying
                    to negotiate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the local development program was the same as the one
                        yowere...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It had a lot of the same elements in it. It required a loof money.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To local government and things of that sort?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. I think the problem was that it was a situation where it was
                    questionable how much control you would have over the money. Who was going to
                    get what? There would have been a lot of jobs involved and a lot of sticky
                    points that had to be ironed out. I don't know if they ever ironed them out.
                    They keep trying.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In fact the mission caved into the government that wanted
                        to stapretty much with the old concept.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I think the mission people did what they felt they needed tdo in order to
                    continue negotiating with the government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There wasn't much latitude for holding out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Right. This is Egypt and the program is going to be there no matter what.
                    It is not a matter of “if” you get the money it is a matter of “when.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you were caught up in this political situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. I was a little bit disappointed but continued to woron the stuff
                    with the NGOs, which I understand is continuing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Building up their capacity?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Trying to sit down and have them participate in the desigof a project to
                    build up their capacity.</p>
                <p>Q: Were there a lot of NGOs in Egypt?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: There were a lot of associations and a number of NGOs and a program like
                    this would probably develop a lot more. But, they had problems on the government
                    side because the government wanted to be very much in control of the NGO
                    movement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else on your Egyptian experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. The other thing about my experience in Egypt was that this was when
                    the re-engineering concept was introduced and it was tested around the AID world
                    and in Egypt. It was an opportunity to learn a lot about what they were calling
                    re-engineering. In a big mission like Egypt where you have 30 large
                    organizations within a big organization, re-engineering was a formidable
                    challenge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did re-engineering mean to you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                <p>PAVICH: The essence of re-engineering is giving authority to the level of
                    management that is responsible for doing the work and eliminating a lot of the
                    people in between. That is what it was supposed to do. But, I don't think it
                    accomplished that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were some of the characteristics?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: We had two processes. The traditionally AID project process where you did
                    your feasibility study, and project paper, etc. and then they were developing at
                    that time the Results Framework and all of the things that go along with that.
                    At one point we had two systems. Instead of making it easier and less
                    bureaucratic, made it twice as hard because you had to work it both ways.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the results system?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The main difference was you no longer had a project. You had an activity
                    which had a number of results that were supporting an over-arching objective.
                    For example, if you want to strengthen civil society, then one of your results
                    might be better organized NGOs working with community groups. There is a
                    tangible result there and you are given money to achieve that result. Once your
                    strategy is approved, you got the money and then you develop your program, your
                    “Result Package,” as they call it now, to achieve those results.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't have to do all of the analysis that you do for
                        projecpapers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes and no. You can't just do things. You need analysis. It sort of
                    duplicates the old process and calls it something different. But, the thing that
                    was promising about it was that it tended to eliminate a lot of other decision
                    makers in the process, so theoretically it would be more responsive and quicker.
                    I don't think the Agency has gotten there yet. I just came back from a mission
                    where they are working with it. Some things have improved, but it has a ways to
                    go. Not everybody understands it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything more you would like to mention about your
                        Egyptiaexperience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No, I think that covers it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You retired from Egypt in June 1996?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes.</p>
                <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                <p>After USAID, work on democracy programs - 1996</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Touch on some of the things you have done since before we
                        go foa wrap up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I retired in June 1996 and came back to the Job Search program. In March
                    1997 I took an assignment in Bulgaria to evaluate the Democracy Network Program.
                    I worked for a U.S. firm, Management Systems International (MSI). A two person
                    team, Larry Hileman and myself, went out to the mission and in three weeks we
                    did a rather superficial evaluation of the Democracy Network Program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The Democracy Network Program is a regional program to allow countries to
                    develop their own democracy network projects or activities with NGOs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is a democracy network?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The democracy network, I guess, is the network of countriethat are
                    working on this program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not within the country?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Inter-region and/or their country. Working with local organizations,
                    local governments, with any of the institutions that you normally associate with
                    a democracy program, such as political parties, the justice system, civil
                    society, the military. When I said it was sort of a superficial evaluation it is
                    because the time allotted was very short, only 15 working days, and we covered a
                    lot of territory without very much background material to work with. So, we had
                    to rely a lot on what we saw and what we heard in interviewing people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the kind of activities we were supporting?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                <p>PAVICH: We were supporting activities to get local groups organized and get them
                    focused on democracy issues. I thought the idea was good. I think the Democracy
                    Network Program is excellent. The problem I had with the way it was being
                    applied in Bulgaria was it was very centralized. It was operating the way the
                    government operated. I felt that the mission wouldn't achieve its Strategic
                    Objective unless they got it out and started working at the lower levels. Of
                    course, I have a bias there, but that was pretty much what I saw. We traveled to
                    all of the major population centers and interviewed well over 200 people, mainly
                    NGO people because there wasn't really any government to speak of at that
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of assistance did we supply? What were we doing
                        witour funds?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: We were just getting started.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were we planning?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The usual, training, management systems, information technology, probably
                    setting up grants to try to get people to work together. It was pretty much in
                    the formative stages. It was a dream place to work because the Bulgarians are
                    highly intelligent, highly educated, highly motivated and dying to be
                    democratic, wanting to do everything under the sun. They had energy to burn.
                    Just to work with them was a pleasure because they are so eager. It was just a
                    matter of explaining to them new ideas. They had been behind the “Iron Curtain”
                    for 40 years and had missed out on many things and needed to learn quickly. I am
                    sure that they are and they will. Being part of that process is one of my
                    ambitions. To get back to situations like that because that is where the action
                    is in democracy. So, I had a good experience in Bulgaria. A lot of the
                    approaches that I worked with and developed in my experience in rural
                    development in the past, the things that were developed in the Three Year
                    Workshops (in Pakistan), all fit very well into this new context, into the
                    re-engineering phase and to what the agency is trying to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any other interesting assignment after you retired?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                <p>PAVICH: After I left Bulgaria in April 1997 I took an assigned in November 1997
                    to develop a democracy strategy in Guyana in South America. That was another
                    interesting experience because as the Guyanese would say “We are a lot like you
                    Americans because none of us are natives, we either came from Africa or India.
                    There is a small group of natives pushed off in the background. We were all
                    under the British colonial system and we broke out and are trying to find our
                    way and form our own democracy.” We worked with the mission there in an
                    assessment of the democracy situation there and helped them with their Results
                    Framework. It was a three week assignment. Guyana is a big country but there
                    aren't many places to go because there is nothing in most of the country other
                    than rain forests. So, we worked mainly in Georgetown, talking to people in the
                    government and NGOs and working on strategy with the mission.</p>
                <p>After Guyana, in December 1997 I went to Tanzania from December 1until March
                    18.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was this assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Again, it was a democracy assessment to develop their Results Framework
                    and their Performance Monitoring and Evaluation system and give them a list of
                    examples of things that they could do in their democracy program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the democracy situation in Tanzania?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: They broke the colonial rule and went into a period of “Scientific
                    Socialism” which sort of went bankrupt after the Soviet Union went under. Now
                    they are converting to a free market economy and democracy. It is not going to
                    be easy. I guess it is easier to do the economic things, at least to get the
                    policies set up and going. There is a lot of suffering there because things are
                    in short supply and many people are out of work. There is likely to be more
                    people out of work, but the investment climate is improving and some medium size
                    businesses are beginning to develop. So, I think they are going to do well
                    there. On the democracy side, in order to get the IMF [International Monetary
                    Fund] to come in and give them the credits, etc. they had to recognize that they
                    couldn't run the country politically the way they were. So, instead of a one
                    party system they...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it an IMF condition to liberalize the political
                        situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0077" n="Page0077"/>
                <p>PAVICH: No, I don't think it was that, but it was part of the logic of where they
                    had to go. It is going to be difficult because they don't have much experience
                    in a multi-party system and the party that is in control doesn't want to lose
                    control, and that is the party that was the party when there was only one party.
                    There is virtually no opposition at this point. A political system needs to be
                    developed, the party system has to be developed, civil society needs to be
                    developed, the justice system needs over hauling, and the civil service also
                    needs to be over hauled, retrained, taught how to operate a decentralized
                    system. The government has to decentralize their activities and be more
                    participatory in the way they govern. That was pretty much what we said in our
                    assessment and what is reflected in their strategic plan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is the mainline of what the activities are going to
                        be?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It is developing civil society, NGOs and to help the government in its
                    reform process in specific areas where it can work closely with civil society
                    organizations and doing things in communities on a democratic basis. Try to
                    stimulate more participatory government at the district and village levels.
                    Then, as I said before, we developed their Performance Monitoring plan which is
                    how you measure your success in achieving these things.</p>
                <p>That was my last assignment. I think, in my career, I made the metamorphose from
                    what they used to call “cowboys” in Vietnam to “Rural Development Jocks” to
                    something more professional in places like Pakistan and then to “Democracy” in
                    Egypt and more Democracy in other areas.</p>
                <p>Concluding observations</p>
                <p>Q: Let's talk a little more generally. What do you see as the key guidelines, key
                    principles that you find people should be following and have in mind when
                    working for AID?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: For me, Brian Atwood's “12 Principles of Participation,” summed up
                    everything that I have learned and thought about from 1962 when I joined the
                    Peace Corps to 1989 when these “Principles” came out. I think that is where
                    things are. People have to be involved in development in order for it to be
                    sustainable. You can't just develop institutions and pour money into economies
                    without getting people involved in the process so that they will support it. In
                    order to support it, I feel, they must have a stake in it. The way they get a
                    stake in it is being involved in the processes. That is a very basic principle
                    of development, as I see it. I remember back in the early '80s when I took the
                    Development Studies Course and they asked us what was our theory of development,
                    I was saying participation, although not exactly in those words. That is what I
                    was thinking at that time and I still think that is where it is. Yes, you have
                    to have the economic development and you have to have discipline and the
                    technology and the policy framework and the government structure to go with
                    that, but you also have to have people involved in and supporting the
                    process.</p>
                <pb facs="0078" n="Page0078"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any particular technique for involving people? That is not
                        particularly easy thing to do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: When I wrote my thesis at the University of Pittsburgh on “Urban
                    Community Development” I identified three things that had to happenorganization,
                    education and development. You had to identify some form of organization or some
                    common theme that people are in agreement about or disagreement about, something
                    that is going to bring them together in an organized way. Once you had that
                    communication then you can begin the process of educating and development. To
                    me, that is the way you do it. If you look at a lot of the methodologies that
                    they are using now, this Rapid Participatory Development approach, it is that
                    you have to find something that people agree upon or want to organize around and
                    begin communicating. When you are able to communicate with them you begin a
                    process of educating. This is what we did in the Three Year workshop. It was
                    bringing people together who had a common problem or who had a common concern or
                    common question and organizing them in a systematic way through various
                    methodologies to begin to talk about it and recognize what they were talking
                    about, giving them a common frame of reference. Once this happens you get them
                    to start prioritizing, to think about what is important. What can you do about
                    it? Who can do this and who can do that? What are you resources? That sort of
                    dialogue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I get the impression that this has recently been
                        discovered. Iit really that new?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened to make people act like this was a new
                        thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I think it is re-engineering.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was wrong before with the old approach to rural
                        development?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: The old approach didn't really fade away, it was interest iit that faded
                    away.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the approach was not that different, it was
                        stilparticipatory and all?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0079" n="Page0079"/>
                <p>PAVICH: Basically I think the approach was similar, but if you worked with
                    village people you had to communicate with them. What are you going to
                    communicate about? Something called development and usually that begins with a
                    problem. So, I think it is quite the same. It is just that it has been
                    reinvented. It is not just something that you can do at the lower level, you can
                    do it at various levels, wherever there is a group of people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why then did rural development get such a bad name?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I don't know, it is hard to say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were so involved in it over the years when it was a
                        big thinand then it faded away.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It evolved, I guess, from the “Point IV” program after World War II
                    (Marshall Plan) when you really had technical people (Project Officers) on the
                    staff and working on these activities. Eventually the number of technicians
                    became smaller and smaller and you had more people who were Program Officers.
                    Then they invented something that was in between a Program Officer and a Project
                    Officer, which also created a new layer of bureaucracy. In a cynical way, I
                    think a lot of it had to do with people's desire to make a career, to get to the
                    top fast as opposed to working at the project level. This afforded an
                    opportunity to do project work for a couple of years somewhere and then become a
                    Project Development Officer and then eventually a Program Officer where you
                    never had to deal with the local stuff. They would be doing the very important
                    programming work, developing the conceptual framework for a program, working on
                    policy issues and all the rest of it. That became very important stepping stones
                    to advancement and promotion. I think a need was created for more of that and
                    less for technical people who could always be hired. In rural development you
                    had thousands of small projects and who wants to fool around with keeping books
                    on so many activities, you can never keep it straight.</p>
                <p>Q: How do you make the participation process which takes a lot of patience and
                    time, etc. consistent with the bureaucratic drive and pressure to commit money
                    and all that? Did you find yourself always caught in a bind on this sort of
                    thing?</p>
                <p>PAVICH: Always caught in a bind. That is why I was so happy when re-engineering
                    came along because - push the responsibility down to the operations level - I
                    thought it was going to save the day, but it hasn't yet. It talks the talk but
                    hasn't walked the walk yet. I think there is a lot of vested interest in keeping
                    the existing procedure the way it is because that is how people got where they
                    are. Also, to push the responsibilities down is a problem. People no longer have
                    the experience. I was just in several missions in the last year and the level of
                    experience isn't what it used to be.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0080" n="Page0080"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In terms of...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Well, everything I say has a bias because I come from one aspect of AID
                    work. I have always thought that the best thing for an AID officer would be to
                    spend his first five or seven years as a project officer doing projects out in
                    the field. Once he or she got that experience then they would qualify to become
                    a Program Officer. I think if the Agency had followed a rule like that they
                    probably would have been better off. They would have had more people with that
                    kind of experience, which they don't have anymore.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They have lost this sort of technical and local
                        developmenorientation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes. When you develop a strategy, somebody has to have a vision of what
                    it is going to look like and/or be like on the ground. With a lot of people who
                    have a very well developed theoretical grasp of the subject matter, democracy
                    for example, they have been trained in political science and know the subject
                    matter. But, taking it down two or three notches, how does it work in the
                    context of a community with personalities, real people and real government with
                    all the things that are involved there, human, political and otherwise, and how
                    do you make something work and how do you see that? How do you take $12 million
                    and visualize that amount in six different places in a big country? The only way
                    you can visualize such things is by having been out there once or twice and seen
                    what's there. My experience has been that there aren't a lot of people who have
                    that experience any more because the bureaucracy thinks there is no need for
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the tendency to rely on NGOs for this? What is your
                        feelinabout NGOs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Yes, there is that tendency. But, here again, in dealing with NGOs you
                    are dealing with young people. Where did they get their experience? The people
                    who created the NGOs probably got their experience the way we did years ago. But
                    the people currently in the NGOs are learning it on the job. They are very
                    dedicated people. I have worked for a lot of NGOs and there is a real high
                    factor of inexperience at ground level. Willingness, commitment and everything
                    good is there, but the practical experience just hasn't developed yet. So, you
                    need a lot of what I did in several countries, to be out there with the local
                    people assuring them they were doing the right thing. Staying with them and
                    telling them to do this and do that, think about this, think about that. I was
                    basing that on the early experience that I had, which by comparison was a
                    lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Looking back over the years, do you think the foreign
                        assistancprogram has had a useful impact?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0081" n="Page0081"/>
                <p>PAVICH: I think we helped shape the law of the world with our foreign assistance.
                    There are many people out there who have benefitted from AID people being near
                    by, coming into their villages, talking with them, working with their
                    government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any particular areas or aspects that you think
                        significant?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I have to say the rural development activities were good because that is
                    when you are dealing with people. I have been in situations where people have
                    looked up at me with lots of respect because they have achieved something. It
                    wasn't that they were getting something, it was that they had achieved
                    something. That is one of life's rewards. If you can get a reward like that from
                    your job you have benefitted enormously.</p>
                <p>From my perspective the AID countries where we have worked these countries have
                    benefitted a lot from the assistance to their people, in developing the skills
                    of their people and their government and in the private and voluntary sectors,
                    development of their agriculture, health, education and everything else we have
                    done. Who else has done that? No one else has done it at the scale we have done
                    it in the past and everybody has always looked to us as a leader. They may not
                    always give us credit for it or say that we were the leader in these things, but
                    you look at what they do and see what it is modeled after. More times than not
                    it is modeled after the work AID has done. Look at re-engineering. We started
                    re-engineering five or six years ago and everybody in the development world is
                    doing it now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there others things in your earlier years that you
                        saw iAID as pioneering?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I think we helped the NGO movement worldwide. Certainly in disaster
                    relief we have been a pioneer. We have added immensely to the structure of the
                    disaster assistance in different countries in organizing groups to do things
                    like that. We did so many good things. By in large, I do not think it was money
                    wasted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How do you feel about your career and working for AID as
                        aagency?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: I think I was very lucky. If it hadn't been for the Peace Corps and
                    Vietnam a person like me probably would not have ended up in. I feel I was lucky
                    because AID was a reward and it shaped my life and I feel good about it as a
                    career. The one thing I am concerned about is that all the good AID has done
                    isn't overlooked, which is why I am grateful that you have this oral
                    history.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0082" n="Page0082"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would you say to somebody who was looking for a
                        career thesdays? Would you recommend going into this business?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It is a different world today. If I were telling my daughter what she
                    should do I would say, “Look, if you have a mind to, and you want to help out
                    and do something for humanity, join the Peace Corps. Get an education, develop a
                    marketable skills, and join the Peace Corps. Go out and learn about people in
                    the developing world. Work with AID for some years, but don't depend on it
                    because it probably won't be around that long.”</p>
                <p>Again, I think we were all lucky because we were in for a lifetime, but I don't
                    know whether it is going to be that way in the future. There is going to be a
                    need for assistance, but you may have a smaller AID organization with an out
                    source contractor for the people you need. The British have a small organization
                    and they would go out and hire people to bring in and do their programs, but now
                    they are sort of going the other way and bringing them all into one
                    organization, but I think AID is going the other way. The AID organization is
                    going to shrink and use private contractors and private organizations more in
                    the future. The young people of today have to be flexible. They have to be able
                    to do a number of things. Working in development, humanitarian assistance might
                    be part of a longer term career that takes them in and out of government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else you would like to add?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: Not at this time, perhaps after I review the interview.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it has been an interesting interview and thank you
                        vermuch for taking the time to talk to me.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PAVICH: It was great.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
