<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001304">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Milton Zatinsky </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Labor Series</p>
                <p>MILTON ZATINSKY</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Morris Weisz </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: March 10, 1993</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is Morris Weisz and the date is Wednesday, March 10,
                        1993. I am interviewing my old friend Milton Zatinsky on his work in the
                        Marshall Plan. We are recording at his home in Miami, Florida, and I would
                        like to ask Milton first to give a general description of his political and
                        social background and his family, and then how he got into trade union
                        work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes. My family was a middle-class New York Jewish family. My father was
                    a small businessman. I was shocked one day to find out that my father's business
                    was on strike. I had already had leanings in the other [more leftist] direction.
                    By the time I was 13 or 14, I was active in the student movement. There the
                    Communists were very active. I decided that they were on the wrong side, and the
                    bad side, of the future of the world and went with the Socialists and the other
                    dissidents.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What school was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: This was DeWitt Clinton High School.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the western Bronx [in New York City].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: From there I became more active in the Yipsels [Young People's
                    Socialist League, the youth group of the Socialist Party]. I became New York
                    City Chairman and finally became National Chairman. I went to work after two
                    years of college. My first full time job. . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which college?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I was at the University of Wisconsin interestingly enough with Joe and
                    Millie Glazer and my first wife, Clair Brandler. Joe left a little bit before I
                    did.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Milt, how did you get out to [the University of]
                        Wisconsin?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: It had a good labor studies program under Selig Perlman, whom I got to
                    know pretty well. I got impatient. Joe, who is older, had graduated. He went to
                    work with Larry Rogan in the Education Department in the CIO Textile Workers
                    Union (TWU), now part of the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, and
                    he let me know that there was an opening as an organizer with the New York Joint
                    Board, TWU, which used a fancy title. I was an international representative or
                    something like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By the way, were those jobs elected or appointed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Representatives, organizers, educational people were all appointed in
                    most unions. There may have been one or two exceptions, but they were basically
                    appointed jobs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was an elected [official].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: By and large [they were appointed.] My wife at that time went to work
                    for the Retail Clerks International Union. She was appointed too. I was never a
                    textile worker, and I didn't feel that I had too much of a future as an
                    organizer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean you quit school after two years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: That's right. And at that point in time, a friend of mine, Morris
                    Milgram, who headed a group called, “The Workers Defense League,” asked me if I
                    would be interested in going to St. Louis. They wanted to set up an education
                    department under a very interesting guy named Harold Gibbons for the Retail and
                    Wholesale Union (RWDSU-CIO).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you put an approximate date on that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: That was in 1945 and 1946. I set the department up and stayed with
                    Harold for a year or two.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was before Harold Gibbons joined the Teamsters?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: This was when he was a Vice President of the Retail Workers Union, CIO.
                    This was basically a warehouse joint board in St. Louis. Years later he went
                    independent. He tried to [affiliate with] the UAW (United Automobile Workers
                    Union), but they felt it was too far afield in jurisdiction. He finally went
                    with Jimmy Hoffa into the Teamsters Union, where he became a very important
                    figure and Hoffa's sort of second in command. That's another story.</p>
                <p>Anyway, getting back [to the story], I came back to New York and did some union
                    public relations work with a friend of mine named Herman Singer. “Guild
                    Associates,” it was called. We represented several unions and the Histadrut
                    (Israeli Federation of Labor) and others. We did some work for the Jewish Labor
                    Committee. Then the job of setting up an education department at the American
                    Newspaper Guild came up. I was not a newspaper man. A fellow named Sam Eubanks
                    was head of the Guild at that time and had been head of the anti-Communist slate
                    that took over the Guild from the left wing. He was something of a Social
                    Democrat himself, and he was delighted [to have me]. I think Danny Bell
                    recommended me strongly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Danny Bell, Professor of . . . . ZATINSKY: Danny Bell,
                        Professor at Columbia University and author of the book, The End of
                        Ideology, and one of the leading sociologists in the world today.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>So there we were [at the Guild]. The program was a good program. We got out a lot
                    of material. We had training programs. It was a little difficult [to do]
                    education [programs for] the Guild. I would walk into a Guild group and they
                    would say, “Educate us? Who educated you?” Here were people, many of whom have
                    advanced degrees themselves. I had gone back at night and finished my Bachelor's
                    [degree] at the New School, but I didn't have any advanced degrees at that time.
                    So I had to explain that this was training and it wasn't education in the
                    broader sense. It was training in labor relations and collective bargaining.
                    (Pause)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, will you continue now?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes. The Guild had then its first national education program. We put
                    out our publication, Guild Activities. We had conferences throughout the
                    country, usually held in university settings: Wisconsin, Penn State. Those I
                    remember. We occasionally brought in experts. There was some resentment, I have
                    to tell you, about a non-newspaper man in this situation. Some felt that they
                    would be more comfortable with somebody who had a newspaper background. Of
                    course the Guild covered the newspaper editorial [staff], the back office, the
                    commercial [staff], and what have you. After a while [the education program was]
                    accepted and started showing some results and looked pretty good. But we had one
                    happenstance that was just timing. Executive Vice President Sam Eubanks, who
                    appointed me and was the one who pushed mostly for this program, resigned or
                    decided not to run again, — It was an elected office. — and the group that took
                    over, or was ready to take over, was not exactly too sympathetic with certain
                    aspects of the program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With the education program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes. So I started looking around.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now all during this period, you were also developing
                        political interests. Before you actually [discuss] your Marshall Plan
                        employment, [please describe] those interests.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes. As a very young man, I was in the American Student Union (ASU).
                    The first day at DeWitt Clinton High School, I said, “Where does the ASU meet?”
                    I was 13. I went to the ASU and there was a meeting, which, it seemed to me, was
                    run by a group that I didn't feel very comfortable with. They turned out to be
                    Communists. There were other groups in opposition to them including the Young
                    Socialists, the young Trotskyites, a few anarchists and what have you. I was
                    young and not that sophisticated, but I realized that I couldn't [join] people
                    who were talking about all the bad things that were happening in the United
                    States, and they were supporting and apologizing for one of the worst
                    dictatorships in the world. It seemed obvious to me then. I don't know why it
                    didn't occur to too many other people. So I wound up working with a group of
                    dissident left-socialists called “the Shermanites.” They were loosely affiliated
                    with the Shachtman group. The Shermanites were a group of people who had broken
                    with Trotskyism and were finding their way to democratic socialism. Although
                    they admired Trotsky as a great thinker and a courageous person, they realized
                    that it was the system of Communism or Bolshevism that led to some of the worst
                    things including the Stalinist dictatorship. So they were one of the early
                    groups that moved away on this issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Around a person named Sherman?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Philip Selznick is the name I most remember. He and a fellow named
                    Irving Ferry, who I think writes today under the name Irving Kristol, . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: William Kristol?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: No, Irving Kristol, his father. William Kristol I don't know at all.
                    There were others: Seymour. Martin Lipset, who was head of the American
                    Sociological Society the last time I looked, since I am a sociology professor
                    now. In my retirement, I can say that Lipset has done an important job and he is
                    an awfully good person. He has a great deal of integrity and brilliance. Anyway,
                    from this group, which was really a transition group because it broke up, most
                    of us went to the Socialists.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Milt, spend a minute on this tendency to use other names.
                        What was the basis for it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: The theory in those days in the late 1930s — I was 14 or 15 in 1938, so
                    I can't say that I was sophisticated. — was that it was a needed subterfuge
                    because America could go fascist and we would have to protect ourselves. There
                    was criticism, for instance, of German Jewish agencies that did not take the
                    precaution of destroying membership lists. When the Nazis took over in Germany,
                    they just picked up Synagogue and organization lists that were left in tact. We
                    felt that “the iron hand of Jack London” could happen here. Looking back, I
                    think we were overly dramatic about it, but at that time it didn't look that far
                    afield.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So Kristol [used] the name Ferry.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes, he was Irving Ferry, and since he was somewhat on the outside
                    looking in, the nickname we gave him was Perry Ferry or periphery.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And similarly Selznick had [an assumed name]?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Sherman, and Lipset was Lewis, and I was Field.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, that's how I remember you first. Go head.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I was young enough to make the transition. I joined the Young Peoples
                    Socialist League. I was 16 or so at the time. I was working with Robin Myers and
                    Irwin Suall and the other leadership. Last I heard Robin Myers was working for
                    the Voice of America. Suall was working for the Anti-Defamation League in charge
                    of its department that checks on extremism and cultism. Within a period of time
                    I became City Chairman, then in my twenties, National Chairman of the Young
                    Socialists. My interests in international affairs and the threat of a Communist
                    move towards world domination was always a problem for me. Some people think
                    that I am a little bit of a nut, although I think that I am pretty balanced.
                    Doesn't everybody?</p>
                <p>Anyway, when I was asked by a fellow named Jerry Bishop from the Textile Workers
                    at that time if I would be interested in setting up a work-study training
                    program for emerging labor leadership from Western Europe, I said that it
                    sounded very interesting, especially since the Communists had not too long
                    before then taken over Czechoslovakia using the labor movement as a major
                    vehicle in the destruction of a beautiful and democratic country. I thought that
                    the rest of Europe could be in similar danger, and this would be one effort that
                    could help create some cadres that could help the other side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was Jerry Bishop?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: He was the engineer for the Textile Workers Union, and Gomberg was in
                    the I.L.G.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was William Gomberg, the engineer, who was setting up
                        the Engineering Department of the International Ladies' Garment Workers'
                        Union.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: It was really at Jerry's suggestion [that I went to work for the
                    Marshall Plan.] In fact, I looked for a copy of Marion Hedges' newsletter at
                    that time, where he announced Jerry's appointment and my appointment with our
                    pictures on the next pages. I couldn't find it though. Maybe I'll come across it
                    later and send it to you, Murray. In the meantime, we went to Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We just used the name of Marion Hedges, who was in charge
                        of labor information programs in the Washington headquarters of the Marshall
                        Plan. Go ahead.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: That's right. This has nothing to do with the later phase when I edited
                    the newsletter for the agency both here and abroad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But at this stage the question was whether you were going
                        to Europe.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: No, that came a little later. What I did [at the Marshall Plan
                    Headquarters in Washington] was to set up this work-study training program.
                    Basically it was something that a good program person could have done. I dealt
                    with the universities to get them to house the participants and provide some
                    technical assistance to the project.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the United States level?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, this is the foreigners coming over [here} ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes. Then we would work with the local unions to get union support and
                    input into the project: speakers, union know-how, etc. We had to set up the
                    program and bring the people over. They were screened overseas by people who I
                    am sure Murray knows better than I do. The idea was to get emerging leadership,
                    not staid leadership, not old time leadership. We were trying to get people in
                    their twenties and thirties who had the potential of eventually replacing people
                    who had been worn out and were not able to do this alone. They needed some help.
                    This [program] gave them a background in American trade union methods, some of
                    which were applicable [to their situation] and some weren't. We understood that.
                    We made that quite clear. We weren't telling them to do it our way. We were just
                    showing them ways that they might pick and choose certain things that would be
                    helpful. But we also showed them American productive methods. Some of this we
                    may have taught too well to the Germans and others, because now they have
                    outstripped us. But at the time, the whole continent of Europe looked like it
                    could easily fall under [Communist influence]. They say that Stalin could have
                    taken Europe by a telephone call in 1946. We were quite concerned with the
                    maintenance of free labor movements and their ability to stand behind democratic
                    countries and to build the strength that would help us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you to comment on a problem which occurred
                        during the Marshall Plan period and which has been raised in some of our
                        interviews. [Marshall Plan] officials tried to identify and bring over [to
                        the United States] the possible emerging leadership of unions in Europe. The
                        problem was that these trips to the United States — and this happens many
                        years later in the developing areas too — were a wonderful opportunity for
                        the top leadership of unions. To what degree did you have to take into
                        account, or do you take into account, the fact that by selecting a so-called
                        “emerging” trade unionist you might be offending the person in charge of the
                        union who was certainly not necessarily interested in giving [away] this
                        benefit of a trip to the United States or creating or building up a possible
                        alternative leadership as it were? Did that ever occur to you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes, that occurred to us. We didn't go down and tell the head of the
                    Lyon Garment Workers' [Union] that “we are taking Joe Forseille, because we
                    think he will be an excellent replacement for you, before you are ready to be
                    replaced.” It wouldn't have been too wise. Whether we told them or not, there
                    were many who felt that this was a needed ingredient, and that it had to be done
                    somewhat on an informal basis. There is no way you could tell who the emerging
                    leaders were. You could only tell who had the potential abilities and the
                    interests and the potential knowledge and dedication, but whether they would
                    emerge in [the union] or whether they would use that knowledge to go into
                    business and set up a perfume company, I didn't know. There was no way we could
                    tie that down nor were we interested in doing that. What we were doing was
                    bringing over [large enough] numbers where we felt that the ferment and the
                    educational dispersement and the interchange of ideas and populations would lead
                    to a better reservoir of potential [leaders]. Would it work out in each
                    situation? Not necessarily, but in the overall it would strengthen our situation
                    for free unionism.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I understand your good purpose in all this, but I was
                        wondering whether you had any feedback from the top leadership? Was this, by
                        the way, only for France or for other [countries as well]?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: 16 countries. Then as one of my goodies, I got a tour with a team of
                    Norwegian trade union women, six of whom somehow could not [be programmed] in
                    the community they wanted. They were given a terrific six week tour, and guess
                    who guided them around the country for six weeks? Hey! (laughter) Somehow I
                    lucked into that situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were Norwegian trade unionists.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes, mostly garment workers. I have some stuff on that. Anyway, this
                    work-study program was there for several years at which time Victor Reuther. .
                    .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excuse me. Were you under a contract to do this? Or were
                        you an employee?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I was an employee of the Marshall Plan, E.C.A., MSA, FOA, and AID. It
                    was all the same organization. It changed its name every time Congress took a
                    look at it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were on their payroll? You were not a contract
                        employee?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I was a GS-13, a permanent employee with “status”. After three years, I
                    had status. I was all set to go on to further work in the agency, when two
                    things happened. First, I got a letter saying that I was going to be let go most
                    regrettably, and they hated to do it, but a Mr. Spector, head of personnel, said
                    that “the necessity for this action is sincerely regretted. However, the
                    requirements facing us leave us no alternative. Your past service time at the
                    Mutual Security Agency is deeply appreciated.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Put a date on that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: That was August 4, 1953.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the relationship between that time and when you
                        were doing this publications work for the organization?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I don't really remember the date [of that]. I think that was later.
                    That was really a job they gave me during a period when they really did not give
                    me any jobs. That was something to keep me out of mischief.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But so far you had only done these work-study groups?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: And I did a certain amount of programming for teams, but that was
                    really not considered to be high-level stuff. You did that to help when somebody
                    was out sick.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were then at a point where there was a change in
                        the administrations. Stassen came in as head of what was renamed the
                        “Foreign Operations Agency” (FOA), and his Personnel Director was Mel
                        Spector, who is one the people directing the Marshall Plan Oral History
                        Project at the present time. Go ahead.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Well, Spector sent me this letter. He said that he was sorry but that
                    he had no choice and he mentioned Section 706A of the Mutual Security Act of
                    1953, which provided that the number of civilian employees [paid] from
                    administrative expense appropriations shall be cut at least 10 percent. I had
                    the honor of being selected as one of these. I understood from the memo that I
                    saw — but I am not sure that the other two saw that same memo — that Philip
                    Heller and Bill Gausmann, both of whom were close friends of mine from the
                    Socialist movement, received similar type letters. They were overseas; one was
                    in Austria; and one was in England to my recollection.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Wasn't Heller in Germany?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: It could have been Germany. He was in both countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Gausmann was an information officer at the Embassy in
                        London?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes. Since I wasn't aware of anything that brought the three of us
                    together aside from our Socialist background, and there was never any lack of
                    appreciation of my work and performance, I went and looked up the [relevant]
                    section of the Mutual Security Act and it turned out that it was very specific
                    about administrative funds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said that the only other two people you knew to whom
                        this applied. . .</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: In that one memo.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: . . . were Heller and Gausmann. But as a matter of fact,
                        did you know whether you three were the only ones who got this letter.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: No, it could be [there were others].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because there were many others</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: There had to be many others. I think we were the first; I think we were
                    famous in that we were the first. But if you take 10 percent of an agency that
                    size, there had to be a lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: The memo I saw specifically mentioned us three. So I read it over and
                    this administrative funds thing hit a bell, because I was paid by program funds.
                    I was working with program people from these various countries and setting up
                    programs.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We have to clarify this by saying that there were two
                        forms of funding for the work done under the Marshall Plan. One was for the
                        hiring of civil servants and for supervising the conduct of work that was
                        done in the international field and the other was for payment of purchases
                        of various things. You have said — and you are correct of course — that the
                        reference in the letter that you received [from Mr. Spector] was to a
                        requirement that [employees paid with] only one type of funds should be
                        [cut], and you actually were being paid from the other type of funds.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: That's true. Well, I checked it with Arthur Goldberg, who was the CIO
                    General Counsel, and he said, “You are 100 percent right.” We sat down and
                    prepared a letter to Mr. Spector outlining what we thought [were my legal rights
                    in this case. The letter concluded,] “Therefore, I request immediate restoration
                    to full pay status and immediate rescinding of this action. As cited in the
                    first paragraph, my last day is such and such; therefore, I would appreciate a
                    reply within the next three days, so that I may seek further advice from
                    counsel, if it is necessary to institute appropriate action.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You are now reading from a letter that you sent to Mr.
                        Spector in reply to his other letter. And theses letters will be in the
                        files of our project and they are dated respectively. . .</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: They are dated in September 1953. There are several letters back and
                    forth. There is a September 21st brief addendum. I won't go into the details of
                    that. They are not importanOne said they were going to make sure that I was
                    going to be terminated right away. The other said they would give me thirty
                    days. It up wound up that they rescinded the action completely. No discussion of
                    the issues.</p>
                <p>So there I was ready to go back to work. Unfortunately, Mr. Thomas Holleran told
                    me. . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thomas Holleran was the Branch Chief in the Marshall Plan
                        Headquarters in Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: He said, “I will deny it, if you quote me. . .” But I think after forty
                    years, there's not too much problem [in quoting him now]. He's been gone a long
                    time. “I've been told not to give you any assignment.” I had a fairly decent job
                    by standards in those days. $8,660 was the [annual salary for a] GS-13 grade
                    level. I had nothing to do. So that was a problem. Finally I convinced them to
                    let me put out a newsletter about [labor] events around the world. That was
                    Labor Affairs. (I have found three copies and given them to Mr. Weisz.) I looked
                    around in Washington [for things to do and worked on] different projects in the
                    various countries. It wasn't exactly a job, but it did keep me out of mischief
                    to some extent.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I was in the Paris office [of the Marshall Plan] at
                        that time. We used Labor News abroad to publicize to foreign readers and
                        those involved in the Marshall Plan operations in Europe the interest of the
                        United States Government in improving labor conditions, improving
                        productivity and in the rebirth of European trade unions and economic
                        development generally.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Well, I thought we did a pretty fair job. Then Victor Reuther nominated
                    me for an opening with the OEEC in Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's the Organization for European Economic
                        Cooperation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Vic and I had been friendly. We worked together in some projects to
                    create [labor] centers to counterbalance a right wing development within foreign
                    labor affairs led by the AFL Coordinator of International Affairs Jay Lovestone,
                    a former Communist, who was very effective organizationally but had gone to the
                    point of involving American trade unions in cooperation with Government
                    agencies, particularly with the CIA We felt this was bad for [labor's]
                    effectiveness, because these things have a way of getting out. Even without
                    getting out, they can undermine the independence of a free labor approach. So we
                    had been in contact and worked on that. (I have a couple of memos that I gave to
                    Murray [Weisz for the project's records]).</p>
                <p>Well, Victor Reuther recommended me for this [OEEC position]. I [would have]
                    worked directly with Gunnar Myrdal, and I was pretty much all set to go. It was
                    approved by. . . I forget the initials in Paris.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: U.S.R.O., the U.S. Representation for Regional
                        Organizations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I would be located in Brussels. This was the OEEC Headquarters, I
                    believe at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: OEEC Headquarters were in Paris. Brussels was the ICFTU
                        Headquarters.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I'm not sure. This goes back almost forty years now. I would have been
                    quite happy in Paris. I made the decision not to take the job. I was offered a
                    job working for an international union with an old friend Harold J. Gibbons to
                    head up a state organizing program for a couple years with the understanding
                    that I would then become the International Affairs Director of the international
                    union, and he was close enough to the international union leadership to do that.
                    I mean I had no question. For reasons that are too personal to go into, it did
                    not work out and the work in St. Louis unfortunately took me away from, rather
                    than into, international labor affairs.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this is very interesting. I am leafing through the
                        three copies of Labor Affairs that you have given me for our project. Let me
                        ask you to comment on a few things. One of them is the whole business of the
                        radical background of many of the people involved in the Marshall Plan labor
                        work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>By the way I see here in Volume 2, Number 2, of March 1955, some very important
                    comments made by Stassen at the Senate Appropriations Committee in which he
                    points to the need for technical assistance programs, part of which was run in
                    the labor program. I gather that this division between the trade unions and
                    Stassen was never stressed in the statements made by Stassen or by the trade
                    union movement, since each of them was using the other in conjunction with
                    supporting excellent work in the Marshall Plan.</p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: You were in Europe during this period and I was in Washington. I was
                    very envious. You had all the fleshpots of Europe on your doorstep, and I had to
                    worry about snow. Stassen came in with an interesting program. Here was a
                    fellow, who was very bright. He was Governor of Minnesota as a young man. They
                    called him “The Boy Governor.” That's how young he was. He was appointed by
                    Eisenhower. He had political ambitions and in fact he kept running for President
                    for ten, fifteen, twenty years with no success at all, but during this time he
                    was head of the Marshall Plan program. He came in with the idea that there was
                    somehow a profusion of “no-goodniks” in the program on the staff. He used a term
                    that they were “New Deal hangers-on.” I don't know if he used the term “bleeding
                    hearts,” but the idea was that they had no serious commitment or organizational
                    experience; they just got appointed on a party basis through the Truman
                    Administration. So what Stassen was going to do was purge them, and he had this
                    “ten percent authorization” in the Act that gave employees no recourse to Civil
                    Service protection. So he started in doing it, and the press got a hold of it,
                    and said, “Hey, wait a second. How do you know who's good and who isn't?” He
                    said, “Well, I am preparing one of the most detailed testing programs known to
                    man.” And he did develop a series of very exacting tests, which everybody GS-11
                    and above [had to take]. That's my recollection. So we took the test.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Including Mr. Stassen, who took it himself.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: No, that was a step later. First we took it, and then the press got it
                    and said, “Hey, wait a second. You mean to say that you are not ready to subject
                    yourself to the same criteria as your staff?” He said, “Oh, I'll take the test.”
                    So he took it too. I did quite well, by the way, and Stassen did pretty well,
                    but not as well as I did. It turned out that the “New Deal hangers-on,” if there
                    was such a thing as Truman appointees, did pretty well. Who did the best of all
                    on the exam? It turned out interestingly enough that people who were used to
                    taking exams recently, people who just gotten out of graduate school in the last
                    couple of years with their Ph.D.'s and MA's in hand, they had been used to
                    taking exams, and they did very well on that. They did better than the chiefs of
                    the divisions taking the exam even though the division chiefs might have been
                    very competent people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any relationship between political activity and the level
                        of the [test result].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: To the extent that we could figure it out — and we couldn't do it
                    [scientifically] because the results were confidential and we didn't have access
                    to the results. You know, people were put on the spot to tell their scores. — we
                    found that those who had a liberal or left background held their own to say the
                    least. Better than average. As for the people who were being fired or dismissed,
                    their grades were given out, and they were among the highest, mine included.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me go into this now that so much time has passed.
                        Perhaps we both can lean back and be a little bit more dispassionate in our
                        analysis of the criticism leveled against the old New Dealers and radicals,
                        etc. On page 24 of your March 1955 copy of Labor Affairs, is a letter to Mr.
                        Barney Taylor, the top trade union guy at the American Embassy, Paris,
                        France, USRO. He was the head of the European program. Your letter covers
                        the question of human relations experts suggested for technical assistance
                        teams with labor-relations interests. Let me go down the names a bit and try
                        to come to some conclusion with you as to the type of people you were
                        recommending, and frankly I was also.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Here's Dr. Erich Fromm, excellent person, whom we all knew and have heard of, a
                    psychiatrist — Wasn't he a psychiatrist among other things? — but he happened to
                    be a Socialist. Right?</p>
                <p>Next one is Seymour M. Lipset. Whatever he is now, he was then an Associate
                    Professor of Sociology, and also a Socialist of sorts.</p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: He considers himself a Social Democrat as does Danny Bell and a lot of
                    the others. He is active in the American Friends of Peace Now. He's in the most
                    liberal wing of the Jewish groupings.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's go down this list a little more. Professor C. Wright
                        Mills, who was the author of White Collar and a very well known
                        sociologically oriented [academic].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I don't know what happened to Mills, but at the time he and Hans Gerth,
                    who was his co-author, were probably the leading figures in the new “sociology
                    of work” and work problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right. The next person is Dr. Joel Seidman, a Professor of
                        Industrial Relations at [the University of] Chicago, who was also a
                        Socialist. Dr. Harold Sheppard, then teaching at Wayne University, who at
                        that time certainly was left-oriented and still is quite liberal. Professor
                        Philip Selznick, Professor of Sociology, also had a Social Democratic
                        background. Donald Rogue worked with Gunner Myrdal. I don't know what his
                        political orientation was.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: If they weren't at least Socialists, I don't think I put them in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's what I wanted to know. Dan Bell. Dr. Aaron
                        Levenstein, even though you identify him as the Labor Director of the
                        Research Institute of America, where he was making a good salary, certainly
                        was a Socialist. Now here you give the names of nine people. Is it accurate
                        for these conservatives to say, “Look at what this [list] is! A bunch of
                        left-wingers far to the left of the government in power who are being
                        recommended as human relations experts to teach the Europeans.” I want you
                        to comment on two things: One, could you have recommended a better mix in
                        terms of political orientation? And secondly, would you assess the value of
                        having people of that orientation do this type of work for a conservative
                        American government? What impact does that have on the European human
                        relations experts?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: What you have to realize, Murray, [is that] in Europe you are dealing
                    with countries which have deep Socialist and Social Democratic traditions and in
                    many cases Socialist governments or soon to be Socialist governments. You have
                    trade unions which have grown up with an ideological framework and background. I
                    give a class in classical political theory at a local Catholic university, and I
                    can't believe that [the students] have never heard of Lenin. They have never
                    heard of Karl Marx and Willy Brandt. Names don't mean anything to them. In
                    Europe names mean something. Traditions mean something. I'm not saying to
                    everybody, but I'm talking about seniors in college. I felt I was just in virgin
                    territory. Now it seems to me that we were suggesting a balance between the
                    “know-nothings” that often come through ordinary civil service channels and
                    [people with] the type of sophistication who are needed to deal with European
                    labor with its rich ideological background. I felt that these people [could do
                    the job]. I was not testing them for ideological purity. I certainly would not
                    recommend anybody who had any pro-Russian, pro-Stalinist orientation. I
                    obviously wouldn't do that. But Social Democrats and independent leftists had
                    knowledge of the ideologies and of the [various political] movements of Europe.
                    They could do a much better job than a person who was not trained, even if he
                    was well-meaning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What you are saying then is that to accomplish the
                        purposes of a government like our government facing a continent which had a
                        mixture of Socialists, semi-Socialists, and conservative governments, a
                        competent way of directing their economic program towards something that
                        would be successful in terms of economic development was to use people from
                        our society who [had a left-wing orientation].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I was making the point that it was in the interest of our government that did not
                    necessarily agree with the orientation of the people who were speaking for it.
                    It was our government that used appropriately people of that orientation to
                    speak to groups in Europe who would accept the judgement of a group of
                    left-wingers in the United States, whom they would have felt closer to in
                    intellectual and political orientation.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I always think that it is helpful when they speak the “same language.”
                    They have heard of the same people. They read the same books. Also they were not
                    trying to indoctrinate the Europeans with any special theory. The Europeans had
                    their own theories. We were trying to give them the ability work more
                    effectively for free trade unionism. I always think it was by happenstance that
                    we had people with a good social-democratic, free trade union background in that
                    situation in Germany. George Silver and Bill Kemsley were in Germany right after
                    the war. It was by accident. For some reason right after the war General
                    Eisenhower, our Chief of Staff in the European Theater, was given information
                    that a destructive element had evolved in Germany under the occupation, where
                    the Social Democrats (SPD) were insisting on maintaining the separation of their
                    union from the pro-Communist trade union group. Eisenhower said, “Well, this is
                    where we have to try to all work together.” It seemed good to him. It was 1945,
                    and things had not broken down yet. So he called in the person who he understood
                    was behind all this mess, a fellow named Kurt Schumacher, who was head of the
                    Social Democratic Party, and who had been in a concentration camp for 12 years
                    and almost died. Eisenhower got to a point where in a good-natured way he said,
                    “You know, we could put you in jail too.” Schumacher said, “You can't do
                    anything to me that hasn't been done already, so go ahead and try.”</p>
                <p>Fortunately there were people like Silver and Kemsley, who were close enough to
                    the situation and knew enough about it, so that people started checking with
                    them and sent information back to the Eisenhower camp that it might be better if
                    Eisenhower left this situation alone. There was no way that the Social Democrats
                    were going to let the Communists come in and take over the union. So Eisenhower
                    backed off. By happenstance Silver and Kemsley were there. Now if you get people
                    of that sophistication on projects, it isn't a question of what their particular
                    political bent is. There is a whole range in the free trade union movement. It
                    is a question that they can probably deal more effectively ideologically against
                    the totalitarians and their friends than they can over in this country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me interrupt to make a cross reference to an earlier
                        interview with Paul Porter, who [described] the two camps within the
                        military occupation of Germany. One group took a simplistic view that
                        Germany had been defeated and therefore [should] suffer the consequences of
                        defeat. Siding with them were [those who] pushed the Morgenthau Plan for the
                        destruction of the German economy, so that Germany could never again
                        threaten the United States or the rest of Europe. Those two groups were
                        supported by the underground Communist movement which had its own objective
                        of destroying Germany for the purposes of the Soviet Union. It was only
                        through the [opposing] influence of people from Wisconsin and the trade
                        union movement and Irving Brown of the AFL and, as Porter says, “some of the
                        CIO people” that the our policies were turned around and the Communist
                        effort defeated. Please comment on that, especially on Paul Porter's
                        emphasis on the old AFL crowd from Wisconsin, Biemiller, Henry Rutz, who was
                        a trade unionist himself, and the intellectuals like Saposs and those who
                        had studied under Perlman and Commons.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Well, every group, every tendency, every milieu has a feeling that its
                    influence and impact on history was a decisive one. And the others' [influence]
                    was more or less peripheral. I think they both have a good case that they
                    contributed and neither contributed as much as they had thought they contributed
                    but a hell of a lot more than was known or accepted by general society, because
                    they did make an important impact. They didn't change the world, but they were
                    one important factor in keeping Europe free and putting a rein on Soviet
                    aggrandizement and forward marching.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good. Milt, with that experience and with what you have
                        done since in social service work and in teaching, etc., could you lean back
                        and tell us what conclusions you come to about the validity of the Marshall
                        Plan program on balance: the good, the bad, and more importantly, in the
                        context of today's situation in Europe, what relevance, if any, did any of
                        our experience have and how would you suggest that that experience be used
                        in the present situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I think we were an important factor in the salvation and reconstruction
                    of Western Europe. Did we do it by ourselves? No way! They did it. Basically the
                    people of these countries did it. We gave them some tools to work with and some
                    help. Now it is always in retrospect that you try to figure out how things had
                    their impact. Was it the Marshall Plan alone? Or was it the Marshall Plan in
                    combination with the energies of entrepreneurialism, of independent unionism,
                    and of other factors that are yet to be analyzed? It usually takes some time to
                    figure that out. I have been working now on a study of the WPA and the CCC That
                    gives us a [longer] period of time, another 15 years to look at the
                    accomplishments. The more [research] I do, the better they look. At the time
                    they looked very mixed. The more you look back at them ,the better they
                    look.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the time we weren't too enthusiastic.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: That's right. You look at all the manpower programs since and not one
                    of them holds a candle to CCC or WPNot that everything they did was right. You
                    are dealing with human beings. I think the Marshall Plan program had an
                    important impact and it helped, but it wasn't the only factor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about today's problems? Any comments on that since I
                        am dipping into your valued experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Well, I have been out of international affairs as an occupation for a
                    long while, almost a lifetime. To the extent that I have any knowledge, it seems
                    to me that [during] these last few years we have for the first time an
                    opportunity to salvage what used to be the Soviet Union from complete
                    destruction, chaos and God knows what will take over under these circumstances.
                    All our predictions turned out to be right. We never expected them to turn out
                    within our lifetime. [I thought] Communism would erode, but I never thought it
                    would disappear. They used to say that the inner contradictions of capitalism
                    would kill us. That was part of the Marxist philosophy. The inner contradictions
                    of Communism under Stalin's leadership killed it. And here we have this
                    opportunity! They are in such desperate straights. They have none of the tools
                    nor the abilities as a country — they do as individuals here and there — to
                    rebuild that economy and to [create] an entrepreneurial economy. They are
                    weighted down by bureaucracies with their old methods. They are torn apart by
                    ethnic and national tensions. If we don't come to their help and things get much
                    worse, for the few dollars that it would cost us — and I mean a few hundred
                    million dollars it would cost us — it is just a small fraction of what we were
                    paying for the military build-up during the Cold War. Just ten percent of that
                    put into the insurance of keeping Russia safe and democratic would be the best
                    investment we could possibly make.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any other comments or wisdom you want to give our project
                        about your experiences?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I don't know how much wisdom I have given so far, but if I can think of
                    any wisdom, I'll send it on to you. That's all I got.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, thanks very much not only for the interview but the
                        material you have given me, which I will copy and send back to you to the
                        extent that you want it back and the other materials I will retain for the
                        use of students and academics. Thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Thank you, Murray.</p>
                <p>Continuation of interview: Tuesday, April 13, 1993</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is Morris Weisz and date is Tuesday, April 13, 1993.
                        I am sitting in Joe Glazer's house with a house guest of his Milton
                        Zatinsky, an old friend of mine, whom I interviewed a month ago in Miami. I
                        am taking advantage of his visit to get some background information on some
                        observations he made in his interview last month about various radical
                        groups in the American political movements and in the American trade union
                        movement. It occurred to Don Kienzle, the Executive Secretary of our project
                        — the Labor Diplomacy Oral History Project — that students using the project
                        materials [would benefit from having more] background information on the
                        various radical movements referred to in the various interviews. This
                        applies especially to the Marshall Plan period, when Americans dealt with
                        Europeans who frequently had some background and experience in radical
                        political movements and related trade union organizations. When our labor
                        attach�s would refer to work they did in various foreign countries, they
                        often commented on the trade union and political people they dealt with
                        abroad in terms of their own backgrounds in the American [trade union
                        movement]. Were they for the AFL? What was the basis for their support of
                        AFL practices and AFL personnel like Irving Brown? Were they in favor of
                        Victor Reuther because of shared political and trade union activities with
                        Victor, the CIO representative in the Marshall Plan period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>So Milt, on the basis of your long background in politics and in trade union
                    work, please give us your views [on various radical movements of the 1930s how
                    they influenced subsequent international labor diplomacy.] You have cautioned me
                    that, of course, it will not be an objective view, because you have a certain
                    background, but that doesn't bother us so much, because we hope to get the views
                    of other people as well, so that future students will be able to come to
                    conclusions based not on some second-hand academic analysis but on hearing the
                    views of people like yourself with first-hand political experience.</p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Let's start at the approach of the popular front period in the
                    mid-1930's. As you know the first popular front government was established in
                    France in 1936 with Communist support under Leon Blum, who was a socialist. In
                    the early 1930's the Communists had a theory called the “third period.” The
                    third period in Communist ideology, which was espoused by Stalin from the top,
                    was that capitalism is entering its third and final period of decay and
                    collapse. Moreover, since people could see that the capitalists were up to no
                    good, the only serious obstacle to this [transformation] to a great new world of
                    the communist dictatorship was the Socialist International (SI), which was still
                    listened to by workers and which prevented workers from getting into the
                    struggle. That was the theory of the third period.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>They had a song in America that started out, “In the needle trades' unions the
                    socialist party is a no good party. It's the third capitalist party of the
                    bosses.” This was their [line]. When Hitler came to power and destroyed the
                    Communist movement in Germany, Stalin saw that a new force [— fascism — had
                    emerged]. It wasn't so-called “British and American imperialism” that was the
                    main threat but a new force that could be a danger to his power in Russia. He
                    changed gears real quickly [and adopted the concept of the] popular front. “We
                    will join together with Socialists and those that we can get to fuse into [a
                    popular front] and anybody else.” He worked at setting up independent unions in
                    the United States. There was not only the regular AFL garment workers union but
                    also a Needle Trades Industrial Union set up by the Communists as their
                    opposition to it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Milt, I'll have to ask you to speak a little. . . No, no,
                        you are not going too far. I asked you to go back further to Leninism, if
                        you will. I am going to ask you to speak a little bit more slowly, because
                        in listening to your other tape. . .</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I go too fast. All right. I'll slow down. Now [the Communists']
                    positions [during] those days were devastating, because there was a split in the
                    working class movement in Germany as Hitler was taking his road to power with
                    his storm troopers. The Socialists were trying to keep constitutional liberties
                    alive in some sort of framework in the Weimar Republic. The Communists, instead
                    of supporting legality and law, set up “red storm troopers.” The more that
                    lawlessness and violence increased, the worse it got, and this gave the Nazis
                    their opportunities So the Communists changed [their position]. They didn't
                    admit they were wrong, but they changed gears and in the mid-1930's started a
                    new “we love you” period with the Socialists.</p>
                <p>One of the first groups in this country that the Communists were able to get to
                    experiment with this [new cooperation] — warily and against the advice of their
                    elders — was the Student League for Industrial Democracy, which represented
                    young Social Democrats and their allies on campus. The Student League for
                    Industrial Democracy went into a united organization with the National Students
                    League, which [represented] the Communists and was tightly knit and well
                    financed. It was surprising [at that time] how well financed these Communists
                    groups were. We know now where the money came from. It came from the Soviet
                    Union. This is all documented now. In a few years a small group [of Communists]
                    took over the combined American Student Union (ASU) and turned the ASU to their
                    own purposes to the point where the ASU was supporting the Hitler-Stalin pact in
                    1939, when [the Soviet Union] turned against the West.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The new organization was [called] the American Students
                        Union?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes, the American Students Union. The young Socialists, the young
                    Trotskyites, and the other non-Stalinist leftists soon became so discouraged by
                    these shifts and turns that they left. The middle-of-the-road liberal types,
                    Socialists like Joseph Lash, a friend of the First Lady Eleanor Roosevelt, and
                    his group [including] Molly Yard, who is now head the National Organization of
                    Women, all left. The American Students Union was [then] left completely in the
                    hands of the Communists, who finally buried it when it no longer served any
                    purpose to them. Now the Communist movement had two main dissident spin-offs. It
                    also had many smaller ones. There is a difference between the. . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Communist political movement, not the student
                        movement.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes, the Communist political movement. The student movement just
                    followed along. The student arm, the trade union arm, and their other arms just
                    followed along with the overall policy which was decided not in this country but
                    by their bosses in Moscow. There were two groups that spun off, both of which
                    are interesting for the purpose [of this discussion]. The first group was the
                    Trotskyites. In 1927 when Trotsky was expelled from Russia, he went to Turkey
                    and Norway. He wound up in Mexico as a guest of Diego Rivera and President
                    Cardenas. There were very few havens for a dissident Communist in those
                    days.</p>
                <p>Trotsky set up his own [international political organization] and in the
                    mid-1930's came to the conclusion that the Socialist movements of the world were
                    ready for a major turn to the left, so he had his small Trotskyite organizations
                    join the overall socialist parties. This did not last too long, and it was not
                    too successful. In America you had the spin off of the young Trotskyites and the
                    Trotskyites' party. They called [the new group] the Socialist Workers' Party,
                    and for the youth group, [as a counterpart] of the Young Peoples' Socialist
                    League of the Socialist Party, they set up the Young People's Socialist League
                    Fourth, because Trotsky at that time believed he had to set up a new “Fourth”
                    Communist International to replace the Third International, the Comintern of the
                    Communists, and the too conservative for him Socialist Second International or
                    Labor and Socialist International. So the new [Trotskyite youth] group was the
                    “YPSL Fourth”.</p>
                <p>Now let me just put that movement aside and discuss the other [major Communist]
                    splinter [group] which came a couple of years later, and that was the “Lovestone
                    group.” They were followers to a certain extent of the Russian leader Nikolai
                    Bukharin. Trotsky was a left opposition leader. Bukharin was a more moderate
                    leader. The Bukharin movement was interesting. Bukharin was the darling of the
                    Communist Party under Lenin. He was young, very bright, and articulate. In
                    Lenin's last will and testament, Lenin talked of Bukharin as the darling of the
                    party, and as the person in whom he had so much hope, but Bukharin was something
                    of a moderate. His group [included] people like Rykov and others.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: People like who?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Rykov. Rykov eventually became President of the Soviet Union, but of
                    course with Stalin's gun to his head. [He and others in the group] were executed
                    in 1938 after a trial which denounced them for being everything from Nazi agents
                    to agents of the imperialist warmongers. God knows what!</p>
                <p>Bukharin was a rather solid person, who had some serious second thoughts about
                    early Communist theory. He went abroad in 1937. His friends and people not that
                    close said, “Why in the world go back? That S.o.b. [Stalin] is going to kill
                    you.” He had one reason to go back. He had a young wife and a very young child,
                    and he had no guarantee that they wouldn't be murdered by Stalin in retribution
                    to his not coming back. His wife, who is still alive, has just recently written
                    a book of her memoirs of her husband, Bukharin. It is a very interesting book
                    and was reviewed in the [New York] Times Book Section a few weeks ago.
                    Yevtushenko wrote a long poem honoring Bukharin's life. Even before Gorbachev,
                    they were beginning to try to rehabilitate Bukharin.</p>
                <p>Bukharin wrote an article or memo while in Paris. He couldn't put his name to it,
                    because he didn't want to sign his wife's death warrant. He met with a fellow
                    named Boris Nikolevsky, who was head of the Research Bureau of the Mensheviks,
                    the moderate Social Democratic opposition to the Communists, and he gave him
                    this long document called “Memoirs of an Old Bolshevik.” He said, “Please
                    publish it, but my name cannot go on it.” But it was pretty obvious, if you read
                    it, who had written it. Nikolevsky after Bukharin's death had no trouble
                    identifying [Bukharin as the author. In the document,] Bukharin talked about the
                    terrible mistake the Communists had made in doing away with multi-party
                    democracy and in concentrating all power in the hands of the state
                    apparatus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which they called “democratic centralism.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: They called it “democratic centralism,” the curtailing an independent
                    press and of access to information, etc. All the aspects of dictatorship.
                    Bukharin said, “We have made such a terrible mistake.” Arthur Koestler's book,
                    Darkness at Noon, is based more or less, according to Koestler, on Bukharin.
                    Rubischev is the name given to the hero in that book.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before you proceed, did his article refer to errors in
                        Stalin's economic program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I hate to say this, Murray, but I haven't read the book in about
                    forty-five years. I couldn't give you very good answer.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because there were some criticisms of the whole effort to
                        do away with the class of the agricultural people [Kulaks].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: He opposed that openly. His public break with Stalin was on the
                    liquidation of the Kulaks as a class and the ending of independent farming.
                    There is no question that Bukharin fought against that and he fought against the
                    mass murder of the Ukrainian farmers through starvation when they were shipping
                    foodstuffs out of the country and their own people were literally starving
                    because Stalin wanted them to go “under heel.” Bukharin opposed all that and
                    that was his real initial sharp break with the Stalinist machine.</p>
                <p>In this country, the pro-Bukharin group was headed by the then General Secretary
                    of the Communist Party, a young man in those days, named Jay Lovestone. He had a
                    group of very sophisticated, capable people [working with him].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are now talking about the late 1920s.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: 1929 was the break. We are talking about 1928, 1929, and 1930. People
                    were coming into the movement like Irving Brown; another was the writer Bertram
                    Wolfe, who was one of the leading figures; and in the trade union movement, a
                    fellow named Charles “Sasha” Zimmerman in the Garment Workers' Union. He left
                    the Communist Needle Trades Industrial Union when he broke with these people and
                    went back to work for the Garment Workers' Union, where I believe he rose to be
                    the first vice president. In addition, they had younger people at that time:
                    Harry Goldberg and some very capable and committed people. Lovestone himself
                    never married. He was a very young Secretary of the Party. [He won] reelection
                    to this job over Earl Browder and William Z. Foster by 85 percent of the vote of
                    the American Communist Party when the party still had votes. He went to the
                    Soviet Union to say, “Why did you override my election?” He brought his top
                    leadership with him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You have to go into your reference to “overriding” this
                        election. What are you referring to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: The Soviet Union negated the election. They simply refused [to accept
                    the results of the election] and said, “This is our organization. We don't want
                    these people. We don't recognize you. We recognize the [ticket] which got 15
                    percent of vote headed by William Z. Foster and Earl Browder.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the nature of discipline [in the world Communist
                        movement] was that the Communist Party of the United States and Communist
                        parties elsewhere were members of the Comintern, and Stalin, in his capacity
                        as the real director of the Comintern, exerted discipline over the Communist
                        Party of the United States, so that it was not an American party but the
                        American branch of the Comintern.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: That's a good description. The Comintern was the international body
                    that had complete control, and I mean complete control [over member parties]. I
                    am not talking about the control of some international bodies over subordinate
                    groups. I am talking, “You say, 'yes'. We say, 'no'. We win. We're in charge.”
                    [Lovestone and his adherents] said, “Oh, you can't do that. You're wrong. It
                    would be better for the American party. . .”</p>
                <p>The Lovestone developed a theory in those days which was called “American
                    Exceptionalism.” What was that? It was that “while what you are doing may be
                    fine in the Soviet Union,” — I don't know how fine it was, but they said it was
                    fine. — “America is exceptional in that we in America have a well-organized
                    working class, self-conscious to a great extent in that workers are joining
                    trade unions, and we have [a high] standard of living where we can provide
                    [basic needs] without a violent revolution or some of the other things [needed]
                    in other Communist [assumptions of power].”</p>
                <p>Now in Marxist theory, Marx too had said that society polarizes into a small
                    group of very rich, militant, tough nasty bosses, the petit bourgeoisie, and a
                    very large group of completely disenfranchised, down-in-the-mouth “proletariat.”
                    Complete polarization made the revolution simple, because you had 95 percent of
                    the people getting rid of the two or three percent with a few clerical people
                    in-between. The Communists believed that religion was the opiate of the people.
                    However, society didn't [actually] develop the way the Communists predicted. The
                    big group developed in the service, technical and new industrial class, and the
                    industrial working class actually shrank somewhat and is still shrinking yet,
                    because of [the nature of] technological change. So society didn't develop quite
                    the way Marx thought it would, but he did say that in the United States and
                    Great Britain, the process [of social transformation] might come about through
                    natural resources and political organization rather than through violent
                    revolution.</p>
                <p>The Comintern did not accept Lovestone's interpretation. Lovestone and his
                    leadership went to the Soviet Union to plead their case before the Comintern.
                    Instead of listening to them, [Stalin and the Comintern] kept them there. It was
                    one of the few mistakes in strategy that Lovestone is guilty of in terms of
                    smart realpolitik. They weren't exactly kidnapped, because they weren't put in
                    jail, but they were kept there [in Moscow] almost indefinitely until they were
                    able through the Comintern officials to turn the American Communist Party over
                    to the small minority that had lost the election. The Lovestone group then set
                    themselves up first as the “Communist Party, Majority.” That name didn't seem to
                    catch on too well, and they finally formed the Independent Labor League of
                    America, which is the name they used more or less throughout the 1930s.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>The literature on all this is rather sparse. Ben Gitlow, who was involved in a
                    lot of this happening, wrote about it. Theodore Draper wrote a book, American
                    Communism [and the Soviet Union], and some other works, which are quite good.
                    Irv Howe and Lou Coser have a book on the history of American Communism. It
                    doesn't go far enough, but, as far as it goes, it is quite accurate and detailed
                    in its references and cross-references. There is also a book called The Divided
                    Left. I wish I could remember who wrote it, Kantor or Kantis, somebody like
                    that, who had a lot of rather good information. But generally this is not a
                    well-researched period.</p>
                <p>Now the interesting thing about the Lovestone and the Trotsky groups is that they
                    went in two different directions. In the Soviet Union the supporters of Trotsky
                    and the supporters of Bukharin tried to join together to fight against Stalinist
                    terror. They waited too long, because all the guns were in one hand. In this
                    country the [respective groups] went in different directions. The Trotskyite
                    movement, as I indicated, set up their Fourth International. Trotsky was
                    assassinated by a Russian agent in 1940; Mark Kahn and (?) Jackson were among
                    the names he used. He was the son of an old time secret police leader. After the
                    murder, he served his time [in jail] and then went to live in a Communist
                    country. He denied that he was a paid assassin. He was an “ideological
                    assassin.”</p>
                <p>The [Trotskyite] movement itself came on very bad times. This started with the
                    invasion of Finland by the Soviet Union. At first, everybody in the Trotskyite
                    movement was shocked. Then Trotsky and some of his trusted leaders said, “Well,
                    while an invasion is not a nice thing, it still may bring a better form of
                    society through the end of private enterprise and [the establishment of]
                    nationalized industry. That in the long run will lead to good things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As I recall, Trotsky said, “It is still a workers'
                        state.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes. He also kept to the theory that it was a workers' state, [albeit]
                    a “bureaucratized” workers' state and one that had “degenerated.” These were the
                    terms that he used. But still, the workers, in essence, have control. The
                    workers didn't know they had this control, because they were in jail, but
                    Trotsky, [based on] his understanding of Marxist-Leninist theory, still felt it
                    was [”a workers' state.” Trotsky's followers] in this country were led by two
                    people, James P. Cannon and Max Shachtman. Cannon, leading the majority, went
                    along with the leader. Shachtman, who had been General Secretary of the Young
                    Communists, the Communist youth movement, when Lovestone was head of the
                    Communist Party, felt that Russia was no longer a progressive society per se,
                    and wrote a book called Bureaucratic Collectivism. [The Soviet Union was
                    presented] as sort of a neutral society with bad aspects to it. [As for] the war
                    with Finland, the Soviet Union was a bad neighbor and [presented] the danger of
                    starting another world war, but even more interesting, [the war against Finland]
                    “was nothing that we could support the Soviet Union on.” In fact Shachtman more
                    or less had a position of a plague on both your houses. “We cannot fight or
                    support either of you.”</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>Within the Shachtman group there were others who said, “Wait a minute. Finland is
                    a democratic country with a large Socialist Party and free elections. The
                    workers are doing fine. They are getting good trade union conditions and they
                    are being attacked by an outside dictatorship. We're supporting Finland. The
                    Soviet is not only not a neutral state, it is a vicious enemy and we oppose it,
                    and we oppose the movement's support of Communist ideology, Bolshevism and
                    Leninism.” A group of about 30 people, all in the youth movement, resigned and
                    left. I was part of that group. I was one of the youngest, and we put out a
                    document called “Defining a tendency,” which we wrote together. I think a fellow
                    named Phil Selznick, who was “Sherman” [of the Shermanites], was the principal
                    editor [of the document].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This document is in the files of our Labor Diplomacy Oral
                        History Project.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Some of the other signers of the document were Marty Lewis or Seymour
                    Martin Lipset, who is now head of the American Sociological Society.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We have to note that the names you are giving are the real
                        names as well as the so-called party names.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes, that's right. Mine was Pete Fields. I was asked when I joined — I
                    was about 14 or 15. — “What's your party name?” I said, “What's that?” And they
                    said, “Okay, you're this.” Seymour Martin Lipset was Marty Lewis; Martin
                    Diamond, the well-known philosopher in the political science area, used the name
                    Martin Needen; Irving Kristol, who later evolved in a more conservative
                    direction (and his son, Bill Kristol, even more conservative), was Irving Ferry
                    and so on. I don't remember each one's name. I'm surprised that I remember any
                    of these. This was over 55 years ago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you put a date to this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: This is 1940, I believe. I was 16 years old.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You started early.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I was a “young-un.” I don't think Lipset was more than 19 and Selznick
                    and Kristol were probably no more than 22. When Phil Selznick stood up before
                    the organization in an open debate with Max Shachtman, who was one of the most
                    brilliant debaters I have ever heard, it was sort of sad. Although Phil did his
                    best and did a fairly good job, he was no match for Max Shachtman, who had a
                    tremendous sense of humor and was a very remarkable person.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We might at this point refer to the [Shachtman group] in
                        case anybody wants to look into it further, because so many people who later
                        became active in the foreign field originally came from the Shachtman
                        group.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Or the Lovestone group.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Or the Lovestone group. You might refer to the title of
                        Shachtman's book.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Bureaucratic Collectivism.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was his first book, but his later analysis was much
                        more conservative. Do you recall the name of that later book?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: No, I don't recall it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: We'll find it. Anyway, the Selznick group had interesting roots. They
                    were mostly academics. I now teach at a university in semi-retirement, but as I
                    said, Marty Lipset is head of the American Sociological Society. Selznick was a
                    leading professor of sociology on the West Coast, the last I heard, and many
                    others were academics. Most of us joined the Young Socialists. Years later when
                    I eventually grew up to be 20 or 21, I became the National Chairman of the Young
                    Socialists and a member of the National Committee of the Socialist Party. Some
                    of the others stayed on and worked in other groups. I had a little group with
                    Martin Lipset and Nathan Glazer, who wasn't exactly a member of the group but
                    was sort of friendly with us, and we worked together in a group called “The
                    Group of Student Action.” But these were side issues.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>The Lovestone group had an even more intriguing history at this juncture. The
                    leader, Jay Lovestone, who never married and was very focused and determined,
                    became the Advisor on International Affairs to the International Ladies' Garment
                    Workers' Union (ILGWU) and its leader David Dubinsky. Up until that point
                    Dubinsky relied on a fellow named Raphael Abramovich, who was ILGWU consultant
                    on international affairs. Abramovich had been one of the top leaders of
                    Menshevik Russian Social Democratic movement and the assistant to a fellow named
                    Julian Martov, who was the leader of the Democratic Socialist Movement in
                    Russia. He was a very close personal friend of Lenin. Abramovich left [the
                    country.] The others couldn't get out so easily. He felt very badly about
                    Martov. Martov wrote his answer to Lenin in a book called. . . Lenin's book was
                    The State and Revolution and Martov's answer was something similar. I forget the
                    full name of Martov's book, but it was an answer to Lenin's book, which Martov
                    felt would lead to a dictatorship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The title wasn't this but it can be described as The State
                        Against the Revolution.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Something like that. Anyway, Abramovich was an old-timer. The
                    Communists were very negative toward Abramovich. When the Communists found out
                    his son was serving in Spain in the Republican forces, they murdered the son,
                    not because of him particularly, but because his father was Abramovich. The
                    Communists had a long memory. I knew Abramovich fairly well. I worked with him
                    on a magazine. We still got support from the Garment Workers' Union, but Jay
                    Lovestone had the ear of the top man, and Jay brought his group with him: Irving
                    Brown, Harry Goldberg, and the others, who were part of their whole group. You
                    think you buy one person, and you are buying a family.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lovestone came in to the International Ladies' Garment
                        Workers' Union when Sasha Zimmerman returned to the ILGWU.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: It could very well be, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Zimmerman told me that when he came back into the ILG he
                        introduced Lovestone, his theoretician in his Communist days, to Dubinsky,
                        who then proceeded to see the value of this wholly-directed person,
                        Lovestone.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Lovestone then somehow moved up to be the head of the AFL's
                    International Affairs Committee and started a whole new era in
                    labor-international work overseas, bringing in his old team of Brown and
                    Goldberg and many others.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me mention the fact that Harry Goldberg remained a
                        member of the Socialist Party, at least a nominal one, for many, many years.
                        In that capacity he wrote excellent musical criticism under the name of Jim
                        Cork. He was given the name Jim Cork. He was a wonderful pianist. Although
                        he claimed never to have been a Communist or a member of Lovestone's group,
                        I never knew of any case in which he disagreed with Jay Lovestone.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: I knew him very well and my feeling was that he was under a
                    Communist-type discipline.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Whether he paid dues or not, I don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The other thing I want to mention, which is not a
                        correction of what you said but an amplification, is that Lovestone came
                        into the International Department as a representative of an organization
                        called the “Free Trade Union Committee” and did not become Director of the
                        International Department of the AFL-CIO until much later. A characteristic
                        of Communists [is that they strive to become the secretary [of an
                        organization], the function in Communist and labor movements in which people
                        process paper and therefore really determine the policies [of the
                        organization].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Well, now that Lovestone was no longer a Communist but a bitter
                    anti-Communist, he [nevertheless] still carried with him many of the tactical
                    and organizational methods of the Communists in terms of a very sharp
                    delineation of goals, keeping a group tightly knit and working together when the
                    other [groups] are amorphous and being able to take advantage of many of those
                    [characteristics]. Anyway, he has had a great deal of influence on labor
                    [movement's international policies], the most controversial one of which was the
                    fact that he dealt with movements in the Middle East that he thought had a
                    chance but wound up to be [some of] the worst movements of all. That was bad
                    judgment, but that [kind of judgment] has been made by other people too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean his association or willingness to work with
                        extremist Arab groups in North Africa?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Well, they became a lot more extremist afterwards. He was under the
                    impression that with some warmth and human understanding he could bring them
                    around. It didn't quite work out that way. That was a bad judgment. That wasn't
                    anything that others weren't doing every day. In the Middle East it is very easy
                    to make bad judgments. But interesting new thing that he did was [to establish]
                    a type of intimate cooperation with American intelligence which labor had
                    previously avoided. Labor felt [up until that time that] it would undermine the
                    independence of a private trade union movement to be part of a governmental
                    operation. There are [other] places that require close cooperation, of course,
                    but [cooperation with the CIA] was felt to be undermining union
                    independence.</p>
                <p>Now going back a few steps, I have already alluded to the work of the Second
                    International, which was the old Socialist and Labor International. The Third
                    International was the Comintern, which was organized by the Communists in 1919
                    to destroy the Socialist International and build a world movement which they
                    thought would take over the world.</p>
                <p>The smaller Fourth International was set up by Trotsky when he saw that his
                    strategy of working with the Socialists was not going to come to fruition. [I
                    have mentioned] the Second, Third, and Fourth [Internationals]. There was, of
                    course, a First [International]. Otherwise we couldn't have started [this
                    discussion] with the Second. The First was organized by Karl Marx in the last
                    century as the International Workermen's Association. It brought together
                    various nascent labor and socialist and radical groups throughout the world into
                    the formation of an international movement, which, as Marx saw it, would lead to
                    the empowerment of the working class to take over and move the next step — the
                    historical economic change to his plan of communism. Now Marx was not too
                    specific as to how the new society would look. He was very critical on his
                    analysis of the shortcomings of existing society. The early Marx had a fairly
                    open and free concept. Everybody would work at what they felt most suited them
                    and a year or two later they would do something else. Later Marx was a little
                    more rigid and with more emphasis on state control. This attitude rubbed many of
                    the European socialist or anarchist leaders the wrong way including a fellow
                    named Mikhail Bakunin, a Russian anarchist leader, who headed up a more
                    libertarian segment in the First International. His idea was that a socialist
                    regime after the revolution that Marx was talking about could become just as
                    repressive or even more so to the workers than the capitalists. At least the
                    capitalists are diverse. Marx was going to centralize everything, and if the
                    state was dictatorial, then the workers would have any chance at all. Their
                    verse in the International Song of the Workers was “We want not condescending
                    saviors to rule us from the judgment hall. We workers ask not for their favors.
                    We will all decide for all.”</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>Bakunin was a very heroic but somewhat strange figure. He was in and out of
                    jails. He nonetheless became so powerful in the International that Marx did not
                    know what to do. He was going to take over at the next few conventions. To
                    prevent this, Marx, with no authorization, bureaucratically moved the
                    headquarters [of the International] to New York and then quietly had it buried
                    when he felt he could no longer control it. Bakunin, who was in and out of
                    jails, was not really in a position to do much with it. He had a follower in
                    Russia, whose name was Dissheiv (?), the hero [Stepan Verhovensky] of
                    Dostoevsky's The Possessed, actually the villain, who acting upon the orders of
                    Bakunin and the central anarchist organization, set about its murderous program.
                    If anybody wants to read an interesting story by one of the best writers of all
                    time, I would strongly recommend The Possessed. Anyway what happened was the
                    decline in the Second, Socialist International and the decline of the First with
                    two tendencies, the anarchist tendencies in the Mediterranean and southern
                    European area. Some in South America. Spain. A large anarchist group movement in
                    Italy, Greece, and other Mediterranean countries had a strong strain of
                    anarcho-syndicalism. In the northern countries (end of side A, tape 2)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would like to draw some analogies between the types of
                        persons who were in the leadership in these movements [as found in] the
                        Marx-Bakunin fight and the Stalin-Bukharin [fight]. In a sense you had a
                        charismatic figure like Bakunin fighting a person who was essentially,
                        whatever other qualities he had, a bureaucrat, a manager, the type of person
                        who would think up the idea of moving the headquarters of an international
                        organization to the United States in order to defeat his charismatic
                        [opponent]. It [helps] you understand Stalin's success as against many of
                        these other people because as General Secretary of the Communist Party he
                        had the [capacity] to change the course of a large organization through his
                        handle on the [organizational] machinery rather than [through] his ability
                        to be a better orator. Comment on that if you will.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Well, personality types are hard to [compare]. You have some crossing
                    over. But it is true that Marx had bureaucratic as well as research and
                    organizational and writing skills. Bakunin didn't have too much time to write.
                    He was out with the people. He was charismatic. Marx wasn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Wasn't Bakunin's theory “the something of the deed”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: He believed in the “propaganda of the deed” rather than in the
                    “propaganda of the written document.” To make the easy transition from Marx to
                    Stalin, I think, is a little too jumpy, because Marx was a leading figure with
                    many different movements. He was [a model for] the dissident Communists who
                    opposed terror and for many Socialists.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You are now talking about the 1870's?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: No, I am talking about the Communists of our day. Marx was one of the
                    inspirations for many other tendencies than Communism and Stalinism. Stalin like
                    Hitler was a unique figure. Sidney Hook wrote an interesting book called The
                    Role of the Hero in History. Marx didn't appreciate [the role of the hero] in
                    his theory that things are inevitable and that the individual vagaries of
                    personality and interrelations are just questions of coloration and mood that
                    change things just a few iotas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Economic determinism.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Economic determinism is the way Marx put it. Now Hook's book is a very
                    interesting book. He takes the Russian Revolution and shows how it could have
                    gone six different ways. If Lenin had decided to do one other thing or if the
                    train through Germany had run into trouble, lots of different things could have
                    happened. The ascent of Stalin showed a complete blind spot on the part of the
                    other Communist leaders, many of whom disliked Stalin intensely. [Stalin was] a
                    person with absolute and complete bureaucratic control [combined] with a
                    ruthlessness. There is lots of material, and hopefully we will find more out as
                    documents become available to the West, that Stalin hastened the death of Lenin
                    through murder. We know that some others [including] Dzerzhinsky were probably
                    murdered medically by Stalin. He had one of his operatives do it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dzerzhinsky?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Dzerzhinsky. Dzerzhinsky was the original head of the Cheka, the
                    Russian Secret Police. Stalin was only involved in power. The fact was that that
                    was the flag that he had to wave and the words that he had to say to get control
                    of power and increase it and hold it. He was an obsessed power maniac.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I may have done Marx an injustice by not agreeing
                        from the very beginning that he was a intellectual giant who was a
                        theoretician of the first order, which certainly Stalin wasn't, but this
                        bureaucratic capability is what interests me and the tendency in all my
                        ex-Trotskyite friends to refer to Stalinism as the evil rather than say
                        Leninism.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Well, the reason for that is not that Lenin was a good guy and Stalin
                    was a bad guy. Lenin did a lot of bad things, everything from the murders at
                    Kronstadt to doing away with the Social Democratic political parties, to the
                    banning of the free press, even to his murder of the entourage around the
                    monarchy. They murdered the Czar; they murdered the nurse and the maid and the
                    cook and the doctor and seven year old kids. I mean that ain't the nicest way to
                    do business, but compared to Stalin, Lenin was just a beginner.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lenin was also an intellectual leader and an academician
                        and a serious thinker in the field.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Stalin wrote one book on the national question and it is very doubtful
                    that he [actually] wrote the book [himself]. He had it written for him by
                    somebody who was probably shot later so he could say, “I wrote the book.” Also,
                    Lenin and Trotsky had one thing in common, however bad what they did may have
                    turned out. In everything they did, they put their own lives and reputations and
                    activities on the line 24 hours a day. They thought they were working to improve
                    the condition of humanity. Stalin did everything [including] murder because he
                    wanted power. He didn't give a shit for the good or the bad. He was concerned
                    with one thing and he was a brutal and later psychopathic — to the point that he
                    went off his rocker — mass murderer. He was in a class with Hitler. In fact he
                    murdered more civilians than Hitler. That wasn't easy!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The reason for going into this is that any student in the
                        field should have some of this background because of the manifestations of
                        these disagreements, policies, tactics in current issues, say in the
                        question of anarcho-syndicalism. It still has some relevance in the fights
                        in Italy in the trade union movement and in Spain.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: One sad part is that before the Second World War the anarchist movement
                    still was a major factor in the radical movements in many countries. Spain, in
                    particular, had the C.N.T. and the F.A.I., which were the largest trade union
                    federations in the country. Their leaders were men of great stature. Their
                    dreams for a free society were beautiful dreams. The war crushed everything.
                    Hitler and Stalin took over most of Europe. This left so little hope, that
                    anarchism has been relegated today to a very small role. It is interesting that
                    in this country, which at one time had a lively anarchist movement, not large
                    but lively, Emma Goldman, who was one of our [anarchists], is becoming a
                    cultural hero. Now, she isn't here to enjoy it. They used to spit in our day
                    when she walked by. Today she is a hero. I see kids in college with Emma
                    Goldman's picture on their shirts. I ask them, “How did you get Emma Goldman?”
                    They say,”She's our hero.” She should have had a chance to see herself as a
                    hero!</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just like nowadays in college Trotskyism is supposed to be
                        something great, whereas there is no relation to what we have understood
                        about Trotsky. Now that you mention the strength of anarchism and
                        syndicalism in Spanish history, I should mention that the trade union
                        aspects of this are described very well in the writings of Victor Alba.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: That is true, and on Spain other works include the Franz Borkenau book
                    and [one by] Arthur Koestler and George Orwell's Homage to Catalonia. These are
                    very telling and interesting books of how the Communists undermined the fight
                    against fascism through their complete subservience to Russian aims. Getting
                    closer to the current situation, the Lovestone group, which had its heyday
                    during the Cold War following World War II, was very influential and the only
                    serious countervailing force within the labor movement was led by Victor Reuther
                    and the United Automobile Workers. He tried to keep the independence of labor's
                    thought and not to make it an instrument of American foreign policy but really a
                    trade union policy. By the way after Lovestone died in 1989 or 1990, the
                    Lovestone group as a group seemed to have lost it focus. Some day it may
                    reestablish itself.</p>
                <p>Now the Trotskyite group moved in a different directions. The Shachtman group,
                    which we discussed earlier, became a workers' party then merged in the 1960's, I
                    believe, with the Socialist Party and the Social Democratic Federation. One
                    would naturally think that they would become the left wing of this movement like
                    the last time the Trotskyites entered the Socialist Party in the 1930's. Au
                    contraire, they became their most conservative wing calling themselves “Social
                    Democrats, U.S.A.,” which is the national group today headed by a fellow named
                    Donald Slaiman and Rachelle Horowitz of the Teachers' Union.</p>
                <p>The other group, the Democratic Socialists of America, which was headed until his
                    death by Mike Harrington, is a more traditional socialist movement. Both groups
                    are small, but they have a group of dedicated people who work very hard in
                    support of their policies. The main factors today in labor work overseas are
                    something that Murray Weisz is in a better position to describe than I am, since
                    I have been sort of out of things the last few years living in Florida.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me mention one characteristic of the Democratic
                        Socialists of America, the group that was led by Harrington until his death,
                        which parallels with what happened in the 1930s and 1940s, namely there is
                        today an unwillingness to stress anti-Communism. They are willing to admit
                        into their group people like Dorothy Healey.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Yes, I saw the Healey thing. She is an unreconstructed communist.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't know if she is unreconstructed, but she will
                        criticize little things in terms of “It may be true that. . .”, but if any
                        political group wants my support, it must clarify its position as against
                        the position of the Communists.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: This is a very interesting thing. It has really nothing to do
                    particularly with the Democratic Socialist of America or the Social Democrats,
                    U.S.A. In the liberal left movement as a whole, if you read the letters to the
                    editor in the [English-language] weekly issue of the Jewish Forward, you get
                    both sides of this. I saw a letter by Kopilow in one issue. Seymour Kopilow
                    teaches actors in New York and is an old friend of mine. Now, what is the issue?
                    Koppie says that there really is very little difference between somebody who
                    went to the Hitler movement and was a Hitler supporter and somebody who went to
                    the Stalin movement and was a Stalin supporter. Now it is true that neither one
                    of them may have actually thrown people into concentration camps or gas
                    chambers. They may have just supported it. They may have said it was an
                    unfortunate historical necessity. “You can't make an omelet without breaking the
                    eggs” was their best line.</p>
                <p>Now, if you take a former Stalinist, who comes out and says, “I'm a socialist
                    now. Nobody in here but us Social Democrats.” I have to say to myself, “Are you
                    ready to repudiate and condemn the murder of 20 million people in Russia by
                    Stalin, the planned murder of Russia's entire Jewish community, the works of
                    Slansky, the murder of the Jewish poets, and all these things?” He said, “No,
                    what I say is that these probably could have been mistakes of judgment. He may
                    have felt that he was surrounded by imperialist forces and he had to be too
                    rough.”</p>
                <p>Now you have others who left the Communist movement, like Jay Lovestone and Max
                    Shachtman, who became anti-Communists. There was a very interesting book called
                    The God that Failed. It was written in the late 1930s or early 1940s about
                    people who went through the Communist experience including the columnist Fisher,
                    the black novelist Richard Wright, and Arthur Koestler.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: George Orwell?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Orwell was never a Communist. Even with all the pressures that they put
                    on him on the left, he never had anything to do with them. They assigned a book
                    to Orwell to write, The Road to Wigan Pier. He went to Wigan Pier, which was a
                    depressed working class area with high unemployment, and he wrote this story
                    about what's wrong with the left. He asked, “What's this talk about Russia? The
                    Russian commissar is half gangster and half megaphone.” What a beautiful
                    description in 1936!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I thought that for a brief period Orwell was a Communist.
                        No?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Not for second.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's interesting. Then Lovestone would have never
                        agreed with him, because Lovestone's real complaint about many people was
                        that they hadn't gone through the fire of being a Communist, and therefore
                        you can't trust them in their anti-Communism.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Orwell's closest friend was Arthur Koestler and together they were
                    against the entire left establishment. Koestler was, of course, an agent of
                    Willy Muntenberg, who headed up the International Workers' Aid, a group which
                    propagandized for the popular front with the Communists. Stalin later had him
                    murdered in France. Koestler was in Spain as a Communist writer, jailed by
                    Franco, and sentenced to die. However, he was one of these guys who lived a
                    charmed life, and he somehow survived and got to England. He and Orwell were
                    sort of blood brothers. One sought understanding through experience and the
                    other through understanding in his heart. There's something wrong with guys who
                    go around murdering and killing a pillaging and saying that they are doing it
                    for a good cause.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, fine. Any other observations you want to make about
                        the background of radicalism and its influence on current situations or
                        anything about the underdeveloped world, now called the developing third
                        world?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Well, I think we should be hesitant in assessing populist charismatic
                    leaders who have little concern for democratic processes. They say, “We've had
                    such a hard time; we have to do these things.” We should not hold them to a
                    standard of how much they have been able to accomplish very quickly, because we
                    know they cannot accomplish too much too quickly in these countries, but a
                    standard of a humanistic approach to the country, to its press, to the free
                    media, to justice, to equal access to the law and stuff like that. If you see
                    these things are in place, the other things will follow. Without these things,
                    there is nothing else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me comment on that. Take a person like Irving Brown,
                        who moved from the European experience, where his opposition was the
                        Communists, to the developing world of Africa, where he could not identify
                        the enemy and could not select friends. There he did a much more
                        sophisticate job in trying to establish trade union leadership. In some
                        cases, he succeeded in encouraging trade union leaders to develop democratic
                        structures. In many other cases, he was unsuccessful to a large degree
                        because of economic constraints.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>ZATINSKY: Irving Brown was not somebody I knew well personally. [He had the] role
                    of almost jet-setting around and attempting to build basically credibly good
                    forces. Sometimes he was fairly successful; other times he did miserably. [He
                    believed] that his own perceptions were better than those of the people on the
                    spot and that he knew more about what a legitimate socialist party is than the
                    Socialist International, which has its committees sifting these things out and
                    investigating them. I don't know! Do the international trade union organizations
                    have some methods? Does the individual free-lancer [like Irving Brown know more
                    about these things?] His half-kidding, half serious title in the labor movement
                    in my day was the “scholar-pumpernickel,” a take-off on the scarlet Pimpernel of
                    old who was supposed to be straightening things out. I'm not taking anything
                    away from him. He was a man of complete dedication. [But take for example] his
                    work with the Baath parties in the Middle East. Now it is true that the Baath
                    parties looked at one time when they were founded as though they were secular
                    social democratic parties. Today they are fascist parties. Saddam Hussein in
                    Iraq and Hafez al-Assad in Syria - they are as close to Middle East fascism as
                    you are going to find. Does that mean that they had to go that way? I don't know
                    the answer to that, and I am not going to undermine Irving Brown's
                    sophistication in making his judgments at the time he made them, because he
                    certainly had as many tools [at his disposal] as any of the people in our
                    Embassies had, if not more. But some place there has to be a process of
                    gathering information, of sifting this stuff out, setting certain standards, and
                    analyzing the thing in a good way. I am sure we do some of it through our
                    Embassy people. We are knowledgeable but not enough of them are
                    knowledgeable</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you. Any other words of wisdom?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ZATINSKY: That's all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you very much, Milt.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
