<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000921">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Christopher H. Phillips </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR CHRISTOPHER H. PHILLIPS</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 12, 1993</p>
                <p>Copyright 2002 ADST</p>
                <p>Q: Could you tell me a bit about your family, where you came from, and about your
                    education. Start with your family and your growing up, and education.</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: My father, William Phillips, was one of the pioneers in helping to
                    establish a career Foreign Service. His own career began in 1902 as private
                    secretary to Ambassador Joseph Choate in London. Subsequently, he was posted to
                    the American Legation in Peking from 1905 until 1907, during the waning days of
                    the Ching Dynasty. The Empress Dowager, Tzu Hsi was, of course, still ruling
                    China at that time. Two years later, he applied for a transfer to Washington,
                    but on reporting to the State Department for a position, discovered there was no
                    appropriate vacancy for him. After some difficulty, a way out of the predicament
                    was found by appointing him to the Messenger Service - the lowest grade of
                    employees in the Department.</p>
                <p>In due course, he was assigned to matters concerned with Far Eastern affairs. A
                    year or two later, he persuaded his seniors to establish a new office to deal
                    with Far Eastern affairs. This resulted in the establishment of the Division of
                    Far Eastern Affairs, of which my father was appointed the first director. He
                    thus became the founding head of what is now the Bureau of East Asian and
                    Pacific Affairs. In 1908 he was named Third Assistant Secretary of State, and
                    during the Wilson administration, was promoted to First Assistant Secretary.
                    After a tour of duty as U.S. Minister to the Netherlands, he returned to
                    Washington in 1922 to assume the post of Under Secretary of State, the number
                    two position in the Department, which was then headed by Secretary Charles Evans
                    Hughes. During the ensuing twenty or more years, my father served as Ambassador
                    to Belgium,1924-1927, as the first American Envoy to, Canada, from 1927 to 1929,
                    as UndeSecretary of State for the second time from, 1933-1936, and as Ambassador
                    to Italy from 1936 to 1941.</p>
                <p>Q: You say that your father was the first U.S. Envoy to Canada. Was that at the
                    time that British Dominions were authorized to establish independent diplomatic
                    relations with other countries?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Yes, that was in 1927 as a result of action taken by thLondon Imperial
                    Conference.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about you then. How did you grow up in this
                        atmosphere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: I think from an early age it did inculcate in me an interest in foreign
                    affairs, and later in life, in political activities. I was born in the American
                    Legation in the Hague, Holland. In later years my parents assured me that since
                    I was born in the Legation residence, I would qualify as a native born American
                    and therefore eligible to be elected President of the United States. That was
                    not exactly the goal of my life, although elective politics did later play a
                    part.</p>
                <p>My earliest memories were of life in the embassy in Brussels where I lived with
                    my parents and my youngest sister for three years. I guess the most vivid of
                    those memories was the arrival of Charles Lindbergh shortly after his
                    transatlantic flight in 1927. After his historic landing in Paris, he visited
                    two or three European capitals, the first being Brussels. My father was away at
                    the time, I believe on consultation in Washington, so at the age of seven I was
                    asked to act as unofficial “charge d'affaires” and to greet Mr. Lindbergh. I
                    remember being stationed at the door of the elevator, and I recall vividly the
                    door opening and this very tall, lean, man in brown leather flying togs,
                    stepping out and accepting my handshake and my welcome to the American Embassy.
                    Shortly thereafter, we left Brussels and moved to Ottawa where my father
                    presented his credentials as the first American Minister to Canada.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were you educated, and what types of subjects
                        interesteyou?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: My schooling began in Ottawa where I went to a small, private boys'
                    school for two years. But as is often the case, being the child of a diplomat, I
                    attended several schools - six in fact. Of those six, the one that had the most
                    lasting impact on my life' was the school from which I graduated to go to
                    Harvard. Avon Old Farms in Avon, Connecticut, was ahead of its time in several
                    respects. For example, there was a program of community service in which every
                    student was required to participate eight hours a week. Its 2000 acres of fields
                    and forest contained both a working dairy farm and a poultry farm in which
                    students could choose to perform their weekly service. The school also had an
                    unusual system of student government which gave students an opportunity to
                    experience the responsibilities of local self government. Officers were elected
                    by secret ballot in elections in which both students and faculty participated. A
                    judicial body could rule up to a recommendation for dismissal from the school. I
                    was elected head of the student government and participated in many other
                    student government activities. I also became active in the Secondary School
                    Society for International Cooperation, a student organization which sponsored
                    meetings and conferences at a number of secondary schools for the purpose of
                    encouraging interest in world affairs.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>Further adding to my growing interest in politics and international affairs, were
                    experiences I had in Washington during Franklin Roosevelt's' first term,
                    Roosevelt had appointed my father his first Under Secretary of State (currently
                    known as the Deputy Secretary) and I had become an ardent Roosevelt enthusiast.
                    My parents had been close friends of the Roosevelt's going back to the Wilson
                    administration when Roosevelt was Assistant Secretary of the Navy and my father,
                    Assistant Secretary of State. My mother was a girlhood friend of Eleanor's and
                    attended her wedding. I well remember, at the impressionable age of 13 or 14, my
                    first visit to the White House. The occasion was a family Christmas party, with
                    only the Roosevelt family, my family and three or four other close friends of
                    the Roosevelts'. The party took place in the East Room, where musicians from the
                    Marine band were assembled to lead us in a program of carol singing. It was a
                    delightfully informal and lively evening, with a good deal of fun and frolic
                    among the children. Experiences such as these further sparked my interest in
                    political life as well as my admiration foRoosevelt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you entered Harvard in 1939, just as World War II
                        started.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: That's right. I found myself among a minority of students who believed
                    that American interests were at stake and that, sooner or later, the U.S. would
                    have to become involved. I became increasingly unhappy with widespread support
                    for a policy of neutrality which prevailed among many students. By the end of my
                    Freshman year, I decided to go west in search of more enlightened views.
                    Montana, where I had spent several summers, and where I had first met the girl
                    who was later to become my wife and the mother of our three children, became my
                    destination. I enrolled as a part time student at Montana State College in
                    Bozeman, and during the summer worked on a nearby ranch. After a year of Montana
                    life, which I greatly enjoyed. I returned to Harvard because, by then, it seemed
                    clear that it was only a matter of time before the U.S. would be drawn into the
                    war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you then complete your studies, or did the American
                        entry intthe war interrupt them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: I was able to complete one more year at Harvard before entering the
                    service. In November, 1942, I enlisted in the U.S. Army Air Corps as a private.
                    I had hoped to be a pilot, but my eyesight was inadequate, and so I was assigned
                    to a non-flying status. Thus began a four year tour of duty with the U.S. Army
                    Air Corps which concluded with an assignment to the military government program
                    for the Far East.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>By that time I had graduated from Officer Candidate School and was proudly
                    wearing my Second Lieutenant bar. I was one of the early participants in the
                    training program for the Far East, which included Korea and Japan. As part of
                    our preparation for the anticipated invasion of Japan, we were put through
                    intensive Japanese language training and area study at Harvard University and at
                    the Presidio of Monterey in California. Thanks to President Truman's historic
                    decision which brought a dramatic end to the war with Japan, all of us who had
                    been preparing for the invasion arrived peacefully in a Japan whose people,
                    surprisingly, seemed to welcome us.</p>
                <p>Japanese Occupation 1945-1946</p>
                <p>I spent a year in Japan on the staff of General MacArthur at his headquarters in
                    the Daichi building in Tokyo. There I was assigned to the Price Control and
                    Rationing Division of the Economic and Scientific Staff Section of SCAP [Supreme
                    Commander for the Allied Powers]. Our job was to establish policies for the
                    distribution of food throughout the country so as to prevent starvation during
                    the difficult first year of the occupation.</p>
                <p>Q: I'd like to go back, since this has pertinence to foreign affairs. What was
                    your impression, I mean here you were a young man on the staff of General
                    MacArthur, obviously way down in the bowels, but what was your impression of
                    MacArthur, and two, how did you feel-what was the atmosphere about dealing with
                    the Japanese and about the relationship to Washington and directions from
                    Washington?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: You're quite right. I was down in the bowels of SCAP, although by that
                    time I had been promoted to the lofty rank of First Lieutenant! This didn't
                    exactly give me day to day access to General MacArthur, but I was able to gain
                    some impressions of his impact on that quite remarkable first year of the
                    occupation. Although, ostensibly guided by directions from Washington, MacArthur
                    exercised a great deal of independent authority. In theory, it was the Far
                    Eastern Advisory Commission, which comprised representatives of all the allied
                    countries, that established general policies for the occupation. In fact, the
                    real authority for issuing policies and directives to SCAP resided in
                    Washington. But MacArthur took a rather imperial view of his role and was not
                    unduly influenced by instructions from Washington or guidance from the Far
                    Eastern Advisory Commission.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the staff around him? Did you get any feel
                        about thstaff and its impact on MacArthur?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: A small group of senior colonels and generals who had been through the
                    war with him exercised the greatest influence - officers such as General
                    Marquette, in charge of the Economic and Scientific Staff Section and General
                    Whitney, who headed up the Government Section. But there were many more junior
                    officers down the line, who from the standpoint of day to day operations, played
                    key roles in implementing SCAP policies. During that first year the staff was
                    almost entirely drawn from our military and naval forces, most of whom had been
                    through the same training programs as had I. We had all participated, to some
                    extent, in the planning operations leading up to the occupation, and were,
                    therefore, well prepared for the tasks that confronted us on our arrival. On the
                    whole it was a smoothly run operation, due in large part to clearly defined
                    policies and MacArthur's extraordinary influence and leadership. We all marveled
                    at how ordinary Japanese seemed to venerate the General. It made one wonder if
                    perhaps they saw in him as a new Imperial being, temporarily replacing the
                    Emperor himself.</p>
                <p>Q: I was wondering, at the time you were there, if one could not have discerned
                    two rather different currents of thinking about occupation policies. On the one
                    hand, New Deal views, though more pragmatic than the earlier days of the
                    Roosevelt presidency, still influenced Washington thinking. At the same time you
                    had a general and his senior officers who generally reflected more conservative
                    views. MacArthur had a lot of autonomy. I would have thought, even in this first
                    year, there would have been some sort of conflict - or did things just sort of
                    click together?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Well you raise a good point. Given these circumstances, one might well
                    have concluded that policy conflicts between Washington and SCAP were
                    inevitable. But in fact things did sort of click together. Of course there were
                    occasional differences of opinion between Washington and SCAP, but overall there
                    were remarkably few. We tend to forget that under MacArthur during the first
                    year of the occupation, some truly radical reforms were introduced into Japan
                    which changed, the whole nature of Japanese society. An example of this was the
                    highly successful land reform program. For many years land tenancy had stood at
                    close to 50 % of the land. As a result of these reforms, absentee ownership of
                    agricultural land was abolished and former tenants were able to buy their land
                    on very favorable terms. At the same time landlords were reimbursed for the
                    property they lost.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you left Japan in 1946 to return to the U.S. What did
                        yothen do?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: I was relieved from active duty just in time to return to Harvard and
                    complete the remaining semester for my degree. With my degree in hand three
                    years late, I began looking for a job. I had a pretty clear idea that I wanted,
                    in due course, to get into politics. I also had a keen interest in foreign
                    affairs and seriously considered the Foreign Service, but I finally decided
                    against that. Bearing in mind my father's very distinguished diplomatic career,
                    I couldn't help feeling that I would face a “no win” situation. If I entered the
                    Foreign Service and did well, it would be said that of course my father's
                    reputation had a lot to do with it. If I did not succeed, there would be
                    invidious comparisons. So I concluded that the best thing to do would be to
                    pursue a political career. The big question was how and when. I was then 27
                    years old, happily married to my Montana bride and the proud father of a
                    two-year old daughter. As luck would have it, the editor of our local daily
                    newspaper had a vacancy for a cub reporter. He offered me the job which I
                    accepted with alacrity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In what town was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Beverly, Massachusetts, which had been the home of my parents and
                    grandparents for some 65 years. Covering City Hall was part of my “beat” for the
                    Beverly Evening Times. In due course, I came to know most of the City Hall
                    officials, including the Mayor with whom I frequently discussed local politics.
                    One day, out of the blue, the Mayor suggested that I consider running for the
                    State Senate. This was a tempting suggestion, but I reminded him that either one
                    of our two State Representatives, both Republicans, might have similar
                    aspirations. Since the incumbent Senator was also a Republican and was well
                    known throughout the District, this could turn out to be a difficult primary
                    election campaign. The Mayor told me he had good reason to believe that neither
                    Representative would be interested, and that therefore I would probably be the
                    only contender. I promised the Mayor to give the matter serious
                    consideration.</p>
                <p>As I later weighed the pros and cons, I realized that the reason I might be the
                    only contender, was that no one else thought the incumbent could be beaten.
                    Being young, and full of self confidence, I convinced myself that I could do so.
                    A few weeks later, I announced my candidacy for the Senate, and immediately
                    began the task of organizing a Districtwide campaign committee. In this effort I
                    was greatly assisted by the help of a group of Beverly residents with whom I had
                    been associated in establishing a local chapter of the United World Federalists.
                    This was an organization which grew out of the experience of the second world
                    war. Many thoughtful and sincere people had become convinced that only a system
                    of limited but enforceable world law could prevent the repetition of such a
                    catastrophe.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>Unrealistic though that dream was in retrospect, it did attract a small but
                    significant national following. As I look back, it seems quite extraordinary
                    that participation in such an organization could have been helpful in winning a
                    State Senate seat. But I think the enthusiasm and loyalty of my UWF fellow
                    members had a lot to do with my success. In any case, after a year of non-stop
                    campaigning, I won the Primary election, and in the ensuing 1948 Presidential
                    election, I defeated my Democratic opponent, thus becoming the youngest
                    Massachusetts State Senator elected up to that time.</p>
                <p>Massachusetts State Senate 1948-1953</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And how long did you serve in the State Senate and what
                        were youparticular legislative interests?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: I was elected to three terms, but as I will explain later, I resigned
                    in the middle of my third term. Those five years were full of interest and
                    challenge. As I look back on them, I realize how invaluable that political and
                    legislative experience was to be in my later years of public service. There were
                    two key legislative issues with which I was very much involved. The first dealt
                    with the use of injunctions in labor disputes. As Chairman of the joint
                    committee on labor and industry, it was my responsibility to try to draft
                    legislation which could pass both Houses of the Legislature, the Senate then
                    being Republican and the House, Democratic. The Democratic Governor, Paul Dever,
                    had proposed legislation that was primarily responsive to labor interests. He
                    apparently thought he could count on the support of two or three liberal
                    Republicans in the Senate, myself included. After consulting with my Republican
                    colleagues, I made a statement on the Senate floor declaring, that though I
                    supported the Governor's objectives, his proposals were unacceptable to us.
                    However, I promised that I would introduce a more acceptable bill the following
                    year. This did not greatly please the Governor or the Senate Democrats, but
                    without our votes the legislation could not be enacted.</p>
                <p>Following adjournment of the Legislature that year I began to focus on the
                    problem of drafting a more balanced anti-injunction bill that would take into
                    account the interests of both labor and management. Knowing very little about
                    the intricacies of labor law, I sought advice from several people. One of them
                    said to me, “There's a young Professor at thHarvard Law School by the name of
                    Archibald Cox who has considerable expertise in such matters. Perhaps he would
                    be willing to work with you.” I called Mr. Cox and he agreed. During the next
                    few months we worked together, I on the political aspects, and he on drafting
                    the legislation. Our efforts bore fruit, and a year later the Cox-Phillips
                    Anti-Injunction Law was enacted. Later, I used to say, with tongue in cheek,
                    that I launched Archibald Cox on his distinguished career. You will recall that
                    he later became Solicitor General of the United States, and Special Prosecutor
                    during the Watergate period.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And what was the second issue that was of special interest
                        to you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: That related to efforts to reserve a Massachusetts television channel
                    for educational purposes. I was appointed Chairman of the Public Commission on
                    Educational Television. This bipartisan Commission included legislators from
                    both Houses, as well as several public members appointed by the Governor. One
                    T.V. channel was then up for grabs, and our task was to build public support for
                    a non-commercial educational channel and to persuade the FCC of its feasibility.
                    At the time, two of the State's major newspapers were working overtime to have
                    the channel assigned for commercial TV use. With the support of then Governor
                    Christian Herter, we obtained a modest appropriation which enabled us to
                    undertake the necessary legal and engineering work. I and several of my
                    colleagues campaigned up and down the State, trying to build support and public
                    interest for educational TV. The Commission's efforts were fruitful and we were
                    able to make a persuasive case to thFCC [Federal Communications Commission]. To
                    make a long story short, a year or so later, FCC approval was finally granted.
                    Thus was born WGBH, Channel 2 in Boston which, subsequently became the
                    grandfather of public television in the U.S.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said that you resigned from the State Senate in the
                        middle oyour third term. Why was that, and where did you go from there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: By 195I had become very active in the Massachusetts Eisenhower for
                    President Committee, of which my Father and Governor Herter were co-chairmen and
                    Chris Herter Jr. and I, co-vice chairmen. I also organized the first slate of
                    delegates pledged to Eisenhower. Opposing us in the Presidential Primary
                    election that Spring, was a slate pledged to Senator Taft. We conducted a lively
                    campaign up and down Essex County, stressing foreign policy differences between
                    the two candidates. We believed that Ike was a man of the world highly respected
                    in other countries, who understood the importance of American leadership in the
                    post -war world. Taft, on the other hand reflected a more isolationist view of
                    America's role similar, in some respects, to the earlier America First Movement.
                    Our slate won handily, and a few months later found me in Chicago as Secretary
                    of the Delegation.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you find that foreign policy played much of a role when it really got down
                    to the nitty-gritty of politics when you were at the convention?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: No, certainly at the convention it did not. And the Eisenhower people,
                    as well as many of the Taft supporters, did not want to have a major party
                    rupture over foreign policy differences. Of course in his acceptance speech,
                    Eisenhower did set forth in general terms his views on foreign policy, but
                    during most of the convention, discussions were focused on domestic issues and
                    convention politics. For me, the whole experience was fascinating - a kind of
                    case study of how the American presidential electoral system works.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>My decision to leave the Senate before the completion of my third term, was a
                    difficult one. A few months after Eisenhower's inauguration, I was invited to
                    come to Washington to take a position in the State Department. I was torn,
                    because here was an opportunity to engage in the conduct of U.S. foreign policy,
                    something I had long wished to do. On the other hand, I was very conscious of my
                    responsibilities to the people who had reelected me to a third term. As a
                    Republican member of the Senate, I could also be severely criticized if my
                    resignation resulted in the election of a Democratic successor. However on that
                    score, I felt quite confident that this would not happen. One of my very close
                    friends from Beverly, Henry Glovsky, who was then serving as a State
                    Representative would, I knew, run for the seat, and there was little doubt that
                    he would be elected with the full support of my campaign organization. This in
                    fact did happen in a special election later that year. And so after carefully
                    weighing the pros and cons, I decided to take the plunge. A few months later my
                    wife and I and our two small children had settled into a rented house in
                    Washington, and I was beginning to learn the State Department ropes, as Special
                    Assistant to Robert Murphy, the Assistant Secretary for United Nations Affairs.
                    Murphy had only recently returned to Washington from Tokyo where he had served
                    as Ambassador for the previous two years. A few months after my arrival, Murphy
                    moved up to the position oDeputy Under Secretary for Political Affairs. A year
                    or so later, I was named Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for International
                    Organization Affairs.</p>
                <p>State Department 1953-1957</p>
                <p>Q: Before we go on, could you give me your impressions of Robert Murphy, what he
                    was like, his style of operation, and so forth?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Well, I remember him as a very attractive person with a good sense of
                    humor, but with strongly held convictions about which he could be very
                    forthright. But behind his Irish charm, was a toughness and intelligence which
                    stood him particularly well during his wartime years iFrench North Africa as
                    President Roosevelt's Personal Representative. Unlike many in the Foreign
                    Service, Murphy was a skillful politician, in a nonpejorative sense. He was
                    politically astute and equally at ease with both foreign and domestic political
                    leaders.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were some of the subjects you were handling at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: On my first day at the office I found, waiting for me on my desk, an
                    enormous stack of documents and a brief memo suggesting that these should be
                    helpful in bringing me up to date on arms control matters. For a recently
                    retired State Senator, this constituted a bit of a challenge. There are few more
                    complex issues than arms control negotiations. Fortunately, this was not to be
                    my major assignment. During a later assignment at the UN, I did play a small
                    role in the negotiations over the Eisenhower Atoms for Peace proposal, which
                    eventually led to the creation of the International Atomic Energy Agency. But
                    during most of my four years as a Deputy Assistant Secretary in the Bureau of
                    International Affairs, I focused mainly on the economic and social programs of
                    the UN.</p>
                <p>This was a period that saw the admission of an increasing number of smaller, less
                    developed countries which looked to the UN for aid and technical assistance in
                    the development of their economies. They pushed for the creation of a Special UN
                    Fund for Economic Development to which the wealthier countries would be expected
                    to contribute. This was opposed by most of the industrialized countries of the
                    west who argued that the World Bank was the appropriate institution for
                    investment projects. We knew that our Congress would never agree to a plan by
                    which the wealthy nations would provide the funds, but have little to say about
                    their use. We were, however, mindful of the feelings of a number of Latin
                    American countries which favored the creation of some kind of UN development
                    program. In an effort to find an acceptable compromise, we took the lead in
                    negotiations which eventually led to the creation of the United Nations Special
                    Fund. Under the leadership of Paul Hoffman, its first Managing Director, the
                    Fund became the principal operating arm of the United Nations in the developing
                    world. It focused on pre-investment projects designed to create conditions in
                    less developed countries that would facilitate both domestic and foreign
                    investment. Over the years, it has proven to be one of the UN's most successful
                    programs. In 1966 it merged with the Expanded Program of Technical Assistance
                    and became known as the UN Development Program [UNDP].</p>
                <p>During my last two or three years, in the Department, we also had to deal with
                    three major political crises: 1. the 1956 Hungarian uprising, which resulted in
                    the exodus of thousands of Hungarian refugees into neighboring Austria. The UN
                    High Commissioner for Refugees, on whose Executive Committee I served as the
                    American member, was instrumental in mobilizing international support for the
                    care and feeding of these refugees; 2. the Suez crisis resulting from Egypt's
                    nationalization of the canal, and the subsequent invasion of Egypt by Israeli,
                    French and British forces; 3. the Congo crisis which led to the introduction of
                    the first ever, UN peacekeeping force of some 18000 blue-helmeted troops. The UN
                    was deeply involved in each of these crises, and our Bureau was kept busy
                    back-stopping the operations of our Mission in New York. It was a challenging
                    and exciting time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were with Robert Murphy to begin with, and then when
                        he moveon you eventually moved to - what was next?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: I continued as Deputy Assistant Secretary for four years, during which
                    time I served under two Assistant Secretaries. The first, David Key, a senior
                    career Foreign Service officer who served only about one year, and the second,
                    Francis Wilcox, former Chief of Staff of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee
                    and a close friend of John Foster Dulles. I became very fond of Francis and
                    benefitted greatly from his extensive knowledge of foreign affairs. He had the
                    full confidence of both Secretary Dulles and Ambassador Henry Cabot Lodge, our
                    Representative to the United Nations.</p>
                <p>Q: What about the dynamics of the State Department? Did matters concern you, say,
                    with the Far East? Walter Robinson was head of the Far Eastern Affairs Bureau at
                    that time, and in a way represented the very conservative wing of the Republican
                    Party. He was a strong supporter of Chiang Kai-shek, was he not?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Oh, yes, Walter Robinson played a key role in all matters relating to
                    China. His overriding concern was to keep the Chinese communists out of the UN.
                    In this he had the full support of Dulles, who, no doubt, was not unmindful of
                    McCarthy's vitriolic attacks against anyone suspected of being “soft on
                    communism.” No position paper which remotely concerned the China question, could
                    be sent to our Mission in New York without Robinson's initials. Each year as we
                    undertook the major lobbying campaign on the so-calleChina credentials issue,
                    one or more of Robinson's officers were on hand to make sure that no stone was
                    left unturned to keep the Republic of China's seat in the UN.</p>
                <p>For another decade these efforts were successful. But most of us dealing with UN
                    affairs, became increasingly skeptical about this annual exercise which involved
                    such an expenditure of political capital. Little by little the margin of support
                    for our resolution diminished and many of us saw the handwriting on the wall.
                    During my second tour of duty at the UN a few years later, I participated in our
                    final and unsuccessful effort to maintain Taiwan's seat as the legal government
                    of all of China.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At this period did McCarthyism hit you, or was that pretty
                        weldead by that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: McCarthyism still hung like a heavy cloud over the Department,
                    particularly for Foreign Service people. I recall, for example, one of the
                    career people in my Bureau, who was probably the Department's outstanding expert
                    on UN economic and social affairs. He had helped draft papers at the Dumbarton
                    Oaks Conference on the UN Charter, and later participated as a member of our
                    delegation to the San Francisco Conference. Walter Kotschnig was born in Austria
                    of Austrian parents. Unfortunately for him, he still spoke with an Austrian
                    accent. To make matters worse, from the standpoint of the McCarthyites in the
                    Department, he had once been a professor at Smith College. That was quite enough
                    to bring him under the suspicion of the Department's Bureau of Security Affairs,
                    then headed by one Scott McLeod, widely regarded as the State Department agent
                    for Senators McCarthy and Styles Bridges of New Hampshire. Time and again, we
                    would include Kotschnig's name in a delegation to a UN meeting at which his
                    expertise could have been invaluable, only to be informed, at the last minute,
                    that his security clearances were not yet complete. It became clear to me that
                    Security had no evidence against Kotschnig on which to base security charges,
                    but they didn't want to clear him. The game was to keep him in perpetual limbo
                    by simply not acting on his security clearance. I finally lost my patience and
                    went up to meet with McLeod. I told him that his Bureau's refusal to either
                    approve or disapprove Kotschnig's clearance was unacceptable. I said, in effect,
                    if you have negative information about him, then tell me. You have an obligation
                    to do so. If you don't, then clear him. This apparently, had some effect,
                    because a week or two later, Kotschnig's clearance was finally granted.</p>
                <p>When he retired in 1971, Walter Kotschnig received the State Department's
                    “Distinguished Honor Award” conferred upon him by Secretary of State William
                    Rogers.</p>
                <p>Q: I believe in 1957 or 1958, you left the Department of State to begin what
                    seemed to be a shift back to domestic affairs. How did that come about?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Yes, in 1957 I began to think about returning to elective politics.
                    Realizing that in the position I then held, I could not engage in political
                    activities, I began making inquiries about a possible Presidential appointment
                    which would release me from the restrictions of the Hatch Act. In due course I
                    received word from the White House that a vacancy existed on the three-member
                    U.S. Civil Service Commission - would I be interested in serving as Vice
                    Chairman of the Commission? The prospect had some appeal to me, not merely
                    because it was a Presidential appointment, but because it dealt with
                    government-wide personnel policies and programs. As Chairman of the Committee on
                    Labor and Industries in the Massachusetts Senate, I had been dealing with
                    similar issues on a State-wide scale. After giving the matter some thought, I
                    accepted the offer. By year's end, I found myself ensconced in a huge office in
                    what was once the Government Patent Office. During the ensuing months, I
                    traveled throughout the country visiting all the regional offices of the
                    Commission and gaining a firsthand impression of the variety and scope of
                    Federal operations nationwide.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Less than a year later, a sudden and quite unexpected turn of events found me
                    back in the world of diplomacy. One day I received a call from Cabot Lodge in
                    New York asking me to come to the U.S. Mission to the UN to serve as our
                    Representative on the UN Economic and Social Council. I said I greatly
                    appreciated the honor but I thought it would be wrong for me leave the Civil
                    Service Commission to which the President had so recently appointed me.
                    Furthermore, I was not keen to move to New York having only just purchased a
                    house in which we had expected to be living for at least the following four
                    years. Cabot's response was characteristically to the point. “If the President
                    decides that it's more important to have you here than at the Civil Service
                    Commission, you should do as he wishes.” That was a pretty clear hint to me that
                    Lodge had already cleared the appointment with the White House. He asked me to
                    think a bit more about this, and said he would be in touch with me again soon. I
                    then discussed the matter with my wife, Mabel on whom the burden of pulling up
                    stakes in Washington and moving to New York with our two young daughters and our
                    six months old son, would most heavily fall. She decided that this was an
                    opportunity we should not turn down. A week later when Lodge called. I agreed to
                    accept the appointment.</p>
                <p>Q: How long did you hold this position and what were your responsibilities as the
                    U.S. Representative on the Economic and Social Council?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: I stayed with the U.S. Mission to the U.N. until shortly after the
                    beginning of the Kennedy Administration. An amusing incident occurred soon after
                    I arrived in New York. To my great surprise, I received an invitation from
                    Eleanor Roosevelt to have dinner with her in her apartment. I was very pleased,
                    of course, since I hadn't seen her for many years and I looked forward to
                    discussing with her some of the human rights and social issues in which she
                    played such a key role during the early days of the UN. She greeted me warmly,
                    saying how glad she was to see me at the UN. “But” she added, “I have one
                    question to ask you which puzzles me. I see that you are serving in a Republican
                    administration, but I remember you as a boy being a rather enthusiastic
                    Democrat.” “Well,” I replied, “you see I come from Massachusetts where being
                    neither Catholic, Irish nor Italian is a bit of a handicap in getting nominated
                    for anything in the Democratic party. I also noted that the Republican party in
                    Massachusetts, at that time, was considered to be more progressive than the
                    Democratic party. She smiled and said, “You're right Chris, I forgive you.”</p>
                <p>There were two other people at the dinner that night, Mr. and Mrs. Joseph Lash,
                    whom I had not previously met. He was United Nations correspondent for the New
                    York Post, and for many years had been a close friend and political associate of
                    Mrs. Roosevelt. A few years later, afteMrs. Roosevelt died, I received a call
                    from Lash, telling me that he was about to write a biography of the Roosevelts.
                    Mrs. Roosevelt had told him that she thought my mother's journals, kept over a
                    period of 60 years, might provide some insights into Mrs. Roosevelt's earlier
                    life. The two had been close friends as young women. And so, with the help of my
                    father, who had survived my mother by three years, we searched through many of
                    the more than 50 journals and discovered a number of interesting anecdotes and
                    incidents involving both Eleanor and Franklin.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>These were later incorporated in Lash's book, “Eleanor and FrankliRoosevelt”
                    published in 1971.</p>
                <p>UN Economic and Social Council 1958-1961Q: Let's talk a bit about your
                    experiences during those three years in New York. Was your position an
                    Ambassadorial appointment?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: No, although it was an Ambassadorial level position which required
                    Senate confirmation, Lodge decided that two Ambassadors, himself and his Deputy,
                    James Wadsworth, were quite enough. In subsequent years, however, the
                    ECOSORepresentative was accorded the rank of Ambassador. My responsibilities as
                    the U.S. Representative on the Economic and Social Council included supervision
                    of the Mission's economic and social affairs staff and participation in all
                    meetings of the Council and in some of its subsidiary bodies, such as the four
                    regional economic commissions. Those commissions were established by the ECOSOC
                    to deal with regional economic and social problems in Europe, Asia, Latin
                    America and Africa The idea was to relieve ECOSOC and the General Assembly of
                    the necessity to deal with matters primarily regional in character. In 1959 I
                    chaired our delegation to a session of the Economic Commission for Asia and the
                    Far East which was held in Broadbeach, Australia, or what is known as the Gold
                    Coast. It was an interesting time to be in Australia. Shortly before the
                    Commission's meetings began, Australia had severed diplomatic relations with the
                    Soviet Union over an alleged spying incident involving Soviet agents. As it
                    turned out, the Commission's meeting provided a good cover for private talks
                    between the Australian Foreign Minister, Lord Casey and the head of the Soviet
                    delegation, Deputy Foreign Minister, Nikolai Firubin. The talks were apparently
                    successful because a short time thereafter, diplomatic relations were
                    resumed.</p>
                <p>I often wondered whether the sandy beaches and the salubrious climate of the Gold
                    Coast may not have contributed to the success. Certainly, the Russians who had
                    come all the way from Moscow's frigid, February weather, were happy to take full
                    advantage of any out-of-doors recreational opportunities. Occasionally, when I
                    went to the beach for an early swim, I encountered members of their delegation
                    approaching the beach in single file behind their leader. Only when they reached
                    the water's edge, did the formation break up and the swimming begin.</p>
                <p>In those days, the Council was a relatively small body with a total membership of
                    only 18. Its membership today is 54 and, in my opinion, it has become a less
                    effective and more unwieldy organization. The U.S. during those earlier years
                    could count on the support of the three or four Latin Americans as well as most
                    of the Europeans. Our influence, therefore, was considerably greater, and the
                    work of the Council, more efficient and more productive than it is today.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>One of the problems which faced, and continues to face ECOSOC, is the role
                    assigned to it by the Charter, to coordinate the activities of the 10 or 12
                    Specialized Agencies. These include such organizations as the World Health
                    Organization, the Food and Agriculture Organization and UNESCO. The trouble is
                    that the Specialized Agencies are relatively autonomous bodies. ECOSOC has no
                    control over their budgets and therefore little leverage in controlling their
                    programs or expenditures. Furthermore, their independent governing bodies tended
                    to reflect the special interests of their national constituencies, which were
                    not necessarily consistent with the policies of member governments concerning
                    the allocation of resources to various UN programs.</p>
                <p>The situation was improved somewhat, by the establishment of the UN Development
                    Program in 1966. Funded by voluntary contributions from member governments, it
                    operates on the basis of country priorities and programs established in
                    consultation with recipient countries. When funds for a country program have
                    been approved by the UNDP Governing Council, the program is carried out by those
                    Specialized Agencies which have the appropriate expertise to implement the
                    program. Thus, they became, in a sense, subcontractors for UNDP. This provided
                    some degree of control over the activities of the Specialized Agencies, thus
                    assuring better utilization of their resources and more coordinated programs at
                    the country level.</p>
                <p>Q: Cabot Lodge - both of you came out of Massachusetts politics, and you say you
                    knew him quite well. How did he operate at the UN and how effective was he?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: During Lodge's tour at the UN we were, of course, still under the
                    influence of McCarthyism, and the United Nations was under attack for being
                    hostile to American interests. Cabot Lodge was very effective in countering
                    those charges. In speaking to audiences around the country, he argued that when
                    U.S. interests are best served by working through the UN, we should do so. On
                    the other hand, there were occasions when our national interests are best served
                    by working outside the UN. In this way Lodge tried to introduce a more balanced
                    approach to the UN and put to rest some of the fears held by those who believed
                    the UN was a threat to our national sovereignty.</p>
                <p>As the U.S. Representative to the UN, Lodge had his strengths and weaknesses. His
                    years in the Senate had prepared him well for the job. He was a skillful
                    politician, articulate and effective in gaining support for U.S. positions.
                    This, of course, was somewhat easier in those days when the membership was about
                    half of today's, and we could usually count on the support of most of the 21
                    American republics. However, there were those at the UN who were privately
                    critical of what they considered to be Lodge's arrogance. Within the U.S.
                    Mission some of the staff found him too quick to make judgments, and not always
                    willing to listen to opposing views.</p>
                <p>Chase Manhattan Bank 1961-1965</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a gap in your official career between 1961 and
                        1969.What did you do in the interim?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Well, as a political appointee of the outgoing Administration I had
                    expected to be replaced by an appointee of the new Administration. That in fact,
                    was the case. During the next four years, I worked for the Chase Manhattan Bank
                    in New York. It had never occurred to me to become a banker, but thanks to David
                    Rockefeller, then President of Chase, I accepted a rather unusual offer. One
                    day, a few months after my departure from the Mission, David invited me to pay
                    him a visit at the bank. During the course of our conversation, he spoke to me
                    of his interest in strengthening the bank's relations with the United Nations
                    and its various Specialized Agencies. He explained that until becoming
                    President, he had taken a personal interest in these matters, but since becoming
                    President, he could no longer devote the time and effort necessary to develop
                    those relations. Would I be interested, he asked, in becoming the Bank's
                    representative for UN affairs? The job, he explained, would entail developing
                    the bank's business relations with the UN and its agencies and keeping in touch
                    with various UN activities and programs which could be of interest to the bank.
                    Additionally, he hoped that I would report periodically on any developments
                    which might impact on the bank's overseas operations. Needless to say, I had
                    little hesitation in accepting what seemed to me a tailor-made job.</p>
                <p>Over the next four years I made twice a year visits to the European- baseUN
                    agencies and to meetings of the Economic Commission for Africa. I met with key
                    secretariat officials and, in some cases, with the Secretaries-General of the
                    organizations, many of whom were well known to me from my ECOSOC days. A year or
                    so before leaving Chase, I was appointeAssistant Vice President for Canadian
                    affairs, in addition to my UN responsibilities. In short, the transition from
                    official to private life was, for me a relatively easy one. Those years with the
                    bank were useful in giving me a broader appreciation of the impact of
                    international trade and finance on relations between nations.</p>
                <p>International Chamber of Commerce 1965-1969</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And so that brings us up to 1965 when I believe you left
                        the ban- what then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: One day, during a summer vacation, I received a long distance call from
                    a colleague who had served with me in the Eisenhower administration. Philip
                    Young, former Chairman of the U.S. Civil Service Commission and later,
                    ambassador to the Netherlands, was then President of the U.S. Council of the
                    International Chamber of Commerce. He was a close friend of Arthur K. Watson
                    oIBM who, at the time, was chairman of the Council Board. Phil told me that he
                    intended to retire as President and had promised Watson that before doing so, he
                    would recommend a successor. Would I be interested? Before giving him my reply,
                    he suggested that I meet with him in his Cooperstown, New York, home after my
                    return. I did so, and following a later meeting with Arthur Watson, I accepted
                    the offer.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>The ICC, as it's called, was founded in 1919 by a group of prominent European and
                    American business leaders, including Thomas Watson of IBM. Its purpose was to
                    work for the freest possible flow of goods, services and capital between
                    countries. The ICC is not a typical national chamber of commerce. Essentially,
                    it's a federation of national business councils or committees, each of which
                    works to promote national policies consistent with the purposes of the
                    organization. It also provides a forum from which the international business
                    community as a whole can examine the whole range of world trade issues. A
                    headquarters with an international secretariat is maintained in Paris, and a
                    number of standing international commissions meet regularly to develop
                    recommendations to governments and intergovernmental organizations. In brief, I
                    worked for a kind of businessmen's United Nations. There were frequent trips to
                    Paris for meetings of the international board of directors, and periodic
                    Assemblies of the entire membership, (some 45 national councils at that time)
                    two of which I attended in Japan and Canada.</p>
                <p>My four years with the ICC were an invaluable experience and seemed to constitute
                    a natural progression from my ECOSOC and bank work. I was now seeing the
                    international economic scene through the eyes of world business leaders who were
                    opposed to protectionism and supportive of liberal trade policies, both of which
                    I strongly approved.</p>
                <p>In 1969, I found myself once again on the move. Shortly after the 1968
                    Presidential elections, I received a call from former Ambassador Charles Yost
                    who was then working on a book at the Council on Foreign Relations. Charlie,
                    whom I had first met when he was Ambassador to Morocco, had recently resigned
                    from government after a long and distinguished career in the Foreign Service.
                    During the election campaign he had served as head of Hubert Humphrey's Task
                    Force on the United Nations. Despite this, he was asked by Richard Nixon to
                    become the U.S. Representative to the United Nations. Clearly, this was an
                    effort by Nixon to project a spirit of bipartisanship in the conduct of foreign
                    affairs. Charlie had not only Democratic credentials, but he had also served as
                    a Deputy to Adlai Stevenson at the UN. His call to me was quite unexpected since
                    I had not seen him for some time. Would I be interested, he asked, in coming
                    back to the UN as Deputy Representative on the Security Council? I assured him
                    that I would be happy to, but I doubted that the White House would approve me
                    for a Presidential appointment because of my participation in the Nelson
                    Rockefeller Presidential Primary campaign. Yost's response was, “leave that to
                    me.” He was obviously persuasive because, a month or two later, I received word
                    that the White House had approved my appointment. Soon thereafter I found myself
                    back at the U.S. Mission in its imposing new building just across the street
                    from the UN. Thus began my second tour of duty at the UN which lasted for almost
                    four years.</p>
                <p>Deputy Permanent Representative to the UN 1969-1973</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>After a year's service as Deputy Representative on the Security Council, I was
                    appointed Deputy Permanent Representative to the UN with the rank of Ambassador
                    Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary. My service with Charlie Yost was cut short by
                    the quite unexpected decision of Nixon to request Yost's resignation. The reason
                    for this action was never disclosed to Yost, nor did the President ever
                    personally discuss the matter with him. To many of us it seemed shabby treatment
                    to accord such an able and distinguished member of the Foreign Service. It was a
                    humiliating experience for Yost and a shock to the Mission staff. For a brief
                    time thereafter I was Charge d'affaires, pending the arrival of the new
                    Representative. Sometime in December, 1970, I received a call from George Bush
                    whom I knew only by name as a former Congressman from Texas. I had known his
                    sister, Nancy Ellis, slightly and had been an admirer of his father, Senator
                    Prescott Bush. Bush told me that the President had just announced his
                    appointment as the new Representative to the UN. He said that he had heard good
                    reports about me, and asked if I would be interested in staying on with him. I
                    said I would be happy to do so. For the next two years we worked together
                    closely and established a warm and friendly relationship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why don't we talk about the whole four years you were
                        there. Whawere the major issues you were dealing with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Well of course as Deputy Permanent Representative, I was in effect,
                    Bush's alter ego. In his absence, or when he was otherwise occupied, I took his
                    place in Security Council meetings and in the meetings of other bodies and
                    committees. However, I also had primary responsibility for several ongoing
                    programs, including the UN Seabeds Committee, plenary meetings of the Economic
                    Commission for Europe, and problems relating to our responsibilities as the host
                    country. The latter dealt with such mundane problems as diplomatic parking
                    violations, the failure of some diplomats to meet their financial obligations or
                    to pay their rents. We, on the other hand, were frequently criticized for
                    failing to provide adequate protection for Missions and Mission personnel. The
                    Soviets in particular, and sometimes for good reason, complained bitterly about
                    harassment and threats against their Mission. Such problems and many more were
                    aired and debated in the Committee on Host Country Relations, and they occupied
                    the full time attention of a small section of our staff. One of our biggest
                    headaches was the handling of diplomatic parking tickets. Diplomats complained
                    frequently about the lack of parking spaces and city officials fumed over what
                    they considered abuse of diplomatic privileges. Unfortunately both sides were,
                    to some extent, justified in their complaints.</p>
                <p>I think from the standpoint of substance, my work as chairman of our delegation
                    to the UN Seabeds committee was the most challenging. This 42-member committee
                    had been established by the General Assembly a year or so prior to my arrival.
                    Its purpose was to try to negotiate a set of principles regarding the use of the
                    seabeds beyond the limits of national jurisdiction. This involved a complex
                    series of issues including fishing, exploitation of mineral resources on the
                    seabed, navigational concerns, national security considerations, pollution
                    problems, and scientific research.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>In order to achieve those objectives, it was essential that the benefits which
                    came from mining seabed mineral resources be shared equitably among all States.
                    Otherwise, the main beneficiaries would be the advanced industrial states. This
                    led to the conclusion that an International Seabed area, beginning beyond the
                    600 foot depth line, should be considered the common heritage of all mankind.
                    Initially, we were instructed to oppose this formulation, presumably because of
                    concerns of American mining and petroleum companies. It soon became apparent
                    that we were pretty well isolated on this issue. I urged Washington to
                    reconsider our position but got little support. Finally, I turned to my fellow
                    Massachusetts friend, Elliott Richardson, who was then Under Secretary of State
                    and asked for his help. Not long thereafter, instructions came through
                    authorizing us to support the common heritage principle for a treaty that would
                    renounce national claims to seabed resources beyond the 600 foot depth line.
                    Resources beyond that line would be available for exploitation by all nations.
                    Our changed position broke what otherwise would have deadlocked the committee's
                    work. In December 1970, the committee adopted a declaration of principles
                    governing the seabed and the ocean floor beyond the limits of national
                    jurisdiction. The declaration represented a major breakthrough, and paved the
                    way for a plenipotentiary conference on the “Law of the Sea,” to begin in 1973.
                    The Seabeds Committee was thereafter converted into a preparatory committee for
                    the Plenipotentiary conference and I stepped down as chairman. I was succeeded
                    by Jack Stevenson, a distinguished New York attorney who had served as State
                    Department Legal Advisor. In 1977 Elliott Richardson became Chairman of our
                    delegation to the Plenipotentiary conference. But despite enormous efforts by
                    Elliott and his delegation, the U.S. was one of the very few members which did
                    not sign the Convention when it was opened for ratification in 1982. Although
                    some 10 years later the Clinton Administration did submit the Convention to the
                    Senate for ratification, the Foreign Relations Committee under the Chairmanship
                    of Senator Jesse Helms, refused to act on it.</p>
                <p>In addition to my duties on the Seabeds committee, I also served as the U.S.
                    representative on the UN Economic Commission for Europe which met periodically
                    in both New York and Geneva. This, of course, was during the period of strained
                    relations between East and West. The Soviets and the eastern bloc countries
                    pushed hard for the admission of East Germany which we initially opposed.
                    Eventually, however, a compromise was reached and the German Democratic Republic
                    was admitted as a full member. Personally, I felt that this made a good deal of
                    sense. The ECE was not primarily a political body. Its membership included all
                    the countries of Europe plus the U.S. It focused on economic problems and served
                    as a bridge between East and West in fostering regional cooperation. The
                    Commission was fortunate to have as its Executive Director, Janos Stavnovnik of
                    Yugoslavia, a distinguished economist, who had the trust and confidence of both
                    East and West. I found him very helpful in devising compromises on controversial
                    issues that were acceptable to both sides.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>Another major issue for us, which had high political stakes, was the question of
                    the admission of the People's Republic of China to the UN. For years the U.S.
                    had succeeded in blocking a vote on the issue by proposing a procedural
                    resolution to defer consideration of the matter. This required only a simple
                    majority vote. By the late '60s support for this resolution was steadily
                    eroding, and it was clear to many of us at the Mission that time was running out
                    and that we would soon be faced with a direct vote on the admission of Peking
                    and the expulsion of Nationalist China. By 1970, the U.S. for the first time,
                    hinted that it might be moving in the direction of a two China arrangement. This
                    “hint” was contained in a speech I gave on November 12, 1970, before the General
                    Assembly. It was interpreted by the New York Times and other newspapers as an
                    easing of our stand against the admission of the PRC. The speech, of course, was
                    carefully drafted by the State Department and approved by the White House. For
                    the first time, we had a few positive things to say about the Chinese people,
                    paying tribute to thei“industry, talents and achievements.” More significantly,
                    we said that the U.S. would like to see the PRC play a constructive role in the
                    family of nations. The press picked this up as the beginning of a shift from a
                    policy of all out opposition to Peking's admission to the UN, to one of
                    opposition to the expulsion of Taiwan. To this end, we sponsored a resolution
                    providing that any vote to change the representation of China would be an
                    “Important Question” requiring a two-thirds vote.</p>
                <p>But the decisive battle over the Chinese representation issue did not occur until
                    the next session of the General Assembly in 1971. By then, it had become clear
                    that we could no longer hold the line. In an effort to stem growing support for
                    the admission of the PRC and the expulsion of the Republic of China, we adopted
                    what we called a policy of dual representation. This was in fact a two-China
                    policy. Both the PRC anTaiwan would be seated in the General Assembly, but the
                    PRC would occupy China's permanent seat in the Security Council. For several
                    months beforthe opening of the General Assembly, we lobbied extensively to line
                    up our votes. Ambassador Bush, myself and Ambassador Tapley Bennett directed
                    regional task forces in which virtually all the Mission staff participated. We
                    kept a running nose count, and although at times the outlook was not
                    encouraging, we believed that if all our promised votes held, we could succeed.
                    But what we had not anticipated was the totally unexpected news, announced by
                    the President on July 15, that Henry Kissinger had just returned from Beijing.
                    Bush had been given no advance notice about the trip from the President, and
                    Secretary of State Bill Rogers, was only informed on the eve of Kissinger's
                    departure. It had become clear to all the world that the U.S. was moving toward
                    a policy of accommodation with China. From that moment on,we began to lose
                    momentum. Votes in favor that had appeared to be solid, became abstentions, and
                    abstentions frequently turned to “no” votes. The news, three months later, that
                    Kissinger was back in Beijing, on a well publicized mission, doomed any
                    lingering hopes for our resolution. The crucial vote took place on the evening
                    of October 25. It was on a resolution, to eliminate the requirement of a
                    two-thirds vote to change the representation of China. It was adopted by a vote
                    of 59 to 55, with 15 abstentions. With the two-thirds requirement removed, the
                    General Assembly, by a majority vote of 76 to 35, ejected the ROC and admitted
                    the PRC as the legal government of China.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>This was a blow to Bush who obviously felt let down. While he, under instructions
                    from Washington, had been waging an all out campaign to preserve Taiwan's seat,
                    the President and Kissinger had been engaged in discussions with China which,
                    once known, would doom his efforts. But, characteristically, Bush never publicly
                    complained and took his defeat with dignity. I will always remember the moving
                    sight of Bush escorting the TaiwaRepresentative from the General Assembly Hall
                    as several third-world delegates danced in the aisles and applauded the U.S.
                    defeat.</p>
                <p>Q: What was your impression of the Nixon administration's attitude towards the
                    UN? Was the President himself very much engaged in UN matters?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Frankly, I don't think the UN was a very high priority issue for Nixon
                    or Henry Kissinger. I think the attitude was - well sometimes it can be helpful
                    to us and when it can we should use it. Otherwise bilateral diplomacy was to be
                    preferred. By contrast, during the Eisenhower period, when Cabot Lodge was
                    Representative, we took a much more affirmative approach towards the UN. For
                    example, we sponsored the so-called Atoms for Peace proposal which led to the
                    establishment of the International Atomic Energy Agency. And, as I've have
                    already noted, we took the initiative which later led to the UN Development
                    Program. Although he gave lip service to the organization, Nixon never took any
                    significant initiatives in the UN comparable to those. There were of course
                    exceptions, the Arab-Israeli conflict being one of them. For both political and
                    foreign policy reasons the White House and senior levels of the State Department
                    became much more involved with UN activities relating to the Middle East.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you do a little comparing and contrasting George
                        Bush's anCharlie Yost's ways of operating and dealing in the UN?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Charlie was both a scholar and a senior career diplomat who had served
                    with distinction in many parts of the world. His outwardly unassuming
                    personality belied an inner shrewdness and intellectual toughness which stood
                    him well in diplomatic negotiations. He was well informed on issues,
                    particularly those relating to the Middle East. On the other hand, he was a very
                    low-key speaker. What he had to say was almost always worth listening to, but
                    his delivery was poor. Though somewhat introverted, he was a thoughtful and
                    decent man and a person of total integrity. Bush was clearly a political person,
                    but in the best sense of that word. He had an extraordinarily effective way of
                    dealing with people and won many friends at the UN. But he came to the UN with
                    virtually no experience in foreign affairs and none in multilateral diplomacy.
                    He worked hard to overcome these deficiencies and in short order was on top of
                    his job. During his first staff meeting, he quickly developed a rapport with all
                    the staff members by telling them that he would rely on them for their knowledge
                    and experience, and he, in return, would provide them the necessary political
                    support from Washington. Bush took his job seriously and did his homework. By
                    the time he left the Mission he had earned the respect and friendship of most of
                    his UN colleagues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And so after four years you left the United Nations in
                        1973-whathen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Yes, I resigned a few months after Bush departed to become Chairman of
                    the Republican National Committee. I left for several reasons, but primarily
                    because I was ready for a change after a pretty strenuous tour of duty at the
                    UN. Nevertheless, I did so with mixed feelings, because those four years were
                    among the most challenging and rewarding years of my life. Where else but at the
                    United Nations could one mingle with representatives of the entire world, and
                    deal with such an extraordinary range of political, economic and social issues
                    affecting all mankind?</p>
                <p>U.S.-China Trade Council 1973-1986</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>A few months before my departure, I received a surprising call from Washington
                    asking if I would be interested in becoming the head of a newly established
                    non-governmental organization to develop trade relations with China. I was one
                    of three candidates being considered for this position. I agreed to have my name
                    put forward, though privately wondering what qualifications I had for the job. I
                    could think of very few! Not long thereafter, I was invited to attend a meeting
                    in Washington for what I assumed would be an interview. The meeting took place
                    in a small board room of the Shoreham hotel. As I entered, I found a dozen or so
                    men seated around a long table, some of whom I recognized from my days with the
                    International Chamber of Commerce and the Chase Manhattan Bank. Don Burnham,
                    then Chairman of Westinghouse Electric, who seemed to be presiding over the
                    meeting, introduced me to each of his colleagues. He then explained that the
                    group constituted the initial Board of Directors of what was to become the
                    National Council for U.S.-China Trade. Their immediate task was to select a full
                    time executive to head up the Council's work. At the conclusion of a few
                    friendly remarks about my public service, I was asked to leave the room. After a
                    brief interlude in an adjoining anteroom, a young staff assistant to one of the
                    Board members, escorted me back to the board room. As I entered, I was greeted
                    by a round of applause and the announcement by the Chairman that I had been
                    elected President of the Council. I expressed appreciation for their vote of
                    confidence in me, and pledged my best efforts to live up to their expectations.
                    “But,” I added, “it would be very helpful if you could give me a bit more
                    guidance about the precise role you see for the Council.” “Oh,” said Don Burnham
                    looking a little puzzled, “you know Chris, just to develop our trade and
                    economic relations with the People' Republic of China.” And so with that
                    “guidance” I embarked on a 13-year period of extraordinary expansion in trade
                    and business relations between the U.S. and China.</p>
                <p>Q: Can you tell me something about the origins of the Council. Was it established
                    as a completely private organization, or was the government involved in any
                    way?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Actually, it was a bit of both. One of the results of the 1972 Shanghai
                    meeting between Nixon and Zhou En-lai was the decision to reopen commercial
                    relations. Of course, at that time, normal diplomatic relations had not yet been
                    established. It was therefore necessary to find a way to cooperate on an
                    “unofficial” basis on matters relating to trade and commerce. It was agreed
                    tha“non-official” organizations would be established in each country for that
                    purpose. The Chinese told us that their organization would be the China Council
                    for the Promotion of International Trade (CCPIT), which they described as an
                    unofficial trade promotion body, but which, in fact, was an adjunct of the
                    Ministry of Foreign Trade.</p>
                <p>Q: It doesn't seem likely that the CCPIT could have been entirely independent of
                    the Chinese government. Was the National Council itself not acting in pretty
                    close cooperation with our government? How would you describe the council's
                    relationship with the government?</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Well, as I said, the decision to establish the Council was a joint
                    undertaking between the government and the private sector. A few months after
                    the Shanghai meeting, a National Security Council Study Memorandum recommended
                    that the NSC encourage the formation of, what was described, as a prestigious,
                    private Sino-American trade council. It would be the U.S. liaison point with the
                    CCPIT and would work in “close, informal association” with the Department of
                    Commerce. That recommendation was approved by the NSC and signed by the
                    President on December 23, 1972. At the suggestion of the State Department, the
                    council's name was changed to “The National Council for U.S.-China Trade.” In
                    later years it was renamed “The U.S.-China Business Council.”</p>
                <p>The Secretary Of Commerce was then requested to appoint a group of business
                    leaders whose firms would be likely to develop commercial relations with China.
                    They would have to agree to undertake the initial work and expense of
                    establishing the Council. The list as finally approved included senior officers
                    from such companies as Chase Manhattan Bank, Hewlett-Packard, Boeing and
                    Cargill. This became the initial Council Board of Directors, the same group with
                    which I met a few months later. And so as you can see, the government played a
                    significant role in establishing the Council, but once established, it operated
                    as a private non-profit organization. We did, however, work in close cooperation
                    with the Departments of State and Commerce and this was well understood by the
                    Chinese. This institutional arrangement seemed to suit them very well. On the
                    one hand, they could say they were working with a private, non-governmental
                    American organization, but one which, nevertheless, had close ties to the
                    American government. My own recent departure from government service and my
                    associations with Ambassador Huang Hua and his staff in New York were also
                    helpful in winning the cooperation of our counterpart organization the
                    CCPIT.</p>
                <p>Q: You were there at the beginning of the reopening of trade with China and were
                    very much a player in that part. As an outsider, it strikes me that there has
                    always been this peculiar sort of relationship with China on the part of
                    Americans - a fascination with the place, plus that lurking thing - I remember
                    that book - “Oil for the lamps of China” - somehow if you can only get the China
                    market you're really going to make a packet. This goes back to the end of our
                    revolutionary period when the China trade was really exotic but rather large.
                    Did you find yourself having to deal with the realities and illusions of
                    Americans as they got involved in this?</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: You're quite right, there's always been a certain amount of ambivalence
                    .iAmerican attitudes towards China. Probably no other country in the world has
                    so fascinated foreigners as China since Marco Polo discovered China some 800
                    years ago. And that fascination for China and things Chinese has had a
                    particular impact on Americans. It goes back to the early days of our history,
                    when U.S. ships began sailing to China, laden with cargoes of furs, lead, silver
                    coins and ginseng, and returning with such luxury goods such as silk,
                    porcelains, and tea. In due course this led to a thriving business for many
                    American traders. It also sparked a kind of China craze. Unfortunately, that was
                    largely based on ignorance and misconceptions about China. I remember a speech
                    by Senator Wherry of Nebraska in 1940. Referring to America's manifest destiny
                    in China, he said, “Let us lift Shanghai ever upward and upward until it becomes
                    just like Kansas City.”</p>
                <p>Q: Can you tell me a little bit about how the National Council established its
                    presence in China and how it interacted with the Chinese?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Well, like everyone else who has dealt with the Chinese, we learned the
                    importance of two key words - patience and perseverance. It was a slow but
                    ultimately successful process. Our first objective was to establish personal
                    contact with the key officials of the CCPIT. To this end, it was decided to send
                    a Board delegation to Beijing at the earliest possible date. This turned out to
                    be in November, 1973, only three months after I reported for work. With a very
                    small staff and only temporary office space, we were hard pressed to meet the
                    deadline. Travel arrangements for a group of senior company officials and their
                    wives, negotiations with the Chinese over an agenda, and the preparation of
                    position papers and statements for the delegation, kept us fully occupied. I was
                    fortunate to have found an excellent Deputy who had once visited China with a
                    member of Congress, Eugene Theroux, a successful young Washington attorney and
                    brother of the well known author, Paul Theroux. Gene played a key role during
                    the Council's formative years.Finally, on Sunday, November 4, our nine-member
                    delegation led by Donald Burnham Chairman of Westinghouse Electric, arrived by
                    train at the border town of Lo Wu in the New Territories of Hong Kong. We
                    disembarked and, carrying our hand luggage across the bridge into the town of
                    Shumchun, we became the first American business delegation to enter the People's
                    Republic of China. I couldn't help contrasting my first visit to Mao's China
                    with my Father's experiences in the China of Empress Tzu Hsi, 70 years earlier.
                    The China that greeted us in 1973 was a China still ruled by Mao Zedong and
                    still in the throes of the cultural revolution, during which a million or more
                    Chinese were killed or died of starvation. Yet for us, little of this was
                    visibly evident. Our few contacts with ordinary Chinese were always friendly and
                    often mixed with a good deal of curiosity - not surprisingly since westerners,
                    especially Americans, were few in number at that time. Tish Hewitt, the wife of
                    Deere &amp; Company chairman, Bill Hewitt, never failed to attract the attention
                    of the Chinese. Her six foot figure and flaming red hair greatly amused them. I
                    remember thinking that not so long ago the Chinese referred to westerners as
                    red-haired barbarians. Nevertheless, Tish was the center of friendly attention
                    wherever she went.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you comment briefly about some of your experiences
                        in Chinduring your years with the Council.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Well, that period, from l973 to my departure in 1986, was a time of
                    enormous change in China. Because of what the Chinese considered to be our
                    quasi-official status, we sometimes had easier access to Chinese officials than
                    our people at the U.S. Liaison Office, then headed by AmbassadoDavid Bruce and
                    his two Deputies, John Holdridge and Alfred Jenkins. I remember, during one of
                    our visits to the Liaison Office, being asked if we would be willing to hold the
                    reception for our host organization, the China Council for the Promotion of
                    International Trade, at the Liaison Office. It was explained that because we had
                    not yet established normal diplomatic relations, Chinese officials would not
                    accept invitations from U.S. officials for events at the Liaison Office.
                    However, if an invitation were extended by the National Council, it would
                    probably be accepted. And so, as it turned out, we introduced the first Chinese
                    trade officials to Ambassador Bruce and his staff. The party was a great
                    success.</p>
                <p>During those early years, our economic relations with China were minimal. In 1973
                    our two-way trade amounted to only 800 million dollars, and most of that
                    consisted of U.S. grain sales to China. The Chinese complained that U.S. exports
                    to China far exceeded our imports of Chinese goods and that this wasn't what
                    they referred to, as mutually beneficial trade. Of course a major challenge for
                    Chinese exporters in those days was to develop foreign markets for such exotic
                    products as Double Happiness bras, White Elephant batteries and the Pansy line
                    of men's shirts. By 1986, the imbalance had begun to shift in China's favor, and
                    during subsequent years, it was the U.S. which complained about trade imbalances
                    with China. Foreign investment or foreign loans to China were then taboo. I
                    remember the Foreign Trade Minister saying during one of our early meetings with
                    him, that China would never grovel for foreign loans or permit foreigners to
                    exploit their natural resources.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>Among my first impressions, of Mao Zedong's China was the ant-hill like quality
                    of these highly disciplined people. Everything and everybody seemed to be in
                    constant motion. Though motor vehicles were few, the constant din of horns and
                    the indifference of the drivers to pedestrians or bicyclists, was sometimes a
                    bit nerve-wracking. The only decent hotel in Beijing then was the old Peking
                    hotel, built sometime in the 1920s. In Beijing and other cities we visited,
                    billboards displayed such slogans as: “bumper harvests with joy,” “ample food
                    and clothing through self-reliance,” e.g. tunnels deep, store grain everywhere
                    and never seek hegemony.” Despite the clearly propagandistic tone of these
                    appeals, they seemed to have an impact on many Chinese. One sensed an underlying
                    feeling of pride in what had been accomplished since “Liberation” - but it was a
                    pride tempered by the recognition that much yet remained to be accomplished. As
                    we were often told, China is still an underdeveloped country.One of our first
                    meetings with a senior Chinese official took place in the Great Hall of the
                    People shortly after our arrival in Beijing. The official, then Vice Premier Li
                    Xiannian, had been a member of the Chinese Communist party Politburo since 1956.
                    He was a close associate oZhou En-lai and was defended by Zhou against attacks
                    during the worst days of the cultural revolution. As a moderate and pragmatist
                    he was said to have been one of the chief architects of China's early economic
                    development program. For all these reasons, we regarded this as a propitious
                    introduction to China's political elite and a clear indication that China was
                    prepared to cooperate with the Council. One of our Board members raised the
                    subject of Chinese oil production. As I recall, the Vice Premier replied
                    something along these lines—”our pre-liberation leaders and the Russians
                    concluded that there was little oil in China, but we didn't agree. We told our
                    engineers to drill as deeply as necessary to find oil, but not so deeply as to
                    come out in the U.S. So far, our oil production has been modest. However, we
                    intend to increase our search for petroleum, but not with the help of
                    foreigners.”</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>A few years later, we visited China's biggest oil producing area at Taching,
                    abou80 miles northwest of Harbin in Manchuria. There we were given an extensive
                    tour of the production and refining facilities, as well as a petrochemical plant
                    which was then producing about five million tons a year. We were told that
                    production had doubled during the preceding 10 years. The Chinese proudly
                    referred to Taching as the “Miracle of Taching”and it was cited as a model for
                    all patriotic Chinese workers to emulate. Despite China's earlier refusal to
                    accept any foreign participation in China's oil exploration and production, it
                    was not long before American and other foreign oil companies became very much
                    involved in both these activities. By 1983 some 20 American oil companies were
                    bidding for seismic survey and drilling concessions as well as selling
                    substantial amounts of equipment and technology to the China National Offshore
                    Oil Corporation. But the really dramatic change in China's policies towards
                    foreign trade and investment, came with the return to power of Deng Xiaoping in
                    1977. I met this remarkable man on several occasions and he impressed me
                    greatly. Twice before, Deng had been purged from power for his unorthodox views.
                    These included such statements as “It makes no difference whether a cat is black
                    or white as long as it catches mice” and, “seeking truth from facts and putting
                    action before ideology.” Those were pretty bold statements at the time. In fact,
                    from the standpoint of orthodox Chinese communist thinking, they were almost
                    heretical. But “putting action before ideology” led to dramatic changes in
                    Chinese life and in China's relations with the rest of the world. Despite our
                    lack of diplomatic relations with China, American companies were becoming
                    increasingly involved in China's development. By the time I left the Council in
                    1986, our two-way trade with China had grown to 8 billion dollars, a tenfold
                    increase over 1973. Our investments there in joint ventures of various kinds had
                    reached a total of about 3 billion dollars. But the Chinese frequently reminded
                    us that business relations could not reach their fullest potential without
                    normal diplomatic relations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain briefly how the Council operated in
                        China anhow it was helpful to American companies?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Well, from the beginning, our basic objective was to educate the
                    American businessman about contemporary China and the opportunities and pitfalls
                    of the Chinese market. We invited a group of distinguished China scholars such
                    as Michael Oxenberg, Harry Harding of Brookings Institution and Doak Barnett of
                    the Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies, to give occasional
                    lectures to our members. Our reference library in Washington became an important
                    source of information on all aspects of China's trade and economy. The China
                    Business Review, the first issue of which was published in 1974, has become the
                    foremost U.S. publication of its kind and is highly regarded within the
                    U.S.-China business community. Within the first few years of the Council's
                    existence, 20 industry committees had been established reflecting both importer
                    and exporter interests. This committee structure became the focal point for
                    planning trade delegation exchanges, and later, for organizing U.S. trade
                    exhibitions in China. By 1979 the Council had established an office in Beijing,
                    which provided a kind of home base for visiting company representatives, helping
                    them to arrange visits with Ministries and Foreign Trade corporations and
                    providing other useful services.</p>
                <p>Q: Returning for a moment to the more political aspects of business relations
                    with China when we had not yet established diplomatic relations, what if any,
                    difficulties did that give rise to?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: As I've already explained, our relations with Chinese officials at all
                    levels, were very good. However, it became increasingly clear that, without
                    normal diplomatic relations, a major expansion of business wasn't going to
                    happen. And so with this in mind, the Council'Executive Committee prepared a
                    policy statement to the U.S. government, urging the Administration to move ahead
                    on the normalization of relations. The statement said that American national
                    interests and the interests of world peace would best be served by a formal
                    government-to-government relationship. It also noted that the prospects for
                    mutually beneficial trade would be greatly improved. This was presented to
                    Zbigniew Brzezinski, the President'National Security Advisor, in June 1977. It
                    was clearly welcomed by the White House, which was already moving in that
                    direction. Without exaggerating the Council's role, I think it's fair to say
                    that we did galvanize a significant part of the American business community,
                    which helped to overcome opposition by the pro-Taiwan lobby and others opposed
                    to recognition of the PRC. Of course, it was also helpful in our relations with
                    Chinese officials who were aware of the Council's role in working for
                    normalization.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>Although the Council was a non governmental organization, Chinese officials
                    sometimes found it a useful channel for political purposes. As a former U.S.
                    Ambassador, I would occasionally be invited to meet informally with officials to
                    “share views” about various aspects of U.S.-China relations. One such meeting
                    was a luncheon in 1982 with Ambassador Chai Zemin and the head of his Commercial
                    Section. After a brief discussion about trade and commercial matters, virtually
                    the entire meeting was devoted to Taiwan. Chai began by assuring me that once
                    the U.S. accepted the principle of China's sovereignty and territorial
                    integrity, other accommodations would be possible. This of course was the
                    standard line, but he then went on to the matter of U.S. arms sales to Taiwan.
                    There were two reasons why the U.S. did this, he said - “pressures from the
                    merchants of death”and the U.S. desire to continue its control over Taiwan. We
                    had other such conversations with Chinese officials, including former Vice
                    Premier Bo Y Bo whom I escorted during his visit to the U.S. in 1980. I
                    remember, particularly, a meeting we had with Premier Zhao Ziyang in 1983. He
                    noted that economic and trade relations were only one aspect of the overall
                    relationship between the two countries, and that it was also necessary to
                    nurture the overall relationship. He then expressed the hope that the Council
                    would exert its utmost efforts to improve overall relations as well as to
                    increase bilateral trade. As I look back on these unofficial discussions with
                    the Chinese, it seems to me that they were primarily intended to open channels
                    of communication with leaders of the American business community who it was
                    assumed had considerable influence with the U.S. government.</p>
                <p>Q: As you look back on those 13 years with the China Council, were there any
                    particular events or experiences that stand out in your memory ?</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Well, I think the year 1976 was, for me a memorable year, both from the
                    standpoint of events in China and my own experiences. It began with the death of
                    Premier Zhou En-lai in January. Zhou was highly respected by most Chinese for
                    his role in curbing some of the excesses of the cultural revolution. Many Party
                    leaders owed their lives to his influence, and Mao depended on Zhou to keep the
                    government functioning during that tumultuous period. Many months after his
                    death, I remember seeing photos of Zhou, draped in black, pinned to billboards
                    on busy downtown streets. But such public indications of support for Zhou and
                    his reformist policies, led to a resurgence of influence by the more hard-line
                    idealogues led by Mao's wife, Jiang Qing and her three colleagues - later
                    referred to as the “Gang of Four.”In July, China experienced a major earthquake
                    which virtually destroyed the coastal cities of Tangchan and Tientsin and did
                    considerable damage to Beijing. It so happened that I was in Beijing at the time
                    for a week of meetings with Chinese officials. That week turned out to be a bit
                    more than I had bargained for. It began on July 22 with a reception for Chinese
                    foreign trade official by the then head of our Liaison Office, Thomas S. Gates.
                    During the following days, my official meetings were interspersed with visits
                    arranged by my hosts to acquaint me with the day-to-day life of the average
                    Chinese. One such visit was a brief ride on Beijing's new 14 mile subway system
                    which was completed in 1969. Few if any foreigners had ridden the system and my
                    colleague John Kamm, our Hong Kong representative, and I were the focus of many
                    curious stares. In an effort to amuse a little one- year old girl who was seated
                    on her Mother's lap beside me, I got a wide-eyed stare and a sudden burst of
                    tears.</p>
                <p>Towards the end of that weeI began to feel increasingly unwell and my Chinese
                    colleagues insisted that I go to the hospital for a checkup. Since my official
                    business at that point was over and because I felt that I might have a fever, I
                    agreed to visit the Sho Dung hospital. This hospital was founded many years ago
                    with Rockefeller funding and later became known as the Capitol hospital. I was
                    given tests and medications and asked to return the following morning. At about
                    midnight that night I was awakened by a telephone call informing me that the
                    tests showed I had bacterial dysentery and that a car was waiting to drive me,
                    immediately, to another hospital. Accompanied by John Kamm and two members of
                    our host organization I was delivered to the Chinese equivalent of “Peking's
                    Number 1 Infectious Diseases” hospital. There, I learned that in addition to
                    bacterial dysentery I also had a salmonella bacteria. Dr. Chang Yu-puo, head of
                    the Foreigners' ward, said that unfortunately one of those bacteria was quite
                    drug resistant, but they would do their best to cure me.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>It was on the fifth day of my sojourn at the hospital that the earthquake struck
                    Beijing. Shortly after 3:30 in the morning, I was awakened by a violent shaking,
                    both vertically and horizontally, accompanied by a low rumbling, thunder-like
                    noise. My room was completely dark, and the light-switch was out of reach in the
                    hall. I vaguely remembered that during an earthquake one is supposed to get some
                    protection by standing under a door frame. But instead, acting on instinct,I
                    dove under the bed where, if the ceiling collapsed, there might be at least some
                    protection from the mattress and bedsprings. As it turned out, after one minute
                    of continuous activity, the quake subsided and my room was still intact. During
                    the next few days, after-shocks continued and all patients were required to
                    sleep in tents out-of-doors. My tentmates were the only other foreigners in the
                    hospital. They were three young Laotian men being treated for chronic hepatitis,
                    and the eight year old daughter of the Tanzanian Ambassador to Beijing, who had
                    been hospitalized for three months with a liver infection. The tent was small
                    and the nights oppressively hot and humid. After three nights, I was much
                    relieved to be told that I could be discharged from the hospital, particularly
                    so since Dr. Chang had told me that this was the season of the
                    encephalitis-carrying mosquito. The tents were not equipped with mosquito
                    netting.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, that week in the hospital gave me a new appreciation of the
                    ordinary Chinese people. The kindness and consideration I received from all the
                    hospital staff, I will always remember. Whenever I was feeling a bit low, they
                    seemed to understand and to find ways to cheer me up. My feelings in this regard
                    were reinforced by the way the hospital staff responded to the huge influx of
                    injured people who had been transported from the devastated city of Tangchan. I
                    had watched the first truck-load being unloaded and I couldn't help noticing the
                    small acts of kindness performed by the orderlies, nurses and doctors. I recall,
                    for instance, watching one of the orderlies combing the hair of a severely
                    injured woman, while nearby another was helping an injured old man wash his
                    hands and face.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>Traditionally, the Chinese regard earthquakes as harbingers of bad news, which in
                    this case proved to be true. Less than two months later, Mao Zedong died and the
                    whole country went into a period of deep mourning. Almost immediately, a major
                    power struggle began between the leftists, led by the Gang of Four, and the
                    moderates supported by then Prime Minister, Hua Guofeng. The moderates won out,
                    and soon the news leaked that Jiang Qing and her three cohorts were under
                    arrest. During the course of a two weeks trip to China with members of our Board
                    in mid- October, we witnessed the extraordinary explosion of public support for
                    the arrests. Everywhere, great crowds of marchers jammed the streets, carrying
                    placards condemning the Gang of Four, and billboards were plastered with
                    effigies of the four hanging from gallows. I remember, particularly, being
                    engulfed in a sea of marchers which, as it approached us in our small vehicle,
                    caused us some concern. We weren't quite sure how they would react to a small
                    group of foreigners in their midst under such emotional circumstances. Trying to
                    reassure them of our friendliness, we smiled and waved at the on-coming tide,
                    and to our considerable relief, they reciprocated. For perhaps a half hour we
                    sat in our car unable to move as the marchers streamed past us. The mood of the
                    crowd was clearly upbeat as it celebrated the downfall of the hated Jiang Qin
                    and her three colleagues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I believe it was in 1986 that you left the China Trade
                        Council.Was it soon thereafter that you were appointed Ambassador to
                        Brunei.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Brunei Darussalam 1989-1991</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: No, in fact I didn't go to Brunei until three years later. For the
                    first year or so, I did some consulting and lecturing on China, including a
                    lecture tour on a Royal Viking cruise ship from Japan to Hong Kong. I also
                    renewed my activities with the United Nations Association of the U.S., and
                    served as the U.S. representative on the Executive Committee of the World
                    Federation of United Nations in Geneva. In that capacity, I attended meetings in
                    such places as East Berlin, Warsaw and Budapest. These and other activities kept
                    me quite fully occupied. When it became clear that Bush was going to run for
                    President in 1988, I offered to help him in any way that I could. I had
                    continued to keep in touch with him while he was Vice President because of our
                    mutual interest in China. Shortly after his candidacy was announced, I was asked
                    to become a member of his National Campaign Committee, and later I served on one
                    of the Issues committees which dealt with Asia and the United Nations. A few
                    months after the election, I received a call from Chase Untermeyer, the
                    President's Special Assistant for Personnel. He asked what I might be interested
                    in doing in the new Administration. I mentioned two possibilities; an
                    appointment as Under Secretary General at the UN - a position traditionally held
                    by an American, or an overseas posting. In the latter case my strong preference
                    would be for an embassy somewhere in Asia or the Pacific. I was realistic enough
                    to know thaI would not be offered a large post because I fell between two
                    categories of appointees to such positions - big contributors to the campaign
                    and career Foreign Service officers. I was neither, although I already had
                    considerable experience in the foreign affairs area. A few days later,
                    Untermeyer called back to say that unfortunately there was only one post in the
                    area remaining to be filled. It was the small but wealthy Sultanate of Brunei
                    Darussalam in Southeast Asia. Would I possibly be interested? I replied, if the
                    President feels that I could usefully serve there, I would be happy to do so.
                    Shortly thereafter, the President called me and said that Untermeyer had
                    reported to him my preferences for a position in his Administration. As I
                    remember the conversation, the President said he was interested that I had
                    mentioned the UN slot because I was one of the first people he had thought about
                    for that position. However, Secretary of State Jim Baker had pressed him to hold
                    that appointment for a senior Foreign Service Officer he had in mind. As for
                    Brunei, the President said, “it's a very small post for which you're much
                    over-qualified, but I hope you will be willing to accept it.” I said I would be
                    happy to do so because in any case, my real preference was to serve as part of
                    his Administration.</p>
                <p>Q: So your next step was to begin preparations for your confirmation hearings.
                    You had been through this process before, so you were essentially an old hand.
                    Did you have any problems?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: No, it turned out to be a breeze. I appeared before a Senate
                    sub-committee with one other nominee, Paul Cleveland, a career FSO, who was
                    headed for Malaysia. We each made brief statements and answered a few questions.
                    As a political appointee, I had expected more detailed questioning. I think the
                    fact that I had been confirmed for two previous Presidential appointments, may
                    have led the committee to believe I was a career officer.</p>
                <p>Q: Tell me a bit about Brunei's history and its significance from the standpoint
                    of U.S. interests. Didn't the Iran-Contra business have some impact on our
                    relations with Brunei?</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Yes, indeed. A few years before my arrival, an Assistant Secretary of
                    State, during the Reagan Administration, visited Brunei for a meeting with the
                    Sultan. The purpose of this visit was to request the Sultan to make a
                    contribution to Iran-Contra activities. Since at that time the Sultan was widely
                    considered to be the richest man in the world, and was known for his generosity,
                    he appeared to be a good prospect. Perhaps a bit naively, the Sultan, agreed,
                    apparently persuaded that it was an anti-communist cause. By prior arrangement,
                    his $10 million check was deposited in a Swiss bank numbered account. As it
                    turned out, the check was deposited to the wrong account, and for some time was
                    lost. By the time it had been recovered, word of the incident had leaked out and
                    was reported in the press. The check was returned to the Sultan who was
                    understandably furious. He never liked publicity about his contributions, and in
                    this case he was made to look slightly ridiculous. The incident was not lightly
                    forgotten, as I later learned. I had received instructions to approach the
                    Brunei government about making a contribution to the UN High Commissioner for
                    Refugees to assist the Philippine Government in dealing with the victims of a
                    massive earthquake which had left thousands of people homeless. The Foreign
                    Minister pointedly suggested that it would be more appropriate to have such a
                    request come from the UN.</p>
                <p>But let me say a few words about the history of this tiny Islamic Sultanate,
                    located on the northwest coast of Borneo, only four degrees above the equator.
                    The earliest references to present-day Brunei, or Brunei Darussalam as it is
                    properly called, were found in early Javanese and Chinese records. They
                    mentioned a kingdom called Bunlai, in the area of present day Brunei Bay, which
                    paid tribute to the Chinese Emperors from the sixth to the ninth centuries.
                    Evidence of this early connection with China, can be seen in the small but
                    excellent museum in Brunei's Capitol. There one can find a remarkable collection
                    of old Chinese coins dating back to the ninth and tenth centuries.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>Historic Brunei didn't really begin until the early 15th century when Islam was
                    introduced by a then pagan ruler who converted to Islam and became the founder
                    of the dynasty which rules Brunei to this day. The present Sultan, Hassanal
                    Bolkia, is the 29th of the royal line. It's easy to forget that the small
                    territory over which the Sultan rules today was at one time a vastly greater
                    area. By the mid-17th century, it included most of Borneo and the Philippines as
                    far north as Luzon, as well as the present day Malaysian states of Sarawak and
                    Sabah. But by the beginning of the 19th century, the Sultan began to suffer
                    major territorial losses. These included the states of Sarawak and Sabah as well
                    as a slice of land carved out of the middle of Brunei by the British adventurer
                    Charles Brooke, the second of three generations of so-called White Rajahs who
                    ruled Sarawak until the end of World War 11. In an effort to prevent any further
                    losses of territory, the Sultan agreed with a British proposal to establish a
                    ResidencSystem which gave the British jurisdiction over both domestic and
                    external affairs, while the Sultan controlled only Islamic religious matters.
                    The arrangement continued until 1959 when internal self-government was
                    re-established. There's an interesting footnote to this story and it relates to
                    the first official U.S. contact with the Sultan of Brunei. In 1845 the USS
                    Constitution “Old Ironsides” arrived in Brunei during its only round-the-world
                    trip. The Captain had been authorized to negotiate for a coaling station in
                    Brunei in exchange for a treaty of protection and trade. Apparently, the Sultan
                    gave serious consideration to the proposal, but finally turned it down in favor
                    of a British protectorate. In 1850, however, the U.S. did sign a commercial
                    treaty with Brunei. Full independence was not achieved until January 1, 1984,
                    and the first U.S. ambassador to Brunei, Barrington King, presented his
                    credentials to the Sultan on May 28 that year.</p>
                <p>Q: I believe you were our third Ambassador to Brunei. When did you present your
                    Credentials, and what was the ceremony like? I suppose it took place in that
                    vast palace said to be the largest in the the world.</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Yes, I presented my Credentials to the Sultan on November 28 1989.
                    You're quite right, the Istana Nural Iman, Palace of the Light of Faith, as it's
                    called, has been described by the Guinness Book of World Records as larger than
                    the Vatican Palace in Rome. Although I wasn't particularly impressed with the
                    external architecture of the building, many of the interior chambers were quite
                    impressive - as for example, the throne room with its 12 massive, 4500 pound
                    crystal chandeliers and magnificent Moroccan carpeting. The palace is about a
                    third of a mile long and contains some two million square feet of space with
                    1800 rooms. It serves not only as the residence for members of the royal family,
                    but it also houses the offices of the Defense Ministry andthe Prime Minister's
                    office.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>As for the presentation ceremony, it had much of the formality and pageantry of
                    the19th century British colonial era. I was escorted to the Palace by the
                    Director of Protocol who picked me up at the embassy and drove me to the Istana.
                    After passing through the large outer gates, we drove up a wide ramp to the main
                    entrance. There, I got out of the car which had pulled up alongside a
                    red-carpeted dais. A military Aide-de -Camp escorted me to the dais, where I
                    faced a smartly uniformed “Prestige Guard of Honor” and an army band. The Guard
                    presented arms and I received the salute of the commanding officer. The band
                    struck up some martial music while the Guard stood “At Attention,”and I stood
                    with as much military bearing as I could muster. Accompanied by the Assistant
                    Grand Chamberlain and the Chief of Protocol, we then entered the Palace, passing
                    through a spacious open courtyard with a large blue circular pool and a water
                    fountain at its center. After a few minutes wait in the Reception Room where the
                    Grand Chamberlain met us, a palace official arrived to announce that His Majesty
                    was ready to receive me. In preparation for the event, I had been carefully
                    briefed by my staff about the protocol requirements for the presentation of
                    credentials. Nevertheless, I approached the Ceremonial Room with some
                    trepidation, hoping that I would remember where and when to bow, and precisely
                    the number of steps to be taken between bows. Nor should I forget not to cross
                    my legs when seated in the Sultan's presence. As it turned out, all went well.
                    Following the ceremony, the Sultan invited me to be seated in a large
                    overstuffed, silk damask chair, while he seated himself opposite me in one of
                    equal splendor. We chatted briefly about my family and my prior activities. I
                    then mentioned that, just before my departure for Brunei, I had visited the USS
                    Constitution in Boston. There I learned that a painting of “Old Ironsides” had
                    been presented to the Sultan some years ago. I had been asked if I could try to
                    find out where the painting might be today. The Sultan assured me that it was
                    still in the Palace, and he arranged to have me see it on my departure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you describe some of the more significant issues you
                        dealwith during your two-year stint in Brunei.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: From my earliest meetings with the Sultan, and in subsequent meetings
                    with other senior officials, it became clear to me how much importance Brunei
                    attached to a continued American presence in the Pacific. As a small but very
                    wealthy Third World country with limited military capabilities, Brunei had to
                    try to compensate for its vulnerabilities. It had only recently become a member
                    of ASEAN, which provided a kind of political and economic regional umbrella but
                    not much security. By the time I arrived on the scene, a modest military
                    relationship with the U.S. was already underway. It was somewhat expanded during
                    my two years there, but mindful of Brunei's reluctance to become too overtly
                    involved with a great power, we didn't play it up. This began with occasional
                    U.S. navy visits to Brunei's main port at Muara. By the time I arrived on the
                    scene, Admiral Hardisty, then Commander- in-Chief of Pacific Forces, had already
                    made his first visit to Brunei and several more were to follow. On one of these
                    he invited the Sultan to board his aircraft carrier. The Sultan, who is an
                    experienced pilot and the owner of an Airbus as well as several Gulf streams and
                    helicopters, was clearly delighted. Each year one or two U.S. navy vessels made
                    calls at Muara, and for two or three days, took part in naval training exercises
                    with Brunei's flotilla of small gunboats. All of these activities created much
                    good will between the two “navies.” Some jungle warfare training for American
                    troops and refueling rights for U.S. military aircraft, were additional areas of
                    cooperation.</p>
                <p>But during 1990, as our negotiations with the Philippines on the renewal of the
                    Clark Airforce Base lease dragged on, there began to be press speculation that
                    the U.S. was considering Brunei as a possible alternative to the Clark air base.
                    Since this kind of speculation could arouse concern within the Brunei
                    government, with which we had never discussed the matter, I denied any knowledge
                    of such plans when questioned by the press. Brunei government officials refused
                    to make any public comments. As it became increasingly likely that the
                    Philippines were not going to renew the lease and that the U.S. might begin to
                    withdraw its forces from the western Pacific, there were expressions of concern
                    from Foreign Ministry officials. At a meeting I had with Lim Jock Seng, the
                    Permanent Secretary of the Ministry, he referred to a recent announcement that
                    the U.S. was planning to withdraw two Fighter Squadrons from the Clark Airforce
                    Base. He said some would interpret this as the beginning of a U.S. withdrawal
                    from the western Pacific. I assured him this would not be the case. My Japanese
                    colleague related to me a conversation he had with Major General Ibnu the Deputy
                    Minister of Defense, concerning the Philippine Base negotiations. The Ambassador
                    said that Ibnu had expressed the hope that the negotiations would succeed, and
                    that Brunei would be concerned by any substantial reduction of the U.S. presence
                    in the region. Ibnu then added, that if the negotiations failed, Brunei would be
                    prepared to provide military facilities to the U.S. similar to arrangements
                    Singapore had with the U.S. He made clear, however, that he was not talking
                    about U.S. bases in Brunei.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>It was largely a consequence of our withdrawal from the Philippines that Brunei
                    became more interested in enhancing military cooperation with the U.S. It became
                    clear to me that they wanted us as a benign protector - to be near but not too
                    near. And so we soon began discussions to broaden our areas of cooperation. By
                    the time I left Brunei, we had begun to negotiate a mini- “Status of Forces
                    Agreement” along the lines of a similar agreement we had with Singapore. We also
                    increased refueling activities and began theatre intelligence briefings for
                    senior Brunei officials. From the standpoint of U.S. interests, we saw Brunei as
                    a potential training site for U.S. forces, given the large areas of vacant space
                    throughout the country. And, in the event of any future military threat in the
                    area, Brunei's excellent airport with its long runways could become a useful
                    alternative landing site for military aircraft.</p>
                <p>Q: Did the outbreak of the Gulf War have any adverse effect on this program of
                    military cooperation? How did Brunei react to the war and the leading role
                    played by the U.S.?</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: I think the answer is, none as to the first question and somewhat
                    ambiguously, as to the second. The official position of the government was to
                    support the coalition's efforts to eject Saddam Hussein from KuwaiThe Sultan
                    told me that had there been no response to Iraq's attack on Kuwait, Saddam would
                    have been tempted to move against other small countries in the area. I asked his
                    opinion about Saddam Hussein's claim that this was a Jihad war. The Sultan
                    denied that there was any legitimacy to this view because Jihad applied only
                    when a non- Muslim country attacked a Muslim country. Despite these assurances
                    by the Sultan, and Brunei's support for the various UN Security Council
                    resolutions, public opinion was strongly pro-Iraq. The average Bruneian saw a
                    big powerful, non-Islamic country ganging up on a small Islamic country. This
                    was reflected in the local media and on occasional placards displayed along the
                    main road between the Embassy and the Residence, as well as one or two telephone
                    bomb threats. However, we never encountered demonstrations or outward signs of
                    hostility. It was clear to me that the Government was keeping close watch on the
                    situation.</p>
                <p>During several visits with the Sultan and other senior officials, I began to note
                    a subtle shift occurring in attitudes toward the conflict. Within the government
                    itself there appeared to be two factions: those, especially in the Foreign
                    Ministry, who believed that Brunei should continue its policy of support for the
                    coalition; and a more religiously hard-line faction which tended to reflect
                    pro-Iraq public opinion. Caught between these opposing views, the Sultan tried
                    to straddle the issues. In a 1991 National Day royal address (Titah) he
                    reaffirmed Brunei's demand for an immediate Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait. But he
                    also expressed strong support for any moves which could result in a peaceful
                    settlement. He then went on with a sharp criticism of the coalition forces,
                    accusing them of violating the mandate of Security Council resolutions and
                    blaming them for widespread destruction and the deaths of innocent people. Only
                    a week or two earlier, the Sultan had told me that he would not wish to see any
                    strains develop between the U.S. and Brunei over the Gulf War. Needless to say
                    Washington was not greatly pleased by this royal address.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>Q: Let's talk a bit about the Sultan and his role as both the religious and
                    secular leader of the country. I understand that he also serves as Prime
                    Minister and Minister of Defense.</p>
                <p>PHILLIPS: ThSultan, of course, is an absolute hereditary ruler who rules through
                    a Cabinet of Ministers similar to the British system. And, as you noted, he also
                    serves as Prime Minister and Minister of Defense. I have often said, in jest,
                    that Brunei is the only absolute monarchy that has a semi-socialist system of
                    government. It provides free education for all Brunei children, and free medical
                    and subsidized housing for all citizens. To top it off, there is no personal
                    income tax.All of this is possible because of the steady stream of revenue from
                    Brunei's offshore oil and gas production. The Sultan himself, seemed to enjoy
                    the respect of most Brunei Malays, who constitute some 55% of the population.
                    It's more difficult to judge the feelings of the Chinese. They represent about
                    25 % of the population, but few of them have been granted citizenship. They are
                    therefore ineligible for the benefits accorded Brunei Malays. Nevertheless, it
                    is the Chinese who constitute the commercial class of the country, and those few
                    who have been granted citizenship play an influential role in the life of the
                    country.</p>
                <p>As for the Sultan, it took me some time to get through his rather formal and
                    reserved personality. Surrounded by all the trappings of a 19th century monarch,
                    one didn't push too hard. I think the breakthrough for me occurred when I
                    presented him with a framed photograph of the earth, taken from one of our
                    spacecraft and autographed by a crew member, who happened to be a close friend
                    of my son-in-law. The Sultan, an experienced pilot and much interested in space
                    exploration, was clearly pleased, particularly when I pointed out that Borneo
                    was at the center of the photograph. In time, I came to realize that beneath
                    this reserved and diffident personality was a natural friendliness and a man who
                    took his responsibilities as secular and religious leader seriously. Unlike
                    other members of the Royal family, the Sultan took a second wife. Though Islamic
                    law allows men up to four wives, this seldom happens in Brunei. Despite
                    widespread criticism within the Royal family, in 1981 he married a very pretty
                    young flight attendant on Royal Brunei Airlines with whom he had fallen in love
                    and for whom he built a second, but substantially smaller palace. Whatever
                    initial hard feelings there may have been, they were no longer evident by the
                    time I arrived. On all official occasions the Sultan was accompanied by both
                    wives - wife number one, Saleha, always seated on his right, and Princess
                    Mariam, his second wife, on his left. As far as one could tell, the relationship
                    was a harmonious one.</p>
                <p>Q: Were there not rumors of misconduct and scandal among some members of the
                    Royal family? Could you comment about these?</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Yes, within the diplomatic community and probably among better informed
                    Bruneians, such rumors were not uncommon. They focused primarily on the actions
                    and activities of one of the Sultan's three brothers, Prince Jefri, who served
                    as Finance Minister and as chairman of the Brunei Investment Agency, which
                    manages Brunei's foreign reserves as well as much of its foreign investments.
                    The rumors related both to financial improprieties and Prince Jefri's personal
                    lifestyle. For example, despite a strict prohibition against the sale or
                    consumption of alcoholic beverages, it was well known that Jefri was importing
                    substantial quantities of these for consumption in a hotel which he owned.
                    Rumors also abounded about the attractive young women he invited to Brunei and
                    put up in his various guest houses, where disco parties and other entertainment
                    were provided. I have no reason to believe that the Sultan was aware of all
                    these goings-on. It's doubtful that anyone would have dared convey such
                    information to the Sultan, but of course there is no way of being sure of that.
                    I was always impressed by the contrast between Prince Jefri and his older
                    brother, Prince Mohamed, the Minister of Foreign Affairs. The latter was a
                    devout person who took his religion and his job seriously. I found him most
                    helpful on a number of occasions, especially during the Gulf War period. At
                    times when it was difficult to get through to the Sultan, I could always rely on
                    Prince Mohamad for help. Of the three brothers, he was considered to be the
                    closest to the Sultan.</p>
                <p>Q: Let's turn for a moment to Brunei's economy. One hears much about the Sultan's
                    enormous wealth, his lavish lifestyle and his extensive overseas investments.
                    Can the economy sustain this indefinitely?</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: I think the answer to that depends largely on how long Brunei's oil and
                    gas reserves last. As of a few years ago, known reserves were about 1.5 billion
                    barrels of oil and 5.6. trillion cubic feet of gas. Some among the petroleum
                    industry people guessed that the end could come early in the 21st century - but
                    that, of course was only a guess. Basically, Brunei is a one-track economy with
                    oil and gas accounting for 70% of its domestic product, and 99% of its exports.
                    The Brunei Shell Petroleum company, which is half owned by the Brunei government
                    and half by Royal Dutch Shell, produces most of the output. The government was
                    well aware of the need to diversify the economy, but doing so had not been easy.
                    During several meetings I had with Abdul Rahman, the Minister for trade and
                    economic affairs, we discussed the current five-year national development plan.
                    This focused on creating new jobs for the indigenous labor force and on efforts
                    to encourage foreign investment which could promote exports. They were talking
                    about such possibilities as the development of a glass-making industry from
                    Brunei's ample silicon resources, the production of pharmaceuticals from
                    products grown in the rain forest, and the development of tourism. None of these
                    seemed to me to offer much hope of success. Next to the petroleum sector,
                    Brunei's major source of earnings is from overseas investments. These are mostly
                    handled by the Brunei Investment Agency, although it is sometimes difficult to
                    know when a particular investment is in the name of BIA or of the Sultan
                    himself. For example, the Dorchester hotel in London is owned by the Sultan, but
                    other hotels such as the Beverly Hills in California and the Holiday Inn in
                    Singapore, are owned by BIA. According to one well informed individual I knew,
                    Brunei's national reserves as of 1991 stood at $30.2 billion. A major portion of
                    the income earned from this portfolio is reinvested, and only petroleum income
                    is used as government revenue. Of course, the Sultan's personal fortune, which
                    is shrouded in secrecy, is not included in those figures.</p>
                <p>And so it seems to me that for the foreseeable future, Brunei's economy will be
                    more directly affected by the world price of oil and gas than any other single
                    factor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before we conclude these discussions, are there any other
                        issueor events you would like to comment on?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>PHILLIPS: Well, there are a couple of matters about which I'd like to say a few
                    words. The first concerns the impact on Brunei of something called Malay Muslim
                    Monarchy, which stresses conservative Islamic values and the uniqueness of
                    Brunei Malayan culture. Its origins go back to the reign of the present Sultan's
                    father, but until recently, it wasn't a major factor in Bruneian life. By the
                    time I left however, it had reemerged as a very significant factor. Most
                    Bruneians appeared to have to have little understanding of just what MIB meant.
                    To those of us in the diplomatic community it seemed to have a distinctly
                    nationalistic and anti-foreign flavor and an intolerance towards non-Islamic
                    religions. During a meeting with the Sultan he was asked for a clarification of
                    the purposes and objectives of MIB. He told us that Brunei had become so
                    influenced by western values that its traditional cultural values were being
                    threatened. It was therefore necessary to restore a balance between foreign and
                    Bruneian cultures. But he assured us that this was not anti-western and that
                    there was nothing chauvinistic about the concept. However, I think there was
                    more to it than that.</p>
                <p>In spite of the Sultan's general popularity, there were signs of growing unrest,
                    particularly among young people, who chafed under the restrictions of life for
                    them - no theaters, no movies, no discos. Additionally, unemployment was growing
                    and had reached almost 6%. One of my ambassadorial colleagues once described it
                    as “unfocused discontent.” It appeared that a small but powerful group of
                    hardliners within the government, led by the Mufti, had persuaded the Sultan
                    that a more conservative Islamic orthodoxy was necessary in order to produce a
                    greater sense of direction to his rule. But these policies were by no means
                    universally popular, either within the government or among ordinary Bruneians.
                    Some of my colleagues in the diplomatic community believed that if continued,
                    they would eventually lead to social unrest and a destabilization of the
                    country. My own hunch was that the influence of such moderates as Pehin Isa, the
                    senior special advisor to the Sultan, and other moderates in the cabinet would
                    eventually prevail.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>The other matter, which caused me more than a little frustration, concerned
                    President Bush's invitation to the Sultan to meet with him in Washington for an
                    official working visit. I had discussed this possibility with the President
                    shortly before my departure for Brunei. He thought it was a good idea and
                    promised to look for an opportunity to arrange the meeting. I wasn't
                    particularly optimistic that anything would come of my suggestion. To my great
                    surprise however, only a few months after my arrival in Brunei, I received
                    instructions to present a letter from the President to the Sultan extending an
                    invitation for the visit which, as I recall, was to be during the month of June.
                    The Sultan was clearly pleased when I presented the letter to him. He asked for
                    a few days to discuss the timing with his staff and promised to respond shortly.
                    A week later, I was asked to return to the Palace for further discussions about
                    the visit. During the course of that meeting, the Sultan asked if his trip to
                    Washington could be postponed to coincide with the opening of the U.N. General
                    Assembly in September. I cautioned him that this might be difficult, because
                    that was the time of year when the President had an especially heavy schedule of
                    visits with foreign leaders attending the General Assembly. Nevertheless, if he
                    wished, I would convey his request to Washington. It was pretty clear to me that
                    the Sultan was hoping to combine his Washington visit with a speech at the
                    opening session of the General Assembly. It seemed highly unlikely that the
                    White House would agree to the Sultan's request. I was therefore not surprised
                    to receive word from Washington that the request had been turned down. To my
                    considerable surprise however, I was then asked to inquire if the Sultan could
                    give us a period of time during which an alternative date might be set. In due
                    course word came back that the month of April, the following year, would be
                    convenient. I passed this on to Washington, and soon thereafter received
                    instructions to deliver an invitation to the Sultan for a visit during the last
                    week of April, 1991. I also told the Foreign Ministry that Washington hoped for
                    a prompt reply because of the President's advanced scheduling requirements. A
                    week went by with no word from the Palace. A few days later a terse instruction
                    arrived from Washington which said, in effect, get a yes or no reply without
                    further delay. I then met with the Foreign Minister and told him I had been
                    instructed to press for an immediate response to the President's invitation. The
                    next day I was called to the Palace for yet another meeting with the Sultan.
                    After expressing his apologies for the delayed reply, he said his advisors had
                    reminded him that the new dates would conflict with his annual post-Ramadan
                    visits to all of Brunei's cities and towns. At that point I was nearly
                    speechless, but I put on the best front I could, saying I was sure the President
                    would be disappointed. My cable reporting this news to Washington, concluded
                    with a strong recommendation against any further Presidential invitations to the
                    Sultan.</p>
                <p>At first, I was puzzled by the Sultan's rather casual handling of an invitation
                    from the President of the United States. Why would he not have jumped at such an
                    opportunity? The answer became apparent to me during my farewell call on the
                    Sultan. At the outset of our conversation, he said how much he regretted that
                    unavoidable commitments had prevented his trip to Washington, and that the
                    missed opportunity was most unfortunate. When I explained to him how difficult
                    it was to arrange Presidential invitations, he responded that he was now very
                    aware of this and was especially appreciative of the efforts made on his
                    behalf.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>It was clear to us in the Embassy that there was no snub intended by the Sultan
                    or his advisers. They simply had no idea of the demands made on the President's
                    time, and naively assumed that they were not dissimilar to those made on the
                    Sultan. We parted on a friendly note, with the Sultan expressing the hope that
                    we might meet again in Washington the following year should he be there on
                    either an official or unofficial visit. I couldn't help wondering if this was a
                    not so subtle hint that he would welcome yet another Presidential
                    invitation!</p>
                <p>Q: I think that concludes this series of interviews. Thank you very much, Mr.
                    Ambassador, for your participation in this oral history program of the
                    Association for Diplomatic Studies.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
