<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001133">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Richard L. Stockman </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>RICHARD L. STOCKMAN</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: October 12, 1993</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is October 12, 1993 and we are talking in of all
                        places Bishkek, Kyrgyzstan and I am talking to Richard L. Stockman. Dick we
                        start off these interviews by asking about your background, something about
                        your parents and where you grew up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: My home of origin was Kansas City, Missouri. I was born in October,
                    1940. My parents were both of German origin. My mother's maternal name was
                    Kaiser. Most of the knowledge I have about her family was that they had lived in
                    and around Kansas City most of her memory, whereas my father by contrast had
                    come from the typical German immigrant group, who had migrated to the States
                    about 1850. According to the records, they went to Philadelphia and then three
                    of the four brothers moved to the Mid West and bought a farm in Glasgow,
                    Missouri. Somehow, some way they met, married and that was the start of my life,
                    the first of eight children.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now you grew up one of eight children and one could safely
                        say in a Catholic family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: That's a good assumption.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I attended a parochial school which was simply across the street in our
                    old neighborhood, a typical, blue collar working class family.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your father doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: My father was by trade basically a salesman . He had worked in all
                    types of sales and settled down into the delivery of bakery goods door to door
                    in which he succeeded pretty well. That career was broken up by two or three
                    years in the Navy during the Second World War when I was a child.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then you went on to school after parochial
                        school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes, I completed one year of high school in Kansas city and then due to
                    the influence of my very staunch Catholic mother and an uncle who was an
                    ordained priest and served his first year in China in 1948-49, I thought I
                    wanted to follow in his footsteps and therefore went to Cape Girardeau ,
                    Missouri, where the Vincentian Fathers has their minor seminary and on to their
                    major seminary in Perryville, Missouri between Cape Girardeau and St. Louis.
                    DePaul University in Chicago and St. John's University in New York are both
                    institutions founded by the Vincentian Fathers. I stayed with that for about
                    nine years until about 1962.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would have covered both high school and
                        university?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes, a total of nine years in that environment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You must have been ready to be ordained weren't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: No, actually I was shy four years of theology. I had completed the
                    course in philosophy and the minor, ironically, was in education. Then I
                    realized that my education was going to be out of the classroom and around the
                    world. After leaving the seminary there was one brief year, not quite a year, of
                    transition in which I taught in a Catholic elementary school, but was drafted
                    into the Service in 1963, in the fall. I served most of my Army time in
                    communications on Rhein Main Air Base in Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is 1963 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: 1965.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get into communications?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: In those days it was prerequisite at State that one have prior military
                    service particularly for those interested in communications, prior military
                    communications experience. Therefore I was more than qualified.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is my first interview with somebody in the
                        communications field. Remember this is an unclassified interview, but I
                        would like to get a feel of how things were done. What was your impression
                        of the state of communications that you were dealing with in the military?
                        We will then contrast it later on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: In the military, as one can easily imagine, the government had
                    thousands of young people to choose from and after a screening process a cadre
                    of people would be selected and put into the communications schooling, etc. The
                    experience and education one received was of course basic and fundamental in the
                    beginning. The longer one stayed in, of course, the more experience one
                    acquired. This overall communications experience was quite solid. It certainly
                    was a good foundation to make a transition into the civilian side of government
                    in those days. In my opinion any way, I think the service experience was more
                    than acceptable to qualify for a position at State, but it was not intelligently
                    used. After the recruitment process and coming on board, the assignment process,
                    was a real disappointment. Keep in mind in those days we are talking about
                    post-Cuba...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are talking about the Cuban crisis of 1962.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes. Kennedy, of course, was assassinated shortly thereafter. The state
                    of affairs at State in communications was, as everyone knows from history, a
                    fiasco. Kennedy was waiting on word from Cuba through our facilities and he
                    simply didn't get it. And what he did get, apparently, was not what he wanted to
                    hear.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I heard Dobrynin talk at Georgetown and say that one of
                        the critical messages was sent by Western Union, which arrived by an elderly
                        gentleman who delivered the message and had no idea what he was doing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I can't vouch for that. but things were extremely fundamental in those
                    days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this a contrast as to how things were with the
                        military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes, I think so. The military, of course, had a huge budget and was
                    geared up for both strategic type operations and mobility. They were very
                    flexible and could do almost anything they wanted, in contrast with a civilian
                    agency or even an agency like State which had not really dedicated many of its
                    resources in a serious way to communications. It was very fledgling in those
                    days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's go to the recruitment and then come back to
                        it. What got you into State?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: That is a very convoluted story in itself. I had always dreamt, in my
                    younger days, to kind of emulate both my father and my uncle, the one who had
                    gone to China for one brief year. I had always been fascinated by travel and
                    wanted to do this all of my life. Of course my first taste of this travel was
                    compliments of Uncle Sam to Germany. So when I got out of the service my first
                    interest was with the airlines because I thought that was the easiest way to
                    accomplish that goal. Unfortunately in those days, TWA with whom I was hired in
                    Kansas City went on strike very shortly after I started in the spring of 1963. I
                    had a near fatal car accident with my family in it as well, which influenced my
                    decision. I almost lost my assignment to State because I delayed reporting to
                    Washington. What really influenced me, I think, was the fact that TWA was going
                    on strike and I needed employment and income. It was accidental, coincidental,
                    that a good friend with whom I worked at TWA told me about interviewers in
                    Kansas City.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they were coming out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes, they were actually going out looking for individuals with prior
                    military service. The reason they were doing this I honestly believe is that
                    prior to this time State communicators, most positions were probably held by
                    senior women exclusively as a result of World War II. Therefore they were
                    looking down the road a bit, post-Cuba, and realized they had to broaden their
                    base in recruitment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There must have been a tremendous emphasis on security.
                        This was the height of the Cold War, there had been some real problems in
                        the communications field. How did you find the clearance business?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well I thought in those days, quite honestly, that the security
                    clearing procedure was quite thorough and in depth. Subsequently when one
                    realizes the difficulty of doing this the proper way, I really thought they did
                    a remarkably quick job of clearing one. I basically interviewed in February,
                    1963 and was hired on July 5 of that year. So the whole process took four or
                    five months only.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's not bad. What about training when you came in? Was
                        there a different way to communicate? Were you learning something different
                        than the military or was it just “Here is your radio, take over,” or
                        something?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well that probably was the most disappointing part of the beginning of
                    the career. I think the assignment process basically was pretty much driven by
                    the Bureau of Personnel more than the Office of Communications. In other words,
                    one was accepted based on the qualifications if one passed all of the hurdles
                    and examinations and eventually got into the training. Most of us knew as we
                    began the training courses where we were going in advance. Posts were
                    categorized by their importance or type of operations. For example, category A,
                    B, C, and D. My first assignment was to Rio de Janeiro. The training in relation
                    to the job, I thought, was adequate, but it certainly would not begin to compare
                    with the very professional training facilities we have today, either in content
                    or in method or duration. It was very superficial, not very professional, to be
                    perfectly honest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sort of patched together?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes. There was more actually, I believe, learning on the job then there
                    was in classroom training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about equipment? I have been a Foreign Service
                        officer for 30 years and have no feel for the equipment at all because
                        usually I was kept out of the room and didn't try to get in there. We are
                        talking about the 1960s. Were they beginning to upgrade things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: If I were to compare the first tour, an assignment in Rio de Janeiro,
                    with today, I would have to say that the equipment, even for its day, was
                    probably a major upgrade from what was commonly used in places like Cuba or
                    other hot spots around the world. However it was very time consuming process.
                    Yes, there was that mystique about the whole operation. There was certainly by
                    today's standards an unhealthy isolation of communications, for security
                    reasons, I suppose, from the rest of the diplomatic community within our own
                    embassies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In some ways I felt that this was counterproductive
                        because communicators often seemed to be lonely people and possibly more
                        susceptible to being taken over by an intelligence service because they were
                        sort of pushed to one side.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I think you are absolutely right in reaching that conclusion because
                    ironically those who were thought to be more vulnerable and susceptible to human
                    interest contact penetration perhaps were put into that position by the very
                    stupidity of that policy. Instead of integrating individuals into the community
                    in a very educated manner, they were to some extent deliberately kept
                    isolated.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. You went to Rio, you went there in 1966 and served
                        until 1968 there. How were you received when you got there? You were married
                        at this point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: No I arrived in Rio very much single. I had virtually broken up a
                    potential marriage by going into the Foreign Service. But the acceptance by
                    staff and personnel in Rio I thought was a very warm reception. Keep in mind
                    that in those days, at least at the large embassies, the administrative cone as
                    we know it today basically had pretty large sections. The communications section
                    was equal in size to the B&amp;F section. There was a form of sponsorship for
                    new arrivals. Needless to say the Brazilian people were very hospitable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1966 where was our embassy, in Rio?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes, it was still located in Rio. Within that two-year time frame that
                    I served, the movement had been started to relocate to Brasilia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From your perspective, was what the political environment
                        in Rio at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: That was a very interesting introduction, I think, to the Foreign
                    Service, certainly far superior to any classroom education one might get. Those
                    were the days, of course, that were bordering on organized terrorism. There was
                    certainly roots of it in Brazil which our US military establishment and other
                    programs we had were directed at eradicating. Unfortunately, I think many of our
                    efforts were misguided in the sense that had there been any attempt to try to
                    successfully eradicate the poverty, the lack of education, and health situation,
                    the roots of terrorism would have also been eradicated. But the political
                    environment was basically a very hostile one there. There was polarization
                    between the military, who had basically run the government pretty successfully,
                    with civilians subordinate to them, and the malcontents who wanted to be in
                    power. And there was trouble in the streets most of the two years. The students
                    were very much activists like they were in the States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me, from the perspective of a communicator, you are
                        sending all these things back and forth, did you find that you really had a
                        chance to get a feel for what was happening or were you so busy just
                        transmitting words?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I think you have truly hit the nail on the head. For better or worse, I
                    think many times that the communicators are given far more credit as being
                    vulnerable targets of intelligence penetration than is rightly the case, for the
                    very reason you pointed out. The overwhelming amount of work and the method in
                    which it was done honestly didn't permit one to read every word. To really fully
                    understand what one was doing would have required a lot more time than we had
                    available to us. And yet, there were certainly ways in which one could acquire a
                    lot of information, knowledge of what was going on, once you realized who the
                    key people in the embassy were. For example, Frank Carlucci was a young, bright
                    Foreign Service officer there, executive officer, and Vernon Walters was the
                    Defense Attach�. I don't think I have to explain those two names.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you picking up a basic rivalry between them at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Oh definitely. There was no question about it. The military
                    establishment was very much feeling its oats in those days. We were right in the
                    middle of Vietnam. They were certainly challenging the civilian part of our
                    government I think in Brazil. After all Vernon Walters could walk right into
                    Castelo Branco's office, the President of Brazil who was a wartime buddy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Castelo Branco's had been with the Brazilian Division in
                        Italy, part of the Fifth Army.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: That is right. I suppose it was a healthy rivalry between the two
                    because it certainly was competitive. It made both groups understand what was
                    going on. But as we know from the last 30 years or so of history, quite
                    frequently there are very distinct points of view. I suppose the prevailing
                    thought is the one that presents the best case that eventually gets the
                    President's ear, depending on the top spokesman in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the military have their own communications or did they
                        use yours?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: They relied exclusively upon the Embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again, this is an unclassified interview, but we are
                        talking about times gone past, CIA did their own business, is that
                        correct?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I don't know what arrangements they had, to tell you the truth. I was
                    unaware of what they were doing.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So often one has the feeling that the CIA goes off and
                        does its thing and maybe the Ambassador knows and maybe the Ambassador
                        doesn't. Who was the Ambassador at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: The ambassador at that time was Tuthill.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jack Tuthill.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes. You probably know him better than I. He came out of the European
                    area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He had this program that was called Operation Top Seek
                        which was trying to reduce the size of our embassy, which he claimed had
                        grown just like Topsy. How did this impact on the communication
                        section?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I think it impacted in several ways. I think your question is “Would we
                    be able to carry our workload and still reduce the work force?” In actual fact
                    before I had left in 1968 the planning of this Topsy Operation had been pushed
                    forward to a certain point where positions within the communications room were
                    already identified for reduction. What types of positions? Well, they were truly
                    luxury by today's standards. There was a messenger or two who literally drove
                    around the streets of Rio delivering message traffic to USAID, the Peace Corps,
                    etc. The only operation inside the embassy at that time was USIS. The others had
                    their own separate buildings in Rio and were huge operations, particularly
                    USAID.</p>
                <p>What other impact? Well, I think it did consume a great deal of his time in
                    planning this and convincing Washington that this situation had gotten out of
                    hand. Certainly he had the classic example of a huge bureaucracy of federal
                    employees in Rio. The very attempt to move the operation to Brasilia put just
                    that much more focus on who was essential and who wasn't. And needless to say I
                    think that was the beginning of downsizing, at least of State in a big time
                    way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you well accepted in Rio?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, the embassy was such a large operation there that quite honestly
                    there was very little embassy social life to which we were invited. Perhaps one
                    or two occasions a year. I recall one reception where astronauts were there.
                    They were celebrities in those days. That would be one example. Perhaps
                    Thanksgiving and an occasional function of a dignitary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was such a big embassy.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes, and the Ambassador's residence was not all that large for
                    entertaining. Of course a tour or two later at smaller embassies that issue did
                    very much come to the forefront because everyone was needed and asked to
                    contribute. One also understood the Foreign Service a lot better. Plus the
                    working hours were more compatible with a little bit of social life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Rio were you pretty much on call a lot?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, our operation there was basically divided into two or three
                    segments. What I call the heart and soul of the operation, namely the
                    telegraphic division, there were simply three of us on rotation duty the whole
                    period even though it was staffed by about ten people. The bureaucracy made
                    newcomers pay their dues. Three of us did that, including the carnival time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this a waste? Isn't there a way of sort of keeping on
                        top of things that things are really going to happen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, one would think so depending upon one's position and how much of
                    this telegraphic traffic you would have access to. You know very well from your
                    own career as you advanced in position and importance you increasingly saw more
                    and more of everyone's telegraphic traffic. Well, you can imagine within the
                    communication section where you handle all of it, in and out going, the
                    workloads were certainly very demanding. The methods of reproduction,
                    transmission, all of these things, were extremely cumbersome.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you talk about reproduction, what are you talking
                        about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, basically whether you have an incoming or outgoing telegram there
                    is a distribution pattern on that telegram. In this day and age, of course, we
                    have these high speed reproduction facilities like Xerox, but in those days you
                    had a huge US AID operation, a building of its own, six or seven stories of a
                    bank building and hundreds of copies of telegrams were required.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it is just reproduction of paper. There was the
                        thermafax and horrible ways of producing copies.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I forget what they called the method, but it consisted of a rotating
                    drum with this terrible liquid. Unfortunately we didn't have a clothing
                    allowance because you needed one on account of this purple dye. It was just a
                    very rudimentary printing press operation. We actually needed messengers to
                    distribute this stuff internally within the embassy and outside the building to
                    other US offices.</p>
                <p>When you move on down the road to later assignments, well, of course, a smaller
                    US embassy would all be self-contained. People would come to the communication
                    center to pick up. But the introduction of the Xerox at least in most of the
                    places where I was, did not really take hold until the early 1970s. No one could
                    afford those things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But at least, from what I gather, although you were kept
                        under rather strict working hours, you were able to get yourself a
                        bride.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, all work and no play makes Jack a dull boy. With a liberal arts
                    background in the seminary I had always had an interest in languages. I felt
                    very strongly that one can not enjoy the benefits of a Foreign Service career
                    without making a bona fide attempt to learn languages. I deliberately chose not
                    to date girls within the embassy so that I could learn the language, and I think
                    I succeeded within six months. Obviously I found a fianc�e of my choice and
                    understood enough to say, “I do.” The Brazilian people were very enjoyable and
                    hospitable. The life after work there in Rio was never a problem. That was a
                    city that was eternally ticking. One could work any shift, and we had three
                    shifts around the clock, and you could always go out and find a restaurant open
                    and entertainment. Life was typical of a tropical assignment. The Brazilians
                    were much Latin in that respect. A great tour.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then, I take it you were all set for the Foreign
                        Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I was sold.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have you coming back to the Department from 1969-70.
                        What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: In those days one of the natural consequences or penalty, so to speak,
                    that we had to pay if we married a foreign spouse.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came back to get her nationalized?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: That is right. Again life is filled with many ironies. Withholding or
                    withdrawing security clearances, one could only work in certain positions in the
                    Department. I seemed to have lucked out and was assigned to the African Bureau
                    and worked on the Nigerian Desk during the Nigerian Civil War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Biafran War.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: It was totally out of cone, so to speak, but to tell you the truth I
                    saw far more sensitive material on that desk without the clearance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression because I think this is a very
                        interesting war? Our policy was essentially, if Africa starts splitting up
                        all hell will break loose because of all the tribal boundaries and we had
                        better stick to the boundaries as they are, imperfect as they may seem. Yet
                        there were an awful lot of attacks on this policy, particularly from the
                        intellectuals and the glamour people, etc., that you should do something for
                        the Biafrans. What were you getting as you were dealing with this
                        thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: It was very interesting because I had served a short TDY in Lom�, Togo
                    prior to this assignment on the African desk in Washington and one of the things
                    that I learned while in Lom� was that Ambassador Albert Sherer was wearing two
                    hats. One of which was to go up to San Fernando Po, a little island, where a lot
                    of humanitarian international airlifts were taking off into Biafra. Consequently
                    there were really two points of view about this war and I do believe that most
                    of the African specialists, who were serving on the desk, were very pro-Biafran.
                    The lobbyist, etc. and the whole Washington scene were very clever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were very strong in Congress. They had some
                        people...there was one man in particular who was a congressional
                        assistant.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, they were the intelligentsia of Nigeria, the Ebos. But you wonder
                    some times looking at history today and the terrible mess there is in Nigeria,
                    was that course of action justified. Should we not have lobbied a little
                    stronger and maybe things would have been different today. Who knows?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think the policy has been, and it is a little hard not
                        to go along with it, that once you start saying, “Okay, if a rebellion
                        starts, we will maybe support the rebellion,” the whole place will
                        absolutely dissolve.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, you know, I think from a historical perspective over the last
                    20-30 years, if you look at most West African countries, or even go a bit
                    further north, all the way from Senegal on down the coast, in nine out of ten
                    cases the military were so corrupt and once the colonial powers had left, things
                    disintegrated to a terrible mess in most every case. The whole infrastructure
                    collapsed, they were greedy, corrupt and certainly didn't develop their
                    countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They are still there pretty much today.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: So, who knows. I guess the African Bureau was not unlike most of the
                    other bureaus where everybody was a specialist and if you recall one of
                    Kissinger's top priorities was to break up these specialty groups and make
                    everyone a generalist, for better or worse.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then you finally broke out of the Department and got
                        yourself off to Tegucigalpa, Honduras from 1970-71.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: That was the supreme irony again of this whole personnel policy,
                    security policy, etc. Specialists like communicators are a supply and demand
                    commodity. You can't run an embassy very effectively without them. You impose
                    penalties on them but suddenly you realize you are short handing yourself. It
                    was a Catch 22, this five-year waiting period for a foreign spouse was quickly
                    reduced to two years and I was hurried into the field. In fact, I was even asked
                    to take an African assignment, little did they realize that the left hand had
                    said stay here and the right hand had said we want you in Africa. So it was not
                    a very well throughout policy and I think they dropped it. The intent was
                    sincerely good in that they did want the foreign spouses to become orientated to
                    US living. It was good for them to have an introduction, after all they were to
                    be representatives of the United States government in some fashion. In many
                    cases many of these wives had come from wealthy, influential families and
                    certainly could make a great contribution quickly. I think the policy overall
                    was basically good. Certainly it would be scrutinized very carefully for foreign
                    spouses behind the iron curtain. In fact, I think it was prohibited and with
                    good reason. There are pros and cons but around four or five years after I was
                    married they dropped many of those conditions. In fact, I don't believe foreign
                    spouses have to become US citizens today. Personally I think that is wrong, I
                    think they should be American citizens.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Honduras in 1970-71?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: The situation was honestly very depressing. We had turned down an
                    assignment in Panama. Our motivation, quite frankly at the time was that we
                    thought we could recover somewhat financially after a tour in Washington, by
                    taking a hardship posting. The local scene there was abject poverty that one
                    found literally on your doorstep. It was the classic example of a banana
                    republic, so to speak, raped, robbed and pillaged by US industry and left in
                    that condition. What the US industry did not take, the local military did. So
                    there was virtually nothing left except a bankrupt country in debt to US banks
                    up to their necks. It was virtually impossible to change anything in terms of
                    constructive US policy that would improve the situation. Greediness and
                    corruption, starting with the President's own wife there who would take funds
                    out of charity organizations for her own purposes, was rampant.</p>
                <p>There was one interesting incident that happened while we were there which shows
                    you how things can happen with an intended design. You recall those hijackings
                    of airplanes in the US at the time?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: They were internal operations, mostly for money and these guys would
                    jump out of the back of these 727s. One of those originated in the States and
                    several weeks later it turned out that he was Honduran by nationality. He
                    eventually turned himself into the US Embassy in the middle of the night, after
                    months and weeks of searching for him. He turned himself in only because he was
                    scared to death that the local people would catch him. He had distributed the
                    money, he claimed, as he made his way down to Honduras, to poor people. Well the
                    local military, of course, were just anxious to get their hands on him for
                    obvious reasons, they wanted the money. So he walked in after weeks and months
                    of attempts to identify him. He looked nothing like the sketches the FBI had. We
                    took him back on a Defense Attach� plane.</p>
                <p>We were going to make a round robin tour of all the countries, we were allowed to
                    do that occasionally with them. We could visit every country except El Salvador
                    because of the soccer war between those two countries.</p>
                <p>There were horror stories of the campesinos massacring people out in the
                    countryside for whatever reasons, political, revenge. There were outright
                    murders in the city at night. There were selected bombings of US offices while
                    we were there. It was a little turbulent and it was a little scary from time to
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the Ambassador at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I think the Ambassador was Hewson Ryan, from USIA.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the atmosphere of the Embassy as far as you were
                        concerned?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Not atypical of Central American embassies. It was a huge US AID
                    operation more than anything else. I quite frankly have utterly no respect for
                    that organization. It is a very harsh criticism, but it is a bureaucracy in its
                    own right that in my opinion accomplished very, very little constructive. There
                    is a lot of propaganda, a lot of smoke blowing, but you don't see results. Never
                    did in any of the countries where I served.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then you moved from this not exactly heaven on earth
                        to Singapore from 1971-73. Now that must have been a pleasant contrast.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, it was for several reasons. The way the assignment came about was
                    not exactly what we hoped for. My intent in those days, we were allowed to start
                    bidding on assignments if you recall...democracy had set in in the assignment
                    process...and I thought it would be a good idea to pick a Far Eastern
                    assignment, one that was English speaking...and we had either Australia or New
                    Zealand in mind...because it would help my wife improve her English and keep her
                    in that environment. Latin America, of course, would throw her right back into
                    her previous environment. We made the bids and Singapore was the result. It was
                    very welcome for us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it an embassy at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes, it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Singapore?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: At that point in time in my young career and family life, it was
                    probably the beginning of what I considered the real education in the real
                    world. Keep in mind in those days we were very, very much into Vietnam and
                    Singapore was more than instrumental in this picture. Singapore, of course, was
                    ruled by the one and only Lee Kuan Yew with his mission to set up the ideal city
                    state. By all criteria I think even at that point he was very successful in
                    doing the impossible. It was quite a contrast in living styles, of course,
                    coming from Honduras to Singapore where you could almost eat off the streets.
                    Our second son was born there and it was ideal for us for raising a family.
                    Education was available. But we really did not get to know a lot of the people
                    like we hoped to. We did get to know a few of the neighbors in our neighborhood.
                    People, of course, other than a few Embassy officers, basically lived in large
                    apartments. We had a detached house which was pretty nice and my wife got to
                    know more people, I believe, than I did. However, professional people, dentists,
                    doctors, etc. were very accommodating and we would invite them home from time to
                    time. It was interesting to hear the local people talk about their conditions
                    there. They were obviously a highly educated people, I think sophisticated by
                    Far East standards. But they were a very regimented people. One of the sad
                    things that one could see was the intense stress and pressure put on young
                    people in this competitive world that they valued and treasured so much. It was
                    not uncommon to hear of young suicides in those days. So I think it did tell you
                    something about this stress that a city state could create.</p>
                <p>Congestion? Yes, there was a lot of that. It was an island of about 10 by 24
                    miles in length, I think. The US military presence there was more or less
                    isolated on one end of the island and it was all in support of Vietnam. Lee Kuan
                    Yew made it very clear that by no stretch was he going to let Singapore become a
                    Hong Kong with all of its overtures. He certainly wanted his country and State
                    to become a financial center and hoped to replace Hong Kong some day in that
                    role. Who knows what will happen as we approach the reversion of Hong Kong to
                    the Mainland in 1997.</p>
                <p>But it was a very enjoyable assignments. The weather was almost overbearing with
                    the humidity and the heat.</p>
                <p>The Embassy, itself, was not large. It was constantly supporting VIP trips
                    because it was a convenient stop off..</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was good for shopping. Who was the Ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: You know, I have a difficult time recalling who the Ambassador was. I
                    don't know why, unless it is because we seldom saw him. Incredibly enough it was
                    not staffed nearly as well as you would have thought Singapore would be in that
                    particular time frame. It was by most standards a small embassy. The foreign
                    service nationals equaled, if not out numbered us. It kind of told you the
                    importance of Singapore in our scale of things.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any communications problems being in a place
                        like that? You were pretty far away from everything.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I think it was the classic example of an operation that was difficult
                    to staff. The actual physical conditions, the working environment, was pathetic.
                    We were crammed into a cubbyhole at the top of the three story building. We were
                    pretty much restricted in what we were allowed to do in terms of operations. The
                    level, sophistication of the equipment was a real disappointment. I would
                    classify it as an info type post rather than an action type post. It was a place
                    that accepted a lot of visitors. For some reasons the communications office
                    there had a lot of difficulty and hardship. People suffered illnesses. The
                    fellow I replaced lost a son there from encephalitis, the mosquito bred disease.
                    A lady had a real serious problem and had to leave prematurely. The morale was
                    not too good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you went from what on the surface would have sounded
                        like a very nice place, but so often that isn't the case on the job. What
                        about your next one that doesn't sound like a very nice place, Lom�, Togo
                        from 1973-75?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: If I can go back to Singapore just briefly, one of the reasons was that
                    Singapore was a terribly expensive place, including the housing. There was no
                    furniture program and staff people did not live well there. We were not
                    permitted to drive left-hand cars, etc. Therefore, I thought in our young family
                    life it would still be possible to take one more semi-hardship tour. It was an
                    opportunity for me to bid on a place that was very key to a sophisticated
                    technical operation we were going to do there and I wanted to be there when it
                    happened. After discussing it with my wife we agreed, we lobbied for it and we
                    got the assignment and enjoyed it very, very much. I think she got her real
                    first taste of good Foreign Service life there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Togo in those days?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, politically Togo was quickly becoming one of the last bastions of
                    freedom in West Africa that had survived the post colonial period when most of
                    the European dominance and presence started to disappear. The British were
                    virtually gone except for some influence in Nigeria. The French were there but
                    behind the scenes commercially more than anything else. The Germans had
                    disappeared. So therefore the President of Togo, Eyadema, was President for life
                    in his own right. He certainly was no model of human rights causes or a pusher
                    in that direction. I think the role of the US embassy there, as small as it was,
                    was vastly more important in relation to its size than most people could
                    appreciate. By that I mean there was a very large North Korean and Russian
                    presence there.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This, of course was of great concern to us during the Cold
                        War.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Absolutely. If you recall in those days the Civil War and the takeover
                    of Angola and a large Cuban presence there; the same thing in Ghana and on down
                    the line it went. In other words, I think a lot of people truly feared there
                    would be a domino effect in Africa. Certainly there was evidence of it starting
                    to happen. So the only way I believe that the importance of Togo got on the map
                    was some very shrewd appointments of US Ambassadors there. One was Nancy Rawls,
                    one of the first female ambassadors who had risen up through the ranks; followed
                    by Ronald Palmer, who was very astute and articulate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was there when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I had a long interview with him on Togo.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: So you can appreciate how dynamic he is. He was a great person to work
                    for. I don't think there was one individual in that embassy, male or female, who
                    did not surely appreciate his liveliness, his dynamic spirit. And he was very
                    successful there. He actually was, I guess, in competition for the Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary that Richard Moose was eventually awarded. I think he was
                    somewhat disappointed that he didn't get it, of course and probably would have
                    done very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are talking about under the Carter Administration which
                        is a little later...1977.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were communications in Togo?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Like I had mentioned, one of the reasons that I wanted to go there so
                    badly was...the State Department had looked over the entire situation and
                    realized that we were quickly getting into a no-win situation on communications.
                    You have one country not getting along with the next...keep in mind that we rely
                    very heavily on commercial leased lines to do most of our communications...and
                    we could see that that was not going to succeed very well, in fact it was
                    becoming almost impossible to maintain communications in a lot of embassies. So
                    they made a decision that they were going to go with a radio communication
                    operation and that was my background in the military and therefore it was quite
                    natural that I would be interested in getting back into that type of operation.
                    Little did I realize before I got there, however, that Lom� and all the
                    equipment earmarked for Lom� was suddenly transshipped into Luanda, in Angola.
                    Unfortunately six weeks after it arrived there and got installed, it fell to the
                    rebels and we lost everything. So that put Lom� far back on the priority list
                    and most of the motivation that I had for being there was kind of lost. I didn't
                    know all of the reasons but I started to piece it together. But I did establish
                    a very good working contact with the French manager of French Cable, the
                    communications department there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, we depended on lines.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, it was a combination there. We would transmit in a very primitive
                    fashion our communications, we called it off line, to the central office in
                    Lom�, through the French facilities and then they would get it back to Paris
                    which was a very big relay point for many, many African posts in those days.
                    They had a huge operation out of Paris. One could spend hours there doing this
                    work. It was extremely tedious and kind of redundant in the manner in which we
                    did it and very time consuming. There were long days and short nights most of
                    that tour. But we extended six months. We thoroughly enjoyed the social life. It
                    was a small international community but people got along extremely well. The
                    education was very elementary in various respects, but wives contributed, they
                    taught school, everyone worked together.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this is the real fun of the Foreign Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: It was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Satellites were not even in the air at that time or
                        not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Of course the military establishment had most of the resources. There
                    were satellites up there and certainly were dedicated. I suppose you really had
                    to be in the inner circle to get access to those things. It certainly wasn't in
                    our budget and planning at that point. However, as progress and technology set
                    in we quickly changed with the times.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But these weren't the times?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: No we are talking about 10 or 12 years prematurely here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then we have you leaving there and going to Geneva
                        from 1975-77. Having gone from high cost Singapore to go to high cost Geneva
                        was this a problem or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: It was a problem as a matter of fact. It was literally going out of the
                    pan into the fire. Of course, salaries had increased slowly and gradually with
                    the years, but as everyone knows Geneva was one of the more expensive Foreign
                    Service posts around in those days, and I suppose still is. But I would have to
                    say that the pluses far offset the minuses. The beauty of the country, the
                    educational facilities available...of course I am talking only about the
                    tangible benefits, we haven't talked about the job yet...but it was a hard
                    decision to make in some respects. After all one would be giving up the drivers
                    position and fall back into the pack which is difficult after having a taste of
                    attending country team meetings, doing planning with an admin officer one on
                    one, to again take a secondary seat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is always one of the hardest things to do. That is
                        why we are able to keep our small posts staffed, people feel much more they
                        belong.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, I had lobbied and made every effort on my own part to obtain some
                    kind of upward mobility. As you well know in the old days of the Foreign Service
                    it never hurt to have a godfather around, which we all realized existed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A godfather being sort of a patron who you can get advice
                        from.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: But you know if you were of such a mind, and I certainly was, I wanted
                    to see as many of the Bureaus and areas of the world as possible during my
                    career. Of course there was give and take if that was your philosophy, you had
                    to take the good with the bad. Also in the bidding process we had to indicate
                    high, low and medium bids. Well, anyway, it was a stroke of good luck. Things
                    turned out for the better. Ironically it led to other assignments, I think.
                    Whether it was by accident or fate, I don't know.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>We got deeply involved from day one. Geneva was an extremely busy post. There
                    were all kinds of work requirements. This was, of course, the Carter
                    Administration years. I remember one of the first dramatic things that came out
                    of the White House and the OMB was the attempt as you can remember to find more
                    sources of revenue. One of the prime targets was the overseas community paying
                    more of their share. Well the attempt to put all of our allowances into the
                    income bracket scared the wits out of most Foreign Service people. How in the
                    world could we ever afford to pay taxes on the educational allowance, travel,
                    etc. It was absurd and as it turned out it didn't happen. But it was certainly
                    food for thought.</p>
                <p>Anyway, as far as the post went the disappointing part of it professionally was
                    that unless you really made a conscious attempt to get to know individuals, one
                    on one, it could be a very impersonal, typical European post. You went to work,
                    you left work, and there was very little social life and friends outside.
                    Certainly the Swiss were not people to make friends with easily. They were
                    rather cold and austere. But, again, I think the success that one has,
                    especially in the communications field frequently is through the contacts that
                    your wife and children make. I have to really give them credit that what social
                    life we did have came primarily through those contacts and a few others we had
                    known before. But one could still do an awful lot on an individual basis. Morale
                    was not the greatest. Joe Meresman was probably one of the real positive lights
                    at that post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: He was the Admin Counselor. He labored continuously for staff
                    personnel, in particular, citing the enormous cost of trying to live there and
                    there was very little support from the IO Bureau.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: IO being International Organizations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: He basically did not win a lot of battles, but he certainly convinced
                    us that he was on our side.</p>
                <p>The interesting part though was that at this particular time on the job the age
                    of communications, the technology and the improvements, were starting to surface
                    and we were making some very dramatic changes in the technology that have an
                    impact to today and will continue to do so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you give an idea about what you are talking
                        about?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes. We changed our operation entirely from a purely mechanical
                    electrical machine type manual operation to computers. This was just a huge
                    dramatic change in modes of operating. Very few people in those days had any
                    prior experience with computers. Most people kind of feared them. It was new to
                    everyone, officer and staff alike. Of course, in Personnel the bead counters'
                    first reaction was “Oh my God, this is the perfect justification for downsizing
                    communications staffing pattern.” Well, that turned out to be entirely false.
                    There is a learning curve with any new change in any profession, but certainly
                    converting to computers. The learning curve exists to this day. We simply can't
                    keep up with the developments. The life expectancy of these things is normally
                    three to five years before there is another generation causing a new learning
                    process. So that was my introduction to the real world of technology in
                    communications.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How exciting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: It was.</p>
                <p>I suppose the other revelation that surfaced was the fact that not everyone can
                    cope with this change. We all tend to think that with younger people come bright
                    minds and better prepared people, etc. That was not necessarily the case as we
                    found out and learned through personnel and staffing changes there.</p>
                <p>Our tour was only two years but nevertheless we were supporting all of the SALT
                    talks, the whole establishment that would go back and forth between Geneva and
                    Washington and the UN. We supported the Multilateral Trade Negotiations; ACDA,
                    arms control; and the whole realm of other visitors to the United Nations there
                    in Geneva. Of course it was not accredited to the country, the capital was in
                    Bern, we were accredited to the United Nations which many people really don't
                    understand. So it was truly a unique assignment.</p>
                <p>I think the one aspect of work that is lost sight of is that as everyone knows
                    Jimmy Carter very much advanced human rights and it was a huge operation there
                    this Human Rights Division. I am trying to recall the name of the man who was so
                    successful, it escapes me now.Oh yes, Ronald Palmer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Actually you can fill some of these names in. You will be
                        getting a draft for editing.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: They were a very small section, very dynamic and very dedicated to that
                    particular interest. But there were huge numbers of refugees who were coming out
                    of the Communist Bloc countries, filtering through Vienna, Austria out of
                    Moscow. So we were required to support this effort in communications. In every
                    case it meant an exchange of telegrams on a given individual or family for every
                    refugee. The UN, of course, was the organization that carried out the details
                    and made it happen. But the US mission was tasked to do that. It was a huge
                    workload.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you know if there were other UN communicators there
                        and if so did you have much contact with them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: No. In fact I honestly know very little about the UN communications
                    system as a group. I have heard a little bit about them through a much later
                    assignment at the UN a year ago. They, of course, do have this communications
                    section. But I don't think it is anywhere near as sophisticated as what the US
                    government has.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then you moved from Geneva to what strikes me as being
                        rather interesting but marginal post, Dublin.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes it is. It is very difficult to understand Dublin, I think, for one
                    particular reason, not being of Irish extraction with a name like Stockman. I
                    think the first words spoken to me at least in that embassy kind of set the
                    tone. “What is a person like you with a name like Stockman doing in our
                    embassy?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I take it was very much an Irish enclave.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: It certainly was. Tom Kelly, the administrator, was eventually replaced
                    by another non-Irishman called John Dieffenderfer. He helped break the ice. Once
                    John came I didn't have any problems.</p>
                <p>In terms of importance, of course, on a scale of one to ten, I think you would
                    honestly have to put Dublin somewhere in the category of 2 to 4. As they say
                    sometimes and not very complimentary, small potatoes in a big patch. But it did
                    have the uncanny way of rising to the top from time to time and there are a few
                    examples that I can cite.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>As you remember in those years, terrorism in Central America, and particularly El
                    Salvador, was getting entirely out of hand. And, of course, Ireland being
                    Catholic and interested in that part of the world had its own mandate to pursue.
                    Well, ironically again, as things happen, the Archbishop of Shannon was in El
                    Salvador when they were installing a new bishop when a massacre occurred in the
                    cathedral and killed Archbishop Romero. Well that set off protests like you have
                    never seen and Ireland was going to lead the pact and condemn this and US policy
                    and everything that went with it, for right or wrong. Perhaps they were
                    absolutely right as we know from things that have been revealed to us later
                    on.</p>
                <p>The other example that really and truly affected communications in a very
                    important way at the time was the Iranian hostage crisis. Now Ireland happened
                    to have the Presidency of the EEC at the time. This was in the beginning of the
                    crisis...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: November, 1979 was when they took it over.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: And somewhere in the end of this thing, of course, as you recall, the
                    hostages were finally released and Ireland played another role there in that the
                    Prime Minister at the time convinced the Ambassador, Ambassador William Shannon,
                    who had come from the New York Times world as a political appointee, to assist
                    in letting the plane touch down in Shannon on the way home. This was obviously
                    for political motives. He was up for reelection one more time. What better
                    mileage could you get than welcoming the hostages home using Shannon airport for
                    refueling purposes, of course, and a chance to get off the plane and rest a bit.
                    Well you know they were quite anxious to get home. They would have rather gone
                    directly home and stopped all the PR, but that was one example of high power
                    politics.</p>
                <p>Another incident happened in the course of that tour where former President Ford
                    was passing through Ireland with a group called Charter Oil, he was on the
                    board. We were asked to support that visit. It was the first of ten worldwide
                    stops with this group. Well, the site was up near the North Ireland border in
                    definite IRA country, so it was going to require quite an extensive effort,
                    primarily on the part of security, let along logistics, to support a visit by a
                    former President in that part of the woods. They had never seen communications
                    in that area ever. They had no telephones. Therefore, one had to find working
                    contacts quickly and get it done. It got done. It worked, it was primitive. We
                    didn't have much Department support at all, but we got it done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find Ambassador Shannon? You know all these
                        political ambassadors seem to be Irish. Right now we have deceased President
                        Kennedy's sister as the Ambassador to Ireland so things haven't changed. But
                        how did you find Ambassador Shannon?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, one on one I think one could say he was a very congenial, dry
                    humored man. He was certainly the academic type who was quite content to come in
                    during business hours, quietly sit in his office and do his think pieces and
                    politicking or whatever he was there to do. It was a well known fact that he
                    communicated directly with the White House. Bureaucratic channels could do what
                    they may, but for the most part he turned things over to the DCM whose name was
                    Charles Rushing, a career diplomat who did not have an easy task. The embassy
                    staffing was one of a kind, with two consular officers. It was primarily a
                    consular post as you can appreciate. Therefore, most of what the Ambassador did
                    was on the PR level making contacts, etc.</p>
                <p>Obviously, though, the IRA was a very touchy thorn in the side for both
                    governments. There were numerous protests in the streets in those days. There
                    were attempts to bomb some of the British at the embassy and in the streets of
                    Dublin. Other incidents as I can recall at the time, there had been a very
                    painful strike of civil servants, particularly the PPT, Post, Phone and
                    Telegraph, right before we got there that summer. There were fuel embargoes or
                    scarcities while we were there. They had had a major snowstorm like they hadn't
                    seen in 50 years. So the unpredictable happened in the course of those three
                    years. I think the economy was quite fragile. US investors would set up shop,
                    get their tax holiday etc... Of course, in EEC fashion, bureaucrats were all
                    over the place, wages were out of proportion to production and inflation was
                    quite high.</p>
                <p>What did we get out of the tour? Well in different shapes and forms I think it
                    was a very fulfilling tour. One met wonderful people there. The restaurants and
                    the food were so-so. But our boys made a wonderful group of friends. The
                    education was as solid as could be expected, very much in British fashion,
                    although they wouldn't admit it. I would say overall it was a very enjoyable
                    tour. Not particularly career enhancing though.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you went off to Riyadh in Saudi Arabia. You certainly
                        are touching every base in the geographic book as far as areas go.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, as I mentioned to you, the philosophy was to see as much of the
                    world as possible. I have to admit we did not bid on this assignment. That was
                    one that was dictated to us and for reasons unknown to me. I think the
                    assignment came about for a couple of reasons. One, perhaps of my own doing and
                    stubbornness. We did not get very good support from the Regional Communications
                    Center in Bonn in Dublin. What little support we did get came out of London and
                    begrudgingly at that. Consequently it was a real source of frustration for the
                    embassy that we could not have better communication facilities there. And I did
                    my best to bring it to the attention of the regional authorities who were
                    frankly shirking their responsibilities. The Ambassador was extremely frustrated
                    with this at times. For example, he lived in a house in Phoenix Park that was an
                    isolated home in the middle of this huge park and frequently had no telephone
                    communications. We could have resolved that very easily with a little bit of
                    money. But for reasons of indifference, it never got accomplished. We knew what
                    the problem was but it simply couldn't be budgeted. I made a lot of waves about
                    that. One of the consequences of it was, “We are going to give you a real
                    assignment where you will shut up.” And that was Riyadh. But it did prove to be
                    truly one of the most challenging jobs I ever had. The timing was absolutely
                    perfect as far as a challenge goes. The Saudis had determined about this time
                    that all foreign missions would relocate in Riyadh which would become the new
                    capital.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before that it had been in Jeddah.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes. How do you do this overnight? Well, most of the huge construction
                    projects in Riyadh, similar to Brasilia, were completed on time as the Saudis
                    insisted. The last was the building of the diplomatic city. Our particular
                    embassy was somewhat behind schedule mostly because of our lackadaisical
                    attitude about this thing and the incompetence, I think, of FBO.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Foreign Buildings Operation, which is not known for its
                        effectiveness.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: But that too in itself was our own undoing. You have to keep in mind at
                    this point in time Ambassador Richard Murphy was the Ambassador...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He and I were in the same entry class.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well you know what a wonderful person he is.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A real expert on the Arab world.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: He is and I have always thought with a bit of sadness that he was
                    shuttled out of the picture when the Persian Gulf developed. For some
                    unexplainable reason his name never surfaced again, maybe by choice or whatever.
                    But at any rate he was Ambassador at the time. There were some very important
                    things happening in that time frame. One of which is, and I will only touch on
                    it lightly for obvious reasons...but there was no question about it that the
                    Iran scandal was unfolding at that very point in time...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the Reagan Administration swapping weapons to try
                        to get hostages out of Beirut.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: And who knows the way the shots were called, but it is a fact that they
                    were taking place. One could see obvious signs of very high level things going
                    on. It is not my place to provide any details, of course, but it kept things on
                    pins and needles. We were attempting during this whole period to constantly
                    upgrade the total lack of communications capability in Riyadh. We were in a very
                    pitiful, leased building which was ill equipped to carry out the mission. My
                    task was to identify these requirements and correct the problem and get it done.
                    All this was to be accomplished in the period of two years, including a building
                    that was not even started when we arrived, right next door, that eventually got
                    put up. We had to tie them together and make it a workable embassy until the
                    diplomatic city could be completed. The support out of Washington and regionally
                    in the beginning was absolutely pathetic. They were not focusing on this
                    whatever. It was a total act of irresponsibility in my way of thinking.
                    Management types should have been called to task. Eventually they got the
                    message in a very, very strong manner. It was feast or famine. I was not going
                    to be the sacrificial lamb. Rocky Suddarth, was the DCM. After all we had to
                    identify suitable homes for the Ambassador, the DCM and others, get telephones
                    put into these homes and all kinds of requirements. Our staff was inadequate. I
                    finally got it increased to a total of three while I was there. There was no
                    diplomatic courier service in place. There was nothing when I arrived. To start
                    from scratch is not an easy task.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you have problems there with your kind of work in
                        communications, is this Near Eastern Affairs Bureau or Communications
                        Bureau?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, at this point in time the Office of Communications unfortunately
                    was not a Bureau. That did not come about until the late '80s. So at this point
                    it was simply an office of communications subordinate to the A Bureau. Now, once
                    we were assigned, of course, to an embassy we became part of the Bureau as part
                    of the staffing pattern, but we nevertheless had to work through regional
                    offices through our chain of command. So we were serving two masters and you
                    know what happens when you do that. Nobody wins and you can do nothing but wrong
                    or fail. So it was a very frustrating time.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>I must say the most delightful part of it, however, was the housing that we
                    eventually got. In the beginning we were all living in prefab homes handed down
                    or subleased through other American firms who had done business and then vacated
                    these places and it was not very nice. In fact it was kind of pathetic. But we
                    survived nine months until we finally got into some very nice established
                    housing which made all the difference in the world. But it is incredible how
                    people stick together in hard times at a post like that. The wives did not
                    particularly resent being there. They were treated decently, chauffeured around
                    by embassy cars, because they couldn't drive. They adapted, I thought,
                    incredibly well. So did the children for that matter. Of course the Saudi
                    practice was to allow education only up to the ninth grade. They wanted the
                    children to go elsewhere after that.</p>
                <p>[Tape 2 - lost beginning of Side A due to tapeover of ending of interview]</p>
                <p>...Needless to say those things have to be honored, they should be honored and I
                    think in most cases they are. There has always been kind of a jealous
                    possessiveness about communications personnel to maybe go too far in the
                    interest of secretness and confidentiality and to perhaps mislead the average
                    customer who has a right to know some things, to deprive them of this in the
                    interest of security, etc. But I think you can appreciate the need for this
                    so-called back channel that you talk about. I really would say that abuse of
                    such a thing, of course, could make an ambassador very, very nervous as the
                    principal officer at any post. Obviously when the chief does not know what the
                    Indians are doing we have a serious problem. When the Secretary of State cannot
                    communicate with his Ambassador in any given country at the level that he wishes
                    to , we have a very serious problem. And, of course, we all know the most
                    classic case of all in our memory when things were really falling apart in
                    Moscow, how difficult it became to reinvent the wheel there. We can't go into a
                    lot of detail, of course, but having been in Washington at the time...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are talking 1987-89.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: We basically have to do what has to be done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because of all the sensitive material flowing through you,
                        have you ever found either security people or inspector generals putting any
                        particular burden on you because of leaks, etc.? Is this a problem that
                        happens to communicators?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, I have never seen any abuse on either side of the fence. Whether
                    enforcement or carrying out one's duties and responsibilities from the
                    communication's center point of view. I think that common sense in most cases
                    prevails. In one rare case, which I have mentioned to you, an individual tried
                    to abuse a position of power and obtain information that he was not entitled to
                    which I refuse to give them, even though they felt they were entitled to.
                    Perhaps I paid a price for maintaining the integrity of the system. If so, so be
                    it. But that would be the one rare instance that I can ever remember along those
                    lines, and it was exceptionable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left Riyadh in 1984 and things were pretty well in
                        place by that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: They were virtually about as good as we could expect them to be until
                    the diplomatic city was completed which I think happened some time in 1985,
                    maybe early 1986. I would love to go back and see it again just out of plain
                    curiosity, although I must say that I was not overly fond of trying to do
                    business in Riyadh before it became a US Embassy. A Liaison Office is no cup of
                    tea to work in. One gets spoiled and becomes very presumptuous all the time of
                    doing business as an embassy employee. A Liaison Office, as you well know and
                    can appreciate, has no diplomatic status. You are very vulnerable to the whims
                    and fancies of local authorities, the airport, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find your working relations with the
                        Saudis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, most contacts with the Saudis are kept to a bare minimum because
                    of the way they like to do business. They are screened by so many buffer zones.
                    On one occasion in two years I was able to meet a Saudi and invite him to our
                    home. At all other times I was dealing basically with Bell Canada employees in
                    the Ministry of PTT, or perhaps British on some occasions. Very rarely a Saudi.
                    That is the way they like to do business. It worked. There was no real problem.
                    It kind of disappointed me in a way that one doesn't get to meet some of the
                    people of a country, but that was Saudi Arabia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you came back to the Department for about four
                        years, 1984-88?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes, that was by choice for several reasons. I was not really very
                    pleased with the promotional progress or the lack thereof and felt that the only
                    way to crack the ice was to go back and prove not only to myself but to the
                    establishment that I could perform my job at a higher level. Even though
                    efficiency reports indicated that, still you had to prove yourself. So I lobbied
                    very strongly for that and was able to wiggle my way into the Department in the
                    Office of Communications Security, of all places. It started there at least. One
                    thing led to another and I ended up most of the time in the Foreign Operations
                    Division which was the heart and soul of working there as a Foreign Service
                    employee. You liaisoned with anyone and everyone from the top of the building to
                    the bottom, but particularly with the Bureaus with whom and for whom you were
                    responsible as a liaison partner.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was within the Office of Security?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, I started in the Office of Communications, Security Division and
                    then moved around to Special Projects to the Foreign Operations Division of the
                    Office of Communications.</p>
                <p>Of course we were in those days in a great transition time in many respects. This
                    whole movement to convert what we called OC, Office of Communications, to the
                    eventual Bureau status of the Information Management, was all taking place. We
                    were very cleverly and subtly downsizing the staffing in communications from
                    roughly 1200 personnel to 900. Very few people realized it. It was basically, I
                    am convinced, a trade-off between management in the Department of technology for
                    downsizing personnel and to some extent the exchange was fair given the
                    advantages of technology. However, in terms of actual expenses I doubt very
                    seriously if either management level, communications management or the bureaus,
                    fully understood the learning curve in this thing, the training involved, the
                    maintenance, the inventory accountability, and logistics. We are talking huge
                    sums of money. Granted one of the real important tradeoffs in the whole process
                    was the reduction in size of the equipment which was something which we never
                    enjoyed before. You could now do many, many more things with a package that was
                    ten times more productive, dynamic and potentially open to all kinds of
                    advantages than ever before. The size of this equipment was miniaturized and
                    therefore you no longer needed large communications centers. You could do a lot
                    more with a lot less, including fewer people. It was undoubtedly the most
                    exciting time that one could ever be in the Department, in my opinion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also by being in the Department you would see the new
                        stuff whereas if you were out at a post you might be at the end of the
                        supply and it may never get there in your time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, we were attempting to do several things at the same time. I would
                    really have to cite two key individuals or three, who were more than
                    instrumental and understood what was going on and implemented it very
                    effectively. That was a fellow by the name of Stu Branch, who was the DAS for
                    OC. His successor was Bob Ribera, who was followed by the final DAS for the
                    Office of Communications, Bob Caffrey. Then, of course, the whole operation was
                    subjugated to the Diplomatic Security Bureau for a while under the A Bureau and
                    eventually it became the Information Management Bureau with one DAS, which it
                    should have been all along. We never had that bureau status before and it caused
                    a lot of problems. Although the budget of OC was huge as was the staffing
                    consuming a good part of the State Department budget overall, it never had the
                    bureau status. There was no way that you could begin to merge and streamline and
                    integrate all of this communications technology to some intelligent form of life
                    without getting all these interests together. I mean the redundancy, the
                    cost...you had for example an unclassified word processing operation that was
                    built on the WANG models of equipment that was cumbersome. One of the ironies of
                    this is the high level group that came out here last week and saw this modern
                    form of computer and everything here in Technicolor and they go back to the
                    Department and are in the 18th century so to speak. They were overwhelmed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know. When I was in Korea we went down the WANG path
                        which was one that basically died because it didn't keep up with the
                        process.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: There are numerous classic examples of this today out in the field and
                    this has become particularly painful when you get into huge budget and fiscal
                    operations, regional centers, and there are several of them around the world,
                    and they are attempting to use this outdated technology and perform all these
                    administrative tasks. The consular operation sees the same thing in their
                    operation trying to do things electronically today instead of using the mail and
                    all the tedious rubber stamping, etc. There is virtually no form of
                    communications or word processing that hasn't been reviewed and integrated into
                    this plan now in the Department. It is long overdue and is really going in the
                    right direction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were in the Department working on these things,
                        we are talking about the mid 80s, did you find real bureaucratic problems
                        with people afraid that their turf was being trampled upon? What were some
                        of the problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Absolutely. The Bureaus had always had their own budgets for word
                    processing, etc., under their own control. They even had training facilities and
                    positions identified overseas which were managed through the Bureaus. It was a
                    competitive game. Those who were clever and savvy enough about the equipment and
                    what it could do, etc., knew how to purchase it, etc., get key individuals who
                    were pre-trained to come on board and go out and take care of these things. But
                    it was not cost effective the way it was being done. They knew it, but they were
                    not about to give up the turf battle. When we got into the classified part of it
                    called CIHS, classified information handling systems, that was handled by the
                    Office of Communications. The whole criteria and the manner in which that was
                    planned and implemented was controlled and operated out of the Office of
                    Communications. It was then on a much more equitable basis, distributing this or
                    that to each of the five Bureaus. The same thing was true of the other forms of
                    communications...secure voice and data traffic. Of course, traditionally, the
                    European Bureau always got the biggest and best of everything for the longest
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Even although its requirements often were not as demanding
                        as say getting something out to Israel or Egypt, or a post under fire.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes. I think beyond the shadow of a doubt, two or three classical
                    confrontations in the Middle East, actual wars between Israel and various Arab
                    countries, and all of the acts of terrorism highlighted this deficiency. All the
                    troubles in Latin and Central America with terrorism, as well, reemphasized the
                    lack of equality in the distribution in the system. It became painfully obvious
                    at the M management level that there was something wrong with this. Finally
                    reviews were put into place and common sense set in. And there was also the
                    whole issue of fighting the drug war. You can't fight very effective drug wars
                    unless you have real time, live time communications capability. It can't be
                    done. Today it can be done, thanks to this integration and strong leadership.
                    Somebody had to come in and dictate and stop these turf battles. It was stupid
                    and senseless.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is where you give the credit to the heads of the
                        Office of Communications while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, they certainly made their contribution. There was a huge program
                    that the Office of Communications was promoting, it was called the Department of
                    State Telecommunication Network. It was more than just a plan. There was an
                    actual request for proposal, and RFP, which is an open bid advertised in all the
                    commercial papers and trade magazines inviting all the communications giants to
                    come up with bid proposals for implementing this plan for the State Department.
                    It was to encompass all other agencies under the State Department auspices
                    overseas. We would provide the umbrella and they would be contributing to the
                    cost. In its design it was a very ambitious, badly needed project. It did not
                    make it all the way through Congress but it certainly is being implemented in
                    other ways today out in the field. In this particular work I am in now as a
                    retired annuitant, I am seeing very strong concrete evidence of it. We have been
                    able to accomplish so much more in the last five years with fewer people and
                    better technology than in the whole previous 25 years that I can remember. It is
                    just incredible the things that can be done today, especially in remote parts of
                    the world like we are in now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you went off not exactly off to a remote area, you
                        went to Ottawa.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, in between that I went off to the Sinai.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, tell me about the Sinai, the Multilateral Forces
                        and Observers.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I did that primarily for two reasons to be very truthful. One was that
                    I was kind of burned out after four years in Washington doing basically two full
                    time jobs. Again the career promotional track settled down after some quiet
                    success in the beginning. I said I would force the issue. And I frankly just
                    wanted to compete in another whole new area. The Office of Communications had
                    initially been responsible for the Camp David implementation process out in the
                    Sinai. In the transition of that operation it then became the task of the MFO
                    based in Rome, an international group of eleven countries to carry out this
                    mandate. And therefore when this invitation appeared in the Department, I bid on
                    it and qualified and spent a year out there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing? Will you explain what this force
                        was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: The MFO was established to, I believe, invite other nations into the
                    peace making process to make it more diplomatic, more appealing to the two
                    factions, Israel and Egypt. And, of course, out of the foreign aide given to
                    both Israel and Egypt to the tune of almost $3.5 billion both countries had to
                    pay the cost of the MFO operations, so it was not for free. There were eleven
                    countries participating in the peacekeeping operation in the northern part of
                    the Sinai desert.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your main task?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: My task and that of the other civilian observers, was to do
                    reconnaissance work by air in each of the four divided zones of the Sinai. One
                    week we would do that by air and the second week we would follow up on the
                    ground physically examining, inspecting, the various sites within a given zone.
                    This would go on week after week. The whole intent and purpose was to assure
                    both parties and our government that the Camp David peace treaty would be kept
                    in tact and therefore any violations that were witnessed or sighted would be
                    immediately discussed and there would be no military arms build up in the Sinai
                    again. It has worked very successfully.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dealing with communications, what particularly were you
                        doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I was truly out of cone, other than the actual gear we used. My role
                    was strictly to this international organization as an observer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were going out either flying or in a jeep and
                        inspect a place?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes. We worked in teams. There would be always two observers and a
                    minimum of one Egyptian or Israeli accompanying us within that zone of
                    operations. But I was completely divorced from my previous work in
                    communications.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have talked to some people who were in one phase or
                        another of this. Could you talk about your impression of how the Israelis
                        treated this and operated and also the Egyptians?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, it was a very interesting operation, I thought. The procedures
                    were clearly established by the Camp David Peace Accord, the treaty that was
                    signed by both parties. It was basically a very simple process in terms of the
                    reconnaissance work and the examination of sites. There was a short advance
                    notice given of where we would be at a given specific time. There was no
                    question of what we were doing and why. There was very little lack of
                    cooperation on either side, both parties understood the nature of the missions.
                    They also understood that if this thing was to be successful they would have to
                    cooperate. I don't think there was any deliberate, malicious attempt by either
                    party to ever violate this treaty or slow us down in our work. They understood
                    what their role was and the importance of it. It was really, truly a unique
                    experience to be able to go out there and do this. We would be on assignment for
                    a one-year leave of absence with full reemployment rights. Some people extended
                    who would retire out there. But we were basically not identified with the State
                    Department at all. We consisted of 12 former military officers and 12 civilians
                    on loan or secondment.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have interviewed some people who were there when this
                        was first set up and at that time there was a feeling that whereas the
                        Egyptians were kind of going along with it, the Israelis kept pushing,
                        trying to slip things in. It was kind of a game for them. There were some
                        showdowns, etc. But I take it by the time you got there it was a fairly
                        mature process and the games had already been played.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I can appreciate what you are saying and in the time frame I was there
                    these difficulties had been ironed out. I know specifically what you are
                    referring to because there is still evidence of what took place out there. Keep
                    in mind as the Israelis retrenched back towards the original borders and gave up
                    reluctantly or otherwise the territory in the Sinai, they did it in phases which
                    I think is exactly what the treaty called for. They obviously were reluctant to
                    give up the territory for obvious reasons. I think today if you were to ask them
                    they are perfectly at peace with this, especially as they have negotiated a
                    peace with the PLO now. They have matured, obviously. In those days, however,
                    the very base on which the MFO is located on was a prior Israeli air base. The
                    process of releasing that and trying to come to what they considered a fair
                    price on that air base and its value, there were a lot of disagreements. They
                    were unhappy. But that is not uncommon with the Israelis. They are not an easy
                    people to please. They never seem to get enough. They are always second-guessing
                    everyone. They always know better.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a pattern one has seen. A small country and if you
                        are not aggressive you can get ground under.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I wouldn't call it insecurity, it is just aggressiveness. But they
                    literally blew up some facilities on that base. They knocked out some windows,
                    destroyed trees, unnecessarily because they didn't get their way. It was
                    restored to some extent. Yes, it may have slowed up the process a little bit.
                    Did they gain anything from this? I doubt it seriously. It was just an act of
                    stubbornness. However at this time they can travel to and from Egypt and vice
                    versa so it was only a question of time.</p>
                <p>The original site, though, of the State Department's communications operation
                    when this all began was up on the Giddi Pass, one of the famous strategic
                    points. There were very important tanks battles and other confrontations that
                    went on in that area. That is where they located the communications sight, it
                    was perfect for this. There were contract operators out there implementing the
                    security zones called E-Systems. They did the actual monitoring. But then they
                    were replaced by the MFO.</p>
                <p>Now the civilian observers who actually do the physical sites and inspections are
                    all Americans, exclusively Americans. All the other contingents simply support
                    the operation.</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you came back to the Department for a little while
                        and then off to Ottawa. Is that right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were in Ottawa for a relatively short time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes. That was not by design or planning. It was a job opportunity that
                    developed my last year in the Department and I could not pass it up. It was a
                    very unique operation going on there. Ottawa is a particular kind of assignment.
                    I assume in the past most of the ambassadors have been political appointees.
                    That speaks for itself. The relationship with the President is always a very
                    close one. So in terms of a standard State Department assignment it is not that.
                    It can be a tough one. Every agency in the Federal phone directory in Washington
                    DC, I think, is up there. A lot of work goes on. There are numerous visitors. It
                    is a very different kind of assignment.</p>
                <p>Anyway the assignment lasted barely a year. I became ill and had to return to the
                    States for treatment for cancer and spent a full year doing that in Kansas City,
                    my home place of residence. At the end of that period I had had a lot of time to
                    think about all these things and felt very strongly that maybe things like this
                    happen for a reason and perhaps it would be in my best interest to retire. We
                    had planned to do that anyway after a four-year assignment in Ottawa, but it was
                    curtailed by about three years.</p>
                <p>So consequently when I started getting some phone calls from Washington from my
                    friends in communications, I didn't exactly know why in the beginning, this was
                    in late 1991 and early part of 1992. Slowly but surely the mystery became
                    revealed and I applied for the retired annuitant program that I am now in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is where you can come back and work up to a certain
                        point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Since you have been doing this, have you concentrated in
                        an area or sort of going off?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, that is one of the good and bad points of this program. We are
                    allowed to work for the most part a maximum of three to six months of the year.
                    In terms of the assignment they basically ask us to be available for worldwide
                    assignment if possible. And to an extent I have been very fortunate because
                    three out of five assignments I have enjoyed so far have been in the former
                    Soviet Union. I went to Tashkent in the summer of 1992, June, July and part of
                    August; followed by Tbilisi in October, November and part of December. In
                    between those two assignments I was asked to go to New York for a brief period,
                    which turned out to be a month. So I had a pretty active year the second half of
                    1992. And then this year when 1993 rolled around there was kind of a down period
                    until about the end of March when they asked me to go to Caracas for about a
                    month. I had never been there before and I enjoyed that. But it was still not
                    the kind of assignment that these are out here in the former Soviet Union. This
                    makes my second trip to Bishkek.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, as long as I have you here, tell me a little about
                        Tashkent. What was your impression?. The Soviet Union has basically
                        collapsed and some of its component parts have become independent states.
                        What was your impression of Tashkent which was the capital of Uzbekistan and
                        what you saw there and also how our very new embassy was operating
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, as you can appreciate, for someone who had never worked or
                    traveled behind the Iron Curtain, almost anything you do or see is an adventure.
                    You arrive knowing very little about the assignment other than a few simple
                    briefings that advanced teams can give you. You might pick up an atlas or some
                    other type of informational guide to give you a clue before you pack or do
                    anything else. But at any rate the initial reactions for me were very, very
                    profound and unforgettable experiences. Tashkent was supposed to have been the
                    fourth largest city in the Soviet Union. I really have my doubts after seeing
                    Tashkent for ten weeks...June, July and August of 1992...I seriously have my
                    doubts about its superpower status...the Soviet Union and Tashkent's role in
                    it...judging by what I saw.</p>
                <p>You arrive there after a very long trip, having overnighted in Moscow. In those
                    days all of us entered through Moscow and fanned out to the various independent
                    states by way of Aeroflot. Well, of course, it is quite a shock to fly on
                    Aeroflot . I don't care how experienced you are traveling, that is a unique
                    experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's it like?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Oh, it is like no other airline in the world. I really think the
                    kindest description you can give of Aeroflot is simply a wide bodied cattle car.
                    They are not designed with comfort in mind or any of the amenities of life that
                    we are accustomed to, as Westerners, as Americans. They are simply devices for
                    getting huge numbers of people point to point at the cheapest possible cost.
                    Some of the impressions I you got will last with me forever. It is a very
                    impersonal experience. You find a seat and somehow as Westerners you seem to get
                    the last remaining seats on this huge plane. They are not very clean, to put it
                    mildly. They are not very comfortable. And I wonder how well they are maintained
                    as far as safety goes. The tires, for example, looked very bald. The ride is
                    okay. You are not about to be entertained on these flights in any form and you
                    are not going to receive any kind of food or drink that you might expect on a
                    normal airline. Consequently you are quite happy when you get there.</p>
                <p>Eventually you get there. The only arrangement for housing was the Intourist
                    Hotel where we stayed for ten solid weeks. Again the same type of experience
                    that the former Soviet Union offered foreigners. The all over city of Tashkent,
                    itself, is kind of unique. They had a major earthquake there in the late '60s.
                    Apparently the entire city had to be completely rebuilt. It took the Soviets,
                    they say, ten years to do that. Judging from the looks of things today, I don't
                    think that they ever went back and remodeled anything. Soviet construction is
                    quite a joke. A US seismologist passed through and took a few days look of the
                    overall city and quickly reached the conclusion that if they were to have
                    another major earthquake of the same proportions, 6 or 7 on the Richter scale,
                    the same thing would happen all over again. In other words they didn't learn
                    much from the previous experience.</p>
                <p>Soviet construction per se is crude, it functions, it is not particularly
                    esthetically pleasing and I really don't have much to say for it. An Intourist
                    hotel might be a classic example of how not to do it. It works, more or less,
                    but certainly is not comfortable. It is monotonous. It is just not a very
                    pleasant experience. Food, drink, culture, customs...Tashkent is described as a
                    moderate Moslem city. People are very sober. They dress very modestly. Nothing
                    is flashy or stylish in their clothing. The food that is available is again
                    pretty much the same type, very basic. You don't see very many over weight
                    people there, which I think speaks for itself. I would expect that the diet is
                    not exceptionally nutritious based upon what we were served in the Intourist
                    hotel day after day. It is not very plentiful either. Meats and dairy products
                    are almost nonexistent.</p>
                <p>The city, itself, is kind of nondescript in the sense that it is not alive. You
                    see huge, huge avenues laid out in typical Soviet style that would dwarf any US
                    city. We would not be able to afford the luxury of taking such huge spaces for
                    large avenues and underpasses for pedestrians. Many and most of these things
                    were designed for two reasons. I think one to psychologically give the people a
                    sense of openness because they were living in such congested, disagreeable
                    apartments and when they got out into the open people had a sense of freedom.
                    They typically have theaters, a building dedicated to annual circus visits,
                    things of this nature that were all very socialist in design and intent.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>You didn't really see what you see so commonly in America. For example, obviously
                    you didn't see churches, because of the prohibition on religion. You didn't see
                    building easily identified as schools. You didn't see hospitals as such. Yes you
                    would see ambulances from time to time. You saw police and civil guards.
                    Tashkent had more than its share of those. They were more readily visible in the
                    government building area grounds for obvious reasons. But likewise they were
                    very apt to stop motorists frequently and randomly one suspects more for bribes
                    then anything else. Or maybe it was their only source of income. Who knows.</p>
                <p>Tashkent, not unlike some other cities I have seen, are very dark at night. They
                    are poorly lighted. It is very dangerous from a physical point of view to walk
                    on their sidewalks at night because they have so many open holes and dangerous
                    debris lying around. There is not the cleanliness and the upkeep of the
                    buildings. There would be debris everywhere. Tashkent in its own right was far
                    better and cleaner than other places that I have seen for whatever reason I
                    don't understand. Maybe because there were the vehicles and crews to do these
                    kinds of chores of maintaining some standard of living and hygiene.</p>
                <p>You would go to open markets where the farming community would sell the products
                    to the local community which was quite an interesting sight. The conclusion that
                    I reached very quickly was that what was produced today is consumed today. Not
                    much technology in terms of preservation which must obviously create great
                    problems in the winter time. How do you survive in the winter? Some very basic
                    questions from which you can draw obvious conclusions just by observing and
                    watching and seeing what goes on. Everywhere you go in this part of the world,
                    also there must be concern about the availability of fuel, whether it is for the
                    few cars that are around or the planes in which you can get in and out of these
                    places. It's becoming a real serious problem for all purposes...government,
                    transportation, industrial production...the lack of vehicles, the maintenance of
                    roads, the availability of fuel. The railroads that you do see, and I have
                    noticed this now in two of the three countries I have been in, look poorly
                    maintained. The equipment is old, it is rusty, it is dilapidated. I don't think
                    you could find anything similar to this anywhere in the US today, other than in
                    a museum, perhaps. It is incredible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of our embassy in Tashkent?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, this was my first experience in this program, working out here in
                    these new CIS countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: CIS stands for?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: At this point of time we used Commonwealth of Independent States.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These are sort of the central Asian states including up
                        through Georgia, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes, I think there is a total of 15.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really former Soviet states not including Latvia, Estonia
                        and Lithuania.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Right. In all probability we will only serve on this program for maybe
                    three or four years total, five perhaps. Maybe they will eventually designate a
                    permanent party. But, anyway, getting back to your point. This particular
                    embassy superficially appeared to be a beautiful building, an ideal selected
                    spot. It was obviously going to be an area in which the Uzbek government wanted
                    the diplomatic missions who were coming to stay in. We were given a building
                    which was originally supposed to be used for say a chamber of commerce or
                    exhibition hall. As it turned out it was anything but functional. It actually
                    had a fully furnished discotheque with refrigerators and everything in the
                    basement of it. We had no real protective security means to cordon off that
                    area. For security reasons in the beginning it was a nightmare. We didn't know
                    who was down there, who would use it. We couldn't use it freely even for a
                    luncheon facility. That is just one of the anomalies of this whole thing.</p>
                <p>As you went into the building there was an atrium running up through 60 percent
                    of the building from the main floor up to the ceiling with non-usable space. We
                    were left with 40 percent of the building to use as an embassy which was just
                    unworkable. No matter what operation you are talking about. Whether it was
                    consular operations or GSO or communications, or USIS, or administration, it
                    really didn't matter. The offices were tiny. In addition, from a physical
                    standpoint of view, the building used the typical aluminum wiring, nothing
                    worked. It was dangerous and easily set on fire. The engineering of it was very
                    poor. The Brazilians have an expression that pretty well sizes it up. They say
                    bonito mas ordinario , “cute but ordinary,” and that was really it in a
                    nutshell.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the spirit of the embassy? Here was a brand new
                        state and we were setting up things. Could you describe the feeling?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: That is a very interesting question because you could ask the same
                    question, of course, in each and every embassy in the 15 newly established
                    places. I actually arrived there after it had been opened for about two and a
                    half months. I was starting from scratch building communications. Even the
                    equipment had not arrived when I was first there. What did come in came in on
                    support flights. But getting to your point and question, initially, of course,
                    there was a tremendous problem in staffing these embassies. You can imagine
                    being tasked with opening 15 embassies at one time. How do you start? Who do you
                    choose? Language skills. Who is available? So somehow you get a team together,
                    brief them and assure them that you will hold their hand and support them. So
                    spirits are high. Volunteers are in some cases ambitious, some are just simply
                    romantic, some are well prepared, and some are not prepared to even do the task
                    that has to be accomplished.</p>
                <p>I would say initially the personal relationships are really key to getting
                    something going effectively. In this particular case, Tashkent, had such a high
                    number in turnover, rotation of TDYers, that it was really painful to those few
                    who were permanent party. They were tired of this constant turnover. They had no
                    assurances that others would volunteer and become permanent party and quite
                    honestly I don't think their expectations were very high. What they did see or
                    were able to predict was not something that you really wanted to think about too
                    long. In other words, .we raised the flag, we opened the doors, a few of us knew
                    what we were supposed to do and how to get it started. We have a cadre of FSNs
                    who didn't even understand what an FSN was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: FSN being Foreign Service National, local employees.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: How these people were selected, cleared and hired god only knows.
                    Obviously mistakes were made. Some of the wrong people may have been hired, some
                    overqualified and unhappy in their jobs as well. They are looking to us for
                    guidance and instruction as to what they are supposed to do not having the
                    faintest idea what GSO stands for...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: General Services Officer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: You can appreciate this situation. In the case of Tashkent there were a
                    few extra demands made upon us there, which eventually started to tax everyone's
                    perseverance and patience. That was security requirements. The building was not
                    in any shape or form whereby we could walk off in the evening and leave it
                    unattended. We literally had to become Marine Security Guards there after hours.
                    So we set up rosters. Everyone took their fair share. In other words from six in
                    the evening until six in the morning we had American presence on the property.
                    You did your fair share and there were only seven or eight of us there so your
                    duty came up pretty regularly.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>There was another problem, the roof was leaking on this new building and it had
                    to be repaired. Well, from a security point of view you can not let a lot of
                    foreign workers on the top of the embassy unattended or unaccompanied. So we had
                    to climb up the side of the building in the hot sun, sit up there and roast with
                    them and do duty on the roof. But not everybody could do this. Some had fear of
                    heights and were afraid to go on the roof. So it seemed like you could not find
                    enough time to do your real job, the job you were sent out there for.</p>
                <p>And then too, I think, older, more experienced people realized that they would
                    have to do a little bit more than they were sent out there to do. They have to
                    be leaders. They have to show a little bit of initiative, motivation and all of
                    those things you would expect of older people. Younger people, if they were not
                    well prepared before coming out there, had to be baby sat. Then there was the
                    language problem. Not everybody could speak Russian. So that became a problem.
                    There were just many logistical problems. You would run out of this or that.
                    Something as simple as a stapler, or paper for a laser jet printer. Something
                    you would take for granted anywhere else. Or the fuses or lights would go and
                    you couldn't find any replacements. This or that wouldn't work. Or the drivers
                    would go off and disappear and leave you stranded at night. What do you do?
                    Hitchhike, take the subway, or what? It was always something new. Or you would
                    go to the airport to pick up some diplomatic pouches. No one had ever done this,
                    so how do we do this? Or how do we pay for these pouches? No one knew how to do
                    it. There was no form. They didn't know how much to charge you for excess
                    baggage. Every time you turned there was a new problem or new question that
                    nobody could answer and therefore nothing happened. And on and on it went.</p>
                <p>I would say that most could enjoy the challenge for about six weeks and then a
                    combination of things would start to set in and you would say, “Well, how many
                    more days do I have to go?” And maybe the next person who came in would have a
                    few more answers. But you kept looking for continuity, but you wouldn't always
                    find it. I think it was painful in the administrative cone. The other
                    officers...there was usually only one officer for each responsibility and some
                    officers had to double up doing political/econ reporting. Those who were
                    qualified in languages had extra duties because they had to help be interpreters
                    all the time and their patience would get thin some times.</p>
                <p>But I think overall most people seriously enjoyed the challenge, but they knew
                    that the only way to get this off the ground eventually was to get a permanent
                    party cadre established there, and that was not easy to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then you went to Georgia, to Tbilisi. Now I assume a
                        great deal that you said about Tashkent applied to Tbilisi. Could you talk
                        about what was different...How are we doing on time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: We are getting pretty late now.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is October 15. Dick, could you follow through. In
                        other words you went to Tbilisi when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: The trip to Tbilisi was about the same time last year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So we are talking around October, 1992. You went into some
                        detail about how things were in Tashkent, what was different in
                        Tbilisi?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: I think just about everything was different in Tbilisi in a sense that
                    Tashkent seemed to be a template of Moscow in many respects, whereas Georgia was
                    very much Georgian, not only in the topography, the weather, but I think more
                    importantly in the people, their independent nature. As we know right now the
                    armed conflict has really not settled down. No thanks to the Russians taking
                    sides surprisingly in a kind of unappreciative way towards Shevardnadze, but I
                    guess maybe that is predictable too. It was basically from the very start a much
                    different trip. The simple logistics of getting into Tbilisi, which is a very
                    poverty stricken country today, with, I think, very limited resources. Almost
                    the entire infrastructure of the country seems to be coming to a grinding
                    halt.</p>
                <p>Transportation, for example. We had to wait in Vienna, Austria because the plane
                    was delayed twelve hours. It is a very unique arrangement that the Austrians
                    have with the government of Georgia to ferry people back and forth. Due to the
                    severe lack of fuel of all kinds for both heating and transportation, but
                    particularly transportation, flights in and out of Tbilisi are limited to once a
                    week, on Saturdays, or at least they were at that time. I doubt that things have
                    improved a year later. At any rate the Austrians had built two marvelous four
                    star hotels, one in Tbilisi, Georgia and the other one up in the Caucus
                    Mountains. They seem to have a monopoly on the tourist industry there, what
                    little there is. Basically they would be catering to rich Europeans and other
                    Westerners who ski and want to get away to a unique romantic type of place. At
                    any rate they also have locked into this hotel arrangement, one charter flight a
                    week, which is a small Aeroflot type plane which carries both cargo and people
                    once a week on Saturdays. That is how we managed to get in there in October.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>In the course of that two and a half months of TDY there it was very interesting.
                    By the contrast the Georgian people are very lively. They are well known for
                    their dancing, their culture, their songs, their history and likewise their
                    food, at least in the times when it was plentiful. They are marvelous
                    entertainers. They will offer 50 toasts a night at any Georgian table to which
                    one would be invited. And yet, it is very sad to be there because you can see
                    the strong, horrible evidence of a civil war that took place right in the heart
                    of Tbilisi where very selectively key government buildings were literally
                    destroyed in the civil war which took place I believe December, January,
                    February of say late 1991, early 1992. Consequently it is almost a miracle that
                    anything of any real importance was left in tact and that Shevardnadze could
                    still run a government. But apparently they did have new parliamentary elections
                    some time in early or mid 1992. His fledgling government was trying to hang on
                    when I arrived there in October, November and December. Consequently what one
                    was able to do in terms of getting a real look at the country was somewhat
                    limited and by that I mean primarily because of very high risk security factors.
                    Travel was or should have been restricted to daylight hours only. At night it
                    was not uncommon to hear gunfire randomly all night long on and off throughout
                    the city and therefore unnecessary travel was completely discouraged. All of us
                    were housed in the four star hotel there at the time for lack of housing, with,
                    I think, two exceptions. Two of the single female officers had found
                    accommodations that were, I guess, adequate. But at any rate the city at night
                    was extremely dark and dangerous and we were pretty much confined to the hotel.
                    We did have a satellite dish on the balcony of my room, which we used for
                    emergency communications after hours. There were numerous military flights,
                    humanitarian assistance in a project called Project Hope, and the third or
                    fourth flight was taking place during the time I was there.</p>
                <p>But to answer your question, this would be somewhat of an explanation of the
                    contrast between the two places.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain the state of relations between Georgia
                        and the United States? What were you doing and how were things working
                        out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, I think the relationship between the two governments, in light of
                    recent past history with Shevardnadze, were probably as excellent as one could
                    expect. Certainly I would imagine that we were doing everything possible to
                    support him and to try and convince the people that this was a beginning, one in
                    which we were quite interested and of course we were doing everything that could
                    be done, piecemeal fashion, to begin to put things together.</p>
                <p>One thing I noticed taking place there that I suppose has also happened in other
                    countries out here, is that there was a team of international jurists there at
                    the time. Apparently they were working together with the new government trying
                    to give them some idea of how to start writing a new constitution. That would
                    really be the first real fundamental legal step in establishing, I suppose, a
                    new democracy that they were not accustomed to.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For the historian later, what was the civil war
                        about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: What little that I could piece together, apparently there were many,
                    not unlike other CIS countries, many ethnic groups who, over perhaps decades and
                    decades had their axes to grind. Perhaps family feuds, turf battles, political
                    battles of whatever sort. I suppose if one uses a little imagination, and
                    perhaps even reads Fitzroy McLean, a British diplomat's book, Eastern Approaches
                    you could get a real feel for what Joseph Stalin did and the repercussions many
                    years later. His mass deportation of ethnic groups to opposite ends of the
                    Soviet Union obviously had its accumulative effect, in my opinion. I believe we
                    are starting to see reaction to this purging, or ethnic cleansing or whatever
                    you might call it.</p>
                <p>Then the fact that he who was in power in the old system had all the perks. And
                    those who were in power didn't want to leave it because it would probably mean a
                    lost of an apartment, a car and all the things that went along with it. So there
                    is a classless society in today's new democracy starting to show what power
                    struggles really mean.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dick, how were we setting up our embassy at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well the embassy there in Tbilisi was certainly a very unique setup.
                    The government had apparently pointed out one building in the early days and
                    designated it as the most suitable for the US embassy. Apparently that was it,
                    there were not many alternative choices. It was a very old, classical building.
                    The very architecture of the building, quite honestly, did not make it very
                    functional for diplomatic purposes. The ceilings were perhaps 20 feet high and
                    it would be very difficult functionally to use all that space effectively, let
                    alone to heat it in the wintertime, which we found out very quickly. The
                    electrical wiring in the building was dilapidated. And yet you could see obvious
                    signs that this was the equivalent of some ministry building with very ornate
                    woodwork and doors, the high ceilings, the tapestry, expensive and old oil
                    paintings in various places throughout the building. In some locations there
                    were fireplaces. So with a little imagination you could just about picture the
                    old establishment, perhaps even the last days of the Tsar, living the life of
                    Riley. And, of course, that came to a quick end.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was our Ambassador while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Kent Brown.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he an experienced Soviet hand?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, I understand that most all of these Ambassadors at one time or
                    another were very experienced Soviet hands. I did not know any of them
                    personally not having served in the Soviet Union or behind the Iron Curtain. But
                    I would certainly say he and his wife were probably two of the most charming
                    people and in my opinion expertly chosen to be ambassador and leaders for a new
                    embassy. They were really, really appreciated by all the embassy staff. And the
                    team loyalty that they had generated was showing obvious results there. Because
                    it is a difficult post in many respects to work in and yet the morale seemed
                    very, very high for obvious reasons, they had very strong leadership.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was it communicationswise?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: The commo set up was pretty much the same as it is in all of these
                    embassies. It was effective. The Achilles heel to all of it, of course, is the
                    city power that we rely upon...most of these embassies that don't have real true
                    generators that we need for emergencies, during power failures in the city...
                    for all practical purposes the telephone installation there and the
                    communications gear was very effective. Thank god.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you were there for how long?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Two and a half months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any consideration because of the fighting that
                        they might close it down again?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: At that point in time I don't think there was any such consideration.
                    There was not actually out right civil war in the city during the time I was
                    there. There were factions, of course, that were doing their thing at nighttime,
                    primarily gun running and smuggling I suppose of all kinds. Of course the lack
                    of fuel kept that to a minimum too. The real true fighting was up in the one
                    corner of the country where they are having the secessionist effort, I believe
                    the Russians are backing to some extent. It did make you feel nervous because
                    after all you came out of the hotel in the morning and you would see the ground
                    covered with shell casings on the street and you could hear it at night.
                    Sometimes umpteen animals would come strolling into the hotel, the lobby, with
                    their automatic weapons, somewhat drunk. So anything could have happened without
                    any advanced notice. So you had to keep your wits about you and look and observe
                    and literally stay out of trouble or avoid it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well then let's move to the Kyrgyz Republic where you are
                        now on a temporary assignment. Were you here when we first set this place
                        up?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: No. My first visit here was this year in July and August.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When was it set up?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, I believe it was one of the very first. I recall seeing it on the
                    front of State Magazine and would guess that was probably in early 1992. There
                    was a large group of us who were recruited in the spring of that year, retired
                    annuitants, to help alleviate the personnel shortages. We eventually got out
                    into the field...most of us went into Moscow and then fanned out over the
                    various CIS countries. This was in May and June, 1992. So I think the few
                    embassies which were able to get open and staffed quickly probably did so in
                    early 1992.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find Kyrgyzstan different from the other
                        places?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, in this situation here...I am particularly fond of Kyrgyzstan.
                    The people are marvelous. I have learned an awful lot in being able to talk with
                    the people about their culture. One can visit a museum that is full of
                    antiquities and historical artifacts. It is very accessible. It shows you a
                    very, very sharp contrast with their historical past up to and including 70
                    years of communism, all within the same museum. So if that is your thing, it is
                    available here. But I would say equally importantly is that fact that one can
                    freely talk to the Kyrgyz people here and get a perspective...this is all in
                    English, of course...of their country and traditions and still get a balanced
                    feel for their patience and tolerance of other ethnic groups, particularly the
                    Russians. I think that really shows a great deal of maturity on their part which
                    may not be the case in many of the other republics. I believe that is really
                    going to be their strongest trump that will really attract US support. And they
                    may make progress far faster than the others. But there are numerous reasons why
                    Bishkek is very enjoyable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What have been the greatest changes in the communications
                        field since you came into the Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Looking back over almost 30 years, I first entered the communications
                    business, which was in the Vietnam era...I was drafted into the US Army and
                    working radio teletype, Morse code communications on Rhein Main Air Base, and in
                    late 1966 I came on board with State expecting to do somewhat the same things. I
                    was a little bit surprised when that was not the case, for various reasons.
                    Nevertheless, looking at the overall state of the art, I would say that we have
                    made astronomical advances in the technology, the management, the budget, the
                    staffing, just about every possible aspect of running this professional cone
                    within State. Most of these dramatic changes have really taken place starting
                    with the appearance of what we call the TERP equipment, which was the beginning
                    of computerization in communications in early to mid 1970s. I think we have made
                    phenomenal progress in an extremely short time thanks to a very generous
                    budget.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is there a difference between the communications person
                        today than there was...when you came in you said you were part of a new wave
                        which was basically to replace mostly women who had been with State during
                        the war where the male communicators ended up in the military. Is there a
                        different type person who is a communicator now than when you came in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Oh, I think definitely so. The average person who was recruited in the
                    mid-sixties and for a period of at least 10 or 12 years to follow was well
                    trained in one branch of the military or another in communications. It was an
                    outright prerequisite to be hired by State to have prior military service in the
                    business. That was all fine and good. Unfortunately, very little progress was
                    made and many of the skills that were recruited with were lost there for a
                    period of time simply because of the way we did business during that period of
                    time about the mid 70's. Of course at some point in all of this business you
                    have technology and personnel and I think that is your question. To answer that
                    question I would say that the person who is recruited today is far better
                    educated, more roundly educated to a higher degree the in the past. Does this
                    make the individuals who are recruited or selected better trained, better
                    prepared? I think today you would probably use the word information management
                    specialist because today is far better we are really looking at systems more
                    than we are components or individual installations. When you look at this whole
                    business on a global or regional scale, you have to have individuals who are
                    able to visualize, to be extremely versatile and flexible and to be able to meet
                    the requirements. I think the overall individual recruited is far superior in
                    many respects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are there many women coming back?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because when you said you were just going to the military,
                        there wouldn't be very many women available.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>STOCKMAN: There were very few women who I ever came in contact with in the
                    military communications field. Perhaps it was just the places where I was
                    assigned.</p>
                <p>To round this up I would say that overall there is a much better balance in both
                    management and in the newest recruited persons, men and women. Certainly their
                    backgrounds come from all types of information management, private industry,
                    government, etc. The individual who is recruited basically is, I suppose
                    expecting far greater achievements in a much quicker pace then we did in our
                    day. I think we were more patient. We were to some extent more disciplined. I
                    think the individual who is recruited today is a different breed of individual.
                    They seem to be very independent, know pretty much what they want out of life,
                    they are perhaps a lot more democratic and understanding. So one his past
                    experience and somehow merge it into today's working environment. Yet we are the
                    bridge, so to speak, of transition from the past to the present and somehow one
                    has to assist and help the new people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One last question on this Dick, at one point I was with
                        the Board of Examiners for the Foreign Service talking to people who were
                        coming out of various other cones to become regular Foreign Service officers
                        in the political, economic and administrative fields. I had several people
                        who came out of the communications side. I was struck by the fact that they
                        might have been doing communications but the really weren't very interested
                        in the political environment where they were. Now talking to you it is very
                        obvious for anybody reading this conversation that you were interested in
                        the political environment. But I would get a hold of people who said, “That
                        is not my business. I am hear to send messages back and forth.” A very
                        narrow view which may have reflected the military background they may have
                        been coming from...you did your job and that was that. I would think one
                        would have to be interested in what was happening in Bishkek and the people
                        in order to survive some of these difficult countries. Do you find a
                        different in the people you are getting as far as that sort of thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: Well, I think you have hit the nail right on the head with this
                    question. I believe that the real challenge for the new Foreign Service, the
                    more democratized Foreign Service, is the administration of personnel actions
                    and assignments, etc. and even at a post of a small size, for the post
                    management to be able to survive and make it work, is going to be in
                    understanding this difference not only in personalities but with the focus, for
                    example, in communications, to integrate that person into the country team
                    effort. Things have to change from the way they were in the past. I saw very
                    dramatic examples of this in a very effective way through the invitation of the
                    ambassador, for example, Ronald Palmer in Lome, Togo. He was excellent in doing
                    this. Also Nancy Rawls at that time. They would be classic examples, there were
                    others. In Riyadh, for example, one would participate very actively. Ottawa was
                    probably the best example of current modern day integration of all staff members
                    into country team meetings and specialized meetings the Ambassador held for
                    administrative officers.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was Tom Niles was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: No, but I can't remember right off hand who it was.</p>
                <p>But the point to make is just this. Some individuals like to practice what we
                    call the green door syndrome. Hide behind the door under the protection of the
                    security umbrella and not come out of the cave, so to speak. Many individuals
                    find that very repulsive and disagreeable and certainly in the case of young
                    married people it is very disagreeable and certainly ostracizes them, and
                    particularly the wife. It makes for a very difficult life and one not very
                    enjoyable.</p>
                <p>My own feelings I think it is what you make it. If you show your true colors you
                    will be accepted. If you make the extra effort you will be accepted. If you
                    reciprocate on a small scale I think you will also be accepted. Again, in the
                    past, there were several efforts made in developing an upward mobility program.
                    I tried on a couple of occasions to get more experience in administration. I
                    didn't succeed, but maybe it happened for a reason.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, one never knows, like the Sinai thing. Well, Dick I
                        want to thank you very much. It has been great.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>STOCKMAN: It has been very enjoyable.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
