<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001624">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Ambassador Sol Polansky </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2010-03-16"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2010-03-16"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>Foreign Affairs Series</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR SOL POLANSKY</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date:July 1,1992</p>
                <p>Copyright 2009 ADST</p>
                <p>[Note: This transcript was not edited by Ambassador Polansky.]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wonder if you could tell me a bit about when and where
                        you were born and about your education and that sort of thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I was born in Newark, New Jersey and my mother told me I was born on
                    the 5th of November, so I used to celebrate my birthday on the 5th of November,
                    until I had to go into the Navy at the start of World War II and I had to
                    produce a birth certificate and, lo and behold, the birth certificate said I was
                    born on the 7th of November, 1926. I don't know how the discrepancy occurred.
                    After that, I put down the 7th of November. That seemed to have a certain amount
                    of appeal when I came into the Foreign Service because my first assignment was
                    Moscow and the Russians celebrate the October Revolution on November 7th. I
                    could tell everybody that I was a child of the Revolution. Now with the end of
                    the Soviet empire, it's lost its meaning. My parents moved from New Jersey when
                    I was about five years old. We got on a bus and as I understand it, because I
                    really don't remember it, rode out to southern California where we had
                    relatives. We went to a town called El Monte, a bedroom community of Los
                    Angeles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We joined the same exodus, because of the Depression. We
                        left Chicago and went to South Pasadena. We took an old Rio I think.I was
                        born in 1928 and we came out in 1931 or 1932.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I went to grammar school and high school in El Monte. In 1944, I joined
                    the Navy. I took the tests for radio technician school, which I passed; I went
                    to boot camp and then went to radio technician school in Del Monte, California,
                    and promptly flunked out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Showing your aptitude for the Foreign Service immediately
                        there!! (lots of laughter)</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: I then enlisted in weatherman's school which I did manage to complete
                    successfully and then was assigned to various Naval Air bases within the United
                    States. Then right, at the end of the war, they were going to put us on a sea
                    plane that was going out to an atomic bomb tesout in the Pacific. For some
                    reason they took all of the reserve enlisted meand officers off the ship. I
                    wound up spending the last months in the Navy at Alameda Naval Air station in
                    California. I was discharged and immediately applied to the University of
                    California at Berkeley, to go to school. It was a good school. I picked it for
                    no apparent reason, except my brother went there, so I went there. Watching kids
                    today sweat through their applications to various schools is an entirely
                    different experience. I really can't explain why, except perhaps because my
                    parents were born in Russia, I then began to study Russian at Berkeley, with the
                    idea of perhaps doing something in the government. I spent four, wonderful years
                    at Berkeley and then at the end of those four years, decided to apply for
                    graduate school at various places, including Columbia, which has a Russian
                    Institute. I was accepted and got in a car with a friend and drove across the
                    United States and wound up in New York City; looked for a place to stay and
                    signed up for classes and spent two years at the Russian Institute.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the view of the Soviet Union and Russia that you
                        were getting? This was after thWar and moving into the Cold War. You did
                        spend a lot of time in the Soviet Union. What were you getting? Were you
                        talking to emigres who had axes to grind?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: No. When I think back on it, first of all academically, at Berkeley,
                    the people who taught us Russian history and government, were all Americans. At
                    Columbia, virtually all the faculty at that time, were Americans. There were no
                    emigres that I had, except for language. John Hazard was a professor of law.
                    Bill Mosely was my advisor and had done a lot of work in the Balkans and on
                    Russia. He had been married to a Russian.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were getting a relatively objective view of the Soviet
                        Union?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: That was certainly what we thought at the time and I think in trying to
                    analyze it, that would still be the case. I don't think there was an obvious,
                    strong, anti-communist bias as such. The Russians were on one side and we were
                    on the other. There were issues of national interest and security where we
                    collided rather than coincided.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You could almost check the progression of the Cold War
                        through out this time. By the time you got out of there in 1952, did you
                        feel that you were learning about the enemy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes, I think we did feel academically that we were learning about the
                    enemy, if you will. That was the way we looked at it. I had the opportunity to
                    go to Moscow, for the State Department, as a translator. At that time, the
                    Foreign Service did not have enough language trained Foreign Service officers
                    and there was in Moscow, a translation bureau that was run by the Americans,
                    British, Canadians, and Australians. It was a joint translation service and they
                    needed somebody. They needed a bachelor. I was engaged at the time, but not
                    married. I took the exam. Bob Tucker was the editor of the joint press reading
                    service in Moscow. I passed the exam and was assigned to Moscow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was not the Foreign Service exam, this was a
                        translator's exam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes. I came in as a staff officer and then was “Wristonized”.The first
                    two years I was in Moscow at the embassy, working as a translator, the
                    atmosphere was a very, very cold one. You had the “Doctor's plot” that was
                    coming up. You felt very much that you were an outsider and you were the enemy.
                    I didn't feel any sense of personal danger, but the political atmosphere was
                    such that, the US was the enemy. There was virtually no contact at the social
                    level. It wasn't a sense of isolation, but no real contact with ordinary
                    Russians, except the few who were working in the translation office with us in a
                    technical capacity. We never really talked about political subjects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This translation service was an extremely important part
                        of our window into the Soviet Union. I can't think of anything more deadly
                        than reading “Izvestia” and “Politika” day after day. How did you approach
                        this? What were we looking for? What was our coverage?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: First of all, I came in as the new member of the staff and took what
                    was handed to me. The way it worked, in the morning, Bob Tucker and his deputy
                    assigned articles from “Pravda” and “Izvestia” that focused on foreign policy
                    issues or editorials, with the idea of translating those as rapidly as we could
                    into English. You were sitting there with what you were going to translate and a
                    secretary/typist was sitting there with stencil paper in the typewriter and you
                    translated and she typed the translation onto the paper. Then it went into Bob
                    for editing. By the end of the morning, there would be a digest of the major
                    news articles in the day's press and that was made into multiple copies and sent
                    around to the various embassies that subscribed to the service. The afternoon
                    was spent looking at longer articles, either in the newspapers about economic or
                    social issues, or from magazines that would supposedly give a broader picture of
                    what was going on economically or socially. That became a second part or edition
                    of the translation service. All of those that were selected by Bob and his
                    deputy for the political content or possible changes in domestic or foreign
                    policy that might be reflected in those articles.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you reaching down into the provincial papers to pick
                        up developments there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: It was limited to the central newspapers—”Pravda”, “Izvestia”," Red
                    Star”, and “Trud”. You have to realize that at the time, it wasn't always that
                    easy to get subscriptions. The general feeling was that the entire media was so
                    controlled by Moscow that if you were really looking for policy direction, or
                    changes in policy, or hints about leadership changes, that all came out of the
                    central press. The local press was really a reflection of national issues and
                    the local issues were too irrelevant to require much attention.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were part of this machine that was beginning to feed
                        this new science of Kremlinology. Were your antennae being sharpened or were
                        you too involved in the daily work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I think I was so involved in having the right translation, really
                    focusing more on the translations themselves—obviously interested in their
                    content because of my interest in the Soviet Union, but it was up to Bob and his
                    deputy to decide what was to be translated. I think we subconsciously felt that
                    we had done our part and now it was up to the guys in the political and economic
                    sections to do whatever analysis that they could derive from those articles for
                    those who couldn't speak Russian.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your feeling about the Embassy? You were there
                        from 1952 until 1955. This was the death of Stalin; the Doctor's plot; the
                        new Troika—it wasn't really a Troika—Malenkov and others. What was life like
                        for you and your impression of the other people at the Embassy.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: Life for us, for me, when I arrived, there were five of us who lived in
                    a house rented by the US government. It was not far from the Foreign Ministry or
                    the Embassy. We had a Russian cook and Russian maids to clean the house. Three
                    of the five were Foreign Service Officers and then there was another translator
                    and myself. At the time we were all bachelors. We all got along well. I work
                    responsibilities didn't keep us separated. We got together in the evening and
                    talked about what was going on. We felt we were a junior part of the Embassy.
                    The other translator and I weren't directly involved in the activities at the
                    Embassy. We weren't excluded from it. After Stalin died, the Embassy itself was
                    forced to move from its location almost on Red Square up to its current location
                    on Tchaikovsky Street. That made it possible to bring together most of the
                    families to one place in terms of apartments. In my case, they wento the Embassy
                    Administrative Officer and DCM and asked if an apartment would be available so
                    that I could get married and bring my wife back to live. They agreed and so I
                    got married by proxy because it was difficult for my wife to get a visa without
                    being married. There were all sorts of problems, but we got that all
                    straightened out. She came and we moved into an apartment in the Embassy
                    compound and we becampart of the younger set of the Embassy. Virtually all of
                    the social life at that time focused on the American community, with some
                    interaction with the Canadians, Australians, British, and Germans. There was
                    very little contact with Russians. Not that we didn't look for it; it was a very
                    uncertain period and there was virtually no contact. I spent three years in
                    Moscow the first time. We had a number of chance conversations in Moscow with
                    Russians but we spent our first three years without having actually known a
                    Russian family or individual in any significant way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were there, George Kennan and Charles Bohlen
                        were Ambassadors. I realize they were somewhat removed, but still it was a
                        small Embassy, did you have much contact?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I arrived in Moscow in time to attend my first diplomatic reception
                    which was given by Mrs. Kennan because Ambassador Kennan was out in Berlin. They
                    wouldn't let him back in. I was saying good-bye to Mrs. Kennan who I had not met
                    before.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He had made his famous statement on ...in Russia, when he
                        got off the plane.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: He didn't come back, so I never really knew him. I met him a couple of
                    times after that. Then Charles Bohlen came. He was a very well liked and
                    respected person and I think he was open to everybody and I think everybody felt
                    that he was very much a leader and we were part of a family in that sense. As a
                    junior member of the Embassy staff by then, I was working in the Agricultural
                    section because the Agricultural Attache knew agriculture but not Russian, and I
                    knew Russian but not agriculture. So we teamed up. We took many trips and I
                    learned a lot from him and saw the Ambassador in that context. When your a
                    junior officer you hold a senior officer in a certain amount of awe,
                    particularly with the kind of reputation he had. He was very well liked by all
                    the women in the embassy. He was so damn handsome and dashing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did the Agricultural Attache do in the Soviet Union
                        at that time and how did you support him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Essentially what we were trying to do was to try and understand what
                    the Soviet agricultural policy was; what the growing conditions were like; what
                    the crops were likely to be, along with the economic and political connotations
                    that that had for the Soviet Union. It amounted to several parts. One was to
                    begin to try to read the pertinent Russian newspapers about agricultural
                    developments. We tried to figure out what was true and what was not. There was
                    also the time when they started their New Lands policy and what that meant for
                    the development of Soviet agriculture, particularly the grain crops. We had that
                    part which was reading the newspaper. The other part, to the extent that we
                    could, was to take trips to the main agricultural regions of the country, either
                    by plane, preferably by train, and sometimes by car. We tried to do that at
                    appropriate times in the growing season, in the harvest season, to try and get
                    first hand impressions as to what the growing season was like and what the crops
                    were like. That wasn't always easy.We had to do all our travel arrangements
                    through ......the Soviet agency that controlled foreigners. We would register a
                    trip and tell them how and when we were going and in effect they would tell us
                    whether we were going and in certain places they would block off part of the
                    proposed schedule. Sometimes they would give us reasons, sometimes they
                    wouldn't. We tried to look as carefully as we could at the crop situation. When
                    we were in cities, we tried to go into as many stores and collective farm
                    markets that we could, to try and get some sense of what the food situation was
                    like; what the food prices were like—whether there were price increases or not.
                    We tried to get some sense of how good the food supply was. This was before the
                    age of satellites so we were, in effect, the eyes and the ears of the US
                    government and of all the agencies that were interested in what was happening in
                    the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the impression of the attache, whom you were
                        supporting, of the efficiency, the developments in Soviet agriculture?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: In terms of the growing seasons, I think that his general impression
                    was that they were not particularly effective or efficient in areas of land that
                    were particularly well cultivated. There were a lot of weeds and that kind of
                    problem. I think he came from an atmosphere and background that suggested the
                    whole idea of collectivized agriculture was not an efficient way to do things.
                    He tended to have those views reinforced by what he saw—the lack of equipment in
                    the fields; the kind of equipment we saw that was not well tended. We didn't
                    always see a lot of equipment in the field or people working hard. Whereas, if
                    we were in a train or car driving through villages and saw the village private
                    plots, that farmers had, they seemed to be much more densely cultivated. When we
                    went to the market and saw what was available, we came away with the impression
                    that no matter how collectivized they were, people tended to devote more
                    attention, more care, and to the extent they could, to their private plots.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any feel for the New Lands Program? This sort of
                        turned into an ecological disaster.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I can tell you, we certainly didn't have the opportunity to talk to
                    Russian farmers. We didn't have the opportunity, voluntarily, or otherwise to
                    become part of that exercise. We flew over the New Lands on our way out to
                    Kazakstan, in the fall of 1954, and it went on endlessly. From a plane, we saw
                    mile after mile of newly plowed fields—vast areas. That was really quite
                    impressive. We wondered where all the machinery was that had done it; we just
                    didn't see it. Now I think it is a disaster, in large part.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of the young officers with whom you were associated with,
                        did any stick out in your mind that you saw later on as the new breed of
                        Soviet specialists?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Oh yes. Bob Barry is one; Tom Niles is another. Those two certainly
                    stood out. Mark Palmer was also there. In some ways, it is sometimes hard to
                    pinpoint, but you knew that they were exceptional in a very capable group of
                    people. They had entirely different personalities, but they stood out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a period from 1952 until 1955, during McCarthyism.
                        Was this striking at all? Did you get any feel from McCarthyism and this
                        almost anti-intellectual movement in the States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I think more in Washington than in the Embassy. I think people were
                    obviously concerned by it, but I can't think of anyone in the Embassy who was
                    affected by it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the security thing? Were the KGB playing games,
                        particularly with you bachelor officers? Or were you pretty isolated from
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: I think we were subjected to it in various ways. In Moscow, at that
                    time, I don't think it was so obvious. I think we were aware of it and warned
                    against it. I was in Warsaw later and the local security people had gotten to a
                    member of the Embassy. I don't remember security in Moscow at that point, within
                    the Embassy, particularly strong. I think it was there. We were warned about,
                    but I don't think the Embassy security officer was a particularly heavy handed
                    person at the time. It was not a major issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did your wife react to this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I think she, in a sense, like I was. Her academic background was not in
                    things Russian. She was an occupational therapist. It sounds strange to people
                    now, but there was really no question about her giving up her possible
                    professional career. We got married and she became part of the Embassy staff.
                    She worked as a typist in JPRand that added some money so that she could travel
                    on some of the trips that I took. She likes children, so she got involved in
                    teaching younger kids at the Anglo-American school. That was very much part of
                    what she wanted to do and became an important part of making life in Moscow more
                    interesting. She was certainly curious enough about life in the Soviet Union,
                    learnesome Russian, interested in the cultural life, went to plays even though
                    she couldn't understand Russian, did as much traveling with me as she could and
                    then with some of the wives from the Embassy. You couldn't travel by yourself
                    then. I think, for her, it was a marvelous experience. Neither she nor I had an
                    idea of what life in an Embassy, in the Foreign Service, would be like, but it
                    worked out very well. She was thoroughly pleased with the assignment and I think
                    with each assignment that we have had, hated to leave, glad to be back to the
                    United States; hated to leave the United States, but once she got where we were
                    going, got very much wrapped up in it and again, would hate to leave when it was
                    time to go. Although we didn't realize it at the time, the whole business of
                    wives being rated, I think grated on her, and she appreciated the liberation in
                    1972. She thought it should have come earlier. I suspect this is true for most
                    people, you really don't know what you are committing yourself to in the Foreign
                    Service. I think she took the best possible things out of our career in the
                    Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you been integrated into the Foreign Service when you
                        came back?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came back in 1955 and served in INR until 1958. What
                        were you doing there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: I was working on Soviet internal, domestic affairs and went through all
                    the various leadership that had gone on in the Soviet Union. I did some basic
                    research papers on Soviet political institutions as well as foreign policy
                    developments and then had a chance to go to Serbo-Croatian language studies, and
                    while I thought that was all right, I asked if I could have Polish instead and
                    they agreed. I took Polish language training and went off to ....</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were in I NR, at the height of Kremlinology,
                        because Stalin was gone and there was a regrouping while you were doing that
                        from 1955 until 1958, who was leading the Kremlinologist? How did you fit
                        into this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I think from my perspective, Boris Klaussen was the guy who interviewed
                    me when I came into the Foreign Service, and my recollection is that, when I
                    came back, he was still head of that part of INR that dealt with the Soviet
                    Union and Eastern Europe. He was the Division Chief. Ken Kirst was a
                    civil-service person who had been in Moscow at the same time that we were there
                    the first time. He was the Section Chief and I worked directly for him. Gordon
                    Tiger came along. That was the nucleus of the Kremlinologists at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've been interviewing Roger Davies who has been talking
                        about his experience. He felt that there was a certain division between the
                        Kennans and Bohlens, who used to really be able to talk to the leadership,
                        really back from the pre-World War II days; they had all these connections,
                        but how more and more you had to read the tea leaves. In other words, you
                        had to look at the newspapers and see who was ranked and keep card files on
                        people and how it was this younger generation that was coming up, of which
                        he was a part of, because the situation had changed, of having to look
                        through this glass in a different manner. Did you have this feeling that
                        there was this change and that it was getting harder to figure out who was
                        doing what to whom?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes, I think so. This business of the differencbetween the older
                    generation, the Kennans and the Bohlens, and the younger generation, I don't
                    think we somehow felt deprived that we didn't have the same kind of access to
                    the Soviet leadership. We may have had, as part of their background and
                    understanding of the Soviet Union, may have been there, but I don't think
                    anybody felt that way. We just accepted the idea that that was not part of our
                    experience. We had gone through the whole business about reading the press and
                    reading Embassy cables about official meetings people in the Embassy might have
                    had with people in the Foreign Ministry from stilted conversations and then the
                    periodic trip reports that people would take whatever chance conversations they
                    or if they went to a .....lecture on foreign policy issues to try and understand
                    what was behind some of the questions that some of the Russian audience might
                    have of the speaker. I think we just accepted it as that was the way it was and
                    realized that the Soviet press was very heavily controlled, but that was the
                    place we could see, if we could divine it, what the changes were in Soviet
                    foreign or domestic policy, because in part, that was the way the Soviet
                    leadership was going to get the line through to the broad masses of the people
                    rather than to the party bureaucracy or the party elite. They were separate. We
                    could see how people were ranked in the leadership. If somebody's name
                    disappeared, we knew something was happening to that person. There was a lot of
                    focus for awhile on the particular ranking of the names of the leadership.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your relationship, as you worked in INR, with the
                        desk?Sometimes there is a feeling that INR does its thing and the desk is so
                        busy doing its thing, that although you are supposedly supporting the Soviet
                        desk, there really isn't all that much time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I think there was that kind of division. I think there was also at that
                    time there were more civil service than Foreign Service officers in INR. There
                    were probably more Foreign Service Officers on the desk than there were civil
                    service, so there was that rivalry or sense or sense of differentiation, even
                    after Wristonization. We felt in INR that we were providing a service to the
                    desk and other parts of the Department since we were the research side and they
                    were the operational side. My recollection is that there was really little
                    informal contact back and forth on a regular basis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had the choice between Serbian-Croatian training and
                        Polish training, which I had about two years later, and I opted for the
                        Yugoslav. Why Polish?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I don't think it was a profound analysis. I thought it was a more
                    important country, more centrally located, larger. It was not based on any long
                    term calculation about how it would potentially affect my career.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mine was based on the much more profound thing. I figured
                        that Poland was flat and Yugoslavia was mountainous and had a nice
                        seacoast.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: It may very well be that, even though the whole business of the
                    relationship between Moscow and Tito had been going on, I suspect we were more
                    influenced by the Poznan riots in 1956.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During your Polish training, did the expatriate Poles
                        training you, give you a strong antipathy for the situation in Poland at
                        that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes, that's true. One of the Polish linguists had a fairly prominent
                    brother in Poland, so there was that kind of family division or rivalry. I think
                    there was a certain amount of antipathy but there was also a certain amount of
                    pride, in Poland, so there was that kind of contrast. We were still
                    experimenting with different types of text books and syllabus. There wasn't an
                    awful lot of bias on their part that would stick out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your first assignment there was to Poznan; you served
                        there from 1959 until 1962 as Deputy Principal Officer. What was the
                        situation in Poznan during this period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: The situation was that the consulate had been opened before and then
                    closed, and we went to open it again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When had it been closed?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: Maybe 1955 or 1956. We went with the idea of finding an office building
                    and accommodations and setting up a consulate. Before we arrived, the Embassy
                    had already found a Polish contractor who was going to do repair work on the
                    building. We met him in Warsaw and then drove down with him and his wife, in
                    several cars, to Poznan. I had the only accident I've ever had in my life in a
                    car then. I was driving, what was then, the consulate's jeep. My wife had gone
                    ahead in our car. I took a curve too fast; it was the fall and there were beet
                    leaves on the road, and it had rained, and I found myself flipped over on the
                    side. I wasn't injured. I turned off the ignition and the Pole with me suggested
                    that we get out and see what we could do. He flagged down a truck. The driver
                    inquired if we were injured and then he said that we should try and get the jeep
                    upright before any police come along and cause problems. We were able to get the
                    jeep up on its four wheels and it started. He said we ought to try the 30 miles
                    to Poznan and he would follow us. I appreciated that and everything worked out
                    all right. It was a different attitude and I found that interesting. The local
                    attitude in Poznan towards the American consulate was a very warm one. The
                    official attitude—we had a terrible Party First Secretary by the name of Jan
                    Schidlock—who was obviously out to make a career as a good strong Communist. He
                    would have as little to do with us as possible. People in the academic and
                    cultural world, within that atmosphere, still strong Communist control, were
                    really quite warm and friendly and were delighted to see us. We were the first
                    consulate there at that time. The Russians came later and then the British and
                    French. We occupied a very favored position. We had a nice building; there was a
                    fair amount of repair that had to be done on it. We lived in the basement of the
                    building for awhile. We did our dishes in the bathtub in the bathroom. It was a
                    nice atmosphere. We had a nice staff; everybody pulled together; it was one of
                    our better experiences.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the general impression of the Poles at that time
                        as a Soviet military ally?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I think we accepted that they were in the Soviet orbit. We had
                    reestablished the consulate in 1959. After the Polish riots in 1956, the feeling
                    was that the Russians were there, they had control, the Poles would do what they
                    had to do. I never really got the feeling that they would do something in a
                    whole hearted way if it came to that militarily. There were a lot of Soviet
                    bases in western Poland that were off limits to us. I think there was a certain
                    amount of necessary toleration on the part of the Poles with respect to the
                    Soviet military.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about working there in terms of the security
                        problems? There are the security police who were working hard to compromise
                        you to do things. Did that work very well?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: We arrived in Poznan after some preliminary negotiations. The building
                    had been given to us that would serve as the consulate as had the apartment for
                    the Principal Officer, an apartment for the Secretary. Initially, we lived in
                    the basement of the building. That worked out very well; it gave us a way to
                    meet some Poles. We drove down from Warsaw, to Poznan, with the Polish
                    contractor who had been given the job of renovating the building and we struck
                    up a nice working relationship with him. He did his business and we moved into
                    the consulate. We were aware of the likelihood that the Poles had the
                    opportunity to do what they wanted with the building, whether the contractor was
                    in cahoots with the secret police or not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are talking about listening devices and the like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes. We must have had three or four visits by our own security people
                    and they could not find anything. At one more visit, I think quite by chance,
                    one of the SY people found a small hole behind a radiator in traditional
                    fashion. They took the radiator out and began chipping away and lo and behold,
                    there was a listening device. A hallowed out dowel went from the surface of the
                    wall, back to this listening device. It was traced down through the basement,
                    under the driveway, into the next yard, which was the school for Polish kids.
                    All of this work was going on, tearing up the building, and none of the Polish
                    employees asked a single question about what was going on. That was the only
                    devicthat we found; there may have been others. We deactivated that and that
                    obviously a clear warning that they had that capability and were using it. In
                    that sense, we saw it, knew it was there. We tried to have a secure room where
                    we could have our conversations and keep our classified materials. We assume,
                    although we have no way of knowing, that that room was not penetrated. In terms
                    of the apartments, we simply warned people that they had to be careful about
                    what they say. In terms of physical security, I don't think we had any feeling
                    that we were under any kind of physical threat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the use of provocateurs? There was the case of
                        the General Service Officer who was caught in the classic “honey” trap. A
                        Polish employee got him to divulge secrets.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: There was that possibility. While I was there, we had a single
                    secretary and a single USIA officer. I think we were aware of it, but as far as
                    we could tell, there was no systematic, concerted effort, to compromise anyone
                    at the consulate. We knew about the case in Warsaw.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about your relations with our Embassy in Warsaw? How
                        did they use Poznan, or did you do your own thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: I think we had a certain sense of being pioneers being out in the
                    western part of Poland and spent a fair amount of time getting around our
                    district to engage in whatever kind of political, economic, and sociological
                    reporting that we could do, which went to the Embassy and the Embassy sent it on
                    to Washington. We took part, sporadically, in Embassy staff meeting. There was
                    no real effort to have a coherent, coordinated reporting plan and to feel part
                    of the Embassy. We didn't feel that we weren't but we did feel a sense of being
                    on our own.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about Jake Beam as Ambassador? What was your
                        impression of him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: It was a junior officer-Ambassador sort of relationship. You stand in
                    awe. I think both with him and with Walt Stoessel, there was a good, cordial
                    relationship, but it was one of physical remove, and then there was the
                    difference of age and rank. I had good relations with both of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about on the consular side? Did you find your office
                        was pretty heavily involved in immigration and social security?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: We were fortunate in that we did not issue visas. All the visa work was
                    done in Warsaw and we simply referred people to Warsaw for immigrant or visitor
                    visas. We did some American protection work, but not a lot. In effect we were
                    there for political and in part for economic and commercial reasons. There was
                    an annual Poznan trade fair at which the U.S. government had a rather sizeable
                    building which we used. Although we didn't conduct an awful lot of commercial
                    activity, that plus the political reporting and representation, were really our
                    main functions. The consular functions at that point, in the first years that we
                    were there, were really secondary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there during the Berlin Wall crisis at the end of
                        1961?Did that have any impact?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: That's a good question. I don't recall it having any major impact
                    either in terms of our reporting or our sense of physical security. I don't
                    recall it closing down the situation or our ability to get around western
                    Poland. I think that before we had arrived, the ability for diplomats to drive,
                    unhindered, through East Germany, to Berlin, that was no longer the case. We
                    didn't recognize East Germany, so we were told that we couldn't go through East
                    Germany at that time. I really don't recall that the building of the Wall
                    created an increased sense of foreboding or heightened tension.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You then moved back to Washington. You were with Soviet
                        affairs for four years, from 1962 until 1966. How was Soviet affairs set up?
                        Where did fit, in those days, in the Department's scheme of things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes, I was in the Office of Soviet Affairs. It was part of EUR and
                    Eastern Europe was a separate office within the Office of Soviet Affairs. There
                    were essentially two parts. There was a bilateral section. I think I had my
                    choice of going into the bilateral or multi-lateral section and I decided I
                    would go into the multi-lateral section. That essentially, not an extension of
                    what I was doing in Moscow, but it was working with different geographic bureaus
                    on Soviet foreign policy issues as they affected us. For a fair amount of the
                    time, I had that part of the office that dealt with European affairs. The idea
                    was to provide the Soviet element with whatever issue was coming up between us
                    and a western or eastern European country. I had also the Far East ansoutheast
                    Asia, less so Africa and Latin America, although they were there and
                    important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the head person as far as Soviet affairs were
                        concerned?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Bob Owen was Director of the Office of Soviet Affairs at first and Herb
                    Okun was his deputy and for awhile Vlad Manoff was in charge of multi-lateral
                    affairs and then Phil Valdez came in after Vlad. I'm sorry, Mac .... was in
                    charge of the Office and Bob was in charge of bilateral affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there in time for the Missile Crisis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes. It was handled above us however. It was not an issue with which we
                    became fully involved at our level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your main concerns during this period from 1962
                        until 1966?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: There was concern about Germany and about Soviet/German relations and
                    how that had an impact on us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we feel that West Germany was solidly in the western
                        camp or did we feel that if the Soviets made the right moves they could
                        nudge them towards a neutral position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: There was some concern about that, but it was not overwhelming. The
                    Russians couldn't offer Germany anything at that point that could induce it
                    towards any kind of neutrality.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we feel that there was much for the Soviets, either
                        through their surrogate Communist parties in Western Europe or as a military
                        force to mess around in Western Europe?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Nothing really pops out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Khrushchev left the scene in about 1966.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes, but I remember more about when Malenkov anKosygin left the scene.
                    I remember more about the business of Khrushchev secret speech about Stalin,
                    which we didn't know about until later. It was the 20th Congress speech.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the speech that the CIA eventually published all
                        over the world. I remember, I was in Saudi Arabia, and I was happily
                        spreading copies around to very disinterested Saudis. It was the first time
                        that Stalin and his regime were attacked in this so-called secret speech. Do
                        you remember hothat played when it first came out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: There was some skepticism about whether it was for real or not and how
                    it was smuggled. It became clear, fairly soon, it seemed to hang together and
                    made a lot of sense and tended to confirm what people in Western Europe and the
                    United States had known about the early parts of the Stalinist regime. I think
                    after the initial skepticism, there wasn't much doubt about the authenticity of
                    the speech.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:Was there any difference between how your office, the State
                        Department was looking at the Soviet Union?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I don't think there was much of a feeling that somehow they had a
                    better insight into the Russians and what they were up to than we did. I don't
                    think the analyses of what the Soviets were doing in different parts of the
                    world were terribly different. In some ways, they had individual sources that
                    were helpful, but I think they were more inclined to generalize about a
                    particuladevelopment from an individual source, than we would have been. I don't
                    recall any major disagreement about analyses.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you getting any feel about the China-Soviet
                        relationship?Were we still talking about China and the Soviet Union being
                        together?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes. I don't think when I was there that there was much of a feeling
                    that there was much of a wedge that you could drive between the two of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You moved from Soviet affairs in 1966 and went to West
                        Berlin where you served from 1966-1968. What were you doing there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I was in the section that nominally dealt with what was going on in
                    East Germany and I acted as the liaison officer with the Soviet Embassy in East
                    Berlin on political matters relating to the four power occupation of Berlin and
                    if there were problems related to the US Military Mission in East Berlin. We
                    would talk with the East Germans and Soviets about it and that was one of my
                    responsibilities. It was basically two things. One was looking at the East
                    Berlin/East German media to try and get some idea of political, economic, and
                    foreign policy developments of the East German regime and then dealing with the
                    Soviet Embassy on a variety of bilateral issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find dealing with the Soviets on these
                        bilateral issues. They were mostly military problems right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Some were military problems not all. There was also the question of
                    unimpeded US civilian access to East Berlin. We went through a process of trying
                    to work out a pass system that civilian members of the US Mission in West Berlin
                    could use to enter without being checked by East Germans. They were, but we
                    worked out with the Russians a system of a flag card, which had identification
                    on it, which the East Germans were not permitted touch, but was held up as one
                    went through the checkpoint. That was a form of identification, but we
                    maintained the fiction that the East Germans were not controlling us. With a
                    certain amount of cooperation from the Russians, that kind of system went into
                    effect, presumably making it easier for Americans to enter East Berlin without
                    being checked by the East German guards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have problems with American military units getting
                        into trouble?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes, periodically, but they never evolved into major problems. There
                    was a standard protest from the Russians on behalf of the East Germans and vice
                    versa. It never became a major sticking point in the relationship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Someone was interviewing Pete Day, who said he discovered,
                        through bitter experience that usually the Soviets, when they complained,
                        had a reason for complaining. He couldn't really trust the American military
                        with giving him the straight story because usually some guys in a jeep were
                        screwing up somewhere and they were trying to cover up.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: I think there may have been some of that and certainly with the
                    Military Liaison Mission field trips. They were out looking for whatever they
                    could find in terms of Soviet and East German forces and equipment. There were
                    certainly cases in which they strayed over the line. My own recollection was
                    that was more the case with the Military Liaison Mission people, who were better
                    trained, and were competent in Russian or German, than it was the case of stray
                    US Military units in East Berlin itself, either as a result of being on tours or
                    patrol in East Berlin. There were regular patrols in East Berlin, but there
                    aren't too many cases where they were at fault.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:Did you have any contact with East Germans at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: We tried to and did have some contact with a very select number of
                    people. It didn't amount to an awful lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have much work with the East German
                        authorities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: No. We had, at least speaking about myself, we had contact with the
                    media world in West Berlin. Brandon Grove and others had the responsibility of
                    liaison with the West Berlin government in terms of the US Military Mission. I
                    had no official responsibilities with the West German or West Berlin
                    governments. The relations we had with West Berliners were really social.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any major problems in this two year
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: No. The main issue was getting the flag system for access to East
                    Berlin down pat. There were not any major issues. We left West Berlin for our
                    next assignment in Moscow right on the eve of the invasion of Czechoslovakia. In
                    fact, we were in East Berlin having dinner with the Finnish commercial
                    representative in East Berlin when it happened. Had we stuck to our original
                    travel plans, we would have been traveling through Czechoslovakia to Moscow by
                    car, but for our own personal reasons, we revised the plans to go up to northern
                    Germany and take a ferry to Helsinki and then down to Moscow. You couldn't tell
                    the night we were in East Berlin. It was quiet and then we came back and heard
                    about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did that have any effect on what we did there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: We left literally about that time. We were listening to West German
                    newspaper correspondents who were broadcasting from Prague about what was
                    happening and then subsequently met one of them on vacation in Greece. We left
                    right after that happened and got to Moscow under the atmosphere of the invasion
                    of Czechoslovakia.Q: You served in the Soviet Union again from 1968 until 1971.
                    What were you doing there?</p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Then I was in charge of the foreign policy or external relations branch
                    of the Political Section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You must have walked in when all hell was breaking loose
                        with this Czech thing; every country had something to say about it. How was
                        this playing back in the Soviet Union?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: It was a tense and cold period in terms of our relations with the
                    Soviet Union. There was a certain amount of official contact in terms of making
                    representations. There was not any great sense of personal concern. There was
                    concern for what the invasion meant for the lack of development of relations. I
                    don't think anybody was concerned for one's physical being or somehow this meant
                    a heightened possibility of a Soviet move west.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As the officer in charge of Soviet external
                        relations—observing them—what did you do? What were you interests and how
                        did you go about getting information?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: It was essentially the same process of trying to use the Soviet media
                    and press to get some idea of how they were looking at issues plus a lot more
                    contact with Western European embassies, particularly the German, British, and
                    French embassies to try and share ideas and experiences and exchange
                    information. It wasn't until a year after that, that we developed some contact
                    among Soviets themselves that added an additional element to reading the media
                    and listening to the radio and watching television. It was not quite the same
                    thing as an INR analysis of the Soviet media, but there was a lot of that
                    still.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the evaluation of Brezhnev at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: We thought he was very much in control and a tough character.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was wondering if there was the feeling that while
                        Brezhnev was a “tough cookie”, Khrushchev was a “loose cannon” and maybe we
                        are better off with a little stability.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: I don't think that was quite the case. We were under the very strong
                    impact of the invasion and what it meant. We didn't think it wagoing to result
                    in any offensive against Western Europe, but we didn't look on Brezhnev as a
                    stable person in the sense of being able to know that things were under control
                    and that was better than under the Kruschev era.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a little before we opened up to China. How was
                        this observed from your point of view?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I arrived in Moscow right after the invasion of Czechoslovakia and left
                    the day that Nixon was going to China and must admit, had essentially, no idea
                    that that was going to happen. I did recall at the time, and do recall now,
                    really heard first from a source in the Romanian Embassy that there was a
                    certain amount of travel going on by Kissinger in that part of the world. People
                    at my level queried the Department on it and basically got nothing back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the differences between living in the Moscow in
                        the Fifties and then again in the late Sixties?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: It was different in the sense that we had somewhat better
                    accommodations that we were able to get, not easily, from the Russians. It was
                    all in diplomatic compounds. For us the improvement toward the middle and end of
                    our stay was the opportunity to meet some Russians in what were obviously very
                    controlled, approved situations. It was better than when I was there from 1952
                    until 1955. That part was an improvement. In terms of traveling, the situation
                    was a little bit better, but again, it was always hard to get away from the
                    office, but there was a fairly travel active program to get and visit different
                    parts of the Soviet Union. The food supply was a little bit better. There were
                    more things to do culturally. It was probably more enjoyable and varied than the
                    first time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel the heavy hand of the KGB as far as
                        provocations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I don't think so. Again, having had gone through one tour, it was maybe
                    easier to go through it the second time. I really didn't feel it was worse or
                    more intrusive in any sense?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jake Beam was your Ambassador. You were closer to him. How
                        did he operate?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: He operated pretty much through his DCM, who was Boris Klaussen. I went
                    with Ambassador Beam frequently to the Foreign Ministry when he had protests or
                    other representations to make to the Foreign Ministry and Gromyko. There wasn't
                    an awful lot of preparation between the two of us as to what he was going to do.
                    I went along as note-taker and helped with the translations. He did what he
                    wanted to do. He was a shy, retiring type. It was uncomfortable for him to be on
                    an informal basis with other people. That burden was taken on by Boris Klaussen,
                    who was the main point of contact. He was a different kind of personality. He
                    was easy to work with. Everyone respected Beam, liked his wife very much. She
                    was a very outgoing, no nonsense kind of person.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the feeling about Kissinger, the National
                        Security Council, and the Soviets? Did you have a feel that they were
                        playing a different game than what you were?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I don't think a different game. I mentioned the business about the
                    Romanian contact and Kissinger's travels to China. I don't recall that there was
                    any great feeling that somehow things were being done in the NSC that were a
                    level apart from or in conflict with what we were doing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left in 1971 and you went to the Cultural Exchange
                        program for a year.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you concerned with there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: The Office of Cultural Presentations, as it was called then, was
                    essentially a world wide program without an awful lot that related to the Soviet
                    Union. My interest at that point was to see if we could increase the amount of
                    cultural presentations in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union. I looked on it as
                    an interesting challenge, at the same time, didn't particularly care for the
                    assignment; I thought it was out of the mainstream. I took on the business of
                    trying to increase the amount of money that could be used for things that
                    related to the Soviet Union. I had to work with ....I also worked with a couple
                    of theater companies out in San Francisco about programs in Moscow. I had the
                    chance to go out the War College.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which War College did you go to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: The International War College?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find yourself, as “Mr. Expert”, telling everybody
                        about the Soviet Union? Were you a source?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I was a source for first hand experience and observations. People did
                    tend to think that I knew more about the Soviet Union than they did. As we moved
                    around from group to group, covering different subjects and geographical areas,
                    it melded into what was going on. I was looked at best as a source, and one of
                    the students.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you got back into Soviet Affairs from 1973 until
                        1976.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: It wasn't necessarily what I wanted to do. At that point I didn't'
                    really want to go back into the Exchanges program, which is what actually did
                    happen. It was the first time I really tried to get out of thing out of things
                    in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union, without success. I thought it would be
                    worthwhile to have an assignment in Latin America, but never having an
                    assignment there, and not having Spanish, there was no place for me. By default,
                    the only thing that was open was on the Exchanges staff, and that is where I was
                    assigned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this under Soviet Affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: It was a separate office and covered both Eastern Europe and the Soviet
                    Union. As a result of one the reorganizations in the Department—trying to cut
                    out positions—the office itself was divided up, with part of it going to SOV as
                    a separate unit, and part of it going to EUR as a separate unit. I wound up
                    being in charge of that part of SOV that dealt with exchanges with the Soviet
                    Union and worked with people on IREX issues. That part of the office worked on a
                    whole range of bilateral exchange agreements that various agencies had with the
                    Soviet Union. I had to work with agencies in terms of implementation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One has the impression that we were really trying to get a
                        reasonable exchange of people; the idea that the more we could reach into
                        influential in another society, the more they will be favorably inclined
                        towards us. At the same time, one gets the impression that the Soviets
                        looked upon this as a way of getting agents into the United States....</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: ....or gain technical information. There is a constant battle between
                    us and the Soviets in terms of how the overall exchange agreement was written;
                    we tried to insist on reciprocity. There was also a battle within the U.S.
                    government and within the academic community—how this is carried out. Many of
                    the agencies, from our perspective, perfectly willing to agree to things with
                    the Russians that didn't provide for reciprocity or didn't give us the
                    opportunity to try to get access to certain institutions in the Soviet Union and
                    to bring over Russians without a comparable number of Americans going in the
                    other direction. In a sense our allies turned out to be the FBI and the CIA
                    against other parts of the Executive Branch and also with respect to the
                    academic programs that were going on. It was not an either or situation, but a
                    fluid one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the value of this exchange
                        program at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I thought by and large if we could get a fair degree of reciprocity, it
                    was worthwhile engaging in. I still think that was the case. I always had the
                    feeling that when the Russians came over this way, they were better prepared for
                    what they wanted to find or learn than we were in going to the Soviet Union. I
                    think in a lot of cases, the people who were involved on our side simply were
                    much more opened with what they wanted to do and less concerned about the
                    reciprocity angle. From my perspective, that was always a problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You ended up as being the heavy bureaucrat.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I'm sure that was the case, not only within the Executive Branch, but
                    also with respect to different parts of the academic community.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The feeling was I assume, that if you hadn't, it would
                        have ended up being completely a one-sided thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes, that was our feeling. Maybe that's true. But when you see what's
                    happened to the Soviet Union, you sort of wonder, would it have made any
                    difference if we hadn't insisted on reciprocity. It's hard to know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there until 1976. You seem like you were
                        repeating yourself—right back to East Berlin from 1976 until 1979.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: At that time I was really interested in going back to see what was
                    happening in that part of Germany. I think we were the last to recognize the
                    East Germans. I really wanted to go back and see what was happening. I thought
                    Germany was important and the East German relationship was important and so went
                    back willingly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation there then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I think from the East German government standpoint, they were delighted
                    to see us there as a symbol of their stability and permanence and international
                    recognition. Before we arrived, Brandon Grove and Ambassador Cooper had worked
                    out an arrangemenfor a rather impressive Chancery Building. The repair and
                    renovation had been completed by the time I arrived. Brandon stayed about
                    eighteen months and then I came. We had the business of finishing up the
                    renovation and getting the Chancery building open. The East Germans were
                    cooperative to a certain extent in making sure the building functioned. At the
                    same time, they made sure that not too many East Germans came in easily without
                    being identified. They were fairly cooperative in providing us with a limited
                    number of local staff. The relationships with the Foreign Ministry were
                    professional. The East German who was in charge of East German/US relations,
                    Hans Martin Geyer, was an old time, long time, Communist who took a certain
                    amount of glee in the fact that the Americans were there. It was an interesting
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your position there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I was DCM.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the Ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: The Ambassador first was John Sherman Cooper, the former Senator from
                    Kentucky. He was a wonderful person. He was succeeded by David Bolen, a career
                    Foreign Service Officer. He had one tour in West Germany, in Bonn, as an
                    economic/commercial officer. He had some German experience, but no Eastern
                    European or Soviet experience. We set about establishing a reporting, work, and
                    consular schedule, and had a USIA operation that we thought was very important.
                    The East Germans gave us a lot of trouble over access to the library. That was a
                    continuing problem the whole time we were there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the country open to you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes, we could travel just about anywhere we wanted to and we tried to.
                    There were no real travel restrictions that we observed and the country was
                    small enough that you could really get around.Q: What was in it for the United
                    States? We finally recognized it after many years of subscribing to the Holstein
                    Document.</p>
                <p>POLANSKY: What was in it for us was essentially, that since just about everybody
                    else recognized it, there was no point in not recognizing it. We maintained a
                    fiction that East Berlin was not the capital of the GDR but was still part of
                    occupied Berlin, so we wanted to maintain that fiction. We wanted to make sure
                    that we understood what was going on in East Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about relations with the East German government? Were
                        you calling on people in the government and how did you find them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: In the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Ministry of Culture, they
                    were proper and correct. They didn't go out of their way to look on us as an
                    opportunity for great increase in contacts. They wanted it, but they realized it
                    was not going to be an easy relationship. The people on the economic side were
                    looking for ways to increase contact with western firms for commerce. We always
                    had an exhibit at the Leipzig Fair which they wanted us to increase. It was
                    important from there standpoint for us to be there, but they didn't give us any
                    incentives for trying to have a favored position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the political and economic
                        strengths and weaknesses of East Germany in this period from 1976 until
                        1979.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: At the time we felt that while there was some outward presentation of
                    stability and confidence that they had somehow created a new East German
                    citizenship, in the sense of separateness, that was really on the surface. Apart
                    from people in the Ministries, we really didn't get a sense that there was a
                    separate East German citizenship or East German nation that went very deep in
                    peoples' thinking. Economically, it certainly looked stronger than any of the
                    other East European economies. We subscribed to the idea that as Germans, they
                    were more efficient and productive than their East European neighbors. There was
                    a sense that they looked down on the Russians and some of their East European
                    allies. The stores, particularly towards the end of our stay there, were better
                    supplied, in terms of foodstuffs and consumer goods, than elsewhere in Eastern
                    Europe, certainly better than the Soviet Union. While there was not this great
                    deep seeded sense of East German “nationhood”, it did look more stable at that
                    time than perhaps it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hindsight is always “20 20”, but in 1989, with the
                        collapse of East Germany, West Germany found itself with what is often
                        termed “an economic basket case”. The highly flaunted industry was outmoded.
                        The workers weren't very good. Yet you have Czechoslovakia and even Poland
                        with what appears to be more vitality. Were we missing something?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: First of all, I'm not sure that the Polish and Czech economies at the
                    present time really are more efficient than what is left of the East German
                    economy. We had the feeling at the time that the East German economy was more
                    productive and effective and West Germans certainly were prepared to put a lot
                    of money into East Germany, in various ways, as part of an effort to maintain
                    the relationships so that the two societies and countries didn't drift apart.
                    That certainly helped the East German economy. Obviously I think we and the West
                    Europeans missed and were taken in by what was really going economically in East
                    Germany. It may very well have declined in the middle and late 1980's. My
                    recollection that in those cases where Western businessmen and American Embassy
                    people were able to visit factories and talk with people, they came away with a
                    fairly favorable impression of what was developing economically.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there the feeling that the Carter administration was
                        taking a new approach towards countries like East Germany?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: No, I don't think so substantively in terms of reaching out to East
                    Germany. I think it was very subjective and more of our own personal assessment.
                    David Bohlen was a black officer, one of the few blacks to achieve the rank of
                    Ambassador at that time. He was sent to East Berlin as our Ambassador. On our
                    part we thought that this was one way the Carter Administration was trying to
                    demonstrate an attitude towards civil and human rights by making a deliberative
                    effort to send a black Ambassador to East Berlin. There was the feeling,
                    particularly after someone like Ambassador Cooper, what kind of message were the
                    Americans trying to send us by sending a black Ambassador to us? The substance
                    of our relationship had a Four Power aspect to it in terms of what we were doing
                    in East Berlin and what we were doing in terms of East Germany. I don't recall
                    that there was a conscious effort somehow to put our relations with East Germany
                    on a par with our relations with West Germany or on a par with our relations
                    with the other countries in Eastern Europe. There was a feeling that if the East
                    Germans want to have a better relationship with us, that they had damn well
                    prove that thewant it, we were not going to give anything away for nothing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in 1979 and served for four years in
                        Vienna?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I was in Vienna from 1979 until 1983. I was DCM and then when Phil
                    Kaiser I became Charge for sixteen or eighteen months until Helen van Damm came.
                    In effect I was running the Embassy for that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were American interest in this period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: They were to make sure Austria knew our interest in keeping Austria
                    neutral as they had proclaimed themselves and at the same time, make sure it was
                    really pro-Western in its attitudes and policies.One of the first thing I
                    remember was the Iran hostage situation and the impact it had on us personally
                    in trying to get the Austrians to understand what the situation was. We were
                    also concerned about whether the Austrians would buy Russian, Eastern European,
                    or Western European fighter planes. We spent a certain amount trying to convince
                    the Austrians to buy US fighter planes. It was not clear by the time I left what
                    they were going to buy. There was also a time when martial law was declared in
                    Poland and there was some concern as to what kind of refugee flow that would
                    create in Austria, what they would do with the Polish refugees that were there,
                    and the efforts of some of them to come to the United States and under what
                    circumstances. In general it was trying to make certain that Austria was a
                    neutral state and pro-Western in its foreign policy and open to American
                    investment in a way that we could do business.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Looking at it as an American diplomat, how did you view
                        Austria? Where did they stand? What were their interests?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: A lot of the first part of it really relates to Bruno Kreisky as
                    Chancellor and that the role that he played and the role that he saw himself
                    playing, particularly in the Middle East and certainly there was no desire on
                    the part of the Administration to cede him a role as arbitrator or guide for
                    what our policy should be in the Middle East.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You are talking about the American administration.What was
                        Kreisky's interest and what was he trying to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: He was trying to play the hand of Arafat and the PLO and trying to get
                    us to accept his perception of the role of the PLO as force in the Middle East;
                    as an organization that we ought to deal with in trying to solve the Middle
                    Eastern crisis. I think he felt that he understood the Middle East and that we
                    did not. He had delegated to himself the role of spokesman and thought that we
                    should essentially understand his perspective on the Middle East as a way of
                    bringing peace to the area.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Here you have the Prime Minister of a neutral state,
                        Austria, who is advocating recognizing the Palestine Liberation
                        Organization, which is not only an anathema to powers that be in Israel but
                        also to the Jewish community and its lobby in the United States. You are the
                        American representative having to deal with this. You must have been under
                        an awful lot of pressure to tell him to “knock it off.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I didn't feel any great pressure. I didn't have any sympathy for his
                    point of view. I think it became fairly clear to Kreisky that the United States
                    was not going to accept his viewpoint. It was done in a candid but polite way.
                    He was realistic enough to know that whatever my personal views were, I was
                    carrying out orders that didn't affect our relationship, which was a good and
                    open one. He was a hard headed politician from his perspective. He didn't
                    particularly like it, but he understood when he was being told no. It didn't
                    have any great impact on his feeling toward me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any assurances that Austria really was
                        neutral, or was it a paper neutrality and Austria was leaning East or
                        West?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: The concern was, at least with respect to Kreisky, was even though he
                    proclaimed neutrality and he was clear in what he said about the Middle East, he
                    was, in someway, more inclined to be sympathetic to and responsive to Soviet
                    positions more than he was with respect to American and NATO positions. He
                    realized that whether we liked it or not, we were prepared to take fairly strong
                    stands on issues with respect to Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union. He could
                    say what he wanted to, but it really wouldn't have an impact on what we did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he coming from the Socialist side of the political
                        spectrum?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Absolutely. He was head of the Socialist Party and he was President,
                    Vice-President, or Chairman of the Socialist International in his international
                    role. There was no question of his political orientation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the impact of the Soviet intervention in
                        Afghanistan hit him? That was in December of 1979.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: He was opposed to it and said so. I think he was forceful in his
                    condemnation of the Soviets at that time. He was not an apologist.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find the change over to the Reagan Administration
                        causing a certain amount of anxiety? Here was Reagan, an arch-conservative
                        and here you have a left-wing Socialist government. Was that a problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: It was a problem in the sense that Kreisky and others were
                    condescending toward Reagan. How could a movie star become President. An
                    attitude that was limited not only to Kreisky and the Austrians. At the same
                    time, it was quite clear, because of what Kreisky wanted to do in terms of his
                    foreign policy interests, that he wanted to meet with Reagan. It didn't come off
                    until 1983 when he came to Washington on an unofficial visit and was received by
                    Reagan at the White House. It was a short meeting; really just a courtesy, but
                    it took him that long to get into the White House. One of the things that Reagan
                    told him at that time was that Helene van Damm, who had been his personal
                    secretary and then Head of Personnel at the White House, was going to become the
                    new Ambassador to Austria. Whatever Kreisky thought personally, he welcomed
                    since she came out of Reagan's inner circle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left Vienna in 1983 and went to START?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes, I was called by Joan Clarke and Larry Eagleburger and asked if I
                    would like to take Jim Goodby's place as the State Department representative on
                    the START delegation—Strategic Arms Reduction Talks. I didn't have any arms
                    control experience, I liked the idea of being part of the team negotiating with
                    the Russians. I went with some misgivings because I was replacing Jim Goodby,
                    who I knew and I admired, but who had been in effect, black balled by Ed Rowney
                    and Sam Watson because they thought he was too liberal and they wanted somebody
                    else. I was acceding to the wishes of Larry Eagleburger and Joan Clarke to
                    takJim's place. I worked out an amicable relationship with Ed Rowney. I found
                    the work interesting. The unfortunate part was that the first round of
                    negotiations I attended in Geneva, was also the last. That was in 1983. The
                    Russians walked out at the end of the year because of the whole INF
                    business—Intermediate Nuclear Force in Germany. It was clear that during the few
                    months of the negotiation, that although we were dealing with strategic arms
                    control issues, the INF, was tactical, we were being held hostage to what
                    happened on the INF talks. It became clear at the end, if we introduced tactical
                    nuclear weapons in Germany, the Russians would walk out of the START talks. The
                    whole two month period, when we were trying to find potential compromises on
                    some of the START issues, was an exercise in futility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you know at the time that we were going to put these
                        short or medium ranged missiles in Germany?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: There is no question about that. There was some hope that the Russians
                    would still have an interest in talking about strategic issues rather than
                    walking out. That turned out not to be the case. We spent the next couple of
                    years doing various studies about different issues; visiting submarine sights in
                    the United States and visiting nuclear missile sights in the United States as
                    part of the effort to keep on top of issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you view the various sides on the American
                        team?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: There was a lot of feeling that you couldn't trust the Russians. You
                    really had to turn over every stone each time they suggested there was some
                    movement on their position. Virtually all of the different agencies that were
                    represented on the team, were all extremely careful and conservative in their
                    view. The way to negotiate with the Russians was not to give them any benefit of
                    doubt at all and to take the most extreme positions on the capabilities of the
                    various Soviet nuclear weapons systems, whether they were airplanes or missiles.
                    For all practical purposes, it turned out to be the right thing to do. It was
                    clear that the Russians were not going to engage in any significant compromise
                    in their position. It became a holding operation. No one really trusted the
                    Russians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You must have come up against our strategic planners in
                        the nuclear field. What was your impression from dealing with these
                        people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I thought they were sincere. I thought they exaggerated the
                    capabilities of the Soviets. Not that the Soviets didn't have very formidable
                    weapons and were trying to conceal the development of new weapons. I don't think
                    there is any question about that at all. It seems that both sides had more than
                    enough weapons to do everything possible in the way of destruction. To add more
                    new weapons, for what might become marginal targets, or to have so many weapons
                    that everything could be blown up, was a nightmare, but it was very much the
                    attitude. I don't think there was any possibility of changing it at the
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have the feeling that you were in a foreign
                        culture when you got into this, having come from the world of
                        diplomacy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: Not totally foreign. Certainly the details and the technicalities were
                    an entirely different culture, but the political culture was not entirely
                    different. The military and some of the intelligence people represented an
                    honest, but conservative aspect of what was our overall foreign policy. I saw it
                    in various ways at embassies in Eastern Europe, so it was not totally alien.
                    They just perceived the threat in a different way. I dealt with until 1985 when
                    there were signs that the Russians were prepared to resume negotiations. There
                    was a change in the leadership of the START delegation when Rowney moved over
                    and John Tower took over and he wanted to have his own deputy, and that turned
                    out to be Ron Lehman. I was without a job and did a couple of short term
                    assignments for Ron Spiers. One of things I did was to head up a team of retired
                    FSO's who looked at the potential damage to all of our cables from the
                    compromise of typewriters at the Embassy in Moscow. It was the Soviet ability to
                    take Embassy typewriters that were in unsecured, unclassified areas and modified
                    them through a retooling of standard typewriters. They would put electronic
                    transmission devices in the typewriter that enabled them to pick up the
                    transmission from the typewriters down through the power lines and the question
                    were, how long had that been going on, how many typewriters were involved, what
                    parts of the embassy were they in, at what period of time, what kind of messages
                    were typed on them. It became a jigsaw puzzle. We spent a number of months
                    working on it. There were several generations of typewriters involved. One of
                    the conclusions we came to, was that the batteries that were installed in the
                    typewriters to permit the transmission of the information, had, in most cases,
                    died during the time. We tried to figure out the shelf life of those batteries.
                    We tried to go through all the out going cables which the Embassy had sent; we
                    divided them up into arms control and political and economic reporting, and
                    consular reporting and eliminate those that didn't have much relevance, and then
                    went through the rest and tried to make some assessment of the degree of damage.
                    Whether it was right or wrong, the assessment that we came to was that, to the
                    extent we could tell that typewriters had been in different parts of the
                    Embassy, that the damage probably wasn't too great because the batteries had
                    expired. Whether that really is the case, I don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the call to Bulgaria come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: It came about after a couple of short term assignments with CSCE
                    conferences, one in Bern and one in Budapest. This is the Conference on Security
                    and Cooperation in Europe. Those were interesting in terms of talking about
                    human rights and related issues. When those were over, I was asked if I wanted
                    to be considered for the post in Sofia and I agreed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There wasn't a competition from the political side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: If there was, it certainly wasn't noticeable! Prague went to Jay
                    Niermczyk, who had been a political appointee, but has been a former Air Attache
                    in Prague.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went to Bulgaria in 1987. As you went, what were
                        American interests and what were you going to try to do in Bulgaria?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: What was quite clear, was that we had very little in the way of
                    significant interest in Bulgaria. Our interests were more in Turkey and the
                    southern flank of NATO and guarding that. We were not expecting much from
                    Bulgaria in terms of US national security interests or US economic or political
                    interests. We certainly didn't expect the Bulgarians to side with us on any
                    issues in the UN. It was a very solid ally of Moscow. It was looked on as a
                    holding operation and we tried at least to increase the exchange programs and
                    open up the possibilities for young Bulgarians to learn about the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about drug interdiction?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: That was certainly an interest; that an arms sales. We spent a lot of
                    time talking to the Bulgarians about drug shipments through Bulgaria from Turkey
                    to Central Europe. It was mainly truck traffic. They flatly denied it and said
                    that they had adequate means to inspect. After awhile we did work out some
                    arrangements for some customs visits from the US, but they were non-productive.
                    The Bulgarians didn't cooperate very much. That became a source of irritation in
                    our relationship. The Bulgarians did not seem to be playing fair.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it just nationalism and they didn't want anyone to
                        interfere or did you feel they had a hand in getting payments?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: There was the feeling that some people were getting paid off. While the
                    Bulgarians put on a face of wanting to be cooperative and understanding, there
                    was nothing in practice that let us believe that they were really trying to stop
                    the traffic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I get the feeling that not an awful lot of attention was
                        being paid to Bulgaria back in Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I think it was negative attention. It was on things like arms and drug
                    sales. A lot of attention, in a relative sense, was paid when Bulgaria started
                    to harass Turks and send them back to Turkey.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about arms sales? Who were they selling to?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: It was never really clear, except to Third World countries. I think it
                    was the drug trafficking more than the arms sales, that caused problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you read the fact that the Bulgarians were all of
                        a sudden forcing the Turks to leave their territory?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I think it developed in a way they really didn't anticipate. It all
                    came out of the CSCE process and that process led to a series of agreements and
                    understandings that all of the countries signed up to, but in fact, provided for
                    more travel and easier access to exit visas and passports. In effect, the
                    Bulgarians were challenged on it by the Turks and any Bulgarian of Turkish
                    descent, who wanted to leave, could get a passport immediately and go. Some
                    Bulgarian Turks thought this might not last long and grabbed on to it. Some did
                    and there were some assertions that the Turks were provoking the whole thing and
                    there was an action\reaction, with the Turks challenging the Bulgarian
                    authorities to let the Turks go and the Bulgarians were saying that they were
                    letting anyone who wanted to, go. Then the Bulgarian Turks went to try and get
                    passports and visas, sold all the houses and their possessions and took off as
                    quickly as they could. From the US government perspective it was a case of the
                    Bulgarians not permitting the Turks to leave in a decent way, they were being
                    harassed and having to sell their property at low cost. The thing just
                    escalated. Over three hundred thousand Bulgarian Turks left in a period of
                    several weeks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing as the US Ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: First of all we were sending Embassy officers around the country to see
                    how Bulgarian Turks were being treated, whether they felt they really could go
                    and if so, under what circumstances. How difficult it was to get a passport and
                    then try and convince the Bulgarian authorities that if they were going to let
                    people go, they do it in a way that was decent and humane. We went down to the
                    border any number of times to see how people were being treated and it was
                    really rather, not brutal, but not conducive to human behavior. They were
                    sitting out in trucks without any means of water or sanitation; they were held
                    for hours at a time and then forced to unpack all of their possessions very
                    carefully in front of Bulgarian customs officials and then forced to put it all
                    together and then creep through the no man's land between Bulgarian and Turkish
                    customs officials. Then on the Turkish side they had to do the same thing over
                    again. It was a very unpleasant set of circumstances in the middle of
                    summer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We just didn't have any particular clout there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: We had a little bit of clout in the sense that the Bulgarians had
                    agreed to CSCE conditions and terms. We certainly had no clout in trying to make
                    it a more reasonable exit for the Bulgarian Turks who wanted to go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were at a momentous time when things in Eastern Europe
                        fell apart.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: We saw what was happening in Czechoslovakia and East Berlion CNN and
                    then saw the Bulgarians themselves take part in the whole process. That became
                    the most rewarding part of the assignment. The most rewarding assignment in the
                    Foreign Service. Not only to watch, but to use whatever appropriate means we
                    had, to bring about change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are talking about the events of 1989. How were the
                        Bulgarians getting their information? How were they reacting initially?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: Some of them were getting their information from Western news sources,
                    where there was RFE or CNN in a smaller way. A fair amount of Western news
                    information was getting through. For the Bulgarians, they saw the Berlin Wall
                    being pierced, they saw it on their own television, so they knew what was
                    happening there. In fact, the piercing of the Wall and the ouster of Honeker
                    happened almost at the same time. Todor Zhirkov was the Bulgarian dictator or
                    Communist Party leader. For the Bulgarians, who saw what was happening elsewhere
                    in Eastern Europe, they used an environmental movement in effect to become the
                    political opposition. They used again a CSCE conference on environmental issues
                    that was taking place in Sofia as a way of getting their message out to the West
                    and drawing some support and inspiration from it. What happened in October was,
                    when the CSCE conference was taking place, some environmentalists wanted to use
                    the occasion to make their protest known to this international conference. The
                    Bulgarian police were not about to let it happen. There was a confrontation and
                    some of the environmentalists were roughed up. The caused some of the Western
                    governments to let the Bulgarians know that they were not going to tolerate this
                    kind of behavior in the conference. It caused a certain amount of turmoil within
                    the Bulgarian Communist Party and that really became a pretext for the more
                    moderate wing of the Bulgarian Communist Party to overthrow Zhirkov as simply
                    being to rigid. They knew from what was happening elsewhere iEastern Europe that
                    Zhirkowas not going to get any support from Gorbachev. In fact, Gorbachev, made
                    it plain that he wouldn't. Consequently, we had been suggesting to the
                    Department, it might be appropriate for Secretary Baker to come to Bulgaria at
                    some point, if he was traveling elsewhere in Eastern Europe, because it did seem
                    that at least there was some movement in the Bulgarian Communist Party toward a
                    more moderate view and it was something we ought to encourage and try and take
                    advantage of. In February of 1990, he did come to Sofia from Moscow, for a very
                    quick trip.He basically told the new Bulgarian Communist leaders, who were
                    really the group around Zhirkov, now without Zhirkov, that if they wanted a
                    better relationship with the US, and they had talked about free and fair
                    elections, that would be the measure of what we would judge Bulgaria by. If they
                    really had free and fair elections, we would respect the outcome and see where
                    we could try and improve and expand the relationship. That became the framework
                    within which we operated for the next four or five months until the Bulgarians
                    really did have elections.We wanted to make sure that the opposition really did
                    have a chance to express its views, had access to the media. I had many
                    discussions with the Bulgarian Prime Minister and others about the availability,
                    for the opposition of newsprint. I got all kinds of excuses from them why
                    newsprint couldn't be available in the quantities the opposition wanted. We
                    traveled all over the country talking about the importance of free elections.
                    The USIA and other organizations helped support the development of a public
                    Bulgarian organization to observe the elections and make sure the elections were
                    being held in a free and fair manner. The National Democratic Institute and the
                    National Republican Institute came in with equipment and gave training on how
                    opposition parties could organize themselves and conduct campaigns. All of this
                    was going on with the Communist Party tolerating it?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had they just lost heart?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: They saw what was happening elsewhere. The Bulgarian Communist Party
                    had been around for a long, long time. I think they felt they might stand a
                    chance to come out better than some of the communist parties did elsewhere in
                    Eastern Europe. They were really the only organized political force in the
                    country with any experience. They ran, in many ways, a more coherent campaign,
                    than the opposition did. The elections were held, there may have been some
                    slight manipulation. We did have, in addition to the unofficial Bulgarian
                    organization that was observing the election, international teams that came to
                    observe the elections, including one from the United States. By and large the
                    feeling was, the elections were free and open.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did it come out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: The results were that the opposition had something like forty three
                    percent and the Communists had something like thirty seven percent. You had a
                    new Parliament that had opposition as well as Communists in it. The opposition
                    was able to name a non-Communist person to be President. The Socialists went
                    along with it. You wound up with the first non Communist government in Bulgaria
                    in over forty-five years in August of 1990, with a non Communist President. It
                    was a very gratifying four or five months when we were able to conduct that kind
                    of activity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about police control? Were you able to see opposition
                        leaders as this went on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: At the beginning, in November of 1989, there was one small opposition
                    group, it stood for Glasnost and Perestroika, we had virtually no contact with
                    them. We gave all sorts of signals that we would like to have contact with them,
                    but for their own reasons, they simply felt it wasn't appropriate. It wasn't
                    until about December of 1989 that we were able to work out a very informal, but
                    useful meeting with Zhelev, who was the leader of this club, who subsequently
                    became the leader of this opposition and later the President. That part of it
                    was a hard go. They simply weren't ready at the time. After Secretary Baker came
                    in February of 1990, then it became easier and then you could see people and
                    have access to all sorts of people; they made themselves available. We went all
                    over the country talking to members of the opposition; talking to members of the
                    Socialist party, members of the Agrarian Party, basically just taking the
                    message we had about free and fair elections if they wanted a better relations
                    with the United States. I think we were unique in that, I don't think any other
                    Western Embassy went through that process the way we did. It's not sort of the
                    thing we were trained to do, it developed out of the circumstances.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left when and by that time had they created a new
                        government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: I left in August of 1990. They had created a new government. Zhelev was
                    sworn in as President on August 1st. I saw him on the fifteenth, just before I
                    left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is now 1993 and Yugoslavia is in a terrible mess. Did
                        Bulgaria have aspirations toward Macedonia, or any parts of Greece or
                        Turkey?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: The answer is no. The democratic opposition that came in really had no
                    territorial ambitions. They wanted to improve their relations with Turkey to the
                    extent that they could.They did virtually everything that the United States
                    asked Bulgaria to do in connection with the Gulf War. ThBulgarians lost oil
                    resources as a result of that. Iraq was one of their main suppliers. They lost a
                    tremendous amount of money, but they went along with the embargo without delay.
                    They let us know that they were going to take a terrible economic beating, but
                    they understood the importance of it and in the first year after the new
                    government came in, what they were trying to do was to demonstrate their
                    readiness in being forthcoming in their support of Western foreign policy on a
                    whole range of things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the concept of “Macegre” or Macedonia show its head at
                        all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: It has its roots back to the 1930s and even earlier. I don't think,
                    except maybe for a few small minority parties during the election period, the
                    idea of a greater Bulgaria, incorporating parts of Macedonia, ever entered into
                    it. There was a Royalist party, there still is, in terms of return to the King.
                    I think the whole question of Macedonia has obviously become more sensitive and
                    significant in connection with what's happening in Yugoslavia. I think a sense
                    of “Macedonianess” is being created in that part of Bulgaria, that is part of
                    Macedonia. My own feeling is that it is artificial on the Bulgarian side. It can
                    be stimulated but it is not being stimulated from the inside, it is being
                    stimulated from the outside. But it exists and it is becoming something that is
                    a little more worrisome to the Bulgarians. I think that is one of the reasons
                    the Bulgarians were very quick to recognize Macedonia as a separate, independent
                    state. I think they hoped that that would calm things down. I think Zhelev has
                    stroked the other party a number of times in order to maintain a relationship
                    wit them. I think there is some concern. If it keeps up in Yugoslavia, I think
                    the concern will increase and so will the sense of Macedonian nationalism.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left Bulgaria in August 1990.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>POLANSKY: Yes, I was assigned to ICAP as International Affairs Advisor. That was
                    quite a change. I didn't care for the quiet aspect of it. The opportunity came
                    along to be assigned to the Citizen's Democracy Corp, which sounded more
                    interesting, since it was an effort to contribute to the change that was taking
                    place in Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union. I was on loan for a year
                    helping to develop the organization and programs. Then when I reached
                    sixty-five, I decided to retire. I could have stayed on and gotten an exception
                    from the State Department. I decided to retire and stay on with the Citizen's
                    Democracy Corps in a paid position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain what the Citizens' Democracy Corps
                        is?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>POLANSKY: It grew out of a speech that President Bush gave in May, 1990. It was
                    an effort to enlist the enthusiasm of the American public as they saw what was
                    happening in Eastern Europe, in terms of the change, and try to develop a
                    non-profit, independent, bipartisan organization that would seek to provide
                    technical assistance to the democratic change and the effort to transform those
                    economies into market economies through providing managerial skills—not money;
                    not joint ventures, not loans. Instead, using the skills of American volunteers
                    and American corporations to work on issues of economic reform on a very
                    practical, micro way. Having people work in companies and organizations in order
                    to suggest how change can take place. The best example was to get people from
                    Union Pacific Railroad, who had absolutely no desire to buy the Polish railroad
                    system or to contribute to it in any way or to sell it things, but to send
                    people over to suggest ways in how the railroad system, which had hotels, farms,
                    and every other kind auxiliary enterprise attached to it, in addition to
                    railroads, could modernize and stream line itself. How it should go about
                    applying for loans from the World Bank in terms of modernizing itself. Supplying
                    that kind of technical assistance was one part of the program. Another part was
                    a clearing house which essentially put together all of the non-profit
                    organizations and all the individuals who expressed interest in helping, into a
                    data bank, and we developed a series of compendiums that listed all the
                    non-profit organizations and made those available to countries in Eastern
                    Europe. Then, in terms of the volunteers, at that time we didn't have our own
                    programs, what we said to organizations that called us for volunteers, was that
                    these people have expressed interest in working in Eastern Europe and they have
                    experience, some of them have language skills. We did not have any way of
                    knowing whether they really had the skills they claimed they did, but if the
                    organizations wanted to talk to them and recruit them, then it was fine. We did
                    that for awhile and after that we decided that there were volunteer programs
                    that we could develop in Eastern Europe and that's what we did. We wound up with
                    a program involving American corporations funding executives. We did a business
                    entrepreneurial program with volunteer American entrepreneurs working with small
                    and medium sized firms in Eastern Europe to try and supply managerial
                    assistance, not money. We put together programs of teams of American volunteers.
                    One example was of people who went to Bulgaria to help the Bulgarians begin the
                    process of starting of an extension service.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
