<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001189">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Philip H. Trezise </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>ASSISTANT SECRETARY PHILIP H. TREZISE</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Willis Armstrong </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 17, 1989</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Phil, tell me about how you got started in the Foreign
                        Service. What was your background before you were in it, and what interested
                        you about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, Bill, I actually came into the Foreign Service by direction of the
                    President. I was a Navy officer stationed in China during World War II, assigned
                    by the Navy to the Office of Strategic Services (OSS). As the war came to an
                    end, the element of OSS with which I was associated was transferred lock, stock,
                    and barrel to the State Department.</p>
                <p>So when I returned to the United States in November or December of 1945, I
                    reported for duty at the Department of State in something then called the Office
                    of Intelligence Research. I was in the Navy still, of course, and I was not
                    discharged until March or April of the following year. In the meantime, I went
                    to work in the China branch of this Office of Intelligence Research.</p>
                <p>When I was discharged from the Navy, I had the choice of staying on in the
                    Department or going off to work for the Continental Can Company, which had
                    offered me a job during the war. The job had been held open. But inertia, I
                    suppose, kept me where I was. So I stayed in the OIR, Office of Intelligence
                    Research, and became a civil servant. I remained a civil servant until the
                    program for amalgamating the Foreign Service and the civil service began in the
                    early 1950s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I didn't realize you were in the same boat I was in that.
                        Yes, I was a civil servant also.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: So in 1953 or '54, I took the oath of office as a Foreign Service
                    officer. I was then still in OIR, but I moved to the policy planning staff not
                    so long afterward. From there I was assigned to the embassy in Japan in 1957.
                    That was the beginning of my career as a Foreign Service officer, after having
                    had six or seven years as a civil servant in the Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your specialization in OIR, Japan?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>TREZISE: No, it was China. But then I didn't stay very long in the China branch,
                    because I was asked by an old friend of yours, Walt Butterworth, to go to
                    Indonesia as a member of a group assigned to the United Nations Good Offices
                    Committee, which was mediating the struggle between the Netherlands and the
                    Republic of Indonesia.</p>
                <p>So I went to Indonesia and was there—that was in 1948—and I stayed most of that
                    year in Indonesia. I came back and, thereafter, moved briefly to the Bureau of
                    Economic Affairs, as it was in those days. I stayed there only briefly because
                    the Office of Intelligence Research asked me if I would like to be assigned to
                    the War College, with the understanding that I would return to OIR.</p>
                <p>So I went to the War College in 1949. I had the '49-'50 year there and then came
                    back to OIR as chief of the Division of Research for the Far East. That, too,
                    was a very brief assignment because they had an opening in the Division of
                    Research for the Near East and South Asia. Despite my lack of area background, I
                    transferred to the Near East Division as division chief.</p>
                <p>I didn't stay there terribly long, probably a year or a year and a half. Then I
                    moved up to be the Deputy Director of the Office of Intelligence Research. From
                    there, I believe in 1954, I moved to the policy planning side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had a lot of successive appointments there, all of
                        very considerable interest.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, they were. Not that I was wildly over qualified, particularly for
                    the Near East Division, but the division was in bad straits. I may say, I
                    probably did straighten it out somewhat. They weren't sure what they were
                    supposed to do and where they were going. I think that I got at least some of
                    the people moving in the right direction.</p>
                <p>It was interesting, too, because that was a period of upheaval in the Near East.
                    King Farouk was overthrown. A leader in Iraq, Nuri al-Said, was killed and a new
                    government was installed. Most important of all was the big upheaval in Iran,
                    when the Shah was overthrown. Mossadegh took over as head of the government of
                    Iran for a couple of years until, through a method that I have never entirely
                    understood, the Shah was restored to power. Some people believe that CIA was
                    instrumental in doing this. Perhaps it was. It wasn't clear to me, from all the
                    intelligence, that the CIA was necessarily the sole instrument. But the Shah did
                    come back and lasted a good long time thereafter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was in oil at that point. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>TREZISE: It was a very interesting period. There was a feeling that both Iran and
                    the United Kingdom would go down the drain because the oil was so important to
                    the two economies. It certainly excited a lot of attention, including our Under
                    Secretary Mr. Hoover who—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I found myself working for Mr. Hoover at that point and
                        also, in effect, working for Mr. Henderson, who had originally hired me for
                        the Foreign Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes, Loy Henderson, he was a great man.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tremendous man.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, that was pretty much it, Bill, up to, as I say, 1954 or
                    thereabout. At that time, I moved over to join Bob Bowie at the policy planning
                    staff. I had had a lot of experience with the staff prior to that as a member of
                    the staff from OIR. You know, the staff was—perhaps still is—a great talking
                    machine, a daily bull session. I would go over to staff meetings when Paul Nitze
                    was in charge and I continued to go off and on as a sort of ex-officio member
                    after Bowie took over.</p>
                <p>So when Bowie suggested I come over as a full-time member—and since I was
                    planning anyway to go overseas—I decided it would be a good stepping stone for
                    my next assignment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Bowie there with Nitze?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He replaced Nitze, didn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes. Bowie had been in Germany with Jack McCloy, and when the Eisenhower
                    administration came in, he was recommended by McCloy. Both, he and Nitze were
                    outstanding people, of course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, they are.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: They were quite influential too. Mr. Dulles, for one, was not easily
                    moved. But Bowie, I think, had his ear and could influence his thinking or at
                    least get him to listen.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever hear of Mr. McBurbo?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Merchant.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Merchant, MacArthur, and Bowie, yes. They were Mr. Dulles' favorites
                    among the Senior people in the Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, the fact is that MacArthur asked me to come to Japan with him. He
                    went to Japan in the early part of 1957, and before he left, he had arranged for
                    me to join him there as economic counselor. Why he chose me I have never known.
                    He didn't explain. But he had had long talks with Bowie, and Bowie, no doubt,
                    had some part in it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: MacArthur, himself, was not a great Far Eastern expert,
                        was he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: By no means.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I knew him. He was in EUR.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: That's right. He was in EUR—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Western Europe, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: He had been in France during the Vichy regime, during the war. He came
                    to have a close acquaintance with General Eisenhower. Not during the war, but
                    certainly after the war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: So he had, really, a direct line to the White House, which few
                    ambassadors had. He could pick up the telephone and reach the President without
                    the problems that most ambassadors would have encountered.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>In any event, I went to Japan in the Spring of '57, and stayed there through
                    MacArthur's tenure and through the first six months or so of Ed Reischauer. Ed
                    took over after the Kennedy victory in 1960. He came in March, I believe, of
                    1961 and I stayed with him until October of that year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you had four years there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: I had four years there. A bit longer than that, actually, because I
                    should have gone home in April, and I stayed until, I think, October. I sent my
                    family home earlier and stayed on because the deputy chief of mission had left.
                    I was acting as DCM until he returned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was an extraordinary period for Japan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: It was indeed. I have often remarked that the first month I was there,
                    the Japanese had a balance-of-payments crisis. It was a true crisis. Their
                    foreign exchange reserve had been drawn down to a few hundred million dollars,
                    and they were really in quite a stew. The reason for the problem was that the
                    country had been growing so fast and had been sucking in imports at a fabulous
                    pace. In those days, believe it or not, Japan had a deficit on trade account.
                    While they were exporting—their exports were growing fast—imports were growing
                    even faster.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I suppose the imports were largely capital goods
                        because—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Capital goods and raw materials. Yes, in those days, consumer goods were
                    not imported on any sizable scale.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Never were. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: To this day, they're not terribly great. Well, the extraordinary things
                    about this episode were, first, that the Finance Minister resigned. That was Mr.
                    Ikeda, who later became Prime Minister. He resigned and somebody else was put in
                    his place.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>The Bank of Japan and the Finance Ministry then imposed a credit squeeze on the
                    economy. Its results were really something to see. I made a trip around Japan at
                    that time to get acquainted with some of the other cities. Everywhere I went
                    there were buildings that had been started and construction had stopped. There
                    were shells of buildings everywhere in the country. The construction boom, which
                    was part of a total boom in Japan, was just choked off because nobody could get
                    credit, and they simply could not continue. There was great anguish in the
                    business community about the policy, but the government stayed with it.</p>
                <p>By the winter, the external account was approaching balance again. Their big
                    deficits were behind them. And by the next summer, the boom had resumed. All
                    that investment activity that had been stopped was under way again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They've never looked back since.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Haven't looked back since. But that would have been '58. Well, '58 and
                    '59 were big years. In '60 they had the political upheaval which involved us, of
                    course. That was the year President Eisenhower was going to make the first ever
                    visit of an American President to Japan. We turned the embassy upside down to
                    plan for that visit. I was writing speeches for the President—not my job at all.
                    The administrative people had everything organized to a T. Everybody knew where
                    he would be, whether he'd turn left or right, where the President would stop,
                    and who would get out of the car first. Everything was organized.</p>
                <p>But then, for reasons really quite extraneous to the United States, a political
                    upheaval arose against the then Prime Minister, Mr. Kishi. We had renegotiated
                    our security treaty, which had been imposed on Japan as a price for the peace
                    treaty. We had renegotiated it to meet many of the Japanese' quite legitimate
                    complaints about its one-sidedness. But the opposition parties, including some
                    of the left-wing trade unions, organized and moved against ratification of the
                    treaty, even though, in fact, all the objectives that the Japanese government
                    had, had been achieved.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, they mounted this enormous campaign, primarily street
                    demonstrations. And just before the President was supposed to arrive, they had a
                    small riot near the Diet building, and a young girl was crushed to death in the
                    fighting between the police and the students. There were mainly students in that
                    demonstration. This was a culmination of some weeks of demonstrating. The upshot
                    was that the government lost its nerve and said it could not guarantee the
                    President's safety if he came. So the visit was called off. The President was
                    already in the Philippines. Instead of going to Japan, he went to Taiwan and had
                    a visit there. He was, of course, furious.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He had quite a temper, Mr. Eisenhower.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes, well, it was kind of crisis in U.S.-Japan relations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember it. I was in Canada at that point. It was a
                        real black eye for the United States.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: It was. It was indeed. And though I'm not an expert on Japanese
                    politics, I have always believed that the problem that Mr. Kishi had was not the
                    treaty. That was chosen by the opposition parties and the trade unions as an
                    excuse for trying to drive Kishi out of office, because he had earlier proposed
                    a new police powers bill. Some of the elements in that bill seemed to hark back
                    to the pre-war system of police control.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: This caused a great deal of unhappiness, not only among the students and
                    the trade unions and the left-wing parties, but in parts of the business
                    community as well. People saw this as something that might turn Japan back
                    toward a period that most Japanese would like to forget.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kishi was the author of this. Indeed, when he came into power, one of his
                    positions was to strengthen the powers of the police over internal security
                    matters. So he was removed from office not long after the aborted presidential
                    visit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Americans think it was basically a pretext?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Basically, it was an excuse chosen by the opposition as the first
                    opening they had. Actually, the police power bill was never enacted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Never was.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: The Diet—the Parliament—simply sat on it because of the widespread
                    opposition. But the thought that somebody would propose it was enough to make
                    Kishi a target. He had been a great friend of the United States. Indeed, there
                    was a point of view that he was the American prime minister. We had chosen him
                    for the job, or so it was said.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's a downside risk in that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>TREZISE: In any event, out he went. Mr. Ikeda came in. There was a wonderful
                    example of a politician doing the right thing. He didn't talk about the security
                    treaty, which by then had been ratified anyway. He said he had a plan for
                    doubling national income in ten years. And everybody seized on the so-called
                    plan. It wasn't a plan at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Release the forces.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: It was just a political statement. We will double national income in ten
                    years. In fact the economy rose at a pace faster than his double national income
                    objective. That would have required a bit more than seven percent growth per
                    year whereas the economy grew at more than nine percent a year during the
                    decade.</p>
                <p>So Mr. Ikeda's regime was a success. He was a Prime Minister for a long time. He
                    died in office, or he got cancer and had to leave office, and died shortly
                    afterward. During his tenure Japan began to come out of its shell. Well, by that
                    time, I was out of Japan and back in the—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long was he in office? From about '60—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: He was in office, I think, for eight years, I believe, or almost eight
                    years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Eight years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: He was succeeded by his brother, who was named in the Japanese fashion.
                    It was not Ikeda, but Sato. I think they had been orphaned and had been adopted
                    by a family. One took the family name and the other did not. In any event, his
                    brother, Mr. Sato, became Prime Minister just before President Nixon won the
                    election in the United States. He was the man with whom Nixon and Kissinger
                    dealt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a long period of great continuity in Japanese
                        politics.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Oh, yes. Well, of course, they have had the same ruling party since
                    1955, and even longer than that, really. In 1955 the two conservative parties,
                    the Liberals and the Democrats, consolidated into a single party, the Liberal
                    Democratic party. That party has governed Japan since.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's had a few ups and downs in the more recent years, but
                        it was very solid for a long time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes, and even in recent years, the downside periods were not so serious.
                    Certainly not as serious as the one they're now in, which is the first true
                    crisis that that party has ever encountered. And it's by no means clear how they
                    will get out of it. However, we are running way ahead of a . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, when you came back from Japan, it was what, 1961,
                        '62?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: In November of '61, I remember reporting for duty in the Bureau of
                    Economic Affairs. Edwin Martin was assistant secretary in those days. And I was
                    to be his senior deputy. The other deputies were Mike Blumenthal and Andy
                    Kerr.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I did business with Blumenthal from Canada, I
                        remember.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, Ed Martin did not stay long as assistant secretary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He had a very short tour as economic assistant
                        secretary.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes, well, he brought me back in, as I say, in November, and I think in
                    December or January he moved on to the Latin American bureau. And Grif Johnson
                    came in to be assistant secretary.</p>
                <p>So I stayed there from 1961 until the end of '65. Grif Johnson had been replaced
                    by Anthony Solomon in the fall of '65. At that point I was due for reassignment
                    anyway and George Ball and Dean Rusk persuaded LBJ that I should be sent to the
                    OECD. No easy task I might say—to persuade LBJ to do anything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On any subject.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: On any subject. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Especially if he had thought about it beforehand.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: He had given me the presidential award only a few months earlier. But
                    that cut no ice. He said, “ I don't care about that.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Presidential award was for work in the Department or
                        in Japan?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>TREZISE: No, in the Department. It was really for the Canadian automobile
                    agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Also on that citation was a negotiation we had with Romania about giving
                    Romania MFN treatment, and otherwise opening commercial relationships with
                    Romania. Romania was beginning to act independently of the Soviet Union on
                    foreign policy questions. So it was desired that we strengthen the regime in
                    Romania. It was, of course, a dictatorship, as it is still.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ceausescu was in then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes, oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He had been there forever, hadn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: They had decided that their relationship with the Soviet Union was too
                    all inclusive, and they wanted to stretch out a bit. And they did in fact, but
                    Ceausescu has not been a terribly attractive playmate over the years. I guess
                    nowadays our relations with Romania are rather poor. But anyway, those were the
                    reasons for the presidential award, called, I think, the Presidential
                    Distinguished Service Award.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you say you got a medal for it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Oh yes, a medal, a lapel button, a plaque, and a picture of myself with
                    LBJ and J. Edgar Hoover. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Proves your security clearance is all right, anyway, or he
                        wouldn't have had his picture taken with you. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: One of the other awardees in the group was a fellow from the FBI, so in
                    the picture taken with LBJ and myself was Hoover.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He couldn't resist the camera, I'm sure. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>TREZISE: Maybe that was it. Well, I think, Bill, that brings us up to where we
                    were on the second part of this tape.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where we started with the OECD job there? Did we?
                        Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes. We had discussed, I guess, the Canadian automobile agreement a bit
                    in the first tape. But it's also on the tape that I edited, so I don't know that
                    we want to go over that again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Essential elements are in there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: And that was a great event of my four years in what was then the E
                    Bureau.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was from '61 to '65?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's see, I came back and had charge of Canadian affairs
                        from '62 to '64.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Date: January 27, 1989Interviewer: Mr. Willis Armstrong</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I am here with Philip Trezise, who is just talking about
                        the free trade agreement in automobiles with Canada which was negotiated
                        1964-1965.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, as you know, the agreement had been something of a contentious
                    matter, or has been until recently, at least, for most of the period since it
                    was signed. Initially, our large balance in automobile trade with Canada more or
                    less vanished. The Treasury became very unhappy about that during the Nixon
                    Administration and, at one point, tried to have the agreement nullified.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They tried that when you were Assistant Secretary?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They had given it up by the time I was Assistant
                        Secretary.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>TREZISE: Oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were still very uncomfortable about it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Grumbling about it, yes. Well, actually, what happened was that, after
                    the initial surge of Canadian exports to the United States, our exports held up
                    more or less to Canada, but it had been a big swing. But in the 70's our surplus
                    in the auto trade recovered because we became a large exporter of parts and
                    components for automobiles, while the Canadians became a large exporter of
                    finished cars. Now that was a very deliberate decision on the part of the
                    Canadians. They thought that assembly was a better part of the operation than
                    making parts, so they skewed the arrangement in favor of assembly. To this day,
                    assembly is still dominant, although now, of course, because of exchange rates
                    and other matters, we're a big importer of parts, as well, from Canada.</p>
                <p>In any case, this had several effects. For one, it caused wages in Canada to
                    generally rise because the assembly people tended in general to be the highest
                    paid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The UAW, because it was in both countries, worked for wage
                        equality.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: That's right. I told Simon [Reisman] while we were negotiating the
                    agreement that Canada must expect that wages would have to rise. The Canadians
                    somehow discounted that. Anyway, it gave the Canadians something of a problem
                    for awhile. In the end, of course, the economy adapted to it and Canada is a
                    much higher wage country than it would have been without the auto agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It also makes for more disparity between Ontario and some
                        of the other provinces in terms of wage levels and income levels.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Exactly. It's no accident that the Quebec provincial and the national
                    government put $250 million into keeping General Motors in Quebec at the Ste.
                    Therese plant, which they were going to give up. In other words, the Canadians
                    put a quarter of a billion dollars into subsidies to keep GM in Quebec. You are
                    quite right. The Ontario opposition to free trade is founded on a
                    misapprehension. The province has benefitted enormously from free trade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They will benefit the most because they are in the best
                        position.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Exactly.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They've got the infrastructure, and the resources, and the
                        people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Sure, the trained people. It's a high wage province, but it has high
                    productivity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They want all that and total independence, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Of course, that's the human condition. I'm reconciled to these things
                    nowadays, though. Well, that was my Deputy Assistant Secretary days. There were
                    lots of other things I suppose I could recall, but that was a high point. In
                    fact, LBJ gave me a medal for it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You deserved it, if I may say so.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, I've forgotten what it's called.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The President's Award for Distinguished Federal Civilian
                        Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: That's right. It's principal shortcoming was there was no money attached
                    to it. It was just a medal, which I've never worn. It's a huge, heavy thing. It
                    would have to be a full dress affair to wear anything like that.</p>
                <p>Then I went to OECD at the end of 1965. By then Tony Solomon had come in to be
                    Assistant Secretary. He wanted his own staff. I had been four years in the job
                    and I was going to move anyway, so OECD looked fine to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had Grif Johnson most of that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes. And Grif was a great fellow to work with and for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He always struck me as a man of excellent instincts.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Excellent instincts and a very honest and decent person.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A very nice person, yes. I was devoted to him, also.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>TREZISE: I had known Grif, initially, when he was a member, as was I, of the
                    Gordon Gray Commission in 1950.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, was he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Walter Salent, Kermit Gordon, and Ray Miksell were among the others.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is Grif still alive?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes. He's retired and lives near Annapolis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Kermit and I went to the same college and I knew him when
                        he was here at Brookings. A fine man also. A great loss.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, I was at OECD for more than three years. I went at the end of 1965
                    and I came back in the spring of 1969. It wasn't quite four years. OECD was an
                    interesting experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me go back just one moment to one point I think is
                        worth emphasis on the Canadian matter. And that is, because Mr. Diefenbaker
                        left office in 1963 and Mr. Pearson took his place, you had a political
                        momentum started under Kennedy and continued under Johnson which, I think,
                        must have been an underlying factor. Of course, I worked on the political
                        side.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, you are absolutely right. As a matter of fact, when LBJ presented
                    the agreement to the press down in Austin, what he stressed was that we had
                    avoided a confrontation and a political dispute with Canada. As far as the
                    automobile agreement itself was concerned, it was entirely political from his
                    point of view. I've forgotten what Pearson said in reply, but I'm sure it was in
                    the same vein.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it's highly questionable whether Pearson ever
                        understood the automobile agreement.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, LBJ also. All that mattered was that Dillon and Ball knew what it
                    was and they wanted it. Dillon, especially, was very anxious to get it done. He
                    was a wonderful person.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. I worked rather closely with Dillon one time. I
                        thought he was great.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes, I have great respect for him. OECD, as you know, covers a whole
                    range of things. It is still the principal agency for international consultation
                    on economic policy. Even though the Group of Seven and others have captured the
                    headlines, it is still OECD where most of the nuts and bolts of economic policy
                    are discussed. But the OECD also deals with trade, and with agriculture, and
                    with all the concerns that this group of industrialized countries have with one
                    another. And, of course, it now includes not only the core group from the old
                    European Marshall Plan Countries and the United States and Canada, but also
                    Japan, Australia, and New Zealand. I suppose in time it will have Korea,
                    Singapore, Brazil, others as members.</p>
                <p>I think it is an institution we need to keep alive and foster. Of course, it does
                    not have money to spend, unlike the World Bank and the Fund. It doesn't really
                    have a treaty to administer or an executive agreement, although there are
                    portions of the OECD charter that do involve specific obligations on capital
                    movements. But, apart from that, it's a talking place.</p>
                <p>During the years that the Kennedy Round was going on I took part, particularly in
                    the final stages, where we negotiated the Canadian and Australian bilaterals.
                    The Canadian one was much the most interesting because we had the zero duty
                    authority and we had lots of low tariffs to bargain with. We could go to zero on
                    anything on which the tariff was five percent or less.</p>
                <p>We'd had some rather desultory talks with Canada, to no conclusion. But in the
                    last week of the Kennedy Round, we became serious about an agreement. The
                    Canadian team was led by Simon Reisman and he had with him pretty much the same
                    people as had taken part in the automobile trade talks in 1964-65.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was Deputy Minister of Finance, wasn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes, I believe so. Anyway, I began at our final session by saying, “You
                    know, we have zero duty authority and I'm prepared to give you free entry for
                    all these things except aluminum.” I couldn't get interagency support on
                    aluminum. And then I offered some other things and I said, “From you, we want,
                    particularly, tariff concessions on machinery.” So I went through the proposal
                    and said that I would like to have their reaction to it.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>Simon, who is nothing if not an inveterate negotiator, he jumped up on his chair,
                    saying “this is a derisory proposition.” He used stronger words than that, too,
                    as was his wont. He went on about what a terrible thing I had offered, primarily
                    because I wasn't going to give them a zero tariff on aluminum. After his tirade
                    I said, “Well, Simon, I don't think we're going to get anywhere right away
                    because you haven't even considered my proposal. Why don't we break for lunch
                    and we'll come back and see how far apart we are.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was in Ottawa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: No, in Geneva.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Paris?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: No. Geneva. It was the Canadian Minister's house, I remember that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think Norman Robertson was involved in that, wasn't he,
                        for awhile?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: I don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He did Kennedy Round after he retired.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: He probably was, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I saw him in Geneva at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, I remember going to see him in Ottawa. He was a fine man, wasn't
                    he.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, a very interesting man.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Anyway, Bob McNeil of the Commerce Department was my partner in this, as
                    was true of the auto agreement. We went off to lunch and shortly thereafter
                    Simon and his troop came in to the restaurant we had chosen. After we had
                    finished our meal and were walking out and Simon beckoned me over to his table
                    and said, “You know, what you suggested is probably all right. Let's go back and
                    see what we've got.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He had to blow his stack first.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: He had to blow his stack. Anyway, we settled.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a marvelous story.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: This seemed at the time like a great success. It probably was in the
                    sense that we got rid of some duties that didn't make any sense and the
                    Canadians did their part reasonably well. But then I went on to the Australians
                    and that was a total failure. To this day I have regrets about that. Not that I
                    could have changed it, I suppose.</p>
                <p>But, you know, I was raised in the Taussig tradition of free trade. But also, the
                    wool tariff was, for Taussig, one of the most abominable of tariffs. And we had
                    authority in the 1962 law to give the Australians free entry for wool. I
                    thought, my God, here I'm going to be part of something historic. We're going to
                    get rid of the wool tariff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Shades of Senator O'Mahoney. I had a lot of arguments with
                        him about the wool tariff.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Oh, yes. The wool tariff goes way back, I suppose, in our history.
                    Anyway, my associates were from the Agriculture Department and they tried hard
                    to be helpful. But trying to get any concession from the Australians in return
                    for the wool tariff—we could give them some other things, but that was the big
                    one—we tried and tried to no avail. We tried, I remember, to find some way to
                    get easier entry for our tobacco in Australia. We would recess and go off and
                    dream up another gimmick. Eventually, of course, we had no settlement with
                    Australia. We didn't reduce the wool tariff and they didn't reduce anything. It
                    was a complete wash. Of course, they got some benefits, I suppose, from the
                    other reductions we made, but on the things of bilateral interest, it was a
                    zero. To this day, I think that was an opportunity lost. It was the Australians'
                    fault.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember negotiating in commodity terms during the
                        Korean War the requirements for wool cloth on the part of the U.S. military.
                        They were astronomical. And they were going to use all the wool in the
                        world, all the wool the world would produce, they'd be glad to use it this
                        year. And, of course, this was silly because synthetics were beginning to
                        come in and all that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>But I spent weeks on end trying to negotiate an agreement to make sure that
                    during the Korean War we got as much wool as we really wanted from Australia.
                    And I failed, too. I had a hell of a lot of interesting conversations. I was
                    dealing with a man called McCarthy who was their High Commissioner in London.
                    This went on for weeks on end. I don't know how many weeks I spent in London
                    arguing commodities during the Korean War. Of course, it was nice to be in
                    London, but the conversations were difficult.</p>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, Australians, maybe they're easier now. They're becoming a bit more
                    free tradish.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, the most recent government they've had in Australia,
                        since about 1984 or 85, Hawke, they've made pretty good sense.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes. Curiously enough, a labor government is more open to free
                    trade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you have to remember the other government, which was
                        Menzies for a long time, almost entirely consisted of sheep farmers. And
                        some suggestions have been made that they weren't much brighter than the
                        sheep. Well, what else was there while you were in OECD? You had the
                        Canadian negotiation. That was a sideline, really.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: OECD was shaping up as a genuine and important body at
                        that time, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were all kinds of discussions.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes. We did all kinds of things there. I guess one that remains in my
                    mind was something that originated with a couple of British people on the OECD
                    staff. They were in charge of something called Science and Technology. The
                    director, a Mr. King, was quite an accomplished person who had lots of ideas,
                    some very bad unfortunately. One that he came up with, or, at least, he adopted,
                    was the idea that there was a big technological gap between the United States
                    and Western Europe and that something should be done to narrow it. In effect, a
                    Marshall Plan for the transfer of technology was needed, or so he argued.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember that. I was in Britain at the time. We used to
                        hear about this from Wedgewood Benn, who became the Minister of Technology.
                        And he was going to set up technology centers all around the country so you
                        could buy some, as in a supermarket.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: To help run this, they brought in a fellow named Bill Branson, who
                    teaches at Princeton now. Branson is one of our top-flight academic economists.
                    But he adopted the King idea, too. Then I began to think, why am I allowing this
                    organization to go into this project anyway? The more I looked at it, the more I
                    realized this was really an attack on two companies, IBM and Boeing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: And so I wrote a memo. I didn't want to do this orally. I wrote to the
                    Secretary General saying that I was simply appalled at the idea that the OECD
                    could pick up so flimsy an idea, aimed at perfectly legitimate firms in the
                    United States. That was kind of a bombshell, I suppose, to the Science and
                    Technology.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that when Kristensen was there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes. Well, they went ahead and wrote a report, which turned out to be
                    essentially nothing. I wouldn't allow them to say anything of the kind that they
                    had in mind originally, so it proved to be quite harmless.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You have a ground rule in the OECD that you don't pick on
                        individual countries, don't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Well, yes. Particularly when there is no case. I was prepared to listen
                    to something reasonable, but this was foolish because the more you looked at it,
                    the more you realized that IBM was the dominant computer maker in Europe. Well,
                    it was in Europe. There wasn't any technological gap. IBM was there making
                    computers in Europe to the best of its ability.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sure.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>TREZISE: And as for Boeing, there were other airplane makers. At that time, the
                    French were still pretty active and they had that small, rather good airplane,
                    the name of which I have now forgotten. But anyway, it didn't make any sense to
                    talk about a technological gap. Anybody could enter the aviation market. Boeing
                    was leading, but there were others. And, furthermore, Boeing dominated the big
                    aircraft sector but smaller planes were being produced elsewhere. Anyway, the
                    upshot of it was that we killed that off pretty well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As I remember now, we heard a lot about it for awhile and
                        then it got lost somewhere.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: There were all sorts of things going on in OECD. I developed an
                    assistance committee for aid to Greece, I recall. But, I guess, in the end,
                    after three and a half years there, I was ready to try something else. When
                    Nixon became President I was called back to Washington quite early in the
                    Administration to talk to the White House about textiles. One of the factions in
                    the White House wanted me to go around to Japan, Korea, Hong Kong, and Taiwan to
                    open the way for a textile negotiation which would expand the cotton textile
                    agreement to cover synthetic fabrics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the origin of the multi-fiber?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes. So I said, sure, I would do it if they allowed me to pick the
                    people that I would have to go along and get a clear mandate from the President
                    as to what he wanted. But that faction was overruled and Morrie Stans was given
                    the responsibility. He went at it rather differently and, I thought, not very
                    wisely. The first thing he did was to come to Europe.</p>
                <p>I remember giving him a luncheon. I was still at OECD and he came there, along
                    with Hank Houtaker, and Carl Gilbert, and others. But all he wanted to talk
                    about to the Europeans was textiles. And, of course, they weren't about to give
                    him anything. They had no reason to. They would ride on our coattails, of
                    course, but they didn't want to get out in front.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Their perception of the problem was the same as the U.S.
                        perception.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Very much, but they weren't ready to jump into an attack on Hong Kong,
                    and so on. The British had their problems. The Stans visit had no point, as far
                    as I could see. The issues were in the Far East.</p>
                <p>Well, anyway, I didn't do that. But while I was there, Mr. Rogers offered me the
                    Assistant Secretary job. I wasn't so sure about that. Frankly, I was hoping I
                    would get another embassy and I delayed.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think I understand that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: I wanted to go to someplace like Sweden, which struck me as an
                    interesting country. I did not expect a major post, but another four years in an
                    embassy appealed to me. Well, I didn't get it. Alex Johnson kept pushing me so I
                    came back and became Assistant Secretary along in April or May.</p>
                <p>Looking back on those two years as Assistant Secretary, I really cannot say that
                    my accomplishments were ones that I'm terribly proud of. One was to put a quota
                    on Canadian oil. And in retrospect, I realize how ill-advised I was. But you
                    remember, in those days we had a kind of a quasi-voluntary arrangement in which
                    the Canadians would restrict their exports of shipments of oil to us, somewhat
                    in accord with the way we treated Venezuela.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had the overland exemption.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: We had the overland exemption.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My wife negotiated that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: That's right. But, of course, we didn't want the overland exemption to
                    allow free movement of oil into the United States. It had to be limited. The
                    Texans and the Oklahoma people wanted to restrict everybody's oil, but Canada
                    was the big loophole, potentially.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They still do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: But then on the other side were Hubert Humphrey and the Minnesotans, who
                    had the refineries which depended on the Canadian oil. It was always a
                    struggle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They'd have to close the refineries if they didn't have
                        Canadian oil.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: That's right. Well, the Texans and the Oklahomans always won. In any
                    case, President Nixon created an interagency committee under George Shultz, who
                    was then Labor Secretary, to look at the oil program we then had. As you
                    remember, we had a quota program, a formal restriction of oil from everybody,
                    except Canada. Mexico was not a big factor then. They were selling only heavy
                    oil, asphalt. They had an overland exemption but their shipments were of no
                    consequence.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We did the Brownsville Loop.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes, that's right. It was very, very heavy oil which was almost asphalt
                    as it came out of the ground. It had to be heated to put it into trucks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They had to heat the trucks in order so it could go
                        through Mexico and come back.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: That was Tom Mann's really weird idea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It sounds like a Tom Mann idea.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: On George Shultz's committee he had Maurice Stans and somebody from the
                    agency in charge of regulating natural gas. But everybody else was prepared to
                    look at a way of getting rid of the quotas and going to a tariff system. And
                    that's what the majority was prepared to recommend. But John Mitchell intervened
                    and so nothing came of that.</p>
                <p>In the course of the Shultz deliberations we had a lot of talk about what to do
                    about Canada. I said, well, why don't we see if we can get the Canadians to
                    agree to free trade in energy, that is have a policy for the North American
                    Continent. Well, it may have been a great idea, but we really didn't do enough
                    work on it. We opened discussions on it with the Canadians and it became clear
                    soon enough we weren't going to get very far with a continental oil policy. So
                    we were back on the quota question.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Continental is a bad word in Canada.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes. Well, as I say, I handled it badly. In retrospect, I can't say that
                    I acted very sensibly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are now getting there, though.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes. But at that time it wasn't feasible. But there we were back with
                    the voluntary quota arrangement in the early part of 1970. And I had, of course,
                    on my delegation the Interior Department people and the Oklahoma-Texas
                    supports.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very close behind you.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes, breathing down my neck. We had a big meeting in Montreal. We went
                    round and round about a Canadian agreement to restrict oil shipments. Remember,
                    by 1970 we were beginning to become a big importer. The Texas surplus was pretty
                    well diminished. And there we were, quite wrongly, trying to restrict Canadian
                    shipment. We should have been saying, “Ship all you wish.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1972 we imported more than we produced. That was the
                        first time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: That's right. But I must say, along with the people who worked with me,
                    including Jim Akins, who was something of a guru on oil, didn't fully appreciate
                    the importance of what was happening. So, in any event, after we came to an
                    impasse in the meeting I said, “well, all right, I'll go back and recommend that
                    we put on a formal quota,” and we did. We got a lot of flack from free traders
                    around town and from Canada, where it was a seven day wonder that the Americans
                    had done this to us. Of course, we were going to do it anyway on a so-called
                    voluntary basis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But it was big enough to take care of most business,
                        wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Oh, yes, sure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't a real problem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: It was a little less than they were asking, but it was more than Texas
                    and Oklahoma would want.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a reasonable judgment on the market.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes. It wasn't all that bad. But, in retrospect, I think if we had done
                    our homework better and been a little braver, I could have said right then and
                    there, well, all right, we'll accept your offer. The White House would have
                    supported me. Peter Flanagan was my contact there and he would have said, “Okay,
                    your judgment does it.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get along with Flanagan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Very well. I didn't have to deal with Kissinger, which was a great
                    thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't have to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: I almost had nothing to do with Kissinger. He interfered now and then,
                    but I could go to Flanagan and talk to him sensibly. I got along well with him.
                    I had no trouble.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I always found that with Flanagan. I always found him a
                        sensible guy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: I thought they didn't give him adequate recognition. They brought in
                    Peterson, who didn't really know anything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get along with him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Not very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you know anybody who does?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: I don't know. I had difficulty with him from the word go. The trouble
                    with Pete was that he was an advertising man. The first thing he did was write a
                    paper which he wanted to publish in the form of a book. The thing was kind of
                    dumb, you know; in fact, it was terrible. Well, we had a big meeting at Camp
                    David to kill it off. I remember Herb Stein and everybody came, and we killed
                    it. But then he kept trying to write this exposition of economic policy and,
                    since he didn't know anything to begin with, it was very difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I found it very difficult. We had him give it to the U.S.
                        Consul for International Business. I was with them from 1969 to 1972 and he
                        came up and made this pitch. He was, obviously, the big know-it-all and
                        do-it-all in Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My problem with him later was that he became a mouthpiece
                        for Kissinger in dealing with Russia. And when I was negotiating lend-lease
                        with the Russians I had three points of instruction: one was Bill Rogers,
                        and one was Flanagan, and one was Kissinger. They never agreed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes, I can imagine.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had a lot of fun. It was quite a circus.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you were fortunate not to have to deal with
                        Kissinger.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: The only time I really had any dealing with Kissinger, the one time in
                    the two years I was Assistant Secretary, had to do with oil. And that must have
                    been in early 1971 when Qadhafi, raised the price of Libyan oil. Libyan oil was
                    the preferred oil for many of the European utilities and users. It was sweet
                    oil, better than what the Saudis sell, and it was cheap, and nearby. So when
                    they raised the price and threatened to withhold oil and so on, it caused
                    considerable stir in Western Europe. Jim Akins was running the oil division or
                    section of the Economics Bureau.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. I remember. I worked with Jim, too. You worked for
                        him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If he was your subordinate, you found yourself working for
                        him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: He was nothing if not an activist. We got along. He came up and he said,
                    in effect, this is likely to get out of hand. Why don't we summon the
                    representatives from the countries that are principally concerned, including
                    Japan, and see if we can't get an understanding on a common position.” I thought
                    that made sense and we did so.</p>
                <p>Then Jim called in the oil companies and he said, “Now, are you fellows going to
                    have a common line? Are you going to negotiate together or are you all going to
                    go off in your own way?” Oh, no, they were going to get together, but they said,
                    “What about anti-trust?” So we went over to the Department of Justice and talked
                    to the anti-trust people. They were rather doubtful but, eventually, we
                    persuaded them that they could give us a letter which would give the companies a
                    certain—it wasn't quite an assurance, but they took it as enough of an
                    assurance. So we had all this buttoned up more or less.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>I got a memo then from Kissinger. The memo actually came down from the Secretary,
                    I suppose. Anyway, it came to my desk saying that, “The President told me that
                    he would like to have an inter-agency study of the oil situation in the world.”
                    The memo said the President needed it or he wanted it by some very early date,
                    in a week, or something like that. Well, I went to see Jack Irwin, the Under
                    Secretary. I said, “Look, I have three people working on oil. One is Akins, an
                    he's going to go off to the Middle East. So I'm down to two people and this
                    bastard wants us to write a big study. What's the purpose of it? We've already
                    done everything. The Secretary knows all about it and he has approved all we've
                    done.” Jack said, “Well, you'd better do it. I don't want to have a fight with
                    anyone.”</p>
                <p>So I called my two people in, I've forgotten who these two fellows were; they
                    were certainly good officers, however. I said, “Look, we've got to do this now.
                    Call a meeting of all the agencies. I'll chair the meeting but you tell me how
                    you want to parcel out the chores.” And damn it, we did it. We did a report in
                    whatever the time was; it was a very tight deadline. But we did it. Nobody ever
                    looked at it, of course, and it made no sense whatsoever, but it was done.</p>
                <p>Rogers must have been away because I would have gone to him, rather than Jack.
                    Later I told Rogers about it and he was furious. This was quite a long time
                    afterward and he was just furious. He gave me hell. He said, “Why didn't you
                    come to me? I would have stopped that.” Q: You weren't here.</p>
                <p>TREZISE: I said, “You weren't here and I went to the Under Secretary.” Well, you
                    know how he was. He calmed down after a little bit. Of course, he understood
                    immediately what had happened was that Kissinger was trying to get into the act
                    and get the State Department doing what he thought was the State Department's
                    chore.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever find Jack Irwin any help on anything when you
                        had a fight with anybody?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I never did, either. He's a nice man.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: When I came to the Department, Richardson was Under Secretary and I
                    could go to him and explain my problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a different story entirely.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>TREZISE: I remember when I came to the Assistant Secretary job one of the first
                    things I took on was a proposed interagency study on aviation policy. There had
                    been one in the Kennedy Administration, which we had to fight over and we did
                    win on that one. And I had taken part on that earlier one so I knew what was up.
                    It was an attempt to elbow the Department out of the aviation negotiating
                    leadership.</p>
                <p>So I went to the first meeting and I said, “I've checked with Secretary Rogers
                    and he said it was time to have a policy review. But he told me to tell you that
                    he is not prepared to give up authority over aviation negotiations. So go ahead
                    with the study. We'll take our full part in it but you must remember, we will
                    not have any discussion about the locus of power for the negotiations.”</p>
                <p>Well, I hadn't told Rogers a thing. I just made that up. I went back and told
                    Richardson what I had done. And he asked if I had told the Secretary and I said,
                    “No, he might not let me do it.” But I said, “You'll support me, won't you?” And
                    he said, “Sure.” Of course, I didn't need any support. Nobody bothered to ask
                    Rogers if he ever said this. So we had the policy study and not a peep about the
                    role of the Department of State.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it continued after I got there. We managed to hang
                        onto the franchise.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: It's pretty well dissipated now. In the years since we've left,
                    everything has gone downhill, it seems to me. But Richardson was really a great
                    helper.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, he's a fine man.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes. You know, he had the right bureaucratic sense, too. If you've got
                    something, why do you want to let somebody else take it away from you.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, he's a good fighter.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Sure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So is Bill Rogers.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Ben Reid, in the Carter Administration, gave away a big chunk of the E
                    Bureau. Why? Because people were pressing him and he wanted to make them happy.
                    Well, I've never believed making other people happy was a necessary
                    objective.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: that's not the purpose of the exercise.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that was what Mr. Bush was saying yesterday to the
                        senior guys. We're almost at the end of the tape. Can you think of anything
                        else in that era? I took on after you were there. I had a rough time for a
                        couple of years and eventually got fired by Henry, mostly over a security
                        trade matter. Did you have much to do with COCOM or that kind of stuff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: A little bit at that time. There were some cases around when I came
                    back. I remember one in which I overruled the Defense Department. But I cleared
                    that one with Richardson before I did it, so I was quite immune. The Secretary
                    of Defense wrote a letter to the Secretary complaining about my action. It was a
                    silly business. Some French company had sold something to the Soviet Union and
                    we wanted to hit the French about it. You know, it was a nothing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To kick the French in the shins.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: But that was rather dying down, I guess. I left, of course, before the
                    big business in 1972 with the wheat, and the big grain deal, and all that. That
                    was your problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, we were in the middle of what was called
                        detente.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was an interesting experience. We managed to get what
                        was then a pretty good trade agreement. We got a pretty good lend-lease
                        settlement from the Russians. We sold them a lot of grain and we got money
                        for it. But then this all foundered on the Kissinger theory on let's have
                        agreements on everything with them even if they don't say anything. And Jack
                        Bennett in the Treasury and I spent all our time scrutinizing these
                        agreements to make sure they didn't say anything. And we thought we were
                        fairly successful and you can't find these agreements now. Although, the
                        trade agreement was good. I think we ought to revive it, myself.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TREZISE: If they get out of Afghanistan in the next few months, Shultz is right,
                    we ought to see what we can do in the way of sensible business.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
