<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001028">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Frank E. Schmelzer </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>FRANK E. SCHMELZER</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Mike Springmann </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: December 1, 1992</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is Mike Springmann recording with Frank Schmelzer on
                        Tuesday, December 1, 1992. Frank, can you talk to us a little bit about what
                        possessed you to go into the Foreign Service? As I recall you were a biology
                        major and interested in music at one time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yes, that is right. As a kid I had a great interest in music, but
                    later on I got interested in the idea of becoming a doctor. While in college, I
                    lost that interest as I broke more and more test tubes and spent more and more
                    time on the science courses, instead of being able to read my 10,000 books.</p>
                <p>I broke loose from this in my senior year and did a lot of auditing. One of the
                    books that I read was Spengler's “Decline of the West.” This sort of struck my
                    fancy for some reason. In the House that I was in at Harvard, Dunster House,
                    Dick Park, was an authority on India. He suggested that I go to graduate school
                    at the University of Pennsylvania to study in their South Asian program, which I
                    did. I was there for one year studying Sanskrit, Hindustani, Indian history,
                    etc.</p>
                <p>After one year my GI Bill funds ran out so I had to go to work for a while. I
                    went up to New York and worked in a couple of banks there. But by that point I
                    was just marking time; I was interested in the Foreign Service because I wanted
                    to go to India.</p>
                <p>Given my background in biochemistry I thought it would be very difficult to pass
                    the Foreign Service examination, so I joined the Foreign Service as a clerk.
                    Sure enough my first assignment was in New Delhi. While there I studied on my
                    own at night...history, economics, and government, things I knew I would need to
                    pass the written exam. I also brushed up my German. I took the written exam
                    there and passed it and then took the oral exam when I came back in 1955.</p>
                <p>My first assignment as an FSO was in Frankfurt where I worked in the Refugee
                    Relief Program. That was fascinating because you had a very quick introduction
                    into all the trouble that people could get in to. Many of our visa applicants
                    were those who had failed to get visas under the earlier refugee program.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would be refugees from the 1939 war being processed
                        when, in the 1950s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yes. I was in Frankfurt 1955 and 1956. Because my German was quite
                    good they made me the so-called Security Officer, which meant that I got all of
                    the nasty cases...all the prostitutes, all the SS guards, all the drug addicts,
                    suspected Communists. It was a very trying job but fascinating. I was quite sure
                    one guy was a Communist agent so I sort of kept him in place for about a year by
                    requiring additional documentation.</p>
                <p>After that I had some more university training. This time it was courtesy of the
                    State Department. First I had nine months of Hindustani at the Foreign Service
                    Institute, then a year of university training at Berkeley consisting of more
                    language and history, etc.</p>
                <p>Then I went to Madras as a political officer. Here we begin to pickup another
                    theme. This was in that period of our history in the Foreign Service when it was
                    fashionable to believe that we had to know everything about everything. I was in
                    the political section and I wanted to stay on until the 1962 general elections.
                    The result was that I stayed in Madras for four years.</p>
                <p>I remember we made an assessment of every one of the constituencies in south
                    India and there were approximately a thousand of them. We made a projection as
                    to who was going to win in each one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were the districts for the...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: ...For the 1962 general election. Most of these were for the state
                    assemblies in the four states of south India, but they also included the members
                    of Parliament that are elected from there to go to New Delhi.</p>
                <p>Galbraith was Ambassador at the time. I remember the word from the Embassy was
                    that he was wondering why we were going to all this trouble. Why not just wait
                    until after the elections were over and read in the newspapers what had
                    happened?</p>
                <p>Well, of course, the answer to that is that if you adopt that more relaxed
                    approach, then you don't know what the election results mean, whereas you do
                    know if you have really been grubbing around beforehand. But I believe we were
                    over-doing it at that time.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>During this period in Madras I was fairly aggressive, perhaps overly so. The
                    result was that at one time the Ministry of External Affairs in New Delhi sent a
                    Diplomatic Note to the Embassy complaining about me. They said that I was being
                    too aggressive in pursuing the Communists in south India. But that was not the
                    real reason, I think. I think the reason I got their goat was that I discovered
                    in one of my trips into southern Madras state that the Congress Party had
                    kidnapped some members of the opposition party, the Dravida Munnetra Kazhagam
                    (DMK), or Dravidian Progressive Federation, and kept them sequestered while some
                    of the local elections were going on so that the DMK, could not exercise its
                    majority rights. And thus the Congress Party maintained their control of that
                    area. I made the mistake of letting one of the local officials know that I had
                    that story. I think that was what was behind the Diplomatic Note.</p>
                <p>Before I went out on tours I would write ahead and make appointments. On one of
                    my trips to Kerala, where the Communist Party is very strong, I had written to
                    make an appointment with the General Secretary of the Communist Party in that
                    state and had no answer from him, but I went to see him anyway. I don't think he
                    liked it.</p>
                <p>Then one time while on tour in Andhra Pradesh I heard that Sanjeeva Reddy,
                    President of the All India Congress Party was in his home. I am afraid I burst
                    in on him and got him out of his bathtub. I was overdoing this.</p>
                <p>But this raises an interesting story. Earlier, while I was in New Delhi, I think
                    I came to the attention of the Communist Party. For one thing I was a Harvard
                    man. Now I read one time that the KGB took out files on anybody who graduated
                    from Harvard. I find that hard to believe because it would be excessive, I
                    think, even for them. But there I was working as a clerk in the Embassy. I had
                    all these friends in New Delhi. A lot of Indian Army officers. I used to give
                    all these parties. Maybe I had a little more profile than I should have had for
                    a clerk, particularly in the eyes of the Russians who used chauffeurs, etc. as
                    their KGB agents.</p>
                <p>One time I gave a large party. I had a lot of thirsty Indian friends and we
                    decided to have some fun and give a “one million BC” party. So we had a greased
                    flag pole, a couple of girls came in tiger skins, all men were stripped to the
                    waist as they came in. I had a 40-gallon barrel of beer that had been sitting
                    there in the shade for about a week so the hops would settle. Indian beer in the
                    bottle was great, but in the barrel it wasn't good. The only people that would
                    drink that stuff were the Indian Army officers. We had a dancing bear and a
                    couple of roast pigs.</p>
                <p>So we were having a pretty good time. As the men came in they stripped to the
                    waist, put on a beard, and I gave them an earthen pot of this beer. This began
                    to draw a crowd. One of my Indian buddies and I were feeling no pain after a
                    while and we went over to the crowd and grabbed this one little guy who was
                    looking in at us. We just lifted him up over the fence, stripped him and made
                    him drink a pot of this stinking beer.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>Well, we shouldn't have done that. About three weeks later the Communist monthly,
                    “The New Age” had a story about our party...”Culture of the Vulture.” It turns
                    out that the little fellow that we had grabbed was the editor of that magazine
                    and he didn't like it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there fallout in the Embassy about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: No, and I thought there might have been, but there was not. They
                    thought it was rather amusing.</p>
                <p>I mention this because later, while I was in Madras sometimes some Indians would
                    confuse me with somebody else from a sister agency. I looked somewhat like him.
                    This was confusing to any Communist who might be following the scene. I also was
                    very friendly with someone with a very sensitive position in one of the Indian
                    Services and there was a very interesting arrangement I had with him. We were
                    just friends.</p>
                <p>Subsequently, an officer came out from Washington to look for somebody to be sent
                    to Afghanistan. They wanted someone with a little pizzazz because it was
                    difficult to operate in the police state environment there. Based on my record
                    they chose me. So I went up Kabul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is before the coup backed by the Soviets?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Oh yes. Well before that. I got there in 1963 and about a week or ten
                    days after arriving Daud, the strongman, was out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which Daud for the tape transcriber and those reading this
                        later on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: I have forgotten his full title, but he was the Prime Minister and the
                    cousin of the King. [From transcriber: Lt. Gen Sardar Mohammad Daud Khan] He was
                    the strongman in the country and on this particular occasion he wanted to do
                    something and threatened to resign if the King did not give him his way. Much to
                    his surprise, on this occasion the King accepted his resignation and Daud was
                    out. Then a reform government came in and soon all these Western educated
                    Afghans who had been hiding came out of the woodwork to take over this new
                    government. It really changed the atmosphere considerably. So slowly, little by
                    little, it was much easier to operate in this new environment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wasn't aware that Afghanistan at this time was a
                        dictatorship.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Well, yes.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I thought it was more relaxed and more along the lines of
                        Iraq and...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: No. Not under Daud. It was essentially a police state. The Afghans
                    were often afraid to talk to foreigners. It was difficult to do the standard
                    kind of reporting which was so easy to do in India.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The King was essentially a figurehead?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: He had been, but on this occasion he stepped forth and under his
                    guidance the new government came in.</p>
                <p>I was a bachelor again at that time and threw a lot of parties. I had been there
                    for a short time when I met one Afghan at the International Club. He had been
                    educated in the United States and it just turned out that he was the Director
                    General of the Ministry of Interior. In other words he ran the police force, the
                    secret police, the jail system. I mean, that man was well informed.</p>
                <p>He had four friends, one of whom was dean of the law school, another was a vice
                    president of a bank, another was a director of one of the departments in the
                    Ministry of Commerce and a member of the extended royal family, and the fifth
                    guy was the son of the one true wealthy industrialist in the country. These five
                    guys were buddies and all hung around together.</p>
                <p>Well, they started coming over to see me. I had booze and occasionally had
                    friends come in, including Peace Corps volunteers. This came to the attention of
                    the Russians and they used to complain to these guys. I was really surprised how
                    ham-handed the Russians would be about this. They would say, “Why do you see
                    Schmelzer? You no see Schmelzer no more.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the KGB from the Soviet Embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yeah. It turned out that one of these KGB officers was talking to them
                    like this. The Afghans would tell me this. This was very interesting to me.
                    Afghanistan at the time was, of course, a neutral country. Our role there was
                    essentially working with our AID program, with the Peace Corps volunteers and
                    with contracts through Pan American for Ariana Airlines and a very small
                    military program which brought trainees to the United States for military
                    training. Essentially what we were trying to do was to counter to some degree
                    the overwhelming presence of the Soviet Union in Afghanistan.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is an extension of the same game the British and the
                        Russians were playing in the last century.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yes, that is right. Of course, working with us on our side of the
                    ledger we had the Germans, the British, the Chinese and the Pakistanis. The
                    Indians were playing their own game.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When I was there they had Indian Army jeeps taking Russian
                        kids to school.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Anyway, this particular KGB guy at embassy cocktail parties in Kabul
                    would come up and start picking a fight with me. (According to the boys, he was
                    the KGB chief in Afghanistan and probably the KGB chief for all of south Asia.
                    He had been formerly in India and they had caught him with his hands in the
                    cookie jar and they expelled him.) I could never understand why he kept doing
                    this. It happened time after time. I would just stand there for a while and
                    listen to him ranting on. Finally I would see maybe an Indonesian over there, or
                    a Pakistani or Indian and I would say, “Hey” and get a few people standing
                    around. Then I would interrupt this KGB guy and turn to an Indian and say, “By
                    the way, I assume you know that you threw this man out of your country because
                    he was caught with his hand in the cookie jar?” And the Russian would stomp away
                    madder than hell. And he would do this all the time.</p>
                <p>Then we began to get into a strange situation where we would have “friendly
                    little parties.” Twelve officers from our Embassy and twelve officers from the
                    Russian Embassy would get together about once a month or so. Now this was not
                    being done elsewhere around the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How large was the American Mission at that time? Was there
                        just the one Embassy in Kabul?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: The Embassy proper was probably about 30-40 people. With AID we
                    probably had 200-300 people there. Our AID program was quite large and given the
                    nature of the Afghan economy, we had to rely heavily upon technicians. Whereas
                    in India, the economy was more advanced so we proportionately had a smaller
                    group of technicians.</p>
                <p>But somehow we had better relations with the Russians, perhaps because
                    Afghanistan was a neutral country. Although we were in an adversarial
                    relationship with them it didn't have the edge that it had in most other
                    countries worldwide.</p>
                <p>So we began to get together. One time the Americans would be the host and it
                    would be at one of our homes, and then the Russians would be the host and it
                    would be in their embassy...I presumed because it would be wired for sound and
                    recorded.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How large was the Russian Embassy at that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: The Russian Embassy was very large. They had put in a new compound
                    while I was there. It was so large, indeed, that some of the Afghans became
                    rather apprehensive and wondered why they needed such a large compound. The only
                    embassy in the physical sense that was comparable had been the British. The
                    British Embassy, of course, had been used as an outgrowth of an imperial power.
                    So the comparison, I think, must have made some Afghans uneasy.</p>
                <p>About this same time I should say that I kept up relations with Taraki.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who is Taraki?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Nur Mohammad Taraki. In 1979 he suddenly emerged as the first
                    Communist leader, prime minister in Afghanistan. I knew him because when I went
                    to the Embassy in 1963, he was in the Embassy as a translator. He had been in
                    India and liked Indian food. He had been in Washington as the press attach� in
                    the Afghan Embassy. He and Daud did not get along. They hated each others' guts.
                    When Taraki went back to Kabul from Washington, he told me he had left a letter
                    with the New York Times implicating Daud in something or other. When he went
                    back to Kabul he told Daud that the New York Times had such a letter and if
                    anything happened to him, the Times would publish a scathing story. I don't know
                    if this is true or not, but this is what he told me.</p>
                <p>After the reform program had been in place a few months, Taraki felt it was safe
                    to leave the employ of the American Embassy and he did. I kept in touch with
                    him. About once a month I would drive down to the old part of town and park
                    under a certain tree and throw open the back door of my Mercedes. He would climb
                    in, lie down on the floor of the car and then I would drive back to my house
                    where the cook would have prepared a nice Indian meal and have left before
                    Taraki and I arrived. I would park the car, close the gate and then he would be
                    free to come into the house and the two of us would talk over the meal. Later I
                    would give him a bottle of scotch and drive him back. I would let him out under
                    the same tree in the old part of Kabul.</p>
                <p>This guy was so well informed. I could prepare interesting airgrams, telegrams,
                    etc. based on my discussion with him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he have an official position at this point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Well, he had opened up a translation business. This was his cover for
                    his political activity.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>I knew he hated the royal family, I knew he had socialist leanings and wanted
                    Afghanistan to advance in one hell of a hurry. But I did not know that he was
                    forming the Communist Party of Afghanistan. Apparently no one else did either.
                    The news that he was doing so only emerged later, when I was back in
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But he was giving you correct information on other
                        things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yes. I don't think he was lying to me. He had wonderful stories, a
                    sharp mind, and sources of information in many parts of the government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did Washington and the Embassy receive your
                        reports?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Well, they were very pleased that I had this great source of
                    information.</p>
                <p>As a result of knowing him and these other five people that I told you about, I
                    was extremely well informed. It was incredible, particularly in a country that
                    had been so difficult to operate in. I was doing quite well.</p>
                <p>Well, at one of these parties with the Russians, I remember that this KGB guy
                    finally got under my skin. I must say there was a lot of trouble over Berlin at
                    that time...of course there had been for years. That was before we came to an
                    agreement with the Russians on that subject. This was probably the spring of
                    1965. We had been talking about Germany and Berlin. I had had a little bit too
                    much to drink and grabbed this guy by the necktie, rather close to his throat,
                    and said, “Listen, you son of a bitch. You know what we are waiting for don't
                    you? We are just waiting for a few Russian troops, three, two, one, to invade,
                    to move into West Berlin. Then you know what is going to happen to your country,
                    don't you? From Leningrad to Vladivostok not a blade of green grass will ever
                    grow again. Your language will disappear from the earth...” My own eyes were too
                    blood shot to realize it, but a couple of the people standing around were
                    reasonably sober, and this guy actually turned white. I don't know whether he
                    thought my position there was more elevated than it was, and that I was
                    presenting a well-considered USG policy decision, but I do know that thereafter
                    he didn't bother me anymore. Who knows, maybe this incident helped to save
                    Berlin!</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>The next get together with the Russians was in their Embassy. I remember at one
                    point—it was rather late in the evening and we were all rather far gone—looking
                    around and seeing a big collection of empty vodka bottles at my end of that long
                    table and realizing that there was no vodka in those bottles there I started
                    pounding on the table. “What, no vodka in this Russian Embassy?” Two or three of
                    the Russians, drunk as they were, tottered to their feet and went down to the
                    cellar and came back with more vodka. Afterwards I went to one cafe that stayed
                    open 24 hours and fortunately two or three of my Afghan buddies were
                    there...fortunately I say because one of the Russians followed me and the next
                    thing I knew I was arm wrestling with him and ended up on the floor. I was able
                    to get up and there was no damage done.</p>
                <p>But one of the other officers, I think it was the head of our information
                    service, was so drunk that night that he collapsed while putting his key in the
                    front door and spent the night on his doorstep.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador heard about this and putting all these things together he decided
                    that maybe the time had come to stop all this. It was getting out of hand. So
                    that was the end of our “friendly parties” with the Russians. But it was fun
                    while it lasted and I think it was really worthwhile.</p>
                <p>Later, of course, I went back to Washington and became the Desk Officer for
                    Afghanistan which worked out very well. Obviously I knew all the players. I was
                    the Ambassador's man in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were the Embassy's emissary to Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yes. And whatever the Ambassador wanted, I tried to get for him,
                    Ambassador Steeves. He appreciated what I was doing for him. I was quite
                    effective, I think, in that line.</p>
                <p>I also had very close relations with the Afghan Embassy here. I set up a system
                    where I would get together with their second ranking officer, Mohammad Rafiq, at
                    least once a month for lunch. I would always bring along at least one other
                    person who had some interest in Afghanistan, somebody from AID, USIA, Commerce,
                    the Agency, DOD, etc. This was a good vehicle for all concerned. The Embassy
                    appreciated it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What time frame was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: I was the Desk Officer for two years, 1965-67.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>This was a lively period. There was a war between India and Pakistan in 1965, and
                    I shared in the additional duty of serving in the Operations Center. Fortunately
                    I was on duty because I knew something about Afghanistan. Suddenly there was a
                    telephone call...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were also doing duty in the Operations Center?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yes. While the war was on there was a task force of officers from
                    South Asian Affairs, so there was always one or two of us there around the
                    clock.</p>
                <p>On this particular occasion the phone rang and it was the Pentagon. There was
                    some general on the line. “Hello, this is General so and so. Who are you?” “I am
                    Frank Schmelzer.” “Well, Schmelzer, I don't know if you know but we have 12
                    C130s which are now just as we speak on their way from Tehran flying toward
                    Rawalpindi.” “Yes, General.” “I think you know that we have this stand-down
                    agreement between India and Pakistan so that these planes can arrive at 6 in the
                    morning and the two air forces, the Indian and Pakistani air forces, would not
                    engage during these two hours so that we can fly out American civilians on these
                    C130s.” “Yes, General, I am aware of that.” “Well, unfortunately, nobody
                    bothered to get permission from the Afghans to overfly their airspace.” “Well,
                    General, I think that was a mistake.” “Well, Schmelzer, is this going to be a
                    problem? What do the Afghans have?” “Well, they have SAM 2 missiles...” “What,
                    SAM 2 missiles?” “Yes. They have MiGs 17s and 19s.” “What?” So we had to send a
                    FLASH cable out to our Embassy and the Ambassador got somebody out of bed and
                    within half an hour or less we had an agreement to overfly the country. As I
                    say, it was a good thing I was there because they might not have bothered to get
                    the agreement and it would have left at very least a very bad feeling among the
                    Afghans. If they had used their missiles or planes they might have shot down
                    some of those aircraft.</p>
                <p>Shortly afterwards I called up the Afghan Ambassador, who was taking a shower,
                    and said, “Well, Mr. Ambassador, as we speak there are C130s flying towards your
                    country on their way to Pakistan. Unfortunately they took off from Tehran
                    without permission from your government to overfly your country.” I heard the
                    Ambassador suck in his breath. I then said, “But we now have your government's
                    agreement.” And I heard him exhale.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>Another story which I think is worth noting is a reflection of just how parochial
                    you can get. There I was the Desk Officer for Afghanistan, a country that most
                    people hadn't heard about. I would have done anything to serve the interests of
                    our relations with that country, and I did. For example. While I was on the Desk
                    the Afghans suddenly decided that they wanted to join the jet age. They came to
                    us...I mentioned earlier that we had this arrangement with Pan American. Pan
                    American had a contract under which they serviced the Afghan airline, Ariana. So
                    it was natural for the Afghans to come to us when they decided that they wanted
                    to purchase a jet. Unfortunately the Afghans told us right off the top that they
                    wanted to use that aircraft to open service to Peking. During that period this
                    was a “no-no.” Treasury regulations precluded moving any American equipment into
                    a Communist dominated country, particularly into Communist China.</p>
                <p>However, Johnson's White House was already looking for some avenue to begin to
                    open the door to Communist China. So I could use that interest in the
                    bureaucratic struggle over this issue. Treasury was against the loan, Pan
                    American was in favor of it, Commerce was in favor of it because it would mean
                    an export of an American aircraft. I don't think the CIA had much feeling about
                    it one way or another. But Treasury was certainly opposed.</p>
                <p>The big problem, of course, was the Ex-Im Bank, because they didn't want to touch
                    this thing, particularly since they were going to Congress for an extension of
                    their charter and for authority to provide additional financing. I was gung ho
                    to get that plane. I did not know that the head of the Ex-Im Bank was dickering
                    with State and hoped to become an ambassador. He assumed that I spoke for the
                    State Department. Whatever the State Department wanted they should get because
                    he wanted to become ambassador. So it was a very interesting bureaucratic
                    tangle.</p>
                <p>Finally we won. We got the jet. Then, of course, the Afghans decided they would
                    not fly to Peking after all. I happened to know their jet pilot who was on one
                    of the early runs. They hadn't had the plane very long. He flew into Frankfurt
                    on his way to London. London tower told him that there was fog and they had
                    better not come in. Well, you know how these Afghans are. They can be rather
                    thick headed at times, and this guy certainly was. He was gung ho, full of oats,
                    a young guy. He decided to go in and in the process cracked up the plane.
                    Fortunately it was insured so the Afghans got another one.</p>
                <p>I mention this parochial aspect because my next...well I had a year subsequently
                    in Personnel with Steeves as his special assistant when he was Director
                    General...but shortly thereafter I went into Political Military affairs (PM)
                    where I had to adopt a completely different attitude. The Secretary of State at
                    that time was heavily engaged, as everyone else was, in the Vietnam
                    exercise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this Dean Rusk?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yes. They were looking for a way out of this thing. The only time I
                    met the Secretary, by the way, was when I was the Desk Officer for Afghanistan.
                    The Afghans had the idea that because they represented a small non-aligned group
                    they might have a role to play in reaching a settlement. I went in with the
                    Afghan Ambassador once while he spoke to Secretary Rusk to push this particular
                    approach. Nothing ever came of it.</p>
                <p>One of the problems that the Secretary faced was the military assistance program.
                    At that point it was still being administered by AID. The Secretary thought that
                    the Bureaus were advancing their own regional interests. No one was pulling it
                    all together. He was not being advised as to how the AID programs and military
                    programs in any given Bureau would impact the other Bureaus, and he needed
                    someone or something to give him a better overview. So he decided to take the
                    military assistance program back from AID and put it in a new office within PM.
                    I was one of the five people who went into this newly created office.</p>
                <p>That was rather interesting. One of the things that they asked me to do was to
                    look at Latin American affairs. I knew nothing about Latin American affairs. I
                    had been to Puerto Rico several times to visit a sister. I couldn't speak
                    Spanish. At that time the seventh floor interest in Latin America was a sort of
                    residual interest. Their main concern was Vietnam.</p>
                <p>Some of the other Bureaus were a little restive about the Latin American Bureau
                    because the very modest military assistance programs that we had in South
                    America were just sufficient to rub some Congressmen the wrong way, particularly
                    Henry Reuss, a liberal from Wisconsin. He had a group around him, only a few in
                    number, who represented the swing vote when it came to voting on the AID
                    program. This made the NEA Bureau, which I had come from, very nervous, because
                    they were afraid that if Brazil or Argentina were to use their military
                    assistance funds or their foreign military sales credits to buy jet planes, this
                    could get Reuss so mad that it would upset the whole AID apple cart and there
                    would be no AID program for India, Jordan, Pakistan, etc.</p>
                <p>So this was one of the elements in the equation. When I attended IG
                    (Interdepartmental Group) meetings for Latin America, which were presided over
                    by the Assistant Secretary of State for Latin American Affairs, I was
                    representing PM. Here I was, a modest ranking officer, an FSO-4 which was
                    equivalent to a Lt. Colonel, and because the seventh floor was engaged
                    elsewhere, I was the one who was representing the seventh floor. I really had
                    much more influence there than I should have had.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Usually I just went along for the ride. That is, I would monitor, but not try to
                    interfere in Latin American Affairs. And the CAPS (country analysis and policy
                    statements) were really an excellent device developed in the Latin American
                    Bureau...I would review those things in draft if I got them in time. When they
                    were approved they became the country statement so that all the agencies in the
                    US government would know what the program was for the ensuing year...AID, State,
                    USIA, DOD, Commerce, CIA, etc. Everyone knew what the program was and the
                    resources to be applied. It was a very good system.</p>
                <p>But every now and then something would go wrong and I would not get advance
                    notice. One day this happened and suddenly I was looking at a draft CASP
                    document about Bolivia as I was walking over to join the meeting. The first
                    sentence nearly gave me heart failure. It said that Bolivia was “vital” to the
                    security of the United States. I said to myself that this was crazy, stupid.
                    What this meant in essence was that if everybody agreed to this, the generals
                    would leave the IG meeting, return to the Pentagon and turn on their computers.
                    The next time you had a little scuffle in the streets of La Paz, an American
                    regimental combat team would fall out of the sky and we would be at war. I
                    exaggerate, but not by much.</p>
                <p>I decided I had to stop this somehow. I read the paper as quickly as possible to
                    try to discover the basis for such a statement. At the meeting I listened as
                    people went along with this without question. I raised my hand and was ignored.
                    The Assistant Secretary may have believed that occasionally I was a trouble
                    maker. So he ignored me. Sitting on the other side of the room was Winston Lord,
                    who was representing the NSC. I was looking at him and thinking. Suddenly I had
                    it. I looked at him, and ignored the Assistant Secretary, and turned to the guy
                    from Commerce and said, “Is this assessment of the importance of Bolivia based
                    on the two and a half war theory or the one and a half war theory?”</p>
                <p>Two or three months before that President Nixon had determined, and this was in a
                    memo from the NSC passed to all the agencies, that henceforth the United States
                    Government only had to be prepared to fight one and a half wars worldwide
                    simultaneously. Previously we had always been prepared to fight two and a half
                    wars. A two and a half war program meant certain things with reference to stock
                    piling. In this case, in reference to Bolivia, it meant tin. With a two and a
                    half war program you needed a big stockpile of tin, but a one and a half wars
                    program didn't need such a big stockpile and maybe the stockpile in existence
                    was large enough to carry you for a good period of time. And that is what it
                    was. They had failed to step down from the two and a half to the one and a half
                    program. So the meeting adjourned.</p>
                <p>Of course I made some enemies there because I made fools of everybody around the
                    table, including the Ambassador who had written the program, the Assistant
                    Secretary of State, the two generals who seemed willing to plug in their DOD
                    computer programs, Winston Lord, who hadn't done his homework, and the Commerce
                    official who answered my question with “two and a half wars.”</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>We met again several weeks later and this time Bolivia was “important,” no longer
                    “vital;” there would be no regimental combat teams.</p>
                <p>It was curious for me to move from Desk Officer where I was so parochial that I
                    risked destroying the Ex-Im Bank by pushing that jet thing through. Perhaps the
                    Ex-Im Bank finessed it legally, I don't know how they did it precisely. But
                    surely they were running a risk. And yet we rammed that jet through.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why was Treasury against it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Because of the regulations and the politics of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But I thought Congress controlled the export import
                        regulations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yes, they did, but Treasury had the exchange regulations and under
                    those exchange regulations they could determine that anything that is an
                    American product should not go into a Communist controlled country. But Commerce
                    wanted to sell the aircraft.</p>
                <p>So there I was a parochial Desk Officer one day and a little over a year later
                    dealing with the big picture in PM. It was very interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you a couple of questions. What was your role
                        in the consulates...Madras and Frankfurt...with the Embassy? Were you
                        running your own independent fiefdom or was it like my experience in Saudi
                        Arabia that whatever you wrote had to be cleared with the higher ups in the
                        Embassy? Did you have your own show?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yes, we did. In Frankfurt we had our own operation, the Refugee Relief
                    Program. We were the largest single unit doing this Germany-wide, although we
                    were getting guidance from the Embassy. In Madras, however, the consulates did
                    their own political reporting and sent copies to the Embassy. We took some
                    guidance from them. They told us what they wanted us to place emphasis on, but,
                    no, we had our own reporting and sent the Embassy copies of it.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>Often we had a different point of view than the Embassy. Sometimes we were better
                    informed than they were, too. For example, I remember the question of Goa when
                    Galbraith was the Ambassador and he was reporting back...the consulates would
                    see some of the Embassy reporting, but not all of it...so we knew that Galbraith
                    was reporting back to Washington that Nehru had assured him that the Indians
                    would not move into Goa. We knew god damn well that he would. We had seen troop
                    movements. It was not that we could read Nehru's mind but we just knew Nehru was
                    going to move in. It was just quite clear. And he did. We tried to tell that to
                    the Embassy, but they couldn't do anything because Galbraith was giving them the
                    line. He was just wrong on this and wouldn't take advice from us or his own
                    political officers on that issue.</p>
                <p>This, of course, gets to another point...You have heard this before and probably
                    have been subjected to it yourself. I refer to the junior officer who seems to
                    be closest to the ground and sometimes comes up with an analysis or a point of
                    view which the seniors don't like. This happened to me in Madras. After two
                    years in Madras I was well tuned in. I would go home at night and the phone
                    would begin to ring and by 8:00 o'clock there would be 20 or 30 Indians there.
                    Of course, they wanted to drink my free booze, but I just had very good
                    relations with these people. So I was extremely well informed. One result of
                    that was that I knew very well what the opposition party, the DMK, was doing. I
                    would tell the Consul General that they would move way ahead in the coming
                    election and in five years would take over the government in that state. Well,
                    that would make him furious because he was getting the New Delhi line from the
                    governor and the chief minister, that the Congress Party was strong and was
                    going to win the elections and that the opposition party was a bunch of creeps
                    and not reliable, etc.</p>
                <p>The Consul General got so mad with me that he would not let me report on Madras
                    state, which I knew so well. I did the other three states. Indeed, I had the
                    best record in India in predicting what was going to happen. But the Consulate
                    “blew” Madras because the guy he made do the reporting on Madras had to reflect
                    the view of the Consul General. I kept telling him that he was making a big
                    mistake.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this show up in your efficiency reports?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Well, it didn't help me any.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you ever sent a dissenting cable to Washington or
                        Official-Informal letters saying you disagreed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: I think that I probably did, I don't remember. I must have sent a
                    letter or two, perhaps not a cable. But you see that sort of thing all the time
                    in the Foreign Service. It is a pity.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>The same thing happened to some degree in Tehran, I am sure. We had people there
                    who knew what was going on. They could speak Farsi. But the Ambassador had to
                    come up with a different line because every time the Shah would come to
                    Washington he would meet the President and charm the pants off of him and
                    whatever the Shah wanted he could get. You just couldn't go against that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were also in the Foreign Service at the time that
                        additional agencies started going overseas...Treasury, Commerce, etc. What
                        was that like? How many of the CIA folks were involved in this change?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Well, the Agency was always there, of course. Our relations with the
                    Agency were quite good. At least mine were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How big a presence did they have?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: At one point they suggested that I might want to join their ranks in
                    Afghanistan. I think because I was so successful with this group of five people
                    that I have mentioned, and also possibly with the way I was seeing Taraki. I
                    guess they found that impressive. But I preferred to remain a cookie pusher.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How big a presence did they have? I was surprised when I
                        went to Jeddah that two thirds of the people there worked for either the CIA
                        or the NSA. I never suspected before that they had their own consulates
                        around the world.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Oh yes. I don't want to comment on the numbers or anything. They
                    weren't overpowering.</p>
                <p>[end of tape one]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is December 8, 1992 and this is the second interview
                        with Frank Schmelzer.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>SCHMELZER: I thought it might be interesting to say a few words about Vietnam
                    where I served in the CORDS program. I was there from the end of 1970 through
                    the late spring of 1972. This particular organization was sort of a parallel
                    government in that there were teams of American advisers attached to their
                    Vietnamese counterparts, as they were called, at all levels of the government,
                    from the district level through the provincial level and, of course, up to the
                    nation's capital in Saigon. There was an American team in each one of the
                    provinces of Vietnam. The chief of the team was either an American military
                    officer, usually a Colonel, or an American Foreign Service Officer, usually a
                    grade 4 or 3, in the old grades [2 or 1 in current grades].</p>
                <p>Initially I went to Nha Trang, but only for a short while. From there I was
                    assigned to Tuy Hoa, which was on the coast of one of the provinces. I was there
                    for about two or three months, just sort of getting used to the system, the
                    so-called pacification program. I think the things that I remember best there
                    are a couple of attacks we had. The VC were more interested in the military side
                    of the compound than they were in us civilians.</p>
                <p>I remember the first time a attack occurred: There was a great deal of commotion
                    and suddenly somebody came running around and got us all in a bunker nearby,
                    slapped helmets on our heads and gave us each a rifle. We were peering through
                    slots waiting for the VC to come after us. There was a lot of ruckus, on the
                    other side of the compound and I think one of the Marines got wounded that
                    night.</p>
                <p>The second time that the VC attacked, some time later, I slept right through the
                    whole thing I am happy to say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you actually get things done there? You had to
                        deal with the Vietnamese army, with civilians and the US Army.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: You would have a huddle among yourselves and decide what you wanted
                    the Vietnamese to do or what you would suggest they should do. Sometimes they
                    would follow your advice and sometimes they wouldn't. If you felt that the
                    matter was sufficiently serious and they were dragging their feet too much and
                    something should be done, then you would kick it up to the next level.</p>
                <p>Since the Vietnamese in each level knew that your line of communications with
                    your own superiors was at least as good as theirs and that if your superior
                    decided to push this thing that he would go to his level, the Vietnamese knew he
                    might get a rocket, get kicked by his superior. So we certainly were
                    influential.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>This structure, by the way, this quasi-parallel government, if you will, was an
                    outgrowth of our experience in China during World War II where we had a lot of
                    goodies to pass on to the Chinese but our own structure was not very effective.
                    So this was designed to overcome some of these problems. I thought in general
                    the organization was pretty good.</p>
                <p>We were also dealing with the Vietnamese civilians. I spent most of my time in
                    Vietnam in Ban Me Thuot up in the Central Highlands. One of the big problems
                    there was the relationship between the Vietnamese and the Montagnards, the
                    indigenous people. The problem was that the Vietnamese were coming in and taking
                    the land. Their style of agriculture was intensive and quite different from that
                    of the Montagnards. It was reminiscent of the English colonists here in the
                    United States and their attitude toward land settlement and the American Indian.
                    The Vietnamese, of course, would go in and take the land and work it very
                    intensively. The Montagnards would look upon the land quite differently. They
                    would cultivate one area for two or three years and then move to another area
                    near by; after another few years they would return to the first area. They
                    wouldn't cultivate the whole area solidly as the Vietnamese would do. But, of
                    course, over time this meant that the Vietnamese were gradually taking more and
                    more land away from the Montagnards. So there was a lot of trouble there.</p>
                <p>Towards the end of my stay, we had come up with something that was really rather
                    effective. We had decided to persuade the Vietnamese government to give title to
                    the Montagnards to specific tracts of land. This was made somewhat easier
                    because so many of the Montagnards had been moved from their traditional
                    villages into protective, fortified areas. The idea was to give them title to
                    those fortified areas and the lands adjacent, so that they would be protected
                    from the Vietnamese encroachment. This also had the additional benefit of making
                    the Montagnards more willing to support the common war effort. This, by the way,
                    was a very serious fracture point. In the spring of 1972 when the North
                    Vietnamese attacked in force, in the Central Highlands, one of the people that I
                    was working with was a deputy in the provincial government who was representing
                    the interests of his Montagnards tribal group. He had suggested to Saigon,
                    through his political leadership, that two divisions of Montagnards be created,
                    armed and trained in order to fend off the North Vietnamese. In fact this
                    request was made before the North Vietnamese attack. The answer from Saigon was
                    no, certainly not. Then it was one division? No. Two regiments? No. One
                    regiment? No. Now had such a Montagnards force been available in the spring of
                    1972, and later in 1975, the result would have been quite different.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>In 1972 the North Vietnamese were held because the South Vietnamese fought quite
                    well and the Americans were still there with air power. But in 1975, of course,
                    they punched right through that area. In the spring of 1972 Ban Me Thuot was the
                    headquarters of one of the South Vietnamese divisions...they had three
                    regiments. One was destroyed by the North Vietnamese army. So another regiment
                    moved North to a pass, about 40-50 miles north of Ban Me Thuot. The North
                    Vietnamese got into that pass and this was rather serious because communications
                    between Ban Me Thuot and the northern provinces had been cut. So the B-52s came
                    in to dislodge the North Vietnamese. They bombed that place for five or six
                    days. On the next day, this particular South Vietnamese regiment went in and got
                    “creamed.”</p>
                <p>The speculation at the time was that somehow the North Vietnamese would sense
                    when the B-52s were coming and they would run out of the pass. The B-52s would
                    bomb the hell out of the place and then the North Vietnamese would move back in.
                    This went on and on. On the sixth day when that regiment went in the North
                    Vietnamese were back in the pass and the South Vietnamese got slaughtered. So
                    then they decided to move the third regiment North. Just about at that time we
                    got news of North Vietnamese tanks being sighted due west of us—that was 15
                    miles away on the other side of the river. The river was the boundary between us
                    and Cambodia. So that made some of us a little nervous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As well it might.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Well, one of the military members of our team had been in the American
                    calvary, as he called it, the Tank Corps, for some 25 years. So I called him in
                    one day and we went up to the map in the office and I said, “Billie, I think it
                    would be nice if you could get into a chopper and see just how much of a barrier
                    that river is.” “Ah, Jesus Christ, don't bother me with that stuff. I have been
                    in the Tank Corps for 25 years and I tell you there is no way the NVA can get
                    tanks across that God damn river.” I said, “Well, look Billie, you are probably
                    right but I would appreciate it if you would just take a chopper and go and
                    look.” “All right, but it is just a waste of time.”</p>
                <p>Well, he went out and took a look. About an hour later he stormed back in and
                    said, “Wow, that river is no problem at all. Come look.” And he dragged me over
                    to the map. He said, “Gee, with 10 tanks I could take this God damn town and
                    reduce it to rubble. Look, here is where you come across, the river is only a
                    few feet deep.” Billie really got carried away, he was so excited.</p>
                <p>Of course, everybody was screaming for various things. One thing that everybody
                    wanted about that time was the “LAWS.” It was sort of a bazooka thing that you
                    put to your shoulder to knock out a tank. Suddenly we started to scream for them
                    too. I put in an order for a 100 of them. It took a little while to get them,
                    but I finally did. After that I had three of those damn things in my desk.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>The other thing I used to keep around was a carbine. I always had it near me when
                    I went to bed at night.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't trust that your diplomatic passport would
                        protect you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: No, no. My hearing improved quite a bit. I got so I could hear a cat
                    walk down that alley outside. And there were a couple of VC attacks on Ban Me
                    Thuot while I was there. But I would just go upstairs where there was another
                    civilian on our team who had been through the wars...he was married to a
                    Montagnards and had a good balcony of solid cement. We would crouch down behind
                    that and wait for the noise to dissipate, which it normally would.</p>
                <p>Our organization was essentially a good one. The basic problem was that we were
                    trying to build a nation in one half a nation and it just wasn't going to work.
                    The South Vietnamese, I think, occasionally had the will to fight and when they
                    did they could do a good job. But, somehow the psychology of the whole thing was
                    wrong. It was their war and we made it our war and that was the biggest mistake.
                    We were just there passing out the goodies and to a certain degree trying to
                    tell them what to do and sometimes they would respond and sometimes they
                    wouldn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did other Foreign Service officers think? Were they
                        telling Washington what worked and what didn't? Or were they told to shut
                        up, this was policy and you will carry it out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Quite a few of the people were disgruntled. I remember one young man
                    in Nha Trang who had been there a short period of time, and he was assigned to
                    one of the districts. He decided after about a week that he was not going to
                    take anymore of this nonsense. He didn't agree with the program. So he just
                    decided that he was going to quit. He came in and fortunately the man in charge
                    of our operation in MR2, military region 2 which included one-fourth of the
                    country...a big chunk of the Central Highlands and a big chunk of the northern
                    coastal areas...that man was a Foreign Service officer and he understood the
                    problem. He talked to this young man and found another job for him in which he
                    did very well. He had a contingent of four or five Vietnamese who would go out
                    and interview people...do in-depth interviews on various aspects of the
                    pacification program on rural development, civilian guards training, etc. It was
                    a very valuable product that he came up with and he enjoyed doing it. It was
                    more similar to a regular Foreign Service activity, so he didn't leave the
                    Foreign Service. In fact, he has done fairly well since.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>In one of my great moments in Ben Me Thuot I was able to use some diplomacy...I
                    say this with tongue in cheek, of course. While I was there initially there were
                    still some American troops, the drawdown had not been completed. So the PX was
                    there and there was a collection of whore houses. The complaint was that the
                    ladies were charging too much for their services. And a lot of these little
                    plastic vials that drugs come in were being seen all around the outskirts of
                    this compound where the ladies were. So it was decided that something had to be
                    done about this. The good colonel in charge of our team decided that this was a
                    problem for the State Department. So I organized a little convoy and we went
                    down there. There was a jeep with MPs, a jeep with translators, etc. I think
                    there were three jeeps that went, with no flags flying. We went there for a
                    prearranged meeting with the madams. They were very polite. The girls were
                    tittering around the corners watching this. I told these ladies that there were
                    complaints about the prices and that it was not right to have drugs on the
                    scene. If there were anymore complaints on either of these two points we would
                    have to declare the place off limits. Of course that would put these women out
                    of business. So things were rather quiet there for a while thereafter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the Foreign Service positions in Vietnam sought after
                        or were they regarded as a punishment detail?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: I think it is fair to say they were not sought after. In fact, as you
                    know, some of the younger officers resigned rather than go to Vietnam. The
                    Department of State was always trying to keep 100 Foreign Service officers in
                    Vietnam. Most were in this CORDS program. That meant that there were one or two
                    in each province. In Tuy Hoa I was the only one, but in Ban Me Thuot there were
                    two of us. No, these positions were not sought after.</p>
                <p>Some of the older officers, of course, the FSO-3s, who saw that their careers
                    were not flourishing, decided to go with it, to roll with this punch. There were
                    some advantages to this. For one thing it was occasionally rather exciting. It
                    was interesting. You learned a lot. You had a chance to see this great
                    bureaucracy in motion. You were learning a great deal about the major problem of
                    the day. And, of course, the Director General would come through every now and
                    then...I think he tried to make it once a year...and would make promises that
                    your next assignment would be a good one.</p>
                <p>I remember that in my case the Director General came through and he asked me
                    where I wanted to go. I said, “Well, Mr. Ambassador, I would like to go to
                    Paris.” “Well, Frank, how would you like to go to French-speaking West Africa?”
                    Then I said, “Well, I would like to go to Rome.” “Well, Frank, how would you
                    like to go to French-speaking West Africa?” I had been working on my French and
                    had used it during the tour. I said, “Mr. Ambassador, I would like to go to
                    French-speaking West Africa.”</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>Of course, when I came back to the Department there was nothing laid on. That is
                    how I ended up in the six-month economics course. I came in on a Monday and went
                    through four Bureaus (I avoided Latin America) and by Thursday I had not seen
                    anything that I liked. There was something in INR that might have been
                    interesting, working on Russian ballistic missiles. Then I heard there was a
                    vacancy in the six-month economics course at FSI beginning the following Monday.
                    I called up and there was one vacancy because one guy had quit. I was asked if I
                    had ever had integral calculus—and I had had two years in fact in college. So I
                    began class the following Monday. This meant I had to give up my home leave. So
                    much for the Director General and his promises of French-speaking West
                    Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your relation with the Embassy there? I was
                        surprised you had a full service Embassy. I still have a publication that
                        the Commercial section produced called “Doing Business in Vietnam.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: For the CORDS program there was very little contact with the Embassy.
                    When we went to Saigon we would go to the Embassy to say hello to the people in
                    the personnel section or the administrative section, or if we knew anyone in the
                    political or economic section we would say hello to them. And sometimes they
                    were interested in our experiences out in the field. They were curious as to how
                    things were going on. But generally speaking there wasn't much of a
                    relationship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You reported to Washington or to the military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: We reported through our own chain of command which meant essentially
                    to the military...more to the military side than to the Embassy. We all did an
                    end-of-tour report. Mine was rather scathing, I must admit. When I went down to
                    Saigon on my way out, the General who was then in charge of this whole program,
                    was shaking his head and said “Frank, did you really have to write a report like
                    that?” “Sorry, General, I really did.” I had many misgivings about this whole
                    thing. I didn't think it was going to work. It was not working really. It was a
                    noble effort but misplaced.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>One of the things that John Paul Vann instituted when he took over MR2 was this
                    idea that all advisers and all counterparts would spend one night a month,
                    preferably once a week, outside their principal abode. In other words you were
                    supposed to go out and spend a night in a village somewhere in order to show
                    your face so that the local Vietnamese would know you were interested in them,
                    to see what was going on, and dislodge VC who might be in the area. Well, I
                    remember one night when I went out with the province chief...he was grumbling
                    all the time. He didn't like this idea. Of course, he would rather stay in his
                    very comfortable palazzo in Ban Me Thuot. He went out with an entourage of about
                    a 100 troops to make sure he was safe during the night. The VC in this province
                    were not very strong anyway. I would guess that they represented at most 3 or 4
                    percent of the population. And they tended to be isolated in one of the areas up
                    against the hills some distance away. Another 15-20 percent were pro-Saigon and
                    the rest of the people, 60-70 percent, didn't care a damn one way or another.
                    This was the problem really. But in any case we spent the night out and came
                    back the next day and were presumably all the better for it. We had to sleep on
                    a table top on that occasion, but we did that sort of thing from time to
                    time.</p>
                <p>A more interesting night out was with John Paul Vann, himself. He came in flying
                    his own chopper and wanted to pick up the province senior adviser or his deputy,
                    i.e., me. I forget why the Colonel couldn't make it, perhaps he was out of town
                    and I was in charge at that time. In any case I went with John Paul Vann and we
                    went all the way down to the southern end of the province where he knew a local
                    Vietnamese school teacher. He spent two or three hours grilling this guy asking
                    him about the local VC, their organization, their channels of communication,
                    etc. It was a rather impressive display on the part of John Paul. I presume in
                    part this was designed to fire me up so that I would be a little more aggressive
                    in winning the war.</p>
                <p>One of the things that I did to preserve my sanity there was to play the flute. I
                    composed short songs and tried to record them, which was difficult because there
                    was always such a racket going on. For one thing, there was a of these cabaret
                    down the street where the troops would go in and buy drinks and dance with the
                    girls. They always had rock and roll music blaring away. And there were choppers
                    always flying around the place. And the road traffic. I would have to get up at
                    about 3 or 4 in the morning when it was relatively quiet and play the flute. I
                    never had any complaints, I am happy to say.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>Drugs were a problem, as I mentioned already. Fortunately not on our CORDS team,
                    as a rule. Although in one of our district teams (there were four district
                    teams) there was a drug addict. We had done a lot to try to rehabilitate the
                    guy. We had taken him down to Nha Trang a couple of times for detoxification and
                    I think he went to Saigon once for similar treatment. Each time he would come
                    back “cured” and each time he was not cured. Of course this created a morale
                    problem for the rest of the team, because they could not rely upon this guy.
                    They couldn't have him stand guard duty because they were afraid that if he got
                    spaced out that the VC would come through and they would all die. And this drug
                    addict was a little unhappy too because he knew what was going to happen to him.
                    Sooner or later the VC would attack and in the confusion he would just happen to
                    be killed. I think it was pretty much understood on both sides that if the VC
                    ever attacked in force that he was going to get it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This guy was an American?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yeah.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And who was going to do him in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: The Americans were going to kill him. This was the common
                    understanding. The only thing you could do about it was to get him out of there
                    and finally we did transfer him out. But the problem was that on paper he was no
                    longer a drug addict because he had been through all of these detoxification
                    programs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember they did that to some of these characters in
                        Germany and Saudi Arabia. The guy had a real problem. He was medically
                        evacuated for cirrhosis of the liver. But he was clean. But they managed to
                        fire one person because they didn't like the fact that she was late to work
                        all of the time. She drank a little too much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: I thought I might say one or two things about the foreign cultures you
                    serve in, because I think this is important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, a lot of people now days do not get plugged into a
                        culture. They sit back with their VCRs and do their time and get out.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>SCHMELZER: I was fortunate because before I went to India I had already had
                    graduate training and had studied Sanskrit, Hindustani, Indian culture, etc. and
                    had a pretty good idea of what to expect. I had also been exposed to Americans
                    who had focused on the language, the history and philosophy of India and then
                    had been shocked by the reality of the thing when they actually got to
                    India.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You get the taxi driver who wants to take you for a tour
                        of New Delhi instead of going down the road a half mile to the hotel.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Precisely. So you know all about this. An extreme example of the
                    importance of this occurred while I was in the Embassy in New Delhi. You know
                    secretaries assigned to the Embassy would usually get one, two or three weeks
                    orientation at the Foreign Service Institute. It was rather short, probably
                    useful, but not always effective as this example indicates.</p>
                <p>Two girls had arrived and within two weeks or so they decided to go out on their
                    own to a temple about 25 or 30 miles north of New Delhi during a festival
                    period. There was a big celebration. They went on their own. Most of the rural
                    people who flocked to this temple for the big show were peasants who had never
                    seen white women before and certainly had never had an opportunity to pinch them
                    on the bottom and the breasts, which they proceeded to do. So these women were
                    jammed into a corner of the temple and were pinched black and blue. They finally
                    got out of there and came back to the Embassy the worse for wear. One of these
                    girls was psychotic and should have been evacuated immediately. She stayed on in
                    the Embassy for two years and hated India and Indians and was a focal point of
                    rage and hatred for those two years she was there. It was just so foolish. She
                    obviously didn't learn anything in that orientation at FSI. Had they gone out to
                    that temple with just one male, Indian or American, they would have had better
                    treatment. And, of course, there really should have been two or three males
                    along. That was one instance.</p>
                <p>Another thing used to happen often, very curious, at cocktail parties. Let's say
                    half of those standing in the room were Indian and the other half Americans and
                    Europeans. You would notice a motion begin. The European and American would
                    begin to back up. And I would watch this...it would be kind of fun to see it on
                    a video and I bet you would have a circle there. What was going on? The Indian
                    and the Americans have a different sense of space. So while the Indian was
                    trying to get close enough to you to be comfortable in his relationship, the
                    American has to back away to regain his proper sense of space. This creates a
                    tiny bit of tension both for the American and the Indian. The Indian senses that
                    the American is not being friendly and the American senses that the Indian is
                    being too pushy. I caught on to this right away and would not back up.
                    Immediately the Indian would sense that I was a friend, that I was on his side.
                    That was very interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this make you more effective because the Indians would
                        automatically open up to you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Right. Absolutely. This was particularly true later on in Madras
                    because I already knew this. When I got to Madras I had no problems at all.</p>
                <p>While I was in Madras the Chinese attacked India. The Cuban missile crisis arose
                    at the same time. I happened to be on tour in Kerala that same week. It was very
                    interesting because the Indians for years had been at pains to be neutral, to
                    exploit their neutralism and to trot out this expression “Hindi Chini Bhai Bhai
                    Hain,” that is the Indians and Chinese were brothers. Within hours of that
                    attack suddenly everything had changed. The Indians were running up to me in the
                    streets and saying, “You Americans, of course, will come and help us after you
                    take care of the Russians, won't you. The Chinese eat rats you know.” It was
                    interesting. Just like that. Here again, the cultural divide. They eat rats! The
                    cultural divide, just like that. Wham!</p>
                <p>Another thing about the Indians that was fascinating to me was their skill in
                    argument. Of course this has been developed over centuries, particularly among
                    the Brahmins. They are masters at this. And the Americans are not so good. We
                    had this type of culture until Gutenberg came along and then we began to read,
                    and no longer to memorize things. We no longer have the classical education
                    which we had until the 19th century where they taught you logic and debating
                    skills. Most Americans don't have that anymore. So in New Delhi I would see
                    Americans reduced to tears from frustration. They would not know how to debate
                    with these Indians. I would watch this and be terribly amused because I could
                    see what the Indian was doing. He was comparing Indian ideals against American
                    practice. And, of course, the deck is obviously stacked in his favor when he
                    does that. The trick is, of course, to state American ideals and compare them to
                    Indian practice. Then the Indians would start to sputter. Of course, people like
                    Krishna Menon and Nehru were using the same trick in a sense. It was really
                    quite interesting.</p>
                <p>The Russians, and I saw this in Kabul, also had strong cultural divides that were
                    interesting. One of them, was with the Chinese...I think the Russians were
                    really innately afraid of them. I remember one time when I was talking to some
                    Russians about Chinese missile development, and you could smell a change,
                    emanating perhaps from their armpits as if some chemical reaction had taken
                    place. Curious.</p>
                <p>In Stuttgart, in 1978 toward the end of my tour, I knew I was going to retire and
                    study music, and I related this to my German friends with interesting reactions.
                    Many had studied music when they were young, had always had a love of music, but
                    had gone on into business, banking, and were married and had children. The
                    German educational system and culture are in some ways more rigid than ours. You
                    could see the eyes of some of these Germans light up. This was something they
                    would like to do, but they couldn't. Their wives would immediately get nervous
                    because they didn't want Hans to even entertain the idea of leaving his good
                    position in the bank to go back to university to study music. It was a threat to
                    them.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>You mention this to an Indian and, of course, it was a great idea. To the Indian
                    it was just the most natural thing in the world. Why? Because the Indians had
                    that traditional sense of the four stages of life. You are young and a student,
                    then a householder, then a civic member of society, and then you prepare for the
                    fourth stage. In the fourth stage you go off into a jungle, read the religious
                    books and prepare to die...to climb up the chain of consciousness, etc. In fact
                    once I actually met a couple of Indians who had done this, who were living up in
                    the foothills of the Himalayas. One had been the president of a medical school
                    in the Punjab and the other one had been a professor.</p>
                <p>Let me say one more brief thing about India, and these are personal experiences
                    that I used indirectly in my second symphony, which I entitled “Taj Mahal.” One
                    of the things that some of us used to do in Delhi was to go out to Humayun's
                    Tomb. I would take a flute and one of the ladies from the Embassy had a guitar
                    and the acoustics in there were so wonderful that a guitar chord would sound
                    just like an organ, and the flute was wonderful too. Another place we visited
                    was Mathura on the Jumna River which is supposed to be the birth place of
                    Krishna. There was a great scene there near his temple. People would go there
                    for the so-called Arati ceremony at evening. They light a little candle and put
                    it on a small piece of bark and float it down the river. They throw chickpeas in
                    the river to feed the turtles, thereby keeping them away from the candles.</p>
                <p>In Agra these turtles are not well fed. An American who had been through there
                    told me the following unhappy story. One morning he happened to be behind the
                    Taj Mahal on the river side where some people were washing clothes. One old man
                    took off his turban to wash it and it got away from him. He stepped into deeper
                    water to get it and a lot of these turtles grabbed him, pulled him under the
                    water and ate him alive in front of everybody. These were the same turtles that
                    you would see at Mathura, but here they were not well fed. A terrible story.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are these the same turtles they are reintroducing back
                        into the rivers to clean up the pollution?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yes, I think so. They have a head the size of your fist. They are a
                    good size.</p>
                <p>In Agra...I saw the Taj Mahal there three times in the full moonlight. A
                    wonderful experience. It just seems to float. I mention this for two reasons.
                    One, because I understand now you can't get in there anymore at night, that they
                    have locked it up, which is a pity. It is a wonderful thing to see in full
                    moonlight. It is almost a mystical experience. And I tried to get a sense of
                    that in the last movement of this symphony...a sense of floating.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me some more about the Refugee Program in Frankfurt?
                        How effective was it? How broad was it? The kinds of people you had in
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: It was a very interesting program and a lot of hard work. Particularly
                    towards the end of it. The legislation for this particular refugee program
                    expired on December 31, 1956. So we knew that we had to process as many of these
                    people as we could because after that date anybody left hanging there would,
                    indeed, be left hanging there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were Germans or people from other parts of
                        Europe?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: There were two groups of people essentially. There were Germans who
                    had been expelled from Eastern Europe and the so-called escapees who were
                    Germans who had escaped from East Germany and other nationalities who had
                    escaped from Eastern Europe. There were Russians, Mongolians, Czechs, Poles,
                    Yugoslavs, Romanians, etc. Now some of these people had been around for a long
                    time because they had been processed initially under the Displaced Persons
                    Program, but for one reason or another had not been granted visas. In many cases
                    they were too close to the Nazi Party or to the SS or they might have been
                    Russians without sufficient documentation, that sort of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any kind of quota or was it if you met the basic
                        qualifications you could go to the States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: The basic qualification was to be an expellee or an escapee. We tried
                    to deal with people who had been there for two years or more so there would be a
                    police record on them. This was not always the case, of course, but we tried to
                    do that. A lot of these people had been there for years already. While I was
                    there the broad strictures, e.g. against mere membership in the Nazi Party, were
                    lifted so we could treat most of these people on a case-by-case basis. The
                    process was that people would make known their interest in getting a visa. Then
                    we would tell them what documentation we required. Time would go by as they met
                    these requirements. There would be the requirement of having a sponsor in the
                    United States. If all these conditions were met on paper, and if we had no
                    obvious questions at that time then we would call them forward for an interview.
                    If all went well, we would then give them a visa and then they would be
                    immediately interviewed by an immigrant official, right there in Frankfurt.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>This of course is unlike the usual procedure where the visa officer gives a
                    person a visa and then he goes to the United States and is admitted or not
                    admitted at the port of entry in New York or wherever it may be. But here the
                    immigration officer was right there because INS was well aware that this Refugee
                    Relief program had many more problems then the regular immigration case. So by
                    having the INS officer there they were able to stop a lot of these people and
                    protect their bureaucratic imperative that way. The result was that we often had
                    a difference of opinion. We would say the person was qualified and the INS
                    officer would say no. Then we would send a memorandum back to Washington and it
                    would be fought out between the State Department and the Immigration and
                    Naturalization Service.</p>
                <p>Later, of course, I was the so-called security officer because my German was
                    pretty good. So I got all the nasty cases, the ones that were a little harder to
                    deal with. I had quite a few instances where I thought the person should be
                    given the break, or should get the visa, because I felt we had settled whatever
                    questions there had been and the INS officer would not agree. I won about 90
                    percent of those cases.</p>
                <p>But you can see why there would be a difference in outlook. The Foreign Service
                    officer was usually a younger man, it might have been his first overseas post,
                    and he was often imbued with more feelings of tenderness towards these people,
                    many of whom had had a hard life. Whereas the INS officer tended to be a
                    hard-bitten older man. Maybe he had spent years on the Rio Grande trying to
                    fight the big fight to keep out the wetbacks, etc. He had had more experience
                    and had built up some feelings that you shouldn't be too soft on these people
                    because eventually there were going to be trouble makers among them.</p>
                <p>Here is an illustration of how much some of these people had gone through. One of
                    the people I gave a visa to was a White Russian. He left the Soviet Union
                    sometime in the 1920s and he ended up in Germany. I don't remember whether he
                    went to Germany immediately or landed in Germany after the war. In any case, for
                    that long period of time, from the 1920s through 1956...he had been a Colonel in
                    the Russian Army when he left...For all that 30 year period he had very poor
                    living conditions, had been sweeping streets—he had not been able to find a good
                    job. He was there with his wife and someone or other. I stood up and saluted him
                    saying, “Colonel, Sir, here is your visa.” The man cried. It was the first time
                    in thirty years that anyone had shown him any respect. Well this was the sort of
                    thing that you were dealing with.</p>
                <p>The trouble people could get into was amazing. I remember a river boat captain
                    who had a boat on the Rhine River. He was charged with incest with his daughter.
                    Well, there was no way that he was going to get a visa. Another guy I had was
                    supposed to be in charge of all the drug operations on the west bank of the
                    Rhine River. I had two US Marines standing in full uniform outside my door when
                    that guy came in because I was going to tell him no. I told him no and he walked
                    out and never caused any trouble.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>There was another interesting thing that happened there. I knew there was going
                    to be trouble over this eventually. I don't know who was running these guys,
                    whether it was CIA, military or what, but every now and then you would see these
                    green papers come through. All paperwork normally was white and suddenly here
                    would be an application on green paper. You would look at it and realize what it
                    was. A little while later this young man would come in, his head closely
                    cropped, in his late twenties or early thirties, a muscular looking fellow,
                    alert, active, with one or two Americans with him from this particular Service.
                    These people were operating behind the Iron Curtain. They were running back and
                    forth carrying out dangerous missions. Their reward later on was to get an
                    immigration visa. Everybody in the building would know that this guy was
                    probably involved in some intelligence work for the Americans.</p>
                <p>I kept telling these intelligence officials that they shouldn't do it this way
                    because eventually you are going to lose one of these guys. Everybody knows. Why
                    are you using green paperwork? Sure enough, one day we gave a guy a visa and a
                    day or two later he disappeared. He was never found again. So then we changed
                    the procedure.</p>
                <p>So I came up with this system...these gentlemen would come through with white
                    paper, would come through with only one person, not two, and I would keep the
                    paperwork and not turn it over to the German locals in the building. Instead,
                    after the locals left, I would go down and open up the safe and take out the
                    seal and stamp it and do all the paperwork. In the meantime I had taken a block
                    of visa numbers from the staff without their knowing it and would do all the
                    work myself. We never lost anyone else after that.</p>
                <p>I also used to deal with all the Russians. There was so much backbiting in the
                    Russian community. Some files on these guys were a foot thick. It was terrible
                    to work with those people.</p>
                <p>Occasionally you got an East German agent. You had to know a certain amount of
                    information about each one of the East European countries. You were not expected
                    to be an expert, but you had to have some sense as to when these people were
                    lying. Because if they lied on something that was material, their visa
                    application would be denied.</p>
                <p>Another thing of interest was that these people had really been through the mill.
                    You bring them in for an interview and before you ask the first question some of
                    these people would start laying out on your desk 10 or 15 documents. Even before
                    you said anything. They were so used to this and were so regimented and
                    indoctrinated and covered by paperwork. The average American would have only a
                    driver's license and social security card and a credit card, but that would be
                    it.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>Several of us FSOs who were in Frankfurt during 1955 and 1956 have been
                    interviewed by the FBI in recent years concerning the procedures we used during
                    our administration of the Refugee Relief Program. The FBI's Office of Special
                    Investigations (OSI) spoke to me on three occasions concerning visas issued then
                    to persons subsequently believed by OSI to be deportable as war criminals
                    because they were guards or otherwise engaged at concentration camps. I assured
                    the FBI that we considered membership in the SS and service as guards to be
                    “material” (but not grounds per se for automatic denial of a visa)—i.e., a basic
                    factor to be reviewed carefully during the visa process, and that withholding
                    such information, or lying about such a background, would be grounds for denial
                    of a visa. OSI found these discussions to be useful as they considered whether
                    or not to open or to pursue deportation proceedings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How much help did you get from your local staff? When I
                        was in Jeddah as visa king, I was trained by my people. After I had been
                        doing this for a while I got a feel for the fraud patterns and a sense of
                        what kind of story was the real stuff and what kind of story was a lie. When
                        you walked in for the first time, how did you get a handle on what was
                        coming down?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: I think that might have been the case if I had been working only with
                    German applicants, but this was quite different. So I got my training from the
                    Americans who had been there before, one in particular. So we didn't rely as
                    much on the German staff.</p>
                <p>Occasionally, if you had applicants who didn't speak German very well, and we had
                    a local who spoke the applicant's language, we would bring him or her in.</p>
                <p>Toward the end of the year we were working seven days a week, ten hours a day.
                    This was in 1956 and we were trying to get as many visas processed as we could
                    before the deadline came up. And then, of course, the Hungarian Revolt broke out
                    in November and that had an impact on our operation. I got jaundice about that
                    time and was in bed for six weeks, so I was out of it. We had to send people to
                    Vienna to process the Hungarians who were flooding in across the border. So our
                    operation kept working right up to New Year's Eve.</p>
                <p>It was a good training. You learned an awful lot about human nature very quickly.
                    You had to. You had to make an assessment of people's character and understand
                    their background.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Foreign Service as a career and the Foreign Service
                        Personnel. Have they changed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: I never thought much about this until the very end. When I was in
                    Stuttgart (1974-78) I suddenly realized that the people coming into the Foreign
                    Service were different animals. Partly because every generation tends to look
                    upon the younger generation to some extent in this way, but in this case I think
                    it was an accurate description.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>When I went into the Foreign Service I knew nothing about our Foreign Service
                    Retirement program. I wasn't interested in it. I didn't care about a lot of
                    these perks. That was secondary. I was interested in learning about India, or
                    the job, whatever, and tried to do what I could to enhance our policies and
                    interests. So that was my focus. If you had to work a little extra on the
                    weekend, or whatever, that was expected.</p>
                <p>Certainly you wanted to entertain and do a good job of it. But while I was in
                    Stuttgart, suddenly we had people who were assigned there with quite a different
                    attitude. They thought that entertaining the Germans was an unnecessary
                    requirement. Why should they do that? And if they did entertain, they were bound
                    to spend as little money as possible. I think you ran into something like
                    that.</p>
                <p>Of course, about that same time you were getting the development of the woman's
                    movement which was partly responsible for this. So suddenly I began to realize
                    there was a different breed. If in the fifties and sixties we had encountered
                    people like this we would have sent them home. You wouldn't tolerate behavior
                    like that.</p>
                <p>And this struck me again when I came back here. One day, while back in the United
                    States and retired, this would have been in the early eighties, I had a call
                    from one of my nephews. He said, “Listen, my former roommate is interested in
                    the Foreign Service. He has passed the written exam but hasn't passed the orals
                    or security exam yet and thought he would like to talk to you.” I said, “Sure,
                    fine.” A couple of minutes later this guy calls me up. He starts talking and I
                    am giving him advice. Then he says, “Gee, I smoked a lot of marijuana when I was
                    a kid, but I am not going to tell the security agent when he asks me that. I
                    don't think I should tell him that.” I say, “Look, you don't want to lie. This
                    is no way to start your career by telling lies. If it happened be truthful about
                    it. They will understand this.” “Oh,” he says. A little later he says, “And then
                    there was a question about my wife's health. My wife is an Indian and has asthma
                    but I am not going to tell anybody about that because...” I say, “Gee, you
                    should tell the truth on these matters.” A minute later he was saying, “Well, I
                    really only want to go into the Foreign Service for a few years anyway. Just
                    long enough to make some business contacts and then I want to go into business
                    for myself.” By that time I nearly hung up the phone. This was amazing. In my
                    day no one ever looked upon the Foreign Service that way. For us earlier it was
                    a wonderful opportunity to serve our country in an interesting way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was severely criticized in Jeddah for entertaining and
                        in Stuttgart they simply cut off my funds. I got no cooperation from the guy
                        who used to rent out his maid for parties. I eventually packed it in and
                        said, “The hell with it, I just can't do it.” I was frustrated. But then
                        nobody else entertained.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Well, we certainly did. We always did. In Madras I used to have
                    parties anywhere from two to two hundred people. I was really set up for it
                    there.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>Nathan, my principal cook and bearer (I also had an assistant cook and a
                    gardener), had great aplomb and could handle anything on short notice. He also
                    could be relied upon the next day for a full report (X had this many whiskies, Y
                    had so many plates of curry, Z tried to take A into the bush). And as I noted
                    above, prohibition made my ample supply of booze quite attractive. (We also had
                    an ayah, or nurse-maid, after our son was born—dismissed, unhappily, when she
                    was found to have leprosy).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well tell me about the agency. I had run into what seemed
                        to be their own consulate in Jeddah, two-thirds of the people working for
                        NSA or CIA. I had never heard of this and really wondered how many
                        consulates around the world were really agency consulates. I know the
                        presence is increasing. The Army Intelligence officers in Stuttgart went
                        from one to three. The communicator's wife worked for the agency and he
                        wanted to retire from State and join the agency because the pay was better.
                        And the last two consul generals? I was not too sure they worked for the
                        State Department.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Well, this is a new trend for me. Although we were always aware that
                    there were agency personnel and knew pretty much who they were, they were never
                    a predominant element. Although we didn't always know exactly what they were
                    doing, at least I didn't know, our relations were generally pretty good. It was
                    in their interest that they have good relations with us for their own reasons,
                    as well as for ours. We would talk about matters of common interest. Often they
                    were very well informed on certain selected subjects, but they didn't have the
                    broader background to put some of the material they had into the proper context.
                    So it was useful on both sides to share notes that way. We would get more of the
                    detail and they would get more of the context.</p>
                <p>Interestingly enough I had a similar relationship with somebody in the British
                    Embassy in Kabul. They didn't have as many people as we did so they were spread
                    rather thin. The result was that my British colleague did a lot of things across
                    the board while I was focusing on political developments in Afghanistan. He was
                    meeting ministers and I was not. So he could tell me things that would be useful
                    and I would tell him a lot that he didn't know. It was a useful
                    relationship.</p>
                <p>But, no, I never had the feeling that the agency, as a group, were running the
                    show. This must be a new development. Or maybe I just never happened to be in a
                    posting where it was the case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would you say was your greatest accomplishment or
                        greatest frustration in your career?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Well, I suppose one frustration was that I didn't advance a little
                    faster than I did. It was clear to me by the time I was 30 or 35 that I would
                    never be ambassador to India. After I realized that I looked upon the Foreign
                    Service as a job and not a career. I always did the best I could, but I didn't
                    feel I had to work 105 percent of the time. I felt that 95 percent was
                    enough.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you started out, State pretty much had the whole ball
                        of wax. By the time you retired, you had Commerce, Treasury, the Armed
                        Forces overseas. State was only one of a number. Did you see any change in
                        the way State operated as a result of that? Were there things that didn't
                        get done because of this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: I don't think I saw that where I was. For example, in Madras there was
                    no Defense personnel. There were in Kabul, but because the DOD programs in Kabul
                    were limited they were not throwing too much weight around. In Hong Kong, I
                    think the same is true. I thought State held up pretty well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have anything further you would like to add?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: Yes. I think there is something else we should add about Hong Kong.
                    Talk about cultural differences and some of the things that the United States is
                    up against! In Hong Kong I knew this great guy from the Japanese Consulate.
                    About once a month he and I would get together for lunch to compare notes about
                    China. I was following Chinese development of oil, coal, steel, and other
                    resources. Takahashi was covering similar facets about China and he was
                    extremely well informed. One day at lunch I asked him about the Japanese
                    presence at the Canton Trade Fair, up river inside China. Twice a year there is
                    a trade fair there, attracting multitudes of foreigners, including the
                    Americans. In the American Consulate it would take us two or three months after
                    the previous trade fair to produce an estimate that there had been, for example,
                    100 American firms there which had done about $50 million of business, and this
                    was probably what they bought and what they sold. It was a very rough estimate
                    of what had transpired.</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>On this particular occasion with Takahashi the trade fair was due to take place
                    in about two months. So I said, “Gee, how many Japanese firms do you think might
                    attend the next Canton trade fair?” “Oh,” he said, “3,456.” I figured he was
                    pulling my leg but decided to go along with it. I said, “Really? How does that
                    compare with the number that were there last time?” “Oh,” he said, “there will
                    be 123 firms fewer.” I said, “Really? Why is that?” And then he told me why.
                    Because in the Japanese steel industry such and such was happening, in the
                    Japanese plastic industry this was going on, in the fishing industry this was
                    happening. He went right down the line. On the Chinese side their basket weaving
                    industry was doing this, their coal industry was doing this, their agricultural
                    problems were such and such. He spoke for 15 minutes telling me precisely why
                    the number of firms was 123 fewer and what they were going to be doing there.
                    This was absolutely incredible because it showed the interplay between the
                    Japanese industry, banking and government. They were so closely intertwined and
                    so well informed and organized. Indeed, similar organization might well be
                    illegal in the United States. In any case this was the sort of thing that we are
                    up against. This would have been 1974, I think, when that conversation took
                    place. You can be assured that I made a detailed report of that
                    conversation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMELZER: I wonder if we shouldn't say something about the Freedom of
                    Information program in which I am now employed as a part time annuitant. I
                    retired in 1978 and immediately went to the campus of American University where
                    I was a full time student studying music and eventually got a Masters degree in
                    composition. In 1981 one of my friends and former Consul General, Walter
                    Jenkins, who was then working in this same office, suggested that this was
                    something that I should be interested in. So I took a look at it and applied. I
                    began working there in 1982 and have been working there ever since except for
                    the two years that Mary Jean and I spent in Florence.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>As you know, the public—journalists, historians, lawyers, members of interest
                    groups and others—ask the Department of State for records on subjects in which
                    they are interested. Documents responsive to these requests are located and then
                    we review them to see if they can be released. We decide to release the
                    documents in full or in part, to deny them, or to refer them to other agencies.
                    This review may require coordination with bureaus within the Department,
                    although given our own backgrounds it is assumed that we will go to the bureaus
                    only when necessary. This background, the review process, consultation among
                    ourselves, and the resources of the Library combine to make us fairly
                    knowledgeable, particularly if the subject matter is several years old. If the
                    documents are of recent origin and sensitive, it is often wise to consult the
                    bureaus. Much of this work is interesting indeed. Sometimes you see before you
                    confirmation of what you had long believed or suspected—e.g., we would have
                    attacked the USSR if they had made a serious move on Berlin. Yes, agents were
                    parachuted into a certain country during early stages of the cold war. The
                    Department of State and our embassies are too subservient to the Israeli lobby.
                    The USG was so deeply, extensively engaged in the internal affairs of selected
                    other countries that even now there could be repercussions were relevant
                    documents released.</p>
                <p>We must also respond to the many Congressional requests for documents, and there
                    were many such requests in 1991 and 1992. These focused on several contentious
                    issues, e.g., whether or not members of the Reagan election campaign made a deal
                    with the Iranians in October, 1980 to keep the hostages beyond the election
                    date, thus assuring President Carter's defeat (”October surprise”); the Bush
                    administration's policy concerning Iraq in the period just before Iraq invaded
                    Kuwait; the role of the administration concerning credits extended to Iraq by
                    the Atlanta branch of the Banca Nazionale del Lavoro (”BNL affair”), Clark
                    Clifford's problems with the BCCI bank, possible “coverup” by successive
                    administration of the presumed fact that American servicemen missing in action
                    were left behind in Vietnam and Cambodia by the Nixon administration (”MIA
                    affair”), etc. Hopefully the number of such Congressional requests will decline
                    now that the election is over, particularly since currently we have a backlog of
                    some 4,300 FOIA cases.</p>
                <p>Currently I am working on the requests of former hostage Terry Anderson, who has
                    asked for information concerning his captors (Hezbollah), fellow hostages and
                    documents concerning himself. I have some 5,000 documents to review. They
                    include occasional communiqu�s issued by Hezbollah which I now read with
                    additional interest given the recent explosion in New York. Given the need to
                    consult with other bureaus, a cumbersome process, Anderson probably will not get
                    much of this material in time to help with the book he's working on.
                    Nevertheless we know that the current process of responding to FOIA requests has
                    improved steadily, and is much better than the process extant before our
                    separate office was created. Previously the bureaus responded to such requests,
                    and their response was often very slow—not surprising, since the bureaus
                    naturally have to respond to current events before they can enjoy the relative
                    luxury of reviewing the record of years gone by.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>I regret that I did not mention the damnest thing I ever saw. In India, of
                    course: once (1954?) on the day after Diwali, a group of us went from Udaipur to
                    Nathdwara on the only day of the year that men of the Bhil, an “untouchable”
                    tribe, were allowed to enter the temple there. What sounds, smells, what a
                    sight...too long to describe it. Suffice it to say that I didn't believe it was
                    real—I kept looking around for the MGM cameras as the bodies of the dead were
                    passed out from the temple where they had died struggling for some of those
                    three tons of hot rice. Or, I could mention the red rose given to son Frederick
                    by the leader (The Mother) of the ashram in Pondicherry—did it really turn
                    white? Or, the hillside in Afghanistan where I saw a large circle of about 100
                    wild donkeys braying loudly as a pair of donkeys inside the circle made
                    love...but we don't want this to become a travelogue.</p>
                <p>It has been an interesting life, and I am glad that I continue to be associated
                    with the Department of State.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
