<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000808">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Leone R. (Nonie) Mendenhall </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Program Foreign Service Spouse Series</p>
                <p>LEONE R. “NONIE” MENDENHALL</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Jewell Fenzi</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: April 19, 1994</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is Jewell Fenzi on April 19, 1994. I am interviewing
                        Nonie Mendenhall at her home in Washington, DC.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Imagine taking a month to get to post! You went to Turkey in 1946.</p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: In October we set out, on the Vulcania, which was an unrestored
                    Italian warship or passenger vessel that had been used for transport. The crew
                    was all south-Italian, the captain was from New York. My parents, of course,
                    expected me to be going. They used to go to Europe all the time. They said that
                    we had to have beautiful long clothes and all that, and a steamer trunk — can
                    you imagine, steamer trunk? We protested but to no avail.</p>
                <p>So there we were. We got aboard the ship and we were below the waterline in a
                    cabin with two bunks. We could barely fit ourselves in, let alone a steamer
                    trunk, that had to go down to the hold. In any case that was quite a voyage. It
                    was one of the first ships to end up in India. It took a whole bunch of
                    missionaries, it took Foreign Service people going out to posts where no one had
                    been during the War; a very motley crew we were; priests going to Rome. The
                    salon consisted of about four chairs and one bare bulb. But it was a wonderful
                    trip — our first trip abroad it was. [sound level is picked up at this point,
                    improving volume of Mendenhall's voice]</p>
                <p>It was wonderful. It took us two weeks to get to Alexandria on the Vulcania. I
                    must say, by the time the two weeks ended the bathrooms were in a deplorable
                    state. There were lots of cabins full of smuggled cigarettes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Destined for India?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>MENDENHALL: No, for Naples. (laughter) I don't know how the passengers for India
                    finally got there, what the last end of the journey was, but we had, I think, a
                    day and a half in Naples. The crew would throw plates into the sea and people
                    dived for them — you know, Naples: it was right after the War. There were still
                    sunken warships in the harbor and the poverty was absolutely deplorable. But
                    there again the Neapolitans are so resilient, I mean the life in the city seemed
                    just as full of vigor and excitement, one would never have expected this after
                    all they'd gone through.</p>
                <p>But the crew was throwing plates out from the ship's dining room and little kids
                    were diving down to retrieve them, to sell later on. One cigarette was precious,
                    a carton was a treasure if they could get hold of one and sell it in town. Then
                    we went on to Alexandria and that was, to novice travelers, an absolute
                    revelation ... Egypt! We had ten days in Egypt, five of them in Alexandria, at a
                    wonderful hotel on the sea run by Swiss. The contrasts between the very
                    deplorable situation on the Vulcania and this Swiss hotel — you can imagine:
                    Everything smelled of jasmine, and the waiters wore lovely long white robes with
                    red sashes. It was very exciting.</p>
                <p>We decided, however, to spend only five days in Alexandria and then go to Cairo.
                    So we boarded a train for Cairo and while Joe was standing in line getting the
                    tickets. We had no money, of course, we were young. Joe was just out of the
                    Army, we had very little money to travel on. So he asked the chap at the caisse
                    there whether we had to go first class, and a voice behind him said, “Yes
                    indeed, you do.”</p>
                <p>Joe turned around and there was a Polish (we found out later) gentleman who had
                    lived about 30 years in Egypt, a textile man, and he said, “If you're traveling
                    with your wife, you must go first class.” Well, they got chatting, Joe got his
                    first class tickets, and when we arrived at the train later on that day, there
                    was our friend with a chauffeur walking two little poodles. The textile merchant
                    invited us immediately into his compartment for tea; in a wonderful
                    old-fashioned Victorian type train to go to Cairo.</p>
                <p>We had tea, then whiskey, and talked all the way to Cairo. Then he invited us to
                    Shepherd's Hotel for dinner. We were to stay in a little pension on the island
                    of Gemalek on the Nile, I can't remember its name. He was staying at the
                    Shepherd Hotel and we just put our suitcases in his room and went to dine. Then
                    he took us to the Royal Automobile Club where King Farouk would gamble away
                    millions and millions of what Egyptian money was called in those days — I don't
                    remember.</p>
                <p>We went dancing, and by the time we were finished with this gentleman it was
                    about two in the morning and we still hadn't gotten to our pension on the
                    island. There we were, scuttling through the streets of Cairo at night with an
                    Arab-speaking driver, speaking no Arabic ourselves. But he got us there.
                    (laughter) And somebody was awake.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>So we had a lovely time in Cairo, and then went back to pick up the tiny Turkish
                    ship called the Aksu [she spells it] and we were immediately greeted by Turkish
                    music in a very nice little cabin and lots of Foreign Service people going to
                    Istanbul and other places. We had a very fine voyage of another ten days through
                    the Aegean. There were still floating mines, so there was still a lookout to
                    watch at night. The first night out in the Mediterranean was terrible. I was
                    deathly seasick, and we had bedbugs. But once they sprayed that took care of it
                    and the rest of the voyage was fine.</p>
                <p>We had things like rose petal jam and goat cheese and tea and Turkish music for
                    breakfast; it was delightful, wonderful. You know, for me, any post that is the
                    least bit exotic I love. My least fascinating post was in a place like
                    Switzerland, which is just like home sort of, only less convenient, you know? I
                    just love the really different places and different people.</p>
                <p>We arrived in Istanbul at dawn one morning with all the minarets just as they
                    were supposed to be, sort of peeking through the haze and the mist. We went
                    immediately to the Pera Palas Hotel, which had its dining room blown out by a
                    bomb rumored to have been intended to kill von Papen, but nobody had proof or
                    evidence of that. We had a wonderful red-velvet plush room and a marble
                    bathroom, a huge room overlooking the Golden Horn, and the Pera Palas was and
                    still is right next to the American Consulate General.</p>
                <p>We stayed there for two or three weeks until we could find housing, which was
                    very difficult in those days, and we had to find a place for $50 a month because
                    that was our housing allowance. I think at that time Joe was getting the grand
                    sum of $3,180 per year. We finally found one of four pre-WWI, pre-fabricated
                    bungalows up along the Bosporus, fairly near Robert College, near Bebek. The
                    houses were set in a garden up above the street, right along the water. There
                    was a coal depot between us and the water, in a little village called Karulesme,
                    which the guidebook called “the ugliest village along the Bosporus.” To me it
                    was wonderful but the guidebook thought it was pretty unattractive.</p>
                <p>Anyway there were these four cottages on various levels in what originally was a
                    Greek monastery, and to get from one to the next you went through covered arched
                    stone stairs and each garden had its little stone steps and high wall. We had to
                    wait some time to get our cottage because there was a couple from some Embassy
                    living in it. So temporarily we had the very topmost cottage, which was empty
                    and looked out across to Asia, of course, on the other side of the Bosporus. And
                    it was lovely!</p>
                <p>Finally we got in and we tore off all the cabbages on the wallpaper and the
                    linoleum on the floor. When Mrs. MacAfee, the wife of our consul general, saw
                    this shabby little place she said, “Oh Mrs. Mendenhall, you can't possibly live
                    in a place like that.” She was of the old school, and I said, “Yes, we shall,
                    it's going to be fine, you just wait till we get it all fixed up.”</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>And we did, and it was lovely but it was very tiny and there was no hot running
                    water; a potbellied stove was in the living room for heat. A dear Greek maid
                    whom we'd hired while still in the Pera Palas, had a little two-burner thing and
                    no refrigerator in the little tiny kitchen. But there was a lady who tended
                    goats up on the hill behind the cottages who came in every morning at six to
                    light the wood-burning bathroom fire and to put coal on the little living room
                    fire. The only problem was that a year or so later when our eldest daughter
                    Penny was born, we had no nursery, because there was just living room/dining
                    room/bedroom and a teeny little front porch. We decided we'd see if we couldn't
                    enclose half of it and make it into a nursery for Penny which is what we did.
                    Infinitesimal, big enough for the crib and maybe a chair or something, but it
                    had a lovely apricot tree outside it and tons of garden just crammed full of
                    everything; grapes, cherries, apricots, oranges. I just loved it.</p>
                <p>You know, your first post has an allure that you never lose, that you have a
                    nostalgia for, don't you think? (Jewell agrees) We've never lost our love for
                    Turkey. It was a wonderful post, the people were. We did no traveling in those
                    days, we had no car and there were no roads, no gas stations. There was no way
                    of traveling to places when later, during two or three trips back, we rented
                    cars and traveled all over Anatolia and Cappodocia. We had never even heard of
                    Cappodocia when we lived in Istanbul. It's very interesting how different it is
                    now from those days. But the bazaars were wonderful, and there were lots of oil
                    people and British Levantine families, and we made lots of friends among the
                    Armenians and Jews and Turks and Greeks. We had a wonderful mixture of friends,
                    some of whom we still see when we go back. Joe still corresponds with his
                    Armenian secretary to the Consul General, Mrs. Kazanjian, who loves him dearly —
                    and mind you, this was 1946-49. And, in fact, we took her out to lunch in the
                    bazaars when we were there the last time. We made friends in Istanbul whom we've
                    never lost.</p>
                <p>So that was a wonderful post. Kedi, our Greek maid, was a very interesting, very
                    plain-looking woman, who was born in Russia of Greek parents who disappeared
                    during the Revolution searching for food one after another. She and her sister
                    were taken by Greeks and put on a ship for Istanbul [Constantinople], ostensibly
                    to be brought up by Greek families there. Arriving in Istanbul, in the moil and
                    toil of the crowd Katie lost her sister, never could find her. There is an
                    addition to this tale but quickly I'll get to the main points about Katie — and
                    she was taken by a Greek family and until she was 14 lived there.</p>
                <p>At about age ten, she realized she was just a slave. They took her out of school,
                    she just had to do housework, so at 14 she left and got herself jobs as
                    housemaid with various people. Finally was employed as cook by the Belgian
                    Consul General's wife, who taught her to cook. She came to us, a marvelous cook,
                    who had [rueful laugh] little scope for her talents because we couldn't afford
                    much more than mackerel for our daily fare! But she became a dear friend, a
                    lovely lady, and we kept up with her for many, many years.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>Finally, many years later, probably 25 years later, she found her sister in
                    Salonika. Some years after we left she went back to Greece, eventually married,
                    then found her sister. Isn't that extraordinary? She and our laundress
                    Lass(phon.sp.) who was also Greek, and the packer for the consulate who had his
                    little shop off the garden in the main space where we all lived, used to come to
                    our kitchen in the afternoon and read coffee grounds, telling us what they
                    thought our future was going to be. It was always good, however! (laughter)
                    Thank God, they were right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You spent, I suppose, much of the time after you settled
                        in taking care of Penny.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: No, the first year I taught school at the American girls preparatory
                    school for Robert College. It was called American; but it was, in fact, all
                    Turkish children. This little school, on the hill on the way up to the College,
                    was just beyond the little village where I did all my shopping, which was a
                    Greek village called Arnautkoy,</p>
                <p>I used to walk from our house to the school; I had a class of about 25 little
                    Turkish girls aged 10, 11 and 12. I taught there the whole first year. I taught
                    them English. They were very sweet, very enthusiastic, very affectionate. Then
                    when I became pregnant I got a bit queasy and had to stop.</p>
                <p>The village of Arnautkoy was very interesting. It was right on the water. It
                    still looks just as it was — still has five or six beautiful old wooden Turkish
                    houses.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Mrs. MacAfee raise any objections to your teaching
                        school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was one of the things that we could do in those
                        days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: That's right, it seemed the proper thing to do, to teach school.
                    Oddly enough I didn't get any objection from Mrs. MacAfee although she did say
                    that I had to carry on my functions as the wife of a Vice Consul; that I
                    remember. But she didn't say it harshly at all, she just thought that was really
                    what I was there for, and that if I could fit in other things without any
                    problem, it was fine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your functions as wife of a Vice Consul?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>MENDENHALL: To help everybody out! (hearty laughter) But you know something? I
                    don't know what it was, perhaps because of my age, I never felt awkward about
                    this. I never felt I was doing what I didn't want to do. I was fortunate in that
                    respect, I think. I never felt put upon, let's put it that way. And also, I did
                    not have a profession other than teaching, and I think this is one of the main
                    things. I didn't feel I was frustrated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: (laughing) You don't mean it that way.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: No, I don't, I mean I wasn't a physicist or a... well, of course a
                    doctor can always practice at any post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not really. I suppose she can as a volunteer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: But you know what I mean, teaching obviously is a profession but
                    teaching is ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The kind of thing it was possible for us to do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: And that we could fit in, often, very easily, anywhere — right. I
                    didn't mean to say that teaching isn't a profession, clearly it is, one of the
                    most vital. No, it was an accepted kind of activity for a Foreign Service wife.
                    Of course, all the strictures put upon us in the brief training we got at the
                    Foreign Service Institute before we went abroad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had training in 1946? That would have been with Mrs.
                        Allen, or Miss Cornelia Bassell?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>MENDENHALL: I don't remember. We had a series of ambassadors' wives who would
                    come and talk to us. You know, in those days it wasn't a very extensive training
                    course. There were several things that the wives did. You could attend certain
                    lectures that were given to our husbands in the old State building, now the
                    Executive Office Building next to the White House. When Mr. Robertson, for
                    example, talked about the Far East, et cetera, we could occasionally attend
                    those lectures. We weren't invited to all of them. And then we had to go hear
                    all about calling cards and the protocols and that sort of thing from older
                    Foreign Service women. It was nothing very rigorous but you were expected to do
                    it.As I remember we got little typewritten things that we were told as wives we
                    should do, but nothing was said about what we shouldn't do. And it was all very
                    nice, casual, and a little frightening because it sometimes sounded a little
                    like the kind of protocol that most of us weren't used to — even buying calling
                    cards. (laughter) That was kind of an astonishing thing to be doing in that day
                    and age, sort of a Henry James or Edith Wharton thing. Anyhow, I never felt
                    oppressed, and I never was frightened. I just thought it was all tremendous.</p>
                <p>As I say, I was never frustrated because I had a particular special kind of
                    profession that I was not able to carry out. And that, I think, today is one of
                    the big problems, and understandably so. I know that if I had been oh, whatever,
                    an aeronautical engineer, or any kind of profession of that nature, I would have
                    found it very difficult to be married to a Foreign Service Officer; no doubt
                    about it. But I did not have that problem, so my whole approach to the Service
                    was one of complete pleasure and joy. Except for an occasional problem with an
                    occasional Officer's wife, I really had no problems. I'm just lucky that way, so
                    I can't be a good example of somebody who had difficulties that I tried to
                    overcome.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My opinion is that those difficulties to be overcome have
                        been magnified and that there are a lot more people who are ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: But I wonder — just of our age, or do you think younger?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, younger from a career point of view. After 1972 there
                        were still personality difficulties and there always will be.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: That is right, that is true. These are sort of just basic problems
                    that arise in any kind of organization. No, it was only; in fact, when I got to
                    Saigon that when I mentioned to one of the older wives that I wanted to teach at
                    the university, or that I wanted to teach. She immediately bridled and said,
                    “Why? Do you need the money?” which I thought was an extraordinary response.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: (after laughter) Goodness! That was in 1960 too [or
                        1962?]</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>MENDENHALL:... and I was really quite annoyed about that. However, it didn't
                    bother me because I just went ahead and did what I wanted to do anyway.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Maybe we can skip over Iceland and Switzerland unless
                        there's something ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: Let me just briefly say about Iceland that the climate was awful and
                    the people were wonderful. In fact, we're going back to Iceland at the end of
                    this trip. We liked the Icelanders very well. Our only problem there was we had
                    a child who was stillborn, our only dismaying event there. Penny was five, and
                    Joe was exceedingly busy — he was on loan there to the Marshall Plan. He was
                    Economic Officer in Turkey.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Our Point IV must have started while you were</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: Yes, but it was not until Iceland that he was on loan to the program.
                    The Economic Counselor in Ankara, Ed Lawson, asked for Joe. When we left
                    Istanbul we were supposed to go to Manila but Lawson wanted Joe to head the
                    Marshall plan in Iceland. So he finally maneuvered it and we went there.
                    (laughing) Fortunately, we hadn't bought our clothes for Manila.</p>
                <p>So we had two years in Iceland. Our next post was Switzerland where we had two
                    more children and I was always pregnant and always cold. That's a terrible way
                    to characterize a beautiful country. But Berne is not an exciting place. It's a
                    beautiful city but the Swiss Germans are very unto themselves and don't like
                    foreigners very much. You don't feel very cozy. We lived out of town because Joe
                    always had to have a garden, and two out of our three summers were chilly. I was
                    not very happy in Switzerland. And also, as I say, it was not a very exotic
                    post.</p>
                <p>Then we came back to the States for the first time after nine years and bought a
                    lovely remodeled barn on Sleepy Hollow Road in northern Virginia, a house we
                    kept for some 18 years. We had a four-year assignment there. During this time I
                    was very busy with house, children, and volunteer work of umpteen kinds
                    including starting a French program at the local elementary school, which was
                    held before classes. I worked for Planned Parenthood, and visiting nurse service
                    — the way all of us did in those years.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>I was awfully glad, however, to get back overseas. I find it's difficult to jump
                    from Foreign Service to being housewife in the United States with no help and
                    carrying on your diplomatic dinners and so forth and so on. I remember one time
                    when Joe was acting temporarily as Cambodian Desk Officer and Prince Sihanouk
                    came to Washington. He was to give a party at the Embassy, his lovely dancers
                    were to perform, etc. We did not know until the very last minute, although Joe
                    worked on the whole program for this of course, whether we could go. It depended
                    on whether certain very important people could not go so we would slip in. At
                    the very last minute we were in fact at the party, as were the three Dulleses,
                    and the Assistant Secretary for the Far East Walter Robertson. “Everybody” was
                    there; and Sihanouk, and his dancers, and it was just lovely. And the next
                    morning I found myself on my hands and knees washing the bathroom floor, in
                    tears, you know, the real Cinderella complex. We all felt it, it was
                    difficult.</p>
                <p>Anyway, off we went to Vietnam, to be there from 1959 to '62. That was the most
                    extraordinary change of everything, you know — arriving at a beautiful villa
                    with four or five lovely people to help you. The children were whisked upstairs
                    and bathed and put to bed, the laundry removed from your suitcases. Oh it was
                    just a different life. And in those days Saigon was a lovely city. Joe was
                    Political Counselor and there were lots of very interesting things happening all
                    the time. I was teaching at the university — American history and civilization,
                    for three years — at the Faculte de Pedagogie, which was funded by AID. The
                    Faculty had two sections, one French and one English, and the young Vietnamese
                    students would go out among the villages and teach English to the children.</p>
                <p>And it was then when the young teachers went out into the field that the
                    schoolhouses were burned, and students who left our Faculty of Pedagogie to go
                    into the countryside were killed. The war was slowly beginning in the
                    countryside.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Peace Corps?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: I think they had IVS, International Volunteers Service. There were
                    Vietnamese students who left our Faculty to go into the countryside who were
                    killed quite often. A lot of my former students are here in the States as
                    immigrants who came over after the war. As you can imagine, those were three
                    very interesting years. We had very good Vietnamese friends, whom we still have,
                    many of whom are here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lyndon Johnson came on a tour to the Far East as Vice
                        President, and you had Ladybird and Mme. Nhu.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>MENDENHALL:... and Mrs. Stephen Smith, a Kennedy daughter, to the house for tea.
                    That was extremely interesting. I had Mme. Nhu several times. My only real
                    problem — I don't know if this belongs in an interview — came at one point,
                    after the Fritz Noltings arrived. They had been told by President Kennedy to get
                    along at all costs with President Diem. By then many at the Embassy were
                    disaffected — not everybody by any means but quite a few. Mrs. Nolting was a
                    charming lady whom I liked very well.</p>
                <p>At a meeting one day, held at Mme. Nhu's request, of all the wives of the Embassy
                    section heads were to ask all of the people in our sections to contribute funds
                    to build a statue to the Truong sisters, who were — what? fourth, fifth, sixth
                    century saviors of Vietnam. By that time in the war, one knew that things were
                    beginning to happen and there were lots of social problems with the soldiers and
                    their families and so forth. I personally happened to think that collecting
                    money for building a statue was the least important thing to do in Vietnam. So,
                    as Mrs. Nolting went around the circle and asked us, I just said no, I couldn't
                    see myself asking my Political section ladies to contribute to this fund. I was
                    “very sorry” — and I was. I said that I, myself, didn't feel that I could
                    either.</p>
                <p>That was the first time I really came up against this kind of a problem in the
                    Foreign Service. I had to be honest about it, I had no chance to consult with
                    Joe, I just did what I thought was right. And as the query went around the
                    circle, almost everybody said they would go along. The wife of the head of AID
                    said she would not ask her people but that she would give her personal check. My
                    Ambassador's wife was very upset with me and we never resumed our former happy
                    relationship. We were really good friends, they had four daughters, we had
                    three, the children were friends. It was a very difficult situation. Later on
                    Joe unfortunately had differences with the Ambassador also because they were on
                    different sides of the Vietnamese problem.</p>
                <p>When I went home to lunch that day I was really concerned and I said, “well, I
                    may have just fixed your career” and explained to Joe what had happened. He
                    said, “I'm glad you did what you did, it's just what I would have done.” So that
                    was one of the very few times, in fact the only one I can really think of, where
                    a policy problem entered my life as the wife of a Foreign Service Officer. There
                    was nothing I could do about it. That afternoon I must say in the commissary I
                    was approached by about five of those ladies, all of whom said that they wished
                    they had done the same. I'm not trying to show how marvelous I am, it's just
                    that it's an example of the kind of dilemmas one gets into occasionally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, and also it casts a light on the thinking on the
                        part of the Ambassador's wife, I would say.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: Well, you see, they were told they had to get along with Diem, so
                    Mme. Nhu, being President Diem's sister, of the family and so forth, Mrs. Nolte
                    felt that she had to.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It isn't as if Mme. Nhu didn't have any money of her own
                        anyway if she wanted a big statue!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: It was outrageous. It was such an example of their lack of connection
                    with their people, at a juncture where obviously it was so clear to everybody
                    that there were going to be problems; that the only way she could think of
                    carrying on her life was to build statues to ancient ladies — it just seemed so
                    ridiculous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this early or late in your career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: It was late, Nolting was the last Ambassador. He was there I think
                    about a year; he was actually there when Johnson came but was not yet
                    functioning. But it was, as you can imagine, fascinating. The Far East is
                    fascinating. Early on we used to go up to Dalat, to a lovely old Vietnamese
                    house that the Ambassador used as his rest spot when he wanted repose. When he
                    wasn't using it he'd let all of us take turns going up there. A whole group of
                    us at once used to go up at Thanksgiving time. It was in the pine forests,
                    rather high, it was cool, and just lovely. Saigon was a fascinating and
                    beautiful city then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Tet buildup and all of that came after?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: Oh yes, much after. We left in '62.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the end of an era.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: In fact we were, right. Joe worked on Vietnam for altogether about 14
                    years, because when he came back to the Department he still worked on Vietnam.
                    Toward the end of our tour of duty we used to hear guns in the distance and we
                    could no longer travel to Bien Hoa, a little town just outside Saigon, and we
                    certainly could not go to Dalat any longer, it was very dangerous to go to those
                    areas.</p>
                <p>But we did travel. We took the children to Angkor Wat over their Easter vacation,
                    and we went to Bangkok — that was when we were in Laos, we went to Malaysia from
                    Bangkok. We did some traveling in the Far East. Then we came back to the States
                    in '62 and were there for three years before we went to Laos.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>The Lao assignment came rather unexpectedly and for the first time we had to
                    leave a child behind; that was pretty tough. Fortunately, Penny had been going
                    to St. Agnes's in Alexandria, and when we learned we were leaving, it was
                    already August, so what to do about poor Penny — there was no high school in
                    Laos. The headmistress agreed to take her as a boarder for the senior year, so
                    at least she was in a school she was accustomed to and familiar with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And friends.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: But she was very unhappy, very homesick. St. Agnes, although also a
                    boarding school, didn't have many boarding students as yet. Anyway, she could
                    stay there, and we took the other children to Laos. Joe was Economic Counselor
                    and head of the AID program; the Ambassador was Bill Sullivan. We had a
                    beautiful house right on the Mekong. Vientiane is a tiny little — well, to us it
                    was beautiful, particularly to the children. But it's a very nondescript little
                    town.</p>
                <p>The Lao are wonderful. Laos has a poetic quality that's extraordinary. We did a
                    lot of traveling, and I did a lot of traveling with my husband because I was
                    interested and there really wasn't much in the way of teaching or volunteer work
                    that could be done in Laos. There wasn't much community activity except in the
                    pagodas, and we couldn't be part of that — whatever social work, faith healing
                    or whatever was done. But then, Joe had an enormous number of people under him,
                    and I had 220 AID wives to worry about. We did a lot of traveling to nondescript
                    little towns.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Two hundred and twenty!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: Most of the wives, to their disma(but it was the only solution) had
                    to live in a little village called Kilometer Six built just for the AID people.
                    This was not for any nefarious reason. It had to be because there just wasn't
                    enough housing in town and rents had begun to escalate enormously. So that the
                    Lao could never find a place to live. The International Voluntary Service young
                    people who arrived thought this was a terrible thing to do — to isolate the
                    Americans from the people, but there were practical problems involved. Many of
                    these wives had never been abroad before and it was very difficult for them.
                    Their husbands were road builders, engineers, contractors — a tremendous AID
                    program was going on — so they were often very unaccustomed to ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A tremendous problem — there was nothing for them to
                        do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: Well, the Kilometer Six community worked pretty well. There was a
                    recreation center, a swimming pool and a movie house. In a sense it was run sort
                    of like an Army base. But you see, what they were upset about was that they
                    could not travel a lot.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>An experience that Penny, our eldest daughter who came for the summer, and I had
                    was of considerable interest. There was a man called Pop Buell who came from a
                    farm in Iowa. He gave up the farm when he was 55 in order to enter the Peace
                    Corps, then he switched to the International Volunteer Service. Mind you, this
                    is an Indiana [sic] farmer, who went in up into the Montagnard mountains, one
                    series of hilltops across from where the Communists were, to help the mountain
                    people in their agricultural development. He learned the language, lived in a
                    dirt floor little house, and in that particular [region] there was also a small
                    hospital and a small nursing school for the Montagnard wounded fighting the
                    Communists.</p>
                <p>Pop Buell asked my husband if he could think of somebody to relieve his nurse and
                    his secretary for a week or so so they could have some recreation and rest. It
                    was pretty difficult living up there. We talked about it, and he suggested Penny
                    and me. So I went up to be sort of mother to the nurses, and Penny went up to be
                    Pop Buell's secretary. There we were, in a tiny little mountain village, with
                    all the Montagnard very close — we could sometimes hear the guns up there. At
                    night Pop Buell wouldn't let us wander around without soldiers taking us to the
                    little dining house. (End of side A)</p>
                <p>(Beginning mid-sentence) Pop sent messages down to the Embassy in Vientiane and
                    Penny said to me, “What am I supposed to do about his grammar? So he said to
                    her, “You can change anything you want. If it doesn't sound right, just do it as
                    you think fit.” It was a very extraordinary experience to be up there. Pop Buell
                    was an extraordinary man, and very well loved by the mountain people.</p>
                <p>Joe and I traveled by air in tiny one-engine airplanes. There were no roads and
                    we used to go to villages. We were talking with friends about this just the
                    other day, that one village we went to never had heard of the wheel. There were
                    pocket-handkerchief landing strips. Those places were extraordinary. We used to
                    take as many of the government ministers as we could get because often those
                    people had never been to the countryside. They couldn't afford to go by air,
                    obviously, and AID included them often.</p>
                <p>Laos was a most extraordinary experience. There was just never a place like Laos
                    — things that happened there. There were two coups d'etat in Saigon when we were
                    there and there was one in Laos when the children were in Vientiane in school.
                    Joe and I were up-country and returned home immediately. We didn't know what was
                    happening as the army base being bombed was right next to the school. As we were
                    having lunch with a whole bunch of Lao military people, this up-country news
                    came through on the radio.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>So we immediately went to the nearest town radioing to the airport to keep any
                    plane there until we got there so that we could get back to Vientiane. Everybody
                    was worried about their children and their families in the situation. It took us
                    about an hour to get to the nearest airport and there was a plane waiting. But
                    the Ambassador said, from Vientiane, that it shouldn't take off because there
                    were a couple of generals who would like to get on the plane with us, and we had
                    to wait for them. We couldn't wait till too late because there were no landing
                    lights in the airport in Vientiane.</p>
                <p>Well, finally everybody got aboard, including the general who was being attacked
                    and who was going through the countryside in a jeep being followed by this rebel
                    in his airplane. Can you imagine?!(laughter)There were no seats on this plane
                    because it was used for rice dropping, so we all sat on the floor along the
                    walls — well, there was one for the general. And we finally took off. As we got
                    close to Vientiane, we didn't know whether the airport there was held by the
                    rebels or by the army, we didn't know whether we should land there or go across
                    the river to Thailand.</p>
                <p>Well, finally it was decided that we would land in Vientiane. And I must say,
                    that general was pretty good; he got up — he'd been sleeping the whole time — he
                    got up and stood in the door with his hand on his chest. We didn't know when he
                    opened the door who was going to be on the other side. It turned out to be the
                    army, so everybody was safe.</p>
                <p>When I got to the house, (there was a young couple standing there with the
                    children). I said, “How was it, were you frightened? No, teacher told us to get
                    under the desks.” The kids said it was just the way it was for them in Vietnam
                    when they were there! (hearty laughter). They were pretty good. We were pretty
                    worried because that was a worrisome thing.</p>
                <p>But some of the trips into these little villages were just fascinating. One time
                    we went to a tiny little village right on the Mekong, it was so beautiful, you
                    can't imagine — it was like a book by Jean-Jacques Rousseau. It's stupid to say
                    these people were happy in the sense that the “happy savage” was happy, you
                    know. But superficially they seemed so serene. The mothers and babies bathing in
                    the river, and nobody starving. There was enough food, and enough rice, at that
                    time in Laos. People could cultivate their little fields, and they had chickens
                    under their houses. It seemed very bucolic and very beautiful.</p>
                <p>But this one time we were with this young chap who worked with AID, who was
                    educated in the States, spoke perfect English of course, and asked me whether
                    I'd like to speak to the ladies in the pagoda. When the ladies in Laos got old
                    they used to cut their hair and stop dyeing it and just become themselves like
                    proper feminist ladies, and then would sit in the pagoda and gossip. They didn't
                    care about attracting men, they were finished having their children, they were
                    just themselves.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>I looked at the group sitting in a corner of the pagoda and I thought wouldn't it
                    be fun to talk to them. Of course I couldn't speak Lao although I studied it.
                    But I'm terrible at tonal languages. So Manorak came and sat next to me and
                    translated for me. We talked about everything — about village life and what
                    they'd like to do. I asked them if they had their choice of traveling, where
                    would they go? They liked to go to Vientiane, the big metropolis Vientiane! A
                    tiny little city, but to them, it was their capital. And what would they like
                    for their children? That was very interesting, because almost all of these old
                    ladies with children and grandchildren who went to school wanted more schools.
                    Interesting because they are very simple people. None of them had been
                    “educated”, but education and schooling to them was the path to betterment.</p>
                <p>Then of course one begins to think, educate the children and then there are not
                    enough jobs. What do they do and where do they go. Do they emigrate or do they
                    hang around Vientiane looking for work. The economy was nil, there was nothing
                    there for educated people to do. Everything is so entwined with everything else.
                    It's awful to say you shouldn't educate children but what are you educating them
                    for?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And what are you taking them from, out of their little
                        villages too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: Exactly. We see now here, with all the Lao immigrants. Our middle
                    daughter, Priscilla, is married to a Vietnamese whom she met in Laos. He was
                    living in Laos. His family started out in Vietnam at the time of the French. His
                    father was half French, and they had to leave Vietnam for Cambodia and finally
                    ended up in Laos, where he grew up. So he's really Lao by culture. They live
                    here in Washington and Priscilla is very involved with the Lao immigrant
                    community here. And they're having terrible problems, Jewell, I mean really
                    terrible.</p>
                <p>The Lao are different from the Vietnamese, they're not entrepreneurs, they don't
                    have that Chinese aspect in their culture that makes the Chinese so vigorous and
                    businesslike. The Lao are much more as we say today “laid back” people.
                    Priscilla and her husband have made a documentary film, still in progress, of
                    the building of the pagoda in northern Virginia for the Lao community. It is now
                    inhabited by five monks. She's also involved with all the health problems of
                    this community, which are manifold because they know nothing about basic
                    sanitary needs and requirements; there's much hepatitis and so forth in the
                    group.</p>
                <p>The name of the film is “Too Much Air to Breathe,” and that's what their abbot
                    said. When the monks came to the United States, all their lovely little closed
                    comfortable secure ways of life, their own little village temples and their own
                    little village, everything, and relationships, have gone. There was no security
                    because there were no fences, there was nothing to enclose them, to keep them
                    in, and that is one of the big problems psychologically for these people. Life
                    in Laos was that way, it was intimate, it was full of contentment of a certain
                    kind. Underdeveloped, of course, from our standpoint.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>But, one more story about Laos that I just have to tell you so that I will be
                    sure to get in this indication of the people. They are Buddhist but they're
                    animists also. (The house that we lived in was a new house and land had to be
                    exorcized, to get the evil spirits out). The AID program built a bridge over a
                    tributary of the Mekong and there was great fanfare when it was finished. The
                    previous bridge had been washed away and they'd been using boats of course and
                    it was very turbulent at times. So that was very difficult. People came from
                    Washington and there was a great event.</p>
                <p>After the ceremonies the province chief came up to Joe and said, “I'm sorry, Mr.
                    Mendenhall, but we have one more problem that has to be solved.” This in great
                    seriousness. That the people in the area were very disturbed because there was
                    no way that the Pi, [she spells it] the spirits of the river could cross the
                    bridge. And if they couldn't get over the bridge, that bridge would eventually
                    be destroyed just as the previous one was. He suggested, to which Joe agreed,
                    that a little tiny ladder be built going up the side of the bridge and over it
                    and down the other side for the Pi to get over, and that's what we did. I often
                    have wondered if the Appropriations Committee of Congress had ever gotten a
                    request for money for this, whether they would have REALLY had a [ladder for
                    Pi]! (both break up in laughter)Wouldn't that have been droll? But anyway, this
                    was really important to them. So the little tiny ladder is still on the bridge,
                    I think. And the bridge still exists.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, that's something I might have contributed to if
                        (laughing) the Ambassador's wife had taken up a collection.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: Right! But that was important to the culture of the people.
                    Precisely. And Joe was known as a pretty hard-nosed tightwad, and he did not
                    disagree with this request at all. But this was life in Laos. And then we lost
                    it, of course. And a lot of our Lao friends are here now, as I said.</p>
                <p>The pagoda is now finished in northern Virginia, near Manassas. It was built out
                    there only because they couldn't afford to get anything closer. It is
                    inconvenient for everybody, and inconvenient for the people who live out there,
                    who are rather conservative Virginia farmers. Priscilla had to have several
                    training sessions with the sheriff's office in Manassas because the people were
                    protesting this pagoda. Relationships were getting very difficult and it was
                    thought that if the sheriff made his people understand a little better what the
                    Lao were like, then the people wouldn't protest so much.</p>
                <p>So Priscilla spent two or three days with the sheriff's office. Now when they
                    have a big festa, the sheriff's deputies go out there and look over the
                    situation to be sure there's no problem. You know the Lao, in their simple way
                    when they have loudspeakers, they do disturb the community when they have a
                    great feast of some kind, religious processions and so on. But I think it's
                    working out pretty well, on the whole.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>Then we came back to the United States again, from '69 to about '72. But then we
                    did our Inspection travel. And that was wonderful. I couldn't go always with Joe
                    — he was Inspector for three years — because we couldn't afford it. Iran and
                    other places were too expensive to go to. And also the children were in and out
                    of boarding school and going to colleges and universities — it was one o“those
                    times.” So part of the time I was with Joe and part of the time I was not.</p>
                <p>The first Inspection tour was Italy, which of course was what determined our
                    future retirement life, because I fell hook line and sinker for Italy. It was so
                    beautiful. We always wanted to go to Italy. We always had planned to go after we
                    retired to live there at least a year and see what we wanted to do. But when we
                    inspected from Trieste to Milan to Florence to Rome, for three or four months,
                    you can imagine how exciting that was. I fell in love with Tuscany.</p>
                <p>And it was a time when the Vietnam war was going badly and we had been very
                    involved for many years. I just thought I couldn't stand one more minute of this
                    agony we were all going through. To arrive in Tuscany, it was just like
                    sanctuary. It was a world so removed from what we had all in America been living
                    through all these years that I just felt I had to stay there. You
                    understand?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: I often have thought why did I, why did we make this decision — I
                    more than Joe, because (she laughs) he was much more conservative about these
                    things than I — but it was a tremendous decision to make. A good deal of it, I
                    finally realized, was because I was just escaping from a very tragic
                    situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which followed you back to Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: Oh yes, in fact, because Joe was still very much involved. The
                    children were at university, there were manifestations, their father was
                    involved in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>My most exciting Inspections, '70 to '72, were of course Italy and Yugoslavia,
                    which were the most beautiful. During the Inspection period also we decided to
                    buy a piece of land in Tuscany. When Joe went off to places like Iran and I
                    could not go with him, then I rented the little restored farmhouse of Anne and
                    “Tully” Torbert in Tuscany for a year. Our youngest daughter Anne left Abbott,
                    with Abbot's permission, to take her senior year at the University for Foreign
                    Students in Perugia, and I spent a year on my own building a house in Italy
                    because our land lay just across a little tiny hill from the same village as the
                    Torberts' house.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>It was a wonderful year; a very needed year for me, because as I mentioned, the
                    terrible agonies of Vietnam affected everybody and I just had to be removed from
                    everything. And there I was, in a little stone cottage with no electricity and
                    only the fireplaces for heat, and a big library, and classical music on a little
                    radio, and a beautiful view over the Val di Chiana; lovely people in the village
                    — I only spoke French, no Italian. It didn't seem to matter because the Italians
                    are very amenable and very eager to help anybody with their language as long as
                    you show some interest in learning it. When I finally started learning Italian,
                    it was of course very prosaic words like “tiles” and “pipes” and “windows” and
                    so forth. But the workmen were wonderful, and I went every morning to our little
                    excavation. Inch by inch the house grew. It went up from November to June, and
                    the Torberts came back to their summer cottage in June. So I had to leave and go
                    into our house before it had a front door. The only windows and the only door
                    were on the master bedroom, and there I lived for a month while everything was
                    finished. But it was a wonderful year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the children come and go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MENDENHALL: They came for vacations. Everybody including my parents were there
                    for Christmas, at which point we could walk on the floor of the second story. We
                    spent a mild and lovely Christmas day having a picnic in Cortona up at the fort,
                    We got to know the village people very well and we very quickly became part of
                    Lucignano. It was lovely. They loved our girls, and the girls loved them, and of
                    course being young American girls they attracted young Italian boys in droves,
                    and that's really how we began our acquaintanceship with the village, through
                    the children.</p>
                <p>So that was a lovely, a wonderful year in fact. When we arrived in Lucignano we
                    didn't know that there were any other foreigners there but the chap from whom we
                    bought the land introduced us to the Torberts, whom Joe had known o“Tully” in
                    the Foreign Service but had never met him. Then we discovered there was another
                    Foreign Service lady who'd been the Consul in Florence, A... Johanssen
                    [phon.sp.] who had retired there many years before. And there was a marvelous
                    pair of old dames — the only way I can describe them — who lived still outside
                    Lucignano in a teeny little scarcely restored cottage in the woods; they'd lived
                    in Italy for about 55 years. An extraordinary pair — one American, the other
                    born of Chinese and Danish parents. (End of tape.)</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>BIOGRAPHIC DATA</p>
                <p>Spouse: Joseph A. Mendenhall</p>
                <p>Spouse's Position: Econ/Com, Political, Marshall Plan (AID), Inspector, AEP</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>Spouse Entered Service: 1946Left Service: 1975You Entered Service: Same</p>
                <p>Status:Spouse of retiree</p>
                <p>Posts: 1946-49Istanbul, Turkey 1949-51Reykjavik, Iceland 1952-55Bern, Switzerland
                    1955-59Washington, DC 1959-62Saigon, Vietnam 1962-65Washington, DC
                    1965-68Vientiane, Laos 1968-69Washington, DC 1970-72FS Inspector, Washington, DC
                    1973-75Tananarive, Madagascar</p>
                <p>Place/Date of birth: New York City, October 2, 1922</p>
                <p>Maiden Name: Reiber</p>
                <p>Parents: Stepfather a lawyer</p>
                <p>Schools: Vassar, BA: Columbia, MA</p>
                <p>Profession: Teacher, Painter</p>
                <p>Date/Place of Marriage: New York, March 17, 1946</p>
                <p>Children:</p>
                <p>Penelope (1946)</p>
                <p>Priscilla (1952)</p>
                <p>Anne (1954)</p>
                <p>Positions held (Please specify Volunteer or Paid):A. At Post: Istanbul -
                    (Paid)Taught at American High School (Robert College); (Paid) Saigon Taught at
                    University (3 years), President, American Wives' Association; Taught at School
                    for Blind; Worked at Go Vap orphanage</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
