<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001005">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with McKinney Russell </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Information Series</p>
                <p>MCKINNEY RUSSELL</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: G. Lewis Schmidt </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 10, 1997</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is May 10, 1997 at the home of McKinney Russell. I am
                        going to ask McKinney to start out by giving us a short statement on where
                        he came from, when and where he was born, and where he was before he came to
                        Washington, and then he will take it from there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: In brief, this is my background. I was born in May 1929 in New York
                    City. My father was a newspaper man for the Brooklyn Eagle, who had come north
                    from Florida just a few months before I was born. My mother was also a
                    southerner from Atlanta. I grew up in New York City. My father worked for the
                    paper right through the Depression. I went to public schools in Brooklyn and
                    went to Midwood High School in the class of 1946, and spent those four years of
                    high school during the Second World War, a fairly formative period in my own
                    life. I was the oldest of the four children. I have a brother and sisters —
                    twins, three years younger — and a younger brother who is 11 years younger.</p>
                <p>The four of us grew up in Brooklyn in the '30s during a relatively carefree and
                    happy time for us as a family. No particular problem during the Depression and
                    living in New York City was a big adventure during those times. Security was not
                    a problem. You could go anywhere on the subway and somehow feel secure with
                    Fiorello La Guardia as the Mayor.</p>
                <p>In 1946, I had the choice of three colleges, Yale Harvard and Dartmouth. I picked
                    Yale and joined the class of 1950 in September of 1946. I spent four years as an
                    undergraduate at the Yale College and, in part because of the influence of the
                    events of the Second World War, in part because I had found in high school that
                    I had a good ear for foreign languages, I decided to major in Russian area
                    studies. I learned Russian fairly well during the three years of intensive study
                    as an undergraduate, and realized rather quickly that the expectations many of
                    us had had that the United States and the Soviet Union would be allies and
                    friends forever, as they had been during the War, were not to be realized.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>When I graduated on June 12 of 1950, it was only 13 days later that very obvious
                    violent proof was given that we and the Soviet Union were not going to get
                    along, when the invasion by North Korea of South Korea launched that war. I had
                    made no particular plans for any graduate study or a career and not too many
                    months went by before I received a letter from President Truman inviting me to
                    join the Armed Forces and do my two years of duty as an enlisted man. After
                    doing a range of different jobs, translation work, odds and ends, just to keep
                    active during the fall of 1950, I was inducted into the U.S. Army in March 1951.
                    I did my two years and most of the period that I was in the Army I spent in the
                    Army of Occupation in West Germany in and around the Frankfurt area. I arrived
                    in Germany on a troop ship with 3000 other GIs on the first of January 1952,
                    following basic training and some specialized training.</p>
                <p>On the troopship I had a moderately interesting experience. I didn't know any
                    German at the time. Among my shipmates was a young Swiss who had been sent by
                    his company, Swissair, to work for them in New York City. His company and he had
                    been careless enough not to realize that, as a resident alien, he was subject at
                    that time to the draft of the U.S. Government, and here was a young Swiss who
                    was actually drafted against his will into the U.S. Army. Why he had let himself
                    fall into that situation, or put up with it, I don't know, but he was an
                    entirely disillusioned young man. Somehow or other, we struck an acquaintance
                    and he said, “Well, I'll pass the time until I get back to Europe and teach you
                    German.” So every day, we walked on the deck and he taught me the basics of the
                    language.</p>
                <p>It didn't help very much though, because nobody on the troop train from
                    Bremerhaven to Bavaria, including me, knew much of the language. I recall that,
                    as the train went south, there was a big sign at every railway station that
                    said, “Ausgang”, and we were naively surprised that the German towns seemed to
                    have the same name. It was only after about 3 or 4 stops that we realized that
                    “Ausgang” was the German word for “exit” and all of the stations of course had
                    quite different names. During the 15 months I was in the Army in Germany, I
                    learned German fairly thoroughly and had a quite active personal social
                    life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you study German? I mean, you never had a formal
                        study...just picking it up and from talking to people...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: Never had any formal study. I picked up quite a lot and found that the
                    experience of living and working there was a stimulating one. I had learned
                    French tolerably well in high school and knew Russian well, and when an
                    opportunity came my way to be discharged from the Army in Europe rather than
                    return to the States directly, I took a job that began as soon as I left the
                    Army in March 1953.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>For two years it took me to a western German city called Kaiserslautern. During
                    those years of the '50s there was a steady stream of refugees and escapees,
                    Soviet citizens disillusioned with their own country who had an opportunity to
                    reach the West, mostly through Berlin. Many of them were Soviet troops from East
                    Germany. These are years before the building of the Berlin wall, and if a Soviet
                    soldier were able to get civilian clothes and reach East Berlin, it was no
                    particular trick to escape into the Western sectors by subway. The U.S.
                    authorities interested in finding out exactly what was going on in East Germany
                    would spend a month or so interrogating these escapees, but they were not going
                    to go anywhere as emigrants, having just come out, and they were bound to spend
                    at least several years in Germany before they would have such a chance.</p>
                <p>A non-governmental organization, with funding from the United States Government
                    under the Presidential Escapee Program, with the rather grand name of American
                    Friends of Russian Freedom, had established a residence, a very simple kind of
                    barracks reception center for about 30 such people in Kaiserslautern. At that
                    time there was a major NATO build-up and consequently there were lots of jobs
                    for drivers, plumbers, electricians and security guards, and so on. As Center
                    Director I was in charge of finding jobs for the escapees and running the
                    Center, a rather challenging job because I was still younger than most of the
                    people I was responsible for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this a paid job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: Those were paid jobs but the pay in those days was not very high. The
                    salaries for social workers are never particularly high, but I recall that my
                    yearly salary when I began working in Kaiserslautern was $3,750 a year, which
                    was enough for a young single fellow to live on, but was not very high on the
                    hog. It was a very important and formative period in my life because every few
                    weeks there were new arrivals of refugee Soviets, including some from Central
                    Asia. They would arrive speaking barely any German, and it was my job, through
                    the German Labor Office, to persuade the Germans to give them a reference to the
                    American office that was hiring for the U.S. Forces build-up.</p>
                <p>It turned out to be a very tough job. There were some rowdies and drunks among
                    the Russians who were very hard to manage. Looking back on this experience, I
                    have to say that it was a particularly important period in my life. As I learned
                    to take responsibility and a leadership role and get things accomplished for my
                    charges, I did some serious growing up. I also had to learn German intensively,
                    and by the time I left, both my German and my Russian were very useful and had
                    been learned quite thoroughly.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>For several years I had had my eye on the U.S. radio stations operating in
                    Munich. The public story in those years was that funding for the two stations
                    came from private contributions by Americans to make it possible for Radio Free
                    Europe to broadcast to five countries in Eastern Europe, that is, Poland,
                    Hungary, Romania, Bulgaria and Czechoslovakia, at the same time that Radio
                    Liberty broadcast from different studios in about fifteen languages of the
                    Soviet Union, principally Russian, of course, but also Ukrainian, Belorussian,
                    Tatar-Bashkir, Georgian, Uzbek, and so on.</p>
                <p>In the spring of 1955, a job as Head of Translation at Radio Liberty opened. I
                    was accepted for it and moved to Munich in my old green Opel car in April 1955.
                    Of course, both stations were funded by the Central Intelligence Agency,
                    although no one told me that for 3 or 4 years. The people ultimately in charge,
                    very few of whom knew any Russian, had no idea of what the broadcasts were
                    actually saying. Thus a number of translations had to be made for their benefit
                    of parts of the program every day. Since the translators were all non-native
                    English speakers, the head of the translation section had to do the editing to
                    make sure that the results actually roughly approximated the English
                    language.</p>
                <p>I had that job for about 6 or 7 months and then progressively moved up within the
                    organization until I left it in October 1962. I became Special Events
                    Correspondent, then Chief Correspondent, then Deputy Head of News. It proved to
                    be a very interesting professional life, calling for a good deal of travel in
                    Europe. I was often in Brussels or Paris and made half a dozen reporting trips
                    to Scandinavia. The point was to inform listeners in the Soviet Union through
                    feature programs which were then translated into Russian and the other
                    languages. We reported on how free trade unions work in Western Europe; what the
                    living conditions were for people in Finland right next to the Soviet Union; how
                    Swedish elections took place in the glare of sharp competition between competing
                    parties, the overall idea being to provide an alternative picture of what life
                    could be in free countries, and not only in the United States. There were
                    broadcasters from New York and Washington, but the radio station broadcast, as
                    did Radio Free Europe, not as an American station like VOA but as voices of
                    their own peoples.</p>
                <p>In 1959, I was on home leave from Munich and had the opportunity of covering the
                    two-week trip to the United States by the then leader of the Soviet Union,
                    Nikita Khrushchev. I traveled with him from Washington to New York, and to the
                    West Coast, up to San Francisco, to the farm in Iowa, and so on. The principal
                    long-term event in my life during those years was meeting the woman whom I
                    married and to whom I have been married ever since. In February of 1957, after I
                    had been in Munich almost 2 years, I met at a dinner party with colleagues from
                    the Radio Liberty, a young woman of French culture, Italian citizenship, and
                    great charm. She had grown up in Tunisia and was visiting friends in Munich. Her
                    name was Stella Boccara. We decided rather quickly that we went very well
                    together and were married not too long thereafter. Our first son McKinney
                    Junior, was born in 1959, in Munich, and our second child, daughter, Valerie,
                    was born in 1961, also in Munich.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>Now I had taken Foreign Service Exam for the Department of State in August 1959
                    at the Consulate in Frankfurt, passed it, and was offered an appointment in the
                    Department of State in the spring of 1960. Having developed a certain
                    professional skill in journalism, and having an interest in the
                    information/cultural side of things, I decided against taking that State
                    Department offer and try my luck with USIA instead. In 1961 on home leave in the
                    States, I took the oral test that was given at that time by USIA before a panel
                    of three USIA Foreign Service Officers. There was no written exam, but the oral
                    exam went well, and after completion of security clearance and so on, in the
                    summer of 1962 I was offered appointment as a Class 5 Officer in USIA, the
                    equivalent of FSO 3 these days. This, of course, meant leaving Munich and coming
                    back to Washington for training. At that time, Stella and I had two small
                    children, one one-year old, and the other three.</p>
                <p>At the time that the letter of invitation came from USIA, there was a note of
                    urgency in the message to the effect that there was a very specific and
                    important job that USIA had already identified which they wanted me to fill.
                    Naively, as it turned out, since I had spent at that time since January 1952—in
                    other words, near 10-1/2 years or so in Europe, and had perfected a knowledge of
                    Russian, German and French, and learned Polish along the way, and passable
                    Swedish—I was pretty sure that the job they had in mind was a grand, important
                    job in Eastern Europe.</p>
                <p>I was sworn in to the Agency at 9 a.m. on October 15, 1962. At 9:10 that same
                    morning, I got my assignment to go as Assistant Information Officer to
                    Leopoldville. Leopoldville, now known as the city of Kinshasa, was the capital
                    of a country then called the ex-Belgian Congo, later as the Congo, then as
                    Zaire, and now once again Congo. People who recall those years know well that
                    after Independence was given to the Congo in June 960, there has been a period
                    of great internal upheaval , uncertainty about who was in charge,
                    assassinations, tribal uprisings. It was a particularly dangerous time and a
                    time when there was a great deal of world concern about Africa. Events in the
                    Congo took several serious negative turns during 1961 and 1962.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...and we were evacuating, I think, a number of Americans
                        and also people of other nations, by military craft about that time, weren't
                        they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: That evacuation effort was the serious and bloody event that came later
                    in November 1964 when there was hostage-taking in the town called Stanleyville,
                    now known as Kisangani. At that time, the Americans, the British and the
                    Belgians collaborated to send in planes to evacuate some 300 hostages.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>When my family and I arrived in the Congo in early 1963, the situation was
                    already one of great uncertainly and disorder. As a first assignment in USIA, it
                    turned out to be one that offered a broad range of experience in new
                    circumstances. I should mention before going on that the entry into the White
                    House in 1961 by John F. Kennedy and his designation of Edward R. Murrow as the
                    Director of USIA were both important factors in leading me to want to work in
                    the Agency.</p>
                <p>That first assignment involved working with Congolese media that had just gained
                    independence and the ability to write what they wanted after 70 years of
                    colonialism, so it was a heady and interesting stuff. They were very
                    inexperienced. One had the opportunity to assist them to develop journalistic
                    skills and they were appreciative of that.</p>
                <p>For reasons that I don't now recall, perhaps because of better transportation
                    links and perhaps because the Congo was not a former French colony, the USIS
                    post in Leopoldville at the time was the producer of a monthly magazine in the
                    form of a tabloid newspaper 16 to 20 pages long, which was called “American
                    Perspectives”. It was published in 105,000 copies edited and printed in
                    Leopoldville and then shipped by air to all of the French-speaking countries in
                    Africa: Senegal, Ivory Coast, Cameroon, Gabon, etc. I had had very little
                    experience with the print media, although I knew radio quite well at the time I
                    came into the Agency.</p>
                <p>I recall that 2 days after my arrival the other Assistant Information Officer, a
                    man named Don Miller, was first to return to the States because of illness or
                    death in his family. He was the editor of the American Perspectives. When he
                    left, the Information Officer informed me the same day that I had just become
                    Acting Editor of the magazine. This was the time when I didn't yet know that you
                    could take a photograph and make it a different size when you printed it. I
                    recall being distinctly daunted and wondering how I had ever gotten into this
                    business when I looked at a big 8” x 11” photograph and I only had a space 2” x
                    4” in which to print it. But you learn quickly in USIA and for the time that my
                    colleague was away, I was editor of the American Perspectives and later
                    contributed to it and wrote for it in the course of the next 2 years.A demanding
                    element of my tenure in the Congo was representing U.S. A.I.D. and explaining
                    American assistance to the Congolese through working with the press. This was
                    not always easy. For example, the corn that we sent as food aid was the kind of
                    yellow corn that we grow and consume in this country. The corn that the
                    Congolese were used to eating was a white variety, and there was a lot of
                    resistance to consuming the food that was sent by the U.S. under Food for
                    Peace.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>They were interesting years because of the uncertainty and the feeling that what
                    one did seemed was very important. One imagined that it made a real difference.
                    Here was this enormous country, the wealthiest in the continent, falling apart
                    and in the news all the time. At the time in November 1964 when the hostages
                    were taken by rebels in the Eastern Congo, in Stanleyville, I was the acting
                    spokesman for the Embassy and learned a lot very fast about talking to the
                    press, either talking to the press or not, and what to say or not to say. It was
                    a very interesting and demanding time because, of course, the fact that the
                    United States had provided the planes to fly in Belgian paratroopers from
                    British Ascension Island in the South Atlantic, only a few years after Congolese
                    independence, created very serious problems for the United States and the other
                    two countries in public affairs terms.</p>
                <p>Here was a new independent African nation, and the United States led by John
                    Kennedy, collaborating with the former colonial powers to fly right into the
                    middle of Africa and shoot the place up. Stanleyville was in a real sense the
                    heart of Africa. It was the very part of the Congo about which Joseph Conrad had
                    written his novel, “Heart of Darkness.” For USIS and for me, there was one
                    memorable event in the wake of the fly-in by the American planes to free the
                    hostages in Stanleyville.</p>
                <p>The Congolese Government, and particularly the United States Embassy and the
                    American Administration, felt an urgent need to publish something to explain and
                    justify the action. The decision was taken by the PAO, a rather famous PAO in
                    USIA history named John Mowinckel, to produce a so-called White Paper about the
                    event. It would be written in English and in French with photographs, and would
                    be distributed widely around the continent in both languages.</p>
                <p>I was given the job in writing and editing and publishing that White Paper. It
                    was a very interesting effort. We managed to get the text written and
                    translated, and the photographs inserted, all in about 6 days time. The West
                    German government had set up a printing press and was supporting the daily
                    newspaper in Kinshasa. We worked out a quick deal with them for them to print it
                    and we had something like 100,000 or more copies of the White Paper produced
                    within less than a week. It was an exciting exercise and may have done some
                    good.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>I had met the Area Director for Africa, at that time Mark Lewis, on a trip he
                    took to Leopoldville some time in 1964. When we left the Congo, I was assigned
                    to go as cultural attach� to Warsaw. The end of our tour in the Congo was a
                    rather tense and difficult time because my wife had to leave early in order to
                    give birth to our third child, Kyle, who was born in Lyon, France, where her
                    parents then lived. Her departure with the two small children with me behind in
                    the Congo was a period of considerable stress for her and the family. We
                    expected to be going back briefly to the States on home leave, and then going to
                    Warsaw, but this was not to be.Agency leadership at that time was very
                    interested in setting the same kind of management and personnel norms for USIA
                    officers as obtained for State officers. A goal was that USIA officers should be
                    designated Foreign Service Officers without any “R” for Foreign Service Reserve,
                    or “I” for Foreign Service Information Officer, on a level of complete equality.
                    Among other things, the standards for length of time overseas were limited, and
                    at that time in the early spring of 1965 when we left the Congo separately to
                    going to Warsaw, I had been abroad since January 1952, between military service
                    and refugee resettlement and Radio Liberty and the Congo.</p>
                <p>This led to the Washington decision, just as I was leaving or just after I had
                    left to join the family in France, that I would not after all be going to Warsaw
                    but was to be reassigned back to the United States. Mark Lewis got in touch with
                    me with some urgency and offered me the position of Policy Officer for the
                    African Area. When we were all back in the States by that spring of 1965, some
                    time like the beginning of May, I became Policy Officer for the African Area of
                    USIA.</p>
                <p>This proved to be something of a stretch, inasmuch as the only field experience I
                    had had was in a very atypical part of Africa, namely the rebellious Congo. The
                    African Area at that time was on the fifth or the sixth floor of 1750
                    Pennsylvania Avenue. This space and several other floors had just recently been
                    taken over and added to the 1776 offices, as the Agency's role expanded. Mark
                    Lewis was Area Director and Bill Weld was Deputy Area Director. Dave Dubois was
                    Program Coordinator and I was Policy Officer.</p>
                <p>It turned out to be a particularly rich assignment because Africa was very much
                    on our minds as a nation and a Foreign Service. The Peace Corps had its first
                    volunteers in many countries in Africa. Interest in Africa was also very high in
                    part because the mid-'60s were a time of surging civil rights activism in the
                    United States. As a result, as Policy Officer, I had a budget of close to
                    three-quarters of a million dollars a year to make films for Africa.</p>
                <p>It was an extremely interesting time to work with creative film-makers. At that
                    time, George Stevens, Jr. was head of the Film Service, a man of great
                    creativity. There were some very good film-makers in the Agency, and we had a
                    cadre of documentary film makers with whom we would work on contract.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>During my 2 years as Policy Officer, we must have made 8 or 10 documentary films.
                    One dealt with the Peace Corps volunteers in Niger, another was about visits to
                    the United States by statesmen like Senegalese President Leopold Senghor. One
                    spectacular film about the First Festival of Negro Arts held in 1966, in
                    Senegal, was a particular success. The film-maker who made that film was a
                    highly talented black documentary film-maker named William Greaves. He and I
                    have remained friends to this day as a result of our collaboration on that film.
                    Greaves is currently making a lengthy documentary on the life and work of Ralph
                    Bunche, and he was here in Washington this week for the dedication of the
                    library of the Department of State as the Ralph Bunche Library.</p>
                <p>In any event, those experiences in the film world were very broadening for me
                    personally, conceiving what a film ought to do, working with the film-maker, and
                    then taking it through the process of rough-cut and fine-cut to see how the film
                    came out in policy terms and artistically. Defining the policy consideration and
                    balancing them against the artistic concerns of the film-maker himself—these
                    were extremely interesting issues.</p>
                <p>Now, some of the films that were made later in the '60s and in the early '70s,
                    particularly those relating to the events in Southeast Asia, touched off some
                    very serious differences and controversies. Some of those films were, of course,
                    never even released, as we know. But these were more simple, straightforward
                    days, and I recall them with a great deal of satisfaction. I hope very much that
                    those documentaries that we made for Africa in mid-'60s are still in the Agency
                    archives and haven't been lost. I know that Greaves's excellent film about the
                    Festival of Negro Arts is still extant. I saw it 5 or 6 years ago. We also made
                    a film about the Second Festival of Negro Arts in Nigeria, which would have been
                    in perhaps late '67, but it was a good deal less successful a film.</p>
                <p>At that time also, in 1966, I was the author of the policy paper that defined the
                    purposes and goals of a new Agency magazine in English and French for Africa.
                    Called “TOPIC”, it was launched in the spring of 1967 and grew and continued
                    until quite recently. Among the things that made its contribution was that TOPIC
                    reported events involving the United States and Africa across the continent. We
                    cross-reported events of interest to Uganda to readers in Cameroon and Togo, for
                    example.At that time, I was also much involved with the VOA broadcasts in
                    English, French, Portuguese, Swahili and Hausa. Altogether, those two years
                    working with Lewis and the others were extremely important formative years in my
                    own development, because I really learned how the Agency worked. I dealt with
                    the publishers, reviewed the Wireless Files, negotiated with the radio
                    broadcasters, and collaborated with film makers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You gained a very broad perspective on the Agency
                        activities then.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>RUSSELL: It was extremely interesting. I recall meeting regularly with other
                    policy officers in 1965, '66, '67. At that time, the Agency Policy Officer was
                    an unusual person named John Pauker whose visiting card, I recall, identified
                    him as John Pauker, Poet and Propagandist. John was an elfin, impish man, who
                    brought together the policy officers from the five Areas every morning, at I
                    think 7:30, in his office, for a conference call with the Voice of America and
                    the Department of State. We had lively discussions about what was going on
                    around the world, what ought to be said, and various approaches were suggested
                    for the various media. Those were never dull times.</p>
                <p>In April 1966, Mark Lewis and I made an extensive trip across Africa, to 10 or 12
                    countries. I remember each of those stops with a good deal of affection. We
                    spent several days in Addis Ababa when Gene Rosenfeld was PAO; went to Kampala,
                    were briefly in Douala in Cameroon, and spent 3 or 4 days in Lagos where Hunt
                    Damon was Public Affairs Officer. We visited Kenya as well, when a very talented
                    black American journalist from Pittsburgh, whose name doesn't come right to
                    mind, was PAO at the time. We were in Ghana a few months after the fall of Kwame
                    Nkrumah, and then ended for 3 or 4 intensive and interesting days in Dakar,
                    Senegal, when Ted Tanen, one of our really great PAOs, was running the program.
                    It was very informative and helpful to me, after return to Washington, in
                    working with the various media that were providing programming for the field
                    posts we had visited.</p>
                <p>The next year, in the spring of 1967, I had an extremely close call of a medical
                    nature. I had gone to the office on a Monday morning early and was troubled by a
                    progressively more insistent pain in the abdomen. By 10 o'clock it was clear
                    that I had something very seriously wrong. I was rushed to the hospital and had
                    a three-hour operation for an inflamed appendix. It was a very close call. I
                    still bless my luck that it happened while I was at 1750 Pennsylvania Avenue,
                    and not airborne somewhere over Central Africa.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>In the middle of '67, after 2 years in the Africa area office, I was transferred
                    to take over the direction of the VOA broadcasts in the 4 languages of the
                    Soviet Union that the Voice broadcast in at that time, Russian, Ukrainian,
                    Georgian and Armenian. My earlier experience at Radio Liberty, where I was
                    Deputy News Director when I left, prepared me for this job, as did my knowledge
                    of Russian. Those 2 years were, I have to say, singularly demanding and
                    complicated. There were 120 people in the division which had been, when I
                    arrived, part of the European Division of the VOA. We all felt rather
                    uncomfortable under that umbrella, since the problems we faced were so
                    different, and I began early on working for the creation of a separate division.
                    After 6 or 8 months, that was successful, and the USSR Division was created.The
                    non-Russian services were much smaller-the Georgian and Armenian services had
                    only 5 or 6 members, the Ukrainian might have had 10-but the Russian had some 85
                    or 90...they were broadcasting in Russian 17 or 18 hours a day. There was a
                    challenging range of complexities in that job. One, of course, was that of
                    creating interesting programs every day for the audience, and it was an audience
                    with which, at that time, I had never had any contact. I had never been to the
                    Soviet Union when I took over this job in August 1967. I had hoped that soon
                    after the move, say within 6 months, I would make a trip there to gain on the
                    ground some direct sense of the audience. I made that trip in December 1967 to
                    all four of the areas, Russia, Ukraine, Armenia and Georgia to which we were
                    broadcasting.</p>
                <p>The policy issues were very complicated, among other things, because there were
                    political differences within the services, often between people who had
                    divergent backgrounds and saw things very differently. In the Russian Service,
                    for example, there were those who had come out after the 1917 Revolution who
                    were men and women already in their sixties. Then there were those who had
                    remained in the West during or after the War. And there were yet others, most of
                    whom had come out in the 1960s. These different generations had very varied
                    different experiences and perspectives and often they were at loggerheads with
                    each other. There was a lot of mediation and keeping people apart that came with
                    heading up that broadcasting unit at the VOA.</p>
                <p>The most striking single event during my tenure was the invasion of
                    Czechoslovakia in 1968. When I joined the VOA, there had been no jamming by
                    Soviet jammers since 1962. It was during the invasion, with the move of Soviet
                    troops into Czechoslovakia, that jamming was reinstated and again created the
                    problems of getting through that interference.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>The mid-'60s were in general a period of Americanization of the VOA broadcasts to
                    the USSR. My immediate predecessor, Terry Catherman, a particularly energetic
                    and effective officer, had spent 3 years there, and had made it his policy to
                    bring on many young Americans whose Russian may not have been perfect but who
                    had a much brighter and fresher approach to broadcasting. He had introduced
                    programs of popular music with the disc jockey work being done by young
                    Americans rather than Russian emigres. Terry's predecessor had been a former
                    Soviet general who had defected in 1934 in Athens, a man named Alexander
                    Barmine. He was a very conscientious, very committed broadcaster, but also a
                    very authoritarian figure, and one who did not think that young Americans whose
                    grammar in using the Russian language that was not perfect should be on the air.
                    Well, Catherman had made a new approach stick during his tenure, and I was very
                    pleased to continue in the same track that he had initiated.</p>
                <p>I was scheduled to go as Cultural Affairs Officer to Moscow in 1968 after one
                    year in the Voice of America, but that transfer was postponed for a year until
                    1969. So I had 2 full years in the VOA, and still have friends from that period.
                    There is a special kind of esprit de corps among Voice people that we foreign
                    service officers came to appreciate very much.The standard procedure in those
                    years was that the heads of the various geographic divisions would be foreign
                    service officers. The head of the Near East Asia Area would be someone who had
                    recently served there, and the result was that there was usually a close and
                    cordial personal relationship between the Agency's foreign service and the
                    broadcasters. At the same time, though, in part because of the pressures that
                    built up when broadcasters had been on the job for 10 or 12 years, 15, 18 years
                    and had gained real expertise as broadcasters. Repeatedly there would be a
                    foreign service officer who would move in as head of the division and this was
                    bound to generate resentment.</p>
                <p>A policy shift began later that saw civil servants, broadcasters with the VOA, at
                    the head of the various division units. This must have started in the early or
                    mid-'70s. By now it's become standard and there are very few, if any, foreign
                    service officers in positions of broadcasting authority at the VOA. But despite
                    some tensions in those years, it was, I thought, a very positive way of keeping
                    two distinct elements of the Agency talking to and working with each other. John
                    Charles Daly was the head of the VOA at that time, a serious American
                    broadcaster and well-liked quizmaster, a very open-spirited, energetic man. An
                    old friend from Radio Liberty days, Francis Ronalds, was VOA program manager. It
                    was a very stimulating and interesting place to work, and I have, as I say, very
                    fond memories of it.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>I then went to Moscow as CAO, arriving in July 1969, arriving on July 2 to be
                    exact, with my wife and children. The 3 children were, at that time, 10, 8 and
                    5. As CAO, I held the number two position in a five-officer post. Five officers
                    and two locals made up the full USIS staff at the American Embassy in Moscow in
                    1969. We were not called USIS but were known as the Press and Cultural Section
                    of the American Embassy, and that was then standard practice in the USSR and
                    Eastern Europe. Arriving on July 2, the first thing that we did that was
                    particularly memorable was to attend the 4th of July events at Spaso House and
                    at the Embassy's dacha. Four or five days later, the Public Affairs Officer,
                    Yale Richmond, left on home leave so that I was Acting PAO within a week after
                    arrival.</p>
                <p>Now on the way back to the United States, Yale Richmond joined the then Director
                    of USIA, Frank Shakespeare, and PAOs from Poland, Hungary, Romania, Yugoslavia
                    and Czechoslovakia, for a PAO Conference in Vienna. This was the first time that
                    Frank Shakespeare had met the Public Affairs Officers from Eastern Europe. He
                    had been appointed by President Nixon as Director of USIA in the spring of 1969,
                    and was a particularly activist anti-Communist in his view of the world.</p>
                <p>Apparently, as I understand the story several public affairs officers later told
                    me, the Director asked each what he thought would happen if Communist power were
                    to collapse tomorrow in each of their countries. How the other people responded
                    I don't know, but Yale Richmond reportedly said that he assumed that after—at
                    that time it would have been some 50 years after the communists seized
                    power—that many people in the Soviet Union would opt for some kind of socialism
                    and that an immediate shift, a total shift into new political direction, seemed
                    to him to be unlikely. This response reportedly made the Director extremely
                    angry and very critical of Yale, to the extent that he removed him as Public
                    Affairs Officer in the Soviet Union more or less on the spot. Yale Richmond
                    never went back to Moscow then, and the USIS secretary, Mary Keeny, packed up
                    his family's effects at his apartment and had them shipped back to the U.S.. He
                    went on to an extremely active and effective tenure in the old CU, and is today
                    a recognized expert on East-West exchanges. But in summer 1969, I thus found
                    myself as PAO in the Soviet Union.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>By late August Frank Shakespeare had decided that I could hack it, that I was the
                    one he wanted to take the job, which put me rather on the spot, because here I
                    was PAO with only two years of overseas experience in the former Belgian Congo.
                    So, although it was at that time a Class I position, old Class I now
                    corresponding to Minister Counselor, my rank at that time was Class III. I was
                    in a way over my head, and had a lot to learn. At that time, I had had, between
                    working in the Radio Liberty and at the VOA, something like 11 years of
                    experience of working and using the Russian language a great deal, so I was
                    quite at home in it. I was able to get much involved in things Soviet without
                    having to worry about interpreters or major misunderstandings.First of all, I
                    was very interested in supporting the VOA. I set up a system, soon after my
                    arrival, of a monthly reporting and analytical airgram to the VOA in Washington.
                    . In those days, the airgram was used a great deal. It was a message sent by
                    pouch, not by telegram, and, in order to give the Voice of America broadcasters
                    a sense of what was going on, what people were talking about, what might be
                    interesting to them, my staff and I wrote every month a detailed airgram telling
                    them what seemed to be on people's minds and trying to reflect the atmospherics
                    of life in the Soviet Union. We also let the broadcasters know what their
                    audibility was—we set up a system of having travelers to other parts of the
                    country take along a VOA radio on loan and try to tune in and report back to us
                    on whether or not they had been able to listen to VOA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to travel quite freely at that time, or were
                        you quite restricted?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: It was always a problem to travel at that time, but what made it
                    necessary for us to travel was a rather interesting circumstance. In return for
                    our agreeing in the original cultural agreement signed, I believe, in 1958 with
                    the Soviet Union, to allow a very limited number of Soviet scholars to come to
                    the United States on an exchange basis, a whole cultural agreement was developed
                    under which there was also a system of national exhibitions. The Soviets would
                    do an exhibition on some aspect of life there that they would send to us, and we
                    in return, i.e., USIA, would mount one and send it to them. Our society, at that
                    time as now, was a completely open one, but theirs unlike the present, was still
                    tightly closed. Naturally, the impact of these national exhibits was far greater
                    in their country than in ours. Our exhibit on education, for example, was shown
                    in 1970 in the city of Baku, the capital of Azerbaijan, which had never seen an
                    exhibit of any kind about anything in the United States. Its popularity was
                    enormous. The arrangement was that an exhibit would be in the country for one
                    year; it would go to 6 cities for about a month in each city and then take a
                    month to pack up and move on by train to the next city.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>Just before I arrived in July of 1969, a new American exhibit on our educational
                    system had opened in Leningrad. The first time that I left Moscow was 3 or 4
                    weeks after arrival to take the measure of this important show. There were
                    serious problems with it, including inadequate coverage of certain aspects of
                    education, not very lively exhibits, in fact, a whole range of problems. The
                    exhibit was to move on to Moscow in September and everyone wanted it to be as
                    successful as possible in the capital. I recall writing a lengthy and detailed
                    critique back to the Agency describing what was lacking or wrong as I saw it,
                    along with comments from Soviet visitors and from the young American guides at
                    the exhibit. The Agency responded very quickly and by the time the exhibit
                    opened in Moscow, a number of improvements had been made.The guides in these
                    exhibits had learned Russian or knew it from the families. They were, of course,
                    the stars of the show, because they would spend 7 or 8 hours a day talking to
                    audiences and explaining, for example, how one got into a university or how
                    public schools worked in the United States. There were 25 or so guides, young
                    men and women and they took advantage of a very interesting opportunity to
                    participate in the exhibits and gain unique access to Soviet citizens who came
                    to the exhibit. It was unquestionably one of the best things that the Agency was
                    ever involved in doing, because the long-range impact on the minds of the young
                    Soviet citizens was very great and lasting.</p>
                <p>The guides and staffs of the exhibits helped make an enormous difference, and
                    many of them have now gone on to many kinds of other things. Jack Harrod was
                    with one of the exhibits, perhaps the education one, and retired recently as
                    Western Europe Area Director. There is a marvelous broadcaster at the Voice of
                    America named Mary Patzer, whose Russian was virtually native, who got her start
                    as an exhibit guide back in the '60s. In any case, the fact that this exhibit,
                    besides going to St. Petersburg and Moscow, went to Ukraine, to Kiev, Baku in
                    Azerbaijan; went to Tashkent in Uzbekistan, and also scheduled to go to
                    Novosibirsk out in Siberia... six altogether interesting cities.</p>
                <p>This meant that the USIS staff, which was called Press and Cultural, had to do
                    the advance work, negotiate with the local Chambers of Commerce, agree on a
                    site, to install the exhibit. It was extremely labor-intensive to do that and
                    demanded a lot of effort. I made 2 or 3 trips to Tashkent by air, 4 or 5 hours
                    from Moscow, or maybe more, to set the exhibit up there for its opening for
                    instance. I recall being scheduled to go to Baku to open the exhibit there, and
                    having prepared a short speech in the local language, which I was never able to
                    give because the plane, it being deepest winter, was never able to take off. I
                    recall that my wife and I spent over 24 hours at one of the airports outside
                    Moscow waiting for the departure of the plane to Baku that never left.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have one question in that regard. The young people who
                        were handling the exhibits up to that point had studied Russian, but these
                        exhibits in other locations required the knowledge of other local
                        languages...for example, Ukrainian, and so forth. Did you have young people
                        who were also sufficiently fluent in these other languages to handle the
                        question and answers involved, in showing the exhibits in these varied
                        places?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: I don't think any exhibit we sent went to Ukraine without having
                    Ukrainian speakers, though there were fewer of them than Russian speakers. There
                    may have been Armenian speakers in those that went to that republic, but the
                    principal effort was that, since Russian was understandable everywhere and we
                    were going to have exhibits going to 6 cities and 3 of them were inside Russia,
                    the guides would need a good command of Russian.</p>
                <p>There is one interesting political event connected with the opening of the
                    education exhibit in Novosibirsk, in Central Siberia. In May of 1970, when the
                    exhibit was supposed to open, everything was all set and was going to be opened
                    on, as I recall, May 9. A very significant group of people were coming from the
                    United States, fascinated by this rare opportunity to go to Siberia. Frank
                    Shakespeare himself was coming; William F. Buckley, who was then a member of the
                    USIA Advisory Commission at the time was coming. There may have been a few
                    Republican members of the Congress that were planning to come. They were all set
                    to leave to go to Moscow around May 4 or 5 and go on to Novosibirsk and to be
                    there for the opening of this American Education Exhibit.</p>
                <p>Two or three days before they were to leave, I received a call very early in the
                    morning from the Foreign Ministry to tell me that the Exhibit could not under
                    any circumstances open on the intended day because there was a shortage of
                    electricity in Novosibirsk. The exhibit used very little electricity, in fact,
                    and the whole story was completely invented, but there was no room for
                    discussion. The exhibit would not open and it would not be open until some time
                    later when the electrical system would be fixed again. As a consequence, all of
                    the visits by the VIPs coming from Washington had to be canceled.</p>
                <p>It was only several days later that we realized what it was that had happened to
                    cause the cancellation, or the postponement rather, because the exhibit did open
                    a week later. That was the precise time, May 1970, when the incursion into the
                    Parrot's Beak Region in Cambodia had been ordered by President Nixon and had
                    touched off a tremendous storm of reaction and criticism in the Communist world.
                    At a time when the propaganda criticism of the United States over this decision
                    was so intensive the Soviets decided that it would look very bad to have Frank
                    Shakespeare and William F. Buckley and other representatives of the American
                    Administration wandering around, being seen, and reported on in Novosibirsk. It
                    was a kind of a lesson to all of us that the reason that people give for
                    something happening can often be far from the reason. It had nothing to do with
                    the electricity. The faulty generator in Novosibirsk was all in Southeast
                    Asia.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>In those days our problems in Moscow were much affected by the problems and
                    challenges of dealing with the Soviet authorities. The Foreign Ministry's
                    Cultural Section, the Ministry of Higher Education, these organizations' people
                    were extremely hard characters to negotiate with because they all had political
                    agendas of their own to limit access and the ability of American cultural
                    diplomats like us to what was going on in the country or influence attitudes
                    there. We had all kinds of complex negotiations about these national exhibits.
                    They would check the list of all of the books in the library that had come in,
                    for example, and if in one of those books there was critical comment about Karl
                    Marx, say, that book had to be withdrawn, not burned, but not put on the
                    shelf.</p>
                <p>There were politics everywhere, and it was rather exhausting. On the other hand,
                    every time that you gained some fresh insight into what was going on in that
                    society, it gave a special satisfaction that you had learned something that you
                    didn't know before, something that was worth knowing and reporting. I found
                    during those years we did a great deal of cultural-political reporting and
                    received even, I recall, a commendation from the Department of State for the
                    quality of the reporting on the cultural activities that we produced.</p>
                <p>Marlin Remick was my Deputy at the time, a stalwart, first-rate negotiator with
                    the Russians, and very helpful. Our Cultural Affairs Officer was Harry Gilmore,
                    a State Officer on loan to USIA, who was later Ambassador in Armenia and is now
                    the head of the Senior Seminar at the Foreign Service Institute. I recall that
                    relations with the Embassy were very close because USIS, called the Press and
                    Cultural Section, was very much part of the Embassy structure and one was
                    treated on a par with other sections.</p>
                <p>Working at this period in Moscow, when access to the society was so limited and
                    policed so rigorously, U.S. correspondents and the Embassy worked quite close
                    together. Every Friday afternoon, the Ambassador would meet in his office in an
                    unclassified way simply to exchange impressions and ideas with the resident
                    American press corps. We entertained each other a lot and became good friends
                    during those years. For example, the New York Times correspondent at the time
                    was Bernard Gwertzman who is now the foreign editor of the Times. A Time
                    Magazine reporter was Stan Cloud, now an author and senior editor of the Time
                    Magazine.Within the Embassy, most officers were people of very high calibre. The
                    recent Ambassador in China, Stapleton Roy was in the Political Section; Mark
                    Palmer, Thomas Niles, William Farrell, Bill Maynes-these were some of the well
                    known names in the diplomatic world who were all in Moscow at that time. It was
                    an important place to be.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>In 1971, I had expected to spend the third year in Moscow, and was hoping perhaps
                    even to get a fourth. In spring of that year, however, there was a major shift
                    in Personnel decided by the Director, still Frank Shakespeare. As a result, 25
                    senior personnel changes all announced the same day, April Fools Day, 1971. The
                    wireless file announced an enormous shakeup worldwide, and among other things
                    that happened was that Gordon Ewing, who was Public Affairs Officer in Bonn at
                    the time, whose political views apparently did not fit those of Shakespeare, was
                    to be replaced. He felt that it was extremely important to get someone in Bonn
                    who knew Communism and had experience in Eastern Europe. Thus it was that my
                    friendly Economic Counselor colleague, who had seen the wireless file before I
                    did called early to say, “Congratulations. You're PAO in Germany”. I said, “That
                    can't be...” but yet it was.</p>
                <p>That is how we left Moscow after just a little over 2 years in July 1971. One
                    interesting thing that happened towards the end of that tour was a farewell kick
                    in the pants from the KGB. They, of course, had obviously kept a file of all of
                    my doings and where I went, since they had a file on everybody. The fact that I
                    was transferred out by the U.S. Government before they had a chance to use their
                    dossier, which contained all sorts of information about where I had gone and
                    people in the press, theater and the dance world and music, and so on, with whom
                    I had had contact, must have riled them. On May 5, 1971, a month after the
                    announcement of my departure, a weekly newspaper called the Literary Gazette
                    published a full-page denunciation of all of my activities as a would-be
                    subverter of the Soviet intelligentsia, listing many activities and contacts we
                    had had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did get into the country later on, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: I got back into the country without difficulty but not for many years. I
                    next spent '71 to '75 in Bonn as PAO, and never was reassigned back to the
                    Soviet Union. There is one Agency officer who has that distinction. Ray Benson
                    was PAO for 3 or 4 years, came out and went back again...altogether he was in
                    charge of USIS for 7 or 8 years. He gained a very fine reputation for his work
                    there</p>
                <p>As for the Bonn assignment, it presented some real and complex challenges, very
                    different from situation in Moscow. I had had 4 officers and 2 locals in the
                    Soviet Union. In Bonn, at that time, the total American officer contingent was
                    31 or 32 and there were something over 200 German local employees. In a sense
                    USIS had been invented after WWII in Germany and Japan. In both places, the
                    American effort at re-education and engaging many USIA officers in seminal
                    cultural and information roles, meant that a very high percentage of USIA
                    officers served in Germany or Japan, especially in Germany.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>For me, it was a big jump to take over the German program. The four years there
                    were rather heavy going in two areas: politics and post structure. There had
                    been enormous agency and government investments in Germany starting in 1945. We
                    had major America House presence in 1971 in Germany, in West Berlin, Hamburg,
                    Hannover, Cologne, Frankfurt, Stuttgart, Munich, in addition to which we had
                    America Houses which were called German-America Institutes, headed by Americans
                    but with German staff, and a lot of German funding in Nuremberg, Heidelberg,
                    Tuebingen, Freiburg, and Saarbrucken. It was a genuine challenge to manage that
                    large an operation because of all of these presences all over the country, in
                    America Houses, and attached to the Consulates General. There were at least two
                    Americans in the main cities and in Frankfurt there were three.</p>
                <p>It was extremely difficult to run the country from the Bonn office because the
                    staff there was so small. We were perhaps six or seven people at the start.
                    There was the Country Cultural Affairs Officer, Michael Weyl, the Country
                    Information Officer, Victor Olason, and only a few others. It seemed to me and
                    to European Area Director Jay Gildner, an activist, energetic officer who had
                    opened the America House in Berlin back in 1959, that in those cities where we
                    had big America Houses, we could profitably move the Branch PAO out of the
                    Consulate General and into our own USIS presence, the America House. Where we
                    had two officers, we reduced the USIS officer presence to one, and we moved
                    positions to Bonn to create a new Program Division there that did programming
                    for the whole country. The effort was to create a coherent program so that the
                    informational messages and the cultural activities had something coherent to do
                    with each other. Until then, each of the big America Houses acted much like an
                    independent fiefdom.</p>
                <p>Strengthening the country post in this way wasn't easy and it created a great
                    deal of difficulty with the Consuls General. Traditionally, the people who
                    headed those big districts, Frankfurt, Munich, Stuttgart, Hamburg, etc., were
                    Class I, that is to say, MC, Minister-Counselor, level officers from the State
                    Department who, under other circumstances, might have been Ambassadors and so
                    they thought of themselves to some extent as Ambassadors. When this
                    reorganization was proposed, it came up against a great deal of opposition from
                    them. I learned one thing in this process that I believe is fundamental to being
                    an effective PAO, and that is how vital it is to get the Ambassador and the DCM
                    on your side and keep them there.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>As this whole process was going forward, I made a special point of making sure
                    that the DCM, Frank Cash, and the Ambassador, Martin Hillenbrand, knew exactly
                    what I was doing and why, so that they would be supportive when blistering
                    telegrams would come in from the Consul General in Munich, for instance, saying,
                    “You can't do this to me! We represent the U.S. in Bavaria!” The shifts resulted
                    in a lot of changes. We reorganized our office space in Bonn to accommodate
                    additional officers. We saved a great deal of money by getting out of the
                    Consulates General because inside them we had been paying very high rents
                    indeed. We had had a Branch PAO, a secretary and two or three locals sitting in
                    the Consulate General in Munich, for example. By putting them into our own
                    America House, which was a very large and comfortable building, we saved
                    ourselves a great deal of money and we used that money to set things up in Bonn.
                    Those four years were full of tensions and questionings and changes. It was
                    altogether the toughest job that I had yet in the Agency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you think was the major addition to economic
                        savings, or the major results of the shift? What did it do for the
                        program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: I think it made the program a great deal stronger because we could now
                    plan programs for the various component elements of the program centrally, in
                    the way that got the best out of the speakers and other resources. We could make
                    sure that the major issues that related to German-American relations were
                    centrally formulated clearly and reflected what one could learn at the Embassy
                    which one couldn't learn at the Consulate General because of the direct line
                    that Bonn had back to Washington.</p>
                <p>In making these changes, we made a number of mistakes. We believed that the
                    creation of an open, large Area Office for USIS in the Bonn Embassy was a good
                    idea. It turned out to be a bad idea. It didn't take into account traditional
                    ways the German staff had worked and it wasn't very well executed. Originally,
                    when we knocked down a number of walls and planned to make partitions, the
                    designer whom we hired, an American, came up with an idea of suspending
                    materials very much like mattresses from the ceiling, which proved to be a
                    perfectly rotten idea. We left the mattresses suspended from the ceiling, for
                    about two days, saw it didn't work at all, and pulled them all down, disposed of
                    them, and did more traditional partitioning instead. I understand that since
                    then, some of those offices that had partitioning walls have been rebuilt
                    because, as you know, succeeding PAOs often see things quite differently.</p>
                <p>The politics were very important at the time because this was the early '70s when
                    the German Government was developing a new set of political initiatives towards
                    Eastern Europe, and particularly towards East Germany. It was very important
                    that we know what was going on and that American perspectives were clearly heard
                    and published in the country. We had a large political and cultural AMPART
                    program of speakers in the America Houses and in the German-American
                    Institutes.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>One of the things about those years that particularly come to mind is that,
                    because Germany had been such a large program for so long, a lot of people back
                    in Washington, at State and in USIA, felt it had to be cut, that there had to be
                    a way to reduce our presences there. During the four years I was in there, from
                    the middle of '71 until the middle of '75, we had a double grand slam of
                    inspections generated in part by this belief. . We had two full-scale Agency
                    inspections, two full-scale State inspections, two Inspector General visits, and
                    two inspections as I recall by the OPM (Office of Personnel Management). It was
                    a constant period of people coming in and pulling things out of the ground to
                    see if they were growing and working. I still remember the Agency inspection
                    team with Gordon Winkler on it. The evening he arrived and came around for a
                    drink at my place, the first words that came out of his mouth were, “OK, Russ.
                    Which post do we close?” He had come to decide: This has got to go; that has got
                    to go.</p>
                <p>There were serious questions raised by a lot of people back in Washington about
                    these proposed cuts, and I was very glad to have an extremely effective and
                    supportive Area Director at that time. But there was a fair amount of blood
                    spilled, a lot of questioning about the whole approach. I think that out of it
                    came a much stronger program. Many of the locations that we then had, for
                    example, had fixed seats which meant very inflexible seating, to say the least.
                    Thus, if you had a small group of 25 or 30 having a political discussion, all
                    you could do was have your audience sitting in the first two rows of an
                    amphitheater that held 250 seats. We took all the seats out of the America House
                    in Cologne and others, for example, and created for better program space. Among
                    other things, the libraries were all color-coded by specific thematic areas and
                    there were other major changes during those whole four years. It was a period of
                    great Sturm und Drang.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did these changes then survive into succeeding years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: Many of them did; all of them not. Within a few years, the five German-
                    American Institutes lost their American officers and locally hired American
                    expatriates were brought in. But the fact that we created one national program,
                    the fact that libraries became up-to-date resource centers, that informational
                    and cultural programs were far better integrated...I think that a good deal more
                    remained than was put back into old ways. It certainly had the effect of shaking
                    things up and getting everybody to ask questions about what the best way of
                    doing things was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you think were the special benefits of that
                        change?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>RUSSELL: I think that we had a great deal of more unified approach, a better
                    focus on the issues that were most important to Germany and the United States.
                    We looked at our posts as a single USIS rather than as individual entities with
                    separate local perspectives, and there was a strong spell-out of policy issues
                    and of the problems that needed to be addressed in the bilateral relationship
                    that we sent from Bonn that had never been there before. And we built up the
                    country post by bringing FSOs in from the individual posts to Bonn-for example,
                    George Henry, a Branch PAO in Hamburg, was brought down to be head of the
                    Program Division in Bonn, and his younger colleague, Tom O'Connor, who was head
                    of the America House became Branch PAO and the head of the America House at the
                    same time. So those years were full of changes and challenges. I was glad,
                    frankly, after two very intensive years in the Soviet Union and four years in
                    Bonn to come back in 1975 to Washington.</p>
                <p>I had a year off, as one of the three Agency officers in the State Department's
                    Senior Seminar. The other two were Jay Gildner, the West European Area Director,
                    and Carl, a Latin-America hand. Altogether, it was a good thing, a real break,
                    and an excellent chance to get acquainted with this country. In those days one
                    of the benefits of being in the senior seminar, which started in August and
                    ended in June, was that in the springtime you could do a personal project of
                    your own choosing, and there were funds available for overseas travel. At that
                    time, I had never been to the Far East and I had never been to India or to the
                    Near East. The theme that I came up with, wondering how I might tie these areas
                    together, was to do a Senior Seminar thesis or report, on the impact of the Yom
                    Kippur War on Japan, which was very heavily, and still is, dependent on the Near
                    East petroleum supplies.</p>
                <p>It was a kind of wild idea because it meant going to Japan for almost two weeks,
                    interviewing people at the Ministry for International Trade and Industry (MITI),
                    the American Embassy; and elsewhere. I went to the Saudi Arabian Embassy and had
                    a long talk with the Ambassador in Tokyo and found out what the impact had been,
                    and then flew from Tokyo to Saudi Arabia with a stop in India. An interesting
                    sideline to the round-the-world travel in that period was that the United States
                    had built such an enormous stock of surplus rupees in India that if you went
                    around the world, you had to stop for a day in India so your tickets could be
                    paid for in rupees. So, when I left Tokyo, I stopped in India, arrived at 4 a.m.
                    in the morning and left at 3 a.m. the next morning. Never went to sleep and felt
                    the full exposure to what you can see in 23 hours in Delhi, then flew on to
                    Karachi and to Dhahran and spent 11 days in Saudi Arabia, 3 days in Kuwait.</p>
                <p>I spent them interviewing those who were involved in the whole process of buying
                    and shipping and managing the transfer of Middle East petroleum to Japan. Next,
                    I wound up with 3 or 4 days in Paris at the International Energy Agency; then
                    came back and had a month to write the report. It was a lot of fun and a nice
                    stretch. In the Senior Seminar period, there is still a possibility for
                    individual research like this, but I hear that the opportunities are
                    considerably less than what it used to be.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the dates that you were in the senior seminar
                        program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: August 1975 until the end of May or early part of June 1976. In 1976, I
                    moved to what was then called IMV, which was the Information Agency...(”I” stood
                    for information, “M” for motion pictures, and “V” for television). IMV at that
                    time was the service providing the television and motion pictures for USIS. A
                    political appointee named Robert Scott was the Director of the Service. I served
                    as his Deputy for 8 or 9 months and then in the spring of 1977—he had been a
                    holdover from the old Republican Administration—John Reinhardt, who was the
                    Director of the Agency from '77 on, decided that it was time Bob Scott to leave.
                    He made me the head of IMV, as Assistant Director for Motion Pictures and
                    Television, which was the job that I held until the middle of 1978. So, for
                    perhaps 15 months, I was in charge of IMV. That period was very interesting
                    because television was really coming up very, very rapidly. It had begun to rise
                    but the number of films that the Agency made was very surprisingly limited, and
                    the films that they made were films that could be used for television. We did a
                    number of things in-house, but we also brought in outside contractors to do
                    specific jobs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These films that were made... Were they documentaries
                        or...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: They were not documentaries in the traditional sense. At that time, the
                    service had already moved in the direction of doing series, so that the PAO in
                    Kenya, for example, could say to Kenya Television, “I have this terrific
                    thirteen part series which would give you a whole season.” Several of us came up
                    with this idea of a series of programs called Century III, pegged to the
                    beginning of the third century of the United States, since 1976 was the year of
                    the 200th anniversary of the Declaration of Independence.</p>
                <p>We had a very interesting time developing the policy approach to doing films
                    about atomic power, education, agriculture, in each one looking at where the
                    United States had been and where it was going, what the new trends were in each
                    field. We made 13 half-hour films in the series called “Century III” and
                    launched a series of films called “Reflections”. The idea there was to identify
                    Americans of great distinction in their fields, in the autumn years of their
                    lives and to do in-depth documentaries about their work.</p>
                <p>The center piece was each one's own reflections about their lives, and so the
                    series was called “Reflections.” Margaret Mead, with whom we did an intensive
                    interview about her life, was the most distinguished woman anthropologist of the
                    century. We also did a program on Leonard Bernstein and his work. These were
                    hour-long documentary films of a very special nature. They were a lot like the
                    contemporary program called, “Biography”, on the Arts and Entertainment Network.
                    They were all Americans; they were all alive; and they could look back on their
                    careers and judge what they had achieved.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>The Director of the Agency at that time, John Reinhardt, did not give very strong
                    support to television. He was much more interested in the exchanges field. I
                    found myself fighting for budget and fighting to keep things alive. One thing we
                    did that was worth particular mentioning was that for the first time in January
                    1977, USIA did a special program about the new Administration. Interviews with
                    President Carter, with Zbigniew Brzezinski, Hamilton Jordan, 8 or 10 key people
                    in the White House, all taped at the White House. We set up these interviews in
                    the basement and recorded them, using an American journalist named Edward P.
                    Morgan as the interviewer.</p>
                <p>Somewhat later, President Carter made his first trip abroad to Brazil, Nigeria,
                    India, and others—to five countries that were not Germany, Japan, Israel, not
                    the places he would automatically be expected to go first. At the White House
                    again, we did messages from President Carter to television audiences in these
                    five countries for airing in advance of his visit. I still have the teleprompter
                    text of what President Carter said to the people of Brazil.I could not then
                    foresee that Brazil would soon figure in my personal and professional life. Lyle
                    Copmann, a very fine USIA officer who was PAO in Brazil, died suddenly in early
                    1978 of a heart attack. For some reason it was very difficult and proved
                    impossible for Director Reinhardt at that time to find the right person to
                    replace him among our colleagues who were Latin America hands. Various people
                    said they couldn't learn Portuguese or they were tired. For whatever reasons the
                    logical people who should have taken the Brazil program all declined one way or
                    the other.</p>
                <p>Thereupon John Reinhardt decided in the spring of '78 that the next PAO in Brazil
                    was going to be yours truly, and he announced that to me at some time like April
                    or May. I said, “Well, John, I have just been running television now for more
                    than a year. I like it here. My daughter is a junior in high school and it's not
                    the time for us to go abroad again.” Director Reinhardt had very strong views
                    about assignments, and he was particularly eager to show that despite the fact
                    that he was the only Agency Director who had been an Agency officer, that he was
                    going to be tougher...so tough on personnel matters that no one could accuse him
                    of being soft on old friends. Several people whom he wanted to assign to various
                    posts abroad really had very strong reasons for not wanting to go at that time,
                    and at least two outstanding Agency officers resigned from the Agency rather
                    than accept the assignment that was being insisted upon by the Director. I said
                    I would rather not go to Brazil at this time. I didn't know any Portuguese; I
                    only had a little bit of college Spanish. He was very insistent, and in June he
                    said, “I insist that you be our...that you take over the Brazil program.” So I
                    did...</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>My family thought seriously at the time about perhaps remaining here in
                    Washington. We had bought a larger house in '73, and when we came back from Bonn
                    in '75, we had fixed it up to the point where we were quite satisfied. We had
                    been living in it for a while and were not ready to go abroad again after just
                    three years here. It was the call of duty, though, and the challenge of a whole
                    new part of the world. Finally, I was very glad that my family decided that they
                    would indeed come with me to Brasilia. Our older boy had already gone to college
                    but our daughter spent her last year of high school at a school in Brasilia, and
                    our younger boy went through four years of high school in Brasilia. It was quite
                    a good school, one-third Americans, one-third Brazilians and one-third of
                    various other nationalities, and it was a good experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My children all went to high school in the American School
                        in Japan, except for our final year in Tokyo when the U.S. Government
                        required that the children attend the U.S. Army School.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: Living in Brasilia at that time was not much fun. It had been in
                    existence at that time for 18 years, but it hadn't worked out terribly well as a
                    city, being so far away from the centers of activity and commerce. They even
                    used to say that the only three categories of people that you met in Brasilia
                    were diplomats, journalists and Congressmen. No artists, no poets, no
                    businessmen. It was a rather artificial kind of place. However, in professional
                    terms, the assignment was a very interesting one. We still had at that time a
                    $10 million program in Brazil, and a very large staff. We had a publishing staff
                    in Rio of 25 Brazilians; we had 4 Americans in Sao Paulo, 4 in Rio, and we had
                    USIS posts in the 3 large cities, that is to say, Brasilia, which was not a
                    large city but the capital; Rio and Sao Paulo, and in 4 other cities as well. We
                    had USIS posts from south to north in Porto Alegre near the Uruguayan border; in
                    Salvador de Bahia, on the coast north of Rio, in Belo Horizonte, the capital of
                    Minas Gerais, an important wealthy province in the central part of the country,
                    and up on the northeast coast in Recife. And there were Americans and locals in
                    all seven posts.</p>
                <p>We arrived there in October 1978, and stayed the full four-year tour until the
                    middle of 1982. Some of the problems that existed in the German program obtained
                    in Brazil too. A lot of branches and the challenges of maintaining a central
                    focus and a centrally run program. The problem was the great distances. West
                    Germany is only as big as Oregon but Brazil is bigger than the United States
                    without Alaska. I found that there was a very real need to bring the staff that
                    were so widely scattered together to get a better sense of itself.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>Soon after I arrived, I started a magazine, a monthly sort of a newsletter, for
                    USIS only. This was the time we were called USICA during those four years, and
                    we called this “Communicando” with ICA capitalized in the middle. The Brazilians
                    are garrulous, outgoing , convivial people, and there were all kinds of stories
                    about individual families and all the birthdays of everybody in the 8 posts,
                    crossword puzzles and jokes, and accounts of successful programs. It was a lot
                    of fun to do. One of the locals in Brasilia was the editor of it. I wrote
                    something for it every month. It was a good thing to do and when we left, one of
                    the best mementos we came away with was that the staff had all the copies of
                    “Communicando” bound in book form. I still have it and still admire it. There
                    are cartoons and drawings and all kinds of lively stuff that helped hold the
                    post together. But as usual, your successors can come in and undo some of your
                    best ideas. Within a month after I left and my successor came, he decided it was
                    “too labor-intensive, too much time was spent. We don't need it.” So he closed
                    it down.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your particular goals and results at that time?
                        What were your major efforts in getting the program started?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: The country had been under military dictatorship for more than a decade
                    when we arrived. Since 1964, there had been a series of generals running the
                    country, and there was still a general named Figueredo in charge of the country.
                    He was somewhat less of an autocrat and wanted very much to return things to
                    democracy and worked fairly steadily towards it. One of our principal problems
                    as USIS was to help encourage that, to project to Brazilians a real sense of how
                    pluralistic democracy works, and keep their sense of the need to support it
                    alive. It was less adventurous when I was PAO than it had been in earlier times.
                    John Mowinckel whom I mentioned earlier, had been PAO in the late '60s-early
                    '70s and he took a lot of chances with dissidents, maintained contacts with
                    people who were on the political outs, and took a lot of chances. He was still
                    based in Rio during his tour.</p>
                <p>The problem of organizing our program in such a way that it was run centrally
                    from the capital was similar to the situation in the German program, as I
                    mentioned. We found that running effective programs required that we develop a
                    very intense network of communication. We made a great deal of use at that time
                    of the telex, in the same way that E-mail is now the communication means of
                    choice of most posts. We sent from the capital by telex an overview of what was
                    happening throughout the country in a given week. This went to all of the Branch
                    posts early in the week and they fed back to us what was going on at their
                    posts. It often worked out that Americans who were in the country as Fulbright
                    professors or as visitors for some other reason, by tightening the connection
                    among the eight posts., could be programmed elsewhere in the country. For
                    example, the novelist, E.L. Doctorow was in Rio to present a new book of his.
                    When we knew he was there, we were able to arrange for him to come up also to
                    the Brazilian capital and perhaps to go to Sao Paulo as well, for a lecture
                    series.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>Those, I think, were among the principal goals, pulling the 8 posts together so
                    that they cohered. Previously there had been little such cohesion. The PAO in
                    Recife was perfectly happy to do things on his own and had hardly any reporting
                    obligations back to Brasilia. The way I set it up, the Deputy PAO was the
                    supervisor of the branches; I was the supervisor of the Deputy, the CAO and the
                    IO and the Exec. In this way the Deputy PAO was a clearing point of what was
                    going on, and he visited all of the branches at least twice a year. He saw what
                    kind of programs were going on, so that the Branch PAOs had a sense that they
                    were really working in a common cause, that they weren't just doing what they
                    felt like doing. Some of the Branch PAOs in Brazil had distinctly weak officers.
                    They didn't last a long time. There was a very weak officer in Porto Alegre who,
                    after a year of non-performance, was eased out. At least once a year, we had a
                    PAO conference where everybody came together. We didn't do it in the capital
                    every year. We did in Brasilia one year, and in Rio, one year, then in Brasilia
                    and then in Sao Paulo. It was extremely important for the PAO of Recife, for
                    example, who otherwise would never even see Sao Paulo, to gain a sense of the
                    country's major city.</p>
                <p>Life in Brazil was a distinct change from Germany, our previous post. As strictly
                    protocol-conscious as the Germans were, they were always on time. If they said
                    they would come, they would come. Brazilians would say they would come, and
                    either not come at all or come an hour late, or come themselves and their wives
                    and come with their four cousins who were visiting them. We learned to be very
                    flexible, and we learned also to enjoy and to give noisy parties. The Brazilians
                    like a special kind of meal that they served called feijoada. We learned how to
                    do that, how to prepare and enjoy it.</p>
                <p>I had hoped to go to London from Brasilia and had put in a bid for it. Someone
                    else had put in a bid earlier and had gotten a prior commitment from the
                    Director that if he went to a post where he absolutely didn't want to go, he
                    could go to London thereafter. So we did not go to London, and we did indeed,
                    instead, go to Spain for 3 years and ran the program there from '82 to '85. Here
                    again, it was a question of having a crash course in the language as we had had
                    to do for Portuguese. Spanish was easier to learn because I knew Portuguese very
                    thoroughly after the four years. I remember scoring 4+ in Portuguese and then
                    immediately proceeded to forget it. When you plunge into a new thing and are
                    concentrating all day, every day on learning Spanish, the similar language
                    begins to fade. After learning Spanish, I ran into the man who had tested me in
                    Portuguese 6 weeks before, and I was barely able to say hello. Very
                    embarrassing.</p>
                <p>The tour in Spain began at a time when Spain had been rid of the Franco
                    dictatorship only 7 years, and various forms of democracy were taking shape. It
                    was a very interesting time to be there. The whole society, from '36/'37 when
                    Franco won the civil war until '75, had been in effect a closed autocratic
                    dictatorship. A lot less severe than the Soviet Union or Nazi Germany, but one
                    nevertheless.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>We had a very lively program in Spain. A lot was going on. A principal effort
                    there was to get a really effective cultural center in place. We had a small
                    library out of the way, dark, and fairly miserable when I got there. One of the
                    early things I set my sights on achieving was to create a really state-of-the
                    art cultural center. It took about almost two years, but we did do it and it has
                    been extremely active and successful ever since. Right downtown, right around
                    the corner from the Parliament, we had set it up so as to be a major source of
                    information about legislation, about legislative procedures, about judicial
                    activities in this country. It was a really very political move that the
                    Cultural Center was opened in downtown Madrid.</p>
                <p>As always, in Agency matters, it's terribly important that we know what is going
                    on back in Washington and that funding is sought when timing is right. We were
                    able to get, I recall, in the German program $280,000 for a major renovation of
                    the America House in Hamburg on the last day before the fiscal year ended,
                    because last-minute funds became available and we had already an approved plan
                    in place to spend it.</p>
                <p>When I got to Madrid, there was an operation in Barcelona, a Branch PAO office in
                    Barcelona, rather small and not extremely active. There was nothing in the south
                    and there was nothing in the north, and we were able to open branches, one in
                    Seville and one in Bilbao, during my time there. They were headed by foreign
                    nationals, and did very good work in public affairs outreach. The exchange
                    program was extremely important. When I arrived, the level of funding that we
                    had for IVs, the International Visitors program in Spain, was only enough to
                    send 18 a year, and we felt a need to persuade Washington that that was not
                    nearly enough. We needed, given the fact that Spain had had this long, long
                    period of authoritarian rule and was now building a democracy and new parties,
                    to have a substantial number of IVs. We managed to increase the IV budget during
                    the first year I was there from 18 to 55, and we sent many politicians,
                    journalists, and others from Spain for the kind of intensive exposure in the
                    United States on the IV program. Fulbright was also very important, and the
                    Fulbright Commission became a vigorous, very well-funded bilateral effort. There
                    were as many Americans as were the Spaniards on it. There were funds for
                    Fulbright as part of the military bases deal with Spain.An unusual law in Spain
                    requires banks to reserve some 5% of their profits for cultural affairs. We were
                    able to make a lot of use of those cultural centers attached to banks as places
                    where we could have performing arts, poetry readings, concerts by U.S. artists.
                    At the same time, we persuaded a number of banks to contribute to the Fulbright
                    fund. The wealthy Banco de Bilbao, regularly every year, gave a million dollars
                    in support of the Fulbright program. The total exchanges budget between the
                    United States and the Spanish Government and private Spanish sources, as I
                    recall, was between $10 and $12 million a year. And we helped it grow and it was
                    very important because it brought in American teachers into Spain, and it got
                    Spanish academics out to this country. I think that the USIS effort in Spain
                    during the early '80s was one of the really important contributory elements to
                    the anchoring of democracy in Spain.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>We had planned to stay there until '86. In December of '84, however, I saw that
                    China was going to open up, and my wife and I decided that was something that we
                    really would be very excited to do. So I applied for the PAO job in China in
                    January of 1985. There was some back and forth, because I had had no Asian
                    experience except the senior seminar trip. I had to agree to spend two years to
                    learn Chinese before going, but eventually, the Area Director at that time,
                    Jodie Lewinsohn, said “China is important and here is a guy who has run Brazil
                    and Germany, and who is crazy enough to say he will learn Chinese. Let's go for
                    it.” So, we came back here in the spring of '85, after three years in Spain,
                    spent a year studying Chinese here, a year studying Chinese in Taiwan, and I
                    became PAO to Beijing in the summer of '87, then spent almost four years—that
                    was my last post overseas—as PAO in Beijing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find Beijing at that time? Was it still pretty
                        closed, or...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: It was closed, but it was open in a lot of interesting ways.There was
                    always in existence a Fulbright program under which the Chinese accepted 25
                    American professors to teach in their universities. Also, there were a lot of
                    academic interchanges between China and the United States. The Chinese had at
                    that time about 20,000 students studying here. Unlike the Soviet Union, the
                    Chinese had always felt that they gained more for letting their young people
                    study here. After the end of the Cultural Revolution in the mid-'60s, there was
                    a big explosion in travel abroad by Chinese students. The Chinese diaspora is
                    very important, you know. If you're Chinese living in San Francisco and your
                    grandnephew is a bright kid of 18 or 19 who wants to come to study in
                    California, you come up with the money and he can get an exit visa, and can go
                    abroad to study. The academic side of things was quite important.</p>
                <p>The notion of being able to have real outreach in China was steadily growing.
                    Until the crackdown in June 1989, the Chinese Government had been more and more
                    open to expanding relationships with the United States. It was quite surprising.
                    The Chinese Academy of Social Sciences, for example, invited me to give a series
                    of talks about the American elections which were coming in the fall of 1988. It
                    looked as if we were going to be able to open cultural centers, and sure enough,
                    we were able to open the first one in Guangzhou (Canton) in the south, about a
                    year after I arrived. I made several trips down there to find and negotiate for
                    a location, because it seemed to us exceedingly important in China that there be
                    access in the major cities to American books and ideas, films and television,
                    and speakers, and so on. During the time that I was there, we opened up a
                    cultural center in Guangzhou and one in Shanghai for the first time, and we were
                    set for the opening in Beijing about 6 months after I left.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>The China years were very sharply marked by the events at Tiananmen Square
                    because many hopeful things fell apart in its wake. The day before the students
                    started marching, the Ambassador had signed the agreement to bring the Peace
                    Corps to China, on April 14, 1989, and the students started marching on April
                    15. For the next 6 weeks, it got bigger and bigger by the day. I used to go most
                    days, afternoon or evening, down to the Square to talk and to listen and to find
                    out what was happening.</p>
                <p>In the middle of May took place the most interesting political time in my career,
                    because Gorbachev came to make party peace with the Chinese on May 15. He was in
                    meetings with the Chinese at the same time that the demonstrations and the
                    excitement grew bigger and louder and louder and bigger. You had this double
                    story going on at the same time, and Gorbachev had brought with him a tremendous
                    journalist corps. Hundreds of people came with him and once they were there,
                    they didn't leave because of the unfolding story of pro-democracy
                    demonstrations. We were very, very much involved in that, in organizing
                    briefings for journalists when the crackdown came. There was a period of 4 or 5
                    days when the Ambassador and I were there, practically the whole time, exposed
                    to the press, dealing with the students, getting Americans out of the country,
                    arranging for the families to leave. It was a very intense time.</p>
                <p>Once that had passed, in the fall of '89 and in the fall of '90, I had two very
                    interesting experiences because I could spend more time outside China because so
                    many of our programs had stopped short or cut back. There was no Fulbright
                    program, for example, for a whole year. My wife and I made a very interesting
                    foray into Mongolia in the fall of 1989. We went for a week by train from
                    Beijing. 42 hours. It was a marvelous trip. I had set the task of finding out
                    what a future USIS in Mongolia would look like. I did an analysis of the
                    university, the cultural scene, the media. I found it interesting and it was
                    helpful when shortly thereafter democracy did come to Mongolia and so did a U.S.
                    Embassy and a USIS. We have PAO there now who is very active. Back then, it was
                    a great fun to be the first officer to go and talk to people to find out what
                    opportunities there would be for us when it did open.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find in Mongolia considerably greater openness
                        than there was in China itself?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: Oh, yes! It was already changing rapidly and in December of that year,
                    for reasons that I don't recall exactly now, there was a kind of backing away
                    from power on the part of the communist party that had been in charge. Great
                    pressure was brought up for changes and they happened very rapidly. The
                    following fall, 1990, we made a similar trip to Tibet to assess the prospects
                    for USIS activities there. Those two fall trips were extremely interesting for
                    both of us, especially since my wife and I could make them together.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any reaction from the Chinese on your Tibet
                        effort?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>RUSSELL: They were very careful but not overtly suspicious. We had to get
                    clearances from fairly high up, I assume, and I had to be careful about who I
                    talked to. As a result of it, the trip we were able to set things up so that we
                    were from time to time able to send speakers and others into Tibet. In China, at
                    the time that I was there, we had 4 branch posts, Chengdu in the far west on the
                    way to Tibet, Guangzhou or Canton in the south, Shanghai on the eastern coast,
                    and Shenyang (which used to be called Mukden when we were kids) up in Manchuria.
                    We had Americans in charge in all four places.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I went to Mukden when young, in 1938.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: It's still an interesting place. I am sorry I never got farther north. I
                    made 3 or 4 trips to Shenyang, but I didn't get up closer to the border. In any
                    case, early in 1991, I had an urgent call from Gene Kopp. My tour was going to
                    end that summer, and he said that he wanted me very much to come back and take
                    over as Counselor of the Agency. Mike Pistor, at that time, had been on the job
                    for 2 years, and was in line for an Ambassadorial post in Africa. He had been
                    offered and he wanted to take on Malawi. So we left China a little early,
                    probably 3 months in advance, in March of 1991, and I came back and took over
                    as...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the Ambassador in China?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>M..R.Very interesting and contrasting individuals. The first two years it was
                    Winston Lord and the second 2 years it was James Lilley. In any case back in
                    Washington, the situation as Counselor was a complex one because Henry Catto had
                    only recently come on board, and there had been a lot of tension between the
                    previous Director, Bruce Gelb, and Deputy Director Kopp. The two plus years that
                    I spent in the Counselor's office were years full of activities. None of the
                    issues that have troubled the Agency since then about its continued existence or
                    its funding had yet arisen. There was a great deal of interest in opening up
                    USIA in Eastern Europe and in the former Soviet Union. I made several trips for
                    Director Catto in 1992, and again in '93. This was the first time I was back to
                    Russia and other parts in all those years. I did several of the initial
                    negotiations about opening American cultural centers in St Petersburg, in
                    Kazakhstan and in Kiev.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>Working with Gene Kopp and Henry Catto was a great joy. Both of them were
                    excellent leaders, very different in their styles but very committed to the
                    Agency and its role, very much aware of the importance, the vital roles played
                    by the foreign service, enjoying very close and cordial relations with the White
                    House and with the Department of State. When Henry Catto was sworn in as
                    Director of the Agency in May of 1991, he was sworn in by the President Bush
                    personally...actually, I am wrong. President Bush was present at the swearing
                    in; he was sworn in by the Supreme Court Justice Kennedy. Those were extremely
                    energetic and interesting years.I found that the political leadership of the
                    Agency at that time, Paula Dobriansky at the head of the P-Bureau, and Bill
                    Glade heading the E-Bureau...I am not sure...I draw a blank about who was the
                    head of VOA at the time... In any case, there was a high degree of cohesion
                    between the political leadership of the Agency and its career elements. I look
                    back on that period as a very positive time. We had strong Area Directors; there
                    was a clear sense that the Counselor was the senior career officer, and what he
                    had to say was listened to and he could affect funding decisions in a meaningful
                    way among the Areas. It was probably fairly sure that within a few months after
                    Henry Catto's departure, after the election of 1992, that the times would change
                    and that the new Director and the new Deputy Director would want their own
                    Counselor. So I was fairly prepared, in the spring of 1993, for a change and
                    felt very fortunate that the ideal final assignment was in sight.</p>
                <p>I applied for and got the diplomatic resident posting at the Fletcher School. I
                    left Washington and the Agency in June of 1993, just before I turned 64,
                    spending the last year teaching up at the Fletcher School and finished teaching
                    in May of 1994, turned 65 on May 28, 1994, retired on May 31, with the feeling
                    that those 33 plus years that I had spent with the Agency had been extremely
                    gratifying and nearly always productive. It was not always easy, and my wife,
                    Stella in particular, deserves tremendous credit for putting up with 25 or 30
                    moves during all those years, and the great demands that were placed on her
                    throughout, but especially during the early part of our tenure up until 1975 or
                    so. The funds available for representation were very limited then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, they were...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>RUSSELL: ...and during the 4 years that I was in Bonn, I was regularly out of
                    pocket, a thousand or more dollars a year. Then something happened in the late
                    '70s and it became a good deal easier, but it still meant that the burden on the
                    wife...the burden was always a serious one, a very constant one: the constant
                    moves, the readjustments and often having to put together a dinner for 20 people
                    on short notice. I look on my own time overall in the Agency as one where I was
                    fortunate in the postings that I got. I was fortunate in the people that I
                    worked with and for, I was fortunate that things had such a great variety of
                    different cultural and linguistic and political environments to work in. I have
                    nothing but appreciation for the assignments. Some of them I was not ready for—I
                    didn't want to go to Brazil in 1978 at all, for example, but I think I made,
                    ultimately, the right decision by saying, “Yes, I would go” but I don't believe
                    the series of challenges...met and successfully met...that I could possibly have
                    worked it all if I haven't had Stella's support.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had a very wide spread of experiences, probably wider
                        than almost anybody else that I know of.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: The thing I miss about my Agency experience is that I was never an Area
                    Director.</p>
                <p>It was just that an interesting post kept coming along. So I have no real
                    regrets...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You probably stirred more things up in the respective
                        posts to which you went than you would have as an Area Director.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: Maybe. I will say that I have always felt more comfortable in USIA than
                    I think I would have felt with the Department of State.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think you probably were much freer and happier in USIA
                        than you would have been going into the State Department.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: That probably wraps it up, I think. I feel a lot of dismay over the
                    current trends within the Agency because I still really believe that the synergy
                    of information, press and education, exchange, and cultural exchange create
                    something that is very powerful that can have real influence over the years.
                    Anything that we are able to do to keep that function integral is something that
                    I think very much worth striving for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think so too, and I am very worried about it because I
                        think what's going to or what it might happen is distressing. Yesterday, I
                        went to the Foreign Service Day. A speaker...a very young fellow...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>RUSSELL: Pat Kennedy? Pat Kennedy is the Acting Head of Management. He is
                    supposed to pull this together... Or Nicholas Burns?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A young fellow with a moustache.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUSSELL: That would be Nicholas Burns...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anyway, he started talking about how glad they are going
                        to be to get USIA back in to State and are probably going to put the
                        Information side into such and such Bureau, and put another part into the
                        Cultural Bureau. I finally got up and said, “I hope that when USIA is
                        brought back, you will not separate them because it is necessary to keep
                        these units together. USIA has spent over 40 years melding these sections
                        together, getting them to operate as a complete entity. The minute you break
                        them apart and put them into different units, you are going to diminish the
                        impact that they have, and damage the contribution that they can make.” But
                        clearly, in Burns' thinking, they will be splitting them in at least three
                        ways.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
