<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001223">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with George S. Vest </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR GEORGE S. VEST</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: July 6, 1990</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: George, could you give a little idea of your background
                        prior to entering the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Very simply, my father was an Episcopal minister in Virginia, rural
                    Virginia primarily. I grew up in an assortment of small towns in Virginia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were born when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Born in 1918. My father moved from Berryville, Virginia in the late 1920s
                    to become the rector of Emmanuel Church in Alexandria. He came to Alexandria
                    simply so that we could go to schools—my sister and I—that would make it
                    possible for us to have a college education, because rural town schools did not
                    prepare you for that back in the 1930s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Virginia was one of the poorer states.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: And Virginia was one of the poorer states. So we moved to Alexandria, where
                    my sister and I did go to these schools. I went as a day student to a very fine
                    prep school on the outskirts of Alexandria called Episcopal High School, where I
                    had a scholarship which made it possible for me to go through there. I then went
                    to the University of Virginia. Very quickly after the first year, had
                    scholarships and jobs which made it possible to work my way through college,
                    which was not really that difficult in those days because there was the National
                    Youth Administration which gave you jobs and supplemented with other kinds of
                    activities.</p>
                <p>After that I went into World War II, directly from the University of Virginia.
                    First, I was drafted and sent to what had been the Bronx National Guard. This
                    was my first experience with foreign environment. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this is really doing it the hard way.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>VEST: But at the government's insistence I was there. Then after OCS, went
                    overseas to England, North Africa, Italy. Was in Italy throughout World War II
                    until the very end.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you with a division</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I was with corps artillery.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Corps artillery.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: After that, I came back. I had never planned to be in the Foreign Service.
                    It had not been in my mind at all up until I was in the war. In fact, I had
                    planned, more or less, to be a plant pathologist. I thought that's what I wanted
                    to do. Plants fascinated me. Overseas in North Africa and in Italy, I began to
                    see a whole series of other things in life, other problems, other possibilities.
                    So, as soon as I came back, I took the Foreign Service exam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How had you heard about the Foreign Service exam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I have no idea. I do not remember how I heard about it. [Laughter] I only
                    know I knew about it. I did it, like a lot of people. I had absolutely not a
                    penny to my name other than a few war bonds I had been made to buy during the
                    war as punishment for infractions of one kind or another. I went back to the
                    University of Virginia. It was on the speeded-up, 12-month course. Worked on a
                    master's degree in history, which was related to my new interest in
                    international affairs. As, frankly, an alternative if I didn't pass the exam, I
                    would have a master's degree which would help me get a teaching job
                    somewhere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, coming from your background, did you have any
                        concern that this was a moneyed organization—the Foreign Service—and that
                        you really had to have money?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>VEST: No, it's very interesting, and it possibly is the result of having been
                    raised as a preacher's son. Whether or not a person had money never seemed to
                    bother me by the time I at least was grown up. I know. When I told several
                    friends at the University of Virginia, they were astonished and said, “Oh, but
                    you have to be rich to ever go anywhere.” One wonderful old woman, a Mrs.
                    Marshall, whose family were well connected with very wealthy people in
                    Philadelphia whose distant relatives had been ambassadors or in the Foreign
                    Service and whose children were friends of mine and she had been more or less
                    almost an adopted god-parent sort of person. I would visit her from time to
                    time. And Mrs. Marshall warned me. She said, “I don't think you should do this.
                    You can never go anywhere if you don't have money and a private income.” She
                    also knew that I was courting a very wonderful person who had no money as well,
                    and so it meant I was breaking both rules. I had no money and I had no intention
                    of marrying money. And she said, “I don't think you can do it.”</p>
                <p>Well, of course, in the pre-1946 Act period, she was right. I wasn't being
                    pressured in that period—because this was '46, 47—I just had that insouciance
                    that youth has, I suppose. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What the hell?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: That somehow I can do it because others are going to do it. It's the post
                    World War II period; we're all going to do things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And with the GI Bill and all, I mean, the world was sort
                        of opening up to a whole generation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes, because I was going back on the GI Bill.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now, how did one get into the Foreign Service? We're
                        talking about 1946, 47. How did you get in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I did the following. I talked to people who had taken the exam—but they had
                    failed the exam, but they described the exam—and I happened to find two people
                    in graduate school with me there. This was the winter of '46, '47, late '46, who
                    were studying with a special course here in Washington, in Georgetown, Franklin
                    Raudebush. And they would come up and go to cram courses with Franklin Raudebush
                    and then they'd come back and they would show me the kind of things he was
                    making them study. So I studied on my own. It was as simple as that.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>I was taking history. I had a very good background in English from undergraduate
                    years. I did get some separate books and read economics in an effort to be able
                    to deal with that portion of the exam that was so touted at that period. I had
                    studied some Spanish before the war, and I got a dictionary, and as I remember,
                    used to read from time to time in a Puerto Rican newspaper, which I could get
                    through the University of Virginia library, and I read the New York Times and
                    Time Magazine. It sounds very simple. I did it all on my own.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But this is normal. You hit the right key. Was it a three
                        and a half day exam, or for military, was there a shortened one?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It's very vague, Stu, and I'm not that certain. I don't believe it was a
                    three and a half day exam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think there was a sort of a catch up because of the
                        military. I took it in '53 and it was three and a half days, but I think,
                        when things were settling down, prior to that, I think there was a desire to
                        get military people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It was a long exam. It wasn't just a short exam. It was a long exam, is all
                    I remember about it, but I have a feeling that it was all done in one day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It may well have been.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: All day long. And the thing I remember about it was that we did have, I
                    think, a five-point bonus they were prepared to give you if you had served in
                    the war. So I knew that when I went in, I would get a five-point bonus. This
                    exam did have all of the major areas I was referring to, including a section on
                    international law, which I tackled truly from the point of common sense, which
                    may be the worst way to consider law. [Laughter] That is the way I took it, in
                    any case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well now, the oral exam. Did you have an oral exam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And how did that go?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>VEST: Oral exam was a very different thing from what we have today. First, you
                    waited some months—and we were certainly in a speeded-up period because, instead
                    of a year and a half to two years, I took that exam, as I recall, in the fall of
                    '46. I graduated, got my master's, and got married in June of '47, and it was
                    midsummer '47, I was offered an appointment. So the process was faster.</p>
                <p>Now, the oral exam. The oral exam, we were told to come to Washington. Maybe
                    elsewhere, they were going to other places. I was in Virginia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think they were pretty much in Washington to control
                        expense.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I was told to come to Washington. There were a number of us there. Most of
                    us, in fact everybody I talked to as we were waiting, was an ex-GI. There were
                    no women and there were no minorities in that group that I saw there. We all,
                    that I talked to, had master's degrees. It was interesting—or were aspirants
                    for—expecting to get—a master's degree. We were told we would have approximately
                    anywhere from a half hour to an hour interview, and at the end of that, we would
                    be told whether we had passed the oral. I, of course, was still studying for my
                    master's.</p>
                <p>The boy who went before me, I still remember, had a master's degree in history
                    from Yale, and he went in and came out. And then there was an interval, and I
                    asked him, “What was it like?” He said, “They asked me everything that I knew
                    nothing about. They asked me nothing about the things I knew something about.”
                    And that was it.</p>
                <p>So I went in, and it was exactly the same. There was a panel, as I remember, I
                    believe of five people. If I'm not mistaken, the center person was someone, I
                    think, a colonel on leave from the Air Force, it's my vague memory. Just as I
                    had been told, they invited you to sit down, and in these smoke- free days, they
                    invited you to be relaxed, have a cigarette if you'd like. I had never smoked in
                    my life. I had tried smoking the night before so I would be able to appear
                    nonchalant. [Laughter] Coughed terribly, and realized that was one area I was
                    going to fail. So I responded to this invitation to kindly sit down and have a
                    smoke. I sort of sharply rapped out, “I don't smoke,” illustrating how ill at
                    ease I was. [Laughter]</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>They proceeded to ask a few questions of one kind or another, and pretty soon
                    went off into areas that really were areas you just did not know. My questions
                    practically all concentrated on national trade and national commerce and what
                    I'd call practical economics. And I was questioned at length about the shoe
                    industry of the United States and ranching and cattle and the leather tanning
                    industries of the United States, and we went through every kind of thing like
                    this. And I was left to decide, “How do you deal with the unknown?” I could see
                    this is what they had chosen to do. They knew my record, and they chose to do
                    this. So it was a constant choice between acknowledging what you didn't know, or
                    attempting to use your common sense to see how far you could go, and this is
                    what it was clearly all about.</p>
                <p>Then there were one or two—still one memorable one which I don't remember the
                    exact detail—but there was a man there from the Department of Labor who looked
                    like Justice Felix Frankfurter. He sat at the left end, and I can still
                    remember. He rapped out a question and said, “Mr. Vest, Justice Oliver Wendell
                    Holmes once said that the continuity of history is not a choice, but a duty.
                    Comment.”</p>
                <p>And I thought to myself, “What in the world? What does it mean?” So I finally
                    said, “I really don't know, unless he was thinking about the DARs.”</p>
                <p>At which the other members laughed, and he said, rather sourly, “Not what he had
                    in mind.” [Laughter] I still don't know what he had in mind.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't either. I was just trying to figure out how I
                        would handle that, and I just don't know.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I do realize when I look back on that one, for example, that along with the
                    other two qualities which I brought to the oral exam, I frankly decided that
                    humor is what you have to use in some hopeless situations, and I obviously did
                    do it.</p>
                <p>I came out of that and waited for about 15 minutes, and then they came out and
                    said, “Okay, you passed the oral exam.” So that was how it was done then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a class when you came in, or were you just sort
                        of an entry replacement?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>VEST: No, there was a class. I came in in that group, it would be about September
                    1947. We were all former GIs. There were 40-some of us, one woman, and a very
                    capable and nice person she was. We had all served in the war. We were a very
                    diverse group of people, but we came from all over the country. The kind of
                    people who would be smoothies from the northeast Ivy League world; to a rancher,
                    whom I can still remember from the far Middle West; a guy who had worked in a
                    factory in Chicago; and a very wealthy man who owned, I gather, hundreds, maybe
                    thousands, of acres down around Arkansas and Texas and so on. We were from all
                    of these backgrounds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So this was not a matter of the eastern establishment
                        reasserting itself?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It was, as far as I was concerned, my class, at least, was the living
                    example of the fact that it was going to be a new Foreign Service. And from the
                    point of view of the senior officers, we were, believe me. We were a new Foreign
                    Service. We were all, in varying ways, inadequately trained by background. We
                    all had the maturing experience of the war, and we had all come to this late in
                    terms of a decision that this is what we wanted to do. We came to it as a
                    result, primarily, of our wartime maturing experiences.</p>
                <p>We had, I don't remember how many weeks, we were in a group. We were headed up
                    and sort of supervised by a very fine senior Foreign Service officer, Mr.
                    Lawrence Taylor, as I remember. It wasn't the A-100 course of today. Once
                    somebody came and gave us an hour's lecture and said, “This is the pouch.”
                    [Chuckles] Another one came for an hour or two and said, “This is consular
                    affairs, and when you have a problem, these are the books you look things up
                    in.” Everything was very, very rapid, and there was no question about the
                    rapidity of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, still probably an offshoot of the military experience
                        where we were all used to getting in and getting on to it. You say, “Invade
                        what country, when?” and get about it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It was one thing we hear an awful lot of stuff about, bonding and teams and
                    so on. It was very interesting. We were not there very long together, and yet we
                    formed a group that have never forgotten each other. Our wives got to know each
                    other, and we have kept up to this day. I was the last of the war group to
                    retire. We had, about a year ago, a reunion, and people came from great
                    distances. We all got together again, so that little first experience still was
                    a bonding experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, your first post was you went to Hamilton, Bermuda.
                        Is that right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from 1947 to '49. I'm going to concentrate
                        more on the latter part of your career, but here was what might seem to be
                        the ideal assignment. In fact, almost too ideal. I know when I came into the
                        Foreign Service, somebody asked me what I'd like to be and I said, “Oh, I'd
                        like to be an ambassador.” But I was thinking underneath, “Consul general of
                        Bermuda really sounds like a nice place to be.” I didn't know anything about
                        it. Was this a positive experience or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Stu, I'd have to say it was—I don't know how to describe it, but I'd have
                    to just talk a little bit about it because it was one of the most important
                    experiences I had in the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>My wife and I had only been married that June. We went there in September to
                    Bermuda. The people were as friendly as could be, and then it's a beautiful
                    place and all the rest. It's the only extremely disagreeable, difficult post
                    I've ever had in my Foreign Service. Now, why? I show my prejudice here. I very
                    much disliked the consul, and I think he deserved my dislike. Very firmly,
                    without going into details, he was a man of another generation, so extraordinary
                    that in our regular Foreign Service world, it could never have happened. This is
                    the case of someone left over during a wartime. And, without going into details,
                    he was very difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you give some illustration of what the problem
                        was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Okay, a couple of illustrations. He was very old school, and, for example,
                    the secretaries were a group of nice, young women. And one day, for example, he
                    came to the door of his office—they were in a pool right there in front of
                    him—and he said to me, “Mr. Vest, I can't think what's happening to the Foreign
                    Service. Look at those young women. There is Olson, dumb Swede.” Miss Olson was
                    sitting there. “Geisweit, dirty German; Jerzack, stupid Pole.” He went right on
                    through, and every one of those young women could hear what he was saying about
                    them. I mean, this is a very oddball. That just illustrates the kind of
                    prejudice that went on inside that man.</p>
                <p>This was still a period when black-white relationships were very sensitive and
                    uncertain in our own country, and certainly very delicate in Bermuda. But his
                    instructions were very clear. Never issue a visa to a black Bermudian without
                    checking it out and getting the proper permission from the white Bermudian who
                    really keeps an eye on him. But I didn't feel I could really live that way.</p>
                <p>There were many, many things like that. This was an oddity of life. His wife was
                    a former fortuneteller, and she would look at the stars in the night and tell
                    him what he was to look out for the next morning. He would come in the morning
                    and call me up and say, “Mr. Vest, I don't want to speak to any dirty foreigners
                    today.” Well, it's hard to be the consul general and not speak to foreigners.
                    [Laughter] It was weird, and the office was just a hot bed of anxiety and
                    hostility.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>The secretaries did not speak to each other. He had managed to have his former
                    secretary made into a vice consul, and he tended to try to run everything
                    through her. He alienated her at some point, and then she was a very fair
                    colleague for me as a new vice consul. He never gave me any instructions. He
                    waited until each time I made a mistake and then he noted it down, and once a
                    month at the beginning of the month, he sent in a confidential report on all of
                    my inadequacies and mistakes. The reason I knew about it was this other vice
                    consul, who had come to like me, quietly showed them to me. So once a month I
                    knew that every mistake I made was being sent to the Department of State.
                    [Chuckles] It was a totally hostile environment, and my wife and I had a
                    challenge. We were not sure to what extent this was really like the Foreign
                    Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you really didn't have much of a chance there. You
                        were fairly isolated to compare people with other people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: We had no basis of comparison. In fact, a couple of senior Foreign Service
                    officers came down and lived with the consul, who had a quarter of a million
                    dollar official residence. They lived in the guest house and they came in to see
                    me. They more or less said you're going to have to learn to do things the way
                    the consul general wants them done, or you can never go ahead in the Foreign
                    Service. Well, I wasn't about to do things the way the consul general wanted
                    them. I hadn't fought World War II to live that way, nor had my wife and I, who
                    had very strong backgrounds. My father was a minister and her father was a
                    former Presbyterian missionary in China who had become the librarian at the
                    University of Virginia and also taught at Princeton. I mean, our parents didn't
                    raise us to give way on certain fundamental principles.</p>
                <p>In the end, the situation exploded, and the director general—my first experience
                    with the director general—one day got off the plane and refused to stay with the
                    consul general, stayed in a hotel, interviewed every single person in the
                    office. And at the end, told the consul general, “You will leave within two
                    months to go to another post.”</p>
                <p>The consul general's unreality was shown in the fact he said, “I've always wanted
                    to be ambassador to New Zealand.” Then the word came, he was sent to be the
                    consul in Gibraltar, with one person working for him. So, obviously, they'd
                    gotten the picture of this man back in Washington, which later I learned from
                    John Burns, a subsequent director general, who told me he had been working on
                    British colonial possessions and they were very well aware that something was
                    wrong, but they didn't know what.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>I was then told I would leave later, and I stayed on for oh, maybe, five months
                    more. And the director general said, “And you were not a positive factor in a
                    very difficult situation”—which I think was quite true—”and you will be sent to
                    a hardship post and we'll see what it is. Normally, we'd select you out, but
                    under the rules, you're entitled to be reviewed and judged by another senior
                    officer.”</p>
                <p>So then my wife and I were sent in '49 to Quito, Ecuador, which we loved.
                    [Chuckles] That was our punishment. But the real thing was, we were terribly
                    fortunate. Our difficult post was our first post. I had the kind of backing from
                    her and we had the kind of background which made us survive it and be quite
                    ready that we were going to live by our standards and what we thought someone
                    should do when they represented our country regardless. And if you couldn't stay
                    in the Foreign Service doing it that way, we'd get out. Well, it was sort of the
                    first time when I was prepared to quit, and periodically in life, you have to be
                    prepared to quit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what about in Quito? This was a positive
                        experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It was a great experience. It was very simple. I worked then for Ambassador
                    Jack Simmons and his wife, Caroline Simmons, two of the most marvelous human
                    beings you could have. They were simply wonderful to us. And I can still
                    remember the two of them came—we invited them to come and have supper in the
                    little house we lived in—and Ambassador Simmons said to me, “George, have you
                    ever looked at your file in Washington? Because when you leave a post, you know,
                    you can see what's been on your file.” And he had just come back from
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>And I said, “No. When I came through Washington, I didn't bother to look in my
                    file.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, you know, you have just about the worst file of any junior
                    officer I've ever known.” Which I knew was no surprise. [Laughter] He was a
                    wonderfully engaging man. He said, “But we are going to do something about
                    that.” [Laughter] He was a great boss. Maury Bernbaum was his deputy, who was a
                    wonderfully kind, thoughtful number two.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Later ambassador to...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Later ambassador in Venezuela.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Venezuela and Ecuador.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>VEST: And Ecuador. And between the Simmons and the Bernbaums, we just had
                    wonderful opportunities. As they did in those days, I worked in the consular
                    section, I worked with the USIA on the side, which was then part of the regular
                    Foreign Service, as did my wife. I worked in the economics section. You know, I
                    just was given every break.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So this was your time to blossom out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: They had been without an administrative officer for almost nine months. So
                    for my first six months I did that, until they got in, finally, an
                    administrative officer. So I had a chance to do everything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You obviously got your second chance, and also the real
                        opportunity to show what you could do. Then you went to Ottawa. This was
                        from 1951 to '54. What were you doing there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: In Ottawa, I really had my break. It certainly was a break to go and work
                    for the Simmons. I had a chance to sort of catch up. In Ottawa, I was the junior
                    boy in the political section. Now, initially there wasn't a whole lot to do. My
                    wife and I enjoyed the team, enjoyed everybody there. In fact, it may be worth
                    just noting how I happened to go to Ottawa, because that's how they can do
                    things in personnel.</p>
                <p>Point of fact, when I was due to leave Quito, I was assigned to go to the
                    Dominican Republic. In other words, there was a rational trend, and they were
                    going to run you through several posts in an area. We spent what little savings
                    we had and bought some tropical clothes in Washington while I was there in an
                    interim for a little course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: S.S. Schwartz?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Well, yes. S.S. Schwartz and anything else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Baltimore, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: We were prepared to go. But I did go into the personnel people, who were
                    not Foreign Service; they were civil service covering the area. And I said, “Now
                    I'm prepared to go, but I think you should know something. And that is that my
                    closest friend in Ecuador was Juan Alfonseca, whose father is a major exile who
                    claims he ought to be the president of the Dominican Republic and probably one
                    of the people most hated by Trujillo. Everybody in Quito knew that the
                    Alfonsecas were our closest friends, practically. So I just want you to know
                    that.”</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>That went like a lead bullet into personnel, and the next thing I knew, I was
                    told I was being sent to Canada. [Laughter] Just one of those, again, quirks of
                    fate we live with. So we took our tropical wardrobe and went to Canada.</p>
                <p>Before Canada, for the first year, I had not done political reporting. I had not
                    done any of that kind of activity. In Ottawa I had, again, good training. I was
                    trained by a wonderful political counselor named Jack Morgan, who just was a
                    superb man, and a great DCM named Don Bliss, who later was ambassador to
                    Ethiopia. Mr. Bliss had come in through the commercial service, so he had a very
                    strong sense of what I'd call the economic side of things, and Jack Morgan was
                    the traditional or what I'd call political purist officer. I was constantly sort
                    of being pushed or invited by one or the other to do things. Couldn't have been
                    a nicer kind of training. They were the best representatives of the old Foreign
                    Service we could have encountered, I don't think I could have found a better
                    pair then they were, the two senior officers.</p>
                <p>They gave me, as a portfolio to follow, what was considered a dead subject at the
                    time. They said, “You follow this and get to know everybody involved in this
                    area.” It was called the St. Lawrence Seaway. And I got to know the engineers,
                    and it was one of those cases where no one thought much was ever going to
                    happen. In the end probably the Canadians would build their own seaway, because
                    they were determined to do so. But it was wonderful fun. I got to know every
                    single person I could. It was a case of you may never be able to do anything in
                    it, but here is a pond. You can paddle it, and I paddled as madly as I
                    could.</p>
                <p>And then Eisenhower got elected, and he passed the Wiley-Dondero Act that would
                    call for a joint American-Canadian St. Lawrence Seaway. And I will never forget
                    the DCM called me in, Mr. Bliss, and said, “Now, George, there are those who
                    would like to take over this activity and feel they should take this activity
                    over now that it is going to be a high-class negotiation, of top concern to
                    everybody. But you have been involved in it and you know all the people in it,
                    so I'm going to leave you responsible for this negotiation.” That was what I
                    would call the real break of all times.</p>
                <p>And that meant that the people down the Bureau of European Affairs knew that I
                    was negotiating it. The people in the Defense Department knew it because the
                    Defense Department was ostensibly in charge of the whole thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Corps of Engineers and all.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Corps of Engineers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like the highway program, all of which had a defense
                        underline.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>VEST: You had the states of Illinois and Michigan and New York and the provinces
                    of Quebec and Ontario, everybody had a hand in it.</p>
                <p>Well, I was left to do that. I began the negotiations and did a good portion of
                    the negotiations. I got to know everybody as a result of it, including Livy
                    Merchant, who was the assistant secretary for European affairs. That was another
                    break.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: George, later you had a great deal of experience with
                        NATO, and, of course, Canada is often forgotten, but it a member of NATO.
                        We're talking about the early '50s. What was our attitude at the embassy and
                        through the State Department, and maybe your attitude, too, towards Canada?
                        The Canadians talk more about how Americans...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Take them for granted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Take them for granted, but how did we look at Canada at
                        that time, would you say?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Let's divide the we. The embassy first.</p>
                <p>The embassy was a very high-spirited, strong morale group, and it took Canada
                    very seriously. Everybody was impressed with what Canada could do or would
                    probably do, and this went all the way through. It wasn't a big embassy. It was
                    a wonderful group. The military were impressed with what the Canadians were
                    doing in the far north and what they were cooperating with our military on. The
                    agriculture attach� thought Canada was one of the greatest things in the world
                    and was going to be one of the breadbaskets of the future. They were building
                    the trans-Canadian pipeline. It doesn't matter what area you were in, for those
                    who worked with them, this was one of the great periods of Canada. I mean, the
                    prime minister was Louis St. Laurent; the foreign minister, external affairs
                    minister, was Mike Pearson; the man in charge of the economy was a great old man
                    named C.D. Howe. These people were tremendous leaders, very important, and they
                    knew everybody in Washington and in New York and in Chicago. It was a very
                    interesting time.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>So, in the work terms and in the embassies—down to their embassy in Washington,
                    and ours up in Ottawa—it was a period of tremendous appreciation. If you went
                    outside that, to some extent to the other areas of the U.S. Government, to
                    elsewhere in the country, there was a general attitude of, well, Canada is a
                    splendid place and the Canadians are splendid people and they're particularly
                    splendid because they're so nearly like us. And there was a considerable
                    atmosphere of taking Canada for granted. Even when the Canadians sat down and
                    said, “We're going to negotiate and have a joint Canadian seaway, and we're
                    going to do it our way. We're not going to expose any of our citizens traveling
                    on that joint Canadian seaway to McCarthyism or anything like that.” They were
                    very forthright and strong on this. But even so, to the Americans at large,
                    there was that attitude.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the Canadians as negotiators? I've talked
                        to somebody who is on our negotiating team—on the last couple of years,
                        we've just had basically a free trade pact with Canada—and said the
                        Canadians were able to play the “You don't understand us, and we're a little
                        country” to a fare-thee-well and that they're some of the toughest
                        negotiators you could imagine. How did you find them in the '50s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: That is exactly the way they were then. There is no strength like the
                    strength of a weaker neighbor dealing with a relatively moral, strong neighbor.
                    They played the weaker neighbor. They would play the fact that their
                    Constitution was weaker than ours where they had a very bad— they always used to
                    claim that, you know, if we have a problem, well, “the provinces won't let us do
                    that.” And, boy, we got the provinces rammed down our throat over and over. Not
                    that it wasn't true up to a point, but they used it. They are very, very tough,
                    able negotiators, and they're just as your other friend described it. That's the
                    way they were then. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>I will say this—and I've done a lot of negotiations since- -they were
                    tremendously fair and honorable negotiators. There is something special about
                    the Canadians which you cannot transpose to many other situations, and that is
                    at a point where we would appear to face irreconcilable difference over
                    something, the Canadians were people you could sit down with over a cup of
                    coffee or a beer and talk and say, “Now come on. We've got to find our way
                    through all this.” They have a nice genius for knowing when to move on from
                    total hard-line position to search for a compromise that's palatable to both
                    sides, and they showed it many times.</p>
                <p>McCarthyism was a case in point, and they were very, very insistent to protect
                    their citizens. But they found a way, and they started very hard and emotional
                    about it that they would not expose people traveling on the seaways—their
                    people—in any way. In the end we found a working compromise, which, again, was
                    something that they found as the last resort. Oh, I have a great respect for
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: George, you mentioned McCarthyism. You might, for the
                        uninitiated, explain why McCarthyism would be a problem. But also, you came
                        into the Foreign Service at a time when McCarthyism was rampant, although
                        you were overseas most of this time. What was your impression at the time,
                        and what did it mean to the Foreign Service that you saw?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Okay. I came in just ahead of McCarthyism, and McCarthyism got well
                    underway shortly thereafter. It did not really impact on me until I got to
                    Canada. Quito was so far away. It is best illustrated by the fact that there was
                    no airplane line that went directly there from outside the country. It had dirt
                    runways, and it never had a congressional visit. [Laughter] That describes
                    Quito, as left to itself.</p>
                <p>Canada was very different, indeed. We had not been in Canada very long before we
                    began to hear the horror stories. People we knew who were being accused of all
                    kinds of things which we felt could hardly be true. In fact, we were confident
                    they weren't true. People we knew who were leaving the Foreign Service because
                    of this particular kind of thing. And then it hit home when my wife's cousin,
                    who had been raised in China and was a very fine scholar in that area, was
                    hounded out of his—he was a professor in the United States—was hounded out of
                    his job and got a job promptly at the University of Toronto, where they were
                    delighted to have him. His only sin had been that, like most China scholars of
                    that period, they had worked with people who were under accusation for one
                    reason or another because, if they were good, they had had some contact with the
                    changing China scene.</p>
                <p>It hit me with real force in two episodes. First one was a story in which Scott
                    McLeod in the State Department, who was then head of the security bureau and a
                    great buddy of McCarthy's, questioned whether or not we should be reading
                    magazines like the Reporter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a moderate left wing, very slightly left
                        wing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I was just going to say very slightly left wing. And this was carried in a
                    little letter to the New York Times magazine section. So I wrote to the Foreign
                    Service Journal. And wrote them a letter, which I invited them to publish, which
                    said that I had subscribed to a wide selection of magazines and felt that, as a
                    Foreign Service officer, I should, and that it included the Reporter and the
                    Atlantic Monthly, both of which were allegedly viewed with some suspicion by Mr.
                    McLeod. And that I thought that we in the Foreign Service should be told whether
                    or not in the Foreign Service this was the kind of conduct that was approved or
                    not.Very interesting. The Foreign Service Journal carefully wrote me right back
                    and said, “We're going to publish your letter, and we will forward it to Mr.
                    McLeod's office, the text, but we are withdrawing your name because we think it
                    might be too controversial.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It gives an idea of the era.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>VEST: That gives you an idea of the era. In point of fact, McLeod did come back
                    and say, “No, the New York Times magazine was wrong. We don't disapprove of
                    Foreign Service officers subscribing to a broad range of magazines. We do think
                    they should be very careful that they are not seduced by ultra liberal
                    propaganda.” [Laughter] And my name did not appear. It made me realize then, you
                    know, how sensitive it was.</p>
                <p>It reached the stage where I was reporting on Canadian attitudes to McCarthyism,
                    and the telegram went to the ambassador, who was a political appointee—a very
                    nice old gentlemen named R. Douglas Stewart—to be approved, and he was very
                    upset. He called me in and he said, “I'm not going to approve this kind of
                    thing.” He very much favored what Senator McCarthy was doing, thought he was
                    doing the right thing, and this was terrible.</p>
                <p>Now I'll have the say that Ambassador Stewart was always very nice to me, and I
                    never felt he held anything against me. I watched how things could be done. This
                    DCM, Mr. Bliss, got into the middle of it and said to the ambassador, “Well, I
                    understand how you feel about this, but George is only reporting Canadian
                    attitudes so that the United States Government will know how things are viewed
                    in Canada and can affect their conduct of policy. But you don't want to have
                    your name on this as approving it. In the future, any telegrams that are
                    reporting on McCarthyism and whatnot, why don't I just have them held until
                    after you've gone home, and I will initial them.” The ambassador was very nice
                    and agreed to this compromise that all telegrams on McCarthyism would come after
                    he went home. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>We followed it. We got more and more stories. I don't mind admitting it made a
                    big impact on my wife and me, and it reached the stage when it hit relatives and
                    friends enough that we seriously had a discussion saying, “Look. If this goes on
                    and unchecked, and we find it impossible to be in the Foreign Service, we might
                    just possibly immigrate to Canada.” Because I had this feeling if I wanted to, I
                    could go there and I could, indeed, serve—I would have felt comfortable serving
                    in the Canadian Foreign Service, and I felt I knew enough people that it was a
                    conceivable thing. That was only casual talk between us and never got further
                    than that. And then, of course, Eisenhower and the Senate and all the rest just
                    gradually took care of all this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, George, I came into the Foreign Service in 1955. I'm
                        not sure if I'm speaking for everybody, but I think this was the attitude.
                        If things got rough on reporting or something, you could not depend on the
                        State Department to back you up. This was a reflection of how we felt about
                        Dulles.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>VEST: That's exactly right. That's why I mentioned that DCM, because we did not
                    have confidence in the State Department. We did have McLeod coming out and
                    acting as he did. We didn't see anybody in the State Department reining him in,
                    and we knew our senior Foreign Service officers were terribly worried. You could
                    tell. It permeated the building. This was why I really was so impressed with the
                    action of that DCM saying, “We have to do this reporting, and I will initial it
                    if you don't want to do it.” But I was in the lucky position in that the senior
                    officers in the embassy were of such a kind that I was fundamentally inspired by
                    them. They provided leadership.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm sure if somebody were to go back and to take a look in
                        our reporting for that period, they would find a great many of the embassies
                        did not report on the reaction to McCarthyism, which was a major issue which
                        obviously should have been reported if you're doing your job. But because of
                        this, this lack of trust.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Ours was the DCM. He was a rock. He was a Vermonter and he was all those
                    things you think of in Vermont. There were two or three junior officers there.
                    The junior officers who worked through that embassy were Phil Habib, Dean Brown,
                    and I, in succession, so we had a pretty good crowd. I followed Dean there, and
                    I remember one of them—I don't know which one it was—saying of Mr. Bliss, he
                    said, “Well, he's a Vermonter. You get the satisfaction of working for him
                    because on your efficiency report, if he says, 'Well done,' it means that you're
                    a superman. He's never going to go beyond well done.” [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, George, you then went back to the State Department
                        from 1954 to '57. What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: This was an actual continuation. They needed someone in the Canadian desk,
                    and I was brought down. And primarily I did the St. Lawrence Seaway and all of
                    the boundary waters problems of U.S.-Canada and the political coverage for the
                    desk in Washington. In other words, I just took the other end of the stick. And
                    this was again wonderful because the Seaway was inherently the province of the
                    Pentagon and the assistant secretary for European affairs, Livy Merchant, so I
                    dealt almost directly with these very senior people. And right down there as a
                    junior boy in the crowd because the Canadian desk was not high on the noble
                    pecking order of European affairs. [Laughter] We had one that was lower, and
                    that was the desk officer for Australia-New Zealand. They had even less credit.
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And no Seaway.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>VEST: But I had the Seaway, and it was wonderful. And I had a great boss again. I
                    owe so much to the great bosses I had. The head of that office was Outerbridge
                    Horsey, and I don't think I've known anybody who was a better boss, taught me
                    more, and drove home something that I didn't need, but I valued, which was what
                    I'd call the importance of integrity and standards and all the rest. I can to
                    this day remember the day Outerbridge—Outer, as we called him—got in all of us
                    in the Canadian desk. There were about five or six of us. He said, “There are a
                    lot of questions that come to us at one time or another from the press,
                    sometimes you have to deal with the press. And just in general to all of you, I
                    want you to know that for the future in your Foreign Service careers, you don't
                    ever lie to the press. You may not answer a question, but don't ever, ever fall
                    into the deliberate lie.” That was at a time when there was many questions about
                    how do you conduct yourself, and I've never forgotten him to this day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This, I think, is probably the one thing that is almost
                        engraved on anybody in the Foreign Service at a certain point. That when you
                        start, if you lie, you've ruined yourself.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: You get caught.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, you get caught, and then it ruins your business.
                        Which is not a lesson, I might add, has not been learned by many of our
                        administrations that have come in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Oh, boy. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then we can move on. I have you in State until 1957
                        and then there's sort of a blank until 1959.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: What happened, Stu, and probably I'm going into too much detail, but it
                    illustrates the happenstance of our career. When people say they can plan your
                    career, don't kid yourself. [Chuckles] At least mine is the absolute example of
                    how little planning you can do.</p>
                <p>I was the Canadian desk. In those days, the Canadian desk in the midsummer was
                    very, very quiet. I ran into the staff assistant to the assistant secretary,
                    Toby Belcher, and he was looking very glum. I said, “Toby, what's the
                    matter?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, I was going to take a vacation, but the guy who was going to fill
                    in for me is suddenly gone off on a gourmet tour of France. I have no one to
                    fill in for me, and now I can't take a vacation.”</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>I said, “Well, look. I can fill in for you and do my work in the Canadian desk at
                    the same time because nobody's doing anything in Canada. They're all off in
                    their little lakeside cabins.” So I went up and filled in for almost three weeks
                    for him as the staff assistant.</p>
                <p>In those days, there was only one staff assistant. He did everything for the
                    assistant secretary and the deputies, and I did them for Assistant Secretary
                    Elbrick, and then Toby came back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it Burke Elbrick</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It was Burke Elbrick. Toby came back from his vacation and I went back to
                    working on the St. Lawrence Seaway and so on. And about two months later, Toby
                    got a chance to go off and be the consul general in Cyprus, and suddenly, they
                    were looking for another staff assistant. Obviously, they looked around and
                    said, “Well, get the guy who did it this summer. He knows what to do and he can
                    move right away.” So I moved suddenly and became for a year the staff assistant
                    to Burke Elbrick.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wonder. Burke Elbrick is one of my favorite people. He
                        was my ambassador in Yugoslavia. I've always considered him a very
                        professional diplomat, and could you describe how he operated and what he
                        was doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: He, for me, was the epitome. When we talk about the old Foreign Service,
                    there are those I didn't care for at all. But in many ways for me, Burke Elbrick
                    and his wife...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Elfie.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Elfie. Burke and Elfie epitomize the best of the old Foreign Service.
                    Totally well-organized. He trained me right away to know what to look for. When
                    I look at today's world of telegrams, he had me going through everything and
                    there would be no more than, normally, about eight to ten telegrams, and that's
                    what he wanted on his desk when he came in. Because he came in and then they all
                    went—the geographic assistant secretaries—for the early morning meeting with
                    Secretary Dulles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And he was the geographic for the EUR?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: He was the one for the European Bureau.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>He had them all there. And he trained me what he wanted, and I was able to do it.
                    He was the most impeccably courteous man, as well as organized. I don't think,
                    in the whole year and plus that I worked with him, that I ever had the slightest
                    harsh word from him. And yet there were times when I really did not do things as
                    well as I should for him. But he didn't criticize openly, is all I can say. I
                    would know where I'd failed. I suppose he knew I knew, but he had self control
                    beyond belief, as far as I was concerned, because Mr. Dulles was a very
                    demanding man.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you talk a little about from your point of view—and
                        we're talking about 1957 to '58. How did the European Bureau weigh in within
                        the State Department with Dulles and all. Was this our prime concern, or how
                        did you feel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: In those days, the assistant secretary every day was in direct contact with
                    the secretary or the deputy secretary, more often the secretary. It just
                    happened. Every day he was involved with him, not just the early morning
                    meeting, which I can't remember whether it was 7:15 or when it was, but he was
                    up there two or three times a day. Now these were days of great change in Europe
                    of NATO under construct, of the Supreme Allied Commander, building SHAPE, of an
                    uncertain political situation inside France, of difficulties with England over
                    Suez. You can see there were lots of things to talk about, but I just know that
                    every day he was up there.</p>
                <p>Now, he worked terribly closely with his deputies, and his deputies were all
                    Foreign Service officers, experienced Foreign Service officers like Jake Beam
                    and John Wesley Jones and so on. It was equally clear when he wasn't around, any
                    one of those deputies went up and felt perfectly comfortable in dealing and
                    discussing issues with Secretary Dulles. So for all of his reputation for a bear
                    of sorts, certainly Mr. Dulles was dealing terribly closely with those
                    geographic bureau representatives that he had there, who were all Foreign
                    Service people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm not sure this is exactly the place to play compare and
                        contrast, but it does seem that, under Eisenhower and Dulles— they obviously
                        were men of very strong opinions on how the world should be—the Foreign
                        Service was a tool which they used as opposed to lately what you do is you
                        interlard a political element in there so that decision making often is
                        removed from the professionals. I think John Kennedy started some of
                        this.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>VEST: No question that there's a great difference. I look back on the Dulles
                    period, and while Mr. Dulles was not a warm, congenial human being by any manner
                    of means, he and Eisenhower used the Foreign Service. You can go back to that
                    period. I don't have my statistics, but the picture of the team that operated
                    there under Eisenhower and Dulles is primarily Foreign Service. There was one
                    outstanding, Assistant Secretary for Far Eastern Affairs Walter Robertson, who
                    was not Foreign Service, but he's the only one. All the others were Foreign
                    Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Counselor of embassy was Douglas MacArthur, who was
                        brought in by Eisenhower who had known him as his political advisor at
                        SHAPE, to make sure that there was a professional right there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: That's right. Now this was characteristic, and I will tell you also, it was
                    the easiest thing in the world to be in touch with the people in the White
                    House. You may have had the vestigial activity, which is now called the NSC,
                    there, and you did work with them. But I cannot tell you how many times I went
                    straight to Colonel Goodpaster, who worked for Sherman Adams as his deputy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was Eisenhower's Chief of Staff.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Chief of Staff. And I would be told, “Take this material over straight to
                    Colonel Goodpaster.” And there was a direct, even flow of advice, information,
                    requests that went straight to the White House without being interfered with by
                    anybody. But it was a period clearly that Eisenhower and Dulles drew on the
                    Foreign Service, and the Foreign Service really was at the heart of things then
                    in a way that I think today people wouldn't realize.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll make the next step. You went to NATO where you
                        worked in what, the Office of the Secretary General? This was 1959 to
                        '63.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: No, to be, again, just to show that chance makes fools of us all. I was
                    there. I'd been Burke's staff assistant. A preceding staff assistant had gone
                    and been made the consul in Florence, and it was a wonderful reward. I spoke
                    some Italian from having been in the war in Italy, and Burke and the others
                    arranged that I would go and be the consul in Florence, with an apartment and a
                    chauffeur and a chance to have a place down on the Mediterranean in the summer
                    and all those wonderful things, and that was what I was going to do next.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>And one day—in that having all been agreed; my wife and I having looked at that
                    as the next step—there wandered into my office a very nice guy named Ray
                    Thurston. Ray Thurston was the political advisor to General Norstad, the Supreme
                    Allied Commander at SHAPE headquarters. And Ray said to me, “I know that you're
                    scheduled to go to Florence, but how would you like to come and be the junior
                    boy who backstops me at Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers, Europe with General
                    Norstad? I'm the political advisor to General Norstad.” “Now,” he said, “you
                    don't have anybody working for you, you're sometimes very much the bag boy who
                    carries the messages around, but it's the heart of things that are really very
                    interesting.” And he described SHAPE and NATO.</p>
                <p>And, in one of those things that you do in life, I said, “Sounds great. I'd
                    prefer that to going to Florence as the consul.” Came home and told my wife,
                    who, bless her heart, has always backed me up, said, “Fine. If that's what you
                    want to do.”</p>
                <p>So I went, and for a year was the number two to the political advisor to General
                    Norstad. Now in this period, General Norstad was an extremely important player
                    in things European, as well as influential in the United States. Of course, he
                    had worked for President Eisenhower when Eisenhower had headed SHAPE. He knew
                    Dulles intimately. He knew MacMillan. He knew all the major European characters.
                    The Supreme Allied Commander in those days was very much a grand satrap or a
                    pendragon, or whatever you want to call it, a tremendous power, probably the
                    last of the great, powerful supreme allied commanders. And it was just when de
                    Gaulle had taken over the government and de Gaulle was gradually agitating to
                    remove France from NATO, or from the NATO military structure, so the reporting
                    and the activities were fantastic.</p>
                <p>Mr. Thurston had a heart attack, and so for about four months, I was the acting
                    political advisor because General Norstad wanted to hold it so that Thurston
                    could come back. I had unusual experiences that were just great, and I did that
                    for a year. And then NATO Secretary General Stikker—Mr. Stikker had been the
                    Dutch foreign minister and the Dutch perm rep to NATO—and he became the next
                    Secretary General.</p>
                <p>The chef de cabinet in NATO had always been a Frenchman. The French were slow
                    under de Gaulle to appoint one. Mr. Stikker, being a Dutchman with all of a
                    Dutchman's toughness and readiness to anger if need be, if he figures he's being
                    pushed around, decided that he would take a chef de cabinet from somewhere else.
                    I had, by that time, gone to work for our perm rep to NATO, Mr. Finletter at
                    NATO.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thomas Finletter.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>VEST: Thomas K. Finletter. I had met Mr. Stikker. I had carried messages to him,
                    whatnot, and so he, in his way, made up his mind one day and simply called me
                    down and told me, “I've chosen you to be my next chef de cabinet.” Now he was a
                    close friend of Norstad's. I'm sure Norstad told him, “This is an American who
                    will lack many of the things you're used to as a European, but he's worked for
                    me for a year and I know he is a dedicated and loyal person and he'll do his
                    damnedest.”</p>
                <p>Because I was shocked beyond belief, I told Mr. Stikker, “Sir, you've made a
                    dreadful mistake. I don't speak fluent enough French, I'm an American, and the
                    Americans should have a low profile in the NATO house. I don't know the way
                    Europeans do things. Really, you should get someone else.”</p>
                <p>And Mr. Stikker looked at me and said, “Well, I've made my decision, so you just
                    go and do the best you can.” He then told Ambassador Finletter—he hadn't even
                    consulted him—and told Secretary of State Dean Rusk. I went to work, and then
                    for three years plus I was seconded away from the U.S. Government on the staff
                    of the NATO international secretariat as the chef de cabinet for Mr.
                    Stikker.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was obviously remarkable training for dealing with
                        European affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Stu, it was absolutely fantastic. First of all, what was inherent in the
                    job is I learned how a European group of diplomats, when they're in NATO, work
                    together or don't work together and who were the good ones and who weren't.
                    Second, I met all of the young diplomats that were to be the senior diplomats a
                    little later on, because they would be part of the NATO structure or working in
                    their permanent delegations. And every time Mr. Stikker visited a foreign
                    country—every time—I accompanied him to every single visit he ever made in three
                    and a half years, including to Presidents back here. And I sat in on every visit
                    and every conversation he ever had, whether it was with a king or a prime
                    minister or a defense minister or the President of the United States or anything
                    else, because that's what he wanted me to do to make a record. He liked a very
                    complete record, and these were his records. So I sat in on everything that was
                    being done in NATO for three and a half years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any problem with dual allegiance?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>VEST: Never. No. Mr. Rusk made it very clear that when I went off, I worked for
                    the Secretary General of NATO, and that was it. Now I had access to American
                    telegrams. I knew what was being done, and Mr. Rusk's instructions were very
                    clear that I was to keep the Secretary General of NATO informed of what was
                    being done so that he could do his job as a major figure responsible for a major
                    policy area. The result was that throughout the time that I was there, I was
                    allowed to go and read the American traffic that was coming in, and I was
                    allowed to inform the Secretary General whatever I wished.</p>
                <p>I would have to say, in all fairness to Ambassador Finletter and to his deputy,
                    who I worked with a lot, Elbridge Durbrow, and Durby and Ambassador Finletter
                    never tried to interfere. They were wonderful people. I mean, really wonderful
                    people. I owe Durby a lot because, in the end, as you know, we have our
                    efficiency reports. Mr. Stikker got this elongated form that he was to fill out
                    the first year. I can still remember it. I had been working for him for about a
                    year. He looked at all this and he said to himself, “This is nonsense,” and he
                    wrote across one space, “I consider this officer is doing an excellent job,
                    quite comparable to that which I would expect from excellent officers in the
                    Dutch Foreign Service.” Signed, Dirk Stikker. That was it. He sent in the form.
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>It went to Durbrow. I scratched my head and thought, “Well, that's the way life
                    is.” Durby sat down and wrote an additional efficiency report, all on his own,
                    because we had no guidance in those days. This was the first time there had ever
                    been an American doing the job. And Durby sat down with great generosity and
                    wrote—and then he showed me what he had done— an efficiency report which tried
                    to give some flavor as to what I was doing and how I was doing it and what
                    regard I had earned from the world for which I had to work, and sent it in. Now,
                    that was a wonderful thing to do. I have so many senior officers to be grateful
                    for, and that's one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: George, what gave Stikker, and you as his hand holder, or
                        whatever you want to call it, bag holder, the greatest problem during this
                        period? Sounds like it must be France.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: No, there were two problems, and Stikker would be the first to say when
                    asked what are my problems. One was France and one was the United States. When
                    he came in, de Gaulle was already there, so France became the increasing problem
                    all the way through, more and more difficulties.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did France—to put this in perspective—actually leave
                        the military</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It did not do so until—if my memory serves me right—about the mid '60s. It
                    had not left, but it had already forecast the direction it was going. It had
                    taken out certain elements of the French fleet in the Mediterranean. In other
                    words, it had begun the incremental process, and you could see it.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>The United States was another thing. Stikker and Norstad began their involvement
                    in the NATO world at a time when there was Eisenhower and Dulles, with whom they
                    had the greatest intimacy and the greatest ease. And then came the Kennedy
                    Administration, and there was a radical change in policy, as well as
                    personalities. The Eisenhower-Dulles Administration had introduced the NATO
                    atomic stockpile. They had had a summit meeting of NATO leaders, which they
                    promised all kinds of missiles and other kinds of nuclear armament to the
                    alliance. In came the Kennedy Administration, and Kennedy and McNamara said,
                    “We've gone too far in nuclear missiles. We are going to have to look to see how
                    we pull back from this enthusiastic, rather unthought through, dependance on
                    nuclear missiles.”</p>
                <p>This meant that—to put it bluntly—things that had been promised at the heads of
                    government NATO summit were not going to be delivered. Stikker and Norstad
                    continued to fight for the fulfillment of those earlier policies an promises
                    They argued and there was a large debate that went on and discussions that
                    constantly went on, but in the end, Norstad was asked to retire because of it
                    and Stikker was fundamentally, rather heavily, frustrated because of it.</p>
                <p>But I never had a problem of divided loyalties because the U.S. never asked me or
                    tried to limit how I did my job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You saw at that time Stikker and Norstad wanting to have
                        an increased nuclear armament there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: For NATO, and shared by the NATO countries. Remember this was the period,
                    for lack of anything else, the U.S. came up with the ill-fated MLF, multilateral
                    force idea, in which there would be nuclear weapons on a mixed-manned,
                    multinational manned, ship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Everybody with different keys.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Everyone with different functions. We never got to the point of defining
                    entirely who else might ever have a key.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, when you're coming up with this MLF, what was
                        Stikker's reaction, and those around him, to that type of thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>VEST: Stikker never had any doubt about one thing, which is that NATO, in the
                    last analysis, to mean anything had to have American involvement. He was a very
                    deeply pro- American man. Even when he was the most frustrated with McNamara and
                    so on, there was never, never any question about— as matter of fact, like a lot
                    of the Dutch, he saw the United States as the hope for the west. I think he felt
                    the MLF was a dubious idea, but if the Americans wanted to propel it, he would
                    see how far it would go.</p>
                <p>There were other ideas that were floated at that time of one kind or another.
                    Basically, he always wanted to try to be helpful to the United States, frankly.
                    He was very pro- American, like so many men of his generation and his
                    experience. He had relatives who lived in the States. He had children who had
                    studied in the States. He preferred to speak English to any other language. He
                    had been the ambassador in Great Britain, but he really spoke a sort of
                    unaccented English.</p>
                <p>It was a period when, however, he had his difficulties. Ambassador Finletter and
                    he were personally very, very antithetical. I mean, Finletter was determined to
                    run everything, and in his way, Mr. Stikker felt he should run things. Finletter
                    was always out to knife Norstad, and for Stikker, Norstad was both a friend and,
                    for him, the Supreme Allied Commander was somebody that everybody ought to try
                    to trust and build up and not knife and in petty, mean way, which frankly was
                    what Finletter did in his comments at all times.</p>
                <p>So it was an unhappy relationship, and there was a further unhappiness that we
                    were trying back here, as I saw it at least, to try to find alternatives to a
                    heavy reliance on nuclear weapons, and we were not that sure how we wanted to
                    move ourselves. When he would talk to McNamara, McNamara would almost as much as
                    say that. This left Stikker at very much a disadvantage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the part that Germany played? Was there unease by
                        Stikker and others about the role of Germany?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Very interesting, Stu, that you should mention this because two things in
                    my memory stand out. One is what I'd call the recollection of residual hostility
                    that came out of the war. If there was one thing that you could pick up from all
                    of the people around there, it was still that residual reserve. When I went to
                    SHAPE in—whatever it was—'58, '59, the Germans had only been part at SHAPE
                    headquarters for about I think eight or ten months, and there were people in—
                    certainly the Danish and Norwegian delegations—military delegations—at SHAPE
                    headquarters who simply refused to speak to any of the Germans who had come
                    there. I mean, they just put them in Coventry. They didn't speak to them, that's
                    all. Which shows you how these things can be.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>That second summer when we came back on home leave, we turned over our house to a
                    very nice, young German officer who had several children and lived in an
                    apartment. And he and his wife and children came and occupied our house while we
                    were on vacation and they paid the rent, but they had a place to come. And when
                    we came back, I still remember, both husband and wife burst into tears, this
                    German officer and his wife, saying they had had such a lovely time and that we
                    were the first people who had been kind to them in the whole time so far since
                    they'd been there. That was how close the background was.</p>
                <p>When you talk to the politicians when I got down to NATO headquarters, when you
                    talked about when there was to be a meeting in one of the capitals, the whole
                    attitude was, “Well, whatever else we do, let's not meet in Bonn. We can meet in
                    Paris or in London on in Rome. There's no reason to have to go to Bonn.” That's
                    when it would come out. So there was strong residual hostility that was still
                    going on there into, I'd say, the early '60s.</p>
                <p>But now to get to the next phase you mentioned—worry about them. Because you had
                    as a defense minister, Mr. Franz Joseph Strauss, pretty cocky, boisterous, bull
                    dog in a china shop, type of person. And typical of it I remember when...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why don't we stop right here for one second.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>[End Tape 1, Side 2] [Begin Tape 2, Side 1]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: George, you were talking about the view of the new
                        Minister of Defense of Germany, Franz Joseph Strauss.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Typical of the problem and of the reserves. In the early years, for
                    example, after the heads of government meeting, the Americans—President
                    Eisenhower—had agreed to make available IRBMs, intercontinental range ballistic
                    missiles, for the alliance, to be stationed in some alliance countries. General
                    Norstad was to be responsible for the program at SHAPE, and he was to find out
                    which countries they would position these new missiles in.</p>
                <p>I still remember the day General Norstad called me in. With sort of a wry smile,
                    he said, “I've been sounding out countries as to which ones would like to have
                    IRBMs. I've just had a visit from Franz Joseph Strauss, and he has said,
                    'Germany would be delighted to be the first country to have the IRBMs.'”
                    [Laughter] And he said, “I counseled him that I really thought it would be a bad
                    idea for Germany to be the first country to have IRBMs,” thereby showing both
                    how maladroit and rambunctious Strauss could be, but how sensitive Norstad was.
                    Ultimately later, you may or may not remember, we did station them in Italy and
                    in Turkey. None were ever positioned in Germany.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>There was in this period considerable reserve and suspicion, verging in some
                    corners to worry about what the Germans might grow to be. They were becoming
                    clearly the major land army in central Europe for the alliance. They, I think,
                    conducted themselves with absolute probity and correctness and discretion. They
                    did not push in NATO or in SHAPE, but there was real sensitivity there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Looking at the other side of the equation, I have been
                        asked by a diplomatic historian saying all this challenge assumptions in
                        these things. Could you look at what our assumption was of the threat, i.e.,
                        the other side of the mountain, the Soviet Union?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: At this time, you're talking about the end of '50, early into the '60s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Into the '60s, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: You never heard anybody in those days, whether they were in NATO
                    headquarters, American official visitors on briefings, the SHAPE headquarters
                    itself, you never heard anybody that didn't give the picture that there was a
                    very serious threat, and that the massive ground forces, tanks, all that kind of
                    thing were of such that you had to do your damnedest to be able to deal with the
                    unexpected. They took it very seriously. I mean, there was no question about
                    this general sense of concern in that period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You assumed that the Soviet Union had hostile
                        intents?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: You assumed that the Soviet Union continued to be governed by the way in
                    which it had been before in early times in this historical period. That if they
                    found enough weakness, they would probe and try to take it, as they did at Kars
                    and Ardahan, as they did in Tabriz.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is there an Iran during that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes. Wherever they felt there was weakness, people believed they would try
                    to probe it and take advantage of it, and so they would have this common defense
                    to make sure that the Soviets had no illusions that there was weakness.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you consider there might be a particular
                        weakness within the NATO, within NATO countries rather than the structure?
                        What concerned you the most? I mean, the people you were working with.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>VEST: I don't have a memory of anyone being weak. There was a special thing that
                    they knew they had to deal with, and that was that the two Scandinavian members,
                    Norway and Denmark, would not allow nuclear weapons to be sited on their soil;
                    therefore, the northern flank was always going to have to be treated specially.
                    There was a feeling that Denmark particularly was susceptible to neutralism. Not
                    Norway particularly, but Denmark.</p>
                <p>The other area weakness was the other flank in Greece- Turkey, where the weakness
                    was not so much a matter that either one of them might flirt with the Soviets,
                    but that they just might get themselves all tangled up irretrievably with each
                    other—as they did repeatedly—giving an opening to be played on by the
                    Soviets.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why this insistence and concern about stationing nuclear
                        arms on a place? I mean, after all, a fairly hefty load of nuclear weapons
                        can be flown in within a matter of hours practically, or delivered anywhere
                        even at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: That fact is true, but the political facts are as following. One, if
                    everybody had nuclear weapons on their soil, then no country is singled out as a
                    target. That's the first. Second, if you have had a long period in which you
                    said, “We will not have nuclear weapons on our soil,” how rapidly could that
                    country take a political decision to allow them to come in? Taking hard
                    political decisions rapidly is not characteristic of democracies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So the idea was a banding together?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Do it together. Everybody be the same kind of target, everybody be ready to
                    do their job together. Now, we did build areas to make it possible to have
                    instantaneous delivery of nuclear missiles to the Scandinavian areas so that
                    they could do it rapidly, but this “no nuclear weapons” had very deep policy
                    meaning for the Scandinavians because I believe they honestly feared, after all
                    that had gone on, that if they took too provocative an action there, this would
                    influence the Russians to be that much tougher with the Finns. The Finns were
                    sort of in the in-between, and there was always a sense of delicacy among the
                    Scandinavians that “We've got to make sure we don't load the plate too heavily
                    and invite real pressure, and perhaps retaliation, on the Finns.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Speaking of missiles, were you with NATO at the time of
                        the missile crisis in October of '63 or '62?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>VEST: Cuba. Where was—you know, I have no idea where I was at the time. I was
                    there, but I was not present when any of the activity took place. I may have
                    been back here. My mother-in-law was ill, and I may have been back here at that
                    time. I know I missed it, and I was told afterwards about Acheson's visit and
                    Acheson's briefing and Acheson's call on de Gaulle and all these things, but I
                    was not around at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you leave this Office of the Secretary
                        General?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It must have been—I'm very, Stu, terrible about dates—probably mid '63, and
                    then I went for a year to the National War College.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: National War College. And then your next assignment was
                        to, what, DCM?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: No. Then I was again, without any action on my part—you know, you get
                    taped—I was then pulled off and was sent to the Bureau of European Affairs RPM,
                    the office that works on regional, political, and military activities,
                    inherently NATO, and I worked in that office for, oh, it must have been three
                    years, as far as I can recall. David Popper was the director at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were our principal concerns during this period? Do
                        you feel Vietnam was a terrible drag on what we were...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It shows you how provincial things can be. In NATO, in my memory I have two
                    big episodes. One is de Gaulle withdrawing the forces—or asking that our forces
                    withdraw from France, and the second was trying to figure out what in the world
                    to do about Mintoff and Malta and getting out of the NATO base which was there
                    in Malta.</p>
                <p>On the first one, I was a party as a junior—more junior participant—to the byplay
                    that went on in Washington once word came that de Gaulle was insisting that we
                    would have to get out of France in the NATO military. Dean Acheson was brought
                    back as special advisor, and in the office up above the sixth floor, they had—I
                    can still to this day remember—a vivid meeting in which, as I recall it, we had
                    the Secretaries of State and Defense, and David Bruce had come back from London,
                    and McGeorge Bundy was there as the NSC advisor to the President, and all the
                    other senior people, and I was the junior person there. Dean Acheson was there
                    and they were arguing, and they were insisting, as a result of this action on de
                    Gaulle's part, that we would look around and figure every single way to throw
                    the book back at France, put our relations to the minimum, retaliate in every
                    punitive way we could. In other words, the hardest possible reaction policy.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>I've never forgotten McGeorge Bundy, because the fever heat was fairly high,
                    McGeorge Bundy said, “Well, all of this is very interesting, because what you're
                    saying is you wish to kick France formally out of NATO.”</p>
                <p>And they agreed, “Yes, that's just what they wanted.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, it's very interesting, but I think that the President of the
                    United States will want to think very carefully before we go so far as to take
                    the act to throw France out of the North Atlantic Council.” And that ended the
                    meeting, and, of course, we never did that. I was very impressed with McGeorge
                    Bundy, who obviously went back to the President and they thought some more, and
                    they adopted a much more graduated policy of coldness and reserve and of
                    non-cooperation in certain areas, but we never took that other step.</p>
                <p>I have never forgotten Dean Acheson called me up, with one other officer whose
                    name I forget now who worked in the German division, and asked about the
                    attitude of the other countries if we should attempt to throw France out. Having
                    worked there— and not only throwing them out, but blackball France in every
                    way—and I told Mr. Acheson that I did not believe that the majority of the
                    European countries would do this to France, that they would simply hold their
                    nose and go on their way. He was used to a kind of European management that he
                    could have done right after World War II, but by mid 1960s, Europeans were not
                    the same group of people. I know when he left he turned to Larry Eagleburger,
                    who was his staffer, saying, “I'm tired of those pantywaists downstairs.” So
                    that is what we did. We were cold, but we never did adopt a virulent response,
                    which would not have changed de Gaulle at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It would have just made things worse.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Which would have embarrassed the Europeans dreadfully, because they had to
                    live with France there next door to them, and so I think that, frankly, the
                    American policy was exactly right, and it's given time for the gradual shift of
                    the world as we see it today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you look, and I'm talking now about July of 1989, we
                        seem to be almost going through the same thing regarding China. It's a
                        completely different situation, but the idea is the Chinese have done some
                        considerable repression after we'd gone through a glowing period and we want
                        to punish. I'm not surprised, but maybe it shows a real problem in our
                        foreign policy process, of wanting to punish, and these are, I think,
                        distinguished people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I think it shows a fundamental problem we have in our own national ethos,
                    because we can get very concerned about things that strike us as morally wrong.
                    We can get upset about this kind of thing, and we feel something should be done
                    about it. Well, frequently there is much less you can do about it than you'd
                    like, and you have to hold your nose and wait.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And things change.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: And things do change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have to keep laying this on a chronological basis. Now,
                        let's see, you were dealing with the political military side, and then after
                        that, you went as deputy chief of mission to the European Community? How
                        about the Mintoff thing? Maybe we might talk a little about Mintoff.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: In the Mintoff thing we just talked a little bit because, in true terms,
                    it's a peanut. But in time and effort and money consumed, it was anything but a
                    peanut. In George Ball you had someone who felt that what we should do is ask
                    Malta to become a NATO member. There were others who said, “If there's one thing
                    we don't want to do it's take on a Malta,” and this was argued very largely. And
                    then when it came time to leave, Mintoff, who was impossibly wily and really a
                    hopeless individual in many ways to deal with. The only way to deal with him was
                    simply to say, “What you're saying doesn't matter as far as we're concerned.”
                    But very few people had the guts to say that when they thought he might turn
                    Malta over to the Russians.</p>
                <p>We had to pay our way out of it, and we had a long argument. That's where I first
                    worked with Peter Carrington, who was then the Minister of Defense for Great
                    Britain, and it was the British NATO headquarters in Malta and they were
                    responsible primarily. The Italians wanted to be sweet and pay. The British
                    wanted to pay as little as possible. And the Americans, worried from the
                    Pentagon about what might happen to the Soviets or somebody moving into Malta,
                    were more inclined to pay then not. It was a long, arduous negotiation, because
                    every time people thought we had a price, Mintoff's view was, “Well, if they can
                    pay that much, they can pay more.” And so eventually we paid and eventually we
                    left, and it never became a member of NATO, which would have been a stupid thing
                    to have done, and it has fallen back into a more natural relationship with the
                    rest of Europe. But it took an awful lot of time. [Laughter] Particularly when
                    George Ball is enthusiastic about something, you have an awful lot of visits to
                    the seventh floor, is all I can say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I will say the seventh floor, for those reading, this is
                        where the Secretary of State and his principal subordinates dwell.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: That's right. I was up there so often. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would this cover the time when you went from this job as
                        deputy chief of mission to the European Community? Or was there something in
                        between?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>VEST: I did this in the NATO office and then worked for Ambassador [John Robert]
                    Schaetzel who was our ambassador to the European Community, who had been the
                    deputy assistant secretary in the EUR.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's Robert Schaetzel.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Robert Schaetzel. And when it came time to get a new deputy, he sent word
                    he'd like me to come and be his deputy chief of mission. This again is one of
                    the sort of happenstances of life. I had not worked—I was familiar with him in
                    the casual sense, because we all worked there together in the Bureau of European
                    Affairs—but I had not worked in any intimate way at all with affairs involving
                    European Community. I had worked in NATO affairs. So I was very reluctant to
                    take the job, but he insisted and reiterated his offer, and so I went to be the
                    DCM to our mission to the European Community.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was '67 to '69.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: '67 to '69. And I'd have to say it was a wonderful experience. It was more,
                    again, a learning experience for me. I was learning to be a DCM. I quickly
                    learned how to deal with making unpleasant decisions known to people, which any
                    DCM has to do. I had great backing and understanding from Bob Schaetzel, who, in
                    turn, was really educating me on the intricacies of the European commission with
                    which I was not particularly familiar. I knew them casually only from previous
                    activities.</p>
                <p>Fortunately, a number of the people who were in the European commission, or the
                    permanent representatives to the European commission, were also people who I'd
                    known in NATO. I began to, what I'd call, reap the harvest of my earlier
                    experiences, because in the French, German, and Italian, were all people I had
                    known as junior officers, met in my earlier experiences in the European scene,
                    so it paid off. They were people I could talk very, very freely to, and I would
                    say it was the most open, easy, transparent relationship. You didn't have a
                    problem. You could pick up a phone and say, “I hear that you all are thinking
                    about a new rule on the control on the import of soybeans. What is it you are
                    thinking about?” and they would tell you. I mean, it wasn't difficult, I'd have
                    to say. They were very open.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were our interests in NATO in the European Community?
                        We're talking about the late '60s, before it had really coalesced to be what
                        it is today.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>VEST: One kind of interest was, I would say, we were still carrying and arguing
                    very much the political value of a more united Europe, so we saw in the European
                    Community and the European commission and all of that activity a political
                    objective that we strongly supported and for which we were still prepared to
                    defer a certain amount when it came to economic or agricultural disadvantage. We
                    would suffer a little bit for that political policy that we were advocating
                    because, among other things, it's one more of those areas where Germany is
                    brought into a European group.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Much of it was grouped around what do you do about Germany
                        and let's get them integrated with everybody else.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It was inherently France-Germany. France and Germany—I would have to give
                    joint genius to de Gaulle and Adenauer. They set up a heartland, which were the
                    two worst enemies, and said, “We are going to be the two best friends, and we
                    will build an European Community around it.” And that is inherently what they
                    set out to do, and, of course, de Gaulle excluded Britain and said, “We're going
                    to do it this continental way.”</p>
                <p>But it was France-Germany. We thought it was immeasurably valuable, and we were
                    prepared to endure quite a lot. We were seen as having been proponents from the
                    beginning, because we had been all the way through. Now in the time that I was
                    there, we began to see the beginnings, I think, of a change. We began to have
                    very serious problems, primarily in the agricultural area. The Europeans joined
                    together in something called the Common Agricultural Policy. This was very
                    expensive for our agriculture. It tended to limit our grain market.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And this was actually our biggest export.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: And this was our biggest export. And, therefore, we began to hit that
                    cutting edge where the political policy is costing too much economically, and in
                    that couple years that I was there I could see the real evolution of that
                    change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you a question. As a Foreign Service officer
                        dealing at this level, I sort of have the gut instinct of this that when
                        there's a push and shove between economics and political, we tend to zero in
                        and say whatever furthers our political goals, and leave the economics to
                        one side. Did you have this feeling? Or were we getting pretty tough on
                        economics?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>VEST: I think it would be very interesting, because I think in the period I'm
                    talking about, you could begin to see exactly that shift. That before I went
                    there, and when I first went there, if there was push to shove between political
                    goal and economic disadvantage, we would end up supporting the political goal.
                    By the time that I left, which was two plus years later, I think the
                    agricultural issues had become large enough you could see that we would not pay
                    any economic price to support that political goal. I mean, after all, you're
                    talking about millions, millions of dollars. Just lots and lots of money is
                    involved, and it affects a huge segment of our voting population, who in turn
                    affect our Congress, who in turn affect our policy. So I could see the change
                    happening at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, did you find that the other members of the European
                        Community were playing on you to say, “Well, go along with this because this
                        will make us stronger politically and more of a bulwark against communism,
                        and just forget about the grain”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: No. At that time there seemed to be a fair degree of differentiation
                    between NATO activities and Community activities and one that has continued
                    almost right on up to the present. What they were saying, “what we're doing in
                    the economic field is only temporary. It's an effort to try to rebuild destroyed
                    areas of life, to rebuild healthy nations. And it's inconvenient to you now, but
                    hang on, it won't last,” was the position they were taking. And to be fair, I
                    think they meant it. I think they thought that the structure they were building,
                    called the Common Agricultural Policy, which exists to this day to our
                    disadvantage, was something that would balance out. Well, they never found a way
                    to balance it out. But I think they meant it when they said, “These are not
                    serious; you're overreacting.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You seemed to switch hats, but sort of in the same
                        area.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I did. I got a telephone call one day from Alex Johnson, and Alex said,
                    “George, the White House has just telephoned, and you're going to go over right
                    away by this Friday and be the DCM at NATO.”And I said, “How did that
                    happen?”</p>
                <p>And they said, “Well, the ambassador to NATO, Bob Ellsworth, has very close
                    connections with the White House, and he's looking for a new DCM, and he's
                    chosen you.” So it was just like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is 1969.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes. I went over to NATO and became the DCM over there. And that was a very
                    interesting period in itself.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: First, before we get into that, Ellsworth was a political
                        appointee, wasn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Ellsworth was a political appointee. He had been one of the campaign
                    managers for Nixon and Schaetzel was still there, being left there even though
                    by background, he was an acknowledged liberal Democrat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Within the NATO structure, which I would assume would be a
                        fairly complicated business. I mean, it's not just one organization and what
                        we're trying to do. It's a fairly difficult place, and there seems to be a
                        tendency to drop political appointees in there, often because one thinks
                        where it's located. Where was it located? Was it in Brussels at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It was in Brussels by then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But it seems to be one of the political plums, almost used
                        on a par with appointing somebody to Luxembourg.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Not quite. In fact, not at all that. It was considered a very important
                    place. This is not always, but most of the time. And among those so important
                    that it was considered the place you would send a political appointee of the
                    highest quality who had easy and immediate access to the President, no matter
                    what happened. Now, if you went back through the list of political appointees
                    who had been there, most of them fell in that area; and just as Ellsworth had
                    been a counselor in the White House after the Nixon election, he came to that.
                    Later, Don Rumsfeld came to that. Close, very close, to the President and to the
                    top leaders of the party.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So this in case, the story that a political appointee is
                        close to the President, which usually isn't the case. It's just somebody who
                        gave money.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: In this case it was meant to be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In this case, it had that. Did you find this worked as
                        opposed, to say, having somebody who dealt in NATO affairs for a long time
                        or a professional Foreign Service officer?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>VEST: Yes, it can work. I mean, my experience with political ambassadors, I'd
                    have to say you just cannot totally generalize. My political ambassador in
                    Canada—the first one when I went there—is owed more than most people realize. He
                    was Stanley Woodward, who had been chief of protocol and knew Truman very well.
                    Well, in the last days of the Truman Administration—this is a divagation, but
                    worth recording of what you can have happen. In the very end of the Truman
                    Administration, Truman was still the President. I think it was December, the
                    month of December.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would be 1952?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes. Truman had lost the election. Eisenhower had not yet been sworn in,
                    and in that week, the Canadians, deciding they could never get the Americans to
                    make up their minds and do anything — the subject which they talked about for 50
                    years—met, and the Canadian Cabinet decided, “We will go ahead with an
                    all-Canadian St. Lawrence Seaway.” And one of the ministers—I think it was C.D.
                    Howe; it may have been Mike Pearson—called Ambassador Woodward and said, “I feel
                    you should know we've met in the Cabinet. We are now prepared to go ahead with
                    an all-Canadian seaway, and we're letting you know. We realize the in-between
                    period you're in, but this is now what's going to happen.”</p>
                <p>Stanley Woodward got on the telephone and called President Truman that night, got
                    him in the evening, and reported all of this to President Truman and said, “This
                    is of too much importance to the United States to let this happen this way. I
                    urge you to get on the telephone and talk to President-elect Eisenhower. I
                    realize how difficult this is, and see if you cannot get a commitment from
                    President-elect Eisenhower that he personally will try to get legislation out of
                    the Congress to allow for a joint U.S.-Canadian seaway.” Truman did that.
                    Eisenhower did—and, I mean, they weren't fun together.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, no.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: But Truman did it, and Eisenhower said, “I will. This is too important.”
                    Truman then called Woodward. Woodward then called the Canadians and said, “The
                    President- elect has given his commitment. Will you hold up until at least you
                    see what comes of that?” And they did. And so today we have a joint
                    U.S.-Canadian seaway. Now that could only have been done by someone who had the
                    personal intimacy that Ambassador Woodward had with Truman. I mean, that is a
                    sample of it.</p>
                <p>In NATO, any number of times the NATO ambassador has telephoned the White House
                    for one reason or another. And, I mean, never anything so totally dramatic as
                    that, but there's been a tradition which left that always as a possibility. Only
                    once—or twice, rather, it seems to me—have they had ambassadors who did not
                    really have that kind of distinction.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>While I was there as a DCM, Ellsworth left, and then for nine months I was a
                    charg�. And they sent as ambassador David Kennedy, who had been the Secretary of
                    the Treasury. Mr. Kennedy was a nice man, but he was not interested at all in
                    the NATO business. He was more interested in international trade, textile,
                    shoes, things of this nature.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He would be much better at the European Community.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Somewhere else. Anyway, he was not interested. He did not have access. It
                    was clearly a matter of a polite shunting aside. I think the present, or the
                    most recent, ambassador there is much the same thing. He was a number two or
                    three in the NSC, and when they cleaned out the NSC there, they sent him off
                    over there. But aside from these two episodes, it's been that way. We had one
                    career officer, Tapley Bennett. He was from Georgia. I think that he had enough
                    of a Georgia rapport with the Georgians in the Carter Administration to make it
                    natural. Certainly, David Abshire, as a political appointee, quite literally,
                    when there was a big revive push to pull the troops down or out of Europe, he
                    got on the phone, not only to the White House, but to Sam Nunn.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sam Nunn being the senator from Georgia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: The senator from Georgia, who had the most influence on what we might do in
                    the NATO military field. And I know David Abshire directly dealt with the White
                    House, the State Department, and the Senate to counter what would have been a
                    premature activity. So it is a political appointee, but normally it has been one
                    of real distinction who could do something.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any memorable problems or situations while
                        you were in NATO, or was it running along a fairly smooth course at that
                        point? We're talking about '69 to '70.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Mine weren't times of great change, but I didn't have much real difficulty.
                    In the period that I was there you got the beginnings of the new policies that
                    came with Nixon and Kissinger in the White House and then Kissinger later as
                    Secretary of State, which is the exploration of MBFR, the exploration of the
                    CSCE, the European Security Conference idea, the negotiation of arrangements
                    governing Berlin. All of these things were underway. They all had to be
                    discussed in NATO. You had the SALT treaty getting underway.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>I'd have to say, generally, I had pretty good cooperation, particularly in the
                    nine months when I was the charg�. Andy Goodpaster by that time was the Supreme
                    Allied Commander. Mel Laird was Secretary of Defense, and I had gotten to know
                    him earlier. Mr. Rogers was Secretary of State, and he was not particularly
                    involved in anything, but he would back you up if need be. Walt Stoessel took
                    over eventually as the assistant secretary for European affairs. We had big
                    arguments as to whether we would go ahead with MBFR and CSCE.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which is?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Mutual Balanced Force Reductions for conventional armaments. And the CSCE,
                    the Conference for Security and Cooperation in Europe, which was to be a
                    negotiation on non- military areas that could be used to reduce tension and
                    enhance cooperation among the countries. What was very interesting is the policy
                    from the State Department clearly favored both of them, doing them both. I had
                    very much the feeling—and I'd have to say I had no instructions ever to back
                    this up—but I had very much the feeling that Mr. Kissinger's crowd in the White
                    House, where he was then in the NSC, would like to have gone ahead with MBFR and
                    would like to have avoided having to go ahead with the CSCE.</p>
                <p>Now the NATO countries, the Scandinavians and so on, were particularly insistent
                    where if you did one, you had to do the other. My guidance out of the State
                    Department left me free to support both of them, so I did, in spite of
                    conversations of people who wandered into town who said, “Well, it would be nice
                    if we didn't have to go ahead with CSCE.” But I didn't have a problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't feel any division in our foreign police
                        apparatus between Kissinger in the NSC and Rogers of the State
                        Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Oh yes, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did this play out in the field?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Rogers and company were saying, “Let's do both.” Kissinger and company were
                    clearly sending signals, “Let's try to not have the CSCE.” There was that right
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From whence came your real orders?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Oh, my orders were very simple. I picked them from the State Department,
                    because they were the ones I liked. [Laughter] It was very simple.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have the feeling that other missions around, where
                        there may have been some division between the two, that there was a certain
                        amount of playing off one?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: No, I couldn't have told you, and I really didn't know. This nine months
                    was just exactly the time when it was all being discussed, and it was a hectic
                    one. And since I was the charg� from month to month to month, I was pretty
                    busily keeping my nose to my own grindstone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, George, could we go on? You then became the director
                        of the Bureau of Military Affairs in 1974.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: No. You've skipped something.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I have some skips here, and I can't...this is for
                        the record.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: What happened after that, you know, I'd been the charg�. Then along came
                    Ambassador Kennedy. I was there, and I had been over four years in Brussels.
                    First at the European Community mission and then at NATO mission. With one of
                    those ironies of life, Mr. Rogers was there for a foreign minister's meeting,
                    and he assured me—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was at that time Secretary of State.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: He assured me I'd be staying on for another year, and about two months
                    later, I got the word that I was being sent to be in charge of our preliminary
                    negotiations on the CSCE. So I then, at my personal expense, left Emily and the
                    three children in Brussels because the schooling was there. It was one of the
                    few times in life when I think anybody's ever moved from riches to rags, because
                    I moved from a DCM residence with servants and everything furnished to a small
                    duplex with stuff that we got out of the embassy storage houses, and it was the
                    other half of a Tunisian nightclub.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Brussels?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: In Brussels. But it meant they could stay there and continue with their
                    schooling, and I went to Helsinki in the fall and headed the U.S. delegation
                    that negotiated the preparatory talks for the CSCE.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>Now we never knew how many months it would be and had no idea when it would end.
                    It was the most fun I've ever had. It was a negotiation where I had very few
                    instructions. I think Mr. Kissinger and Mr. Rogers were more or less canceling
                    each other out back in Washington as far as I could tell. And we negotiated the
                    whole thing, which set the framework for the subsequent European security
                    conference procedure and the areas we would pursue and all the rest. I had good
                    backing from the State Department, very good backing in every way that I wanted.
                    I had one horrendous episode.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me just stop right here for a second.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You're saying you had one horrendous episode.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I had one horrendous episode. We had reached that stage where the Russians,
                    of course, were pushing us to do as little as possible and to certainly not get
                    involved in human rights, and the Europeans, our NATO allies and the
                    Scandinavians and the neutrals, were anxious to broaden the scope of the
                    activity and to involve some responsibility for human rights in this whole
                    activity. At about that time—and I was speaking in favor of human rights and
                    going on and having a solid base.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is under the Nixon Administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Under the Nixon Administration, with guidance from Secretary of State
                    Rogers. At about that time, there was some NATO meetings in the U.S., and all of
                    the NATO ambassadors from Washington were invited out to San Clemente.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: San Clemente being the summer home in California of
                        President Nixon.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>VEST: And while they were there, Henry Kissinger, the head of the NSC, gave them
                    a briefing, and the briefing was of sufficient startling quality that it
                    obviously led each of these separate ambassadors to then send telegrams off to
                    their Helsinki representative and to their capitals. And I was then called in by
                    my various negotiating friends. Again, many of them people I'd known from my
                    earlier days in NATO. We were a very frank group. The Luxembourg, the Belgian,
                    the Dutch, the Canadian, the British, the Norwegian—and I can't think who else,
                    but I can remember all of them—one by one all called me in and asked me to read
                    their telegram, which is a very unusual procedure. And the essence of each of
                    these telegrams was very clear. That Mr. Kissinger had said to them, “I think
                    you're being very wrong in all this effort you're making about human rights in
                    the European security conference activity at Helsinki. What's important is MBFR,
                    and you shouldn't be bothering with any of this. You shouldn't make it that
                    difficult for the Soviets. You should forget all this business about human
                    rights. This is not the right place to do this. Forget it. It's not really very
                    important.” Anyway, CSCE isn't important, MBFR is. Don't exacerbate the
                    Russians. Give in.”</p>
                <p>Well, each of these people let me read their telegram and said, “What is the
                    policy?” Well, I was flabbergasted, of course, and angry, and, of course, to
                    each of them I said, “The policy is the policy of the United States Government
                    as reflected in my instructions, and we are supporting a strong human rights
                    activity in the CSCE.”</p>
                <p>I then wrote a letter. First I got out and hiked across the ice near the hotel
                    for about a half an hour across and half an hour back in the dead of winter, and
                    I then came back and wrote one of those intemperate letters to the assistant
                    secretary for European affairs, Walt Stoessel, saying, “This was happened. It's
                    impossible. How can you expect me to carry on a negotiation when something like
                    this has been done, and what am I to do about this, so on and so on.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I might, just for somebody reading, you were careful
                        enough. It may have been intemperate, but you wrote a letter.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because the worst thing in the world is to write...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: For that one I wrote a letter. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain why for somebody doing this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>VEST: Because I knew there would be many copies all over, and I did not know what
                    was happening in Washington. I didn't know whether maybe things were in process
                    of change and that Mr. Rogers was going to give up. I wanted to know where we
                    were going, but I didn't feel I could do anything unless I knew.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I want to stress this point, George, because these
                        interviews are aimed at people who are researching, and there's an addiction
                        to reading the cable traffic.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Okay. I see your point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There are times when cables aren't appropriate, because
                        one, you might be sending something in which could bring lightning on your
                        head. But you want to find out, but you don't say, “What is this? I'm
                        getting this in official traffic.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: In this case, it might have gotten spread around and then created a rumpus
                    of another nature and of another level between Kissinger and Rogers with
                    unintended consequences. It might go either way.</p>
                <p>And so I wanted to find out. I got a wonderful letter back from Walt Stoessel
                    which said more or less as follows: “Dear George. I do know how you feel. This
                    happens to me quite often. [Laughter] Now what can you do about it? I really
                    don't know what you can do about it except go by your instructions. At least you
                    know they are instructions which have the clearance and the authority of the
                    Secretary of State, who is still the Secretary of State.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So Kissinger really was a loose cannon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: He was a very loose cannon.</p>
                <p>The result was that I did go ahead with it. And periodically I would get
                    telephone calls from Washington saying, “You're being very strong on human
                    rights.” And I would say, “But I feel I'm entitled to.” There would be nervous
                    members— and this is interesting—nervous members of the State Department who
                    knew about these fights that were going on between Rogers and Kissinger and felt
                    maybe we should trim a little bit. Well, we didn't trim.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I might add that my impression is that, out of this whole
                        Helsinki thing, it's human rights that has been the point. In fact, I can't
                        think of anything else. I'm sure there were.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: There were, but they would be minor if not for the human rights. That's
                    what it's about.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And it was done under the Nixon Administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It was done under the Nixon Administration, with the instructions of
                    Rogers, under the constant effort of Kissinger to undercut it. [Laughter] I have
                    another wonderful episode that I can't resist telling.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Please.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: And that is I went back to Washington at a certain point—I did
                    periodically—and I went over to the NSC staff and I called on one of they key
                    staffers there who was following all of this with Kissinger. And I said, “Am I
                    doing this job satisfactorily from your point of view?”</p>
                <p>“Well, sure,” he said.</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, of course, there's a balance here of how far we push the Russians
                    and when we stop. Is that balance all right that I've achieved so far?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Sure. Just fine. Why do you keep asking?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, because the East Germans tell the West Germans that the Russians
                    told them that Henry Kissinger said we were being too tough and that he would
                    try and get us to calm down, and so I just want to know what the truth is.”
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>This guy laughed and he said, “Well, Henry Kissinger has a lot of conversations
                    with Dobrynin. I mean, maybe that's been interpreted that way by the Soviets.”
                    [Laughter] It was great fun.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, tell me. One hears a great deal about the Soviets as
                        negotiators. How did you find what you might call negotiating style, our
                        negotiating being your negotiating style, and the Soviet ones? How did this
                        play out?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>VEST: I'd have to start with one thing, Stu, because it was a fascinating
                    experience for me. Of course, a totally new experience. The Soviet
                    negotiator—they had three ambassadors there, but one really did it all—was a
                    chap named Mendelevich. Now Lev Mendelevich had long experience at Geneva and
                    with the United Nations. He was one of their most experienced persons in dealing
                    with the outside world. He spoke quite good English, better than Dobrynin, and
                    was an extremely clever and experienced diplomat. I did the whole negotiation
                    with him all the way through. I had certain assets. He had a great sense of
                    humor, and I have a number of wonderful episodes to remember that because he did
                    have humor. He was a loyal, convinced, absolutely dedicated I am sure, Soviet
                    representative.</p>
                <p>A couple of things. I learned gradually when he was speaking from Moscow and when
                    he was really negotiating with us. I learned that we had to put up with some
                    awful repetitive bluster in this multi-national 33-man table. I learned how to
                    deal with it and he knew he was communicating without ever giving some things
                    away. He had the kind of humor, I can still remember. One great bluster, he put
                    on a big table-pounding speech. He didn't take off his shoe, but it was just
                    about the only thing. And then he was followed by the Pole and then the East
                    German and then by the Romanian and then by the Bulgarian and then by the Czech,
                    and they each did just about the same thing. And I couldn't resist it. I asked
                    for the floor, and I said, “Mr. Chairman. I have just a very brief remark to
                    say. Up here in this long winter in Helsinki, I have been rereading some of the
                    Latin poets that I studied in school, and I discover in the Latin poet Juvenal
                    the following statement, which seems to be so pertinent: 'To hear the same thing
                    said over and over calls for bowels of iron.'” [Laughter] I said, “We all now
                    have bowels of iron.” Well, Mendelevich himself roared with laughter, and they
                    had been all so serious all the way through.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd have to say for the record, you're pounding your fist
                        down.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: But we reached the stage finally, for example, in the end we came to the
                    point where we couldn't decide when they'd finally give in and just agree that
                    this was going to be the end of this preliminary phase. And we finally reached a
                    stage of understanding where he said to me, “You have been watching. I know
                    you're aware of how many times I have to make a record. Now, I'm going to be
                    very precise. I'm going to have to be very angry for two weeks, and I'm going to
                    have to make a lot of speeches and threats for two weeks. I'm convinced that you
                    and your friends are not going to change. But at the end of two weeks, if that
                    is the case, I will go back to Moscow to have further discussions, and I believe
                    that Moscow will recognize what the situation is, but I'm telling you now.”
                    Well, he did. He pounded the table and was saying he was angry and outrageous
                    for two weeks, threatening and all kinds of things. Left, came back, and agreed
                    to wind up the preparatory conference.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>So you could communicate. He could be a mean, tough fighter. Threaten, bully,
                    anything, and yet he could sort of chuckle at the end and say, “Well, I didn't
                    win on that one.” He's probably not typical. He's not the Gromyko style. He's
                    another style.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the things I've heard repeated over the years is
                        that Foreign Service officers are not really trained in negotiation and
                        we're used to too much conciliation and all this. You said this is the first
                        real negotiation you had. Did you feel like a virgin at an orgy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Stu, really not at all, because you realize things when you look back. I
                    hadn't been in charge, but I had done an awful lot of negotiation of the St.
                    Lawrence Seaway, and that meant often I was doing some of it by myself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And with the Canadians, who we said are rough
                        negotiators.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Who are friends, but tough. Dealing with the NATO Council for nine months
                    as the charg� meant that I was negotiating with people all the time, I realized.
                    Actually, after the first, say, month, I didn't feel particularly ill at ease in
                    the negotiation. In fact, I felt comfortable enough at the negotiation that I
                    started a process by which every couple of months I tried to change who my
                    experts were so that I would develop a group of people in Embassy Moscow and
                    back in Washington and in the Pentagon who were familiar with all that was going
                    on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they would be back in the seats of places where it
                        would be important</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: For example, I had, among the people who advised me from the Soviet world,
                    I had Mark Garrison out of Embassy Moscow, who was later the DCM and charg�
                    there, I had Stape Roy, I had Curt Kamman, all of these people distinguished in
                    our Soviet world. Each one as a younger officer came through and spent a time
                    with me. I felt comfortable enough that I didn't mind having new people coming
                    in. I'd have to admit. I had more fun probably than anything else I've ever done
                    in my whole career, because I was totally in charge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Speaking about negotiating techniques as an American, did
                        you have your two weeks of bluster that you would go and make things for the
                        record?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: No. I never did it for the following reason. I might have if the situation
                    had called for it. In fact, I always counted it as one of the higher compliments
                    I got from a very distinguished Swedish ambassador who was there, who had been
                    in Moscow and was a superb man, Ambassador Ruding. Our two governments were not
                    intimate at that time. In fact, they were very cold, very cold.</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, no. With the Vietnam War on, we were down to sub-zero
                        as far as relations at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: But Ruding one day said to me, “I know what you're doing, and I just want
                    to say I think it's exactly right. We do not want this conference to degenerate
                    into a slanging match between the Soviets and the United States. That will
                    obscure everything else. It will change the tone, and it will make it impossible
                    for the rest of us to keep working and emerge with what we want. You've managed
                    to be clear and firm and you never have been angry or intemperate at all, and
                    that has meant that we have kept it a conference of the whole, instead of the
                    two big boys fighting.” So I never did, and it was a deliberate choice on my
                    part.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You really felt like you were in control of the
                        situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I knew I was in control of the situation because I could control, in point
                    of fact, I could control the NATO group. And there already was a European
                    Community group, which were some of the same countries but with Ireland. I could
                    control them, and through the Germans and the Scandinavians, we really
                    controlled the neutrals primarily, particularly Sweden, Austria, people like
                    that. So we really had the preponderance. There was never any question. If we
                    sat there, we could control what happened, and we did. Because we ended up with
                    a staged conference that we decided. We decided where and how it would be set
                    up. We decided what would be the agenda and how far human rights would play into
                    it. All of this was done as what we wanted. None of it was exactly what the
                    Soviets wanted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And mainly because of almost, I won't say a paralysis, but
                        because of the Kissinger-Rogers sort of impasse. You weren't getting people
                        breathing over your neck from Washington, which can ruin any good
                        negotiation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I can't resist just reporting one last one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, good. Please do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Because it symbolized so much this kind of thing. There was this impasse.
                    We were coming to the end of the preparatory talks. The question was, “Where
                    should the formal conferences take place?” It was agreed that the opening stage
                    would take place in Helsinki. The next stage would take place in Geneva, which
                    is more convenient for the mass of people. And then the third and final stage,
                    which would rap up and launch a document, where would that take place?</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>The Soviets and a great many others were saying, “Well, we'll just stay in
                    Geneva. It will be convenient.” The Scandinavians were saying, “No. To wrap it
                    up formally, let's come back. The third stage should be in Helsinki.” Well, this
                    got to be quite heated, and it was, I felt, obvious that the Russians preferred
                    to have it stay on in Geneva. There have been dozens of proclamations that came
                    out of Geneva, and who remembers which ones they are?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because now one thinks of Finland and that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: But if you're going to have something, it ought to be the Helsinki
                    document. It ought to be done in Helsinki. Well, the arguments were going on.
                    Meanwhile, I assured the Scandinavians, “I'm with you and I'll stay with you
                    until the end. We're going to argue this third phase has to be in Helsinki and
                    it'll be a Helsinki document, not a Geneva document.”</p>
                <p>I let them know in Washington when the last decisive meeting was going to be, and
                    Washington let me know that they couldn't get any guidance out to me because
                    there was enough confusion back in Washington. They didn't say with whom, about
                    what, but just that they couldn't get any guidance to me, which was fine. So I
                    said, “Fine. I'm going to do what I want.”</p>
                <p>We were having our meeting in the Conference Center, which is just outside
                    Helsinki, the last meeting to decide this. And I got a telephone message passed
                    to me from the embassy saying a telegram with guidance had come in from
                    Washington and was classified. So I immediately responded, “Since it's
                    classified, you cannot tell me anything over the phone so I suggest you send a
                    courier out with the message.” Meanwhile, I roundly supported the Swedes and the
                    Norwegians and the Danes that it would be Helsinki for the third phase.</p>
                <p>We were getting near the end of our argument and it was going to have to be
                    agreed, and when the courier came with the envelope for me with the
                    instructions. It was one of the few times, just like a little play, and he tried
                    to hand it to me. I said, “Not now, I'm busy.” So he kept saying, “Here's this
                    instruction,” and I kept saying, “Just not now.” I supported them to the end. We
                    firmly agreed the last phase would be in Helsinki and that it would be the
                    Helsinki document, and I opened my instructions and they said I was to support
                    Geneva. [Laughter] Obviously Kissinger had been gotten to and they let it go
                    through.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's so interesting because, George, looking back on it
                        now, everybody thinks of the Helsinki Accords, and they know exactly what
                        you're talking about. But, as you say, the Geneva thing, my God, what are
                        you talking about? I mean, hundreds of things have gone on there, it doesn't
                        mean anything. If nothing else, from a very strong PR side. I mean, you're
                        always hearing about the Helsinki group and this and that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>VEST: The Helsinki process.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Was this in your mind at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes. And it was clearly in the minds of the Scandinavians. The
                    Scandinavians, this Ambassador Ruding whom I referred to, who is still alive,
                    but up in Sweden retired, felt very clearly that we were beginning a process, if
                    it made any difference at all, if it was to matter, we were going to have to
                    call it something special and make it be something special. And there was no
                    question in their minds that's what they were doing. I thought they were right,
                    and I was delighted to go right with them. [Laughter] And I might say, the whole
                    group of the European Community countries were right there with them, as well.
                    And the neutrals were, so there was nobody but the Warsaw Pact and the Soviets,
                    and they caved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Their ideas was they knew the same thing, and they were
                        trying to dilute this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: They were trying to dilute it. They hoped to be able to move it all to
                    Geneva and gradually dilute the whole process. Now, of course, conceivably they
                    could have diluted the process in Geneva, and it would mean nothing. But what
                    you did have was something that continued to be fought on in Geneva so that when
                    you did ratify it, you had something worth ratifying.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was in it for the Soviets to get this
                        agreement?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: What was what?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was in it for the Soviets to go along with this
                        agreement?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I believe the Soviets hoped—and here it's very general coming from me—that
                    in this whole activity, they would gradually get the western grouping plus
                    neutrals, which started out very close, that they would gradually get some of
                    the western countries to move over and be more neutralist. In other words, they
                    could divide the western camp. And, of course, in the western camp you have
                    neutral-minded people, certainly in Denmark and Norway, among others, and they
                    were hoping they could split the west.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>Years later, I ran into Mendelevich. He was in Washington. They were about to
                    begin in the Carter years on an Indian Ocean negotiation which never got
                    underway. And I think he must have had a little bit to drink or something
                    because we were upstairs on the seventh floor and I said, “Well, I'm delighted
                    to see you're taking on another negotiation with us.” And he said, “Yes. You
                    Americans won the last one. I'm going to win this one.” [Laughter] He recognized
                    that the west had won that negotiation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't know how much I can presume upon you. How are you
                        doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Stop the button for one minute. [Tape interruption]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Coming from this set of negotiations, then you became the
                        director of the Bureau of Political and Military Affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: No. Then I didn't do that either.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I usually can figure out who did what, but yours is
                        confusing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: One of those unusual things happened. I went on to Geneva, and was only in
                    Geneva a short time for this CSCE negotiation when Henry Kissinger took over as
                    Secretary of State. And Kissinger, I have always assumed, prompted by Larry
                    Eagleburger, who knew me well and had worked with me, invited me to come back
                    and be the press spokesman. So I was the press spokesman for Henry Kissinger
                    when he took over as Secretary of State, and I did it for about eight months,
                    throughout most of the shuttle diplomacy. Traveled with him, dealt with the
                    press, and went out to Moscow with him, and all the things you do as a press
                    spokesman. But we were not really a very compatible couple as a press spokesman,
                    and eventually I just went in one morning and said, “I think you would be
                    happier and I would be happier if you get another press spokesman,” so he did.
                    Then he gave me another job. I thought I was going to be fired, but I didn't get
                    fired.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression, let's say at this time when you
                        were the spokesman—later on there will be other times—but your impression of
                        Henry Kissinger. These were the first few months of him as Secretary of
                        State.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: These were the first few months and a period when the presidency was more
                    and more under attack, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. It was during the Watergate period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Watergate was building. It was all right there.</p>
                <p>I think he's about the most complex person I've ever had to try to fathom and get
                    along with. He is brilliant. He is brilliantly articulate. He is very insecure
                    as a human being. He is capable of what I consider to be either childish, or
                    playfully misleading, to outright deception, and almost enjoying each them as
                    sort of a game. He's extraordinarily sensitive. That goes with the insecurity.
                    He is capable of being cruel, cruel to the point of sadism, and yet it's not
                    always that. I mean, frequently he does believe you get results from contrived
                    competition.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you give any examples that you can think of on how he
                        operated in this field of contrived competition, cruelty?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It was so much a matter of his day-to-day activity that it would be hard
                    to. I can't really pull a single thing out. What is equally remarkable about
                    this hopeless man to work around was, he brought together, because of his gifts,
                    he also brought together a group of extraordinarily talented, dedicated people
                    who continued to work in this context. I mean, people like Larry Eagleburger,
                    Win Lord, Joe Sisco, Roy Atherton. You know, you can go right on through. There
                    were superb people who worked for him. Personally, I admired his qualities,
                    particularly his capacity, of his brilliance, to try to look ahead to perceive
                    further down the road. Not a quality that Americans are very much given to.
                    Well, I admired it all. I found him such a distasteful human being to be around,
                    closely around. This is why I left as a press spokesman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did he treat you? I mean, as his press spokesman, in
                        some ways, is supposed to be the Secretary's alter ego the way it's
                        used.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I would have to say he was very, and basically, he was pretty nice to me. I
                    had one episode, which early on may have been the best episode one could have. I
                    came in and he was going to brief me for the noon briefing, which he normally
                    did each day. We had a little talk about what to say and what to avoid. And the
                    phone rang and it was Al Haig, then heading the NSC. I offered to leave the
                    room, and Kissinger said, “No, just go over there by the window and wait.” And
                    they were talking about the deputy Secretary of State, Ken Rush, and I could
                    tell from the conversation that Haig was saying that they were thinking about
                    having Ken Rush come over and be one of the counselors in the White House. And
                    Kissinger said, “Look. This man is so stupid.” He went on and on in the most
                    derogatory terms about what an ass he was and how hopeless he was, and if there
                    was one thing he didn't want, he didn't want that kind of a man in the White
                    House.” And he told Al Haig, “Whatever you do, prevent that from happening,
                    because this man is a mess. He's not worth anything.”</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>He then picked up the phone and called Rush and said in the most endless, syrupy
                    way, “Ken, I've had some rumor that you might be wanted to go somewhere else,
                    and I just want you to know that I can't possibly get along without you. There's
                    no known way I can carry all the burdens I'm doing if I didn't have you here.
                    You are my strong right arm, etc., etc., etc. And I depend on you, and so on and
                    so on.” And when it was all over, I just turned to him and said, “Mr. Secretary,
                    anytime you're not satisfied with the way I do my job, please just tell it to me
                    straight. I'm a Foreign Service officer. I can go off and do something else.
                    Don't beat around the bush. Just tell me you don't like the way I'm doing
                    something.” In retrospect, that was probably the healthiest thing I ever did,
                    because it set a sort of relationship.</p>
                <p>He was devious. Then I also early on found I had another situation. I remember we
                    were in London, and I had a telephone call. I was in his suite at the time, and
                    I had a telephone call from one of the major newspaper pundits saying, “I hear
                    Henry Kissinger is saying all kinds of nasty things about my newest columns, and
                    I'm very unhappy and I just want to make sure he knows how upset I am about
                    this.” And I knew that I'd heard Henry Kissinger saying all kinds of nasty
                    things and I said, “Well, Joe, don't worry. I'll make sure that this message is
                    passed.”</p>
                <p>Secretary Kissinger came back. I told him about it, and he said, “Well, call him
                    back right away and tell him that those reports that he's heard, that those
                    reports are all lies.”</p>
                <p>Now I knew they weren't lies. So I thought a minute and I said, “Well, very well,
                    Mr. Secretary. I will call him back and tell him that you say they are all
                    lies.”</p>
                <p>And he thought about that a minute, and he said, “Well, on further thought, maybe
                    I'd better call him myself.” But there was that kind of an uncertainty, as far
                    as I was concerned.</p>
                <p>Brilliant. Nobody can question that. But for a Secretary of State, there are two
                    or three qualities. One is brilliance, far-seeing thought. Another is
                    reliability. You know, when I look at various Secretaries of State, I have a
                    feeling that there are a great many times when Mr. Vance and Mr. Shultz got more
                    trust and more out—certainly of our friends in other countries—because they had
                    total confidence in these two men. And they could not be sure, particularly as
                    time has gone on and he was making all his stories and telling what he's told,
                    they could not be sure of Henry Kissinger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it goes back to what you learned in Quito, and that
                        is you never lie as a diplomat. The Secretary of State is the top
                        diplomat.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you run across when you were there, or maybe even
                        later on because we're talking about Henry Kissinger, about, say, the
                        problem that I've had come up in some of these interviews, particularly
                        about Iran where you don't report on the—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Maybe we better stop.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why don't we stop right here. [Tape interruption]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>One thing I'd like to ask—we're talking about Henry Kissinger—in the people
                    around you and what you knew, what was some of the impressions that they had of
                    dealing with him? In some of these interviews I've heard horror stories, for
                    example, in Iran of saying, “Don't report anything against the Shah. The Shah's
                    our friend, and only report on one side on this.” This is to the political
                    counselor, Andy Kilgore. I mean, there are things of this nature of wanting to
                    have everything fit within a framework. Were there mutterings within the Foreign
                    Service and the State Department because of this?</p>
                <p>VEST: There were mutterings. I first ran up against it when I took over as
                    director of the political and military office. I hadn't been there too long
                    before the question came up of giving a certain...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from 1974 to '77?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes, that's right. After I resigned as press spokesman, thinking it was the
                    end of my career, again I didn't understand Henry Kissinger. He sent word and
                    asked me if I'd like to be—he was on his honeymoon; I had arranged it and then
                    given up the job—and he said, “Would you like to do this job?” and I said,
                    “Well, sure.” So there I was.</p>
                <p>There was a very, very delicate missile system which hadn't been given to
                    anybody, and there were many reasons why it shouldn't be given to the Shah. He
                    had heard about it. And I felt, well, at least we should argue and put all the
                    aspects up to Henry Kissinger before we went along with the disposition of the
                    military to go ahead and make this missile system available to the Shah. The
                    only evidence that I deliberately came up against of the kind of thing you're
                    talking about was a number of people said to me, “There isn't any point in doing
                    anything like that. He doesn't want to hear that. He's got his general rule
                    already made up. Anything the Shah wants, the Shah will get, so there's no point
                    in even trying to tell him there's a down side to any of it.” We sent up, I
                    would have to say, a relatively moderate message, a memo, to the Secretary on
                    the disadvantages of this, and as far as I know, it was never read. I've never
                    had any evidence that anyone had ever received it.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about in other matters? Was there the feeling, well,
                        let's not present too many things to the Secretary because once he has made
                        up his mind, that's it and this is a windmill against which not to
                        tilt?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I really can't say, because there was a strange mixture in Henry Kissinger.
                    Certainly, some people constantly gave him things he didn't want to listen to.
                    Win Lord was one, and Win Lord saw it as his job heading the policy planning
                    staff to stimulate Henry Kissinger to think about areas he didn't want to think
                    about. Economics and agriculture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: South America and Africa.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: South America and Africa. You know, a whole series of these. And Henry
                    Kissinger respected Win Lord enough that he would stop and look over, but there
                    was only a small handful of people for whom he would stop. Now once he stopped,
                    he was very serious. I was involved in it because Win Lord put up to him the
                    problem of nuclear energy—this is public nuclear energy—nuclear energy
                    proliferation which could proliferate into a military danger, and made Henry
                    interested enough so that Henry authorized the nuclear negotiation with the
                    major countries—Russia, Japan, Britain, Canada, Germany and so on, France. And I
                    did the nuclear supplier negotiation for Mr. Kissinger, which ran on for about a
                    year and a half, and we worked out the basic nuclear supplier guidelines for the
                    nuclear supplier countries, which are still the fundamental guide on what kind
                    of technology and material you sell and turnover to other people.</p>
                <p>Now Henry Kissinger wasn't interested in this at all, but Win Lord got him to do
                    it. He got him to Africa. [Laughter] But you had to be very, very sure of
                    yourself in dealing with Kissinger, and only a few people were that sure. Win
                    Lord was, Larry Eagleburger was, Hal Saunders was, who worked in the Bureau of
                    Near Eastern Affairs. They were among the few who really could make Henry
                    Kissinger stop and think about something. He had the understandable arrogance,
                    intellectual arrogance, of a man who's normally right and normally sees further
                    than most other people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, isn't there, too, the problem of somebody who looks
                        upon the world as something which you can manipulate. Therefore, this is
                        very, in a way, European, rather than what you're talking about. Looking at
                        your career, which is essentially a very random one which is bouncing over,
                        but one can look at it and say, “Well, you're a European specialist and you
                        did this and that.” I mean, it looks like a very well- planned, thought-out
                        career, and it's not. You then moved down to the Bureau of Political
                        Military Affairs. What did that mean at the time? What did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>VEST: A very strange mixed bag, I discovered. Technically, we were responsible to
                    be involved in MBFR negotiations, and had some people who were true experts in
                    that area. But Henry Kissinger normally had that taken care of by Hal
                    Sonnenfeldt. We had, and did carry through, all of the negotiations and
                    activities and follow-up activities associated with bases worldwide that led you
                    to everything from Diego Garcia in the middle of the Indian Ocean, special
                    activities with Australia and other nations out in the Pacific, or elsewhere.
                    There were a great many political and military arrangements with one country or
                    another which, for the most part, were relatively highly classified. We did
                    manage all of those negotiations and were the linchpin with the Defense
                    Department for all of that.</p>
                <p>We did the same thing for the control of the sale of military hardware. The
                    Political and Military Bureau controls, is the controller, licenser, for the
                    sale of a great percentage of our military hardware if it's being just publicly
                    sold and bought by people in the country. We were the manager for the complete
                    military supply arrangements worldwide. Wherever there was security assistance,
                    it was centrally run and controlled out of the Political and Military Bureau.
                    That and many others. I mean, it was also one of those areas when we got to the
                    question of what should we do about, as I mentioned earlier, the regular nuclear
                    supply issues, there was a question where it would go. In the end, it was put in
                    the Political and Military Bureau, although it might well have been in the
                    Scientific Bureau. And in fact, the assistant secretary was Dixie Lee Ray,
                    former head of the AEC.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For oceans and scientific affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: In all of that. And in the end, it was put in the Political and Military
                    Bureau, and I given the negotiation responsibility for all those things. So it
                    was somewhat of a mixed bag. It did not get into the heartland, SALT, and MBFR
                    negotiations, which it might normally have done, but Kissinger carefully kept
                    that to Sonnenfeldt and his own little sort of inner grouping. I knew that was
                    just one of the things you had to face.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: George, I'm working now with our oral history program to
                        develop a set of interviews using- -Tom Stern is working on this- -to do a
                        set of interviews on arms sales. Because this is something, again to
                        somebody not involved in this, looks like we're doing an awful lot. We talk
                        peace, peace, peace, but when the chips are down, our bargaining chips seems
                        to be send some more tanks or airplanes to countries, particularly to the
                        Middle East. We are proliferating weapons all over the place in competition
                        or something with the French and the British and the Israelis and the
                        Soviets. When you were there—we're talking about '74 to '77—how did the
                        bureau view weapons being sold or given to various countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: We had a general policy guidance which, generally speaking, was very
                    permissive. I just have to say that was the normal approach.</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was the philosophy behind</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: The philosophy was a combination in the positive sense. We may not be able
                    to give you money to influence you, but we can give you arms and that will
                    influence you. And on the negative sense, if we don't do it, someone else will.
                    I'm just extrapolating in the simplistic way. But there was very little question
                    in that period that we should be involved in it.</p>
                <p>Now for me it was an interesting evolution, because when in 1958 I was engaged
                    with Norstad in the sale—or delivery in many cases, not the sale—of any amount
                    of military hardware to restore our NATO allies to strength. So that was one
                    kind of basis. But by the time I came back to it again in this period in the mid
                    '70s, it was a tool for influence with no particular rationale as to restraint.
                    It had become accepted as a tool of influence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because I think it obviously is wide open to question. I
                        mean, looking at it today, do you make for a better world by putting your
                        money into swords and not into plowshares, and then dumping them in places
                        where they can be used.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you're saying that there weren't people, a la George
                        Ball, or somebody like this, saying, “Hey, wait a minute. What are we
                        doing?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Not in Henry Kissinger's time, not at all. It was not a part of his sort of
                    rare politic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How much did the arms merchants play? I mean, did you find
                        yourself being sort of their salesmen? Or were they influential? Was this
                        mainly policy or was this arms?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: If there were arms sales influences, they came in through the Pentagon.
                    They didn't come to us in the Political and Military Bureau at all. And I know
                    they did have their influence, because that was when I first began to be offered
                    outside jobs. [Laughter] I won't mention which arms companies and which aircraft
                    companies came to me and asked me would I like to retire and work for them. My
                    wife and I discussed it, and I said, “No, we don't need money.” [Laughter] But,
                    no, it didn't affect us.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have the feeling that the Pentagon, in savings of
                        quantity or whatever you might say, was pushing the delivery of sales, or is
                        it just the only thing they knew to play with and hand out guns?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Honestly, Stu, I had no real feeling one way or the other. The level of
                    people that I was dealing with in ISA, when we talked about arms sales and
                    deliveries and special terms and all the rest to go to this or that place, there
                    was always a rationale attached to it. We want to strengthen this part of the
                    world and we want to short circuit this or that and so on. So there was always a
                    rationale given, but there was very little thought given to the fact that, well,
                    maybe it would just be better not to spread those arms around at all. I mention
                    the one time that we tried and it didn't get anywhere. The idea was clearly that
                    whatever the Shah wanted, he should have.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I must say that, although I didn't follow these
                        things. I mean, I was on the normal Foreign Service gossip circuit and all
                        and it was in the papers and all, but there was real concern of what the
                        hell are we doing in Iran, of dumping all these things there. This is not a
                        very safe place. I mean, it wasn't a surprise, and there was great concern,
                        both in public and sort of, at least in the Foreign Service, about putting
                        this stuff there. But you were there, part of the pipeline. What did you
                        feel about this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: As I said, we tried just once and then I was told very clearly, “Look,
                    there's a policy decision.” I thought it was foolish and short-sighted and I
                    regretted it, but I'd have to say I didn't take it much further.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I was wondering. Were there any people who dealt
                        with the Middle East who had come by and say, “George, my God. You know,
                        Iran just isn't that stable a place”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It's interesting. Out of everybody in that building in that period that I
                    can remember, I remember only one person who came by—and maybe I didn't know
                    some of the people who were worrying, obviously—but I just remember one person,
                    who was in the policy planning staff, who was deeply upset and felt, “Look,
                    we're getting ourselves way down into something very, very wrong and ultimately
                    dangerous. We shouldn't be sending all of this there at this stage. We're
                    feeding somebody who's not got the right balance.” And this particular person in
                    the policy planning staff in due course fell into disfavor, I noticed. In fact,
                    he left the Government after that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>VEST: I cannot think of his name right away. Oh, I know. Tom Thornton. But I
                    didn't get it from anyone else. Nobody in the Bureau of Near Eastern Affairs
                    ever came by emitting even a moo of discontent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the pouring of arms both into Israel, and then
                        were you there when we were beginning to do it into Egypt?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: We had many discussions about the fact that we seemed to be buying an
                    arrangement between Israel and Egypt by virtue of giving them almost the most of
                    our aid and an enormous amount of our military equipment and, among other
                    things, also talking about nuclear reactors before we were through. There were
                    big arguments, but they were, I would have to say, I was not allowed to be part
                    of it. But this was a very large and very precise policy decision which the
                    Secretary of State took at the level of his top advisors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Am I right in saying the Bureau of Political and Military
                        Affairs was, at least in policy matters, there would be the Near Eastern
                        Bureau and the European Bureau, which would be at basically a somewhat
                        higher level in the technical?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Absolutely right. I would say that the Bureau of Political and Military
                    Affairs distinctly had a second rank in all these matters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It technically was of equal rank?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Well, all bureaus are technically alike in point of fact. Normally the
                    geographic bureaus have the largest say in life. This is a natural consequence
                    of the structure in the State Department. Other bureaus from time to time have
                    more weight—INR, Pol-Mil, international organizations, policy planning staff and
                    that sort. Certainly in the period when I was there, I would say it was strictly
                    in a second-class category.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would like to move on then when you moved to the next
                        higher ramp, which was the assistant secretary for EUR, which has always
                        been of, I think one can almost say, paramount interest. When the chips are
                        down, our concern about European Affairs has remained constant, whereas from
                        time to time in the Middle East they'll flare up and in the Far East. Never
                        for Africa or Latin America, except for aberrations under recent
                        administration. How did this job come about? You were there from 1977 to
                        '81, which is exactly the Carter years.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>VEST: How it came about is very clear cut. Chance is the largest element, and
                    it's really quite true. [Laughter] In fact, I was due to go to be the ambassador
                    to Pakistan. I had the agr�ment, everything. What happened was the Carter
                    Administration offered the job of ambassador to Paris to three— or maybe four, I
                    don't know; Art Hartman might know—political appointees, each of which turned it
                    down.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good God.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: So, for whatever their Democratic reasons were, and the White House said to
                    Secretary Vance, new in this job, “Would you like to send a career officer to be
                    the ambassador to France?” So he had known him for sometime before and he was
                    still there, Arthur Hartman, was at that stage our assistant secretary for
                    European affairs. Vance asked Arthur, “Would you like to be the ambassador to
                    France?” and in whatever length of time was necessary, Arthur said, “But, yes.”
                    After which they looked around, as I understand it, and said, “And now if you're
                    going to go there, we've got to get a replacement.” And I don't know who
                    recommended me to Mr. Vance, but I was due to go up the next day to appear
                    before the Foreign Relations Committee to go to Pakistan, and I was told by Mr.
                    Vance, “Don't go. I want you to be the assistant secretary for European
                    affairs.” And I've never known whether it was Arthur Hartman's doing or whose
                    doing, but anyway, it was just like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the transition work between the Ford
                        Administration and the Carter Administration, because the next change was
                        not a nice one in a way? But how about between these two?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: This transition, as far as I could see it, was a very neat and comfortable
                    one. Vance and Brzezinski and the others who were coming down who would have
                    something to do with foreign policy, from at least some of my observation had a
                    very clear picture as to whom they wanted to bring down to do jobs. But they
                    were very considerate of the outgoing administration. Secretary Kissinger was
                    able to say to Secretary Vance, “I have these people I recommend to you, and I
                    think you should do something for them.”</p>
                <p>Instead of the people being considered suspect, Mr. Vance carefully took note of
                    that. I mean, these were the people who had worked for Kissinger. Arthur Hartman
                    went to Paris. Larry Eagleburger went to Belgrade. I took over as assistant
                    secretary for European affairs. There could hardly have been more open kind of
                    treatment than we had right then and there. And Roy Atherton went as ambassador
                    to Cairo. So, you see, we were given very, very, I would say, courteous,
                    thoughtful treatment.</p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>Similarly, as we took over, and I can say this as assistant secretary of European
                    affairs, there was never any reserve at all from the word go. You had been given
                    that job, you were given the credit that you were going to be a true
                    professional, honest advisor to the best of your ability and you were part of
                    the team. And we were treated that way from the beginning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did this come from? Was this from the President, do
                        you think? Or was it Vance?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I think it was primarily Mr. Vance. Mr. Vance had had long experience in
                    government. He had worked under several administrations. He didn't have the
                    least hesitation about what he expected and how he wanted them to do, and people
                    responded to him. Now he brought with him an inner group, as does everybody,
                    Dick Moose and quite a number of them, but I would have to say within a matter
                    of a month, they were all working very, very comfortably together with those of
                    us who had stayed on from the other administration. I didn't have a feeling of
                    being a second-class type at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a feeling of a shifting of policy gears as
                        far with the new administration? I mean, a real major shift as far as
                        European affairs were concerned?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: No. Fundamentally, no. A couple of things were. Europe is one of the
                    easiest places to have continuity. Major areas when you look at it. You have a
                    Soviet Union with whom you wish to explore when it's possible. That didn't
                    change, because you went right on with your SALT-type negotiations. Western
                    allies strong support for NATO never changed at all. Carter went right off to a
                    heads of government meeting in London.</p>
                <p>Support for the European Community, that continued as well. There was never any
                    question about that, and we didn't happen to have very large economic
                    dislocations at that point. Support for the military. What is not normally
                    realized is that in conjunction with all this, Carter began a rather careful
                    increase of military budgets, military support, which is all again tied into
                    western Europe.</p>
                <p>Eastern Europe, for in spite of anything which might have been said by Mr.
                    Brzezinski, we continued just what had existed before, which was a policy of
                    looking at each member of the Warsaw Pact as an individual, separate entity with
                    which you tried to do business, and it might be different depending on how that
                    particular country acted. So the larger policy directions, it seemed to me, were
                    still being carried forward. This is more true probably of Europe than it would
                    be of anyplace else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. You couldn't play the human rights angle or things
                        like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>VEST: You can play the human rights angle, but only up to a point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then that would only be in eastern Europe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: And that would only be in eastern Europe, and you cannot force our allies
                    to go but so far. You began to have your differences when the Soviets acted up.
                    For example, the Soviets go into Iran—I mean Afghanistan—you've got a problem.
                    What do you do about the Olympics? You see that. Then you begin to have
                    differences of attitude of how to react to something, but our fundamental
                    relationships stayed on track.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the role of Brzezinski as you saw it then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Brzezinski for me is a little hard to keep in perspective, because you had
                    a very interesting phenomenon. You had Henry Kissinger act to head the NSC and
                    completely distort the emphasis that had been there and for which it was
                    originally set up. And then along came Brzezinski—and very interesting with his
                    background and Kissinger's background— Brzezinski set out, if anything, to outdo
                    Kissinger. He is, by my standards, a sort of small-bore Kissinger. Noisier, but
                    less wise. He had very strong antipathies. I mean, he was by temperament so
                    strongly anti-Soviet—or anti-Russian—and anti- German. These are things that
                    only a Pole could so strongly be, and it came out over and over again.</p>
                <p>He was ready at the beginning of the four years of the Carter Administration, he
                    was ready to believe that the Germans are just about to have another Rapallo,
                    look out. I mean, which was completely silly at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Another what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Another Rapallo.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, a Rapallo. Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: An agreement with the east.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Rapallo Pact of 1920-something.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>VEST: Yes. He was so worried about the Soviets, when we got ready to set up a
                    committee that would pull together all of the actions of the various agencies of
                    government in relation to the Soviets as we opened up our way of doing things
                    with them, that initially he was going to insist that that committee had to be
                    chaired by him, or somebody over in the NSC. I went to him and I said, “You
                    know, that is a fundamental policy responsibility of the Secretary of State, and
                    I won't agree to it. I will take it to Mr. Vance, and I believe Mr. Vance will
                    take it to the President.” And we had really quite a knockdown, drag out
                    discussion of it.</p>
                <p>I had known Brzezinski and his deputy both before.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who's his deputy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: His deputy was...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We can fill it in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It'll come back. As a young Foreign Service officer, he worked for me in
                    the '60s—David Aaron—and I knew David very well and had kept up with him
                    casually when he left the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>But Brzezinski was so worried about Marshall Shulman, whom he thought was
                    terribly soft on the Russians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Marshall Shulman was...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Was the special senior advisor on Soviet affairs in the State Department
                    for Mr. Vance.In the end, I persuaded Brzezinski, “Let us set up this committee
                    and Marshall Shulman and I will be joint chairmen for the committee, and we will
                    always insist that you have a senior representative from the NSC sitting on the
                    committee,” which is the way we got around it. But he was very suspicious. He
                    was very intrusive. He did not play fair. He would do things behind people's
                    back. Mr. Vance, I know many times, complained about it, and Mr. Vance is the
                    kind of person who never spoke ill of anybody. He was one of those greatly
                    reserved and dignified gentlemen.</p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>One day he and I were, I think it was in Italy, and we were swimming in the
                    ambassadorial swimming pool after one of those big dinners, and we would paddle
                    up and down. Vance and I were alone there. The guard was standing nearby. And he
                    said in an outburst—which for him was an outburst—he said, “What I cannot
                    understand about Brzezinski is, you know, over and over he lies to me.” And Mr.
                    Vance, couldn't believe that someone in that position would just lie to him.</p>
                <p>And I said to Mr. Vance, “Well, I know what you mean, but I think Brzezinski is
                    fundamentally in many ways an adolescent who thinks it's fun to try to get
                    around and to tell stories and get around somebody. There's no other explaining
                    an adult acting the way he does.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Secretary Vance's interest in European affairs as
                        opposed to other ones? How did you deal with him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Mr. Vance was very, very close to the other foreign ministers of the major
                    western powers— Genscher, Peter Carrington, the French, the Italians, and so on.
                    He is a living example—I mentioned earlier—that you can build up trust and it
                    can take you far, and these other foreign ministers certainly had confidence in
                    him. I can't cite you an example, but I can just remember so many. I just have
                    this picture over and over again. When he told them something—in the earlier
                    time it was David Owen, not Peter Carrington—when he told them something nobody
                    ever questioned that Mr. Vance was telling them the nearest thing to the truth
                    that he could give. In other words, they trusted him and respected him.</p>
                <p>And when we were talking to them about what was going on in Iran, when we wanted
                    them to freeze Iranian assets, when we talked to them about what was our policy
                    in response to Afghanistan, he was someone who they just totally respected. It
                    was a period when as time went by, as you know, the President's public prestige
                    went down, down, down, not necessarily correct that it should have, but it did.
                    And all of that was being picked up in the newspapers and repeated in the
                    European newspapers, and in that context, when Mr. Vance said something, they
                    listened. In Germany, especially, this was the case. I would say in Germany, it
                    was the most valuable of them all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm going to ask. Looking back on this period, I would
                        think that our relationship with Germany was probably the most crucial in
                        that period. Would you agree with me?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And this was not helped by the fact that we had two men,
                        one named Carter and the other was Helmut Schmidt, who, I take it, it was
                        almost visceral, a dislike between the two. Is this a correct
                        perception?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: This is a correct perception, but you'd have to also make it a three-man
                    operation, because Brzezinski was there feeding Carter all the time. Now, Helmut
                    Schmidt was not one of the easy people in the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was at that time a chancellor of West Germany?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: He was the chancellor. He was very pro- American underneath. He was very
                    pro-NATO. He was keeping the Socialist Party of Germany on the moderate
                    direction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was head of the Socialist Party.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: A bulk, probably a majority of the Socialists, would have gone further to
                    the left, and he was keeping them where he did in relation to our activities in
                    NATO, in relation to the Soviets, you know, whatever you want to call it. Every
                    time there was a chance, Brzezinski would add to the problem, and there were
                    many episodes when I watched it. I mean, I can remember when it's typical of
                    it.</p>
                <p>We had a visit. There was a question of what you should say in relation to the
                    Middle East. Von Schaden, representing the Germans, and I sat down and we worked
                    out a public statement, which I think was a fair public statement. It certainly
                    was acceptable to Hal Saunders and Roy Atherton, who were the Near Eastern
                    experts. And when it was telephone over to the White House, Brzezinski went to
                    the President and said, “Oh, this is much too difficult. This is not something
                    we should say. Much too hard on Israel,” blaming Schmidt for causing all the
                    trouble when this was not something that Schmidt himself had negotiated nor had
                    any of us. It was the compromise we thought we'd found.</p>
                <p>Later at the dinner, I happened to be talking to Carter, and he mentioned it, you
                    know. I said, “What a splendid toast you'd given.” He said, “Well, I don't owe
                    him anything after what he did on that statement on the Middle East.” So he
                    clearly was blaming Schmidt when Schmidt wasn't the one.</p>
                <p>Later Schmidt, in the middle of the SALT treaty, Schmidt had been to Bohemian
                    Grove—interesting enough, I think as the guest of George Shultz, then of
                    Bechtel.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bohemian Grove being a fancy place up in the Redwoods that
                        rich industrialists and all used, outside of San Francisco.VEST: The most
                        powerful people of the west gather for that meeting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>He flew in. We had total warning. We all knew about it. Ambassador Von Schaden
                    and I went out. It was said that Brzezinski would be out at the airport. Schmidt
                    would just step down and then transfer to a German military plane and go on from
                    Dulles. We got there and we waited. Nobody turned up from the NSC. I telephoned.
                    They said, “Oh, Brzezinski has it all under control.” Brzezinski never turned
                    up. Nobody turned up.</p>
                <p>So Schmidt, the chancellor, gets out of the plane, nobody is there from the White
                    House to visit him after he's been told to expect somebody there, and I did the
                    best I could. I've known him for a number of years, and he had a meeting of the
                    press in which he proceeded to say, “Every European leader of any responsibility
                    whatsoever fully supports President Carter's magnificent SALT II treaty. We are
                    all delighted with it. His leadership is fundamental and indispensable for us
                    all.”</p>
                <p>He went right all the way through, because the press were there ready, primed by
                    the Senate discussion, to attack the SALT II treaty. He delivered it all, and
                    turned to me at the end as he was getting on the plane. I just drove out with
                    him, and as he got ready to go up the runway he said, “And now, George, I have
                    been a good boy.” [Laughter] Got on the plane, and God knows what he said to his
                    people on his way back to Germany. But, you know, just a common courtesy had
                    been turned into an insult, and he knew it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about Carter, Schmidt, and the neutron bomb? Was that
                        part of your business? You might explain what it is.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes. Well, the idea behind the neutron bomb— time has gone through enough,
                    Stu, I'm vague myself about much of it. But the idea was to have a particular
                    kind of bomb, and that you might even remember better than I what it's
                    functioning was and what made it so delicate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think, if I recall, it radiated. It other words, it
                        would kill people without killing property.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: That's right, it radiated. It would kill people without blowing up
                    buildings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And, although it was called the true capitalist thing
                        preserving property, I think the military rationale behind it was that if
                        you created too much rubble, it made the battlefield dirty in order to
                        operate.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>VEST: And it would be disadvantageous to you to do your job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To run your tanks or something like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: And that's why the bomb was created.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But it was not portrayed that way.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It became quickly portrayed as “it kills people.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And protects property.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Protects property. Nevertheless, we fought hard for it. All I can tell you
                    is the following. We took it up in NATO, and we took it up with the Germans and
                    the British as the key players in this. Both the Germans and the British had
                    agreed to back it. We even had a scenario, just like a play, in which everybody
                    was going to say in the NATO Council. So it was all clear, you know, what we
                    were going to do, and it was due to happen next week. The next thing I knew I
                    got a telephone call at home from Mr. Vance. It was on a Sunday, I think, but I
                    was at home, and he said, “George, I just want you to know that none of it is
                    going to happen. The President has vetoed the whole thing.”</p>
                <p>And I said, “Why?”</p>
                <p>And he said, “Well, I don't have enough details to be able to tell you here and
                    now on the phone.” What I was told later, I talked to people like Stu Eizenstat
                    and others who were in the White House. Stu Eizenstat said, “It was very clear.
                    Mr. Carter himself told me that Brzezinski himself told him that the Germans
                    were going to back out.”</p>
                <p>I said, “But the Germans weren't about to back out. They'd already signed on to a
                    whole scenario.” Well, that's what Mr. Carter believed was that the Germans were
                    going to back out so he would drop it first, even after we had gone so far. So,
                    in the end, that is what happened.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For you, the real cleanup came afterwards, didn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: The real cleanup came later. I accompanied Warren Christopher, the Deputy
                    Secretary of State, and we flew over to Germany to try to explain. . .</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The inexplicable.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: . . . to the Germans. We first stopped in Bonn and saw Genscher, who was
                    relieved to have the thing go because he particularly didn't like it. And then
                    we flew onto Hamburg and called on Schmidt, and Schmidt was in his private home
                    there, and known to be a totally tempestuous man, at best.</p>
                <p>Christopher and I both were frankly very worried, and Ambassador Walt Stoessel
                    flew down from Bonn.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was our ambassador.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: He was our ambassador to Bonn. And the three of us met with Schmidt, and
                    the only other person there was Jurgen Ruhfus, who is now the German ambassador
                    to Washington, who was then the sort of chef de cabinet for Schmidt. Mrs.
                    Schmidt was there and saw us into the dining room. We all sat around the table.
                    She carefully served us all some beer and it was all very nice, and Schmidt was
                    very cool. He did make the point. He said, “You realize that I personally,
                    personally, had to threaten to resign to make the government in Bonn, the
                    Bundestag, agree to going ahead with this. And I only did this about a day and a
                    half ago, and now you have done this.”</p>
                <p>Mr. Christopher did the best one could of this, and I don't remember too much
                    what he said because it wasn't very easy and very convincing, and we left. And
                    flying out, the three of us, Stoessel, Christopher and I, Christopher said,
                    “Well, I don't understand. You warned me how tempestuous and difficult Schmidt
                    was, but he seemed to be very controlled. He didn't seem to be upset at
                    all.”</p>
                <p>Walt Stoessel and I both jumped in just about the same time saying exactly the
                    same thing, that, “Look, it's too serious to be excited about and lose your
                    self-control because, from his point of view, the leader of the free world has
                    just signaled to the world outside that he doesn't have the guts to follow
                    through on something.” And from Schmidt's point of view, that's what it was, and
                    he no longer had respect for Carter as a leader after that. And both Walt and I
                    agreed this is exactly what it was. And he was. He was just as cool as could be.
                    What a wonderful period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During that period, was there any other particular moments
                        or areas of major concern?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: In the earlier stages, we had Greece, Turkey. We had to resume—this was
                    almost more politics in our country than over there—we had to resume the sale
                    and delivery of arms to Turkey. We had stopped it because of the Cyprus
                    situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was the Cyprus situation in July of '74?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes. And we went to the Senate. It was approved. I met sort of steadily
                    with Sarbanes and Brademas and the other Greek-American people on the Hill.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's interesting how powerful the Greek lobby is. I mean,
                        one always thinks of the Israeli and Jewish lobby, but the Greek is
                        probably, well, second.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It's second. I mean, I've had a lot of personal experience with each.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Each being the congressional...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: The Jewish-American lobbies—and without any question, the most powerful
                    lobby in political terms inside our country—but I think equally there's no
                    question the Greek- American lobby, much, much smaller, much more pointed in its
                    concerns, is the next most effective. They are absolutely fantastically well
                    organized and able.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did we want to resume arms shipments to Turkey?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: You had the case of a NATO ally who, really, whose armaments were frankly
                    beginning to be out of date, limited. You know, the armed forces were getting to
                    be genuinely in a bad way. And as a NATO ally, you had two things. You were,
                    one, having an increasingly, poorly armed ally; and second, you were creating
                    increasing strains inside a society, which is a rather shallow, western-oriented
                    society where the military represented a major component factor. And so, in NATO
                    terms, there was a very, very strong desire to help, go ahead and modernize the
                    Turkish military.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Looking at it from both the NATO and the European...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: It wasn't having any affect on the Cyprus situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Looking at the Greek-Turkish business from the point of
                        view of European affairs—American view of European affairs— and NATO, how
                        important did we find Greece in this? Greece, in a way, seems to spend most
                        of its time pointed towards Turkey rather than Bulgaria or something like
                        that. Was Greece something we almost would discount and were more concerned
                        about Turkey from a military support of NATO point of view?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>VEST: You can never discount either one of them. Geographically, they are both in
                    extraordinary...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying that Greece points at Turkey, and Turkey
                        points at Greece, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: And both are absolutely delicate pieces of real estate in relation to the
                    eastern Mediterranean and the Soviet world, so you constantly have to try to
                    have them do something that is constructive and to have them point less at each
                    other. And that has been the role of these two countries inside NATO ever since
                    they joined. There's never been any major difference in this kind of approach on
                    their part. And it still is.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you deal with this? Was this something that you
                        spent a lot of time on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: The only thing I can say is I dealt with it by virtue of the fact that I
                    was good friends with the diplomatic people on both sides. And we were
                    constantly negotiating on Cyprus, trying to get the sides to come together in
                    Cyprus and to get the Turks, who were part of it, to work with us, and there
                    never was that opportune moment where the parties involved, all of them, really
                    were ready, because the Greek Cypriots never really wanted to settle, as far as
                    from my point of view.</p>
                <p>I had the good fortune that key people in the Greek foreign office were people I
                    had known, and the equivalent of assistant secretary for political military
                    affairs in the Turkish foreign office, one of the most powerful at that time
                    because he was the one the military trusted, he was someone I had known as a
                    junior officer when I started in NATO. He was their most recent ambassador here,
                    Ambassador Elekdag. He and I had known each other since we were very junior
                    officers, so I could always really speak very, very candidly and openly and work
                    with them.</p>
                <p>You did your best to soft-pedal the differences, to restrain them, and to remind
                    them that they had this other concern they needed to watch, as well. There are
                    only moments when Greeks and Turks are really ready to do things together, and
                    you have to capitalize on those moments. Now none of those moments honestly came
                    in the four years that I was assistant secretary for European affairs. A little
                    later, when Ozal more recently was made head of the Turkish Government, you hit
                    one of those moments and they've had a much better rapport. Not a rapport, but a
                    relationship, in more recent years. Otherwise, it's very difficult always.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before we move to your next assignment, were there any
                        other matters that maybe we should cover in the '77 to '81 period in
                        Europe?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                <p>VEST: I don't think so, but one. We talked about Mr. Vance's difficulties with
                    Brzezinski. I'd like to put in another kind of plug in terms of what can be
                    achieved with the NSC. I mentioned that I had the good fortune that David Aaron,
                    who was the deputy head of the NSC, I'd known at any earlier time when we were
                    younger and we had known and kept up with each casually.</p>
                <p>I worked with the NSC on European matters for four years. Successfully I had one,
                    whoever was the responsible one for European affairs. I never had formal
                    committees, or joint committees, with the NSC on Europe ever. I avoided them for
                    all four years, but I brought over whoever was responsible in the NSC for
                    European affairs frequently to have lunch with me, or I would go over and have
                    lunch with him. When I went overseas, I was very generous in inviting that
                    particular person, whoever was in the job at the time, to go along with me, as
                    long as they did not report independently.</p>
                <p>Once one of them reported independently and I could tell, and I called him in. I
                    said, “If it's ever done again, I'll never let you go anywhere with me again.
                    But if you want to be inside with me, fine. Don't ever report independently.”
                    And they never did, as far as I could see. But I took these people with me, and
                    when Brzezinski wanted a special IG (a high level study group with NSC), as they
                    called it, on Germany, I never had one. I just said, “I don't need one. We'll
                    keep talking here. We'll keep in touch.” So I had a very happy relationship in
                    that sense that I got along, we did the job. It took extra work, but then our
                    government was set up that way and we made it work. And the people who had that
                    job—one was Bob Blackwill, who is now over in the NSC working for the present
                    administration—and others, we got along all right. So you can make almost any—I
                    think the real essence of what I'm saying is, if you get people of reasonable
                    probity and reasonable goodwill, you can make anything work, even if it's the
                    wrong kind of structure. But it takes a little extra time, a little extra work.
                    But it did work, and I was very grateful to them because they played it straight
                    with me and we made it work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then a new administration came in, the Reagan
                        Administration, in 1981, in which for the first four years you served as the
                        ambassador to the European Communities. How did this come about, because I
                        would have thought this would have been a political plum for somebody? This
                        was as close to a hostile takeover as one can have ideologically, and there
                        was an awful lot, on the part of the Reagan Administration, of people who
                        have worked for the previous administration, even in professional
                        capacities, as being tainted, if not worse. So how did you get this
                        job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I'm not entirely sure, but you're quite right. I would have said I had
                    double jeopardy for that new crowd coming in. I had worked for Henry Kissinger
                    and for Carter. Either one of them was a little bit of a taint. [Laughter]</p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>There may have been several factors. Haig had known me. He had been Supreme
                    Allied Commander Europe, and an able one, when I was assistant secretary for
                    European affairs, so we knew each other vaguely, not well. Larry Eagleburger was
                    working closely. He had taken over as assistant secretary of the European
                    affairs, and he and I had known each other for years and we knew each other well
                    and were friends. So, inside the building at least, I had friendships or
                    acquaintanceships.</p>
                <p>My name was sent over by Haig for a couple of embassies. Each time, the White
                    House turned them down flat. So I had come to the conclusion that I was not
                    really the kind of person they wanted, and for lack of anything else to do, I
                    had been doing some projects for the new Deputy Secretary of State, Judge Clark,
                    whom I found to be a very pleasant man and easy to do things for. He was very
                    forthright in starting out by saying what he didn't know and “tell me what I
                    should do about this and that.” So I was in the middle of a particular project
                    for him.</p>
                <p>I discussed it with the director general at the time, “Shouldn't I just retire?”
                    and the director general said, “I think you should. We've submitted your name
                    enough times to know that the White House isn't going to let you do
                    anything.”</p>
                <p>And so I went in, on a Tuesday it was, and said to Judge Clark, “I just want you
                    to know I'm going to be retiring, and almost right away, but I wanted you to
                    know that this project I'm doing, I will get somebody else to carry this project
                    on. So I just wanted you to be aware of the change.”</p>
                <p>And I never will know all the details. Judge Clark simply said to me, “You're
                    going to retire?”</p>
                <p>And I said, “Yes.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Do you want to retire?”</p>
                <p>I said, “No, not specially, but I don't want to hang around if I don't have some
                    work to do.”</p>
                <p>And he said, “Well, just hang on for a few days.” And on Thursday he came back
                    and said, “How would you like to be the ambassador to the European
                    Community?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, I'd love it.” [Laughter] I had never thought of it. And that's it.
                    And I've never known who was responsible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, obviously he was a very close, personal friend of
                        President Reagan and probably could override the normal, political
                        appointee-types in the White House.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>VEST: But it was as quick as that, and he was always extremely nice to me
                    afterwards. He was instrumental, when the usual slowness was going on, he was
                    instrumental in simply calling and saying to everybody, including the security
                    people, “Speed this up. We need to get him over there right away.” And later,
                    when he was in the White House heading the NSC, when senior people came over
                    from the European Commission— he didn't like too much to get involved in seeing
                    people like that—he would always take time to see them. So I always have to have
                    a soft spot for Judge Clark. [Chuckles]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were ambassador there from 1981 to '85. What were your
                        prime concerns at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Let me make a sort of a general umbrella statement. When I was there as a
                    DCM, you remember I said I could see that we were reaching the stage that we
                    were unprepared to pay, but just so much economically for the political
                    advantage of a movement, toward uniting Europe. By the time I went there, and I
                    had watched it through in the remaining period, of course, I would say we had
                    come to the next stage in our policy very conclusively. We were not prepared to
                    pay very much. We would give lip service to the idea that political unity is so
                    important that we will pay a lot for it, but we were prepared to pay
                    considerably less, and so the balance was clearly shifting now.</p>
                <p>I found the balance, the problems, primarily in two areas. One was agriculture.
                    Very, very enormous—you're into billion dollars—of sales when you get to
                    soybeans and corn products and wheat and all the other things, and we took a
                    very strong line on this one—the strongest line I think the Commission had ever
                    seen us—in saying we would be prepared to fight for our rights in GATT and
                    anywhere else. and retaliate. So we had a new stage we had reached. And that
                    went on all the way through my four years. In one area or another, it could be
                    canned fruits and vegetables at one stage, and it was always soybeans and wheat
                    and corn products all the way through, because that's a couple of billion
                    dollars right there and 800 million in something called corn gluten, which goes
                    into animal feed.</p>
                <p>In addition, we hit the real problem with steel, pipe and tube. We had rust belt
                    places.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These refer to the old industrial areas in the
                        Midwest.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Like Pittsburgh, where we had the old aging steel plants that were no
                    longer producing competitively with new efficient steel plants in Japan and
                    Korea, Spain, and others that were coming on, plus some in Europe. So we had
                    very, very serious differences there, because Europe had modern and old steel
                    industry. We had modern and old steel industry.</p>
                <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                <p>So the other major thing that occupied a good hunk of the period was an extended
                    steel negotiation, which was carried on primarily on our side. The agent back
                    here was Mac Baldridge, the Secretary of Commerce, together with, from time to
                    time, Bill Brock, the head of STR, Special Trade Representative. I was the agent
                    over there primarily, and we were dealing with the European Commission,
                    commissioner being Mr. D'Avignon.</p>
                <p>We carried that through. It took us almost two years. We negotiated a pipe and
                    tube agreement, which has governed, some would say restrictively, but others
                    would say beneficially, the amount and flows of pipe and tube sales. It went
                    into effect for five years, and will expire this September. And one of the
                    newest problems which President Bush will have will be whether to extend that
                    agreement, amend it, or cancel it, because, in the meantime, the pipe and tube
                    industry has done very well. Industries have modernized. They are competitive.
                    Not all of them, but enough. But there's just one real weak area.</p>
                <p>But that was a wonderful negotiation. I've never had more fun, because each day I
                    would be on the end of the line to Mac Baldridge—or to Bill Brock, usually to
                    Mac—saying, “Okay, now the Community moved this far. We've even brought the
                    Italians into line with the Germans and the French.”</p>
                <p>Or, at another time, I can remember I called him and I said, “We've got all these
                    continental Europeans going along on this negotiation, but the British, still
                    believing that they could play on that special relationship, have sent—and it's
                    already headed over there—a special delegation headed by a deputy cabinet
                    minister to try to see if they can't make a special side deal.” And there's a
                    temptation on our part, if you can maybe divide and conquer, you concede, and
                    there were always people back here who would say, “Let's try to divide them
                    up.”</p>
                <p>And here's where you get to your political thing. Our political thing is to
                    encourage the evolution of a European Community, or a united Europe, at least,
                    if you can, negotiate with them as an entity. So I called Baldridge and said,
                    “The Brits are on their way. Please don't receive them, because then the whole
                    crowd over here in Europe will fall to pieces.”</p>
                <p>He was a wonderful guy to deal with. And he said, “Well, then what should I
                    do?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Just have your deputy Secretary of Commerce speak to their delegation,
                    because theirs is headed by a deputy cabinet minister, and have him tell them
                    that you can't agree to anything because you're negotiating with the European
                    Community.” And they did, and we were able to carry on through. But we were back
                    at that fundamental premise do you divide and conquer or do you pursue your
                    known and definite interest, but do it with the European Community for your
                    political. That's where we've stuck as a policy ever since.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think that in a way you were fortunate, because of
                        these difficult negotiations, that you were representing the Reagan
                        Administration, which did take a, you might say, harder nosed view of trade
                        than one which was more manipulative. You know the Kissinger-Brzezinski real
                        politic-type things.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I think you could do it, and one, I agree we were terribly lucky. Well, one
                    of the Reagan Administration's deep-seated principles, was to try to maintain
                    world trade and an open trading system and to avoid tariffs and avoid trade
                    barriers. This is one of the ones President Reagan viscerally felt very strongly
                    about, probably more viscerally so than any President in recent time and any
                    that we could have had.</p>
                <p>You add to that a guy like Baldridge, who had been a top big businessman himself,
                    so he knew exactly what he was talking about. The combination meant we did have,
                    I think, the ideal backing to carry through this negotiation. It was really very
                    good. Better than—I hate to say, but I have to. If the Democrats had been in
                    power with their tradition of being responsive to economic forces, we would not
                    have been able to carry this through as well as we did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There are a tide sometimes where Nixon can open up to
                        China, where a Democrat probably- -Humphrey probably—couldn't have gotten
                        away with it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: And you probably would not have had anybody being as firm on the business
                    of trying to avoid trade wars as we had in that moment in Reagan and
                    Baldridge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved in the pipeline business for gas?
                        This was a major...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes, the gas pipeline. Oh.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you explain what that was? It always struck me as
                        being a fight we didn't need to get into.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Well, it certainly was true, and the wonderful part was that we had that
                    same basic fight years before.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain what it was?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                <p>VEST: Well, earlier on, the first one of these had been a proposal that the
                    Soviets would build a pipeline that would ship oil, petroleum products, through
                    to central Europe. And we in the West, or the United States especially, strongly
                    opposed that saying the Europeans will be dependent on Soviet gasoline, oil
                    products. We lost that one in the end. It was cheaper, so it was built. Europe
                    was not dependent on the Soviet Union because it continued this stuff from all
                    over the world still. By later times, it had it from the North Sea, as we all
                    know.</p>
                <p>This particular one was on natural gas, and they were proposing to build a big
                    natural gas pipeline that would come all the way across the Soviet Union and
                    into central Europe. We said, “Oh, no. You will be dependent on natural gas and
                    city after city can be cut off, and we will not allow any of our subsidiaries,
                    or any European company that has contracts as a result of deals with our
                    subsidiaries, to provide any material for the building of that pipeline. We're
                    opposed to it.” Which meant that there were a lot of European companies that had
                    business arrangements with American companies and expertise and technology and
                    so on, which we were saying, “You European companies can't do it, because
                    there's been that much technology traded back and forth.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's kind of trying to unscramble eggs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: We were saying, for example, to the French Government, “You French
                    companies, we, American Government, are telling you, French companies, you may
                    not bid anything on that contract.” And it created an enormous uproar, and I
                    don't know anybody who was in Europe at the time, I don't know anybody at all,
                    who didn't send back the message who didn't say it won't work. It simply won't
                    work. The Europeans are not going to be ordered around by the United States
                    Government, and that's what it is from their point of view.</p>
                <p>Well, the Reagan Administration bulldozed ahead. The Europeans began to be more
                    and more nasty. It was very, very badly received all over. I don't think we
                    could have done anything to rouse local nationalism more than this. It also
                    raised questions about whether any European business should do anything with
                    American business in the future, which had very large implications for American
                    business with what lay down the way. And, in the middle of all this, people were
                    telling Washington it isn't working.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were telling them, too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I had done it. I know our ambassador to Belgium had done it. Our ambassador
                    to Germany, a very, very respected elder statesman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Arthur Burns?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                <p>VEST: Arthur Burns had done it in spades and said, you know, how terribly wrong
                    this is from the point of Germany. And, at that point, they changed Secretaries
                    of State, and all by himself back over in Washington here, backed by Larry
                    Eagleburger and Walter Stoessel and I don't know who else, Mr. Shultz just sort
                    of turned that whole thing around, and we had conducted a magnificent
                    retreat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was the impetus for this coming from? I mean, not
                        the retreat, but the drive.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: The drive, as far as I know, came out of what I'd call the conservative
                    Republican world. You mustn't trust the Soviets; you mustn't ever be
                    controllable in any way by the Soviets.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the worst case scenario of all that's happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: In the worst case scenario, yes. Now, remember, in one sense there was
                    a—and I used to argue this much at least with my friends in Europe—there is some
                    basis for concern, because at the moment, the Europeans were intending to put
                    all of their gas plans, or at least most of them, on that pipeline out of the
                    Soviet Union. They could have been having some out of the North Sea. They could
                    have had container gas from other places, and they weren't thinking through very
                    carefully that maybe, by putting so many of their eggs in one basket, they
                    weren't doing themselves a very good deal, either economically or from a
                    security point. A view in point of fact, over time Russian gas hasn't been that
                    much of a bargain. So, you see, it hasn't worked out entirely the way they
                    thought it would.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, George, should we move on to your last job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Sure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After dealing with these matters, you all of a sudden came
                        back to take—I'm not sure. I would suspect it might have been a fine job as
                        far as a job goes, but as far as the pressures on you, I can't think of a
                        worse one—and that's Director General, at a particularly difficult time with
                        the impact of a new Foreign Service act. And you were there from '85 to '89.
                        You had extended your retirement. How did you get talked into that?
                        [Chuckles]</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0077" n="Page0077"/>
                <p>VEST: It's really the simplest thing in the world. Mr. Shultz called and asked me
                    to come back, and no one would tell me what it was. And he was a wonderful man,
                    Mr. Shultz, and he called me into his office. I sat down, and he said, “George,
                    I see that you are due to retire next year. Now I want you to know you have the
                    following choices. If you want to retire next year, you can do so. I understand;
                    you're entitled to it. If you want to stay on as ambassador longer in the
                    Community—which was a very generous thing for him to do, which was being
                    exceptional—if you want to stay on as ambassador to the Community, I will have
                    you stay as long as you want, but I would like you to come back the beginning of
                    next year to be the Director General, because it's suddenly fallen vacant.”</p>
                <p>So naturally I said, “Yes, sir. I'll be back.” There was never any question about
                    that. You know as well as I do that Foreign Service means service when you're
                    asked to serve.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think you and I know, but we belong to a somewhat
                        different generation. I think it's not quite as...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I think each generation learns it anew.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I hope you're right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I do. I think so. I really do. Each generation learns it anew, and it was
                    easier for mine be cause my generation, many of us learned it in the war. That
                    was service to begin with.</p>
                <p>But, no, he asked, and so I was very, enormously flattered and very pleased to
                    come back. I came back in February, and just left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: February of '85?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: '85. I just came back, and I didn't get confirmed by the Senate until June,
                    but I just came back at once.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, could you explain what the situation was at the
                        time? In the first place, what basically the job of Director General is and
                        then what was the particular problems that you were going to be faced
                        with.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0078" n="Page0078"/>
                <p>VEST: These come from the same origins. There was a new act passed, the new act
                    of 1986 governing the Foreign Service. And in the course of that act, first of
                    all, the act took all aspects of personnel—Foreign Service and Civil Service,
                    worldwide and in the building, everything involving personnel—and put it under
                    the immediate responsibility of the Director General. Prior to the act of 1986,
                    the director general did not personally run personnel himself. He sat above it
                    and did policy and very important assignments. But with that one, you had it
                    from the nitty gritty from the bottom up, and the director general was
                    responsible for everything from the advertising, examination, appointment, job
                    assignments worldwide, discipline when things went wrong—it means firing people
                    from time to time, or lesser discipline—promotion and recommending the senior
                    most choices where Foreign Service officers go. In other words, everything
                    involving the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>That was on the one hand. Now in that same Foreign Service act was a second
                    thing, which was entirely revolutionary for our Foreign Service. Before 1946,
                    when you came into the Foreign Service, you could reasonably aspire to a
                    lifetime career if you did a reasonable job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Up until about age 60, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Age 60 to the early 60s. What that had done was, because of our normal
                    niceness as Americans, we had never of come to terms with the fact that if
                    you're going to maintain a Service, you're going to have to fire some people for
                    being inefficient or acting improperly or doing it improperly or doing whatever,
                    and we had not adequately applied this business of if you're at the bottom of
                    your class, you should retire. And so we had far too many chiefs in relation to
                    the Indians, in relation to the number of jobs to be filled. A great many. In
                    fact, the year that I took over the job, there were over 200 senior officers who
                    had no job of any kind to do and were drawing top senior salaries and just
                    having coffee in the cafeteria and agitating, hoping they could find a job
                    someday.</p>
                <p>The new Foreign Service act instituted an up-or-out system, which set out to have
                    a rational system related to the number of jobs to be filled in the Foreign
                    Service, with a steady proportion of promotions and, at the senior levels, a
                    certain number of people would be honorably retired under varying conditions
                    which led to that retirement. This would mean that a certain number of people
                    would be lost at various stages at the top, beginning primarily with some at the
                    early 50s, some in the late 50s, and some in the early 60s. But in our senior
                    group, there would be a significant number of people who would be asked to
                    retire. Honorable retirement with all perquisites and allowances you'd normally
                    get at such a time, a system which was comparable to the way in which captains
                    in the Navy, colonels in the Army, who do not make general and admiral, are
                    asked to retire. In fact, frankly, a system which, if you looked larger, is
                    increasingly applied in law firms, in colleges, those who get tenure and those
                    who do not. I mean, the up-or-out system is largely a facet of our society
                    today.</p>
                <pb facs="0079" n="Page0079"/>
                <p>But we had never had it before. And a whole bunch of people had worked for years
                    in the Foreign Service and were suddenly told, “This is applicable to you,” and
                    they were outraged. They said, “You changed the rules in the middle of the game.
                    We were misled as to whether we should compete for these senior slots.” Many
                    things were said, and there was very, very deep-seated anger, agitation, unease,
                    and a great many people were complaining and morale was very deeply affected by
                    it. There was no question.</p>
                <p>To put this into effect, it just happened that it would come into effect with
                    significant numbers of people being asked to retire exactly during the period
                    when I was going to be the director general. [Laughter] Its effectiveness came
                    with my arrival.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With friends like George Shultz, who needs enemies?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I had the dubious honor, and the not at all dubious pleasure, of putting
                    this into effect, and we had many new things. People grieved and went to law,
                    made lawsuits about this, and there were people who felt very upset about it,
                    wives who were deeply offended. I mean, it was an extremely difficult period. I
                    would have to say, however, as we went on through it, one, I had total backing
                    from Secretary Shultz; and secondly—it meant even more important in one sense
                    because it was a day-to-day thing—I had total backing from the Under Secretary
                    of State, Ron Spiers, and without that kind of backing, it couldn't possibly
                    have been done. If you're going to put in all new rules, try to do it as
                    honestly and as compassionately as you can. You do have to do a lot of
                    disagreeable things, and you're going to have to be backed so that people aren't
                    going to try to undercut what you've done. And I was never undercut by either
                    Secretary Shultz or Spiers, and every time I went to them, I was backed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this is very good, because so often it's easy to do
                        an end run and come around and, well, do that, but I've got my friend.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I have to say I never had an end run once. Never once in the four years did
                    Mr. Shultz ever ask me to show any favoritism of any kind to anybody, and I know
                    he had plenty of people approach him. And just once the Deputy Secretary of
                    State, Mr. Whitehead, edged up toward something like that and he said, “I have
                    never asked before and I know it's rarely done.”</p>
                <p>“But,” I said, “Mr. Shultz has never done it ever.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before he had a chance to collect.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: And Mr. Whitehead backed away. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0080" n="Page0080"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you getting pressures from the White House?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: No, I didn't get pressures. I got inquiries from the Hill, plenty of
                    inquires from staffers. Jesse Helms' staff was particularly critical, and I
                    would have hour-long conversations with Senator Helms' staffers, who were not
                    benignly motivated at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the motivation, because they couldn't have had
                        that many constituents? Senator Helms is from North Carolina and has played
                        a sort of a—it's not quite gadflies, is too benign a term, but has been
                        basically an avowed opponent of much of the Foreign Service for policy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I don't know to what extent Senator Helms has been manipulated or how much
                    he thinks himself. He may be what you would call a populist who thinks that the
                    Foreign Service is an elitist, somewhat suspect, kind of crowd, and he may
                    genuinely feel that way for all I know. However, I do know he had on his staff
                    people who certainly played on his antipathy. One of whom was a former Foreign
                    Service officer who had been a failure, one of those few who had been a real
                    failure in the Foreign Service and had been forced to retire, and he was
                    extremely hostile to everything we did, for reasons that are personal and
                    understandable.</p>
                <p>Another member of his staff, whom I met with several times, was simply one of
                    these unbelievably dyed-in-the-wool conservatives who, if you followed him down
                    the track for an hour or two where he had argued why do you do this this way and
                    why don't you do it that way, he would end up with the statement, “Well, I
                    believe that the people in the Foreign Service should be chosen and be
                    representative of the will of the nation. And they have elected a Republican
                    President and we got a Republican Senate and the majority of each incoming class
                    should be of valid Republicans.”</p>
                <p>And I would say, “Well, we don't take anybody into the Foreign Service because of
                    their politics.”</p>
                <p>“Well, you should.” At the end, that's where he ended. It was very
                    interesting.</p>
                <p>But in the end, I would just have to say this. I got many inquiries from the
                    Hill, and most of the inquiries were understandable. Because when someone who'd
                    work for years credibly in the Foreign Service was told, “You have to retire,”
                    you know, it's perfectly easy for somebody to say, “How did this come about?” So
                    I had a pretty busy time constantly explaining, “It came about because you have
                    a new act of 1986 which you have voted, and I'm implementing it as honestly as I
                    can.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you happen to know off hand did Jesse Helms vote for
                        the act?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0081" n="Page0081"/>
                <p>VEST: I don't. I don't really know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that was, of course, a major problem during your
                        time. Another one that is a constant theme is the lack—and I guess it's
                        true—of recruitment of minorities into the Foreign Service, and this would
                        fall within your jurisdiction. How did you approach this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: There was never any question that we would like more minorities. I mean,
                    there was a valid policy. We sent special recruiters to the historic black
                    colleges. I wrote and sent material to the president of every single historical
                    black college in the country, and I wrote the letter and signed it myself, not
                    with a machine, but personally, and still we did not get as many as we'd like,
                    even remotely. The number usually stuck around 6% of each incoming group.</p>
                <p>I then personally, Stu, took the time off and went out and did the personal
                    recruiting myself in California, starting at San Diego, the University of San
                    Diego, going on up to Los Angeles, Pasadena, Stanford, Berkeley, and did them
                    all. It took about two and a half weeks. Went to every college, met with the
                    students, with the professors, with the heads of departments, with the black
                    student clubs and the Hispanic clubs, which there are both through many of those
                    places. And it was a very interesting experience, because there were plenty of
                    people, minorities, who were interested and would listen, but what I found over
                    and over again, was high quality minority students were offered such great jobs,
                    either they were offered the job by IBM or offered scholarships to go to law
                    schools or med schools or what have you, that the cream of the minority students
                    simply, for understandable reasons, opted for something else.</p>
                <p>Now I don't really know the answer to that. I do know that people argue about
                    this, but I do know that we are not alone in this. There are just enough, at the
                    moment, high quality minority students graduating from our colleges to fill all
                    of the things that a now minority-conscience society is prepared to do things
                    with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me stop right here.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>[End Tape 3, Side 2] [Begin Tape 4, Side 1]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: . . . my time in the Foreign Service and all is that, even
                        when we do recruit, there's a tendency to get somebody to give often an
                        equivalent to a special grade on the test or say, “All right, because you
                        are either Hispanic or black, you get a special edge on the exam.” But yet,
                        once they're brought in, they're sort of dumped into the general group to
                        perform as Foreign Service officers. I mean, logic would say when you have a
                        highly selective crew and you bring people in under a different and
                        obviously lesser standard, the odds are you've got a problem.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0082" n="Page0082"/>
                <p>VEST: You haven't helped the individual.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, you haven't.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: And you've disadvantaged the Service. That was a program that was in effect
                    when I came in as Director General of the Foreign Service. It was a special
                    program to bring in minorities at the mid grade, and it was for minorities and
                    women. And when I took over this job, in the first year I amended the program
                    entirely. First, we made it no longer applicable to women, because enough women
                    were coming in by the regular exam basis throughout. On minorities, I said we
                    will still have a minority entry program, but we are going to do something that
                    we have not done before. We are going to have a very careful and thorough type
                    of examination which any mid- level minority applicant must go through. And we
                    are going to watch their assignments and performance for two successive
                    assignments so that they get properly looked at.</p>
                <p>Now the reason for that was, when I looked into the previous mid-level minority
                    group that we brought into the Foreign Service, I found two major defects. A
                    certain number of them must have looked all right superficially, but quickly
                    turned out not to be really satisfactory and they were at a disadvantage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that's part of the phenomenon and something which
                        isn't really spoken about, but you know there's what is equivalent to a
                        black degree. The universities, business, everybody is making special
                        things.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Well, in this case, they didn't have to take a written exam. They came
                    in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they came in looking good, but for a part of
                        this...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Then we had a problem. The other half of that problem, though, lay in the
                    fact, I discovered when I talked to as many of them as I could every time they
                    came through town, I found a certain number of very highly qualified people who
                    simply were impossibly badly assigned. A guy who'd run a bank in the
                    Philippines—and he had run the bank, a branch bank in the Philippines for an
                    American firm—was put for two successive times issuing visas in a remote visa
                    mill. Not a big one, but a little one, and he was fed up. He said, “I'm not
                    going on to do this kind of thing indefinitely,” and he quit. Well, I don't
                    blame him. He's dead right.</p>
                <pb facs="0083" n="Page0083"/>
                <p>So what we do, or did when I instituted it, we very much reduced the program. We
                    said no more for women. We will aim to get, if we can, six to ten high-grade
                    applicants a year. We will run them through an oral exam, just like the oral
                    exam that we give to people who have entered the Foreign Service. In fact, we
                    will put them in with a class that's going through so that nobody knows they're
                    not the same. You see what I'm getting at?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: And at the end of that, we have the second phase which we do which is
                    called the in basket challenge which they go through, and they would do that. In
                    other words, they skipped the written exam, but they got run through just like
                    everybody else. But there was one extra thing. I saw to it that my minority
                    counselor, who I had in personnel, was a very, very able...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: A black woman, Stephanie Gillespie. I saw to it that she was able to sit on
                    every board where one of these was going through so that no one could ever say
                    that we were disadvantaging them, because Stephanie was one of those immensely
                    intelligent people whose first feeling would be, “I want to be properly
                    represented by my minority compatriots.” And the result is a number of them
                    first of all were selected, looked great. One who had a Ph.D. and had had a job
                    for a while in AID simply did not pass, and it was so close that I said, “Okay.
                    Later we'll give her one more chance.” She didn't pass it the second time, so
                    she simply did not get hired. There are enough other factors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's hard to do it, but it's what you have to do to have a
                        better system.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: We have ended up not being able to get ten that we were totally comfortable
                    with. We had about, last year, we had six or eight, but we have done that to
                    continue to try to get highly—we have some very remarkable people who come in by
                    it. One or two I think are really terrific. It's a very, very limited window and
                    I think one that does not disadvantage the Service and does not penalize the
                    officer. But I've accepted the fact that, when you bring them in, you have to
                    watch at least two assignments to make sure that these people who are
                    disadvantaged because they're coming in—they don't come in at the two level,
                    they come in at the three level. So it's not very high above, but still, it's a
                    little higher, and they know they have some catch up to do. Anyway, I think we
                    found a balance, and it's working I think now. And I don't believe we're
                    bringing in handicapped people or treating them badly. I think we're doing it
                    right.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0084" n="Page0084"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, George, there's another one that has been—you
                        inherited part of it, but it had been going on for a long time— and that is
                        the assignment of women, particularly as you get farther up. Specifically,
                        one of the areas where there's been even a court case saying that women were
                        not being appointed in proportionate numbers to being DCMs. In the time you
                        were there, how did you handle this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Well, we frankly faced that, because I would be blunt to say my
                    predecessors, for various reasons—this is where EEO really has meaning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The EEO being the Equal Opportunity Office.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Yes. We had not appointed many senior women officers to DCMs. I can tell
                    you, when I was assistant secretary for European affairs, where we had a large
                    number of political appointee ambassadors, they would come in and talk to me and
                    they would say, “Now we would like your advice as to who we could consider for a
                    DCM.” And I would give them some names, and they would almost invariably say,
                    “No, we're not interested in any women officers. Our wives have never been the
                    wife of an ambassador. They're going to need help. We want a married DCM.” I
                    mean, that's very straight forward.</p>
                <p>I can tell you in the more recent time, I know our ambassador to Paris looked at
                    two officers, both of them very, very good. No question about it. I know both of
                    them and they really were first-class. One's married, the other was divorced,
                    and the ambassador was very frank with me. He said, “Well, we need help, so I'm
                    taking the one who's married.” And this is part of it, and a big part of it, but
                    not all of it.</p>
                <p>What we did do about it, we ran something which is simply called the DCM
                    committee, and we ran it very seriously. The DCM committee I chaired, and on it
                    sat the under secretary for management, the under secretary for political
                    affairs and my head of personnel as the recording scribe. For every DCM position
                    that came up, we got recommendations from the bureau, from the bureau of
                    personnel, if need be from the bureau of economic affairs, wherever, from the
                    desk officer. But then we, as a committee, picked who we considered to be
                    eligible to be put on a list to be made available to the ambassador. And,
                    occasionally, we had a list in which it was very clear that the woman officer
                    was far and away the best officer. Now there was no question about this. We were
                    deliberately setting out to try to move senior women officers into that world,
                    give them the responsibility.</p>
                <pb facs="0085" n="Page0085"/>
                <p>It began to catch on. We have had most recently a woman DCM in South Africa, no
                    small place to have such a thing. We've had them in Haiti, we've had them in
                    other places. It's begun to be accepted in the trade. One, we've had more good
                    women officers at the senior levels and nobody questions it, and they speak the
                    language and they've had the experience. When you're doing something like that,
                    people begin to accept it. And frankly, where the Foreign Service ambassadors, I
                    have called them in and I've just said frankly, “Look.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Take the Foreign Service ambassador.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Foreign Service officers. I've called them in and I would say, “Look,
                    you're going to this country. The DCM committee has met and we would very, very
                    strongly like you to accept as your DCM such and such officer. Now we wouldn't
                    do this if we didn't think she was terrific. Look into the record yourself and
                    see if you don't think she'd do a darn good job as your DCM.” And by and large,
                    we've began to get a response to it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean, everybody reads the tea leaves. When push comes to
                        shove, you'd rather have a good person than a not so good person.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: And also, most career Foreign Service officers, by the time they become
                    ambassador, they or their wives do not need a DCM's wife necessarily to do these
                    things.</p>
                <p>But anyway, we have begun to make real headway, and I think it's now an accepted
                    fact. I believe that the wide open choice of women in all the senior jobs is
                    something that, with the kind of class of wonderful women we're getting now as
                    officers, that the next four to five years will see that just become a sort of a
                    normal part.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The pump has been primed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I think the pump has been primed. I'm very happy about our women offices. I
                    think they're wonderful. Roz Ridgway is a symbol of what's to come.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, George, the last question on this. You were the
                        director of personnel, but you also had the White House political
                        appointments. How did this play in your office, political appointees?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0086" n="Page0086"/>
                <p>VEST: Let me just say that to the extent I got involved in it, which meant from
                    time to time I accompanied the Deputy Secretary of State when this was discussed
                    over in the White House. Generally speaking, you get a pretty clear picture
                    beforehand as to whether or not the White House is adamantly going to send a
                    politico, but we'd go over and discuss it and sometimes it went back and forth
                    one way or the other.</p>
                <p>At my level, I've been through two administrations. The Reagan Administration,
                    the conversations over there were among the most humiliating and insulting which
                    I've ever been through. I mean, they did not care at all about anything but what
                    they could do in the political sense about their own political crowd. We sent
                    one of our really good black officer's name over three times for an embassy, and
                    each time they sent a political appointee of relatively poor value to take those
                    posts. It shows you how little they cared. They were about the most maladroit
                    people you could have.</p>
                <p>One lovely one—I won't use any names so I don't think it will hurt anybody—but
                    the post fell vacant. It was a wonderful episode. On a Tuesday, I got a
                    telephone call from the ambassador in this particular post, and he said,
                    “George, I'm tired of being an ambassador. This is not the fun I thought it was.
                    I'm going back to my business in California.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, fine. Send in a telegram and a resignation, and we'll send you
                    orders and all the rest.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Oh, I don't need any of that. I've already got my tickets, and I'm
                    leaving on Saturday.” So he left, and that is when I looked around. I thought we
                    had a nice post for this black Foreign Service officer. Back came the White
                    House saying, “No. Mrs. Reagan has a friend who is a- -one of the people who
                    work on your toes—podiatrist. Has a friend who's a podiatrist out in San
                    Francisco, and she would like him to have this post. So we had to process
                    it.</p>
                <p>When the security things came in, the security people had done it and they tried
                    to be as polite about it as they could, but they said that his key group of
                    friends in San Francisco were a group of transvestites, and they didn't know how
                    well that would go down in this particular country. And I've nothing against
                    transvestites, but most countries don't welcome that kind of thing too casually.
                    So the question was, “What should we do about this?” so I asked the seventh
                    floor, “What should we do about this?” and the seventh floor said, “We think you
                    should bury it and never follow it through.”</p>
                <p>So we would periodically get inquiries from this podiatrist in San Francisco, but
                    we never really managed to process the thing, and the Reagan Administration left
                    and that was the end of that. But, no, they were crass. These were people who
                    later ended up in court or in jail. They didn't know how to pick their people.
                    If they'd, you know, given some money, that's all that mattered.</p>
                <pb facs="0087" n="Page0087"/>
                <p>On the other hand, then came the Bush crowd, very clearly going to do something
                    for their team. And they put forward quite a lot of people, but I would have to
                    say they didn't seem to have as many oddballs and they were very considerate in
                    the way we talked things out. I didn't get any insults. I mean, the
                    conversations with the Reagan White House were simply, by my standards,
                    insulting, and out of the Bush Administration, it was not insulting. It was a
                    straight forward fact we're going to do this many. We're not going to hang on to
                    the last administration. As time goes on, as the administration goes on, unlike
                    the Reagan Administration which tried to increase the percentage over eight
                    years, the Bush people made it very clear we aim to repay the original group,
                    but reduce over time the number of political appointees. And, further, if by
                    putting in a political appointee, we're disposing a Foreign Service ambassador,
                    you let us know because we'll ensure he gets another assignment somewhere. And
                    by and large, they were doing that. So there was a gentlemanly quality and less
                    offensive, is the only way I could describe it. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I think it's the right term.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Well, George, I've kept you here. My God, we've been going since 9:30 and it's
                    now 3:02. We usually end up these interview with two questions. One, I think
                    this would be a very hard one for you to answer, but looking back on your
                    career, what gave you the greatest satisfaction? You've had a lot of high
                    points.</p>
                <p>VEST: No one thing gave me the greatest satisfaction other than the large,
                    general thing. It sounds trite, but I just have to say it. I never really cared
                    about money, and I never really cared about rank or distinction. I never thought
                    I was going to get past old FS-03. For me, it was just all the way through a
                    very exciting, rewarding thing to serve your country and do something that you
                    thought was worth doing. And, sure there's some flat stages, but mostly you
                    conclude...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your Hamilton, Bermuda. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Even the Hamilton, Bermuda had one bright reward, but I left. All those
                    people who didn't speak to each other got together and came together at the
                    woman vice consul's house and had drinks—it was the only time in year and a half
                    I was there they were ever together—to say goodbye to Emily and me, because we
                    had made friends with all of them. That was an achievement for us. But I felt I
                    was serving my country, and that was it. There was no special anything else.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0088" n="Page0088"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The last question we ask, and this is certainly maybe an
                        obvious question to ask somebody you only less than a year ago was our chief
                        recruiter, but we ask everybody. If a young person came to you and said,
                        “Mr. Ambassador, what do you think about the Foreign Service as a career for
                        me?” How would you reply?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I will reply to this, because I've had it happen a lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I'm sure you have. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Because I don't automatically say, “Oh, yes. Go into the Foreign Service.”
                    I normally have tried to say, “Look. The Foreign Service is one of the most
                    extraordinary, rewarding, frustrating, and difficult careers you can get into.
                    You need to think carefully what you're getting into, what you and your wife are
                    getting into, because if you're married, the Foreign Service asks demands of the
                    whole family.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Or the spouse, you might also say.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: Or spouse. You would say spouse today. And I would say, do say, “I think
                    it's, for me, it was one of the most exciting, rewarding careers I could ever
                    have asked for. I know all the downside. I don't think the downsides should
                    deter you. I think you should, however, carefully know yourself. What is it you
                    want to do? How is it you want to live? What are your values? What do you value?
                    If fundamentally you really want to make money, you shouldn't go into the
                    Foreign Service, you ought to go into law or do some of these other things.
                    Foreign Service is a very special kind of group, but people are going to tell
                    you, 'Okay, it's got all kinds of crooks, I mean, funny sides to it. You can
                    never get ahead if you don't have money or you didn't go to an ivy league
                    school.' I would just say all of those are phonies. They are not true. Any
                    American can rise to anything in this Foreign Service if he has the quality and
                    the luck. You have to have the quality to take advantage of the luck.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And to know when the windows of opportunity are open.
                        Sometimes people get too clever and they don't understand.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VEST: I have remained very enthusiastic. I consider, particularly in the world of
                    today where more and more people are trying to think what is it that matters.
                    There is another generation that's come after the yuppie generation. There's
                    another bunch of young people who are saying, “I want to do something that
                    matters in my life.” Well, the Foreign Service matters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, George, I want to thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0089" n="Page0089"/>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
