<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001011">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Irving Sablosky </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>IRVING SABLOSKY</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: March 21, 2000</p>
                <p>Copyright 2002 ADST</p>
                <p>Q: Well, let's start with when and where you were born.</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I was born in Indianapolis, Indiana on March 5, 1924.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you tell me about your family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes, my father and mother were both born in the United States, in New
                    York or there-about. Their families moved to Indianapolis in the early 1900s, I
                    guess. They were married in 1920. They had two children, myself and my brother,
                    who is three years older. All four grandparents were immigrants from the old
                    country. The maternal grandparents were froAustria and Germany. The paternal
                    grandparents were from Russia, what was then Russia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Probably Poland or the Ukraine?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Probably now. It is around Grodno. We don't know exactly. The name
                    Sablosky was apparently an immigration official's invention - the real name
                    might have been Zablodovsky. There is a town now in Poland called Zabludow,
                    where the Zablodovskys probably came from. That is as close as we get, but we
                    are not dead sure that the name was Zablodovsky. That seemed to be the most
                    likely thing. Since we know that my grandfather on the Sablosky side said he
                    came from the Grodno area, and Zabludow is indeed in the Grodno area, it's
                    probably it. They came to the states in the 1880s, before there was any Ellis
                    Island, and settled in New York. I don't know what my grandfather Sablosky did
                    before he came to Indianapolis. Grandpa Rosner rolled cigars.</p>
                <p>Q: Oh, yes, that is very famous. People used to sit around and read to the cigar
                    roller. It was quite an elite group, actually. Quite intellectual.</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Maybe, yes. He was said to have been a scholar. That is what attracted
                    my grandmother to him apparently. He was considered kind of a catch, since he
                    was a scholarly cigar roller.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cigar rollers, particularly immigrant cigar rollers in New
                        York,were considered sort of part of an elite group.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I didn't know that.</p>
                <p>Q: They used to hire readers who, while rolling cigars, would read whatever. They
                    were usually rather intellectual things. It was a very interesting group.</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Grandpa Sablosky started as a street peddler, and then started a little
                    department store in Indianapolis in a fairly poor neighborhood. The store grew
                    to have several branches, neighborhood department stores in Indianapolis. My
                    father went into that business when he was old enough. Mother completed high
                    school. She always wanted to go to college but never could because she had to
                    work. My dad finished high school but never went to college. He never wanted to.
                    He expected to work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By 1924, when you were born, were there brothers and
                        sisters?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: My older brother had been born in 1921. By then, the families were in
                    Indianapolis. When they got married, they bought a small house at 34th and
                    Broadway in Indianapolis. That is where I was born. I lived there the first 13,
                    14 years of my life, in that same little house. The neighborhood has completely
                    changed now. I tried to take my new wife there in 1983 to show her the house,
                    but it was a parking lot in a very black neighborhood.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was family life like growing up? Was it pretty
                        weloriented around the store?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes, around the store, and around the family itself. We had the four
                    grandparents all in the town of Indianapolis. I hadn't realized until I was
                    quite a bit older, how rare it was to have all four grandparents in one town. I
                    remember my brother and I went to one of the grandparents' houses on Saturday to
                    play and Sunday, after Sunday School, we went to the other grandparents for
                    lunch and the afternoon. That was a very important thing - being with the
                    grandparents. Of course, on all the Jewish holidays, we were with the
                    grandparents.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your family Orthodox?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No. They were what they called “Conservative Jews.” think it still
                    exists.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think so too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: It's somewhere between Orthodox and Reform. The Sablosky grandparents
                    were inclined to be more Orthodox. They went to an Orthodox synagogue for a
                    while, but then settled on the Bethel congregation which was in that very
                    neighborhood where we lived. It was conservative. The Rosners, my mother's
                    parents, were Reformed. They came from, Germany, Austria, where the Reformed
                    movement was strong.. So, there was a little difference between them, but
                    everyone got along very well. Dad, particularly through the depression era, went
                    through a period of being rather religious. Generally, we were a pretty secular
                    family. We never kept kosher or anything like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your neighborhood more or less Jewish, or ethnic?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No, nothing. It was a completely mixed neighborhood. One of my friends,
                    who lived diagonally across the street from us, once asked me about what it was
                    like to be Jewish. I offered to take him to a temple to show him what a temple
                    looked like. He was a little scared, and he wasn't sure he was supposed to go in
                    there. He wasn't sure that I was supposed to let him go in there, but of course,
                    it was okay. Being Jewish was a little exotic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about schooling?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Public schools. I went to a kindergarten, Mrs. Cook's Kindergarten, I
                    think it was called. I guess that was private, but when I was five and a half, I
                    went to public school number 76, about three quarters of a mile from our house.
                    I walked there in all kinds of weather. This was grades one through eight. I got
                    through the eighth grade and then they changed the system so that seventh began
                    junior high school. SI “graduated” (without ceremony) from the eighth grade and
                    went to Shortridge High School.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were in, essentially elementary school, do you
                        recalwhat subjects interested you? Did you start reading early?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: We read. My mother was great for reading. Dad not so much, but mother
                    was. We used the public library a lot. I enjoyed Math. In seventh grade, we had
                    a music appreciation course which really caught my fancy. I really got into
                    music then. I remember the teacher's name was Mrs. Swan. When I was 13, about
                    the time we got out of grade school, I started taking piano lessons. I have a
                    favorite story. I had been preparing for my bar mitzvah then, and was going to a
                    Hebrew school. I did rather well with the language. I had a knack for language,
                    apparently. At the same time, my cousin, who lived down the street, had a piano.
                    I used to like to go to my cousin's house and play away. My brother was
                    convinced I was some kind of a genius because I could play Home on the Range
                    with harmony. So, after the bar mitzvah, since I was doing so well in the Hebrew
                    school, my father wanted me to continue there. But, I hated it. I tried to find
                    some way not to go. My brother did a very fine thing for me. He said, “Why don't
                    you let him have piano lessons?” I said, “Yes, piano lessons.” So, I started
                    taking piano lessons. Music became my main interest. After high school, I went
                    to Indiana University, the School of Music, and majored in composition..</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about in high school? Did you pretty much concentrate
                        omusic? I would think it would be a little hard to in that era.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I didn't do any music in high school at all. It was all outside of
                    school, all extracurricular. In high school, I belonged to something called the
                    Shortridge Senate, where we were an imitation U.S. senate. We debated various
                    issues. I guess that was my first contact with public affairs. I was very much
                    interested in literature and belonged to a drama club. I had a wonderful English
                    teacher. She interested me in writing very much. Nora Thomas was her name. I
                    won't forget her. I wrote some poetry in those days, and Nora Thomas to
                    encourage me to do that. She would always encourage my interest in reading
                    poetry, which I still do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In other words, it sounds like you had a pretty
                        remarkableducation, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I think Shortridge had the reputation of being a very good school. One
                    teacher I remember was Frank Wade, who was the Chemistry teacher. I had no real
                    interest in Chemistry, but he could interest anybody in Chemistry. He was the
                    model teacher who kept the students really thinking and imagining, as if they
                    were discovering everything for the first time. When he gave examinations, he
                    said we could use our books or anything, because the sin wasn't in not knowing
                    something, it was not knowing where to find it. Of course, you had to find it in
                    a certain amount of time. I remember Frank Wade very well. He was a fine
                    man.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about sports?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I was never good in sports. My brother was. I liked to ride my bike out
                    into the country and go into the woods, and that sort of thing. Of course, I
                    practiced the piano. I had a couple friends, Martin Marks, who was my piano
                    teacher's son, and a very fine pianist himself. My other friend was Al
                    Dobrowitz, who was the butcher's son. We talked about music and lots of
                    things.</p>
                <p>Q: While you were in high school, in Indianapolis, which wasn't that small a
                    town, did you have that much access to performances of one kind or another?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes, the Indianapolis Symphony, which is pretty well known. Fabian
                    Sevitzky was the conductor. Well, first it was Ferdinand Shaeffer, when I was
                    really young, and then Fabian Sevitzky. I went to symphony concerts sometimes.
                    They played concerts for schools too in those days, and I think that probably
                    still happens. They would come in small ensembles to the school or the kids
                    would go on a bus down to hear the symphony. So, we did that. That's about all
                    of that kind of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your family willing to accept a music student in the
                        family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Reluctantly. Mother didn't mind so much. Dad, of course, wanted me to
                    go into the business. He really expected me to go into the business and I have
                    always admired him for saying, “Okay,” to the music thing. When I wanted to go
                    to college to study music and not go to a business school, he said, “Okay,” and
                    stuck with me all the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During the summers, would you work at the store?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Oh yes. It was a source of income.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By the time you got to high school, how had the stores
                        developed?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The main store was at the corner of Massachusetts and College Avenue,
                    which was a very busy intersection, in a rather poor, working-class
                    neighborhood. Dad considered our competitor to be Sears. He wanted to keep
                    people from going to Sears with attractive prices and good merchandise. The idea
                    of the store was to provide decent merchandise at fair prices. There was a very
                    mixed, black and white clientele, and mixed black and white staff, too. This was
                    in the middle of some pretty hard times. This was in the 1930s, 1940s. The store
                    went through some very hard times. There was a period there when Dad would come
                    home at night and would say that he might not have a business to go back to the
                    next day. My grandfather, his father, made some bad real estate investments,
                    which put the family in debt. My father had to work to overcome that. Gradually,
                    he really took over the store. It was his consuming occupation.</p>
                <p>Q: Indiana, from what I recall, was divided. The south was white southerners and
                    the north was more industrial, standard Midwestern. Where did Indianapolis
                    fall?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Indianapolis was right smack in the middle. It was a market town, I
                    guess. There was a big central market and there were corn fields all around it.
                    But, it was a big town, even then. I think, in the 1930s, it was supposed to
                    have had a population of close to 500,000. We were taught in school that it was
                    the largest city in the United States not on a navigable waterway.</p>
                <p>Q: Oh, yes. I grew up in Annapolis for a time. We were told that we were the only
                    state capitol not connected by sea or railway. Did you see any manifestations of
                    race problems?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Not really. The races were pretty segregated. In Shortridge High
                    School, there may have been a couple... We called them Negroes in those days...
                    black students. But, there was a black high school, Crispus Attucks High School.
                    That is where the blacks were pretty much expected to go. My mother usually had
                    a cleaning lady who was black. So, I knew black people from the start. We had
                    lunch at the Sabloskys (my grandfather's) on Saturday. Then, we would go to the
                    store in the afternoon to work. My grandfather would see black men on the
                    street, walking. He would stop the car and say, “Would you like to work?” He
                    would give them work. Black people did the heavy work. They carried
                    boxes....</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about politics? Particularly the New Deal and all. How
                        dithat play in your household?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: My father was a great Roosevelt fan, and went into the New Deal,
                    wholeheartedly, I would say. Later, he became disaffected as so many people did.
                    As they got more wealthy... He never became terribly wealthy but once the
                    Depression was over, I think he became somewhat disaffected with Roosevelt. But,
                    in the early days, Roosevelt was great in our household, and he's still great
                    with me.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>Q: I think with many of us, he was sort of the household God. What about the
                    developments in Europe? Everyone thinks of the rise of Hitler, fascism, also
                    with the Soviet Union. Was this way over the horizon, in another place, or was
                    there a connection, or family following it or not?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: We heard some discussion of the events, well essentially, Germany, in
                    the temple. The rabbi would bring it up in sermons from time to time with
                    warnings, flags, that sort of thing, that something should be done. The Soviet
                    Union didn't really loom as a problem in my childhood, as I remember.</p>
                <p>Q: Jewish families coming particularly to New York more, came out of the
                    socialist tradition. They either got caught on one side or the other on the
                    communist issue, but your family didn't really come out of that socialist
                    workers type.</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No, not at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You graduated from high school when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: 1941. What a year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was going to say...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I can remember December 7th very well at the fraternity house in
                    Bloomington, Indiana, hearing the news on the radio. All of us were aware that
                    we were going to be going.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the draft?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: We had deferrals for being in school. Many boys in the fraternity house
                    volunteered very quickly, or got into some program like the V-5 or the V-7.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: V-12.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: My brother went into V-7 to become a naval officer, which he did. But,
                    I was only 17 at the time, so I wasn't eligible yet, but soon became. I tried to
                    get into a V- 5, as it was, at that time. But, they didn't want me for some
                    physical reason or other.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For the naval thing, they were very strict on eyes, at
                        that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I don't know that it was eyes. But, anyway, I guess I was drafted. I'm
                    not really sure whether I enlisted or was drafted. I think I was drafted. My
                    number came up and I went into something called ASTP, Army Specialized Training
                    Program, which was for college kids. It was kind of an officer training track,
                    but with no promises. They put us into basic training in Fort Benning, Georgia,
                    where the regular Army people did not like these college kids very much. Anyway,
                    it was a pretty tough basic. In fact, by the time we were finished with basic,
                    the whole ASTP thing had been pretty well abandoned, so I found myself in the
                    infantry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go in the infantry?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: First to England for staging. That must have been August or September
                    1944. I went into the Army in 1943. We staged in a place in England, near
                    Oxford, near the town of Fairford on the Coln River. Then, we went to France -
                    not in the first wave: It was October or November by the time we got there. We
                    went in through Le Havre. I'd seen some damage in England as a result of the
                    bombing, and the V-1 and V-2 rockets. The V-1 were very audible. They came
                    putting over - buzz-bombs, we called them.. We heard those often. With the V-2s,
                    you could see a peculiar, question-mark shaped cloud in the sky, and you knew a
                    V-2 had passed over. We saw rubble there, but nothing compared to Le Havre,
                    which was simply flattened. It was pretty hair raising when we got there. Then
                    we went farther into France, past Rouen, and over to the Schnee-Eiffel, [in] the
                    Ardennes forest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you in a division?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I was in the 422nd regiment of the 106th division, whicwas right in the
                    thick of the Battle of the Bulge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was going to say, you got there right at a very
                        interestintime.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: We were on the front line or beyond the front line, guess, at the time
                    we were all captured. They captured battalions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Three regiments went, didn't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I don't really know the particulars.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that the first action that your regiment had
                        seen?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were put up there for what? Training?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Exactly. We were doing target practice, on what we thought were
                    impressed Russian troops on the other side of the line there. The weather got
                    very bad. There was a lot of snow. We lost any kind of reconnaissance, and the
                    Germans shifted the personnel over there, and crack troops, started coming over.
                    Before we knew it, they surrounded us. That is the story of the Battle of the
                    Bulge. It is certainly well enough known. What I have read of it, it's pretty
                    accurate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened to you? What did they do with your regiment
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: They surrounded our unit. We were in a town called Schoenberg. I
                    remember that very well. Theoretically, we were going to try to take that town.
                    I was in a heavy weapons company, 81 millimeter mortars. We were going to fire
                    the mortars, not the usual trajectory, but fire them as if they were cannons, at
                    this town. We were supposedly going to take that town; then, we could make
                    contact with American troops - none of which happened. The valley below us
                    filled with German tanks. They had promised us tank support, the last radio
                    message we had, we were getting tank support. The only tanks that came were
                    German tanks. Our battalion commander just directed us to destroy our sights,
                    and we were taken prisoner. They could have slaughtered us, very easily, some
                    were. Our unit was not. They took us prisoners, right on the border of Germany
                    and Belgium. Schoenberg is still in Belgium, but barely. It is all German
                    speaking there. Then, we started walking. We carried a few wounded off the
                    field. There weren't so many. There had been some firing, but not a great deal.
                    We walked across the Rhine, to Koblenz, and then a little further to Limburg, I
                    guess. From there, we were put into boxcars. We were taken to a place about 60
                    miles south of Berlin, Stalag 4-B. Mostly British RAF pilots had been there
                    since 1941. They were pretty entrenched too, and weren't too glad to see these
                    Yanks who were losing the war for them, come in. They were okay and took good
                    care of us, actually. The Brits did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long were you in the prison camp?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I guess we must have gotten there shortly after the turn of the year,
                    into 1945. I was there until April 23rd, when the Russians liberated us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do in a prison camp? There you all are.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: It was sort of a continuous depression, and of course constant hunger.
                    You read. There was a little library, and we could read. I read, I took notes, I
                    kept a journal. I tried to write down whatever music I could remember, just
                    drawing staffs with a pencil on paper. I tried to remember all of Beethoven
                    Seventh Symphony, which I couldn't do. I don't know why I picked that. I tried
                    to write some canons, and other exercises in harmony, just to keep the old brain
                    working. It was a very depressing experience. We were starving. I lost a lot of
                    weight. But, we were not mistreated, really, beyond not being fed. Then, there
                    came a time when... This is a strange story. Every once in a while, people would
                    be called out on work detail. We didn't know where they went to work - we didn't
                    know then where they went. The most famous story of this, of course, is Kirk
                    Vonnegut's, in Slaughterhouse 5. They pulled him out to go to Dresden. They
                    finally called my name to go out on a work party. In the barracks, where they
                    were getting us ready to go out, some guy I knew (I don't know from where or
                    when) said, “Irv Sablosky, what are you doing here?” I said, “The same thing you
                    are doing here. Going off to work, I guess.” He said, “They aren't going to send
                    you out. You are Jewish, aren't you?” I said, “Yes.” He said, “Well, they don't
                    send the Jews out.” I said, “What kind of thing is that?” He said, “The story
                    according to the party line is that Jews won't fight for their country and so
                    they can't be prisoners of war, so they are not taken out of the prisoner of war
                    camps and shown to the public.” It didn't make a hell of a lot of sense. But, he
                    said, “Show them your dog tags.” I had my dog tags with the “H” on them. He
                    said, “Show your dog tags to the sergeant over there, and see what happens.”
                    Being as depressed as I naturally was, and demoralized, and whatever else you
                    can call it, I said, “What the hell, why not?” Maybe it will be the gas chamber,
                    but we'll see what happens if I show them the dog tags. In fact, I felt a little
                    guilty about it, because when I came into the camp, a British soldier had
                    processed us on the way into the camp. When he was writing on this form, he
                    asked my religion. I told him Jewish. He said, “I'll put down Protestant.” I
                    said, “Well, I'm Jewish. The “H” is on my dog tags.” He said, “I'll put down
                    Protestant.” I said, “Do what you want.” I had been feeling a little guilty
                    about that. Now, when the chips were down, I was going to be Jewish, whether it
                    was to my advantage or not. I suspected it might be. So, I showed my dog tags to
                    the sergeant, and sure enough, he got angry, but he got me out of there, back to
                    the barracks where I had been. I didn't go out on work detail. I think I can be
                    grateful for thait may have saved my life. So, in a very strange way, being
                    Jewish at that point was an asset in Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I heard that they had taken some Jewish GIs and put
                        them into regular concentration camps. There were some cases of that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I guess that is what my British friend had in mind when he put
                    dowProtestant. We didn't really know what was going on. I don't think the extent
                    of the concentration camps, the gassings, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened when the Russians took over?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The Russians came in one night. Our German guard disappeared over-
                    night, and in came the Russians. The German guard or two that were found still
                    there, were very badly treated. They were dragged behind horses, for example.
                    The Germans had miserably treated the Russian prisoners - quite differently from
                    the way they treated British and American prisoners. The Russians and the Poles
                    were really badly starved and beaten. The Russians took it out on them. But,
                    they loved the Americans. So, they took us out of there and took us on trucks,
                    down to the town of Riesa, where they had taken over apartment buildings. They
                    put us there, and kept us for a month, waiting for an exchange of prisoners,
                    during which time, we were all kind of grilled. In my case anyway, I think, with
                    a name like Sablosky, they thought it might be a Russian name. We learned later
                    that the Russians who had been taken prisoner, who survived, maybe didn't
                    survive when they got back to Russia. They were looking for any Russians hidden
                    among the Americans. So, I had a pretty tough grilling. I was a smart aleck, I
                    guess, at the time, and still am, I suppose. The Russian inquisitors asked me if
                    I spoke Russian. I said, “No.” He then said something in Russian. I responded
                    “Nye panyemayu.” It was the only word in Russian I had ever learned. But, I had
                    to show off. Then, they really started questioning me in Russian, which I didn't
                    understand a word of. They finally became convinced that I didn't understand any
                    and Sablosky was not really a crypto-Russian. It was pretty scary. I got out of
                    there all right. I didn't learn until later what was happening to Russians who
                    were found, which I think is the reason we were reluctant to exchange prisoners
                    then. Because we didn't want to give any Russians back to them and have them
                    sent to Siberia, or something, which I guess, is what happened. So, anyway, we
                    were amongst the Russians. We had been liberated on April 23rd. On May 23rd
                    exactly, we took a truck to an airport near Leipzig and were flown to France
                    where we went into a rehabilitation center. We spent almost another month
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were they doing, just processing you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The Russians?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I mean when you were at the rehabilitation place.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Well, more or less, and building us up. We were alpretty
                    debilitated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it just that the Germans didn't have enough food
                        themselveor was it a deliberate policy not to feed?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I really think they didn't have enough food themselves. We got some Red
                    Cross packages. The Red Cross was supposed to get these packets of food to each
                    prisoner. We would generally share one, maybe once a month, or once every couple
                    weeks, we would get a package that was shared among a dozen or sixteen people.
                    The rumor was that the Germans were taking the Red Cross food, which is quite
                    possible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By, the summer of 1945, what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Went back to the United States and went to Fort Sam Houston for duty in
                    San Antonio, Texas. I was in something - I don't remember exactly what it was
                    called - it was the section that arranged entertainment for the troops.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Special services.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Special services, there you go. Since I had studied music, they thought
                    that maybe I could help out with the band or something like that, which I did. I
                    started a little jazz combo. I really didn't know much about playing jazz, but
                    there were some jazz musicians there. They put me in charge. We played for
                    officers club dances. I just waved a stick in front of everyone. Once in
                    rehearsal, I tried to play the piano, but that didn't go. I can't play that kind
                    of piano. Then, after a time, my name came up for discharge. I went to Camp
                    Atterbury, in Indiana, near Indianapolis, and was discharged.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then what, back to Indiana?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Back to school.</p>
                <p>Q: Let's talk a bit about the University of Indiana. You were taking the
                    classical composition, practice playing, and all that sort of thing?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: It was mainly music. For electives, I took German. I took Physics. I
                    don't quite know why I took Physics. The only course I ever got a low grade in.
                    I came out with a “B” or something like that - and a number of literature
                    courses. I enjoyed that. I wrote for the school paper, The Indiana Daily
                    Student. I wrote a music column - music reviews. They had a lot of musical
                    events at the University. I wrote about some student recitals, and I wrote about
                    professional concerts, including things like Paul Robeson. I enjoyed writing
                    about music. That landed me my first job. On graduation, in 1947, the head of
                    the journalism department at Indiana heard from someone in Chicago that there
                    was an opening for a music critic at The Chicago Daily News. So, I went for an
                    interview. They hired me right out of school. I guess I was the youngest music
                    critic on a major daily newspaper in the U.S.A.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this was when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: June 1947.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The paper was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The Chicago Daily News. It was a Knight newspaper.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was The Chicago Daily News in the spectrum of
                        newspapers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Oh, it was a very good newspaper. It wasn't until the 1970s that it
                    folded, finally. It was owned by John S. Knight. It had been owned by Frank
                    Knox.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Secretary of the Navy and vice-presidential
                        candidate.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Exactly, and it had had people writing for it, like Ben Hecht and Carl
                    Sandburg. It had a huge reputation. It was not at its peak when Knight took it
                    over but it was still a very respected paper. The Tribune was obviously the
                    highest-circulating paper. But, The Daily News was number two in circulation,
                    and it was respected as an independent newspaper, politically. It was an evening
                    paper - an afternoon paper, which was not good for it later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long were you the music critic there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Ten years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: 1947 to 1957?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: That's right. Q: What was the music scene like in Chicago in this
                    period?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: It was rich. It was a period when the Chicago Symphony got to be at its
                    peak under Fritz Reiner. When I first got there, Artur Rodzinski had just become
                    the conductor. He lasted a couple years, then Rafael Kubelik came, and then
                    Fritz Reiner. The Lyric Opera of Chicago was just getting started. It had its
                    opening seasons with both Callas and Tebaldi on the roster, Tito Gobbi,
                    everybody, Nicola Rossi-Lemeni. Really all the great singers of the day were
                    there. The ballet scene was big, too.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>Q: Looking back at your experience, you had been working on composition. I would
                    imagine that writing for ballet, all these things... How did you bring yourself
                    up to speed so you could do this?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I just did it. As far as the composition goes, the theory was that I
                    was going to do this writing about music as a profession and do my writing of
                    music in my spare time. It turned out to be very little spare time. The
                    composition of music just fell by the wayside, largely I think, for lack of
                    talent and because I was inherently lazy. Writing about music took over. I did
                    that all the time. I always liked to write and had been writing music criticism
                    in college. So writing about music came to me quite naturally. I enjoyed doing
                    it for 10 years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Chicago have the equivalent of Eastman School or
                        Juilliard?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Not quite that level. There was the Chicago Musical College. This was
                    the top school headed by Rudolf Ganz, a great pianist. Then, the universities
                    there, Roosevelt University, DePaul University, Northwestern - all had music
                    departments. The University of Chicago was mainly academic, not performance.
                    But, these others did have performance aspects. So, there was a lot going on,
                    academically, in Chicago. The Chicago Symphony has a training orchestra called
                    The Chicago Civic Orchestra, which is one of the first-rate training orchestras
                    in the states.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Chicago has had a reputation, even going way back, of
                        stroncivic support for the arts, didn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Oh, sure, with the Art Institute at the center of it. It is a very
                    lively art scene. There is no question. The theater, too - there was the “Second
                    City” group - some experimental theater - and the LaSalle theater had its own
                    little company that was doing Shakespeare, and various other things. There was a
                    lot of theater. On the music scene, I had the pleasure of really writing about
                    whatever I wanted to write about. I was the only music critic on the staff and
                    could pick what I wanted to write about. So, I wrote about jazz as well as
                    classical music. There was a lot of jazz going on in Chicago. That was during
                    the folk music revival. There was a lot happening. I immersed myself in it, new
                    music too. The composers' forum, that sort of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the powers that be in the newspaper? Did they
                        sort olet you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Oh, absolutely. Partly because I think I was doing okay, but partly
                    because they really weren't interested in music. They had a music critic because
                    a major paper was supposed to have a music critic. I filled the bill for
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you run across anytime when some mogul's daughter was
                        havina recital that you had to cover?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No. I never did anything like that. I once wrote about Margaret Truman.
                    In fact, I went to Milwaukee once... This is kind of a gag. I wrote a
                    tongue-and-cheek “serious” critique of a performance given at the Musicians
                    Union Convention by Harry Truman at the piano and James Petrillo on the
                    trumpet.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Petrillo was head of the Musicians Union. They did play,
                        didn'they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: They did, indeed. It was front page.</p>
                <p>Q: Obviously, during this time you were immersed in music, were you paying any
                    attention to what was developing in the world? Things like the Cold War, the
                    Korean War, etc.?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Well, yes. Through music, I was very conscious of what was going on in
                    the Soviet Union because of the story of Shostakovich and Prokofiev's problems
                    with the regime, the composers' union, and when they were denounced. At the
                    time, there was a book called Musical Uproar in Moscow by Alexander Werth. That
                    was really the first detailed account I had heard. In the '50s, the Soviets
                    tried to patch up this image a bit by sending over such artists as David
                    Oistrakh and Emil Gilels. They were careful not to talk politics when we
                    interviewed them. But we were already conscious of the political side of music,
                    when Henry Wallace was a candidate for president.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, 1948, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: That was right in there. In the folk music scene in Chicago, people
                    like Studs Terkel were very much involved. Pete Seeger came to town. There was a
                    lot o“left wing” activity. So, one was aware that something was going on, that
                    something was cooking, politically. More and more artists were coming over from
                    Europe who never had before. During this period, there was a new consciousness
                    of music in the Orient. Troops of musicians were coming from India, from Bali. I
                    was tremendously impressed by Ravi Shankar. His brother, Uday Shankar, was
                    really the pioneer in bringing Indian music and dance to the States. That and
                    the dancers of Bali who came over for the first time, I think in the early 1950s
                    - I was really knocked out by those things. I really wanted to get into
                    that.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there much coming out of Japan, for example, at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Kabuki. The Kabuki Dance Theater Company came to Chicago. It was the
                    first time they had ever been in the United States. It was the first time we had
                    ever seen anything like that in our lives. It was tremendously exciting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the Chicago audiences on music and
                        things? Werthey knowledgeable?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Pretty knowledgeable, yes. It was the first time I ran into the second
                    city complex, but it's real. I ran into it again when I served in Cebu in the
                    Philippines, which was at rivalry with Manila. I served in Hamburg. Again, a
                    second city. So, I can tell you, there is a second city complex.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, what happened in 1957?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: In 1957, I began to get restless. I began casting about. I began to
                    think seriously about changing my life. I had been divorced in 1954. I remarried
                    in 1955 and our first child - a son - was born in 1956. (Two daughters from my
                    first marriage lived with their mother.) I was beginning to wonder whether I
                    wanted to do music critiquing for the rest of my life. Where was I going to
                    advance? The place to advance from being music critic of The Chicago Daily News
                    would be to go to New York, and do the same thing. Did I really want to do that?
                    I was really getting a little bored about writing about the same people playing
                    the same music night after night. Sometimes I would go to seven, eight concerts
                    in a week. Sometimes I would review a Saturday evening, a Sunday afternoon and a
                    Sunday evening concert in the same paper. I began looking around, thinking about
                    what else I could do. I thought of public relations, things that had to do with
                    writing. Public relations, advertising; I didn't think I had the temperament to
                    be in advertising. So, I was looking around a bit. I met a man at a party at a
                    friend's house who was leaving his job as public relations director for the
                    telephone company there, to go with U.S. Information Agency. I talked with him.
                    His name was Stafford Davis. He told me about what USIA did. I had never heard
                    of it. It sounded really interesting. He told me that if I was interested in
                    what he was talking about, I should hear about their cultural affairs program.
                    So, he told me a little about that. And I certainly was interested. He said they
                    were recruiting people. If I was serious, he would get somebody in touch with
                    me. Sure enough, Carl Larsen, who wrote for the Chicago Sun Times, called me up
                    and asked if I'd be interested in being interviewed. I told him I was. He sent
                    me the Form 171, something like that. I filled it out. I was thinking seriously
                    about it; Pat, and I were discussing it. Several weeks passed and I got a call
                    asking if I could come to be interviewed by a panel that was coming to Chicago
                    to interview prospective recruits. I said, “Okay.” I went to the interview. When
                    I came out of the interview, Carl Larsen was there. He said, “Did they talk
                    salary?” I said, “Yes, we did talk salary.” He said, “Well, then you are in.”
                    They didn't make any commitment at all, but he said that if they talked money,
                    they are taking you seriously.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you recall what sort of questions they were
                        asking?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: They asked about current affairs, a lot. It was mostly general
                    background. I think they were a little chary of me because I was in music. My
                    education concentrated in music, I was writing about music. Though I was a
                    journalist, which is what they were looking for, a narrow music background
                    threatened them, so they asked me about sports. Actually, I was clever enough at
                    that time to suspect that something like that was going to happen, so a few days
                    before that, I read the sports pages. When they asked me if I was interested in
                    sports, I said, “Well, I've never been good in sports. But, I have noticed that
                    Don Larsen pitched the first no-hit game in the World Series the other day.” So,
                    they seem convinced by that, that I was a rounded character. Maybe it didn't
                    have anything to do with anything, but I thought of it as a kind of a victory.
                    So, suddenly this was obviously a serious thing. Should my wife and I really be
                    thinking of packing up? (By now, we had a baby son to think about, too.) I told
                    the managing editor that this possibility had come up. In fact, I wasn't quite
                    that honest. I hadn't said anything to anybody. Our intellectual columnist,
                    Sydney Harris, who was friendly to me on the paper, came to me and said,
                    “Irving, are you looking for a government job?” I said, “Why?” He said, “Because
                    the FBI is around. If you are considering something, you had better tell
                    Norlander because you don't want them popping in to see him before he hears
                    about it.” That was very nice of Sidney. So, I told Ev Norlander, the managing
                    editor, that this was in the wind, and it may or may not happen. Sure enough, it
                    happened. In remarkably short order, they called and wanted me to be in
                    Washington in three weeks. I said that that was impossible. I guess that was
                    right at the beginning of the year. So, we made it in April. Pat and I and our
                    little boy drove out to Washington in April and I started a new career and a new
                    life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you got there in April of?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: 1957.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you come in? Did you start out in training?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes, I came into a training program. There were between 25 and 30 of us
                    who were coming in at that time. USIA was anticipating an increase in budget, we
                    understood. The new director was Arthur Larson, who was a buddy of Eisenhower's.
                    Things were on the upswing. That is why they were recruiting. So, we went into
                    what was to be an eight-week training program at USIA. We were to be trained to
                    be USIA officers. Before the eight weeks were over, Arthur Larson had appeared
                    before the Congress and the budget was slashed brutally. The posts for which
                    many of us had been intended were eliminated, including mine. I heard much later
                    that I had been slated to be Assistant Cultural Affairs Officer in Florence. It
                    was abolished before I even knew it existed. So, I was in Washington then for 14
                    months, waiting for an assignment. I was in limbo. We called ourselves the
                    legion of the dammed, because we had all been sworn in and we were all now
                    employees of the U.S. government. We had no place to go and were in sort of
                    make-work jobs. The work they made for me, or which I made, was to write
                    background materials about American music for use by cultural affairs officers
                    abroad. Then, David Cooper, who was head of the music division of USIA at that
                    time, saw these and said, “We should do a major pamphlet.” So, I did write the
                    text of a really handsome Life magazine size pamphlet on American music. It was
                    the first time the agency had produced anything like that. It went all over and
                    was translated in many, many languages. That took a lot of time, and that was
                    certainly well worth doing. In fact, it stood me in good personal stead later,
                    when I had a year of American studies under agency auspices 1963-1964. I went to
                    the University of Chicago for that training year. I met Daniel Boorstin, the
                    historian, who was at that time working on the second volume of his trilogy,
                    called The Americans. He was trying to figure out how to handle the development
                    of American music during that period, mid-19th century to end of the 19th
                    century. So, he asked me for some recommendations about sources he might look
                    into. I gave him a list and I also gave him the very condensed pamphlet, which
                    would give him some background on it. He called me up in the middle of the
                    night, one night, and said, “You have to do a book for us, for the University of
                    Chicago's American Civilization series.” I said, “I can't do a book, I am not a
                    scholar. I am a journalist.” He said, “You can, you have almost done it.” He
                    seduced me into writing a book, which I did. I started on it while I was there
                    in Chicago in the American studies thing. Then, when I came back to Washington
                    for German language training, whatever time I could get away from German
                    language training, I worked on the book. I kept working on the book in any spare
                    time I could find in Hamburg, when I got there. I worked on it on the weekends,
                    I took leave, I worked on it whenever I could. Finally, I got it finished. It
                    was published in 1969 - American Music, which is maybe the best thing I ever
                    did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the tie between the agency and this book?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: There was no tie. It was just that Boorstin got the idea from the
                    pamphlet I had done for the agency and said that I could do a full book on the
                    subject. Later, the Agency took the published book into its translation program,
                    and it was published in Spanish, Portuguese, Vietnamese, Korean... quite a few
                    languages.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the agency's interest in music, when you arrived
                        therin 1957? During the early years? What were they doing music wise?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: As I said, they had David Cooper, who was the music division. David and
                    an assistant (Elaine Fry) were the music division. Their primary function, I
                    think, was to keep the posts informed of musical events in which there might be
                    an interest abroad. And they furnished phonograph records, long-playing records,
                    for the libraries. They selected the records to be sent to the USIS libraries
                    overseas, where they were much used. They also did some presentations to
                    universities and so forth abroad of records, and books on music. The idea was,
                    and this is true of the Voice of America, too, that the field of music offered
                    an excellent prism through which to view American culture. It's innovativeness,
                    its accomplishment. Few people abroad really were aware that there were so many
                    symphony orchestras in the United States, or opera companies, or serious
                    composers, beyond jazz, which they may have had an inkling about. But, they
                    didn't know about American music. We had a whole world of music in the United
                    States which told a wonderful story about the country, about its growth, about
                    its differences from Europe or from any other country.</p>
                <p>Q: Music is not my expertise by any means, but it does seem that it has only been
                    in the last several decades that we have really looked at our musical heritage.
                    Prior to that, it seemed that not much was played. There was quite a revival of
                    some of the people who were popular, including people like Scott Joplin, of that
                    nature. Were you beginning to see people who thought that we really had
                    something here?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I think that may have been the case. That development is largely
                    post-World War II. I think the general public probably didn't get with it for a
                    decade or so after that. The agency, I think, was on to it, insofar as they had
                    actually gotten themselves a musical advisor. That is what the job was called.
                    David Cooper was the musical advisor for the agency. A man named Angelo Egan
                    followed him and then Daryl Dayton was, for many years, the musical advisor for
                    the agency. They did a very good job of getting the materials out to the
                    posts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was in Belgrade in the early 1960s. I had a wonderful
                        timgoing to the library there and taping all the music comedy records.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Musical comedies, absolutely. That is a feature of American musical
                    life that people in other countries love, once they get acquainted with it. It
                    is very American. Jazz, of course, in a big way, and the folk music. But, also,
                    the concert music, which was the least familiar abroad, but which became a
                    tremendous influence on European music, not to mention in other countries.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>Q: Later, were you seeing the Tchaikovsky competition, Van Cliburn, and all that?
                    There was Saul Hurok. Wasn't he doing most of the fishing for the classical
                    performances?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The concert managements helped somewhat, but they were mainly
                    interested in the stars. Hurok was mainly bringing people in from Europe. Most
                    of his stable were foreign artists. The biggest factor in the post-war
                    development of American music I think was the conservatories, the music schools,
                    which were so very good. They turned out such splendidly trained musicians,
                    which is still the case. The amount of talent and the quality of the training in
                    American music is unequaled in anywhere in the world. When I was in Hamburg,
                    which was 1965 to 1968, 16 of the top singers of the Hamburg Staatsoper were
                    Americans. There were about 600 American singers in German opera houses. The
                    German directors said that the Americans were better trained and would work
                    harder than the local people. They wanted the Americans. It's a credit to our
                    training ground here</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You wrote this book while you were in Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Mostly in Washington, actually. I finished it when I wain Hamburg.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you find the material for the book?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The Library of Congress, almost totally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it more biographical, on who was doing it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: It's a narrative history from the time of the Pilgrims to the 1960s,
                    covering the development of all kinds of music, except religious. Generally, it
                    was an attempt to place the development of music in the context of American
                    history. There is no musical analysis in it at all. It is really for a general
                    reader who wants to get a brief survey of the whole field of American music,
                    where does it come from.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, we have all these ethnic strains like the
                        Appalachiamountains, each one was quite distinct. Your first post was
                        Hamburg?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No, my first post was Korea, after those 14 months ilimbo.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good heavens. You were in Korea from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: 1958 to 1960. I went out as publications officer, on the basis of my
                    having written these pamphlets in Washington. I not only wrote on music, but I
                    also wrote one called, The Strange Case of Mr. K, which was about Khrushchev's
                    double talk on many subjects, exposing the Russian disinformation. I wrote a
                    couple of political things like that. Anyway, I was publications officer in
                    Korea. We had a major pamphlet program there. I wrote pamphlets - the texts of
                    pamphlets, on different subjects, which were translated into Korean, for
                    distribution to schools, to journalists, intellectuals, etc. One was on Abraham
                    Lincoln, for example - it was the Lincoln sesquicentennial that year (1959), so
                    I wrote something called. Abraham Lincoln and American Democracy. In Korea, we
                    were trying to influence the government toward democratic ideals. It was mostly
                    quotations from Abraham Lincoln on the nature of democracy. This was translated
                    into Korean, and put into schools. The idea was that it was going to inspire
                    Korea ideals of democracy, which it certainly did. 1960 was the year Syngman
                    Rhee was thrown out as president. I'm not trying to take responsibility for
                    that...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, students had a hand in that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: They did, indeed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Korea like, when you went there in 1958?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Korea was on the verge of modernizing. It was still a very traditional
                    culture, with a very sophisticated, University educated elite. They were
                    certainly starting then to make what became the new Korea. The USIS post and the
                    embassy - the political section and the economic section - were very well
                    plugged into that elite. We were very well received there. There were no wraps
                    on what we could do. What better friend did Korea have than the United States at
                    that time? It was very hard, I think, when the revolution came, which was
                    inevitable. Rhee was planting the seeds himself. He was teaching democracy. His
                    schools were teaching American democracy. The logical conclusion of that was
                    that they weren't going to have a dictator anymore. That happened while I was
                    there. It was fascinating to see. I don't doubt that we were a factor in it.
                    When it did happen, the Koreans wanted to hear immediately: with the students in
                    the streets, where did the embassy come down? We felt we had to make some kind
                    of a statement to the press and to the students who were gathered in front of
                    the Embassy. It was quite an experience for me as a kind of neophyte Foreign
                    Service officer. I happened to be acting Press Officer at the time, and I
                    remember a very tense meeting with the Deputy Chief of Mission, Marshall Green,
                    and Don Ranard who was Political Officer, and maybe a couple of others, as we
                    worked out the language of a statement, going virtually without instructions
                    from Washington. We finally issued a press release in which the Embassy stated
                    that we couldn't interfere in the internal affairs of another country, but that
                    the Embassy trusted the Korean government would address any justifiable
                    grievances of the protestors. The fact that the embassy would say something
                    about justifiable grievances was dynamite, and I had the feeling that we were
                    making history there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how did you find working in Korea? Did you have a
                        Koreastaff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Oh, yes. The publications officer was in the press office, which had
                    the press attache, and the information officer in it. There was also a huge AID
                    program in Korea. The AID program had its own information officer, also a USIA
                    man. We had a staff of maybe six translating whatever we needed. We didn't
                    attempt to write anything in Korean, but these people were very good in
                    translation. The hardest thing that had to do was to translate for the press. We
                    would get on the wireless file transcripts of Eisenhower's press conferences. I
                    don't know if you remember those. There were so many ellipses, unfinished
                    sentences. We would try to translate those for the newspapers in Korea. We would
                    put out a Korean translation of the transcript. My translator would come and ask
                    what a particular sentence meant. It was undecipherable. So, I was really making
                    American policy. I had to say it in plain enough English that it could be
                    translated. It was hard.</p>
                <p>Q: It's really interesting because I'm told that Eisenhower was a superb briefer
                    in the military, which you are trained to do. You are not trained to drift all
                    over the place. You say it in very precise terms. But, ______________________
                    latitude because nobody could pin him down as to what he was saying.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>How was the economy, from your perspective, in Korea at that time?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I don't think I could answer that now, from this distance. I believe
                    things were looking up in Korea at the time. The industrialization was certainly
                    starting, and also the AID program - it made many mistakes, but I think they
                    also did a lot of things right. It made a difference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any chance to use your knowledge of musical
                        affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes, every place I was, starting in Korea. I gave talks on American
                    music. We had an information center in Seoul. An officer named Bernard Lavin,
                    who was a terrific officer, ran it. He had conferences on American civilization
                    - and not just on American: he arranged for discussions where there would be
                    comparisons of Korean and American civilizations. So, I was often called upon to
                    give a talk with illustrations on American music, jazz, concert music, whatever
                    there was. I worked up two or three standard illustrated lectures with recorded
                    examples on the history of jazz, on the American and the European musical
                    traditions, the contrast. Recent trends in American music for very sophisticated
                    audiences, I would do that. I did it at all my posts. It was my hobby horse, I
                    guess.</p>
                <p>Q: I would have thought that Korea would have been quite a receptive place, at a
                    higher level for music, because even today, some of our top violinists,
                    conductors, come out of Korea. You go to a normal kisaeng party, which is the
                    geisha house, and the guys will jump up and sing opera for you at the drop of a
                    hat. They have beautiful baritones.SABLOSKY: At the end of any dinner, everybody
                    goes around the table and sings a song. Herb Baumgartner, the information
                    officer, and I used to sing Take Me Out To The Ballgame. That was our song.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I used to sing Old McDonald Had A Farm.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: You were in Korea, too, weren't you?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was there in 1976.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes - how else would you know about Kisaeng houses?</p>
                <p>Q: It was frightening, because they were very good. We are talking about for me,
                    in the late 1970s, but they certainly absorbed western music.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Even in the late 1950s when I was there. There were two symphony
                    orchestras in Seoul at that time. There was the Seoul Symphony, which was the
                    regular symphony orchestra and the Korean Broadcasting System Symphony
                    Orchestra, which was the better orchestra. The conductors of both of them were
                    American trained, I believe. I know the Broadcasting orchestra was... The
                    orchestras were not bad at all. They had wonderful singers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Wonderful real baritones, boy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Sopranos, too. Very talented.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was obviously fostered at a very early level in the
                        regulaschool system.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Did you get involved with the press, at all?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: A little. I was acting press officer sometimes. Of course, journalists,
                    even for the cultural affairs officers, were some of our main contacts. We went
                    out with them a lot, and had them to our houses, and so forth. Many journalists
                    were English speaking. One of the most important ones for me was not English
                    speaking. His name was Chang Chun Ha. He was the editor/publisher of a magazine
                    called Sassang-gye, which was an intellectual journal really, a quarterly. He
                    was very interested in the United States and reprinted my pamphlet about Lincoln
                    in his magazine. He later got the Magsaysay award. He came to the Philippines to
                    accept it. I was in the Philippines, and we had him over, and had a party for
                    him. He was a fascinating man, a wonderful man and very deep. He was connected
                    to us by the number one Korean assistant in the Cultural Affairs sections, in
                    the cultural office, a man named Park So-jin. He knew Chang very well. He
                    thought I would get along with Chang, even though we needed a translator between
                    us. He knew a little English, and I knew a little Korean, but very little, in
                    both cases. With mediators, we could converse. We really hit it off. It was not
                    only very pleasant, but it was important because Chang's magazine was
                    important.</p>
                <p>Q: After the student revolt, which overthrew Rhee... In the first place, while
                    Rhee was the president, he had been the president for a long time, and it was
                    probably beginning to wear thin. Did you sense a disquiet about Rhee within the
                    embassy, kind of wishing he would go away?</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Oh, I think the political officers wished he would go away, but the
                    revolution really centered on his vice president, Li Ki-poong, who I think was
                    involved in some corruption. It was Li Ki-poong's reelection which triggered the
                    revolution. It was a rigged election. The students went out against it. Li
                    Ki-poong's house was burned down. The regime had become corrupt. So, yes, I
                    think we were wishing Mr. Rhee would go away. There was kind of a mystique
                    around him, among the general populous I think, not among the sophisticated
                    journalists. With the journalists, there was a lot of skepticism, but there was
                    still a certain mystique, as I say, about Rhee. You didn't really talk against
                    Rhee. You could talk against Li Ki-poong.</p>
                <p>Q: What was the impression of the newspapers there, like the Hankuk Ilbo, and
                    other ones? Were they pretty good or sort of preachers of certain powers?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No. You mentioned the Hankuk Ilbo. Mr. Chang who ran that newspaper,
                    which was very independent, didn't really talk anti-regime, but he was as close
                    as you could come to it. His paper was very popular. He was a very independent
                    character. The Chosun Ilbowas a very high-class paper. We would have dinner
                    sometimes with Mr. Hong, the publisher. He was a very fine man. He was an older
                    man. I was young at the time, so I knew some of the younger reporters. I think
                    one of them was named Hong also. I can't remember that well. But, Hong, the
                    publisher was a very imposing man, and a very independent thinker.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the ambassador, Walter
                        McConaughy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: My impression of him was that he was a very wise, prudent man. He had
                    been in Pakistan before, I think. He and Mrs. McConaughy were very southern. She
                    was quite charming. She was very southern. She didn't quite know how to do
                    things without help, so she got a lot of help from the embassy. But, she was
                    charming, and they liked her. Ambassador McConaughy had everybody's respect. He
                    didn't give the impression of being the most decisive man in the world, or the
                    fastest, but very wise and prudent, he was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about during this time, was the threat from North
                        Korethere? Was this a matter of concern?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Not especially. I had the occasion to go up to Panmunjong to one of the
                    sessions of the Truce Commission, to observe. I guess occasionally, there would
                    be an incident at the 38th parallel, at the DMZ, as they called it. But, it
                    wasn't hot. There weren't submarines and things like that, certainly not during
                    that period, as I remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1960, whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: In 1960, home leave, transfer to the Philippines, to Cebu,where I was
                    going to be Branch Public Affairs Officer.</p>
                <p>Q: I must say that going to Cebu with a music critic background seems to be a
                    cast in your bread on sparse waters. If that is the right way to put it.</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Well, we are all generalists. The idea of having a branch post, I had
                    asked for it. On the personnel form, where they ask where for your next post, I
                    had put Cebu, Chiang Mai, Thailand, and maybe somewhere in Burma, where it would
                    be a so-called one man post. There were many other people there. A one-man post
                    was certainly a misnomer. But, I actually got Cebu. That was my second choice, I
                    think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Cebu from 1960 until?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: 1963.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Cebu like at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Cebu is like a western town. People carry guns, and yet there was a
                    very sophisticated, often Spanish-influenced, upper-class. There was no
                    orchestra in Cebu. I think there was not very much music really in Cebu. In
                    people's houses, there was. There were newspapers. The first television station
                    in Cebu opened while I was there. They put me on doing a newscast. The influence
                    of the clergy was very strong. The biggest university there was the University
                    of San Carlos, which was run by the SVD, the Society of the Divine Word, partly
                    American and partly Dutch. It was mostly a Dutch order, but the head of it, the
                    rector of the university, was Father Rigney, who was an American from Chicago.
                    He had spent many years in a Chinese communist prison camp. That is where he
                    ended up, I think literally, he died in Cebu. He was a very anticommunist man.
                    Cebu was the seat of the Osme�a family. Osme�a having been the former president,
                    and now by the time I was there, his son, Sergio, who was a senator, had his
                    political machine centered in Cebu. It was the second city. It was a rich city.
                    Shipping was the main thing. There was a U.S. air base on Mactan Island, nearby,
                    which was across the strait.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there an insurrection going around in that area?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No, not in that area at all. Not around Cebu. In Mindanao, there was
                    supposedly some. As Public Affairs Officer in Cebu, I had the only branch port
                    post outside Manila. They had had branch posts all over the southern
                    Philippines. But, now, Cebu was the only one left. So, I covered the whole
                    central and southern Philippines. I went into Mindanao, and all the way down to
                    the Sulu Islands. It was fascinating. It was a real adventure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I imagine it would be.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Philippine Airlines flew these old C-47s everywhere you could fly. They
                    were good, the pilots. So, I went to as many places as I could go. We had a
                    consulate in Cebu. There was a principal officer and a vice-consul. There were
                    two consuls during my period, Robert Yost and Lyle Lane. Then, there were a
                    couple vice consuls. One of those, in fact was Charles Bray, who later became
                    deputy head of USIA. He was also later head of the Foreign Service Institute.
                    Charlie came to Cebu as a junior officer. I was still pretty junior, too, but I
                    wasn't quite as junior as Charlie. Anyway, the consuls and the USIS guy, whoever
                    it was, traveled all over. It was fascinating. We met so many people. The
                    Philippine welcome is incredible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would imagine so. In a way, I don't imagine you had much
                        of selling job to do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No, but an informing job to do because there were a lot of wrong
                    impressions about the United States there. There were a lot of aspects of
                    American life that they weren't familiar with. The racial situation in the
                    United States was of interest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was just beginning to heat up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: So, we had a lot of occasions to talk about that because there were
                    changes taking place in the states at that time. In lectures, I often talked
                    about jazz there. When you talk to somebody about the history of jazz, the
                    question and comment period afterwards leads to all kinds of other places. It is
                    a wonderful opportunity to talk about anything that might be on their minds. It
                    was a wonderful chance to exchange views about the United States and clear up
                    some misperceptions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the press? How did you find the press
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I would say the Cebu press was pretty provincial. I hope the Cebuanos
                    don't hear me say this. The Manila press was pretty wild. The newspapers there
                    were subject to strong political influence. They represented political leaders,
                    generally. People had a newspaper, and so it was their spokesman, and sometimes
                    not quite responsible. But, they were lively. Some were in English. There were
                    also papers in Cebuano. There was a Cebuano paper, but I think most people read
                    the Cebu Republic News, I think it was called. It was the main newspaper. One of
                    the Manila papers had a Cebu edition that was published in Cebu. I can't
                    remember which paper it was. It may have been the Manila Chronicle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this time in Cebu, were there any major events that
                        sorof grabbed your attention there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes, there were two that I can think of off-hand. One was the return of
                    General MacArthur, who came to Cebu. He went to Leyte, of course. I didn't go to
                    Leyte with him; the consul did, I think, and the ambassador did. He came through
                    Cebu and was received in Cebu with a tremendous parade, and all kinds of
                    jubilation. It was quite a thing to see. Then, there was a change of presidents,
                    from Garcia, who was considered quite corrupt and who had been in power quite a
                    long time, to Macapagal, who was the first of the Liberal party, who promised
                    real democracy, and a brake on corruption. I think Macapagal kept his promise,
                    pretty much. I think he was followed by Marcos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When Marcos came in, he wasn't considered too bad. They
                        sapower corrupts.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Some friends of ours back then said if Marcos came in apresident, he
                    would end up being a dictator. They saw it coming.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think this might be a good place to stop. We will pick
                        it unext time. You left Cebu in 1963, and where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Went for a year of American studies at the University oChicago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right, we will pick it up then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Today is the 3rd of April 2000. Irving, we want to talk a littlmore about
                    Cebu.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I would just like to backtrack a little bit Stuart, since I mentioned
                    what I thought were two globally important things that we really had very little
                    to do with. The Consulate, of course, had a role in the MacArthur visit, but it
                    was generally a Philippine government affair; we were peripheral to it. There
                    were a couple of things that I would like to mention that were very important to
                    us from a program standpoint. One was the appearance of Rudolf Serkin in Cebu,
                    brought there by what was called then the President's International Program of
                    Cultural Presentations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You should mention who that is.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Then, the president was Dwight Eisenhower, of course. The performer was
                    Rudolf Serkin, one of the greatest pianists of the times. For him to come to a
                    place as remote as Cebu, was really quite unprecedented. There was a great
                    question before he came to Cebu and that was, can we find a piano - a concert
                    grand for him to play on? Fortunately, by that time, I was acquainted with a
                    piano teacher in Cebu whose husband was a shipping magnate, so to speak. They
                    had a nine-foot Steinway in their living room. I talked with Mrs. Sala and asked
                    whether she would permit it to be used for a Serkin concert. We were going to do
                    it in a nice auditorium in St. Theresa's College in Cebu and would she allow it
                    to be transported to St. Theresa's College. Of course, she said she would be
                    honored to do so. So, we got Mrs. Sala's piano over to the hall and Serkin came
                    to town. He was just marvelous. That was really historic, from the standpoint of
                    Cebu and from the standpoint of USIS in the Philippines presenting something at
                    that level. It was very, very well received. The other thing, along the same
                    line, was the Alvin Ailey Dance Company, which was brand new at the time. This
                    was 1962. Of course, in the next 10 years, they became one of the top companies
                    in the United States. This was a predominantly black, modern dance company.
                    Alvin Ailey performed not only in Cebu, but we took him down to Cotabato City in
                    the Mindanao, in the middle of Mindanao, in the Muslim country. They, of course,
                    had never seen anything like this. The company was tremendously exciting, and
                    everybody was excited by it. It was quite a cultural achievement for the
                    USA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the local governments there in Cebu
                        anMindanao? Did you have many dealings with them?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Always, yes. I traveled to all of the main cities in Mindanao and from
                    the islands of Panay and Negros in the north down to Zamboanga City and even to
                    Jolo in the Sulu Islands. Everywhere I went, of course, I would meet the mayor,
                    as a representative of the U.S. They were always tremendously friendly. I would
                    have a nine o'clock appointment with the mayor, and he would pull out the
                    brandy. The attitude toward Americans was invariably friendly. Then I would call
                    at the local college or university and touch base with educators there. I found
                    that the legendary Philippine hospitality was real - and that interest in the
                    United States was real, too which meant interest in the books and films and
                    other materials we were able to furnish..</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left the Philippines when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: In 1963.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1963, whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The word came that I was going to go Hamburg. I would be Director of
                    the Amerika Haus (the USIS Information Center) there. To prepare me for that, I
                    proposed that I take an academic year at the University of Chicago, in American
                    Studies. That request was granted. So, I went to Chicago in the fall of 1963,
                    and stayed for the school year, 1963 - 1964. They didn't really have an
                    integrated American Studies curriculum, but I took American Literature, American
                    History, etc. Walter Johnson was the main history professor, head of the History
                    Department at that time. Daniel Boorstin was the other professor there, with
                    whom I had a number of courses. It was just a marvelous year, because I had
                    never really formally studied American History and Literature. I, of course,
                    dabbled in it, but that hadn't been my field. It was good preparation for what I
                    was going to do. Then, we came to Washington, after the school year, in the
                    summer of 1964, for German language training. (”We” being my wife, Pat, and our
                    four children - ages one to eight.) I had had a little German in college, so I
                    had a little start on it. But, German language training was a very wonderful
                    course. I had a very good teacher. We got along well. I came out speaking
                    German.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Hamburg from 1965 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: 1965 to 1968.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you talk about how you saw Hamburg at that time, and
                        whathe German/American relations were in that area?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Hamburg, is a north German capitol, very close to England. English is
                    very widely spoken. It is different from the rest of Germany, in many respects,
                    and proud of it. They were proud to being the last major city to be taken over
                    by Hitler. At this point, the Hamburgers were very receptive to American
                    presence. Hamburg, of course, was the second city in Germany... I think I
                    mentioned before about the second city complex... Hamburg was greatly affected
                    by the division of Germany. Though the “Oder-Neisse Line” lay about 30 miles
                    east of Hamburg, it effectively cut off Hamburg's commerce on the Elbe River.
                    The greatness of the port had diminished, and Hamburg was feeling it. Anyway,
                    the great shipping companies were there. Hamburg University was very important
                    there. An important contact there was Fritz Fischer, the professor of German
                    History who was controversial at the time because he was the first to raise the
                    idea that Germany was at fault for World War I. I got to know Fritz Fischer a
                    little bit. Another was Guenther Moltmann, who was doing American studies at the
                    University of Hamburg. He was a very fine man. One project we had at the Amerika
                    Haus at that time was to try to get instituted by the education ministry or
                    office a curriculum in American studies for the Gymnasium - that would be upper
                    high school, not just in Hamburg, also in the surrounding territory, but mainly
                    in Hamburg. We had some luck with that, actually. There was a very fine German
                    national employee of ours, Rheinhard Kapishke, who worked very hard on this, and
                    he had very good contacts in education circles. We helped the education
                    department fashion and distribute a new curriculum in American studies, which
                    had not existed before at that level. Those who go to the Gymnasium are most
                    likely going to university and possibly lead the country in the future.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, one of the gaps in European education that has been pointed out has been
                    American studies. The United States has been terribly important to Europe. Most
                    Americans who reach leadership roles have gotten a pretty solid dose of European
                    history, whether it sticks or not, is another thing, but this is true in any
                    course. But, the Europeans often don't really get much about American history.
                    So, they are trying to understand us from a rather frail base.</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: That is exactly right. What happened, generally, around that time at
                    European universities was that American Literature was taught as part of English
                    Literature. There would be an English Literature department, and some American
                    Literature was attached to that. American History hardly it all, only as it
                    related to the literature. So, you hoped to get a rounded curriculum in American
                    History, Literature, Politics, even Geography.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that you were in competition with the
                        BritisCouncil at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Not really in competition. Of course, the British Council was teaching
                    English. It was a very active program, it had resources beyond ours. The Amerika
                    Haus had a fine library and a wonderful clientele, mostly of university
                    students. We were right across the street from the University of Hamburg campus.
                    It was well trafficked, so we had lectures, of course, and exhibits. The British
                    Council did similar work, and we worked closely together. The head of the
                    British Council, and I, and the French cultural representative and the Italian -
                    the four of us would have lunch together every once in a while. We were all in
                    the same business, and worked together very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would imagine that the Hamburg cultural life would be
                        quitrich, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Oh, yes. The Hamburg Staatsoper was one of the best in the country,
                    featuring at that time, 16 major American singers - Tatiana Troyanos was there,
                    Arlene Saunders, Jeanette Scovotti, Richard Cassilly... There were some very
                    good and very valued American singers there at that time. In fact, we arranged a
                    recital at the Amerika Haus to show them off. They appeared in pairs - joint
                    recitals. They were glad to do that for the Amerika Haus at no fee. They just
                    did it for their country's sake. The programs were very well received.</p>
                <p>Q: This was a period, wasn't it, when an American opera singer... to get solid
                    work and to develop their repertoire would find that particularly Germany was
                    the place to go.</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes, at that time, there were something like 600 American singers in
                    German opera houses. Of course, there is an opera house on every corner in
                    Germany. But, they got to love the American singers because they were very well
                    trained, and were willing to work, often harder than German singers. Once the
                    German singers were in the opera company, they were civil servants, and tended
                    to coast. The Americans didn't become... few were actually appointed as civil
                    servants. They were the younger singers. They were getting started. They were
                    learning new roles, and they worked harder at it than the German singers did. So
                    they were highly valued.</p>
                <p>Q: 1965 to 1968 was at the height of the civil rights movement in the United
                    States. How was that playing in Germany? I mean, were you working on that?</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes, we certainly were. There was a lot of interest in it. We didn't
                    address it really, but allowed it to show. James Baldwin, for instance, came
                    through Hamburg on his own and we had a reception for him at the Amerika Haus.
                    He was somebody who had to be presented in the America Haus. We were honoring
                    James Baldwin, and giving access to him. He spoke freely. Even radical
                    Americans, when they are abroad, are suddenly more consciously American, and
                    proud of it. Baldwin was not an exception. He was not crazy about the civil
                    rights situation in the United States, but he did recognize that it was
                    happening. Patricia Roberts Harris came through also. It wasn't exactly easy to
                    see that she was black, but she passed for black. She lectured for us at the
                    Amerika Haus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She had been a professor and was an ambassador, and a
                        member othe cabinet, I think, at one time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I don't know that she was actually in the cabinet.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But, she had a fairly high position.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: She was a lawyer, and she spoke about the American judicial system, and
                    of course, got into Civil Rights. What happened at these lectures often was that
                    there would be a general, or even a very specific subject of the lecture, and in
                    the question period, anything might come up. If it was a black lecturer, of
                    course, the Civil Rights movement came up. As the years went on, the Vietnam War
                    came up more and more, though we did not program directly on the Vietnam War, a
                    question arose and was discussed often in our programs, not only in Hamburg, but
                    in outlying towns in which we held programs as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the German media in... What is the main
                        paper,is it Die Welt?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Die Welt is published in Berlin, but it had a Hamburedition, and Die
                    Zeit was the weekly. It was published in Hamburg.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your job to monitor the press?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: We certainly kept track of it. Ray Benson, the Public Affairs officer
                    in Hamburg had that primary responsibility. I was responsible for the Amerika
                    Haus the public programs there. Ray and his staff were doing most of the
                    monitoring.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ray is up in Vermont now. I talked with him about a week
                        ago.I'm getting a professor at the University of Vermont to interview
                        him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: That's great. That's perfect. Ray would have the story, all of his
                    history in Yugoslavia and Russia, is invaluable. He is so articulate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: His parents were communists. They took him to Russia as a
                        kid,and then left.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The father stayed there, and the mother brought him back. Ray is a
                    fountain of information. He has total recall, and he is very articulate. That
                    will be a very good contribution to your program, I'm sure. He was the Public
                    Affairs officer in Hamburg at the time I was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the Amerika Hauser in Germany?
                        Wharole were they playing during the mid-1960s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The numbers were being reduced by the time I left Hamburg. At that time
                    there were nine left of the original 30, I believe. A number of the rest had
                    become bi-national centers, called German-American Institutes. They were run and
                    financed by the Germans. We furnished books for the library. In some cases, the
                    American director remained in the Amerika Haus. I think they played a very
                    important role. They were a center mainly for the university students, and some
                    of the upper high school students. For Germans, this was a source of information
                    about the United States. One thing that impressed them maybe more anything was
                    our shelf of periodicals. We had periodicals of every shade, from left to right,
                    in American politics, and literature, whatever. The fact that these were open
                    shelf, American-style libraries was a new concept to the Germans, and the
                    variety of periodicals which were offered, with no regard to whether they were
                    for or anti-government, was a demonstration of American democracy, for sure, and
                    openness.</p>
                <p>Q: Were you just letting people know about America or were people coming over and
                    using the library for all sorts of things, including getting more information
                    about Physics, and that sort of thing?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Well, our libraries were limited in that sense. They wouldn't really
                    find an extensive collection on Physics in our libraries. Our libraries were
                    mainly about the United States. We did have the Encyclopedia Britannica and
                    Americana, but it was a library about the United States. That is what they came
                    here for. They were curious about the United States, and they wanted to be
                    informed about it. The journalists used it too for background research. They
                    trusted it. It certainly was not a slanted library. It was a real library.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Soviets have an equivalent organization in
                        Hamburg?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No, they did not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about English training? Was that left to the
                        BritisCouncil?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: We didn't do English language training in Hamburg, or Germany at all,
                    as far as I knew. The German American Institute, the former Amerika Haus often
                    had English teaching as part of their curriculum, but we did not do that.</p>
                <p>Q: What was your impression of the University of Hamburg? Did it rest somewhere,
                    at least in the political spectrum, right, left? What sort of activity was going
                    on at the university?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: My impression is that it was a very high level of scholarship,
                    certainly highly regarded among the German universities. It was very strong in
                    Science, and finance, I believe. Also, because the kind of city that Hamburg
                    was. I would say that the faculty I knew tended to be a little to the left.
                    There was a lot of Marxist type thinking in the German universities at the time,
                    but not communism. Marxist from the academic standpoint and the philosophical
                    approach to economics, mainly. The Vietnam War did become a factor in the last
                    year I was there. We hadn't really had any friction on it, until then. Late in
                    my time there, I would go out and lecture, in, say, L�neburg, 30 miles from
                    Hamburg. We would go to a youth group affiliated with the social-democratic
                    labor unions (the DGB). My lecture was on the history of American jazz, which
                    attracted a lot of interest there. That was one of the advantages I had in
                    lecturing. But, the question period was about Vietnam. That happened a number of
                    times when I was lecturing on something completely different, but the questions
                    were about Vietnam. I carried a number of Dean Rusk official statements and
                    would quote from them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in 1968, and whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: In 1968, I came back to Washington. Let me just mention one thing about
                    the Vietnam War. During my last weeks of my stay in Hamburg, we had an incident.
                    We were presenting a lecture by an American who was with the German radio in
                    Berlin, RIAS, the radio in the free sector of Berlin. He was coming over to
                    lecture in German on NATO, the North Atlantic Alliance. He was supposed to be
                    fairly scholarly. It was a technical lecture. The police warned us ahead of time
                    that a student group planned a demonstration against our role in Vietnam. They
                    were going to break up the lecture. They suggested that we might be wise to call
                    the program off.. Well, I didn't want to be buffaloed. Ray Benson and I
                    discussed it and decided we would go ahead with it. The police asked us what we
                    wanted them to do if something happened. We assured them that we could handle
                    it. The students who came to these lectures were a faithful public and they
                    would help us, and it would be okay. One of the thoughts in my mind was that I
                    didn't want to have pictures in the newspapers of police carrying students out
                    of the Amerika Haus. So, what happened was that I got up to introduce the
                    speaker. Mind you, it was not on the subject of Vietnam at all. I started to
                    introduce the speaker and heckling started from about 10 people in the audience
                    of 150. They also had bottles of champagne and they started popping the corks,
                    just making a racket. I pleaded for silence so that we could go on with the
                    program, and if they wanted to discuss something, this was a democratic
                    institution, and we certainly were open to any kind of open discussion, but
                    let's give the speaker a chance to give his lecture, then we can discuss
                    anything you want. They wouldn't stop. It was obvious that the thing couldn't go
                    on, so I finally called it off, at that point, on the spot. I apologized to the
                    people who really wanted to stay and hear the lecture. We called it quits for
                    the evening.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the audience's reaction?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Most of the audience wanted to hear the lecture. They were kind of
                    disgusted. I think that was the main reaction. They left quietly. I have to say
                    that one of the most rewarding aspects of my tour in Hamburg was the chance to
                    associate with some of the younger generation of Germans. Many were quite
                    outstanding, and it was interesting to find that many consciously thought of
                    themselves not as Germans first but as Europeans - some turned to a European
                    identity really as an alternative to German nationalism, which they found
                    unsympathetic. It was an attitude that was new to me at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then, in 1968, you left, and where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I came back to Washington. A new magazine had just started at the
                    agency called Dialogue magazine, edited by a man named Nathan Glick. This was
                    going to be a quarterly academic type journal for intellectuals, to be
                    distributed worldwide in English. Later, it got into other languages. It was
                    just getting off the ground. I think they had published one issue. They needed
                    an assistant editor, associate editor, I was called. So, they assigned me there,
                    to help get things going with my journalistic background.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from 1968 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: A little over a year with Dialogue magazine. After that, I went to what
                    was then called IOP, the Office of Policy and Plans. There was a very impressive
                    woman there named Barbara White, who was the senior woman officer in the agency
                    at the time. Maybe Pat van Delden, who had been Deputy Public Affairs Officer in
                    Germany, was senior to Barbara. But, Barbara White was a senior woman officer;
                    she was the Deputy Chief of Policy and Plans, and I worked for her in the
                    planning office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right. Well, let's go back to Dialogue. From 1968 to
                        1969,what was your target audience and how was the magazine being
                        framed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The target audience was intellectual leadership in the universities and
                    in the governments of the countries. It was to be on a very high plane, maybe
                    like the Partisan Review or Sewanee Review, maybe a mixture of the two. It dealt
                    with political thought in the U.S., and also with literary criticism and trends
                    the arts. It was also in a somewhat lighter in vein, like Harpers, or the
                    Atlantic. It consisted mainly of reprints of articles from such magazines,
                    essentially. We would get permission to use pertinent articles which might be on
                    political trends or sociological trends or literary trends, something that would
                    show the range and direction of thought in the intellectual sector of the United
                    States. We figured, that to begin with anyway, that audience in most countries,
                    could read it in English. Later it was translated into Spanish. It was picked up
                    for publication in Latin America, and some other languages too. It was a great
                    success.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there as an associate editor. Did you have
                        debates owere the criteria for what sort of articles to choose?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Oh, yes. Nat and I would talk the over the possibilities. Nat was full
                    of ideas. He would do thematic issues, for instance. He did one issue on films,
                    for example, from many different standpoints - not only the cinematic
                    standpoint, but the social, and political standpoint. The magazine stood or fell
                    on its integrity as an intellectual journal. So, we tried to get a pretty good
                    spectrum of opinions. Of course, we weren't going to have anything that was
                    really radically anti-American... but the choice was pretty wide open. Nat was
                    an ingenious editor. He did it very well. What we did a good part of the time
                    was reading all the magazines we could get our hands on to get articles that
                    could, at least, be adapted. Sometimes we didn't use the full article. We would
                    use excerpts with the permission of the author. Sometimes Nat commissioned
                    pieces for the magazine.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>Q: Did you find it was difficult to have a magazine which was essentially on a
                    worldwide basis? You would have the Spanish market. You would have the Asian
                    market, and the European market. Would you have to keep in mind, how well this
                    will play there, and that will play there?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: To a certain extent, but if I remember correctly, as the magazine
                    developed, it began to have an Asian supplement, a Latin American supplement,
                    for articles that were more parochial.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it must have been pretty exciting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: It was. It was fun, and I think it made a contribution..</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you getting any response or was it too new to get
                        feedbacfrom the field?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: From our offices in the field, the feedback was very positive. It
                    definitely had that. From leadership, I don't recall that during my period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1969, you went over to Policy and Plans. How long were
                        yothere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Until 1971, when I went to Thailand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did Policy and Plans do at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: One thing we were working on at that time was... As you recall, the
                    Cultural exchange programs were administered by something called CU, the
                    Educational Cultural Affairs Bureau of the State Department. This was separate
                    from USIA, but we administered the programs overseas. One bureaucratic thing we
                    were working on, and spent a lot of time on at the time, was to get coordinated
                    country planning from the Washington side. There was never any problem in the
                    field because the Cultural Affairs officer, who was the USIS person, also ran
                    the cultural program. He reported both to the Washington office of USIA, and to
                    the bureau in the State Department. But, there were two separate country plans.
                    There was the CU country plan and the USIS country plan. To get these things
                    coordinated, and even melded was a policy planning project. Eventually, the CU
                    bureau was absorbed into USIA..</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: 1969 to 1971 was the beginning of the Nixon
                        administration. Diyou see a shift in policy at all with this new
                        administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I think we became aware of a narrower approach to what were doing, more
                    of an emphasis on anti-communism, maybe a narrower approach to selection of
                    speakers and those abroad to represent the United States under our program. I
                    think that was on the conservative side of the political spectrum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a magazine at one point, I don't know if it was
                        stilgoing then, called Problems of Communism. Was that going?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes, it was, indeed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was it felt? Was this considered an intellectual
                        magazine owas it pointed toward trying to make the communists look bad?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No, not the latter. It was certainly an intellectual magazine. I think
                    it probably, in a way, was the model for Dialogue. Nat's conception was to do
                    something on the broader spectrum of American culture and civilization that
                    would be on an intellectual level with Problems of Communism. Problems of
                    Communism was a highly academic journal of theoretical articles on Marxist
                    philosophy and the way it was being carried out in the Soviet Union. It was
                    highly technical and theoretical. Abraham Brumberg, the editor of it, kept it on
                    a very high level.</p>
                <p>Q: I would think that there would always be the battle that continues to rage but
                    the things you were doing with Dialogue and in Policy and Plans was really
                    long-term, reaching out, making people understand about the United States, our
                    system. Those who are practical would say, “We've got the Vietnam policy today,
                    and why don't you concentrate everything on Vietnam?” I mean, did this battle
                    rage while you were there?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Oh it was constant in USIA, the short-term ad hoc day-by-day policy
                    questions versus the long-term. George Shultz, I think, mentioned foreign policy
                    being like a garden. You don't just go day-to-day with your garden, you have to
                    water it and cultivate it, and ultimately, the flowers grow. You have to take
                    care of it in good weather so that it will survive the bad weather;. That was
                    the underlining philosophy, I guess, of our long term programs. Some of the
                    long-term programs being the exchange programs, the arts programs, etc. Of
                    course, those had been whittled away through the years, in favor of a more ad
                    hoc approach. Advocacy is a word that comes up a lot. In recent years, advocacy
                    has been regarded as the sole purpose of USIA programs. The longer term
                    cultivating programs have languished.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think it is a mistake. Well, in the Policy and Plans,
                        did yofind yourself immersed in Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No, not so much. I wasn't, anyway. Of course, it was there, but we went
                    with the Secretary's and the President's statements, or William Bundy's, or
                    whoever happened to be speaking at the time. There were clear policy guidelines
                    being given by them. Our office was the policy liaison with Voice of America,
                    for example. We monitored the Voice's broadcasts, to make sure they didn't
                    violate the policy line. The Voice, of course, being very jealous of its
                    independence and didn't like being guided by the office over at 175Pennsylvania
                    Avenue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, in 1971, you were off again.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: In 1971, off to Bangkok as a Cultural Affairs officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from 1971 to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: 1973.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was our ambassador and what was the embassy like when
                        you gothere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The ambassador was Leonard Unger. It was a big embassy. Of course,
                    there was big American business in Bangkok. There was the U.N. AID program in
                    which Americans were involved. There was a U.S. AID program. There was an Army
                    hospital. There were nearby bases. The huge air base was in southern Thailand.
                    There was a big American military presence. There were many activities in
                    Bangkok at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your Public Affairs officer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Jack Hedges, during that whole time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cultural Affairs officer meant what at that time in
                        Thailand?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Cultural Affairs officer meant contact with the universities and
                    cultural community. We had branch posts in Chiang Mai, Song-kla, Khon Kaen... In
                    those places, there were information centers - libraries - under our office's
                    supervision. In Bangkok, we had a bi-national center, called the AUA, American
                    University Association. The binational center had a mixed Thai and American
                    Board of Directors with a distinguished Thai president and with an American
                    executive director, Jack Juergens at that time. Again, it was very comparable to
                    the Amerika Haus in Hamburg. It had the same kinds of programs. I wasn't exactly
                    in charge. Jack Juergens and I worked together on that. Our programs were very
                    much coordinated. We would program lectures at the AUA and worked very closely
                    with Jack. He helped to carry out the cultural programs. There was also a book
                    publication program, a translation book program that was in our office. There
                    was the exchange program. There was a Fulbright commission in Thailand. I was
                    the vice chairman. There was a Thai chairman, and I was the vice chairman of the
                    Fulbright Commission, which again had a board of Americans and Thais, with an
                    American executive director, Doug Batson. The Commission was in charge of
                    awarding Fulbright grants, supervising the selection of American Fulbright
                    scholars who were moving to Thailand, and choosing those Thais who were going to
                    the United States under the Fulbright program.</p>
                <p>Q: How did this exchange program work? I would have thought you would have a lot
                    more Thais wanting to go to the United States than Americans wanting to come to
                    Thailand.</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I think that is true. I don't remember the numbers, but the number of
                    American Fulbrighters coming to Thailand was probably smaller than the number of
                    Thais to go to the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were the Thais going in the United States? What were
                        themainly after?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: They were mostly at the graduate level. They had come from the
                    university in Thailand, and were going for an advanced degree in the United
                    States, and went to a wide range of universities, depending on what university
                    was interested in having a Thai scholar. Thais have a good record of going to
                    the U.S., staying there two or three years, getting their degree and coming home
                    to Thailand.</p>
                <p>Q: What about cultural events? The Thais being an Oriental society. I would think
                    they would be less interested in American culture than maybe the Europeans.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No, the Thais are extremely open culturally. They are very confident in
                    their own culture. I didn't discover any xenophobia in Thailand. I think it is
                    partly because of their history of having never been colonized from the west,
                    with a brief Japanese occupation. But there is no chip on their shoulder. So,
                    they were interested in other cultures, and always have been open to western
                    culture. There is an interesting thing going on there; western countries working
                    to bring western cultures to Thailand. The Germans, for example, the Goethe Haus
                    in Bangkok, our counterpart, actually sponsored a Thai orchestra that played
                    western music. They hired a conductor to come live in Thailand and conduct this
                    Thai orchestra. The concertmaster, and reallythe leader, was a man named Usni
                    Pramoj, the son of a former Premier, Seni Pramoj. An American project was under
                    the auspices not of USIS or the U.S. Government, but of the JDR Third
                    Foundation. They brought to Bangkok a string quartet of American players which
                    was to be in residence at the Department of Fine Arts in Bangkok, which was the
                    center of Thai music. But the aim of this was to introduce western music into
                    Thai curriculum. The quartet was led by Edgar Schenkman, a very fine musician
                    who had been conductor of the Richmond Orchestra and the orchestra at Norfolk.
                    He had been head of the opera department at Juilliard School. He was a
                    first-rate musician. His wife was an accomplished violinist. There were just two
                    other members. She was the first violinist in the quartet, and then there was a
                    second violinist, and a wonderful young cellist. They played concerts of string
                    quartet music, and taught western music at the conservatory, at this Department
                    of Fine Arts. Of course, we took advantage of the presence of these people. That
                    is, we arranged for them to play public concerts in Bangkok and in outlying
                    places in Thailand. We even coordinated with other posts in southeast Asia to
                    have the quartet travel under USIS auspices. The concerts were a demonstration
                    of American accomplishment in string quartet playing. So, we tried to ride
                    piggyback on such things as that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If I recall, early on, maybe when he was crowned Prince,
                        the Kinof Thailand, I connect him with jazz.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Jazz, that's right. He played the clarinet and I think the saxophone,
                    too. King Bhumiphal Aduljadet... At that time, the American pianist Agustin
                    Anievas came to perform at the AUA, under our auspices. He gave a wonderful
                    recital. We had word from the Queen's office that they would like to have a
                    Anievas give a command performance at the palace. Our senior Thai staff member
                    was M.R. Puckpring Thongyai - really, a member of the royal family. Through her,
                    we had a direct line to the palace. She relayed the Palace's invitation to Gus
                    Anievas and was prepared to make the necessary arrangements. Fortunately, he had
                    the time and we went to the palace. The Queen herself was ill at the time, so
                    the royal audience consisted of the King and his young daughter who was studying
                    the piano. I got a kick out of being there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this time, did Vietnam intrude at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Oh, it was ever-present. We were aware of the B-52s flying from
                    Sataheep over in the direction of Vietnam, when we said we were not bombing
                    Cambodia. Vietnam was a presence, but it wasn't talked about very much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there general interest in American culture and all
                        iThailand?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Oh, yes. Thai artists were very much influenced by the abstract
                    expressionists. Art exhibits of Thai artists were often dominated by that kind
                    of art. They were very good, too. Even pop art was coming into Thailand at that
                    point. The Thais were very much abreast of whatever was going on. But, they were
                    also very proud of their own culture and very protective of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there much effort by the Thais to export their culture
                        anwhat type of culture was coming out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: One of the people I got to know there was Princess Chumbhot, who was
                    prominent in the art world in Thailand, what Usni Pramoj was to the music world.
                    She had, in her small palace in Bangkok, a Thai music group, which she was very
                    proud of. She asked me if there was a possibility, if she had a recording made
                    of her group, that I could help her get it pressed and distributed in the United
                    States. So, I actually got in touch with Moses Asch of Folkways Records and
                    asked if he was interested in an authentic recording of Thai music, made with
                    very fine equipment the Princess had access to in a studio in Bangkok. He was
                    interested and we sent him a tape. He did publish a record called Drums of
                    Thailand in the Folkways library, which is still extant.</p>
                <p>Q: What about the performing arts, plays and things of this nature? Was there
                    much, either in translation or in the original language that we were
                    pushing?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: We weren't pushing that sort of thing. We had musical groups and there
                    was a theater group that came. In Thailand, there was enough of an American and
                    British community that they had their own theater group and put on plays. Edgar
                    Schenkman of the quartet also took a hand in the Bangkok Opera Company, which
                    was mostly British and Americans, but some Thai singers, too. They put on the
                    Menotti opera, The Medium. They did a very good job of it. So, there were things
                    like that. We had visiting artists. The Duke Ellington orchestra came through
                    under commercial sponsorship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, in 1973, whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Again, back to the USA for almost three years. This time, first as
                    German desk officer and the policy officer in the European area of USIA. I seem
                    to have this cultural identification overseas and the policy identification in
                    the states.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this period, on the German desk, what were your
                        concerns?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The biggest concern was establishing posts in East Germany. We didn't
                    have anything in East Germany. The State Department head finally wangled a way
                    for us to establish a USIS post in East Berlin. So, there was a lot going on in
                    preparing for that. Our Public Affairs officer, Pick Littell, had already been
                    chosen. We were designing the program and went over and looked at the
                    premises.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved or give support or anything on
                        thnegotiations of this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The main negotiations had taken place before, in the
                    StatDepartment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As German desk officer, you covered both, east and
                        west?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you feel that the USIA effort in East Germany had
                        nevebeen there before? What were the problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: The main problem was simply getting access to the public - or making it
                    possible for the public to gain access to us. That was a painstaking job, to
                    establish contact with the press, with the public, in general. We had a small
                    library, and of course, people who came there were carefully watched by the
                    police. They were obviously under surveillance. It was a very difficult
                    situation, but little by little, the library did win a clientele.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you feel that there were attempts by the German democratic republic, the
                    East German government, to sabotage the access of our information,
                    culturally?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: As I say, there were policemen stationed across the street from the
                    door and the people who went in were noted. That was a deterrent.</p>
                <p>Q: Were you sensing any change in West Germany, toward the United States, at this
                    point? Were we getting increasingly concerned, new generation, with Vietnam, and
                    protest movements taking place all over Europe?</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Let's see, 1973 to 1976. I'm trying to think what the issues might have
                    been. I don't believe there was any movement at that time that we were
                    following. Mainly, what was happening with the USIS posts was they were
                    dwindling. We were closing America Houses and closing libraries in West Germany.
                    But, we carried on an active program, within the limits of diminishing
                    resources.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then, you moved over to the European area? What were you
                        dointhere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: It was all in the European area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was all in the European area. How about France, while
                        yowere dealing with Europe?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: There was a French desk officer, Mary Gawronski. There was a French
                    desk just as there was a German desk. We were all in the area. When I went into
                    it, it was “IWE,” the Western European area, in which I was the German desk
                    officer. Then, that was combined with the east European office, which was
                    responsible for programs in the Soviet Union, etc. so that it was renamed “IEU,”
                    covering all of Europe, under Jock Shirley. That's when I became deputy policy
                    officer, then policy officer for the European Area.</p>
                <p>In the policy officer job, a big part of it was keeping track of the Voice of
                    America, coordinating policy with the State Department. I attended meetings at
                    the State Department in the European area there. We had a brown bag lunch with
                    the policy officers from the other areas to discuss whatever problems there
                    might be, and meetings at the Voice, a lot of telephoning to the Voice.
                    Particularly after we haEastern Europe in our area, the Voice was sometimes
                    prickly because a number of the broadcasters and the broadcast services there
                    were expatriates from those countries, who were really very strongly
                    opinionated. They would get their digs into some of their editorials, which we
                    tried to ease a little bit. We tried to keep the Voice sounding cool and
                    objective, as much as possible.</p>
                <p>Q: Someone I was talking to, it was Jeff Dietrich, I think, with every USIS
                    officer moving in the field and out, saying that work in Washington for the USIA
                    is not much fun, because overseas you really are doing something. Whereas when
                    you come back to Washington, you realize you are not dealing with much policy.
                    It is more a support role, because the policy thing is handled by the Department
                    of State. You feel secondary whereas you are really on the front line overseas.
                    Did you find this?</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes, indeed. As policy officer in the European area, one of the main
                    things I was responsible for was monitoring the country plans. The country plan,
                    of course, was a document that's written at the post, which is to set forth the
                    objectives of the operation in the country in view of policy issues that exist
                    between the U.S. and the country, which can be affected by information and
                    cultural programs. The objectives are specified and the programs designed to
                    carry them out are mapped out in the country plans. In the area office, we would
                    read those country plans and studies them to make sure they are on track. That
                    is a largely academic exercise, in a way, because overseas, it's pretty obvious
                    what you have to do, without referring to a country plan. There, “on the
                    ground,” it's no longer at all academic; it's personal contact, whom you get to
                    know, what you can sense that could be affected by what you do, what
                    opportunities you can take advantage of within the scope of the budget. While
                    there are big worries about budgets in Washington, and always the feeling there
                    wasn't going to be enough money, overseas, I never knew of a really good idea
                    that money couldn't be found for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: 1976, whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: 1976 to London. At the end of the bicentennial year, I went there as
                    Culture Affairs officer. For several years, they had had so-called “super CAOs”
                    in London. These were top-notch academics - Wayne Wilcox and Robin Winks,
                    Cleanth Brooks, Charles Ritcheson had been academic Cultural Affairs officers
                    there, imported from American universities to be in touch with the British
                    universities, at a high level. For some reason, in 1976, it was thought it was
                    time to go back to what we call a professional CAO in London, and I was it. So,
                    I was the first after some years. I had my work cut out for me because it was a
                    time of dwindling resources, dwindling staff; and in England, the opportunities
                    are so great - there is so great a demand for our participation, so great a
                    potential for activity - that you just find yourself saying “no” a lot of the
                    time. To me, it was very frustrating because there were so many things you could
                    do, but you can't do, because there isn't the staff or money for it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from 1976 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: 1979.</p>
                <p>Q: In a way, one almost wonders what we would do in the cultural field, because
                    the ties are so close that it sort of goes on... It's like the dog barks at the
                    caravan, but the caravan moves on. In a way, no matter what you did, these ties
                    would be back and forth.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Well, that is certainly true. We talked about the special relationship,
                    and I think that does exist. Of course, there is a tie of the language, many
                    jokes are made about it. But there are a lot of misconceptions, too. It was
                    worth a shot to try to demonstrate the vitality and depth of cultural
                    achievement in the United States. Of course, the British academics know our
                    writers and so forth. In the field of American music, some of the Brits knew
                    more about “doo-wop” than I did - and they knew jazz. But they weren't that
                    conversant with American concert music. That was a field in which I had some
                    expertise, so I gave lectures, in a number of universities, on recent trends in
                    American concert music. Again, the field of American studies - as it had been in
                    Hamburg - was very important to us. Many British universities were establishing
                    departments of American studies; alongside the departments that associated
                    American literature and British literature, they were now teaching film, jazz,
                    folklore, and American literature as American literature. There was an
                    opportunity here for us to reinforce that and encourage it. We certainly did
                    that. One thing we did, for example, was to sponsor a study which would
                    coordinate the holdings in American studies in the libraries at all the British
                    universities, so one university would know what another university had. Making
                    these connections was very important to us. We managed to come up with $25,000
                    to support the project, and they were able to make a catalogue that would be
                    used for coordination among the libraries. We helped to sponsor other activities
                    of the British Association of American Studies. Whatever we could do to
                    strengthen that movement, we did.</p>
                <p>Q: What one always hears about the chattering class in England and Great Britain,
                    these are the people who appear on TV and talk shows, write columns for the
                    major papers. That is a relatively small group. They are not quite the same as
                    the intellectuals, say, in France, but they sort of pass for that. Did you mark
                    these as being one of your targets?</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Journalists, in general, were among the people we made an effort to be
                    in touch with. Not so much for the Cultural Affairs Section as for the Press
                    Attache and the Information section. It seems to be a little compartmentalized.
                    We, of course, had contacts with the cultural writers of the newspapers,
                    particularly, the music critics, the dance critics, the art critics, people like
                    that. One example - when the American poet Robert Lowell died, an acquaintance
                    of mine at the National Theater liked the idea of arranging a memorial poetry
                    reading in the Embassy auditorium, with some of the leading actors from the
                    National Theater taking part. Harold Pinter insisted on taking part; he wanted
                    to read. Ronald Pickup was another participant. Helen Mirren attended, but she
                    didn't actually read. Anyway, it was a well-attended program, invitational, for
                    a very select audience with wonderful cooperation of the National Theater in
                    honor of an American poet who had many admirers in England. Another example:
                    When the BBC Symphony performed Elliott Carter's Piano Concerto, we arranged for
                    a conversation in the embassy auditorium betweeCarter, who was there for the
                    performance, Charles Rosen, the American pianist who was the soloist, and
                    William Glock, who for years had been head of BBC music, to discuss Carter's
                    music on the stage of the Embassy auditorium. Again, the audience was a
                    carefully selected group of academics, journalists, political and cultural
                    leaders... The Queen's silver jubilee took place in that year, 1979, I guess it
                    was, or maybe 1978. Anyway, we wanted to do something about that, so we arranged
                    what we called a series of Jubilee Lectures in the embassy auditorium. Bill
                    Leuchtenberg from Columbia University came and gave the first address. We had
                    four lectures, Leuchtenberg, David Owen, who was Foreign Secretary at the time,
                    talking about the transatlantic alliance and its history, Anthony Quinton, about
                    American philosophy, and George W. Ball, who was Undersecretary of State. The
                    lectures were then published as a book called America and Britain. So, that was
                    pretty substantial. Also for the Queen's silver jubilee, we latched onto the
                    American Ballet Theater, which was in Europe at the time. They actually had a
                    couple of free dates, and with the cooperation of the State Department (Jean
                    Lashly, in the Office of Cultural and Educational Affairs (CU), to be specific -
                    this was before CU was integrated into USIA) we got some extra money to bring
                    them over to London to do a week's season in honor of the Queen's jubilee, under
                    the auspices of the embassy and the State Department, with an additional
                    contribution from a private-sector co-sponsor, American Express, I think it
                    was.</p>
                <p>Q: It would strike me that you were really dealing with, as you say, the field
                    was so great that you must have really had a crush in you time and efforts,
                    didn't you?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes, indeed. It was very exciting...the people we dealt with... For
                    instance, when Philip Roth was in town, we (my wife and I, that is) had a brunch
                    at which he met fellow writers like Malcolm Bradbury and V.S. Pritchett and
                    Angus Wilson, Eric Mottram, the poet and professor of American literature at the
                    University of London... We had the same kind of thing at the time that Steve
                    Reich, the composer was performing in London with his group. We had an evening
                    set aside for Steve Reich, and some of the younger British composers - Michael
                    Nyman and Brian Eno, and several others of the avant garde. We could do things
                    like that. You had such easy access to all these people. It was wonderful to
                    become acquainted with them.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>Q: How did you find the music and cultural type critics of the British papers?
                    This has been your thing before, and how did you find them, particularly in
                    dealing with American things?</p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I thought the level of criticism in London was quite respectable. They
                    did not condescend to American music. I think American music was respected in
                    that quarter. London, of course, was and I think probably still is, the most
                    musical city in the world. There is more going on musically in London than
                    anyplace else that I can think of. There are four or five orchestras, countless
                    chamber music groups, two major opera companies, and a smaller opera company. It
                    is just amazing what goes on in London. It has gotten a lot more expensive, but
                    it was comparatively inexpensive at that time, certainly less than what you
                    would pay for similar programs in New York.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, 1979, you were off again.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: No, in 1979, I was back in the USA. Unfortunately, my wife was ill. She
                    had cancer just before we went to London, and was being treated while we were in
                    London. She was in remission for a year in London, but in the end, the cancer
                    returned, so we went back to the United States for further treatment.
                    Unfortunately, she died in 1980.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's too bad.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I had retired at the end of 1979, so I could spend mortime with her.
                    So, that was where the career ended.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Have you kept up with any of the cultural work since that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Yes, in fact, in 1981, after Pat died, I was called back to Europe. Lee
                    Johnson was the coordinator for USIS' Regional Resources Unit in London, and
                    handled programming throughout Europe. Ray Benson, at that time was PAO in
                    Yugoslavia, and they asked me to do a lecture tour, talking about American
                    music, mostly in Eastern Europe. So, I went to Greece, to Athens and
                    Thessaloniki, to Austria, (Vienna). I went to Skopje and Titograd, and Zagreb
                    and Ljubljana in Yugoslavia. I was supposed to have gone to Bulgaria, but the
                    Bulgarians decided that they didn't want me, and wouldn't give me a visa.
                    Nevertheless, I did go to Prague, and lectured there. That was an experience
                    that I will never forget.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How so?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Well, in Prague, Western music, and especially avant-garde music were
                    considered subversive. The post there - Mike Hoffman, the PAO, and the CAO Alice
                    Lemaistre - were in touch with what was called the Jazz Section of the
                    Composer's Union in Prague. The Jazz Section invited me to talk to the
                    membership about current trends in American concert music. The Jazz Section
                    wasn't just musicians, but it was journalists and university people, too. They
                    assembled an audience of 120 people to hear me talk and play tapes of recent
                    American music. The president of the Jazz Section, Karel Srp, was harassed by
                    the police. We didn't know until the last moment if they would let the lecture
                    take place. They did. Not only did I give my lecture, but they played for me
                    some examples of avant garde Czech music I certainly had never heard before.
                    Music was for them a lifeline to the west; it was a symbol of freedom of thought
                    and innovation, for which the Czechs were starving. The Czech government was
                    right to consider it subversive. It's very important, jazz itself, but also all
                    the work of avant garde composers in Europe and the U.S.; the jazz section
                    published a magazine - which was later banned - about trends in western music,
                    including rock music and jazz, and so forth. It was quite moving to see this
                    turnout for American music among people whom it endangered.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about when you were in Yugoslavia. How were you
                        receivethere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: Oh, very well. I gave my illustrated lectures mostly in music schools,
                    at the universities there, where people wanted to keep up with musical trends in
                    Europe and the United States; these audiences were often pretty well-informed
                    about contemporary music in Europe and had more than a little knowledge too of
                    what went on in the United States. In Yugoslavia, of course, they were much more
                    open to the west than in Prague. But, out in a place like Titograd...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which is now known as “Podgorica...”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: That's right. They really hadn't had much contact with American concert
                    music. One of the lectures I had prepared was called “American Music and the
                    European Tradition,” where I tried to show how American composers had at first
                    tried to follow the established European musical tradition but then had split
                    from it to create something new and uniquely American. Of course, in the
                    process, I tried also to convey something of the openness of American society,
                    its innovativeness and creativity, and the accomplishments of our composers and
                    performers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It sounds like it was quite a trip.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: It was.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is probably a good place to stop, don't you
                        think?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: I think so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Great. Well, I really appreciate this. This has been
                        fun.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SABLOSKY: For me, too. Thank you.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
